<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cleaning Up the Dry Cleaners; High Cost of Going Green Limits Promising Technology</title>
    <meta content="Y15CLE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000216T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1176644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dry Cleaning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hangers Cleaners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Micell Technologies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cleansers, Detergents and Soaps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D91431F936A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cleaning Up the Dry Cleaners; High Cost of Going Green Limits Promising Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hangers Cleaners is trying to sell dry-cleaning industry and its customers on radically different technology that does not use hazardous or toxic chemicals; Hangers uses biodegradable soap dissolved not in water but in liquefied carbon dioxide, substance so safe it is used to decaffeinate coffee and inject fizz into soft drinks; backers of Hangers see it as high-profile model of 'green chemistry,' unofficial name that government officials gave to various programs in 1991 aimed at weaning society from its reliance on noxious chemcials; Micell Technologies owns technology and Hangers name; Hangers has opened only handful of stores, rather than 500 outlets and $50 million in sales it expected by end of last year, providing strong evidence that environmental benefits matter only after customers are satisfied about cost, quality and convenience; cost of each machine is about $150,000, compared with $60,000 for top-of-the-line perc system handling similar-sized loads; graph; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For over a decade, the dry cleaning business has looked like a tantalizing opportunity for environmentally minded entrepreneurs. Despite increasing regulations aimed at cutting air pollution and groundwater contamination, not to mention criticism from groups like Greenpeace and Consumers Union, a vast majority of the nation's roughly 33,000 dry cleaners persist in using toxic chemicals linked to cancer, nervous system ailments and other health hazards.</p>
        <p>''Green cleaners'' using water and new biodegradable detergents sprang up in many communities in the 1990's, with some reporting customers coming from 20 miles or more away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For over a decade, the dry cleaning business has looked like a tantalizing opportunity for environmentally minded entrepreneurs. Despite increasing regulations aimed at cutting air pollution and groundwater contamination, not to mention criticism from groups like Greenpeace and Consumers Union, a vast majority of the nation's roughly 33,000 dry cleaners persist in using toxic chemicals linked to cancer, nervous system ailments and other health hazards.</p>
        <p>''Green cleaners'' using water and new biodegradable detergents sprang up in many communities in the 1990's, with some reporting customers coming from 20 miles or more away.</p>
        <p>But few existing dry cleaners were inclined to switch because ''wet cleaning'' takes longer, increases labor costs and can easily lead to shrinkage or other quality problems. Many felt vindicated when Ecomat, a wet cleaner that featured ad slogans like ''Is Your Dry Cleaner Killing You?'' went bankrupt in 1998.</p>
        <p>Now the green spotlight is being claimed by Hangers Cleaners, which is trying to sell the industry and its customers on a radically different technology. Hangers uses a biodegradable soap dissolved not in water but in liquefied carbon dioxide, a substance so safe it is used to decaffeinate coffee and inject the fizz into soft drinks.</p>
        <p>The backers of Hangers see it as a high-profile model of ''green chemistry,'' the unofficial name that government officials gave to various programs in 1991 aimed at weaning society from its reliance on noxious chemicals. Repeat business at the first stores is high, and potential franchisees have signed up for more than 40 territories ranging as far west as Lincoln, Neb., according to Micell Technologies, which owns the technology and the Hangers name.</p>
        <p>Still, Hangers has been on a slower track than it hoped when its technology won the Environmental Protection Agency's Green Chemistry Challenge Award in 1997. Rather than the 500 outlets and $50 million in sales it expected by the end of last year, it has opened only a handful of stores, providing strong evidence that environmental benefits matter only after customers are satisfied about cost, quality and convenience.</p>
        <p>''The environmental opportunity can't lead change,'' conceded Kirk Kinsell, chief executive of Micell, based in Raleigh, N.C.</p>
        <p>A look at the hurdles Hangers has encountered underscores how constant improvements in existing technology and numerous other competitive factors affecting a particular business can slow environmental innovation, even in industries that look simple to outsiders.</p>
        <p>The main public face of Hangers so far has belonged to Joseph M. DeSimone, a 35-year-old professor of chemistry and chemical engineering at the University of North Carolina and North Carolina State.</p>
        <p>Although the buildup of carbon dioxide gas in the atmosphere has been cited as a big factor in global warming, Mr. DeSimone is one of many researchers investigating compressed or liquefied carbon dioxide as a substitute for other chemicals because it is widely available, inexpensive and much less hazardous.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeSimone was diverted from his initial research on how liquefied carbon dioxide could replace toxic chemicals used in making plastic by the realization that it could also stand in for perchloroethylene, a widely used industrial chemical that is the most popular dry-cleaning solvent. Perc, as it is known, had become a big concern for government regulators because of strong evidence that it causes cancer, and possibly numerous other ailments, for cleaning workers and even residents of nearby buildings.</p>
        <p>Perc vapors and discharges also contaminate groundwater. By the 1990's, dry cleaners were the biggest remaining source of such pollution.</p>
        <p>The key was to develop a detergent that could dissolve in carbon dioxide, because even though carbon dioxide penetrates clothing easily, it does not bind to dirt, food or grease on its own. By 1996, the crucial detergent in hand, Mr. DeSimone and two former students formed Micell with the first installments of what became $20 million in venture capital.</p>
        <p>Most of the money came from Unifi, a large textile company based in Greensboro, N.C., that had been tracking possible uses of carbon dioxide in dyeing operations, and the George Soros Management Fund. Unifi now owns 40 percent of Micell.</p>
        <p>Micell assumed it had a ready market in dry cleaners nervous about perc, which earned a reputation as a versatile and powerful degreaser during World War II and rapidly replaced the petroleum-based solvents that had frequently been fire hazards in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Environmental regulations were driving up operating and waste-disposal costs for perc systems. Everything the chemical touched except the clothes themselves was deemed a hazardous waste as a result of the 1990 Clean Air Act, requiring extensive paperwork and special disposal. Cities like New York passed regulations requiring cleaners in residential buildings to close or invest tens of thousands of dollars in new equipment that prevented perc from being released. Some landlords pressed cleaners to close down or switch to cleaner methods.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, though, cleaners were not as afraid of perc's near-term future as Micell anticipated. Their equipment suppliers developed systems so efficient that the entire industry used just 72 million pounds of perc in 1998, down from 235 million a decade earlier. The newest designs virtually eliminated accidental spills and emissions.</p>
        <p>Those that are moving away from the chemical are not necessarily seeing Micell as their best option. Some are expanding their use of water. Others are turning to the newest petroleum solvents, which are making a comeback because suppliers like Exxon created improved cleaners that are harder to ignite.</p>
        <p>Micell's equipment design is also proving to be a major hurdle. Its current cleaning system is easy to operate, but the 10-ton rectangle of pipes, reservoirs, pumps and filters dwarfs anything else on the market and is far too large for the cramped quarters of many dry cleaners. More important, at $150,000 a unit, it is often far too expensive.</p>
        <p>Top-of-the-line perc systems handling similar-sized loads cost about $60,000. Petroleum systems are not much more, and wet-cleaning systems cost as little as $20,000. And many cleaners are particularly reluctant to make big new capital investments after enduring several years when the trend toward casual dress hurt sales, which industry experts estimate were about $6.5 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Micell says its equipment cleans more quickly and reduces operating costs in so many ways that the extra cost is recouped within three years, assuming pricing that matches higher-end cleaners. But many in the industry remain skeptical.</p>
        <p>''I visited the first shop in Wilmington, N.C., and didn't see any evidence that it's more productive,'' said William Seitz, executive director of the Neighborhood Cleaners Association International, a New York trade group. Other cleaners say they are convinced that the process is more productive and, because it operates at room temperature, gentler on clothes, but not that it can clean as well as perc.</p>
        <p>Micell's decision to create the Hangers franchise concept to market the technology is another complication. Micell assumed that franchising and exclusive territories would help overcome cleaners' qualms about the big investment in equipment. But many cleaners do not believe the Hangers name is as valuable as the familiar names that have often hung on their stores for generations.</p>
        <p>Some, like Bruce Barish, a third-generation owner of Ernest Winzer Cleaners in the Bronx, say they are interested in the technology but are leaning toward working with a competing dioxide design from Global Technologies, an El Segundo, Calif., company that has been progressing more slowly toward commercialization than Micell. Global has licensed seven manufacturers to make machinery, which it said would be widely available later this year with no franchising strings attached.</p>
        <p>The market was muddied further by the sudden appearance last year of Zoots, a Newton, Mass., enterprise founded by Thomas Stemberg, the chairman and chief executive of Staples, and Todd Krasnow, one of his top lieutenants. Zoots is counting on marketing and expansion skills learned at Staples to help it quickly create a nationwide cleaning company emphasizing drive-through service and other conveniences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krasnow, Zoots's chief executive, said that he wanted nothing to do with perc and that petroleum cleaning systems met Zoots's quality and environmental needs.</p>
        <p>''It will be the marketing geniuses versus the technology mavens,'' joked Sam Brickle, the 62-year-old Rhode Island industrialist who bought the rights from Micell to develop the Hangers concept in New England.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brickle, who owns the last major mills in the region's once-thriving textile industry, knows plenty about competition. At this stage of Hangers' development, such experience has become more crucial to Hangers' chances of fulfilling its green-chemistry promise than Mr. DeSimone's technical brilliance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brickle rejected Micell's original concept of putting its machines in stores. His cleaning plant is in a former metal recycling mill in an industrial park he owns. Some customers come right to the plant, but most clothes arrive from the three Hangers shops that have opened in recent months. The plan is to open 3 more by summer and a total of up to 25 within a 20-mile radius.</p>
        <p>Hangers of New England executives are also searching for locations near Fairfield, Conn., Lowell, Mass., and Manchester, N.H., to set up similar factories with satellite stores.</p>
        <p>Like many an investor in green-chemistry innovations, Mr. Brickle is ending up more deeply involved than he originally envisioned. ''My initial goal was to sell 1,000 franchises in New England,'' he said, reflecting on his surprise at perc's continued hold on the industry. ''Now it looks like we'll have to own a lot of them.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 16, 2000, Wednesday  A chart in Business Day yesterday  about the dry cleaning industry's use of the chemical known as perc omitted a scale label. The quantities were expressed in millions of pounds: consumption declined from 235 million pounds in 1988 to 72 million in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 16, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day yesterday  about the dry cleaning industry's use of the chemical known as perc omitted a scale label. The quantities were expressed in millions of pounds: consumption declined from 235 million pounds in 1988 to 72 million in 1998.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
