<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bad Shoe Days Down Under</title>
    <meta content="10NIXO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1229569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nixon, Rob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drewe, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shark Net: Memories and Murder (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1DF1530F933A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bad Shoe Days Down Under</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rob Nixon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nixon, Rob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rob Nixon reviews book Shark Net: Memories and Murder by Robert Drewe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Shark Net</p>
        <p>Memories and Murder.</p>
        <p>By Robert Drewe.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Shark Net</p>
        <p>Memories and Murder.</p>
        <p>By Robert Drewe.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Robert Drewe's memoir -- like the beaches of his native Western Australia -- has a surface calm and an undertow of menace. The author of five novels and two volumes of short stories, Drewe has produced a captivating account of his upbringing in the sun-sedated suburbs of 1950's Perth. Separated from the rest of Australia by a vast desert and from the rest of the world by an ocean, Perth may be the planet's most isolated city. ''The coastline,'' Drewe observes, ''reminded me of ancient religious backdrops at Sunday school: the Dead Sea and places waiting for a miracle.''</p>
        <p>Redemption from boredom arrives in a sinister guise. For four years, a serial killer strikes randomly, shaking Perth's suburbanites out of their insular torpor. The eight killings appear to have no pattern: the man hatchets an heiress, shoots a student in bed, runs down a woman with his car. Until the killer's appearance, Perth's most threatening serial criminal was the cyclist who repeatedly crashed through the display window at Shirley's Frock Salon and made love to the mannequins.</p>
        <p>''The Shark Net'' has a mixed-genre feel: a coming-of-age story with undertones of noir memoir Drewe tracks brilliantly the emotional challenges of a bicoastal boyhood, Australian style. At the age of 6, he treks with his family from Melbourne to Perth, 2,000 miles to the west. In Perth, he has to learn the local rites from scratch: there, he discovers, real boys always go barefoot, revel in digging sand-dune tunnels and, most definitively, know how to urinate on moss.</p>
        <p>''My new friend Nick Howell was the chief exponent. . . . He was pleased to have us move into the neighborhood. He'd already killed all the moss along the lee side of his own house down the road, and the Ivimeys' moss at 34 Leon Road. He'd nearly finished Miss Thomas's side fence at 35, and the three France girls at 32 wouldn't let him anywhere near their walls.'' Drewe gains a loyal friend by offering ''moss access'' to the family home. Soon, together, they've terminated the neighborhood's remaining lichens in showers of acid rain.</p>
        <p>If Drewe's mastery over moss wins him friends, his failures on the footwear front become a racking source of shame. The problem starts with his father, an assistant manager at Dunlop. One might have thought that in Perth, half a century ago, a boy would have had a decent shot at living a no-logo childhood. But Drewe has been branded at birth: the company child of a company man whose primary sign of affection is giving his son, each Christmas, a new pair of Dunlop Bumper leisure shoes. To be seen in ''covered feet'' by Perth's beach-toughened barefoot boys is humiliating enough. But to appear in public wearing Dunlop Bumper leisure shoes is to jeopardize all hope of peer acceptance. With chocolate-brown fake suede uppers and clunky yellow rubber soles, his father's proud product threatens to turn the son into an outcast. One drenching and the leisure shoe stays wet for a week, acquiring the texture of ''wet otter skin'' and a slimy stink.</p>
        <p>''The Shark Net'' is often drolly funny, and nowhere more so than in Drewe's evocation of life in an outpost of the Dunlop empire, in which his father serves as a fanatic missionary. The memoir's emotional heart is this rubber-mediated father-son relationship: Dunlop as prophylactic to male intimacy. In the Drewe household, the only unforgivable sin is brand infidelity. No son dared put Goodyear tires on his bike.</p>
        <p>A superb portrait emerges of the tight-lipped 1950's company man who occasionally brightens into conversation to explain how experts selected Dunlop's yellow and black colors after scientists had proved they were ''the most arresting to the human eye.'' Amid all this corporate airlessness, Drewe's spirited mother finds an ally in the family parakeet, which she trains to squawk sardonically, ''Today you'll use a Dunlop product.'' Dunlop even seeks to regiment family urination, but young Drewe manages to stage some precocious desecration. In the bathroom, ''males stood and aimed from two rubber footprints wittily set into the Dunlop bathroom flooring at the approximate average adult firing range. If you were still a child, of course, more often than not you missed.''</p>
        <p>At his best -- notably in the memoir's first half -- Drewe calls to mind Roddy Doyle and Nick Hornby, those maestros at dramatizing budding male bluster. ''The Shark Net'' can be wonderful on the half-knowledge and anxious ignorance that fuel each stage of the journey from boyhood into adolescence. Learning to dance the Creep at beach parties is one such moment: ''It was dizzying enough to Creep up against the bolstered breasts and panty-girdled pelvis of a 15-year-old normally spotted at the bus stop in a tartan uniform. To tightly clasp a 16-year-old stranger, a sweatered stenographer or shop assistant, a girl who worked, was a thrill we knew we didn't deserve.'' In a scene of exquisite sexual gaucherie, Drewe tries to court an indifferent girl by arriving on her doorstep with a freshly caught and profusely bleeding shark draped around his neck. Unimpressed, she shuts the door on him -- but not before noting that the kind of shark he is wearing doesn't even boast proper teeth.</p>
        <p>When the action in ''The Shark Net'' shifts from adolescence to early adulthood, the writing becomes more muted and diffuse. This is ironic, since, at least on the surface, the later material would appear to hold the greater dramatic possibilities. Drewe, now a cub reporter, trawls the beachfront for tabloid-style stories: swimmers mauled by sharks and -- his dream story -- the arrest of Perth's serial killer.</p>
        <p>A small-town memoir replete with crime must seem a publicist's dream. Yet the killings appear almost incidental to the book's creativity. The murderer becomes most interesting when he illuminates the quirkily perceptive young Drewe's yearnings and fears. This writer's metier -- his imaginative home turf -- isn't murder mysteries but beachside suburbia's quotidian macabre. He recalls, with exactly the right intensity, all the crucial forms of local knowledge. Drewe's unfashionable refusal to play up the overtly dramatic feels just right. Our emotional life, especially when we're young, doesn't observe media hierarchies. We can all relive that age when imprisonment inside a pair of Dunlop Bumper leisure shoes was a fate way scarier than coexistence with a serial killer.</p>
        <p>Rob Nixon is Rachel Carson professor of English at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. His most recent book is ''Dreambirds: The Strange History of the Ostrich in Fashion, Food, and Fortune.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rob Nixon is Rachel Carson professor of English at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. His most recent book is ''Dreambirds: The Strange History of the Ostrich in Fashion, Food, and Fortune.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
