<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Influx Of Tourists To Far North Of Canada</title>
    <meta content="13CANA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northwest Territories (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yukon Territory (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nunavut (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Yukon, the Northwest Territories and Nunavut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7D8123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Influx Of Tourists To Far North Of Canada</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>YELLOWKNIFE, Northwest Territories</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada's three northern territories, home to only 100,000 people sprinkled across 1.5 million square miles, formerly attracted only fur trappers and gold miners; now there is tourism boom in all three: Northwest Territories, Yukon Territories and Nunavut; in Yukon Territory, tourism has become No 1 economic activity; many Europeans and Asians are visiting, but bulk of visitors are from United States; new hotels in every major town and increasingly reliable, if expensive, air links are attracting older and more affluent tourists; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With tee-off times set for midnight, the summer solstice golf tournament was fast approaching when Rebecca Jaud faced an increasingly familiar problem for this Arctic city: no rooms at the inns.</p>
        <p>''I was calling bed and breakfast operators to see if they could loan camping equipment so tourists could sleep in their backyards,'' said Ms. Jaud, who runs this city's increasingly busy visitors center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With tee-off times set for midnight, the summer solstice golf tournament was fast approaching when Rebecca Jaud faced an increasingly familiar problem for this Arctic city: no rooms at the inns.</p>
        <p>''I was calling bed and breakfast operators to see if they could loan camping equipment so tourists could sleep in their backyards,'' said Ms. Jaud, who runs this city's increasingly busy visitors center.</p>
        <p>Yellowknife, on the northern tip of the Great Slave Lake, has traditionally been the Saturday night destination of choice for fur trappers, gold miners and lonely Mounties.</p>
        <p>But as evidenced by two new hotels nearing completion here, a new sushi restaurant with Japanese-speaking staff, and travel advertisements fattening Up Here magazine, Yellowknife and Canada's north are undergoing a tourism boom.</p>
        <p>''We are just crazy with Europeans,'' Darielle Talarico, manager of Go Wild Tours, said in Inuvik, a town above the Arctic Circle, as she prepared to send another group of visitors down the Dempster Highway to Whitehorse, 1,000 miles to the south. This summer, weekly flights link Zurich and Frankfurt with Whitehorse, capital of the Yukon Territory, where tourism has become the No. 1 economic activity.</p>
        <p>Although Germans flood the Yukon, French flock to Nunavut and 10,000 Japanese tourists come to Yellowknife every winter to view the northern lights, Canada's northern tourism boom is largely fueled by Americans, who account for about three-quarters of the nation's foreign visitors every year.</p>
        <p>Much as affluent Americans migrate south in the winter to escape the cold, more now migrate north in the summer to escape the heat.</p>
        <p>In a reversal in 1998, more Americans made overnight trips to Canada than Canadians made overnight trips to the United States. With northern tourism growing faster than southern tourism, American overnight trips to Canada increased by 24 percent in the 1990's, hitting 15.2 million last year, while American trips to Mexico grew by 14 percent during the decade, hitting 18.3 million last year.</p>
        <p>Many Americans are lured by the Canadian dollar, which lingers near historically low levels. But while they may find good prices on their summer trip, they still find that coming north does not necessarily mean an escape from global warming. In mid-July, air-conditioners were going full blast in this city, 275 miles south of the Arctic Circle.</p>
        <p>''In Edmonton it was so hot we had to put things under the kickstands so the bikes wouldn't sink into the asphalt,'' said Lloyd Schaffer, a retired computer systems analyst who motorcycled here from Waterloo, Iowa, with a friend. ''We love Canada. The people are so friendly. The prices are good up here.''</p>
        <p>Canada's three northern territories, home to only 100,000 people sprinkled across 1.5 million square miles, have traditionally been seen as a preserve of the Indiana Jones adventure traveler.</p>
        <p>Now, with good hotels in every major town and increasingly reliable, if expensive, air links, it is often older and more affluent tourists who can be found here.</p>
        <p>''I loved it so much that we are going next year on a Russian icebreaker, from Churchill in the Hudson Bay to Greenland,'' said Sam Wagonfeld, a retired Denver child psychologist, after spending a week in July touring Eskimo villages and archaeological sites with his wife, Sally Allen. The five members of the tour group, who flew around Nunavut, Canada's new eastern Arctic territory, were all in their 60's.</p>
        <p>In Yellowknife, arriving visitors often say they are surprised by the amenities offered by this territorial capital of 18,000 people.</p>
        <p>Harry Symington, who moved here from Hong Kong to manage the Explorer, the city's largest hotel, said, ''People say: 'You've got a city here, high-rise buildings. We thought you would be living out of trailers.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
