<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE163DF93AA1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Belgrade Opposition Urges Anti-Milosevic Protests  Leaders of Serbia's opposition called a rally in Belgrade for this afternoon to ask the people to perform ''any act of civil disobedience they have at their disposal'' until President Slobodan Milosevic left office.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The opposition leader Vojislav Kostunica says that if he becomes president he will try to shape a country with a new sense of itself and its place in the world, a normal European nation, with skepticism for American foreign-policy goals.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Belgrade Opposition Urges Anti-Milosevic Protests  Leaders of Serbia's opposition called a rally in Belgrade for this afternoon to ask the people to perform ''any act of civil disobedience they have at their disposal'' until President Slobodan Milosevic left office.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The opposition leader Vojislav Kostunica says that if he becomes president he will try to shape a country with a new sense of itself and its place in the world, a normal European nation, with skepticism for American foreign-policy goals.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Agent Pressed on Lockerbie  An F.B.I. agent, cross-examined by lawyers for two Libyans accused of bombing Pan Am Flight 103, was vague about details of his investigation, including interviews with a Libyan double-agent whose testimony was also assailed by the defense.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Danes Deal a Blow to the Euro  Denmark voted not to join Europe's common currency, the euro, undermining an already fragile monetary experiment and turning its back on the rapid political integration championed by France and Germany.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Peru Leader in Washington  President Alberto K. Fujimori flew to Washington to seek support from the United States and inter-American countries and organizations for his plan to transfer power to an elected successor, American officials said. The officials said that Mr. Fujimori's hold on power remained precarious and that his dismissed intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos, who has strong ties to the military, remained capable of influencing events in Peru.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Clash at the Temple Mount  Ariel Sharon, the right-wing Israeli opposition leader, led a group of legislators under tight security onto the bitterly contested Temple Mount to assert Jewish claims there, setting off a stone-throwing clash that left several Palestinians and more than two dozen policemen injured.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Suharto Charges Dismissed  An Indonesian court dismissed the corruption case against former President Suharto after court-appointed doctors declared him medically unfit for trial. The announcement sparked violent clashes.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-23</p>
        <p>The Number of Uninsured Is Reported to Decline  The Census Bureau said the number of Americans without health insurance declined to 42.6 million, a reduction of 1.7 million from 1998 and a break with an 11-year trend.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Punishments at Nuclear Lab  Workers at the Los Alamos weapons lab have been notified that disciplinary actions, possibly including a dismissal, are imminent in the case of computer drives that vanished from a safe and were later found behind a copying machine at the lab.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Gore Hits Bush Tax Cuts  Vice President Al Gore said ''prosperity itself will be on the ballot'' on Nov. 7 and portrayed Gov. George W. Bush's tax cut proposal as a threat to the country's economic health.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Bush Hits Gore Spending Plans  Gov. George W. Bush tacitly praised President Clinton's past calls for an end to ''big government'' and said Vice President Al Gore was endangering prosperity by having ''cast his lot with the old Democratic party'' in proposing a new level of federal spending and regulation.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Move to Keep Money Flowing  The Senate passed a stopgap spending measure to allow the government to function through Oct. 6, seven days after the end of its fiscal year.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Pessimism on Climate Treaty  Several Republican senators expressed concern that talks to flesh out details of a global warming treaty signed by the Clinton administration in 1998 would never produce a document the Senate would pass.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>U.S. Loses Round on Tobacco  A federal judge in Washington threw out part of the government's suit against the tobacco industry, narrowing the avenues by which the Justice Department could seek billions of dollars in damages.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>New Charges for a Fugitive  A federal indictment accused Boston's most infamous, and elusive, mobster, James Bulger, and a longtime associate with involvement in the deaths of 21 people between them in ''a reign of intimidation and murder that spanned some 25 years.''</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Lazio to Speak at Event To Raise G.O.P. Soft Money  Rick A. Lazio, who has pressed to expunge soft money from the Senate race with Hillary Rodham Clinton, will be a featured speaker a fund-raising dinner expected to raise several million dollars in soft money for the State Republican Party.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Revamping Buildings Dept.  Mayor Giuliani announced steps to overhaul the Buildings Department, acknowledging that it has long been mired in systemic corruption.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Selling Off the Herd  Seventy-five of the 500 life-size cows in the public art event CowParade New York 2000 were auctioned off for charity. The rest of the herd is being auctioned online.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>French Abortion Pill  The F.D.A. approved the marketing of the abortion-inducing pill mifepristone, or RU-486. Its distributor said it would be available to doctors in about four weeks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Breast Cancer Study  A third of American women who had lumpectomies or other breast-conserving operations for early-stage breast cancer from 1990 to 1995 did not get other needed treatments.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Network Keeps Organ Contract  The government renewed its contract with the United Network for Organ Sharing, which runs the nation's organ transplant system, apparently ending a two-year dispute over the way organs are distributed.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-26; E27-40</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Pierre Trudeau  The former Canadian prime minister, who defended his vision of federalism and unity against the forces of Quebec separatism, was 80.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Frank Wills  The night watchman who discovered the Watergate burglary in 1972 was 52. The cause was reported to be a brain tumor.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-20</p>
        <p>Views of Time Warner Deals  European antitrust regulators plan to block Time Warner's joint venture with the British music conglomerate EMI Group but are much closer to approving Time Warner's $135 billion merger with America Online, people close to the talks said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Indicts Ex-Executives  Albert J. Bergonzi and Jay P. Gilbertson, former executives of a Georgia medical software concern, HBO &amp; Company, which was later acquired by McKesson, were accused of costing investors more than $9 billion through fraud schemes.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Saudis to Pump More Crude  Saudi Arabia pledged to pump more crude to weaken prices that have recently hit 10-year highs. The move undercut a display of unity by OPEC heads of state at the conclusion of their Venezuela summit meeting and sent prices tumbling nearly 4 percent, to $30.34 a barrel.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Another Loss, Still No Playoffs  The Yankees lost to the Tampa Bay Devil Rays, 11-3, and failed to clinch a spot in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
        <p>S1-8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Milosevic's trickery; importing cheaper drugs; Steven R. Weisman on Joseph Lieberman and Jewish law.</p>
        <p>Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E40  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E26  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
