<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up the Garden Path</title>
    <meta content="13EDERLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sabbagh, Karl</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rum Affair, A: A True Story of Botanical Fraud (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6D6163CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up the Garden Path</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Eder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews book A Rum Affair: A True Story of Botanical Fraud by Karl Sabbagh; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Rum Affair</p>
        <p>A True Story of Botanical Fraud.</p>
        <p>By Karl Sabbagh.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Rum Affair</p>
        <p>A True Story of Botanical Fraud.</p>
        <p>By Karl Sabbagh.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $24.</p>
        <p>In the late 1940's, John Raven, a British classics scholar and avid amateur botanizer, exposed a biology panjandrum, Prof. John Heslop Harrison of the Royal Society, for fraudulently introducing alien sedges on the Hebridean island of Rum in order to advance a pet theory. Exposed him in a manner of speaking, that is. Having investigated zealously and written a fiery report, Raven sealed it in his college library.</p>
        <p>Karl Sabbagh has unsealed it in ''A Rum Affair.'' A mix of engaging wit and serious inquiry, his book is several things. It gives as many details as could be found of a half-century-old scientific scandal that is perhaps only ostensibly teapot-size. It is a portrait of the academic ecosystem, with its backbiting and back-watching. It is a portrait of the larky upper-class sleuth of King's College, Cambridge, and his thunderous middle-class quarry at the red-brick University of Newcastle -- Victorians both, in eccentricity and the class gulf, and a reminder just how far into the 20th century the Victorian tide ran. It is a fairly light though interesting discussion of the occasional hiccup in science's cycle. (Tedious observation gives birth to dizzying theory, which gives birth, usually, to further observation, but once in a while -- in the certainty that the theory is sound, revolutionary and worthy of honors -- to cutting a corner or two.)</p>
        <p>And, finally, ''A Rum Affair'' belongs to the seemingly inexhaustible genre of What a Strange People the English Are. (There is a French genre too.) It should be added that ''Rum'' is a very pleasurable example; and that there are no better masters at finding life in their national cliches than the English themselves.</p>
        <p>Surely, English eccentricity has been more than a comic trait. You could argue that it was a substitute for revolution. You could even argue that it was a substitute for religion, blossoming as faith inclined to rigidify and evaporate at the same time. If you're no longer quite sure that God invented you in his image, the possibility remains of inventing yourself in your own image.</p>
        <p>There is a fine eccentricity on display throughout Sabbagh's book -- for instance in his account of stumbling upon his story. A King's College man himself, he read the obituaries in the college newsletter for lines such as these:</p>
        <p>''In College, he organized nocturnal races, naked except for gowns, on the older Fellows' tricycles.''</p>
        <p>''He served as a surgeon sublieutenant in destroyers . . . and remembered his ship shelling the British lines in Gallipoli, a mistake he attributed to his commanding officer's breakfasting on port and pineapple chunks.''</p>
        <p>Then one day Sabbagh came upon an obituary of Raven, with a brief mention of his having produced a damning, unpublished report about ''a reputable biologist.'' The item stuck in his mind for 17 years or so until he mentioned it to a botanist, who identified the man and suggested that the scandal was widely known in the profession. Sabbagh, a writer and television producer, was duly uncorked.</p>
        <p>''A Rum Affair'' sets out the case that Raven developed against Harrison, and touches on other areas in which Harrison, a major figure in his field, may have faked results. His sightings of the Large Blue butterfly were fraudulent, one naturalist insisted to Sabbagh. The same for water beetles, a leading water-beetle man claimed.</p>
        <p>Harrison's thesis asserted that parts of the Hebrides had escaped the ice age. His ''evidence'' was a dozen or so species of lichens and other plants, virtually nonexistent on the mainland, that he claimed to have found on Rum. This could have indicated that the ice sheets that destroyed such plants elsewhere had spared Rum. Or -- what a number of other botanists suspected and Raven set out to investigate -- it could point to evidence-rigging: maybe the plants Harrison said he had found, he had brought with him.</p>
        <p>When Raven discovered nine or ten specimens of the Carex bicolor sedge growing neatly in a cleared spot (one wilted, as if badly planted) and nowhere else on the island; when specimens of two ''surviving'' species were found in a single clump -- and again, nowhere else; and when the soil from one of Harrison's specimens differed from the soil where it reportedly grew, the case seemed clear.</p>
        <p>Raven printed some of his findings in Nature in 1949, though without accusing Harrison. As a result, a number of species were subsequently de-listed in the botany registers. Harrison wrote to Raven charging betrayal and conspiracy, but he was able to keep his professorship and much of his reputation as biology's grand, if difficult, old man. What the public was spared, though, and the insiders only whispered, was gorily dismembered in Raven's 12,000-word report. He concluded:</p>
        <p>''That the Professor is deliberately indulging in the most culpable dishonesty in order to secure for himself an immediate reputation and an immortal place in the annals of British botany.'' Raven's next words reflected the class aspect of the drama: ''The Professor is clearly a man of very humble origin: he is in fact, I have been told credibly enough, the son of a miner. He is obviously able and almost equally obviously ambitious.''</p>
        <p>Two men. One resting, despite nervous tummy, on privilege passed down from his his father: Canon Charles Raven, Master of Cambridge's Christ's College and himself a well-connected botanizer. The other an ironworker's (not a miner's) son. One was graceful, witty, self-deprecating; a gentleman warrior and lethal. The other was pale, with glaring black eyes and a Hitler mustache; all assertion and no humor at all. He was generous to his disciples and ruthless when any disagreed with him. He lacked the tentativeness expected of British academics when voicing their certainties. No ''it would seem'' for him; only ''it is.''</p>
        <p>Harrison was ''the type of which dictators are made,'' Raven wrote, and a number of his colleagues were happy to see him upended. Privately, it is true, but in a still class-ridden Britain, a fact was more of a fact if it was private.</p>
        <p>Raven was right, of course; but perhaps there was a certain situational rightness in the decision not to publish. Botany for him was a morality and a passion; but it was a curatorial passion, quite separate from position (his was assured), as well as from science's churning hunger to see beyond what can be seen. In Harrison, up from the foundry, passion and position were inseparable. To a true scientist, science is both identity and wings; and so it was for Harrison, crooked flight and all.</p>
        <p>Richard Eder writes book reviews and articles for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Eder writes book reviews and articles for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
