<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3D81E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>W.H.O. Report Details Tobacco Company Tactics  Industry documents show that cigarette makers took part for years in a campaign to influence and undermine the World Health Organization's antismoking efforts worldwide, the agency said. The document also accuses leading tobacco companies of using a network of front organizations and groups with industry ties to thwart the organization.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Pinochet May Lose Immunity  The Chilean Supreme Court voted in secret to strip Gen. Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, according to radio and news Web site accounts in Santiago. Such a decision would remove the last legal obstacle to a full criminal inquiry and would let the former dictator be tried.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>W.H.O. Report Details Tobacco Company Tactics  Industry documents show that cigarette makers took part for years in a campaign to influence and undermine the World Health Organization's antismoking efforts worldwide, the agency said. The document also accuses leading tobacco companies of using a network of front organizations and groups with industry ties to thwart the organization.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Pinochet May Lose Immunity  The Chilean Supreme Court voted in secret to strip Gen. Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, according to radio and news Web site accounts in Santiago. Such a decision would remove the last legal obstacle to a full criminal inquiry and would let the former dictator be tried.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Life for G.I. in Kosovo Killing  A United States military court in Germany sentenced Staff Sgt. Frank J. Ronghi to life in prison without parole for the murder of an 11-year-old Kosovo Albanian girl. His sentence is the most severe available to an American military court holding a trial in Germany, where the death penalty does not exist.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Bosnian in U.S. Civil Case  A civil lawsuit against Dr. Radovan Karadzic, the former leader of the Bosnian Serbs, began in federal court in Manhattan with a witness fainting on the stand as she described her captivity, rape and torture during the Balkans conflict in 1992. Dr. Karadzic has been indicted for genocide by the international war crimes tribunal in The Hague, but has avoided capture and is believed to be hiding in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>American Family Sues Syria  The family of an Israeli-American, Ira Weinstein, killed in a 1996 terrorist attack in Jerusalem, filed suit in New York against Syria, contending that it had provided critical support to Hamas, the militant Palestinian group whose members carried out the suicide bombing.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Israeli Leader Faces the Right  Prime Minister Ehud Barak's political problems deepened as his right-wing opponents, sensing blood with their defeat of Shimon Peres, his presidential candidate, vowed to bring down his government.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Clashes Over Venezuela Vote  President Hugo Chavez used troops to quash street protests and remove an opposition party governor who had accused the governing party of trying to alter the outcome of elections last weekend.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>No Clues in Concorde Debris  French investigators said they had not found any engine parts in the trail of debris shed by an Air France Concorde on its brief flight before crashing near Charles de Gaulle Airport outside Paris on July 25. In a statement, the Bureau of Accident Investigations also said it had found no evidence of any ''particular problem before the departure of the flight.''</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-23</p>
        <p>McCain Vouches for Bush On Handling Foreign Policy  Senator John McCain shed his rebellious image to play admiring party stalwart atthe Republican National Convention, commending Gov. George W. Bush to independents and Democrats. He and other military heroes who spoke offered assurances that Mr. Bush would ably defend national interests abroad. Joining the chorus and delivering the other high-profile speech was Condoleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's chief international affairs adviser who, as an African American, also underscores his pledge to place members of minorities in consequential roles.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Former President George Bush put President Clinton on notice over Mr. Clinton's belittling of his son.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Television ratings indicated only a small fraction of the prime-time audience watched the first night.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia police arrested scores of protesters seeking to disrupt the convention with illegal hit-and-run demonstrations that snarled evening rush-hour traffic.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The Elite of G.O.P. Donors  The Republican Party's platinum-level sponsors, the Republican Regents, are a group of 139 people and corporations that party officials say have each given at least $250,000 in soft money since January 1999. But federal campaign records show only 54 corporations and individuals as having given that much, because some donors have split their donations into smaller checks, at the suggestion of party officials.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Study Questions Brady Law  There is no evidence that the Brady law requiring background checks of handgun buyers reduced homicide rates since it took effect in 1994, a study in The Journal of the American Medical Association reported. The Clinton administration and others quickly criticized the report.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The Rise of an Illicit Drug  Drug experts warned that the use of the psychedelic drug Ecstasy has risen sharply, particularly among young people, raising fears that government faces a major new front in its efforts to curb illegal drugs.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Heat Wave Draining the West  A lingering heat wave in the West drove demand for electric power in California near record levels and brought the state close to a full-scale power emergency.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Bankruptcy Fraud Charges For Fallen Stock Promoter  Robert E. Brennan, a prominent pitchman for hot, little-known stocks that he promoted in the 1980's in television ads for his First Jersey Securities, was charged with criminal fraud involving a bankruptcy claim, and, for the first time, he could face a prison term. Though he has lost or settled civil cases and owes $200 million in fines and restitution to defrauded investors, he has never before been charged with a crime.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>An Online Real Estate Lode  New York City's three largest real estate brokerage firms plan to share listings by combining them into one huge database that buyers and renters can view on the Internet.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Giuliani's Cancer Treatment  Mayor Giuliani acknowledged that he has been having hormone treatments for his prostate cancer for two and a half months. He indicated that this was a preliminary therapy.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>The School of Business  Columbia University is venturing further and faster than its peer institutions in forming partnerships with Internet businesses, reflecting a shift in academic culture.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Plan to Aid Worst Schools  Chancellor Harold O. Levy announced a plan to lure experienced instructors from private and parochial schools into the poorest public schools by raising starting pay.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>New Approach on Warming  The United States, preparing for international talks on cutting levels of heat-trapping gases that may be warming the climate, wants countries to get as much credit for using forests and fields to sop up carbon dioxide as for cutting emissions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Early Abuse, Later Stress  Women physically or sexually abused in childhood show exaggerated physiological responses to stressful events, a study found.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-20</p>
        <p>Selling Priceline Shares  Jay S. Walker, the founder of Priceline.com, agreed to sell $190 million of his shares to Liberty Media and Paul Allen's Vulcan Ventures. Mr. Walker said he would invest the after-tax proceeds of $125 million in Priceline's WebHouse Club, an affiliate that sells groceries and gas.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Mixed Reports on Auto Sales  G.M. and DaimlerChrysler said sales fell in July, leaving both unable to reduce bloated inventories of minivans, pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles. But Ford and foreign automakers announced strong sales and balanced inventories.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>P.&amp; G. Performance Lags  Procter &amp; Gamble, beset by rising costs, management turmoil and credibility problems on Wall Street, reported fourth-quarter results in line with lowered forecasts. The company also said earnings growth in the first half of its new fiscal year would be sluggish.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C21</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: The defense debate begins; consolidating power in Venezuela; Brent Staples on the G.O.P. convention's minstrelsy.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
