<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate Rises Over a Quick(er) Climate Fix</title>
    <meta content="03GREE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/science/03GREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001004T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soot</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hague (Netherlands)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/The Hague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0DE133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate Rises Over a Quick(er) Climate Fix</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atmospheric scientists differ on where to aim efforts to stave off prospect of global warming from buildup of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere; some say main target should be carbon dioxide, most common greenhouse gas, while others say most practical solution is to focus first on less common, but more powerful substances possibly influencing climate, like methane, ozone and soot; debate comes just as negotiators from more than 150 countries prepare to head to The Hague to put flesh on bones of 1997 Kyoto Protocol, treaty outlining commitments by industrialized countries to reduce their greenhouse emissions and help poor countries avoid new emissions as their economies grow; photos; graphs; chart (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sharp new debate has sprung up among atmospheric scientists over where to aim efforts to stave off the prospect of global warming from the buildup of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Some say the main target should be carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas, while others say the most practical solution is to focus first on less common, but more powerful, substances possibly influencing climate, like methane, ozone and soot.</p>
        <p>The debate comes just as negotiators from more than 150 countries are preparing to head to The Hague next month to put flesh on the bones of the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, a treaty outlining commitments by industrialized countries to reduce their greenhouse emissions and help poor countries avoid new emissions as their economies grow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sharp new debate has sprung up among atmospheric scientists over where to aim efforts to stave off the prospect of global warming from the buildup of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Some say the main target should be carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas, while others say the most practical solution is to focus first on less common, but more powerful, substances possibly influencing climate, like methane, ozone and soot.</p>
        <p>The debate comes just as negotiators from more than 150 countries are preparing to head to The Hague next month to put flesh on the bones of the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, a treaty outlining commitments by industrialized countries to reduce their greenhouse emissions and help poor countries avoid new emissions as their economies grow.</p>
        <p>The argument for attacking the less common greenhouse ingredients is mainly based on the idea that these substances contribute to harmful air pollution as well as climate change -- and so an easier case can be made to policy makers and the public to clean them up.</p>
        <p>They are also relatively easy to attack with existing or developing technologies, whereas carbon dioxide can still generally be reduced only by burning less fuel.</p>
        <p>Proponents of this strategy, most notably Dr. James E. Hansen, an influential NASA climate expert, say that cutting carbon dioxide, at least in the short term, is a far more daunting task because it is a basic byproduct of burning coal and oil. In other words it is a basic byproduct of almost every aspect of modern life.</p>
        <p>But there are problems with focusing on other heat-trapping substances, as well, other scientists say. Soot and the other greenhouse gases, they argue, constitute an extraordinarily complex brew whose influence on climate and interactions with each other and with clouds and other atmospheric ingredients are still poorly understood.</p>
        <p>''When you add in their chemical interactions, most scientists' eyes glaze over, it's so complicated,'' said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric chemist who is chief scientist of Environmental Defense, a private conservation group.</p>
        <p>The debate was spurred last August, when Dr. Hansen and a team of his colleagues at NASA's Goddard Institute for Space Studies, which is based in Manhattan, published ''Global Warming in the 21st Century: An Alternative Scenario,'' in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>In the paper, they said that deep cuts in carbon dioxide emissions were probably impossible in the short run, while the other gases and soot were already targets because of their contribution to old-fashioned pollution. In its conclusion, the team used a word rarely found in studies of global warming: ''optimistic.''</p>
        <p>The analysis has since been criticized by some longtime colleagues of Dr. Hansen and embraced by industry groups and elected officials who have long voiced doubt about the science behind climate change and the need for big cuts in fossil fuel use.</p>
        <p>Just last Thursday, for example, Dr. Hansen's findings were repeatedly cited by Republican senators holding a hearing questioning the need for the Kyoto Protocol, which has been signed by more than 100 countries but has yet to be ratified by any industrial powers. Many of the treaty's provisions focus on cutting carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen's critics, including many influential experts on the atmosphere and climate, say that emissions of all of the gases should be curtailed wherever this is possible and not too expensive but that cutting carbon dioxide must still be a top priority.</p>
        <p>For his part, Dr. Hansen said that both sides in the debate had largely either misrepresented or misinterpreted his study. He said the fundamental goal was simply to find the most efficient -- and politically and economically palatable -- way to cleanse the atmosphere of human effluents that have the biggest impact on climate.</p>
        <p>He said he still hoped that once the dust settled, policy makers from all parts of the spectrum might find merit in the proposal.</p>
        <p>''I think it may be possible to get conservatives and liberals to agree on common-sense steps that slow down the climate experiment,'' Dr. Hansen said.</p>
        <p>The ''climate experiment'' to which he referred is a substantial rise in the amount of greenhouse gases released into the air by human activities since the start of the Industrial Revolution. So far, the insulating effect of these gases is the equivalent of turning on two one-watt Christmas tree light bulbs over each square yard of the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>That does not seem like much additional energy, Dr. Hansen said, but as a comparison he and others have calculated that the extra wattage accounting for the difference between the last ice age and current equable conditions is 6 to 9 watts per square yard.</p>
        <p>If greenhouse gas concentrations continue to rise, the human-caused increase in energy bathing the surface could exceed four watts per square yard, a rise that begins to approach the change from the last ice age until now. That is bound to jog climate, Dr. Hansen said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen, besides being a respected climate scientist, is an inveterate pot stirrer who in the sweltering summer of 1988 told a Senate committee ''it is time to stop waffling'' about climate change, adding that signs had emerged that humans were causing some of the global warming measured in the 20th century.</p>
        <p>His new analysis is clearly intended to provoke his peers to re-examine assumptions made over the last 10 years, particularly by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, a body of hundreds of scientists working together under the auspices of the United Nations to assess global warming and possible responses. Their first update in five years is due in January.</p>
        <p>Most atmospheric scientists have long recognized that more than a dozen greenhouse gases and various kinds of particles emitted by combustion and industry affect the flow of energy to and from the earth. (Most particles reflect sunlight like a parasol, cooling the planet; carbon soot tends to absorb energy and heat up.)</p>
        <p>But for the last decade, carbon dioxide has been the main target of climate experts and diplomats trying to stabilize climate. Its concentration in the atmosphere has risen by a third from levels seen before the Industrial Revolution; once added to the air, it takes many decades to disappear; and levels could double from pre-industrial amounts by the end of the new century, scientists project. Also important, it is relatively easy to measure the emissions and their sources and ''sinks,'' and processes that remove them from the air are fairly well understood.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Hansen noted that carbon dioxide emissions are not continuing their relentless climb at anywhere near the pace set in the last century, as fuels are used more efficiently and dirty ones, like coal, are supplanted by cleaner ones, like natural gas.</p>
        <p>Rather than seeking relatively costly additional cuts in carbon dioxide now, he said, the best return on an environmental investment in the short term would be to look at the other greenhouse culprits on his list. Then, later in the new century, when technologies have matured that offer sources of energy without new streams of carbon dioxide, the emphasis can shift back to that gas.</p>
        <p>Here is his thinking on the best targets for action now.</p>
        <p>First there is black carbon -- microscopic soot particles released from inefficient diesel engines, unfiltered power plants or burning forests. These tiny particles, besides harming lungs, absorb heat and also -- like other particles in the air -- form seeds for cloud droplets. They tend to make clouds darker, Dr. Hansen says, reducing clouds' tendency to reflect sunlight and make the earth's surface cooler.</p>
        <p>He said that if continuing efforts to reduce conventional pollution from fossil-fuel burning spread from wealthy countries to developing countries, the amount of this heat-trapping substance in the air would quickly drop.</p>
        <p>Methane is on most lists of priorities for reducing the greenhouse effect, and Dr. Hansen said it had, if anything, been underplayed as an important target. Methane comes both from natural sources like bogs and from a host of human sources, including coal mines, leaking pipelines, landfills, belching cattle and rice paddies.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen's study concluded that efforts to shift to rice-farming methods where fields are drained more frequently could cut releases. Also, his team pointed to Australian research showing that changing feeding patterns or mixing certain anti-gas additives in feed for tropical cattle cut by 40 percent their release of this gas without interfering with growth. With two billion cows, sheep, and goats belching away -- half of them in the tropics -- there is plenty of potential to cut into the greenhouse effect, he and supporters say.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Goddard analysis emphasizes the importance of reducing ozone, an evanescent gas that is not on the list of greenhouse gases considered under the Kyoto Protocol because it is not directly produced by human activities.</p>
        <p>Ozone, a poisonous molecule consisting of three oxygen atoms, is continually formed and destroyed when sunlight hits air, particularly when that air is laden with nitrogen oxides, hydrocarbons, or other emissions from burning fuels or forests. This is the lung-searing brew called smog.</p>
        <p>Separately, ozone is formed high in the stratosphere, where it shields the planet from harmful radiation. Wherever it exists, it traps heat.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen said that as with carbon soot, as China, Mexico and other industrializing countries start to enact pollution controls to cut smog, they will also indirectly be lessening their greenhouse impact.</p>
        <p>But other scientists say the situation is not that clear-cut. One reason ozone has largely been left out of greenhouse equations so far is that its relationships with other greenhouse gases and other compounds in the air are almost impossibly complex.</p>
        <p>For example, extremely reactive hydroxyl radicals, OH, which are created as ozone encounters other compounds, destroy methane molecules. In essence, one greenhouse gas eats the other.</p>
        <p>''OH is the detergent of the atmosphere, scrubbing everything,'' said Dr. Monika Mayer, a research scientist in the climate program at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. She published a study last month in The Journal of Geophysical Research -- Atmospheres in which she and several colleagues concluded that future trends for ozone and methane would largely cancel each other out.</p>
        <p>Generally, she said, models show that although ozone should increase in cities, on average around the globe levels should drop, and this will allow methane to persist longer in the air because there will be fewer hydroxyl radicals there to destroy it.</p>
        <p>The effects of all of this on climate, she concluded in the paper, are likely to be a wash.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ralph J. Cicerone, an atmospheric scientist and chancellor of the University of California at Irvine, said he agreed with Dr. Hansen that the complexity of chemistry in the atmosphere should not deter efforts to cut ozone, methane and other substances that contribute both to pollution and climate problems.</p>
        <p>He pointed to recent work showing that although levels of ozone and nitrogen oxides, which help create ozone, have been dropping over the United States and western Europe, they are relentlessly rising elsewhere.</p>
        <p>One study, Dr. Cicerone said, showed that nitrogen oxide concentrations in China, South Korea, Taiwan and Japan rose 60 percent from 1997 to 1998. There is plenty of concrete benefit to be gained, with little of the potential pain that might come from putting the same effort into reducing carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>But other scientists fear that any shift away from reducing burning of coal and oil would only impede long-term progress toward limiting the human influence on climate.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing is to stabilize all these emissions,'' said Dr. Thomas P. Ackerman, chief scientist in the Energy Department's atmospheric radiation measurement program in Richland, Wash. ''And there's no way you're going to do that without attacking the fossil-fuel problem. We're a society that likes to have simple solutions, but there are no easy answers here.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Dr. Hansen seems satisfied simply to have nudged the climate debate toward considering partial, common-sense solutions that he feels have been neglected.</p>
        <p>He added that one way to spur interest would be to illustrate the other harmful qualities of the greenhouse ingredients on his list up close and personal.</p>
        <p>Maybe, he said, it would make sense to ''lock people in a room with a good bit of ozone and black carbon in the air until they come up with some positive ideas.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 4, 2000, Wednesday  An article in Science Times yesterday about efforts to stave off global warming misstated the period in which emissions of nitrogen oxides from four Asian countries rose 60 percent. It was 1987 to 1998, not 1997 to 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 4, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about efforts to stave off global warming misstated the period in which emissions of nitrogen oxides from four Asian countries rose 60 percent. It was 1987 to 1998, not 1997 to 1998.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
