<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping Deadly Gas Out of Home</title>
    <meta content="21HOME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DF143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping Deadly Gas Out of Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column offers advice on preventing carbon monoxide poisoning; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR anyone who heard or read accounts of the deaths of six people from carbon monoxide poisoning in a home in Roslyn Heights, N.Y., earlier this month, the initial reactions of shock, horror and sadness are likely to have been followed by a chilling realization: ''That could have been me. That could have been my family.''</p>
        <p>''Tragedies like this happen, or come close to happening, more frequently than you might think,'' said Dr. Thomas H. Greiner, an associate professor at Iowa State University in Ames. ''But fortunately, they're almost always preventable.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR anyone who heard or read accounts of the deaths of six people from carbon monoxide poisoning in a home in Roslyn Heights, N.Y., earlier this month, the initial reactions of shock, horror and sadness are likely to have been followed by a chilling realization: ''That could have been me. That could have been my family.''</p>
        <p>''Tragedies like this happen, or come close to happening, more frequently than you might think,'' said Dr. Thomas H. Greiner, an associate professor at Iowa State University in Ames. ''But fortunately, they're almost always preventable.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Greiner, who specializes in housing issues in the university's department of agricultural and biosystems engineering, said that carbon monoxide poisoning has ''haunted mankind since the discovery of fire and remains the most common cause of death due to poisoning.'' In fact, in the United States each year 3,500 to 4,000 deaths are attributable to carbon monoxide poisoning.</p>
        <p>Of those deaths, ''fires cause approximately two-thirds of the known fatalities,'' he said, ''with automobile exhaust and faulty heating equipment causing the remaining one-third.''</p>
        <p>In homes, Dr. Greiner said, the place where carbon monoxide is most likely to be found is in the garage. And since carbon monoxide has about the same density as the surrounding air, it can easily seep into the house from the garage through even tiny cracks and openings. With that in mind, Dr. Greiner said that the garage door should always be opened before starting the car and  the amount of time the car idles in the garage should be kept to a minimum. Likewise, he said, when returning home, the engine should be turned off immediately after entering the garage and certainly before the door is closed.</p>
        <p>While such advice may appear rather obvious, he said, there are a great many incidents of increased levels of carbon monoxide inside the home that are caused by the migration of fumes from the garage to the living space. That happens most often, he said, when a homeowner starts the car in the garage on a cold morning, when the fuel mixture is at its richest, and then lets the car idle for a few minutes to warm up.</p>
        <p>''Even though you may have opened the garage door,'' he said, ''just a couple of minutes of running the car when the engine is cold can put a huge amount of carbon monoxide in the garage.'' Then, he said, when the car is backed out and the door is closed, the gas slowly seeps into the house.</p>
        <p>''Carbon monoxide is an extremely dangerous poison because it cannot be seen, smelled or tasted,'' Dr. Greiner said. ''And breathing air with a concentration of just one hundred parts per million of carbon monoxide for two hours can cause poisoning symptoms.''</p>
        <p>Even more troubling, he said, is that early symptoms, which are similar to those of the  flu, may not even be noticed. ''Because carbon monoxide reduces oxygen delivery to the brain,'' Dr. Greiner said, ''persons with elevated levels in their blood do not think clearly and might not recognize the warning signs.''</p>
        <p>There are other potential sources of the carbon dioxide inside the house itself. For example, he said, carbon monoxide can be created by unvented appliances like gas stoves, ovens and clothes dryers. It can also be produced by gas- or oil-burning heating systems and gas water heaters.</p>
        <p>''It is vital to have the heating system checked by an expert at least once a year,'' he said, explaining that an improperly adjusted furnace or water heater can produce large amounts of carbon monoxide. And while the exhaust gases from such appliances are generally vented out of the house through the chimney, problems can occur, for example, when there are leaks or openings in the ducts of a hot-air heating system.</p>
        <p>In some cases, he said, a furnace in a small utility room can pull in so much air that it creates negative pressure. If that happens, it is possible for gases that might otherwise go up the chimney to be sucked into the ducts and be distributed throughout the house.</p>
        <p>Investigators said that something similar happened in the house in Roslyn Heights, on Long Island. They also noted that the house had a carbon monoxide detector but that it had been disconnected last summer  because it kept going off.</p>
        <p>''As houses become tighter, providing proper combustion air and avoiding excessive depressurization is critical,'' Dr. Greiner said. Highly efficient weatherization and insulation, and enclosing furnaces and water heaters in tightly constructed utility rooms, can adversely affect the safe operation of the heating system.</p>
        <p>An even more dangerous situation can result when furnaces, water heaters and appliances like clothes dryers are not properly vented.</p>
        <p>''All it takes to have a serious problem is for a squirrel or a bird to build a nest in the chimney,'' said Robert Bellini, an owner of Varsity Plumbing, a plumbing and heating contractor in Flushing, Queens.  When that happens, he said, exhaust gases from a furnace or water heater will back up into the house. And while the homeowner might smell the exhaust gases from an oil-fired furnace, those from a gas-fired furnace or water heater might not be noticed.</p>
        <p>''Another big source of problems are do-it-yourselfers,'' Mr. Bellini said. ''You can go out to a home center and buy a hot water heater, and the guy at the store will give you tips on how to install it yourself,'' he said. ''What they don't tell you is that the new unit you bought may need a different flue size than the original one. Or that the vent piping has to go together a certain way and with a certain pitch. And they usually don't tell you to inspect the chimney.''</p>
        <p>Apart from having appliances professionally installed and maintained, Mr. Bellini said, the most significant step that homeowners can take is to buy a carbon monoxide detector and alarm.</p>
        <p>''Unless you have an all-electric house, you should definitely have an alarm,'' he said. ''And I highly recommend an alarm that has an LCD screen with a digital display.'' Such an alarm, he said, will provide a homeowner with a visible indication of how many parts per million of carbon monoxide are in the air.</p>
        <p>''The display will alert you to the fact that carbon monoxide is building up before the alarm even sounds,'' he said, adding that such a detector would also make it possible for the homeowner to address the problem before it became dangerous.</p>
        <p>Mark Scheifer, the vice president for marketing for Kidde Safety in Mebane, N.C., said that carbon monoxide detectors, with or without a digital display, can be battery-powered or plug-in units.</p>
        <p>''On the plug-in models, we recommend one with a battery backup,'' he said, to keep the unit operating if the electricity goes off.</p>
        <p>The prices for carbon monoxide detectors range from about $20 to $50.</p>
        <p>Debbie Hanson, the director of external affairs for First Alert, an alarm manufacturer in Aurora, Ill.,  said that if there is only one carbon monoxide detector in a house, it should be installed in the hallway outside the sleeping area.</p>
        <p>''If you have an additional alarm, you can put it in the family room or the recreation room,'' she said. Since carbon monoxide is about the same weight as air, she said, it is generally not necessary to mount the units on the ceiling.</p>
        <p>''You can sit it on a shelf or mount it on a wall,'' she said. ''And if the alarm goes off, make sure you find out why. Just because you may not be feeling any symptoms doesn't mean there isn't a problem.''</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
