<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore, Invoking Spirit of 'Silent Spring' Author, Talks of Defending Environment</title>
    <meta content="13DEMS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ON THE TRAIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barstow, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carson, Rachel (1907-64)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Silent Spring (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3D6123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore, Invoking Spirit of 'Silent Spring' Author, Talks of Defending Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARSTOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barstow, David</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGDALE, Pa., Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, who has endorsements of major environmental groups, sees environment as issue on which he has decided edge over Gov George W Bush; Gore visits Springdale, Pa, homestead of Rachel Carson, and claims spiritual kinship with author of book that is widely regarded as founding document in environmental movement, Silent Spring; Gore's apparent strategy of blending rhetoric of environmental awareness with larger populist theme of 'fighting for the people' and taking on big business is aimed chiefly at Bush, but also at Ralph Nader, who, according to some polls, is eating into Gore's voter base with appeals to environmental advocates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there is an issue in which Vice President Al Gore feels he has a decided edge over Gov. George W. Bush, it is the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has written a best-seller on the subject; he has the endorsements of the major environmental groups and, as he loves to note, Mr. Bush presides over a state that consistently ranks at or near the bottom for air and water quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there is an issue in which Vice President Al Gore feels he has a decided edge over Gov. George W. Bush, it is the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has written a best-seller on the subject; he has the endorsements of the major environmental groups and, as he loves to note, Mr. Bush presides over a state that consistently ranks at or near the bottom for air and water quality.</p>
        <p>Today, with some polls showing him gaining ground on Mr. Bush, Mr. Gore stood on a ridge overlooking the Allegheny River and claimed spiritual kinship with the late Rachel Carson, who in 1962 wrote ''Silent Spring,'' widely regarded as a founding document in the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carson was born here, an Allegheny Valley town 12 miles northeast of Pittsburgh, and Mr. Gore came here intent on drawing parallels between her life's work and his own passion for the environment. Like Ms. Carson, he said, he spent time in his youth wandering his family's farm in Carthage, Tenn., ''looking for critters'' and learning to love nature.</p>
        <p>He recalled how, when he was a teenager, his mother bought a copy of ''Silent Spring'' and then spent the next few weeks over breakfast discussing with Mr. Gore and his sister, Nancy, the book's warning against pesticides and other chemicals.</p>
        <p>Where Ms. Carson had started studying the environment as a teenager, publishing her first article at age 14, Mr. Gore recalled studying at Harvard University under Professor Roger Revelle, a pioneer in researching the atmospheric effects of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>''A long time ago,'' Mr. Gore told several hundred people gathered on the lawn of Springdale High School, ''I joined with the spirit of Rachel Carson in committing myself to a new springtime filled with the sounds of wild birds, with the sounds of children learning about and appreciating the environment.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Carson's work, which first drew attention to the dangers of DDT, has been criticized by chemical manufacturers and some scientists. She has been accused of overstating the case against pesticides, of abandoning objectivity for bitter polemics.</p>
        <p>But her main findings about the dangers of pesticides and insecticides to the environment continue to have broad acceptance, and Mr. Gore again drew a parallel with his own 1992 book that warned against the dangers of global warning.</p>
        <p>''When she published 'Silent Spring,' she was the target of a very well-orchestrated, well-financed attack from special interests that were profiting from pollution,'' he said. He mocked industry advertisements showing children walking through clouds of pesticides to demonstrate their harmlessness, and likewise, he said, he had been the target of similar corporate ''propaganda''</p>
        <p>''When I published 'Earth in the Balance,' '' he said, ''I became the subject of a lot of attacks, and I want you to know I wear those attacks as a badge of honor.''</p>
        <p>Although much of Mr. Gore's performance here today amounted to a routine stump speech on a favorite subject, it also demonstrated something about his overall campaign strategy. Mr. Gore, several of his aides said, is determined to blend the rhetoric of environmental awareness with his larger populist theme of ''fighting for the people'' and taking on big business.</p>
        <p>It is a strategy aimed chiefly at Mr. Bush, whom the Gore campaign has accused of being a captive of big oil.</p>
        <p>''Follow the smoke to the campaign contributions,'' said Chris Lehane, Mr. Gore's campaign press secretary.</p>
        <p>But the strategy is also aimed at Ralph Nader, the consumer advocate and Green Party candidate who, according to some polls, has been eating into Mr. Gore's voter base with appeals to environmental advocates and union members, particularly in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ON THE TRAIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
