<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D6173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Leaders of Syria Building Support for Son of Assad  The party and nation that Hafez al-Assad ruled for 30 years until his death on Saturday moved swiftly to anoint his son, Bashar, as Syria's new president, raising prospects that at least the nominal trappings of power in the highly militarized state may pass peacefully to a new generation. The younger Mr. Assad secured a number of new titles and positions, cementing his claim to his father's job.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Leaders of Syria Building Support for Son of Assad  The party and nation that Hafez al-Assad ruled for 30 years until his death on Saturday moved swiftly to anoint his son, Bashar, as Syria's new president, raising prospects that at least the nominal trappings of power in the highly militarized state may pass peacefully to a new generation. The younger Mr. Assad secured a number of new titles and positions, cementing his claim to his father's job.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israeli leaders proclaimed that the death of Mr. Assad, a sworn enemy of their state, ushered out an old era in the Middle East. But no one could predict what that portended beyond a potentially problematic transition period.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Damascus was a contrast in silence -- of mourning and secretive political maneuvering -- and the noisy grief of tens of thousands of people. Public gatherings are not generally permitted, but residents of the capital streamed into the streets, watched by security guards.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>In a border village in the Golan Heights, members of Mr. Assad's minority Alawite sect chanted and wept in a demonstration of loyalty to Syria at a memorial ceremony with a peculiar twist. After Israel's recent withdrawal from Lebanon, United Nations teams surveying the border determined that part of it actually lies in Lebanon. The villagers bitterly oppose being divided.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Korean Summit Hopes Still High  South Korean officials remained confident that the first summit meeting with North Korea would proceed normally tomorrow despite an unexpected 24-hour delay. North Korean officials surprised their southern counterparts with a request for the delay of the three-day meeting because of unspecified ''minor technical reasons.''</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Push to Weaken World Court  The United States, isolated among the nations of the world, is going into a crucial conference on the soon-to-be-established International Criminal Court still asking for changes in its charter. Unless some compromise can be found, legal experts say, a major step in international law will be taken without United States participation, even though Americans have been at the forefront of demanding trials for leaders like Pol Pot and Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Montenegro Vote as Barometer  Montenegrins voted in two local elections that were being closely watched as a barometer of relations between the small Western-leaning republic and President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia. Both outsiders and residents fear that a rupture with Belgrade would cause another of the Balkan wars that have erupted since the old Communist Yugoslavia began splitting apart.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A Battle in Congo Ends  Rwandan troops drove Ugandan forces from Congo's third-largest city after a fierce seven-hour battle that ended a week of widespread shelling and enabled the United Nations to deploy forces between the two armies and prepare for their withdrawal.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-27</p>
        <p>Death Sentences Reversed In Two of Three Appeals  The most far-reaching study of the death penalty in the United States has found that two out of three convictions were overturned on appeal, mostly because of serious errors by incompetent defense lawyers or overzealous police officers and prosecutors who withheld evidence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>G.O.P. to Push Drug Benefits  House Republicans will flesh out their proposal for Medicare drug benefits this week and try to push it through two House committees in three days, despite fierce objections from many Democrats.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Housing Costs Beyond Reach  The nation's expanding economy has produced an unintended downside, rapidly increasing housing costs that are denying many working-class wage earners an affordable place to live, especially in urban areas.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Making the Case for Gore  The Gore campaign is enlisting scores of character witnesses and deploying them on talk shows and the campaign trail. Their job is to attest to Vice President Al Gore's humanity and make the case for his policy proposals.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Perot Backers Are Ousted  Several supporters of the Reform Party's founder, Ross Perot, have been unseated in Texas, in a coup described as a ''storming by the Pat Buchanan brigade.''</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Impact of Global Warming  A warming of the global climate is likely to have substantial consequences for better and worse around the United States in coming decades, including bumper crops in the heartland, chronic erosion of coasts, summer water shortages and winter floods in the West, a federal study has concluded.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Embracing Diversity at Exeter  A decision by trustees at Phillips Exeter Academy in New Hampshire to allow gay and lesbian couples to serve as dormitory parents reflects how much schools like Exeter, once almost exclusively for affluent white boys, have sought to embrace diversity, often with growing pains.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>State Senate Republicans Show a More Liberal Side  The Senate Republicans, long a redoubt of conservatism in a liberal state, have made an astonishing march leftward in approving legislation in the last several months, with an election looming. Joseph L. Bruno, Republican majority leader of the State Senate, said, ''We're in a business where times change.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Census Takers Finishing the Job  An army of census takers has surpassed the Census Bureau's efforts in 1990 and nearly completed the agency's task of accounting for New Yorkers who did not complete their mail-in forms this spring, the Census Bureau said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>3 More Killed in Surge in Crime  An outbreak of violence that began Friday night continued unabated yesterday when 3 people were killed and 28 others were stabbed or shot in attacks throughout New York City, the police said. Over the weekend, a total of 60 people were shot or stabbed, and 6 of the victims died.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A Party in Honor of Puerto Rico  Politicians and protesters vied for attention at the National Puerto Rican Day Parade, as hundreds of thousands of people joined in a celebration of Puerto Rican culture, music and ethnic pride.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Deadline in Auction Inquiry  Justice Department prosecutors, facing an important deadline next month, are redoubling their efforts to prove that Sotheby's and Christie's hatched a scheme to fix the prices they charged buyers and sellers and that the collusion began as early as 1991.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>City Ballet Appoints Briton  The New York City Ballet has named Andrea Quinn, the music director of the Royal Ballet in London, as its new music director.</p>
        <p>E3</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Pacers Take Game 3  Reggie Miller erupted for 33 points on 11-of-22 shooting and 9 for 9 from the foul line as Indiana defeated the Los Angeles Lakers, 100-91. The Lakers lead the four-of-seven-game series, two games to one.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-20</p>
        <p>Microsoft as Major Lobbyist  Microsoft is mobilizing a pervasive lobbying and public relations campaign in an effort to temper the impact of a potentially devastating federal court ruling and generate positive public and political opinion.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The government had to build a relationship of cooperation and trust with the industry to bring and win the Microsoft suit.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Canada as Top U.S. Oil Supplier  Canada is now the No. 1 energy supplier to the United States, the world's largest energy importer. In the last decade, Canada nearly doubled its oil exports and nearly tripled its natural gas exports to the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Setback for Mining Concern  A diamond-mining company with close ties to the governments of Congo and Zimbabwe may be thwarted in an effort to trade on the London Stock Exchange after reports of British government opposition to its plans, executives said.</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>I.B.M. Laptop to Use Linux  I.B.M. said it would introduce a portable computer that runs the Linux operating system, bolstering support for the system, which competes with Microsoft's Windows.</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6-7</p>
        <p>Houshang Golshiri  One of Iran's leading secular writers and a prominent advocate of free speech and human rights in his homeland, he was 63.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: Syria after Hafez al-Assad; how to move the schools; health tasks before the Legislature.  Columns: William Safire, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E4</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7</p>
        <p>Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>B8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
