<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Remote Mesa, Ranchers and Environmentalists Seek a Middle Ground</title>
    <meta content="26GRAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/26/science/26GRAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1258180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grass</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blakeslee, Sandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D91238F935A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Remote Mesa, Ranchers and Environmentalists Seek a Middle Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blakeslee, Sandra</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA FE, N.M.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dozens of environmentalists and cattle ranchers in northern New Mexico devise 'grass bank' to resolve long, bitter arguments over how national forests should be used; grass bank is a large chunk of national forest that serves as kind of summer camp for cows that usually graze on other federal land; while their animals are away at 'camp' for three or more summers, ranchers restore the land they would normally graze, clearing pastures, building fences around streams and other vulnerable areas, and repairing damage caused by decades of overuse and fire suppression; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exasperated by long, bitter arguments over how national forests should be used, dozens of environmentalists and cattle ranchers in northern New Mexico have devised their own solution. They have created a ''grass bank.''</p>
        <p>A grass bank is a large chunk of national forest that serves as a kind of summer camp for cows that usually graze on other federal land. While their animals are away at ''camp'' for three or more summers, ranchers restore the land they would normally graze, clearing pastures, building fences around streams and other vulnerable areas, and repairing damage caused by decades of overuse and fire suppression.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exasperated by long, bitter arguments over how national forests should be used, dozens of environmentalists and cattle ranchers in northern New Mexico have devised their own solution. They have created a ''grass bank.''</p>
        <p>A grass bank is a large chunk of national forest that serves as a kind of summer camp for cows that usually graze on other federal land. While their animals are away at ''camp'' for three or more summers, ranchers restore the land they would normally graze, clearing pastures, building fences around streams and other vulnerable areas, and repairing damage caused by decades of overuse and fire suppression.</p>
        <p>The grass bank idea is simple, said Ellie Towns, who supervises the United States Forest Service in Arizona and New Mexico. But it was not easy to put into effect, given the bitterness that has divided environmentalists and ranchers in the region. ''We need flexibility and trust to do things that are new,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ed Marston, publisher of High Country News in Paonia, Colo., which  chronicles change in the intermountain West, said grass banks were a good example of the ways people with different interests were finding to work collaboratively and overcome decades of mutual mistrust.</p>
        <p>Many scientists applaud the effort. A hundred years of fire suppression and grazing have drastically altered Western landscapes, said Dr. Craig Allen, an ecologist with the United States Geological Survey's Jemez Mountains Field Station, northwest of here at Bandelier National Monument. ''Our whole mindset has to be rethought if we want to have healthy forests and grasslands,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That includes coming to terms with a clash of values between the ranchers who use the land and the large numbers of newcomers with backpacks and hiking boots who are eager to enjoy the landscape, said William de Buys, a consultant to the Conservation Fund, a national environmental organization based in Arlington, Va., and a leader in the grass bank movement in New Mexico. People raised back East, Mr. de Buys said, ''have a culturally based Arbor Day sentimentality about trees.''</p>
        <p>''They think more trees are always good,'' he said. In the West, though, he said, more trees may mean only that suppression of natural fires has allowed trees to encroach on naturally open grasslands.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Buys spoke at a conference here recently that introduced the grass bank concept to scores of ranchers and community organizers from seven Western states. Many said they would start grass banks at home on either private or government-leased properties.</p>
        <p>The meeting's sponsors included the Conservation Fund, the Northern New Mexico Stockmen's Association, the United States Forest Service, the Cooperative Extension Service of New Mexico State University and two groups that foster close collaborations between ranchers and environmentalists: the Quivira Coalition and the Malpai Borderlands Group.</p>
        <p>But the divide between ranchers and environmentalists is not easy to bridge, and groups that maintain a hard-line stance on grazing issues were conspicuously absent.</p>
        <p>''We don't oppose grass banks as a tool per se,'' said Caren Cowan, executive director of the statewide New Mexico Cattle Growers' Association, which represents about 2,000 ranchers, half of whom graze their livestock on public lands. ''But we don't want anyone to tell us how to run our business.'' Ms. Cowan did not attend the conference.</p>
        <p>Two environmental groups active in the region, Forest Guardians and the Southwest Center for Biodiversity, were unable to attend.</p>
        <p>John Horning, a leader of Forest Guardians in Santa Fe, said that grazing was antithetical to rangeland and forest health. Both groups are taking part in a lawsuit that seeks to stop all grazing on public lands until federal officials can prove that endangered species are being protected from the destruction of their habitats.</p>
        <p>Hard-liners on both sides will never agree on anything, said Courtney White, director of the Quivira Coalition, which is seeking a middle ground. ''Well, we say a pox on both their houses,'' Mr. White said.</p>
        <p>The landscape, he said, is suffering from a complex mix of problems -- past overgrazing, fire suppression, climate change -- that can be ameliorated with human ingenuity and progressive ranch management.</p>
        <p>Though some environmentalists criticize their opponents as ''Rolex ranchers'' who enjoy taxpayer subsidies as they graze their cattle on public land, the vast majority of ranchers are barely getting by, said Palemon Martinez, secretary-treasurer of the Northern New Mexico Stockman's Association, a small organization representing a community of traditional Hispanic ranchers. ''This is the oldest ranching community in America,'' Mr. Martinez said.</p>
        <p>He said a typical rancher, with a dozen or so cows, might sell calves in the fall to put a child through community college or the like, but ''I can assure you that no one from around here has ever made a profit grazing on public lands.''</p>
        <p>Though these families have been grazing cattle in the region for more than 400 years and consider ranching an intrinsic part of life, ranchers today must also work other jobs to make ends meet.</p>
        <p>Ranchers and environmentalists who came to the meeting call themselves members of ''the radical center.'' Indeed, the grass bank idea was born seven years ago from an earlier collaboration, the Malpai Borderlands Group, formed on the southern border of New Mexico and Arizona.</p>
        <p>To preserve open space, ranchers there promised never to develop their lands, in exchange for the right to graze their livestock on a large, grass-rich ranch during dry years. By keeping homes out of the area, ranchers could burn thousands of acres at a time and keep grasslands, which depend on fire, healthy.</p>
        <p>After visiting the Malpai three years ago, Mr. de Buys (pronounced de-BWEES) learned that a 240-acre ranch on a large mesa south of Pecos, N.M., was for sale. The buyer was entitled to graze 36,000 acres of national forest with up to 325 cattle year-round (or more animals if they used the land part time). The Conservation Fund bought the ranch for $475,000 and named it the Valle Grande Grass Bank.</p>
        <p>It then reached out to ranchers in northern New Mexico. It was a hard sell at first, Mr. Martinez said. But last summer, 19 ranchers sent 340 cows and calves to the grass bank. Then they worked with the forest service to improve their grazing allotments in the national forest.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the grass bank helped raise $250,000 from federal and philanthropic sources to support the effort and restore grasslands on the Valle Grande property. The restoration may take two to five years.</p>
        <p>Most people don't realize that southwestern forests should not be thick with trees and woody shrubs like pinon and juniper, Dr. Allen said. Until 120 years ago, they were more like open savannas, with clumps of trees interspersed with open patches of grasslands. In wet years, grass became abundant and choked out trees and shrubs. But in dry years, fire would race over vast areas to consume grasses as well as most tree seedlings.</p>
        <p>This cycle stopped in the late 1800's, Dr. Allen said, when early ranchers brought cows, goats and sheep whose heavy grazing left the land shorn of grass. The denuded land no longer burned, and trees and shrubs began to spread.</p>
        <p>Between 1935 and 1981, the Jemez Mountains in northern New Mexico lost 55 percent of their most productive grassland species as trees and woody shrubs encroached on open spaces, Dr. Allen said. Livestock were squeezed onto the remaining open space, which increased harm to riverbank areas.</p>
        <p>To repair the damage, ranchers and forest service workers participating in the Valle Grande Grass Bank have been building fences around streams to keep cattle away. They are cutting small trees and shrubs with chain saws. And after they let grassy areas build up for a year or two, they are setting fires to restore the natural ecosystem.</p>
        <p>It's too soon to see significant results, said Cecilia Romero Seesholtz, a district ranger who works with participating ranchers. But hundreds of acres have been treated and more work is scheduled, she said.</p>
        <p>Monitoring the results is critical if the grass bank approach is to be accepted by all the groups involved in it, Mr. de Buys said. ''We don't want to simply be a Band-Aid for bad management,'' he said. ''The improvements have to be sustained.''</p>
        <p>Proponents of grass banks say they may represent the only escape from an impasse in which neither people nor land can win.</p>
        <p>''You can't run nature in reverse,'' Mr. de Buys said. ''If we remove all the cows from public lands, we won't get back to a naturalistic fire regime, because that would mean huge fires burning over thousands of miles. Too many people live here now. It's too dangerous. The only way to get savannas back on public lands is to get ranchers working to restore and protect the landscape.''</p>
        <p>If that ends up protecting an old-fashioned and much beloved way of life among small ranchers, he said, ''that's all the better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
