<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada's New Territory Beckons Tourists North</title>
    <meta content="19REP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/19/travel/19REP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nunavut (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Yukon, the Northwest Territories and Nunavut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1D91138F93AA25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada's New Territory Beckons Tourists North</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Brooke Correspondent's Report on visiting Nunavut, Canada's new Arctic territory; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOOKING for an upside to global warming, Canadian tourism authorities recently calculated that for every degree a North American summer rises above the norm, tourism spending in Canada climbs by about $250 million. Increasingly, an advance guard of travelers is venturing into the far north, to Nunavut, Canada's new Arctic territory, carved out of the eastern half of the Northwest Territories last year.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, the number of cruise ships docking each summer in Nunavut's coastal villages has increased from 3 to 12. And between 1994 and 1999 tourism to the territory increased by 14 percent, from 16,000 tourists to 18,227. For independent visitors, the formation of Nunavut has accelerated the spread of comfortable hotels in the territory, made air service more reliable and prompted publication of an encyclopedic, easy-to-read guide, ''The Nunavut Handbook: Traveling in Canada's Arctic,'' edited by Marion Soubliere (Nortext Multimedia, 1999, $21.50).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOOKING for an upside to global warming, Canadian tourism authorities recently calculated that for every degree a North American summer rises above the norm, tourism spending in Canada climbs by about $250 million. Increasingly, an advance guard of travelers is venturing into the far north, to Nunavut, Canada's new Arctic territory, carved out of the eastern half of the Northwest Territories last year.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, the number of cruise ships docking each summer in Nunavut's coastal villages has increased from 3 to 12. And between 1994 and 1999 tourism to the territory increased by 14 percent, from 16,000 tourists to 18,227. For independent visitors, the formation of Nunavut has accelerated the spread of comfortable hotels in the territory, made air service more reliable and prompted publication of an encyclopedic, easy-to-read guide, ''The Nunavut Handbook: Traveling in Canada's Arctic,'' edited by Marion Soubliere (Nortext Multimedia, 1999, $21.50).</p>
        <p>Wilderness is a major attraction in a territory with only 28,000 people sprinkled over an area roughly five times the size of California. Spare and serene, almost all of Nunavut lies above the tree line.</p>
        <p>''It is so quiet, it is a good place to disconnect from all your problems in the south,'' said Josee Auclair, whose tour company, Canadian Arctic Holidays, in Aylmer, Quebec, opened a camp on Somerset Island this summer. ''People are surprised you can get so close to the wildlife. I spent one afternoon with a visitor from Chicago watching an arctic fox.''</p>
        <p>With today's Arctic tourist more apt to shoot a camera than a rifle, people come in summer to watch humpback whales spouting in fjords, narwhals swimming among icebergs and, though a professional armed guide might be advisable in this case, polar bears hunting seals. During the polar winter, a dark period, the flickering, purple aurora borealis lights up the northern sky. In the spring, after the sun returns, there are dog sled rides, cross-country ski treks and trips to the edge of the ice floes.</p>
        <p>For summer visitors fleeing hot weather, Nunavut offers temperatures from the 40's Fahrenheit in the High Arctic to the 60's around Iqaluit, on the southern end of Baffin Island. Comparable temperatures in winter range from the minus 40's to near zero.</p>
        <p>Adventurers turned off by congested parks in the United States will find that  Nunavut has national parks that are so uncrowded, they seem almost like private reserves. The busiest, Auyuittuq, a Massachusetts-size expanse of glaciers, fjords and craggy peaks, drew 467 visitors from April 1999 through last March. Quttinirpaaq, about 500 miles south of the North Pole, had 192 visitors for the year ending last March.</p>
        <p>One of the 192, Jerry Kobalenko, who is writing a book on Ellesmere Island, the site of the park, said that the abundant wildlife reminded him of East Africa. ''I have looked over the landscape and seen 20 musk ox and dozens of arctic hare,'' he said. ''It's an arctic Serengeti.'' Without trees, visitors say, it is easy to watch wildlife.</p>
        <p>Encompassing the traditional lands of the Inuit, Nunavut also has cultural attractions: traditional throat singing, drum dancing, soapstone carving and ancient campsites.</p>
        <p>Well-traveled upper-income North Americans and Europeans in their 40's and 50's are the types of travelers who increasingly visit the Canadian Arctic, said Maureen Bundgaard, the marketing director for Nunavut Tourism, a nonprofit association run by 130 of the territory's outfitters, hotels, restaurants and tour operators. It has an informative, if somewhat dated Web site, www.nunatour.nt.ca. The organization publishes a 70-page Nunavut vacation planner.</p>
        <p>In a region without roads, the only way into the Arctic for decades was by bush plane. But in recent years, reliable, if expensive, air service to Nunavut has developed from Winnipeg, Manitoba, and Ottawa.</p>
        <p>From Winnipeg, two competing airlines, Calm Air, an Air Canada affiliate, and Kivalliq Air, a no-frills company, puddle-jump up the western shore of Hudson Bay, cross the Arctic Circle and stop at a series of small settlements, almost all on the water.</p>
        <p>From Ottawa, First Air, also an Air Canada affiliate, funnels passengers north to Iqaluit, the capital. Iqaluit is now the air hub for the eastern Arctic and Greenland.</p>
        <p>In summer, air travel is increasingly reliable. This reporter took four First Air flights in late summer: from Resolute in the high Arctic, down to Iqaluit, over to Greenland and back, and down to Ottawa. All were on time and went off smoothly with one hitch: an intermediary stop skipped due to fog. Almost the same number of flights run in winter, but often face weather delays.</p>
        <p>Air bargains are scarce in the Arctic. Although these tickets were bought weeks in advance, with two Saturday-night stopovers, the 3,200-mile trip was $1,633. Round-trip fares between Ottawa and Iqaluit usually start around $870. From Winnipeg, it is possible to fly on Kivalliq to Repulse Bay, a village on the Arctic Circle, on a round-trip standby fare of about $540.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
