<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even in Frigid North, Hints of Warmer Temperatures</title>
    <meta content="10POLE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/science/10POLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alert (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D6103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even in Frigid North, Hints of Warmer Temperatures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>ALERT, Canada</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People stationed at Canadian military base in Alert, which is 500 miles from North Pole, prepare to kick off four months of polar night with 'sunset party' on Oct 14; artificially built like a lunar colony, combined weather station and radio listening post stands on barren, treeless bluff halfway between Canada's last Inuit community and North Pole; cold weather shaped construction of station, and windows are quadruple paned and permanently sealed; at each entrance, pair of thick refrigerator doors blocks winter cold of 50 below; but even here, on Ellesmere Island, North America's northernmost tip, inhabitants think they see hints of climate change, of warmer temperatures; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the men and women stationed at this Canadian military base prepare to kick off four months of polar night with a ''sunset party'' on Oct. 14, the threat of global warming seems far from the northernmost human settlement in the world.</p>
        <p>Until the sun peeks over the horizon again on March 1, workers going outside will clip themselves to orange rope ''lifelines'' to avoid getting lost in the frigid, 24-hour night. Artificially built like a lunar colony, this combined weather station and radio listening post stands on a barren, treeless bluff halfway between Canada's last Inuit community and the North Pole, 507 miles north of here. Alert, in the territory of Nunavut, is as far from Toronto, 2,700 miles, as New York City is from the Amazon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the men and women stationed at this Canadian military base prepare to kick off four months of polar night with a ''sunset party'' on Oct. 14, the threat of global warming seems far from the northernmost human settlement in the world.</p>
        <p>Until the sun peeks over the horizon again on March 1, workers going outside will clip themselves to orange rope ''lifelines'' to avoid getting lost in the frigid, 24-hour night. Artificially built like a lunar colony, this combined weather station and radio listening post stands on a barren, treeless bluff halfway between Canada's last Inuit community and the North Pole, 507 miles north of here. Alert, in the territory of Nunavut, is as far from Toronto, 2,700 miles, as New York City is from the Amazon.</p>
        <p>Cold weather shaped the construction of this station. Windows are quadruple paned and permanently sealed. At each entrance, a pair of thick refrigerator doors blocks the winter cold of 50 below.</p>
        <p>Cigarette smoke wafts freely through dormitories and bars, as Alert is the last Canadian military post to allow smoking indoors. For much of the year, smoking outdoors would be a death sentence.</p>
        <p>But even here, on Ellesmere Island, North America's northernmost tip, the inhabitants think they can see hints of climate change. Glaciers are receding. Winter rains are blamed for declining populations of Peary Caribou. And guides who regularly lead skiing expeditions to the pole say spring temperatures are rising.</p>
        <p>''It has been a lot warmer in the last few years,'' said Richard Weber, a Canadian cross-country ski champion who has led groups to the pole every April since 1995. On the treks, Mr. Weber said,  the temperatures have risen from about 15 below to about zero.</p>
        <p>Analysis of half a century of temperature readings collected since Alert's weather station opened in the spring of 1950 show barely any changes in recorded temperatures, said Henry Hengeveld, the science adviser on climate change for Environment Canada, a federal government ministry based in Ottawa. Alert, he added, appeared to be on a climatic fault line between the western Arctic, where recorded temperatures rose slightly in the late 20th century, and the eastern Arctic, where they fell slightly.</p>
        <p>John H. MacIver, the weather station manager here, stressed that individual observations around the Arctic often conflict with one another, producing a still murky picture of climate trends in the high Arctic.</p>
        <p>He cautioned that the mile-wide stretch of open water encountered in August by scientists and tourists on the Russian icebreaker Yamal could be ''a weather blip,'' or caused by wind moving ice.</p>
        <p>A 21-year veteran of the high Arctic, he explained that ''polar ice is like a rubber raft out in the middle of the lake'' during the summer.</p>
        <p>''Ice conditions have been deteriorating a lot earlier, a lot of leads of water have been opening up,'' he continued one morning in late August before releasing into a 25-mile-an-hour wind a large white balloon with weather instruments attached.</p>
        <p>It was a typical day of 24-hour sun in late summer, a season when temperatures briefly nose above freezing on 77 days. An Arctic gale blew sleet and snow, icebergs gave off luminous glows of blue and green, and military mechanics deiced airplane wings with house brooms.</p>
        <p>Even in the summer, Canada's Arctic is such a forbidding environment that Devon Island, just south of Ellesmere, was used this July to test vehicles for exploration on Mars.</p>
        <p>In Alert, the rocky landscape of shale is bare of all signs of life, save tiny tundra plants. When a wind is not blowing, the eerie silence is nearly total, broken occasionally by the cry of a bird.</p>
        <p>But satellite studies of the North Pole ice cap, at the peak of summer, show that it has shrunk by about 6 percent over the last 20 years. Sonar testing from submarines indicates that the cap's thickness has been reduced by 42 percent since the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Noting these studies, Mr. Hengeveld speculated on the significance of the tourists' observations of open water 500 miles north of here in August.  ''With the trend toward less ice extent and less ice thickness, we can expect this to happen more frequently,'' he said. ''It is, unfortunately, a harbinger of things to come.''</p>
        <p>Scientists predict that if enough ice melts in the Arctic, some warm Gulf Stream waters could be diverted into the area, warming Greenland and the Canadian Arctic, but lowering temperatures in Britain and Norway. Although Britain and Canada share the same latitudes, the Gulf Stream gives Britain milder winters.</p>
        <p>If Arctic warming trends continue unchecked over the next 100 years, up to 60 percent of Northern Canada's habitat could be ''fundamentally altered,'' risking a loss of up to 20 percent of species, says a report released in late August by the World Wildlife Fund and the David Suzuki Foundation, a Canadian environmental group.</p>
        <p>Predicting that some plants needing colder climates will have to migrate 100 times as fast as they did when the last ice age ended, the report's authors concluded: ''Very few plant species can move at rates faster than one kilometer per year, and yet this is what will be required in many parts of the world.''</p>
        <p>At Ellesmere Island National Park, which starts 25 miles south of this military post, clues have been detected by some of the few adventurers who venture each year into this wilderness of unnamed peaks and glaciers.</p>
        <p>Jerry Kobalenko, who is writing a book about the wildly beautiful island, a land mass nearly the size of Britain, flashed through photos of glaciers on his laptop computer.</p>
        <p>One photo, taken in 1898 by the Norwegian explorer Otto Sverdrup, shows the high mound of a glacier pushing through a mountain pass. A photo taken two years ago by Mr. Kobalenko of the same valley shows the glacier has receded, with shale and gravel where rock-hard ice used to be.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, flying in the cargo hold of a Canadian military C-130 over the park, he peered out of a porthole and exclaimed: ''You see that shrinking? You can see how it once filled that valley.''</p>
        <p>On the ground, Josee Auclair, an adventure travel guide, recalled the burning power of the sun she encountered three years ago on a skiing trip in northern Greenland with her husband, Richard Weber. Attributing this to the thinning ozone cover at the pole, she said that one day she put cream and zinc oxide only on her face, but neglected her neck and regretted it. ''My neck swelled up. I had blisters all over my neck,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At their summer tourist camp on Somerset Island, south of Ellesmere, they noticed this August that permafrost soil was melting, causing banks to collapse into the Cunningham River.</p>
        <p>In Nunavut, a vast territory that is home to only 26,000 people, longtime residents complain of similar unsettling changes: cases of sunburn in the summer, rain in midwinter and early ice breakups that cut short spring hunts.</p>
        <p>Elderly residents have been unnerved by sightings of unfamiliar southern species -- wolverines, grizzly bears, robins and even a swan.</p>
        <p>Here on Ellesmere Island, biologists attribute the sharp declines in Peary Caribou populations to the winter rains that have sealed vital forage vegetation under sheets of ice.</p>
        <p>To the south, around the Hudson Bay, Canadian wildlife scientists reported last year that polar bears were 90 to 220 pounds lighter than they were in the 1960's.</p>
        <p>The weight loss is apparently related to the ice-melting patterns: sea ice now is melting earlier in the spring, making it more difficult for the bears to gorge on seal pups.</p>
        <p>Since the 1960's, the primary mission of the military post here has been to listen to Russian military radio traffic on the far side of the pole.</p>
        <p>But weather is the cold war that is waged daily by the soldiers and technicians who rotate through here for six months of duty. During mild weather windows, first in the spring and again in the late summer, the Canadian military flies an Arctic version of the Berlin airlift, shuttling in food, supplies and enough fuel to feed power generators that burn 60 gallons of diesel an hour. The only locally supplied product is water, which is pumped from a nearby lake through pipes that are heated to avoid freezing.</p>
        <p>In mid-July, when scientists were announcing in Washington that global warming was thinning Greenland's ice cap, residents of Alert were forced to postpone their annual ''Polar Plunge'' in Dumbell Bay.</p>
        <p>Although rising temperatures may be thinning the ice cap, visible from here on a clear day, swimmers here faced a midsummer day of pack ice in the bay and two inches of snow on the ground.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
