<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Far, Plenty of Water</title>
    <meta content="21DRAU$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservoirs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDB143AF932A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Far, Plenty of Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>WANAQUE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Drought warning remains in effect in New Jersey despite fact that north Jersey water supply system stands at 99.8 percent capacity; statewide drought emergency resulted in water restrictions from August to September 1999; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Wanaque Reservoir looks full  all 29.6 billion gallons. The foliage around its 30 miles of shoreline is lush, and the sound of birdsong gives a sense of well-being. The thought of the drought that left New Jersey crisp and dry last summer seem remote.</p>
        <p>''We're at about 99.8 percent capacity,'' said Phil White, a spokesman for the North Jersey District Water Supply Commission, which oversees the reservoir system here and supplies water to one in five people in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Wanaque Reservoir looks full  all 29.6 billion gallons. The foliage around its 30 miles of shoreline is lush, and the sound of birdsong gives a sense of well-being. The thought of the drought that left New Jersey crisp and dry last summer seem remote.</p>
        <p>''We're at about 99.8 percent capacity,'' said Phil White, a spokesman for the North Jersey District Water Supply Commission, which oversees the reservoir system here and supplies water to one in five people in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''It's assumed that if we're at 100 percent capacity June 1st,'' Mr. White said on a recent hot day, ''we will be able to provide the promised allotment of various municipalities we serve until June 1st of the following year.''</p>
        <p>But he warned, ''It looked fine this time last year also.''</p>
        <p>Then came August. Governor Whitman declared a statewide drought emergency and imposed water restructions when a severe lack of rain, periods of blistering heat and unusually high consumption left the state's 13 reservoirs at 69.8 percent of capacity. She lifted the ban in September, only after Hurricane Floyd deluged the state and replenished the water supply.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, a drought warning remains in effect, even though the reservoirs in the northeastern part of the state are near capacity, according to the state's Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>The Wanaque (pronounced WAN na cue) supplies water to 2.5 million people in Essex, Hudson, Bergen, Union, Morris, and Passaic counties.</p>
        <p>Aquifers in the south, which depend on ground water, have reached normal and above-normal levels, and others remain low but not as bad as last year at this time, the United States Geological Survey says.</p>
        <p>Against this backdrop, the state climatologist, David A. Robinson, and other experts say there is simply no way of knowing whether there will be a repeat of last summer's simmer.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the numbers, roughly every three out of four months in the past two years have had below-average precipitation,'' Dr. Robinson said. The driest July through September of the century occurred in 1998, he added, and the second driest April through July in 1999.</p>
        <p>''In other words, we have been rescued from serious water woes by just a few months -- most notably January of 1999 when we had a series of northeasters dump a lot of rain on the state and Floyd on Sept. 16, 1999. One could make a case that without those two periods, our reservoirs would be well below normal today.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, moderate to severe drought conditions currently exist in parts of the nation's midsection, South and Southwest -- about a quarter of the contiguous 48 states. Moreover, many scientists believe that global warming will increase the frequency and severity of droughts.</p>
        <p>March was the only month with above normal precipitation in New Jersey since Hurricane Floyd, Mr. Robinson said. April, with its cloudy weather and pewriodic mists and drizzles was deceptive. It actually was ''a little below normal,'' he said, while rainfall in central Jersey last month was about 30 percent below normal.</p>
        <p>That said, officials maintain that conditions are not looking bad this year.</p>
        <p>''At this point last year, we were in much worse shape in terms of water,'' said Assistant Commissioner Ray Cantor who oversees land use management and water supply for the State's Department of Environmental Protection. ''We're 5.7 percentage points above average for this time of year.''</p>
        <p>As for the South Jersey, Tony Navoy, assistant district chief of the state's office of the Geological Survey which monitors ground water levels and stream flow throughout the state, said: ''We're in better condition than we were last year, although it will take another year or two to climb out. Generally speaking when you have a couple dry years like we've had recently, you don't jump up over night. The levels go up in the winter and go down in the summer.''</p>
        <p>Since last summer, the state has been trying to intensify its water-monitoring efforts to get more ''real time'' data on subjects like stream flow more quickly, said Deputy Commissioner Bob Tudor, who oversees planning for the state's environmental agency. Toward that end, the state is in the process of linking up with satellite telemetry, he added.</p>
        <p>The Department also plans to break the state down into five or six regions, enabling  it to work with water suppliers in each area as well as the Geological Survey to study such factors as rainfall and streamflow before determining whether -- and what type of -- water restructions are necessary.</p>
        <p>''We want to have monitoring capability that is regional in nature and that allows us to take statewide action or not and to communicate to the public in that region what kind of conservation measures to take,'' Mr. Tudor said.</p>
        <p>Officials say that among long-range plans, the state has begun a water resource management program in which water issues are seen in terms of drainage basins rather than political boundaries. In late 1998, the environmental agency set up a Division of Watershed Management to protect 20 watersheds and has been giving funds and support to watershed management associations, community organizations and residents in each watershed area to work together to identify problems and suggest solutions in the coming years.</p>
        <p>But Jeff Tittell, executive director of the New Jersey chapter of the Sierra Club, said none of these measures really address the drought problem.</p>
        <p>''They have a plan to tell people to conserve,'' Mr. Tittell said. ''They have a plan to monitor, but they don't have any real plan to deal either with the cause of drought or the ways to prevent drought.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tittle said that the state calculates its water yields on average demand rather than peak demand during a low-yield period like a drought. Calculations should also take into account changes in some water supply areas brought on by a surge in new development, he added.</p>
        <p>''You pave over landscape and cut down trees, you get less water recharging your ground water because the pavement and your lawns cause more run-off,'' Mr. Tittell said.</p>
        <p>As for the environmental agency's water resource management plan, he said it only delays a solution to pollution problems that have been known for years.</p>
        <p>''We don't need another five years studying the problem, and another five years to come up with a clean-up plan,'' Mr. Tittell said.</p>
        <p>For his part, Dr. Robinson, the climatologist, said a prolonged drought in New Jersey like the one in 1964 could have more dire  effects because the state is more built up with more people now than it was then. He added that there has not been a prolonged period of rainfall deficit lasting multiple years since the mid-1960's.</p>
        <p>''I'd be much more concerned now if the reservoirs were below normal, but given they are full, I'm still concerned because of this long-term pattern we've been in over the last two years when we've had many more dry months than wet months,'' Dr. Robinson said. ''I'm not sounding an alarm, but I will cautiously be looking at the rainfall totals this summer.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
