<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Stamford; Center Aims to Educate On Long Island Sound</title>
    <meta content="17VIEW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stamford (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cove Island Park (Stamford, Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Soundwaters Community Center For Environmental Education</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0D61438F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1305" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Stamford; Center Aims to Educate On Long Island Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on SoundWaters Community Center for Environmental Education, which is set to open in 200-year-old converted house in Cove Island Park in Stamford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE brown ducks swimming in the inlets, the gulls swooping low in the sky, the herons stalking fish in the shallows -- all are testimony to the diverse ecology of Long Island Sound. They could also be advertisements for the environmental center about to open in a 200-year-old converted house in Cove Island Park in Stamford.</p>
        <p>The Sound is a delicate estuary within 50 miles of 25 million people. Those humans -- and the threats their activities pose to the health of the Sound -- motivated Len Miller to found an organization in 1989 to educate people about the wonders of Long Island Sound and the dangers it faces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE brown ducks swimming in the inlets, the gulls swooping low in the sky, the herons stalking fish in the shallows -- all are testimony to the diverse ecology of Long Island Sound. They could also be advertisements for the environmental center about to open in a 200-year-old converted house in Cove Island Park in Stamford.</p>
        <p>The Sound is a delicate estuary within 50 miles of 25 million people. Those humans -- and the threats their activities pose to the health of the Sound -- motivated Len Miller to found an organization in 1989 to educate people about the wonders of Long Island Sound and the dangers it faces.</p>
        <p>SoundWaters began with a schooner that serves as a floating classroom where students learn through a hands-on curriculum. The ship also offers programs for adults, including lectures presented by ecologists,  musicians, artists and historians; teacher-training workshops; and weekend ecology sails. SoundWaters then expanded to offer land-based programs, including classroom workshops and field trips, summer camp, community gardens, and nature programsfor older residents.</p>
        <p>''I felt that if there is going to be any improvement in Long Island Sound,'' Mr. Miller said, ''there must be two things: education and cooperation between corporations, government and individuals. There was criticism of me back in '89, people who said you could not have cooperation between environmentalists and corporations,'' but he pointed out that today the groups more commonly work together.</p>
        <p>He said the SoundWaters Community Center for Environmental Education, which will have its grand opening next weekend, will greatly enhance the opportunities to  provide education to people of all ages.</p>
        <p>The center is taking shape in the rehabilitated Holly House, a mansion that was built during the 18th and 19th centuries. It looked well-maintained on the outside, but the inside had almost rotted away, said Bill Boysen, executive director of SoundWaters. It had to be completely rebuilt, and that gave the group the opportunity to build a model of environmentally responsible development.</p>
        <p>The large room that will be a lecture hall keeps the building's original oak flooring, but other rooms downstairs have floor coverings made of recycled tires, while the carpeting in offices upstairs is made from recycled plastic bottles. In the laboratory and classroom in the back, cabinets and countertops were milk jugs in a previous life. The tile in the bathrooms was once auto glass. The paint used throughout is low in volatile organic compounds. And the heating and air-conditioning system is geothermal, drawing water that is a constant 56 degrees from six 500-foot-deep wells under the patio. The building uses no fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>''It's 10 to 15 percent more expensive than fossil fuels'' to build, Mr. Boysen said, ''but we hope it will serve as a model for others.'' Mr. Miller added that once the center is built, if oil prices remain at current levels, SoundWaters hopes to recoup the cost of construction within a few years.</p>
        <p>The city of Stamford owns Holly House, and agreed to lease it to SoundWaters for $1 a year for 30 years. After that, SoundWaters will pay a market rate subsidized by the city. ''Dannel Malloy, the mayor of Stamford, has been a great supporter,'' Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>The board of the organization committed  to raising $2 million to renovate the building and create the exhibits, and has raised more  than 90 percent of that so far, Mr. Boysen said. Donors include the state of Connecticut, foundations, individuals and half a dozen large Connecticut-based companies</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, an accountant who lives and works in Stamford, is chairman of the board of SoundWaters. Mr. Boysen came to the organization as a volunteer and took over the helm after 25 years as an executive with Bristol-Myers Squibb pharmaceuticals. The two men have extensive contacts in the business community. One of the rooms in the new center is called the Environmental Business Room, where every two months a different local business will promote its efforts to be environmentally friendly and teach others how they can do likewise.</p>
        <p>The heart of the center is the Waters of the World exhibit, which demonstrates the interconnection of muddy pond water, fast-flowing river water, brackish water where rivers meet the sea, and salt water like that  in Long Island Sound. There is a manmade salt marsh on one side of the room, where''tides'' come in and go out (through human  intervention), providing habitats for various creatures at low and high tide.</p>
        <p>Chris Evers, an educator with SoundWaters, took a break from feeding squid to the tank-dwelling fish, all native to the Sound, to explain the organization's emphasis on the Long Island Sound watershed. The area includes most of Connecticut and parts of Massachusetts, Vermont and New Hampshire extending to Canada.</p>
        <p>That notion is reinforced with a pinball game called Rainball, in which the player shoots balls representing rain that come to rest in the ''Sound'' at the bottom of the frame through various pathways -- a car wash, a factory, a farm. ''The point is to show that all water in the watershed ends up in Long Island Sound,'' Mr. Evers said.</p>
        <p>Admission to the center is free, with fees charged for special programs.</p>
        <p>Another special feature of the center is a program called Celebrate the Earth. It explores the spiritual relationship between humans and the natural world through many faiths -- Christianity, Judaism, Buddhism, Native American religions and others. It is part of the opening weekend activities and will continue thereafter on the first and third Sunday afternoons of the month starting Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>Danny Martin, a former priest and a friend of Mr. Miller's, said he had just completed his doctorate in ecology and spirituality at Fordham University in 1988 when the two men began discussing the ideas that led to SoundWaters. ''I feel it came out of a spiritual impulse,'' Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>''It implies certain values: integrity, beauty, humility. We engaged people out of their memories of the Sound, their memories of their childhood.''</p>
        <p>He's been on the board from the beginning, and is working with many religious leaders to create Celebrate the Earth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller stressed the role of the community in the new center. ''If it is important to the community, it is important to the environment. History teaches us that many cultures practiced and believed that, and it is becoming obvious that we must think that way again.</p>
        <p>''Try to consider having a healthy, viable community with unhealthy air and polluted waters. We cannot, and the connection of a healthy environment to a healthy community, and, in fact, to healthy people, will be one of the many premises we will try to teach at the SoundWaters Community Center.''</p>
        <p>The grand opening of SoundWaters Community Center for Environmental Education takes place from 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. on Saturday and from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. next Sunday. It features habitat stations, kayaking lessons, bulb planting, bird watching, storytelling, an arts and learning tent, and entertainment. Information: (203) 323-1978 or www.soundwaters.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
