<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rotting? Stinking? Perfect!</title>
    <meta content="22TERESIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teresi, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dekkers, Midas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marx-Macdonald, Sherry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Way of All Flesh, The: The Romance of Ruins (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF143FF931A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rotting? Stinking? Perfect!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dick Teresi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Teresi, Dick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Teresi reviews book The Way of All Flesh: The Romance of Ruins by Midas Dekkers, translated by Sherry Marx-Macdonald (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WAY OF ALL FLESH</p>
        <p>The Romance of Ruins.</p>
        <p>By Midas Dekkers.</p>
        <p>Translated by Sherry Marx-Macdonald.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 280 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WAY OF ALL FLESH</p>
        <p>The Romance of Ruins.</p>
        <p>By Midas Dekkers.</p>
        <p>Translated by Sherry Marx-Macdonald.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 280 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $25.</p>
        <p>Having fallen asleep at a meeting called by my publisher, I awoke to find that, in my slumber, she had named me editor of Longevity, a magazine dedicated to the proposition that aging and death were passe. Death took exception, and within a few years the publication's president, its executive editor, its chief writer and an art director had all gone to early graves, as did the magazine itself, to the applause of a grateful nation. I escaped unscathed, having been mercifully fired after the third issue for, among other things, suggesting a change in the publication's name to Morbidity.</p>
        <p>Midas Dekkers would approve, ridiculing, as he does, our obsession with staying youthful and alive. ''The Way of All Flesh'' is a celebration of decay and death, an acknowledgment that ''life is a way of dying slowly.'' Dekkers, the Netherlands' most popular writer-biologist, is hardly profound -- he lacks the organizational ability to create a coherent point of view -- yet his is an entertaining book that offers up a concatenation of facts revealing that life is a fetid and rotting affair. I decay, therefore I am.</p>
        <p>Dekkers says that we do not develop as children, plateau as adults and then rapidly decline as geezers. Rather, we begin life with a period of rapid decline, and end it with a slow, gentle demise: ''During a single month in a baby's life, the ability to replace old cells with new diminishes more rapidly than during one whole year of an old person's life.'' Dekkers likes decaying things, cut flowers in a vase, for instance. ''People delight in watching them die,'' he writes. ''All patients feel better after watching their flowers die before they do.'' He admires the semen of men between the ages of 60 and 90, as it contains more sperm per milliliter than that of mere youths. Dekkers loves ruins and decaying art. The only way to find good paintings, he says, is to look among the works of lesser-known masters who escaped the 19th-century restoration frenzy. ''Perhaps all restorers should be banished to the same island, far away from here -- and I'd be happy to see all nature conservationists sent there too.'' Fresh meat? No one buys fresh meat from the butcher, he points out. It would turn stiff in the shopping bag on the way home. What butchers sell is actually carrion -- meat that has gone limp after 36 hours. The author probably has no future as a food critic or menu writer.</p>
        <p>He adopts an epater le bourgeois attitude, but I suspect it's just a quasi-hip affectation. If dying things are beautiful, why does he offer up such gruesome descriptions? Male salmon, he writes, ''develop thick hooked jaws and hunchbacks. After spawning, they become covered with a fungus that begins to eat away at them, while inside, one organ after another starts to give way.'' Beef stew doesn't come off much better. Leftover dinner stew, he writes, is swarming with a million staphylococci by lunchtime the following day, after being ''thumbed, sneezed and coughed on.'' Of course, here in America it is less customary to sneeze in the stew. (Note to self: cancel supper invitation to Midas Dekkers.)</p>
        <p>Dekkers is immensely popular in Europe, a kind of Dutch Isaac Asimov. The beloved Asimov was famous for typing faster than he could write. Dekkers writes faster than he can research. He implies that acid rain is caused by the hole in the ozone layer, says the writer John McPhee is a geologist and confuses Empedocles with Pythagoras. He states that subatomic particles decay with ''predictable regularity.'' (Not really. That's why we measure their life span in half-lives.) Dekkers says that human babies are genderless: ''There's no difference at all between males and females at this stage.'' He admits later that he has no children. (I had sort of guessed this.) He also insists that birds show no sign of age, a statement to which my neighbor, the biologist Theodore Sargent, responds, ''This sounds crazy to me!'' Caged birds age conspicuously, Sargent says, and bird banders use a variety of criteria to estimate age. ''Cats stay children all their lives,'' Dekkers continues, asserting that adult cats remain as playful as kittens. (I doubt he has tabbies either.)</p>
        <p>Most annoying is his treatment of evolution. Dekkers lectures us that nature is ruled by chance, that there is no progress in evolution, that ''life has no goal.'' His approach, on the other hand, is entirely teleological. He relates a breathless string of ''just so'' stories: humans originally inhabited wide, open plains, so our babies scream at the top of their lungs; cancer cells instill ''fear in the body'' so that a system of checks has been introduced into each cell; only the ''best'' eggs and the ''very bravest'' sperm unite. What happened to chance? My favorite: barnacle larvae are immobile, Dekkers explains, so they have penises many times the length of their own bodies in order to ''penetrate a neighboring female.'' How, then, would the author explain John Holmes, the highly mobile yet well-endowed porn star? (Besides, barnacles are hermaphrodites; wouldn't short penises be more adaptive?)</p>
        <p>THE translator, Sherry Marx-Macdonald, has done an admirable job of replacing Dekkers's long, clumsy Dutch words with good short English ones. The spelling and punctuation are annoyingly British (here in America we prefer our periods and commas inside the quotation marks), and the word choice is sometimes puzzling (Marx-Macdonald doesn't maintain the distinction between ''further'' and ''farther''), but anyone who can take Dutch and make it not-Dutch deserves an honored place in society.</p>
        <p>Dekkers himself may not translate to our culture as well as his prose; his idiosyncrasies extend beyond sneezing into the occasional stew. In the past he has written about bestiality, and he opposes laws that prohibit sex between adults and children, saying such laws result in ''sex-starved maniacs'' and ''nitwits.''</p>
        <p>Children, Dekkers says, need lots of practice and the guidance of adult coaches. Sex, he says, is just like soccer. (Note to self: bone up on corner kick techniques before upcoming romantic weekend.) Dekkers is not a young man, and I take some comfort -- as do soccer moms worldwide -- that his libido, like spawning salmon and festering leftovers, will eventually decay, wither and die.</p>
        <p>Dick Teresi is writing a book about the non-European roots of science.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dick Teresi is writing a book about the non-European roots of science.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
