<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Sinking Feeling, Again</title>
    <meta content="29VENI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Subsidence</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adriatic Sea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ammerman, Albert J (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DD1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Sinking Feeling, Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Albert J Ammerman and other archaeologist studying origins of Venice say study of artifacts and structures that lets them estimate both past and future rates of subsidence indicates that city is sinking faster than ever; findings suggest multibillion-dollar plan to build floodgates to save city from rising waters is doomed; Ammerman, concerned that encroaching Adriatic Sea could devastate city in coming century, calls for fresh approach to saving city; map; graphs; diagrams; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Science often rests on chance discoveries. So it is that an American archaeologist studying the origins of Venice has stumbled on clues suggesting that a multibillion-dollar plan to build floodgates to save the city from rising waters is doomed.</p>
        <p>''Be careful,'' Dr. Albert J. Ammerman warned as he pulled a tarp from an archaeological dig, freeing swarms of mud wasps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Science often rests on chance discoveries. So it is that an American archaeologist studying the origins of Venice has stumbled on clues suggesting that a multibillion-dollar plan to build floodgates to save the city from rising waters is doomed.</p>
        <p>''Be careful,'' Dr. Albert J. Ammerman warned as he pulled a tarp from an archaeological dig, freeing swarms of mud wasps.</p>
        <p>The pit, 10 feet deep and more than 30 feet wide, had been dug next to an ancient basilica. The hole was below sea level, with a pump keeping it from filling with water. At its bottom lay one of the oldest known signs of human habitation in the Venetian archipelago -- a stone walkway dated to around the second century.</p>
        <p>This and kindred discoveries show that, over the ages, people living here have had to haul in countless tons of dirt, silt, wood and stone to fortify their swampy isles and keep their homes and cities from disappearing into the sea. And the findings suggest that the floodgates plan -- one of the biggest public works projects of all time -- could produce as many problems as it solves, causing wide ecologic damage.</p>
        <p>''You have to see this to understand how the ground builds up,'' said Dr. Ammerman, a Colgate University archaeologist who has studied the origins of Venice for more than a decade. That the city rests on millions of wooden stilts pounded into marshy ground is well known. But the surprising age and abundance of other kinds of supporting materials is only now coming to light, with large implications for public policy.</p>
        <p>The lost world of artifacts and structures is letting Dr. Ammerman and his colleagues in Italy and the United States estimate both past and future rates of subsidence. The news is bad for a city whose famous piazzas and streets already flood with alarming regularity.</p>
        <p>For complex reasons, the scientists say, Venice is sinking faster than ever and in the coming century the encroaching waters of the Adriatic Sea could devastate this celebrated city of art and architecture. The situation will only get worse if global warming causes seas to rise.</p>
        <p>In fact, they say, surging waters will overwhelm the main way Italy is planning to fight the danger -- 79 mobile floodgates meant to cut off the Venetian lagoon and its islands from the highest of the high tides. The plan, drawn up decades ago and debated since then, is on the verge of approval by the Italian government. It is estimated to cost $2 billion to $4 billion, and has won backing from Italian companies eager for the work.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ammerman, 58, an expert about things Venetian, has decided to air his findings widely in hopes of thwarting the project and spurring research on alternative ways of saving Venice, a cultural icon that 10 million people visit each year. It is also his home when he is not at Colgate, in Hamilton, N.Y.</p>
        <p>His finds ''are raising basic questions about the feasibility'' of the mobile floodgates, he wrote last week in the journal Science. Saving the city will take fresh thinking, he added, perhaps through an international competition for new ideas.</p>
        <p>''It's a test case for the future,'' said Charles E. McClennen, a Colgate geologist who aids Dr. Ammerman's inquiries here and who collaborated on the Science article. ''We got into this research by accident. But now we see its general importance for cities in many coastal regions.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ammerman's work is financed by Colgate, the Delmas Foundation, the Kress Foundation and the National Geographic Society.</p>
        <p>That Venetians live a few precarious inches above sea level is evident to any visitor to this city of 117  islands. Its canals teem not only with gondolas and motorboats but fish large and small, as well as algae and seaweed. On hot summer days, the canals at low tide give off a pungent odor said to be based partly on decomposing sea life and partly on the outflows of ancient plumbing.</p>
        <p>Every day, the tides here go up and down about three feet. Tides that are more extreme, known as ''acqua alta,'' or high water, tend to occur between October and April and periodically inundate Venice, most alarmingly in 1966 when flooding caused wide damage and economic losses. The tidal surges are driven by heavy rains, winter weather patterns and southerly winds that blow Adriatic waters northward.</p>
        <p>On many old buildings, the red bricks of the ground floors are coated by a patina of white -- corrosive sea salt soaked up by the absorbent bricks, which weakens them and causes them crumble.</p>
        <p>Low wooden doors are often stained or rotted away at the bottom because of past flooding, and commercial shop doors often have metal guides that allow the quick installation of waterproof gates. Raised walkways are set up in in winter floods. And some tour books recommend high boots.</p>
        <p>It was sheer accident that Dr. Ammerman came to delve into the origins of Venice, and that his work opened a new window on the dimensions of the flooding menace.</p>
        <p>An environmental archaeologist trained at the University of London, he worked in Italy in the 1970's and 1980's studying sites around Parma, Calabria and Rome, including the Forum.</p>
        <p>A specialty of his was extracting core samples and dating materials to better understand the original context of ancient objects and monuments.</p>
        <p>In 1989, Dr. Ammerman was living in Venice, happy to have a break from Rome's gritty bustle, when Dr. Maurizia de Min, a senior archaeologist at Venice's Superintendency of Monuments, asked him for assistance. She was helping restore a church, San Lorenzo, and wanted him to probe beneath it.</p>
        <p>''We hit stuff three feet down,'' he recalled. ''We hit archaeological things. We moved lower. It was always the same -- layers of living and building materials.''</p>
        <p>''That was the turning point,'' Dr. Ammerman said. ''We started to realize that there was a whole world down there that no one had ever imagined.''</p>
        <p>Historians have long known that Venice rose to power in the ninth century, its swampy isolation a bulwark against invaders, its location on the Adriatic a boon for trade. But the scientists managed to illuminate its lost infancy, going back more than 500 years further.</p>
        <p>Through the 1990's, working closely with Dr. de Min and the Superintendency of Monuments, Dr. Ammerman investigated six sites in Venice and its lagoon. Each proved a revelation about past habitation and building practices, the evidence always surprisingly deep and speaking volumes about subsidence rates over the ages.</p>
        <p>The most extensive dig was on Torcello, an island in the lagoon about a half hour's boat ride from Venice. Some of the first Venetians landed there while fleeing the barbarians.</p>
        <p>During a recent visit to Torcello, Dr. Ammerman stepped carefully into the deep pit where the scientists had uncovered the low stone walkway dated to the second century. Pointing to an area higher up, and thus younger, he noted a stone hearth, dated to the sixth century, and, higher still, a road surface made of aligned stones, dated to about the seventh.</p>
        <p>Given the ground's softness, he said, ''people had to keep building up'' or face destruction from encroaching tides and waves.</p>
        <p>A major breakthrough in his work was understanding that the depth of such artifacts could yield a way to gauge old sea levels, and thus the rate of ground subsidence over the centuries.</p>
        <p>For instance, Dr. Ammerman found that the second-century walkway, probably of Roman origin, had been erected near the edge of the island about 20 inches above what was then the sea level.</p>
        <p>Back at his apartment in Venice, he displayed a long, clear plastic tube filled with a deep core sample recently taken from below the walkway area, its streaks of brown and yellow telling of its composition.</p>
        <p>Scores of such samples and depth calculations have revealed the arc of accelerating subsidence since the Venetian lagoon formed 6,000 years ago. Dr. Ammerman calculates that, per century, human artifacts sank at a rate of about three inches, then five, then 10, with the fastest decline in the 20th century.</p>
        <p>The causes of the speedup are complex, he said. Factors include local industry's pumping of water from beneath the Venice region (which has been stopped), the oxidation of peat that forms as part of the substrate, the compaction of spongy sediments under the growing weight of buildings and slow changes in plate tectonics and the region's geology.</p>
        <p>In June 1999, Dr. Ammerman, Dr. McClennen, Dr. de Min and Dr. Rupert Housley of the University of Glasgow published an overview of their speedup findings in Antiquity, a top archaeology journal.</p>
        <p>It was this research that led Dr. Ammerman to conclude that Italy's main solution to the flooding problem would not work because it was based on flawed estimates of the subsidence rate.</p>
        <p>The floodgates, he reasoned, would have to close 94 to 150 times each year during high tides, destroying the lagoon's delicate ecological balance, basically cutting it off from the sea and its cleansing flows.</p>
        <p>The floodgates would be built in lines at the entrances to the Venetian lagoon. Lying flat in housings on the seabed, they would in theory have no effect on shipping or regular tides. When storm surges were forecast, compressed air would be pumped into their hollow inner cavities, forcing out water and causing the hinged gates to tilt upward and rise to the surface to block incoming swells.</p>
        <p>Since the worst tides come mostly in winter, Dr. Ammerman and Dr. McClennen wrote last week in Science, gate closure ''will end up taking place repeatedly, day after day and week after week.''</p>
        <p>Defenders of the plan are unmoved, saying Dr. Ammerman is exaggerating the difficulties. Anyway, they say, if the water rises faster than expected, as Dr. Ammerman says it will, the barriers are all the more crucial.</p>
        <p>''The gates become even more urgent if the worst scenarios are right,'' said Dr. Rafael L. Bras, an environmental engineer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who led an international assessment of the floodgate plan.</p>
        <p>But in all likelihood, he said, the gates would have to close far less often than Dr. Ammerman foresees and would do little or no ecological harm.</p>
        <p>The Consorzio Venezia Nuova, the bloc of Italian companies eager to build the floodgates, Friday denounced the Colgate researchers as ''clearly less concerned with the validity of scientific data than they are with attempting to persuade the Italian government to withdraw the concession granted to Italian construction companies.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Ahmet S. Cakmak, an emeritus professor of civil engineering at Princeton, who reviewed Dr. Ammerman's calculations on soil mechanics, strongly defended the archaeologist. ''He has done a very careful study,'' Dr. Cakmak said yesterday in a telephone interview. ''I support him completely.''</p>
        <p>John Keahey, a journalist writing a book about saving Venice, said Dr. Ammerman's arguments were ''having a big impact'' on Italian politicians. ''They could use this as an excuse to delay a decision,'' Mr. Keahey said. ''The government is in a struggle to survive, and they would probably rather use the money to give the citizens a tax break.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ammerman said the Consorzio would rather attack him and spend money than face the facts.</p>
        <p>''Everybody wants a silver bullet,'' he said. ''But that doesn't exist,'' at least not yet.</p>
        <p>Something may emerge in an international competition, he said. But in the meantime, Venice needs to continue what it has already started: raising sidewalks and canal walls, elevating power supplies and telephone lines and moving people out of the first floors of residences.</p>
        <p>''People should do what people have always done here since the beginning, which is to build up the ground,'' Dr. Ammerman added, stressing the importance of old strategies. ''This buys you time to work up a better solution that doesn't create equally bad problems.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
