<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apology Highlights ABC Reporter's Contrarian Image</title>
    <meta content="14ABC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000815T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stossel, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Twenty/twenty (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Relations and Publicity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organic Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DA133FF937A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apology Highlights ABC Reporter's Contrarian Image</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG and FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity; Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On-air apology by ABC news magazine 20/20 correspondent John Stossel for inaccuracies in a news feature highlights his controversial position at ABC; Stossel is a man of strong opinions, trait that does not always go over well within network's news division, and he has drawn strong criticism from liberals and praise from conservatives for his reports on environmental and consumer issues; reporting error, in which Stossel cited pesticide tests that were never done in segment on organic foods, is putting him under scrutiny by a wider audience while creating a public relations mess for ABC News; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last Friday evening on the TV news magazine ''20/20,'' John Stossel, the square-jawed consumer and environmental correspondent, was forced to do something relatively rare for ABC News or any other network news operation: deliver an apology on the air for inaccuracies in a news feature.</p>
        <p>What was not so rare, though, was Mr. Stossel's being in the thick of a controversy at ABC. He is a man of strong opinions, even about the work of his colleagues -- a trait that does not always go over well within the network's news division.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last Friday evening on the TV news magazine ''20/20,'' John Stossel, the square-jawed consumer and environmental correspondent, was forced to do something relatively rare for ABC News or any other network news operation: deliver an apology on the air for inaccuracies in a news feature.</p>
        <p>What was not so rare, though, was Mr. Stossel's being in the thick of a controversy at ABC. He is a man of strong opinions, even about the work of his colleagues -- a trait that does not always go over well within the network's news division.</p>
        <p>Last month, for instance, Mr. Stossel took aim at the environmentalist icon Erin Brockovich, the feisty legal secretary portrayed by Julia Roberts in a recent movie. On the program ''20/20,'' he cast doubt on  the lawsuit she helped bring charging Pacific Gas and Electric with contaminating the groundwater in Hinkley, Calif.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stossel believed that his ''20/20'' co-anchor, Cynthia McFadden, among other reporters, had too blindly accepted Ms. Brockovich's case in an earlier ABC News report. So he discussed fighting it out with  Ms. McFadden in a broadcast.</p>
        <p>This made Ms. McFadden angry, people familiar with the situation said, and she complained loudly to her supervisors. She told colleagues she would refuse to appear on the program. When it was shown, Elizabeth Vargas was the anchor. The segment did not refer to Ms. McFadden's report.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Ms. Brockovich demanded that Mr. Stossel apologize for his ''dangerous and misleading broadcast.'' He did not.</p>
        <p>All in all, just another day for Mr. Stossel. Reviled in some quarters as an ideologue and crusader, admired in others for his fresh, contrarian approach, Mr. Stossel is an anomaly in television journalism. Reporters are generally forced to keep their ideologies to themselves. Mr. Stossel is allowed to make his views known.</p>
        <p>And that he does. An unabashed libertarian, he has argued that greed is good for the economy; that environmentalists are ''scaremongers'' with vastly overblown fears of global warming and pollution, and, even, that seat belts in school buses are a waste of money.</p>
        <p>His views have put him under intense scrutiny in the hothouse world of environmental and consumer politics. And now an error made in a recent ''20/20'' segment -- in which he cited pesticide tests that were never done to debunk the assumed benefits of organic foods -- has put him under scrutiny by a wider audience while creating a public relations mess for ABC News. From now on, Mr. Stossel is likely to draw even more attention.</p>
        <p>As coverage and criticism of Mr. Stossel spread last week, ABC, a unit of Walt Disney, took the rare step of publicly reprimanding him, and suspending the producer of the report, David W. Fitzpatrick, for one month, without pay. On ''20/20'' Friday night, Mr. Stossel apologized.</p>
        <p>''I apologize for the error,'' he said, saying he mistakenly thought the tests referred to in the report had been conducted. ''I am deeply sorry I misled you.'' But he said the gist of his report was accurate.</p>
        <p>The whole episode sent jitters throughout ABC News, which recently took heat for allowing the actor Leonardo DiCaprio to interview President Clinton about environmental issues on a prime-time special, a move that split the division internally. Executives tried to figure out how the pesticide error made it through what they describe as an elaborate vetting process.</p>
        <p>Shelley Ross, the executive producer of ''Good Morning America,'' sent an e-mail to her staff members, warning them to take all complaints about their reports seriously. Mr. Stossel and his producer, the message said, were punished not so much for their mistake, ''but for the arrogance of ignoring complaint letters that followed.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists still insist that Mr. Stossel should be fired. But ABC executives said they would do no such thing.</p>
        <p>By all appearances, they are fond of Mr. Stossel. His edgy, distinctive approach tests well in audience research. And, in fact, he is allowed to operate within the news division as a sort of island unto himself. He is given the sort of freedom no other ABC reporter has: though not labeled a commentator, he is allowed to take a point of view and report  stories based on that point of view. He has his own unit of 8 to 10 staff members who help him with his weekly segments on ''20/ 20,'' and with his various prime-time specials.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Stossel said he wanted to answer his critics directly, but ABC would not allow it, making Phyllis McGrady, an ABC News senior vice president, available instead.</p>
        <p>Ms. McGrady said executives like Mr. Stossel's work because his reporting goes against the grain of the established media and offers the network something fresh and different. Though he avoids the traditional pose of objectivity, he bases his conclusions on hard reporting, she said. This hard-edged approach, she said, makes him a target of the powerful groups he offends.</p>
        <p>''He's an original thinker, and he is not afraid to tackle complicated issues,'' she said. ''He takes on issues that are thought-provoking and what he is wanting and hoping for and, yes, advocating for, is for you to become a freer thinker, to basically stand back and look at it from every perspective.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stossel's point of view is welcomed by various conservative and industry groups. Though ABC has a general policy against paid public speaking engagements, as are  some of his colleagues, Mr. Stossel is allowed to accept such offers. He was quoted in the March 2000 issue of Brill's Content magazine as saying he had spoken to 27 groups in the last two years, collecting hundreds of thousands of dollars in fees. An ABC executive said those engagements were approved because all of the money he collects went to charity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stossel is advertised, along with Charlton Heston, as one of the most sought-after speakers of the Young America's Foundation, a conservative group. This year, a spokesman for the Y.A.F. said, Mr. Stossel had given speeches at three schools, including Washington &amp; Lee University, the Stetson School of Law in Florida and Florida State University.</p>
        <p>His strong views, combined with speaking engagements before conservative groups, opens Mr. Stossel up to criticism. So heated is his opposition that FAIR, a liberal-minded media watchdog group, has an entire Web site devoted to what it sees as distortions.</p>
        <p>As serious as the pesticide mistake was, there is a general belief within ABC News that the situation was worsened because of the lobbying prowess of the groups Mr. Stossel tends to provoke.</p>
        <p>Still, the organic food mistake certainly played directly into Mr. Stossel's critics' accusations that he is biased and tailors his reporting and statistics to fit his fervent belief system -- in this case, that organic farmers are preying on fear of chemicals to sell overpriced food with its own problems.</p>
        <p>During his initial report, shown on Feb. 4, to an audience of 12 million, Mr. Stossel said that tests commissioned by ABC showed conventional produce did not necessarily have more pesticide residue than did organic produce, debunking a main selling point for organic food.</p>
        <p>But the two researchers who were commissioned by ABC -- Dr. Michael Doyle, a scientist at the University of Georgia, and Dr. Lester Crawford, director of the Center for Food and Nutrition Policy at Georgetown University -- said they had never tested produce for pesticide residue.</p>
        <p>Dr. Crawford said that he had tested samples of organic and conventional chicken and that those tests had found traces of pesticides in the regular poultry, not in the organic. Those findings were not mentioned in the ''20/20'' segment.</p>
        <p>After the report was first broadcast, advocates with the Environmental Working Group wrote a letter that alerted Mr. Stossel that the researchers said they had not conducted the tests. The report ran again on July 7 with the same information, however.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was not until The New York Times raised the issue in a Media Talk column on July 31 that ABC News began to investigate the situation in earnest and found that the test results in question did not exist.</p>
        <p>ABC executives said on Friday that they believed that the erroneous reference to pesticide tests was the result of honest mistake, though a serious one. There are valid explanations for all of the critics' charges, they said.</p>
        <p>They said Mr. Fitzpatrick was receiving a spate of different test results on organic and conventional foods, had become confused and somehow had developed the solid notion that produce was tested for pesticide residue.</p>
        <p>Even when he was contacted by the environmentalists, executives said, Mr. Fitzpatrick continued to believe that he had the results in question. In a subsequent conversation with Dr. Crawford, when Mr. Fitzpatrick asked if pesticide tests had been performed, Dr. Crawford answered in the affirmative. Dr. Crawford said in a recent interview that he did so because he was referring to the pesticide tests performed on chicken.</p>
        <p>Why were the chicken tests, which would go against the grain of Mr. Stossel's argument, not included in the report? In his apology, Mr. Stossel said he did not refer to them because he was focusing on produce.</p>
        <p>Michael Jacobsen, executive director of the Center for Science in the Public Interest -- whose group is supported by subcribers to its publications and by the Rockefeller Family Fund and the Park Foundation -- said though he found Mr. Stossel's erroneous organic food report egregious, he was not surprised by it. He said he believed it to be in keeping with what he sees as Mr. Sossel's bias in favor of industry.</p>
        <p>That such an accusation could be attached to Mr. Stossel would have been unimaginable 10 years ago. His point of view has evolved drastically in the course of his career. Once a dogged consumer reporter for WCBS-TV, the local New York City CBS station, and then for ABC, he won his early reputation railing against corporate America. But in the early 1990's, his views changed. He evolved into a true believer in the free market and came to believe that advocates and the media were unnecessarily scaring consumers.</p>
        <p>His transformation took place in an ideologically charged arena. Evidence about the impact of toxic substances on humans is hotly disputed.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Stossel's transformation has angered liberal groups, it has delighted conservative ones.</p>
        <p>Walter Olsen, of the libertarian-oriented Manhattan Institite, said Mr. Stossel was now ''filling in what we don't get from the rest of'' the media. Other reporters, Mr. Olsen said, ''have broadcast grossly misleading stuff over the years.''</p>
        <p>Though he apologized on night for the error, the gist of his statement was that his segment was still correct. The clear message from Mr. Stossel: despite this setback, he intends to continue his brand of journalism. But, he said in his apology: ''All we have in this business is our credibility -- your trust that we get it right. I will make every effort to see that it never happens again.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA  Correction:  August 15, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Business Day yesterday about controversy over the reporting of ABC's consumer and environmental correspondent, John Stossel, misspelled the surname of a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute who has defended Mr. Stossel. The defender is Walter Olson, not Olsen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 15, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about controversy over the reporting of ABC's consumer and environmental correspondent, John Stossel, misspelled the surname of a senior fellow at the Manhattan Institute who has defended Mr. Stossel. The defender is Walter Olson, not Olsen.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
