<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The State of the World, and the World to Be, in 149 Chapters</title>
    <meta content="Y07NAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/07/world/07NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED71439F934A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The State of the World, and the World to Be, in 149 Chapters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan tells 149 world leaders attending 'millennium summit' that they have ability to transform lives of six billion people; each leader is allowed five-minute speech, but meeting will probably be remembered more for private meetings in hotel suites and diplomatic offices around New York City than for anything said in cavernous hall of General Assembly; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The question hangs out there: Why would 149 world leaders leave their not-always-stable governments unattended to come to New York and make five-minute speeches, mostly to each other and the television cameras from back home?</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan had an answer today as he lifted his glass to the biggest power lunch in history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The question hangs out there: Why would 149 world leaders leave their not-always-stable governments unattended to come to New York and make five-minute speeches, mostly to each other and the television cameras from back home?</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan had an answer today as he lifted his glass to the biggest power lunch in history.</p>
        <p>''You,'' he said, looking out over the world's political elite, ''have the authority to speak for, and the ability to transform, the lives of six billion people.''</p>
        <p>This ''millennium summit'' was a gamble, organized not to celebrate a new page on the calendar but to look ahead at what kind of a global society the leaders hope to achieve in this century, if not the millennium to come.</p>
        <p>But from the start, everyone knew that it would go beyond that, and would probably be remembered more for the private meetings in hotel suites and diplomatic offices around town than for anything said in the cavernous hall of the General Assembly.</p>
        <p>There was a kind of easy camaraderie born of the unusual event, with back-slapping, hugs, kisses and the puzzled faces of interpreters trying to keep up with the in-jokes.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, for one, could not resist telling President Jiang Zemin of China, as they sat down to lunch, what a softball interview the Chinese leader had with CBS's ''60 Minutes.'' ''Mike Wallace is so mean to us,'' Mr. Clinton complained to his lunch-table buddies, ''and he was purring in front of him.''</p>
        <p>President Fidel Castro of Cuba, whose reputation for long-winded speeches is legendary, brought laughter to the Assembly late in the afternoon when he took out a white handkerchief and covered the timer on the lectern. But he stayed within the allotted time -- and waved triumphantly before retaking his seat.</p>
        <p>For an hour early this morning, many of the world's most familiar faces passed by the knot of protocol officers waiting at the canopied delegates' entrance to United Nations headquarters. As speeches began -- they are expected to go on well into Friday evening -- the stock-taking that emerged was not so much of the world the leaders hoped to see, but of the stark realities out there.</p>
        <p>''The statistics of poverty and inequality in our world are shocking and shameful,'' said Prime Minister Bertie Ahern of Ireland. ''Half the world's population struggling on less than $2 a day, over half a billion on less than $1. A quarter of a billion children of 14 and under working, sometimes in terrible conditions. Death from preventable and treatable diseases -- 10 people will die of malaria in the five minutes I take to address you.''</p>
        <p>President Olusegun Obasanjo of Nigeria -- who shared a lunch table with Mr. Clinton, Mr. Annan, Mr. Jiang, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, two kings and several others -- is currently chairman of the Group of 77, a forum for developing nations. In an interview on Monday, when Mr. Obasanjo had more than five minutes to explain what the third world was seeking at these meetings, he said:</p>
        <p>''The wishes of the developing world are simple. We are all living in the same house, whether you are developed or not developed. What we are saying is that some of us in this house are living in superluxurious rooms; others are living in something not better than an unkempt kitchen where pipes are leaking and there is no toilet. We are saying, 'Look, in the interest of all of us, let us living in the superluxurious rooms pay a bit of attention to those who are living where the pipes are leaking, or we'll all be badly affected.'</p>
        <p>''That's the message.''</p>
        <p>There were repeated warnings to heed the dark side of globalization, the technology and health gaps as well as the unbalanced use of natural resources. There were also calls for a more democratic United Nations, with a Security Council more reflective of a membership that has changed profoundly since the organization's founding in 1945.</p>
        <p>''If we want this United Nations organization to fulfill its lofty goals, indeed if we want it to remain relevant in the 21st century,'' Prime Minister Said W. Musa of Belize said in his speech, ''we must remake it into an organization that takes global governance away from the self-appointed few and brings greater democracy to all its operations.''</p>
        <p>A number of speakers took the opportunity to float their own international initiatives.</p>
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia proposed a project in cooperation with the International Atomic Energy Agency to destroy radioactive materials and exclude them from civilian energy use. He also suggested that the 40th anniversary next spring of the first manned space flight -- by a Russian -- be commemorated by an international conference on the prevention of the military uses of space.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Putin and President Jiang were robbed of their biggest arms-control target, the proposed American nuclear missile defense, when Mr. Clinton delayed deployment last week. Mr. Putin did reaffirm the importance that Russia attaches to the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty, which many nations say would be directly threatened by a new American system.</p>
        <p>The angriest speaker of this first day of the summit meeting was probably Prime Minister Lester B. Bird of Antigua, who went on the attack against the Group of 7 industrialized nations and the larger Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development for their efforts to tighten or close down tax havens.</p>
        <p>''While the spin doctors of the O.E.C.D. have attempted to cloak their position in moral rectitude with references to the evils of money laundering,'' he said, ''harmful tax competition has nothing to do with money laundering.'' He said the campaign was a ploy by ''what amounts to a high-tax cartel'' of rich nations.</p>
        <p>His passion illustrated the difficulties in selling international financial regulation to those countries that believe they can only stand to lose when rules are tightened.</p>
        <p>There were some overtones of sadness and poignancy in many of today's 60-plus speeches. Starting with Secretary General Annan, there were condemnations of the killings of three international aid workers, and perhaps a fourth, in West Timor by rampaging Indonesian militias. Indonesia's president, Abdurrahman Wahid, whose nation's army and police patrol the island to prevent trouble, sat impassively in the hall. (He speaks on Thursday.)</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Prime Minister Blair called attention to the plight of Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, the Burmese democracy leader, who is enduring a new round of repression under a military junta that robbed her of an election victory a decade ago.</p>
        <p>''I do not wish to leave the U.N. without saying this,'' Mr. Blair said. ''The treatment of Aung San Suu Kyi by the Burmese regime is a disgrace. I call on the Burmese government to let her go free, and I call on fellow world leaders to back that call.''</p>
        <p>It was left to President Maumoon Abdul Gayoom of the Maldives to plumb the existential depths, as he spoke for those island nations threatened with extinction in rising seas caused by global warming. ''When the U.N. meets to usher in yet another century,'' he said, ''will the Maldives and other low-lying nations be represented here?''</p>
        <p>As his five minutes ended, he added: ''My time at the podium is up. But I pray that that of my country is not.''</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
