<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DF1E3BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Though Polls Favor Rival, Milosevic Is Likely to 'Win'  Opinion polls for Yugoslavia's presidential election indicate that President Slobodan Milosevic is trailing the main candidate of Serbia's opposition, Vojislav Kostunica. But even the opposition expects Mr. Milosevic to declare victory, and he has the support of Serbs who credit the president's unceasing message that the current leader is better than the foreign-financed opposition.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Though Polls Favor Rival, Milosevic Is Likely to 'Win'  Opinion polls for Yugoslavia's presidential election indicate that President Slobodan Milosevic is trailing the main candidate of Serbia's opposition, Vojislav Kostunica. But even the opposition expects Mr. Milosevic to declare victory, and he has the support of Serbs who credit the president's unceasing message that the current leader is better than the foreign-financed opposition.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Iran Reduces Jews' Sentences  An appeals court in Iran reduced the sentences of 10 Iranian Jews who had been convicted of cooperating with Israel in a trial that drew international scrutiny and criticism.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Warning on North Korea  A Pentagon report said North Korea remained a military threat, despite recent signs of a diplomatic warming on the Korean peninsula.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Peru Military Supports Fujimori  Military leaders publicly backed President Alberto K. Fujimori, dampening speculation that the armed forces might move to oust him. They said they respected the president's authority and decision to dismantle the intelligence service, whose chief was recently shown on videotape apparently offering a bribe to an opposition congressman.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Chirac Accused in Videotape  A videotaped confession by an aide who died last year accuses President Jacques Chirac of France of operating a slush fund financed by kickbacks while he was mayor of Paris. Mr. Chirac dismissed the accusations as a ''fantastic story.''</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>India to Pull Peacekeepers  India told the United Nations that it would withdraw its troops from the organization's peace-keeping force in Sierra Leone, in the wake of a dispute between African leaders and the force's Indian commander.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Plan to Expand Admissions  The University of California's president, seeking to lessen the effect of a state ban on affirmative action, proposed expanding guarantees of provisional admission to the top 12.5 percent of students at every high school, up from the current 4 percent.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-23</p>
        <p>Gore Seeks Oil Release To Stabilize Prices  Vice President Al Gore said the White House should release a modest amount of oil from government stockpiles to stabilize oil prices, a move that Gov. George W. Bush denounced as a political ploy that could endanger national security.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>On Death and Deterrence  The dozen states that have no death penalty have no higher homicide rates than states with the death penalty, government statistics and a New York Times survey show.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pollution Tests 'Falsified'  Federal officials said thousands of environmental safety tests at Superfund locations, landfills and other hazardous waste sites from 1994 to 1997 would have to be repeated because the company that performed the tests, Intertek Testing Services, falsified the results.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Investigation Assailed  Mayor Bill Campbell of Atlanta denounced federal officials as ''forces of evil'' for looking at his private life as they investigate possible corruption in government contracts.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Computers and the Disabled  President Clinton announced initiatives intended to raise the number of disabled people with access to computers and the Web.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Calories and Longevity  Biologists say they have shown why a lower-calorie diet prolongs life span, at least in lab rodents.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Doubt on Anti-Warming Tactic  A German study found that old forests were superior to new plantations of trees in sopping up carbon dioxide, a heat-trapping gas released by burning fossil fuels. New plantations figure prominently in a proposed treaty to fight global warming.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Tougher Strains of Gonorrhea  Federal health officials say data from Hawaii and Missouri indicate that gonorrhea is becoming resistant to a wider variety of antibiotics.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Aid for Mutilation Victims  A little-known operation developed in World War I has been used to restore some grasping ability to people whose hands were chopped off with machetes in terrorist attacks during the civil war in Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Port Authority Curbs New La Guardia Flights  The Port Authority, citing ''unacceptable'' delays, told airlines that they could not add more flights at La Guardia's busiest flying times, morning and evening. Airline executives questioned whether the authority could impose such limits.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Effort to Curtail Soft Money  Lazio and Clinton campaign officials met to discuss an agreement to stop the use of soft money in the Senate campaign. If a deal is reached, Hillary Rodham Clinton may be at a disadvantage, since her official campaign committee's fund-raising has lagged that of Rick A. Lazio's.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Web Retailer Coming to Bronx  City officials said a major Internet retailer, Webvan Group, would take over a huge vacant building in the South Bronx that once served as an Alexander's distribution center, a move that would provide 900 jobs.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>U.S. Women End Losing Streak  The United States softball team beat New Zealand, 2-0, their first victory in Sydney after two losses.</p>
        <p>D6</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
        <p>S1-8</p>
        <p>A Faulty Apparatus  An error made in the measurement of the vault apparatus during the women's Olympic all-around final cast doubt on the validity of the outcome and might have cost the former world champion Svetlana Khorkina a chance to win a medal.</p>
        <p>S1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-28; E29-42</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Edward S. Gordon  A commercial real estate broker who built one of the largest real estate service companies in the New York City area, the Edward S. Gordon Company, he was 65.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Gherman Titov  The second Russian to fly in space and the first man to sleep there, during his daylong flight in 1961, was 65. The general died of carbon monoxide poisoning in a sauna.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Icahn Walks Away From G.M.  The billionaire investor Carl C. Icahn has sold his stake in General Motors, just a month after telling it he might buy as much as 15 percent of its shares. Mr. Icahn would not disclose when he sold his shares or the size of his stake, but he said it was less than $15 million. He was said to be angry that G.M. had disclosed his plans, driving up the share price.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bickering Over Auto Safety  Firestone assailed the safety of Ford Explorers at a House hearing, as the companies criticized each other's products, and executives tried to explain internal documents that congressmen found incriminating.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Weighs New Tire Inquiry  Federal officials said they were considering opening a formal investigation of Cooper Tire and Rubber, citing lawsuits asserting that dozens of deaths and serious injuries had been caused by premature tread separations on tires it made.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Warning From Intel  The chip maker warned after the markets closed that its third-quarter revenues were likely to be below expectations, mainly because of weaker European demand for its chips.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Reckless campaign spending -- soft money in New York, Mr. Corzine's gifts in New Jersey; oil for the winter; free Lori Berenson.  Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E40  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E28  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>A22</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
