<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida Utility Settles Air Pollution Lawsuit</title>
    <meta content="Y01AIR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1180467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Electric Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD81339F932A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida Utility Settles Air Pollution Lawsuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government's campaign to make seven utilities bring old coal-fired electric plants up to modern pollution standards shows its first results when Tampa Electric Co agrees to spend about $1 billion to switch one plant to natural gas and make major changes at second (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government's campaign to make seven utilities bring old coal-fired electric plants up to modern pollution standards showed its first results today when a Florida utility agreed to spend about $1 billion to switch one plant to natural gas and make major changes at a second.</p>
        <p>The Tampa Electric Company did not admit guilt but agreed to pay a penalty of $3.5 million to settle civil charges brought by the Environmental Protection Agency under the Clean Air Act. The utility also agreed to spend $10 million on pollution control research and experimentation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The government's campaign to make seven utilities bring old coal-fired electric plants up to modern pollution standards showed its first results today when a Florida utility agreed to spend about $1 billion to switch one plant to natural gas and make major changes at a second.</p>
        <p>The Tampa Electric Company did not admit guilt but agreed to pay a penalty of $3.5 million to settle civil charges brought by the Environmental Protection Agency under the Clean Air Act. The utility also agreed to spend $10 million on pollution control research and experimentation.</p>
        <p>The federal agreement supersedes a settlement that the utility had made with the State of Florida. That agreement was contingent on Tampa Electric's being allowed by the state Public Service Commission to pass along the cost of the re-engineering of the plants to its customers.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said today's settlement in the case that was brought last November was a legal wedge to gain agreements with the other six utilities. They hinted that they would bring charges against more utilities under a provision of the Clean Air Act requiring that when old plants are modernized they be brought up to current air pollution standards.</p>
        <p>''This is a precedent that will send a signal to the other companies that this is what we think is appropriate control,'' said Sylvia Lowrance, principal deputy assistant administrator of the agency.</p>
        <p>Carol M. Browner, the agency administrator, said the change would reduce emissions that cause or aggravate respiratory disorders.</p>
        <p>The executives said that their willingness to convert the plant was based in part on plans taking shape for a new gas line in Florida and on the fact that existing equipment is near the end of its life. As well, a new gas plant could make electricity at the same price as the old coal plant.</p>
        <p>The plant, Gannon, was built in 1957, and company officials said that rebuilding it as a gas-fired plant would allow them to use the steam turbines and some other equipment and raise its output at a time when the demand for electricity is growing rapidly. The agreement, they said, would also protect them in case the agency set more stringent rules on coal plants in the future.</p>
        <p>''This is actually a business decision, in light of what all is going on in the environmental area,'' said Spence Autry, a vice president of the utility, who negotiated the deal. ''It puts us in a very good position for whatever could come down the pike later on.''</p>
        <p>The rebuilt Gannon plant, using high-efficiency natural gas technology, would produce electricity for about the same price as the coal plant, he said.</p>
        <p>The other utilities charged with Tampa Electric in November were adamant that the settlement, which had been rumored since the company reached the state agreement in December, did not have any bearing on them.</p>
        <p>''The settlement with TECO really has no impact on our case,'' said Pat Hemlepp, a spokesman for American Electric Power, which uses the most coal among the investor-owned utilities. ''We don't feel pressured by this to have any rush to settlement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hemlepp said that there were no settlement discussions under way but that ''we are always willing to talk about reasonable solutions to this enforcement action.''</p>
        <p>Electricity experts pointed out that Tampa Electric is smaller than the other utilities in the case and, unlike the bigger defendants, can commit to switching to natural gas without affecting the national market for that fuel.</p>
        <p>The federal settlement requires Tampa Electric to make changes at a second coal-fired station, Big Bend. The company has agreed to improve the performance of scrubbers, which reduce emissions that cause acid rain, and to install another kind of system to control smog-forming nitrogen oxide emissions by 2010. If the utility cannot meet that deadline, the plant must be shut down or switched to natural gas by 2007.</p>
        <p>Changing to natural gas reduces emissions sharply. Ms. Browner said that switching Gannon to natural gas would reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, by 60 tons a year, and fine particles, which are lung irritants, by 2,000 tons per year. Nitrogen oxide would fall by 30 tons per year. ''These are very, very large reductions,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
