<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Falling Short on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="28TUE2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/28/opinion/28TUE2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6DC173DF93BA15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Falling Short on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial laments that 170 countries gathered in The Hague to address threat of global warming fell short of main objective to translate 1997 Kyoto Accord into detailed, enforceable treaty; says recriminations should not obscure fact that significant progress was made on important issues or diminish resolve of nations to move ahead at next meeting in May 2001 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 170 countries that gathered in The Hague to address the threat of global warming have fallen short of their main objective, which was to translate the 1997 Kyoto Accord into a detailed, enforceable treaty. The British are blaming the French, the French are blaming the Germans, and nearly everyone is blaming the United States. But the inconclusive result and the post-conference recriminations should not obscure the fact that significant progress was made on important issues. Nor should it diminish the resolve of these nations to move forward when they reconvene next May.</p>
        <p>The United States, by far the biggest producer of the greenhouse gases that are believed to be a big part of the warming problem, has a special obligation to see that the diplomacy continues. Whoever is chosen as the next American president needs to put the matter on his agenda right away and assemble a team to continue the negotiations. This should present no problem for Al Gore, an architect of the Kyoto agreement. For George W. Bush, who has acknowledged that global warming is a problem but has criticized Kyoto as placing too heavy a burden on the United States, it will mean a fast trip up the learning curve on a complicated issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 170 countries that gathered in The Hague to address the threat of global warming have fallen short of their main objective, which was to translate the 1997 Kyoto Accord into a detailed, enforceable treaty. The British are blaming the French, the French are blaming the Germans, and nearly everyone is blaming the United States. But the inconclusive result and the post-conference recriminations should not obscure the fact that significant progress was made on important issues. Nor should it diminish the resolve of these nations to move forward when they reconvene next May.</p>
        <p>The United States, by far the biggest producer of the greenhouse gases that are believed to be a big part of the warming problem, has a special obligation to see that the diplomacy continues. Whoever is chosen as the next American president needs to put the matter on his agenda right away and assemble a team to continue the negotiations. This should present no problem for Al Gore, an architect of the Kyoto agreement. For George W. Bush, who has acknowledged that global warming is a problem but has criticized Kyoto as placing too heavy a burden on the United States, it will mean a fast trip up the learning curve on a complicated issue.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto agreement committed the industrialized countries to cut their greenhouse gas emissions below 1990 levels by 5.2 percent. The dominant greenhouse gas is carbon dioxide, caused by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil in power plants and vehicles. In principle, the agreement allowed nations to meet their targets in several ways. They could make ''real'' reductions in fossil fuel use, for example by investing heavily in cleaner fuels and cleaner plants. They could earn credits by investing in clean-air projects in other countries, or by buying those credits on the open market from other countries that had already met their targets. They could also claim credit for so-called carbon ''sinks'' -- forests that remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere through photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>The talks in The Hague collapsed mainly because the industrialized countries could not agree on how much credit should be given for trees. The United States' opening proposal was clearly unacceptable. It wanted to meet half its goal by counting its existing forests, a proposal the Europeans quite properly suspected as a scheme to get something for nothing. On the other hand, the Europeans showed scant appreciation for political realities in the United States, including Congress's deep suspicion of any treaty that would threaten economic growth by imposing crippling burdens on energy use. By the end of the conference, the United States had reduced the credits it wanted for forests and other sinks by nearly three-fourths -- a reasonable compromise, but not to some Europeans.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there was heartening progress on other issues, including vital cost-effective mechanisms that will allow nations to trade emissions credits on the open market and claim credit for investing in clean-fuel projects abroad. There was also agreement on meaningful penalties for non-compliance. That progress -- and the increasingly persuasive science about the perils of global warming -- are reasons enough to try again in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
