<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED8173AF93BA25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1342" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>2 Panels in Congress Give Backing to China Trade Bill  Committees in the House and the Senate overwhelmingly endorsed the administration's China trade bill, contributing to a growing sense among its backers that the measure was headed for passage. Half a dozen previously uncommitted House Republicans and Democrats announced their support for the legislation, which would permanently grant China normal trading privileges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush, calling trade relations with China the work of ''13 years and three administrations,'' urged Republicans and Democrats alike to support President Clinton and vote for the bill next week.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>2 Panels in Congress Give Backing to China Trade Bill  Committees in the House and the Senate overwhelmingly endorsed the administration's China trade bill, contributing to a growing sense among its backers that the measure was headed for passage. Half a dozen previously uncommitted House Republicans and Democrats announced their support for the legislation, which would permanently grant China normal trading privileges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush, calling trade relations with China the work of ''13 years and three administrations,'' urged Republicans and Democrats alike to support President Clinton and vote for the bill next week.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton on National Security  President Clinton told the graduating class of the United States Coast Guard Academy that the world was becoming more dangerous, with new threats from disease, terrorism and even global warming.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Sierra Leone Rebel Captured  Foday Sankoh, who vanished nine days ago after dealing humiliating blows to the United Nations peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone, was captured in Freetown, outside his abandoned house. United Nations and British officials said he was in the custody of Sierra Leone's government and was being protected by British paratroopers. The United Nations is trying to negotiate the release of 270 peacekeepers held hostage by Mr. Sankoh's group.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Discussions began at the United Nations on whether legal options exist to bring Mr. Sankoh to justice, because no international tribunal has automatic jurisdiction over him.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Ethiopia Pushes into Eritrea  Ethiopia's drive into Eritrea intensified as dozens of tanks and thousands of troops streamed north to join a battle for control of the area around the strategic town of Barentu.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Belgrade TV Station Seized  The government seized control of the main opposition television station, accusing it of advocating an uprising. Taken by surprise, opposition politicians talked of the beginning of an outright dictatorship under President Slobodan Milosevic and called an immediate protest rally; 20,000 people took to the streets.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Dominican Republic Results  The electoral council said Hipolito Mejia of the left-leaning Dominican Revolutionary Party had won 49.85 percent of the vote, with 99 percent of the ballots counted. Earlier, Mr. Mejia declared himself the winner of Tuesday's presidential election.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Minister Denies Bribery Charge  Finance Minister Kiichi Miyazawa of Japan denied charges that when he was prime minister he bribed a politician for his silence. The politician, Kishiro Nakamura, who was construction minister from 1992 to 1993, testified against Mr. Miyazawa on Monday.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-29</p>
        <p>2 With Klan Ties Charged In 1963 Church Bombing  Thomas E. Blanton Jr., 61, and Bobby Frank Cherry, 69, two longtime suspects in the bombing that killed four black girls at the 16th Street Baptist Church in Birmingham, Ala., were indicted on murder charges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Trends in Domestic Violence  A Justice Department study showed a big drop in domestic murders, particularly the killings of black men by their black female partners, which fell 74 percent over the last two decades. But the number of white women killed by their husbands and boyfriends rose slightly.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Employers Faulted on Coverage  Congressional investigators say thousands of employers are violating a federal law that requires similar levels of insurance coverage for mental and physical illnesses.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Fire's Risk Underestimated  A National Park Service plan for igniting what has become the largest fire in New Mexico history foresaw ''moderate'' risk that the prescribed blaze would go beyond its limits.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Missile System Faulted  An M.I.T. professor, Theodore A. Postol, said there is a major flaw in the Pentagon's antimissile plan and urged the White House to investigate what he said was a cover-up.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Decline in Draft Registration  The government said 88 percent of young men now register for the draft at age 18, as required by law. The last draftee was inducted in 1973, and the highest level of registration since then was 97.7 percent, in 1991.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Espionage Trial in Miami  Opening statements were made in the trial of an immigration official, Mariano Faget, who is accused of leaking classified information.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Gore's Warning to Retirees  Vice President Al Gore told a convention of older people that Gov. George W. Bush's plan to let workers invest some of their Social Security taxes could jeopardize retirement benefits of current recipients.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Sentiment for One Big Primary  Americans would prefer a single national primary to the present system, which they feel gives too much influence to early states, a New York Times/CBS News Poll found.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Assessing Pollutant's Effect  E.P.A. scientists say in a draft report that dioxin is 10 times more likely to cause cancer than previously estimated. But some experts doubt that the report's conclusions will stand up to a review board's scrutiny.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Diet and Hypertension  A diet low in salt and high in fruits, vegetables and low-fat dairy products was found to lower blood pressure as much as medication did.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Treating Chronic Depression  A study indicates that a combination of antidepressants and psychotherapy works significantly better than either treatment alone.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Speaker Silver Challenged By a Fellow Democrat  The second-ranking member of the State Assembly, Michael J. Bragman, said he would try to overthrow Speaker Sheldon Silver in a vote on Monday. The speaker then removed Mr. Bragman as majority leader.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Tape Shows Florio Reversal  Jim Florio said he had ''no difficulty'' with a limited investment of the Social Security trust fund in stocks, according to a tape recording of remarks he made a year ago. Mr. Florio has recently demonized Jon S. Corzine, his opponent for the Democratic Senate nomination in New Jersey, for supporting a ''risky scheme'' that would invest government money in the stock market.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Restaurant Inspections, Online  The Department of Health inaugurated a Web site listing every blemish noted by inspectors at all licensed restaurants in the five boroughs.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Levy Named Chancellor  The Board of Education unanimously removed the 'interim' from Harold O. Levy's title; he is expected to be offered a two-year contract.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Suit on Equality in Education  Civil rights groups sued California, saying the disparities between the best and worst public schools were so great as to violate the state Constitution's guarantee of a free and equal public education for all.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Miami Leads Knicks, 3-2  The Heat beat the Knicks, 87-81, leaving Miami one victory away from clinching their playoff series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>A 19-Year Record Finally Falls  Susie O'Neill, a 26-year-old Australian, broke swimming's oldest record by finishing the 200-meter butterfly in 2 minutes 5.81 seconds.</p>
        <p>D4</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Midler vs. 'Millionaire'  Bette Midler will make her first attempt at a television series this fall with ''The Bette Show,'' a comedy that CBS will put up against ABC's ratings star, ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>E10</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-24</p>
        <p>U.S. Holding Firm on Breakup  The government defended its plan to break up Microsoft in court documents that disparaged Microsoft's alternative proposal as ''a cosmetic remedy that would have virtually no competitive significance.''</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New Chief at Mattel  Mattel hired the chief executive of Kraft Foods, Robert A. Eckert, 45, as chairman and chief executive. He succeeds Jill E. Barad, who quit in February after failing to turn around a software unit Mattel had bought.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Ethics Intensifies  Fox and TheStreet.com battled over the future of a cable television program on investing in a growing dispute over the promotion of TheStreet.com's stock on the program by the company's co-founder, James J. Cramer.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-12</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-22</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: Alabama's long search for justice; the last battle of the gulf war; fresh leadership at 110 Livingston.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E5  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E10  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
