<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Layers of Evidence Suggest Mars Had Water</title>
    <meta content="Y05MAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/05/science/05MARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1252701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Malin Space Science Systems</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malin, Michael C (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edgett, Kenneth S (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDB143CF936A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Layers of Evidence Suggest Mars Had Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New analysis of spacecraft photography of Mars appears to show that, in its earliest history, much of planet had lakes and shallow seas that left distinct layers of sedimentary rock where fossil record of life, if it existed, would most likely be preserved; photos; evidence is that Mars, though cold and arid now, apparently was once warmer, with denser atmosphere and, presumably, standing water where there could have been life; Dr Michael C Malin of Mars Global Surveyor explains in statement issued by NASA; he and Dr Kenneth S Edgett have also written report to be published in Science; Malin Space Science Systems operates spacecraft camera for NASA (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new analysis of spacecraft photography of Mars appears to show that in its earliest history, much of the planet was a land of lakes and shallow seas and that this left distinct layers of sedimentary rock where a fossil record of Martian life, if it ever existed, is most likely to be preserved.</p>
        <p>The discovery, scientists said, provided some of the most striking evidence yet that Mars, though cold and arid now, was once a warmer world with a denser atmosphere and presumably substantial amounts of flowing and standing water. And where there has been liquid water, scientists say, there could have been life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new analysis of spacecraft photography of Mars appears to show that in its earliest history, much of the planet was a land of lakes and shallow seas and that this left distinct layers of sedimentary rock where a fossil record of Martian life, if it ever existed, is most likely to be preserved.</p>
        <p>The discovery, scientists said, provided some of the most striking evidence yet that Mars, though cold and arid now, was once a warmer world with a denser atmosphere and presumably substantial amounts of flowing and standing water. And where there has been liquid water, scientists say, there could have been life.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued yesterday by NASA, Dr. Michael C. Malin, principal investigator for photography on the Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft, announced: ''We see distinct, thick layers of rock within craters and other depressions for which a number of lines of evidence indicate that they may have formed in lakes or shallow seas. We have never before had this type of irrefutable evidence that sedimentary rocks are widespread on Mars.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Malin added that the latest photographs showed that ''early Mars was very dynamic and may have been a lot more like Earth than many of us had been thinking.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Malin and Dr. Kenneth S. Edgett, both with Malin Space Science Systems in San Diego, which operates the spacecraft camera for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, have also written a formal report of their analysis to be published in Friday's issue of the journal Science. In the article, they described pictures from the Mars Global Surveyor that showed outcrops of horizontal sedimentary layers that they estimated as dating from the earliest period of preserved Martian history, 4.3 billion to 3.5 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>Some of the layering had been observed by earlier spacecraft, but never in such detail or over such a broad expanse of Mars.</p>
        <p>Scientists generally praised the research as reinforcing theories that Mars billions of years ago had a warmer climate that was potentially more favorable to life in some form.</p>
        <p>A few of the most spectacular outcrops examined in the photographs were more than two miles deep, accumulations of fine-grained particles turned to rock. Nearly all of them were observed inside craters and chasms, like the huge continent-long Valles Marineris. The prevalence of sedimentary layers within basinlike terrain suggested that they were deposited by water, perhaps in lakes that filled the ancient craters for periods of time, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Malin and Dr. Edgett said the  sediments ''argue for small, closed catchment and depositional basins.'' In a few cases where no craters appeared to be involved, the outcrops hinted at ''the possible existence of shallow seas,'' they added.</p>
        <p>Dr. Malin said the photographs showed that the outcrops constituted ''hundreds and hundreds of identically thick layers, which is almost impossible to have without water.''</p>
        <p>The scientists acknowledged that their interpretation of the photographs would be appealing to those who investigate Mars for any possible evidence that it had a much different climate in the distant past and so could have harbored some forms of life, however briefly.</p>
        <p>''The pictures described here, in fact, show exactly the types of materials in which the record of Martian life, if it ever existed, is most likely to be preserved,'' Dr. Mallin and Dr. Edgett concluded in the journal report.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce C. Murray, a planetary geologist at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, said, ''That layering is really important stuff.''</p>
        <p>Not only does it focus attention on a very early period of Martian geology, of which knowledge is sparse, but the new findings, Dr. Murray said in an interview, also provide an intriguing geological record of ''when there was an Earthlike atmosphere'' on Mars. The atmosphere, he explained, would have had to be relatively dense -- not tenuous, as it is today -- for the Martian surface to have had craters filled with lakes of water.</p>
        <p>Mars today has a thin atmosphere, composed almost entirely of carbon dioxide. As a smaller planet than Earth, Mars presumably lacked the gravitational strength to hold on to most of the atmosphere and water it may have started with, when the solar system originated 4.6 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jim Garvin, the Mars exploration program scientist for NASA, said the findings ''tell us that more study both from orbit and at the surface is needed to decipher the tantalizing history of water on Mars.''</p>
        <p>The growing evidence for water on Mars, which may have been especially abundant in the past, has encouraged scientists in their search for signs that primitive life may have once arisen on the neighboring planet. A study of spacecraft photographs in June produced strong evidence of gullies, sinuous valleys and other eroded Martian landscape produced by flowing water in recent times.</p>
        <p>Scientists commenting on the June report suggested that water, frozen beneath the surface, may still erupt from time to time in brief floods.</p>
        <p>In their analysis of the more ancient evidence, Dr. Malin and Dr. Edgett conceded that the sedimentary deposits could have been laid down in other ways besides lakes. Wind, volcanic eruptions and even an asteroid impact could have had similar effects. But the widespread phenomenon is more satisfactorily explained by lakes' forming in the basins, geologists said.</p>
        <p>The two scientists favored a scenario in which sediments may have been transported into the lakes in regular, swift pulses, building up thin layers. The thicker layers may have been the result of an especially deep or stagnant lake, in which sediments were laid down over much longer periods.</p>
        <p>Dr. Edgett said the ancient sediments are ''going to tell us a lot about what early Mars was like, and maybe the early Earth as well, since we don't have a lot of rocks on our own planet from this time period.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
