<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y27CAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/politics/27CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7DB1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
        <p>BOY SCOUTS TAKE ISSUE -- The campaign of Gov. George W. Bush stirred up unhappiness yesterday on an unusual front: The Boy Scouts of America want the campaign to excise a 3 1/2-second image of scouts raising a flag from a new commercial, which talks about education and never mentions the scouts directly. Gregg Shields, national spokesman for the scouts, said their lawyer had told Bush campaign that ''it would be inappropriate to imply any endorsement by the Boy Scouts of America.'' Mr. Shields said such use of scout pictures in political ads happened from time to time, but the spots were ordinarily altered after complaints. Mindy Tucker, speaking for the Bush campaign in Austin, said no complaint had been received.</p>
        <p>Adam Clymer (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
        <p>BOY SCOUTS TAKE ISSUE -- The campaign of Gov. George W. Bush stirred up unhappiness yesterday on an unusual front: The Boy Scouts of America want the campaign to excise a 3 1/2-second image of scouts raising a flag from a new commercial, which talks about education and never mentions the scouts directly. Gregg Shields, national spokesman for the scouts, said their lawyer had told Bush campaign that ''it would be inappropriate to imply any endorsement by the Boy Scouts of America.'' Mr. Shields said such use of scout pictures in political ads happened from time to time, but the spots were ordinarily altered after complaints. Mindy Tucker, speaking for the Bush campaign in Austin, said no complaint had been received.</p>
        <p>Adam Clymer (NYT)</p>
        <p>IACOCCA SPEAKS OUT FOR BUSH -- Lee A. Iacocca, the former Chrysler chairman who became a household name in the 1980's by appearing in car commercials, is now appearing in a Republican television campaign in Michigan, contending that Vice President Al Gore's views on the environment are a threat to jobs in the state's automotive industry. ''Al Gore may see the car as our enemy, but in Michigan, it's our jobs,'' Mr. Iacocca says in the 30-second television commercials, designed to help Gov. George W. Bush steal some of the heavily Democratic auto union vote. He accuses Mr. Gore of holding extreme views on vehicles, the internal combustion engine and the effect of exhaust emissions on global warming. Democratic leaders in the state are already firing back at Mr. Iacocca, saying that he was never a true friend of auto workers.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE THIRD PARTIES</p>
        <p>ELECTION GUIDE IS FOUND LACKING -- Third-party candidates do not agree on many issues, but in Denver they agree on one: The Rocky Mountain News has treated them unfairly, they say. The newspaper's 24-page election guide published last Sunday all but ignored them. The only third-party candidates mentioned were those running for president. They received a line each, compared with full reports on Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. The Denver Post, a rival, published a 52-page election guide, including information on all candidates who provided some. On Wednesday, representatives from Colorado's third parties -- Libertarian, Reform, Green, Natural Law and Constitution -- took to the streets, protesting in front of the newspaper's downtown offices.</p>
        <p>Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>RULING AGAINST WEB COMPANY -- A North Carolina company has been instructed by a federal court to give up Internet Web addresses that steer potential supporters of Patrick J. Buchanan to pornographic sites. The court, in a decision handed down a few days ago, ordered the owner of the sites, Rendina Solutions of Durham, to hand over the Web addresses to Mr. Buchanan's Reform Party presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The campaign had filed suit complaining that the addresses -- all named for the Reform Party ticket -- contained links to pornographic material. Mr. Buchanan's official site is buchananreform.org. The suit also complained that the head of the company, Mark Rendina, had tried to persuade the Buchanan campaign to buy the offending sites for $10,000.</p>
        <p>In ordering the company to hand over the addresses, the court cited a new federal law making it illegal to register another person's name on the Web with the intent to profit. The company will have an opportunity to appeal the ruling during a hearing on Oct. 30.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ON THE TRAIL</p>
        <p>FUN WITH STATE CAPITALS -- In the end, it was hard to tell whether he had taught her so well after all. Vice President Al Gore's 23-year-old daughter, Kristin, a comedy writer for the Fox TV program ''Futurama,'' has been introducing her father at rallies in the Pacific Northwest. In her lighthearted speeches, she has credited him with teaching her to list the Beatles' albums in chronological order and with grilling her on state capitals. At a rally in Portland, Ore., on Sunday night, she demonstrated his pedagogical skill by announcing that the capital of Oregon was Salem, while admitting that she used to ''fall into the Portland trap.'' But at a rally later in the week in Everett, Wash., it was hard to know whether she was joking, or had fallen into another trap of the Pacific Northwest. ''He also was the guy,'' she said of her father, ''who helped me study for my third-grade state capital quiz. Seattle. Got it down.'' The crowd hissed loud enough to be heard in Olympia, the real state capital. Gore aides later insisted the line was just one of her standard jokes.</p>
        <p>Kevin Sack (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE STATES</p>
        <p>A BROTHERLY CONNECTION -- Why has more than half of the money in the campaign treasury for the state auditor of North Carolina come from Atlanta? The answer apparently lies in his last name. The auditor, Ralph Campbell, is the older brother of Bill Campbell, Atlanta's mayor, and $115,000 of the $228,000 he has raised in his re-election campaign has come from Atlanta donors. The contributors include Atlanta's police chief and city attorney, as well as one of Mayor Campbell's security officers and several companies that do business with the city. Ralph Campbell's opponent in the race, Leslie Merritt, has submitted the campaign finance reports to the F.B.I., which is already investigating Mayor Campbell as part of a wider inquiry into possible corruption in government contracts in Atlanta. Ralph Campbell says the money was raised legitimately, by one brother helping another.</p>
        <p>David Firestone (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE TELEPHONE CAMPAIGN</p>
        <p>ED ASNER ON THE LINE -- Democrats have begun making tens of thousands of recorded phone calls featuring the actor Ed Asner assailing George W. Bush's Social Security plan.</p>
        <p>The calls, begun over the weekend in several battleground states, echo the message being delivered this week in more than $10 million worth of television advertising. A direct-mail blitz is to follow. Like the television commercials and the letters about to be mailed, the phone calls suggest Mr. Bush cannot maintain benefits for retirees and at the same time allow younger workers to divert some of their tax money into private accounts.</p>
        <p>''George W. Bush has a proposal that would undermine Social Security, even threatening current benefits,'' warns Mr. Asner, an advocate of liberal causes who is best known for playing Lou Grant on ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show.'' He says that ''intelligent changes'' are needed in the Social Security program ''but not at the cost of current retirees.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 100,000 calls will be made, according to officials of the Democratic National Committee.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE TRAVEL LOG</p>
        <p>THE NUMBERS -- Vice President Al Gore took his message of environmental prosperity to Midwestern swing states yesterday, while Gov. George W. Bush headed for Pennsylvania, an Eastern swing state. The numbers:</p>
        <p>Length of Official Day: Gore, 18 hours; Bush 13 hours</p>
        <p>States Visited: Gore, 4; Bush, 3</p>
        <p>Official Events: Gore, 5; Bush 3</p>
        <p>Cities/Towns Visited: Gore, 4 (Moline, Ill., Davenport, Iowa; Madison, Wis., and Charleston, W.V.); Bush, 4 (Tampa, Fla.; Pittsburgh and Erie, Pa.; and Toledo, Ohio)</p>
        <p>Miles traveled: Gore, 920; Bush, 1172</p>
        <p>Main message: Gore, environment; Bush, leadership</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
