<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Role in Ads Puts Focus on Bush Friend</title>
    <meta content="Y06WYL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1181872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POWER BROKER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Sam Wyly</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyly, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DF1238F935A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Role in Ads Puts Focus on Bush Friend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr. with RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard; Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., March 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sam Wyly, wealthy Dallas investor who spent $2.5 million for television advertisements smearing environmental record of Republican presidential candidate Sen John McCain, has been major financial backer of Gov George W Bush's political career for several years and major figure in cozy world of Texas business and Republican politics for more than three decades; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sam Wyly, the wealthy Dallas investor, has spent a lot of money in recent years on two goals that suddenly converged last week: Boosting the political career of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and improving the fortunes of his Vermont-based power company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyly, a major figure in the cozy world of Texas business and Republican politics for more than three decades, last week admitted paying $2.5 million for televised advertisements attacking the environmental record of Senator John McCain, who is battling Mr. Bush for the Republican presidential nomination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sam Wyly, the wealthy Dallas investor, has spent a lot of money in recent years on two goals that suddenly converged last week: Boosting the political career of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and improving the fortunes of his Vermont-based power company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyly, a major figure in the cozy world of Texas business and Republican politics for more than three decades, last week admitted paying $2.5 million for televised advertisements attacking the environmental record of Senator John McCain, who is battling Mr. Bush for the Republican presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>Bush officials deny playing any role in the advertisements, which Mr. Wyly said were produced solely by him and his son. But the flap, coming just before the primaries that could decide the nomination, has focused attention on a central member of the wealthy group of Texas businessmen who have played a large role bankrolling Mr. Bush's seven-year-old political career.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the elite,'' said Craig McDonald, director of Texans for Public Justice, a nonprofit group in Austin that tracks money in Texas politics. ''He's one of the movers and shakers. He's very big money in the state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McDonald said donations by Mr. Wyly and his brother, Charles, to Mr. Bush's two campaigns for governor totaled about $210,000, putting them behind only Enron Corporation and members of the Bass family, the Fort Worth, billionaires, as the largest source of Mr. Bush's money for those races.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyly, in an interview on Friday, said he ''of course'' hoped that the advertisements would aid Mr. Bush's chances against Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>''We would like to see all the Congressmen and senators and everybody who's running for everything talking about clean air,'' Mr. Wyly said. ''We have a mission for clean air through clean energy. We're just getting started. This won't be the only primary or the only election we'll be bringing our issue to.''</p>
        <p>He added that the $2.5 million advertising buy, which is paying for advertisements that run through Tuesday, may be expanded. ''We're thinking about doing more and doing it nationwide, but we haven't made a decision on that.''</p>
        <p>Tom Smith, a longtime environmental activist in Texas, said he met Mr. Wyly last spring while lawmakers in Austin debated a bill that would open the Texas electric utility industry to competition -- and which could help Greenmountain.com, a concern in South Burlington, Vt., that his family has invested in, by allowing customers to buy renewable energy in the open market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith, the Texas director of Ralph Nader's group, Public Citizen, was concerned that provisions requiring certain coal-fired power plants to reduce their pollution might be left out of the bill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyly ''allowed that he was a major donor to both the older and younger Bushes, and he asked how he could help.'' Mr. Smith told him to go lobby the governor, which he said Mr. Wyly did. Eventually, the bill passed with the provision. ''Wyly was helpful, though I'm not sure he was pivotal. But he certainly got the governor's attention.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said he was impressed with Mr. Wyly, who he said appeared to be committed to environmental causes. But he added that many environmental advocates had doubts about how environmentally friendly Mr. Wyly's energy company actually is, and that they have also been critical of Mr. Bush's environmental record.</p>
        <p>Further, he said, the episode ''is a crystalline example of what donors get from Bush for their contributions -- an opportunity to make their pitch.''</p>
        <p>Steve Wolens, the Democratic legislator who wrote the House version of the bill, said he met with Mr. Wyly for almost three hours last year, but that Mr. Wyly never sought to influence him on specific provisions of the bill.</p>
        <p>''He was obsessed with talking about the environment. I just wasn't expecting it from a Republican,'' said Mr. Wolens, who said he was surprised by Mr. Wyly's views on a number of issues, including support for abortion rights. ''There was nothing right wing about the man at all.''</p>
        <p>Bush officials confirm that Mr. Wyly met with Mr. Bush to lobby him, but they said the power-plant provisions had Mr. Bush's support anyway. Dan Bartlett, a Bush spokesman, added that Mr. Bush ''met with all kinds of people'' on the bill.</p>
        <p>Along with his brother, the 65-year-old Mr. Wyly oversees a family fortune that some estimate at $1 billion, made through computer services, oil and mining, steakhouses, retailing, e-commerce, and the operation of a large hedge fund that invests money for institutions and wealthy individuals.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Wyly's early years are reminiscent of another politically active Dallas computer services executive, Ross Perot. Mr. Wyly founded University Computing in 1963, using mainframes at Southern Methodist University to do jobs for customers. By the 1960's, the brothers had become very large Republican campaign donors, and President Nixon appointed Sam Wyly chairman of a federal panel charged with improving business opportunities for minorities.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, Mr. Wyly suffered several setbacks, including the failure of an expensive plan to build a data transmission network to compete against what was then called American Telephone &amp; Telegraph, and a scrape in 1979 with the Securities and Exchange Commission, which had accused him of violating securities laws.</p>
        <p>But more recently he has enjoyed some big successes. One is the Dallas-based hedge fund he founded, Maverick Capital, which has grown into one of the largest in the country, with $4 billion under management.  And just last month, two of his publicly traded companies, Sterling Commerce and Sterling Software, were sold for $3.9 billion each to separate buyers. Lately, he has focused attention on GreenMountain.com. The Wyly family has invested more than $100 million in the firm, and Mr. Wyly is chairman.</p>
        <p>Long a top donor to Governor Bush and other Texas Republicans, Mr. Wyly has other close ties to the Bush camp.</p>
        <p>James B. Francis Jr., a friend and informal adviser to Mr. Bush, has worked as a political adviser to Mr. Wyly, counseling him in 1997 on a proposal in the Texas Legislature -- that both Mr. Wyly and Mr. Bush opposed -- that would have caused certain investment partnerships to pay the state equivalent of a business income tax. The proposal failed.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, Mr. Francis allowed a Dallas lawyer and political consultant who had worked for Mr. Wyly, Jeb Hensarling, to share office space, and the two even formed a partnership, F-H &amp; Associates, that did work for the Wyly family. Mr. Hensarling, who helped Mr. Wyly put the commercials on the air last week, did not return a telephone call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>''Sam is a longtime Republican activist going back into the 60's,'' said Mr. Francis, who is head of the ''Pioneers,'' people who have raised at least $100,000 for Mr. Bush's presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Francis, in an interview on Sunday, said he had not talked to either Wyly brother in a few months.  ''Sam is a damn passionate man. I bet he said, 'I want to help Bush,' and Jeb, who works for him, said, 'You can do an independent expenditure,' and off they went. That's total speculation, but I bet that's what happened.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether the advertisements will affect the primaries on Tuesday. But they have given Mr. McCain, who has accused Bush ''cronies'' of evading federal campaign-finance laws, an issue that he says exemplifies everything he has fought against as he has tried to reform campaign-finance laws. Mr. McCain says it is ludicrous to believe that the Bush camp had no role in, or knowledge of, the advertisements.</p>
        <p>In response, a Bush spokesman, referring to Mr. McCain's campaign bus, said Sunday, ''The closer the Straight Talk Express gets to the garage, the more junk they throw at us from its window.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POWER BROKER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
