<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Human Nature: Born Or Made?</title>
    <meta content="14EVO.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1183764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goode, Erica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Darwin, Charles Robert (1809-82)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3D9133BF937A25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Human Nature: Born Or Made?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERICA GOODE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goode, Erica</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Concepts put forth by evolutionary psychologists provoke controversy; evolutionary psychology holds that human mind is not a 'blank slate,' but instead comprises specialized mental mechanisms for solving problems faced long ago; evolutionary psychologists attempt to use principles of evolutionary biology in studying human mind; evolutionary psychologists have ushered Charles Darwin into new and provocative areas, including sexual attraction between men and women, parenting, jealousy and violence, as well as less touchy regions like learning of language and organization of perception; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When two scientists proposed in a recent book that rape was best viewed as a sexual act with its roots in evolution, it set off a squall of protest from feminists and social scientists, won the researchers appearances on programs like ''Dateline NBC,'' and became the talk of the cocktail party circuit. Even last week the controversy continued, with the book's authors engaging in a rancorous exchange over a critical review in the scientific journal Nature.</p>
        <p>But the case put forward by Dr. Randy Thornhill and Dr. Craig Palmer in ''A Natural History of Rape: Biological Bases of Sexual Coercion,'' published last month by the MIT Press, was not, as some assumed, a fringe theory developed by a pair of renegade researchers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When two scientists proposed in a recent book that rape was best viewed as a sexual act with its roots in evolution, it set off a squall of protest from feminists and social scientists, won the researchers appearances on programs like ''Dateline NBC,'' and became the talk of the cocktail party circuit. Even last week the controversy continued, with the book's authors engaging in a rancorous exchange over a critical review in the scientific journal Nature.</p>
        <p>But the case put forward by Dr. Randy Thornhill and Dr. Craig Palmer in ''A Natural History of Rape: Biological Bases of Sexual Coercion,'' published last month by the MIT Press, was not, as some assumed, a fringe theory developed by a pair of renegade researchers.</p>
        <p>Rather, the arguments made by Dr. Thornhill and Dr. Palmer fit into a larger theoretical framework, the work of a group of scientists who have ushered Darwin into new and provocative areas, including sexual attraction between men and women, parenting, jealousy and violence, as well as less touchy regions like the learning of language and the organization of perception.</p>
        <p>And while some of these researchers, who call their approach ''evolutionary psychology'' (other scientists view it as only one way of approaching evolutionary psychology), would quibble with some of the methods used and conclusions drawn by the authors of the rape book, most would endorse the larger principles that underlie the work.</p>
        <p>The general notion that much of what humans do today evolved in the Pleistocene has seeped into popular culture, and some findings have achieved the status of sound bites: ''Men are polygamous, women monogamous,'' for example, or ''Women rank wealth and status higher in selecting a mate; men put a higher priority on reproductive potential.'' The actor Michael Douglas may have had such precepts in mind when he was asked in a recent interview about his engagement to an actress much younger than he. ''It's something that has existed as long as time,'' he replied. ''As long as history, there have been older men with younger women.''</p>
        <p>The scientists whose work is reflected in such statements, albeit in oversimplified form, are not just trying to attract public attention. They are trying to reshape psychology, placing at its center the question of how the mind was ''designed'' by evolution millions of years ago to solve specific problems faced by human ancestors in an environment very different from the modern world.</p>
        <p>In constructing this new psychology, evolutionary psychologists have crafted a novel approach that differs in crucial respects from other, more traditional ways of viewing the mind, and from methods of other evolutionary scientists who study human behavior.</p>
        <p>For example, the researchers dispute the view that the human mind is a ''general purpose computer'' that is programmed by parents, schools and other cultural influences only after birth. They see the mind as preprogrammed, made up of specialized mechanisms -- ''modules'' or ''organs''-- that predispose all human beings to think and act in certain ways, especially when it comes to basic endeavors like selecting a mate, fighting off sexual competitors or deciding what is safe to eat.</p>
        <p>The genes for these complex mental mechanisms, the argument goes, were passed on through the generations because they were adaptive, enhancing survival or reproductive success, and eventually, they spread widely and became standard equipment.</p>
        <p>But in the year 2000, such mechanisms may or may not be adaptive, and may or may not represent aspects of behavior that society wants to encourage. For example, even if rape was adaptive in the distant past, a notion that even many of Dr. Thornhill and Dr. Palmer's like-minded colleagues think dubious, that would not mean that it is excusable or should not be heavily punished.</p>
        <p>Evolutionary psychologists argue that their job is to approach the mind as an ancient engineering project, developing and testing out hypotheses about what ''design problems'' needed solving, and what universal mental structures might have been designed, by the pressures to survive and reproduce, to solve them.</p>
        <p>Such an approach, they assert, offers a badly needed bridge between psychology and the natural sciences, and will ultimately provide a much firmer foundation for the understanding of human behavior.</p>
        <p>''Psychologists should be interested in evolutionary biology for the same reason that hikers should be interested in an aerial map of an unfamiliar territory that they plan to explore on foot,'' wrote Dr. Leda Cosmides, Dr. John Tooby and Dr. John Barkow in the introduction to ''The Adapted Mind: Evolutionary Psychology and the Generation of Culture'' (Oxford, 1992). ''If they look at the map, they are much less likely to lose their way.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cosmides and her husband, Dr. Tooby, both professors at the University of California at Santa Barbara, are widely regarded as intellectual leaders of the evolutionary psychology school. Joined by several other scientists, including Dr. Donald Symons, also at Santa Barbara, and Dr. Margo Wilson and Dr. Martin Daly, both of McMaster University in Hamilton, Ontario, they hammered out the basic principles of their approach in the mid-1980's in a series of meetings at a hotel in Palm Desert, Calif.</p>
        <p>In the intervening years, this nucleus has expanded to encompass a wide variety of researchers in different areas, including Dr. David M. Buss, a psychologist at the University of Texas, Dr. Thornhill at the University of New Mexico and Dr. Steven Pinker, a psychologist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and the author of ''Words and Rules: The Ingredients of Language'' (Basic Books, 1999) and ''How The Mind Works,'' (W. W. Norton, 1997).</p>
        <p>Evolutionary psychologists have not always carried on their campaign quietly.</p>
        <p>They have issued a noisy assault on the way the social sciences have done business for the last 50 years, asserting that social scientists have a collective phobia about possible biological influences on behavior and an obsession with more ''politically correct'' environmental explanations. Some researchers have thrust their work into the spotlight by pursuing topics that seem guaranteed to push people's emotional buttons, rape being only the latest example.</p>
        <p>In the process, the scientists have gained a reputation for a self-confidence bordering on arrogance, and a style of scholarly debate so unapologetic and uncompromising that, as one observer put it, ''They just make people mad.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps as a result, the scientists' work and occasionally the scientists themselves have attracted no shortage of criticism, from social scientists and within evolutionary science itself.</p>
        <p>Critics have assailed their scientific methods, suggested that some work is tinged by sexism and disputed most of the major tenets of the scientists' approach. And some worry that the studies will be misused by politicians and advocacy groups, who are often quick to blur the distinction between theory and fact.</p>
        <p>''The fact is,'' said Dr. Jerry Coyne, an evolutionary biologist at the University of Chicago and a co-author of the critical review of Dr. Thornhill and Dr. Palmer's book in Nature, ''that evolutionary psychology, except for its barest claims, remains highly controversial, and there are ideological agendas on both sides.''</p>
        <p>The Background  A Disturbing Legacy Of Twisting Darwin</p>
        <p>At the most basic level, some critics oppose any effort to link evolution and human behavior.</p>
        <p>''There are a whole bunch of people who think it's dehumanizing to talk about humans in biological terms,'' said Dr. Robert Boyd, an evolutionary anthropologist at the University of California at Los Angeles. ''They think it's just kind of distasteful.''</p>
        <p>In some cases, people confuse the ''biological'' approach of evolutionary science, which seeks to understand how genes contributed to the evolution of humans as a species, with the field of behavioral genetics, which investigates to what extent heredity accounts for how traits like shyness or schizophrenia vary from person to person.</p>
        <p>But biology, applied to human behavior, also has a disturbing history of misuse. College students in introductory courses are taught the perils of ''social Darwinism,'' a 19th-century theory that borrowed catch words of evolutionary thinking and twisted them into a justification for class differences: the struggle for wealth and power, social Darwinists argued, was a battle for ''survival of the fittest,'' a term coined by Herbert Spencer, an English philosopher.</p>
        <p>Darwin's theory, stretched and distorted in various ways, was also called upon by the Nazis as a rationale for genocide, and has been a staple of forced sterilization campaigns and racist propaganda.</p>
        <p>In the decades after World War II, the record of these abuses created a distrust of biological explanations for human behavior.</p>
        <p>But sensitivity could also turn into virtual censorship, as Dr. E. O. Wilson, a renowned entomologist at Harvard, discovered after publishing his now-classic book, ''Sociobiology,'' in 1975. The book, mostly devoted to a discussion of animal behavior, included a final chapter extending evolutionary theory into the realm of human affairs. It was heavily criticized, and in 1978, as Dr. Wilson began to speak about his theories at a meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science in Washington, protesters heckled him and dumped a pitcher of water on his head.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephen Jay Gould, a paleontologist, and Dr. Richard Lewontin, a population geneticist, both of Harvard, have been the most vocal and prolific of sociobiology's critics, writing a famous 1979 paper, ''The Spandrels of San Marco and the Panglossian Paradigm: A Critique of the Adaptationist Program.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gould, in particular, has continued to find fault with the work of scientists, including evolutionary psychologists, who seek to explain traits as ''adaptations.'' In fact, he argues, many traits are not the products of natural selection, favored because they enhance reproduction or survival, but are simply random byproducts of other evolutionary developments.</p>
        <p>The Issues  Controversial Task, Abundance of Critics</p>
        <p>Some evolutionary biologists have also historically opposed applying Darwinian principles to humans, not because they have moral misgivings about such research, but because they think the task is simply too complicated.</p>
        <p>Trying to determine the evolutionary forces that shaped animal behavior is hard enough, they argue. But to tease out the legacy of evolution from the effects of thousands of years of human culture presents almost insurmountable obstacles, particularly given the limits on the kinds of experiments that can be done with people.</p>
        <p>Yet in the last 20 years, advances in genetics and molecular science have made it impossible to ignore the evidence that biology has at least some impact on how people behave and have made the discussion of genetic influences more widely accepted.</p>
        <p>And evolutionary scientists, able to go about their work in a more tolerant climate, have begun to develop a variety of methods for applying Darwinian principles to humans. Evolutionary psychology, as defined by Dr. Cosmides, Dr. Tooby and others, might involve laboratory experiments, cross-cultural studies and other approaches.</p>
        <p>Other researchers use mathematical models to study foraging and other behavior in modern hunter-gatherer societies. Still others do comparative studies, looking for similarities and differences between humans and animals.</p>
        <p>And the Human Behavior and Evolution Society, founded 15 years ago, counts 1,000 members from a wide variety of disciplines, including biology, psychology, anthropology, law and medicine, who study topics as diverse as the way pheromones coordinate female menstrual cycles and hunting practices among the Ache of Paraguay.</p>
        <p>Still, some evolutionary psychologists feel their arguments for biology must overcome substantial resistance.</p>
        <p>''There is a flagrant double standard that's applied to the evidence,'' said Dr. Buss, whose latest book, ''The Dangerous Passion'' (Free Press, 2000) deals with jealousy, and who has recently proposed that human beings may have a specialized mental module for murder.</p>
        <p>''If it's an evolutionary hypothesis, you have to document mountains of evidence before anyone will take it seriously, and even then it will be dismissed,'' Dr. Buss said. ''On the contrary, if you say there is a sex difference and it's all due to media violence, then the standards are low and everyone accepts it without any evidence.''</p>
        <p>The Real Question  Not a Simple Matter Of Nature/Nurture</p>
        <p>The nature/nurture dichotomy, however, is in many ways spurious. No evolutionary scientist would dispute that culture is a powerful influence, or that environmental forces shape behavior. Darwin himself was in a sense a ''nurturist'': it was the  environment, after all, with all of its threats, possibilities and complications, that in his theory ultimately determined which traits were ''successful'' and passed on to future generations, and which were not.</p>
        <p>A more sophisticated debate, and one central to many of the most knowledgeable critiques of evolutionary psychology, revolves around more subtle distinctions, like the timing of evolutionary change, the criteria used to decide whether something is an adaptation. Then there is the question of the relative balance of culture and genes in determining how humans behave.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cosmides and Dr. Tooby argue that the complex mechanisms, or ''design features,'' that they believe make up the structure of the human mind evolved over millions of years, as combinations of genes proved successful at reproducing themselves, and gradually spread through the species, eventually becoming universal.</p>
        <p>Because of this, they assert, it makes little sense to study traits that vary from group to group, or society to society. Humans are basically all the same, they argue, with only a ''dusting'' of difference. Nor, they say, is it worthwhile to ask whether a particular behavior is adaptive -- in the sense of producing more offspring -- in the modern world. Doing so, they say, can lead scientists wildly astray.</p>
        <p>In an example given by Dr. Cosmides, a scientist might argue that smoking cigarettes is ''adaptive'' for teenage girls because it causes boys to think they are cool. The boys are then more likely to choose them as sexual partners.</p>
        <p>Instead, researchers should ask what purpose behavior might have served during the period in which it evolved, a time evolutionary psychologists refer to as the Environment of Evolutionary Adaptedness and sometimes pinpoint in the Pleistocene Era, when human ancestors lived in hunter-gatherer groups.</p>
        <p>In the modern world, Dr. Cosmides, Dr. Tooby and others argue,  humans are not ''fitness maximizers,'' continually strategizing to make the most of their chances at reproduction and survival.</p>
        <p>Rather, they are ''adaptation executors,'' carrying out programs written into the mind's machinery long ago. ''The machinery doesn't know its own programming,'' Dr. Cosmides and Dr. Tooby are fond of saying.</p>
        <p>Other scientists, however, object that this view is much too narrow, that it requires assumptions that are impossible to test and ignores the possibility that evolution might in some cases have proceeded at a faster pace.</p>
        <p>They also find the notion of studying only universal traits perplexing: in studies of animal behavior, a standard procedure is to study how traits vary in different environmental circumstances and to explore the effects of different traits on reproduction.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a time machine,'' said Dr. Patricia Adair Gowaty, professor of ecology at the University of Georgia. ''We don't even know for the Pleistocene what the social and environmental conditions were. The only evidence we have for these things is the behavior itself.''</p>
        <p>The work of Dr. Gowaty, who studies birds, Dr. Sarah Blaffer Hrdy, a professor emerita at the University of California at Davis who studies primates, and other researchers, some of whom study humans, offers an evolutionary view of male-female relations that differs sharply from that painted by evolutionary psychologists like Dr. Buss.</p>
        <p>''It really is frustrating to me,'' Dr. Gowaty said, ''when I read these evolutionary psychologists saying that you can't look at selective process in real-time environments, because these novel environments might not be like environments of the past. That might be so. Then again, that might not be so.''</p>
        <p>The Dissent  Saying That Culture Plays a Greater Role</p>
        <p>Other critics complain that evolutionary psychologists often underemphasize the extent to which culture influences human behavior, and ignore equally plausible cultural explanations for their data.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alice Eagly, for example, a social psychologist at Northwestern University, has been critical of Dr. Buss's research showing that women rank wealth and status higher in choosing a sexual partner, while men put a higher priority on physical attractiveness.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't argue that there are no differences between men and women,'' Dr. Eagly said. ''But there remains a big question whether things as specific as a preference for money are built in genetically.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Boyd, of U.C.L.A., also said that culture's impact on behavior was often underplayed in evolutionary psychologists' work.</p>
        <p>While Dr. Tooby, Dr. Cosmides and others have written extensively about the ways in which culture might be shaped by the mental mechanisms humans have evolved, for example, they have spent far less time on the reverse proposition, that culture itself transmits knowledge about how to solve problems from generation to generation.</p>
        <p>''From my research perspective,'' Dr. Boyd said, ''evolutionary psychologists place a much smaller emphasis on cultural variation than I think is empirically going on. I'm inclined to think of cultures as evolving over fairly long periods of time, accumulating information, some of it adaptive, some not adaptive. I still take an evolutionary perspective, but I don't think we have to have it all coded in the genes.''</p>
        <p>For their part, Dr. Cosmides and Dr. Tooby respond that theirs is ''the first intellectual community that does know what to do with culture,'' and that can truly address the way biology and culture interact in creating human societies.</p>
        <p>In fact, Dr. Tooby said, he entered graduate school in anthropology at Harvard in part because ''I was interested in cracking the problem of culture, in what was the underlying mechanism.''</p>
        <p>Yet the word ''mechanism'' is in itself controversial. The notion that the mind is specialized is considered gospel by the ''Santa Barbara Church,'' as one scientist jokingly referred to Dr. Tooby, Dr. Cosmides and their colleagues. But many researchers remain skeptical that the same specialization that has been demonstrated for some brain functions -- vision, for example -- holds when it comes to complex patterns of behavior.</p>
        <p>Dr. Boyd, for example, said: ''I am convinced that we don't understand the brain well enough to make these assumptions. I've read the two sides of this argument, and it seems to me that it's an open question.''</p>
        <p>The Future  A Young Field Still Taking Shape</p>
        <p>Many scientific disciplines are riddled with internal disagreements. Physicists fight about why particles have different masses. Climatologists do battle over global warming.</p>
        <p>Yet the intensity of emotion that infuses any discussion of evolutionary psychology is unusual, even among scientists.</p>
        <p>In part, the reason may be that the star actors in this scientific drama are human beings, and the question at issue is the nature of being human.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tooby says he sometimes worries ''that evolutionary psychology will die because of sociological reasons.''</p>
        <p>''Almost all that anyone has heard about evolutionary psychology has to do with sex and violence,'' he said. ''But there is insight to be found for hundreds of really critical topics.''</p>
        <p>Other evolutionary scientists who study human behavior say they, too, are worried: they worry that the controversy is dividing researchers who should be working together, and that the work of a relatively small group of scholars is inviting a hostility that the field -- just recovering from two decades of embattled debate -- hardly needs.</p>
        <p>The antidote to such fears, many say, is the faith that constructive scientific argument often leads to greater knowledge, and the belief that, for a field still in its infancy, patience is a virtue.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we really know how to do evolutionary psychology yet,'' said Dr. Randolph Nesse, director of the Evolution and Human Adaptation Program at the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan. ''I think we have great trouble formulating our hypotheses, and even more trouble figuring out how to test them. We know we have a powerful principle, that will eventually provide a foundation for a deeper and richer psychology. But we have a lot of work to do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
