<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE NOMINEES; On Economic Affairs, Bush's Man for Commerce Dept. Is His First Pick (and Easiest)</title>
    <meta content="Y20NAM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/20/politics/20NAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Donald L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDE1139F933A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1061" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE NOMINEES; On Economic Affairs, Bush's Man for Commerce Dept. Is His First Pick (and Easiest)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>President-elect George W Bush is expected to name Donald L Evans, his campaign chairman and longtime friend, as secretary of commerce; appointment is first, and perhaps easiest, step for Bush in assembling economic team from swirl of competing candidates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush's decision to name Donald L. Evans, his campaign chairman and longtime friend, as secretary of commerce is his first and perhaps easiest step in assembling an economic team from a swirl of competing candidates who have less binding ties to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The appointment, which Republican officials said would be announced Wednesday, would give Mr. Evans, a 54-year-old oil industry executive, control of 31,000 employees in a sprawling government bureaucracy that is responsible for promoting trade, counting the number of Americans, measuring the economy, and approving patents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush's decision to name Donald L. Evans, his campaign chairman and longtime friend, as secretary of commerce is his first and perhaps easiest step in assembling an economic team from a swirl of competing candidates who have less binding ties to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The appointment, which Republican officials said would be announced Wednesday, would give Mr. Evans, a 54-year-old oil industry executive, control of 31,000 employees in a sprawling government bureaucracy that is responsible for promoting trade, counting the number of Americans, measuring the economy, and approving patents.</p>
        <p>It would also be a prominent prize for Mr. Evans, who raised a record $100 million for Mr. Bush's campaign but whose public policy experience is limited to service on the University of Texas board of regents, a position Mr. Bush named him to after Mr. Evans helped lead previous Bush campaign efforts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans's appointment is expected to be the first major economic appointment by Mr. Bush, who has been reviewing candidates for secretary of the treasury and the United States trade representative along with his White House economic staff for several weeks.</p>
        <p>Paul H. O'Neill, who is retiring this month as chairman of Alcoa, is considered by some Bush supporters to be the leading candidate for the Treasury post. Mr. O'Neill served in the Office of Management and Budget in the Nixon and Ford administrations before turning to the private sector, where he was credited with reviving Alcoa, the aluminum manufacturer.</p>
        <p>People who know Mr. O'Neill described him as an effective public servant and a successful chief executive, a record of achievement in both public and private sectors that appealed especially to Dick Cheney, the vice president-elect who knew Mr. O'Neill from when they both worked for President Gerald R. Ford.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill has advised the last three presidents on public policy issues. He served on commissions set up by President George Bush to study education and social security and discussed environmental policy with President Clinton.</p>
        <p>His comments on environmental issues have not endeared him to conservatives.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill participated in at least two sessions with President Clinton as part of a corporate advisory body convened to discuss global warming, Clinton administration officials said.</p>
        <p>Participants in one 1997 meeting described Mr. O'Neill as more willing to consider steps to tackle global warming than most of his corporate counterparts, but more skeptical about global-warming trends than some Clinton administration officials.</p>
        <p>At a session on global warming held by the American Enterprise Institute, Mr. O'Neill described having had a debate with Jane Fonda, the actress, about whether industrialists could be friends of the environment. He said they could, Mr. O'Neill told participants.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a Clinton economic summit meeting in 1992, Mr. O'Neill strongly favored taxing gasoline as a way of promoting environmentally sustainable economic development.</p>
        <p>''It certainly has been clear to me, and has been for a long time, that we need a gasoline tax,'' he said, a comment that was reprinted in today's issue of The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>The sentiment, which echoed a longstanding proposal by Vice President Al Gore and contradicts Mr. Bush's campaign pledge to reduce taxes and energy costs, has caused rumbles among conservatives.</p>
        <p>''I hope that the comment was just a youthful indiscretion and that he has since renounced that position to Bush,'' said Grover Norquist, president of the conservative think tank Americans for Tax Reform.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. O'Neill is hardly a radical environmentalist. People who know him said his comments about energy and environmental policy could be seen as good public relations for Alcoa, which operates aluminum smelters that are noted polluters and consumers of energy.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether Mr. O'Neill's past comments injure his candidacy for the Treasury job. The other names most often mentioned for the post include Walter V. Shipley, the former chairman of the Chase Manhattan Corporation; John M. Hennessy, the former chairman of Credit Suisse First Boston and Donald B. Marron, the chairman of PaineWebber Group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is also expected in coming days to decide among competing candidates for the job of United States trade representative.</p>
        <p>Some Bush supporters favor Robert B. Zoellick, a former official who has served in the State and Treasury Departments as well as the White House under Presidents Ronald Reagan and Bush. But he is also considered the leading candidate for the head of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>Other candidates include Jennifer B. Dunn, a Republican congresswoman from Washington State; Richard D. Parsons, the president of Time Warner; and Rudy Boschwitz, a former senator of Minnesota.</p>
        <p>As commerce secretary, Mr. Evans would take a job that at least since the Nixon administration has been viewed as a post where trusted allies serve as the president's ambassador to corporate America.</p>
        <p>Now the chief executive and chairman of Tom Brown Inc., an oil company based in Midland, Tex., Mr. Evans, a native of Houston, is by some accounts Mr. Bush's closest ally outside his family. The two were born the same month, July 1946, and have been inseparable since Mr. Evans married a childhood schoolmate of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether Mr. Bush or Mr. Evans sees the Commerce Department job as a substantive part of the administration's economic program. Though it has a role in trade policy, many of its units operate without top-level political guidance.</p>
        <p>In several recent administrations, commerce secretaries have been criticized for appointing loyal political retainers to government posts and using the department as a platform to raise campaign funds.</p>
        <p>House Republicans, furious at what they described as Commerce's political role, voted to close the department in 1996 and assign its duties to other agencies. The Senate did not pass the measure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
