<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DD1138F930A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Another Difficult Week Looms for Weary Israelis  When a hijacked Russian passenger plane landed in Israel, it heightened a prevalent feeling among Israelis that this tense period is bound to be defined by unpredictable and unsettling events. The incident temporarily diverted Prime Minister Ehud Barak, who was en route to Washington for talks with President Clinton. Israel later learned that Yitzhak Rabin's widow, Leah Rabin, had died.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Another Difficult Week Looms for Weary Israelis  When a hijacked Russian passenger plane landed in Israel, it heightened a prevalent feeling among Israelis that this tense period is bound to be defined by unpredictable and unsettling events. The incident temporarily diverted Prime Minister Ehud Barak, who was en route to Washington for talks with President Clinton. Israel later learned that Yitzhak Rabin's widow, Leah Rabin, had died.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak met with President Clinton at the White House for what promised to be a sober accounting of what the two men could achieve -- or prevent -- in the short time the president, and perhaps the prime minister, remain in office.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Leaders of the world's Muslim nations attending the meeting of the Organization of the Islamic Conference bitterly condemned Israel and promised the Palestinians their full political and financial support.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Aftermath of Horrific Fire  The Austrian government declared a state of mourning, and workers began extracting the bodies of about 155 people, including 8 Americans, who perished in Austria's worst Alpine disaster when a cable car was destroyed in a tunnel inferno.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Tommy Suharto Still on the Run  Hutomo Mandala Putra, the youngest son of former President Suharto of Indonesia, has remained free through legal maneuvers and mishaps six weeks after being sentenced to prison on corruption charges. The failure to capture the fugitive, known in Indonesia as Tommy, is raising questions about the government's commitment to establishing a new rule of law.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Plea for Aid After Milosevic  The people of Serbia have suffered prolonged electric shortages and soaring inflation rates since former President Slobodan Milosevic was overthrown in October, and officials say they need $500 million in support to get through the winter.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Investigation of Fujimori Funds  Peru's state prosecutor ordered an investigation after a magazine reported that Pablo Escobar, the slain Colombian drug baron, gave $1 million to President Alberto K. Fujimori's now fugitive intelligence chief, Vladimiro Montesinos, to contribute to Mr. Fujimori's first electoral campaign.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-27</p>
        <p>Battle for the Presidency Continues as Fronts Shift  As lawyers prepared to square off in federal court over Gov. George W. Bush's efforts to block hand recounts of Florida's disputed vote tallies, election officials in at least two counties conducted manual recounts and spokesmen for Mr. Bush and Vice President Al Gore again took to the airwaves in sharp disagreement over how to end the deadlock.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Many prominent Republicans and party operatives are questioning Mr. Bush's strategy in the last days before the election, saying the campaign's top advisers were so confident that they made mistakes that probably cost Mr. Bush a comfortable victory. The biggest complaint is that Bush strategists were so certain that they had locked up many swing states that in the closing days of the campaign they sent the candidate on a victory lap to states he had little chance of winning, like California and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Immediately after the hand recount in four precincts in Palm Beach County, Fla., ended, the Palm Beach County Canvassing Board approved an unprecedented recount of all 462,657 presidential ballots, saying it was the only way to determine the true intent of all the voters.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>In Broward County, Fla., 6,686 voters handed in ballots seemingly without marking a choice for president. The Republicans say they believe the counting machines. The Democrats say a hand recount will prove that it is a matter of poorly set equipment that refilled holes punched by voters. The dispute might be resolved today when county officials plan to inspect a sampling of ballots.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>A full day behind schedule, after tangled legal wrangles, serious deliberations over what color pens to use and squabbles over such grave matters as the passing of notes, human hands finally got to work to manually recount the ballots in Volusia County, Fla.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>DNA Takes On Boston Strangler  Two parallel efforts are under way to determine if the woman known as the infamous killer's youngest and last victim, 19-year-old Mary Sullivan, was in fact killed by the man who long claimed to be the Boston Strangler, Albert DeSalvo. The efforts offer two chances that DNA evidence will finally lay to rest the most terrifying crime mystery ever to strike Boston. For years, some have argued that the strangler, or stranglers, might still be out there.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Residents Sign Up to Block Calls From Telemarketers  New York State residents are flocking to get their names on a registry of people who do not want to receive any unsolicited calls from telemarketing companies, which starting next spring could face stiff fines if they call a home or business that is registered.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Teacher Talks Turn Tense  The contract for New York City's 78,000 public school teachers expires on Wednesday, and labor negotiations have become tense as the city seeks major changes that could reshape its schools, including merit-based raises for teachers, a longer school day and and faster, easier ways to dismiss incompetent teachers. City officials are looking to these negotiations as a rare opportunity to win sweeping changes to improve New York's troubled schools and loosen contract restrictions, like tenure protections, that they view as impediments to better education.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Talks on Global Warming Treaty  After four years of tortuous negotiations, a treaty aimed at curtailing global warming faces its greatest obstacles in the next two weeks as officials from around the world meet work out the fine print. The talks, which begin today in The Hague, come on the heels of new scientific reports showing the strongest evidence yet that the burning of fossil fuels has contributed substantially to a warming trend that could disrupt weather patterns, ecosystems and agriculture.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6-7</p>
        <p>Leah Rabin  Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin's widow, who emerged from his shadow after he was assassinated and became a forceful advocate of his peace policies, was 72.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Jacques Chaban-Delmas  A former French prime minister who tried to embrace social change despite the resistance of his conservative colleagues, he was 85.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-26</p>
        <p>Musicians Join Copyright Fight  The copyright dispute between MP3.com and the Universal Music Group enters its final phase this week, and the Internet music start-up has been joined in a key argument by a group of recording artists led by Don Henley and Sheryl Crow. The group, the Recording Artists Coalition, is trying to avert the possibility that all recording artists would have to file suit against their labels challenging copyright claims that could be validated by the ruling on the case.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>No OPEC Production Decision  The Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries put off until January any decision on changing production levels and named the Venezuelan oil minister, Ali Rodriguez Araque, secretary general.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>EBay Wins Bootleg Case  A judge in California ruled that eBay could not be held liable for bootleg recordings sold on its Web site, a decision that could set the stage for how courts respond to accusations of fraud in online auctions.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>First Chapter for the Crypt  The Metropolitan Museum of Art went rummaging under its Grand Staircase to come up with a new gallery, nicknamed ''the Crypt,'' which opens this week.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: Florida's crucial vote count; the American role in Mideast peace; illegal tobacco traffic.  Columns: William Safire, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E4  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A14  Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D11</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
