<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Chicken, the Egg and the Reign of Gasoline</title>
    <meta content="16FUEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D61E3EF935A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Chicken, the Egg and the Reign of Gasoline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Failure of efforts to get Americans to favor alternative fuels and consume less gasoline, especially imported gasoline, discussed in light of recent sharp price increases at the pump; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE upon a time, just after the Persian Gulf war and the oil-price spike  it caused, the government came up with yet another plan to reduce American dependence on imported oil.</p>
        <p>The big idea was to promote alternative fuels for vehicles. The plan Congress passed in 1992 was intended, by the far-off year of 2000, to replace 10 percent of the gasoline and diesel fuel used by cars, pickups, vans and sport utility vehicles with something not made from oil. By 2010, it was supposed to replace 30 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE upon a time, just after the Persian Gulf war and the oil-price spike  it caused, the government came up with yet another plan to reduce American dependence on imported oil.</p>
        <p>The big idea was to promote alternative fuels for vehicles. The plan Congress passed in 1992 was intended, by the far-off year of 2000, to replace 10 percent of the gasoline and diesel fuel used by cars, pickups, vans and sport utility vehicles with something not made from oil. By 2010, it was supposed to replace 30 percent.</p>
        <p>So far, it has been a fairy tale. There are indeed about one million cars and light trucks on the road equipped to run on natural gas, ethanol, methanol, propane or some other substitute, but hardly any of them ever do. The country has made only about an eyedropper-full of progress for each gallon of gasoline or diesel burned.</p>
        <p>Many advocates of alternative fuel blame the car companies. Car companies blame the Energy Department. The Energy Department blames Congress. And everybody, by and large, still uses gasoline.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Energy Department say they have tried hard to make the 1992 program work, but that they were hobbled from the start by weaknesses in the plan, contained in the Energy Policy Act. ''It's like going after a grizzly bear with a fly swatter,'' said one Energy Department official, who asked not to be further identified.</p>
        <p>Nobody ever thought it would be easy. The authors of the plan recognized the obvious, that no one would buy a nongasoline car  until its fuel was available at filling stations all over the country, and that no one would build the filling stations until there were cars to use the fuel. They tried to solve the chicken-and-egg problem by tapping the buying power of large public and private vehicle fleets.</p>
        <p>The law, passed by a Democratic Congress and signed by President George Bush, required two categories of fleet owners --  the federal and state governments, and companies that sell electricity and natural gas -- to include a certain share of alternative-fuel vehicles among their new purchases. The figure for the federal government this year is 75 percent.</p>
        <p>But the law contained a crucial compromise. It called for vehicles that could use alternative fuels, not those that must use them, to spare fleet owners any danger of being held hostage by fuel suppliers.</p>
        <p>Today, some 30 light-duty vehicle models -- sedans, station wagons, mini-vans, pickups and sport utility vehicles -- are built to run solely on some alternative fuel, usually natural gas or propane. But ''sales are still stuck in the basement,'' said the Energy Department official, accounting for fewer than 1 of every 1,000 light vehicles sold.</p>
        <p>A second, more successful provision called for stretching gasoline supplies by adding filler chemicals to ordinary gasoline, like Hamburger Helper to ground beef. But the most popular, known as M.T.B.E., proved to be a threat to groundwater supplies, and the Clinton administration now wants to ban it.</p>
        <p>Other parts of the law worked better; for example, energy use per square foot in federal buildings has been cut by more than 20 percent. But that saves coal and natural gas, not gasoline. The effort to diversify transportation fuel has had some success in heavy vehicles like trucks and buses, but not in the light vehicles that use most of the fuel.</p>
        <p>One giant hurdle is retail availability. Of the 145,000 gas stations in the United States, only about 50 sell fuel that is more than 10 percent ethanol. None are in Washington, so parked in the garage beneath the Energy Department headquarters are three ethanol-ready cars that have never seen any fuel but unleaded regular. (The federal government is helping to open an ethanol pump at a station near the Pentagon in Arlington, Va.)</p>
        <p>About 1,300 places have compressed natural gas, but most are bus depots, United Parcel Service hubs or the like. Only a few dozen are ordinary service stations. That creates a special problem, because natural-gas vehicles typically go only about half as far on a tankful as gasoline vehicles do.</p>
        <p>Some fuel companies tried to help; in the early 1990's, Amoco added natural gas at 37 of its service stations, at a cost of more than $250,000 apiece. But sales were so slow -- the equivalent of 20 gallons of gasoline a day  -- that the company gave up.</p>
        <p>THE authors of the Energy Policy Act hoped that fleets would get the ball rolling, and that high gasoline prices would lead to demand for alternative fuels. But they were wrong, partly because for years the price of gasoline did not cooperate. Natural gas and ethanol are roughly competitive with what gasoline was selling for last year, and are notably cheaper than gasoline today. But expectations are paramount, and most car shoppers today do not believe that gas will remain expensive for very long.</p>
        <p>''The increased use of alternative fuels very much depends on the price of gasoline,'' said Dan W. Reicher, assistant secretary of energy for efficiency and renewable energy. ''At least today, ethanol is a very competitive fuel.'' With a tax subsidy already in place, he added, suppliers ''can make money at a price point somewhat below the current price of gasoline.''</p>
        <p>Except perhaps for electric cars, the technology needed for the vehicles is mostly in place. ''We've proven they work,'' said Bill Webster, director of fleet management at the General Services Administration, which buys much of the government's car fleet, including 27,000 alternative-fuel vehicles. ''The problem is, you have to have an infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>Another problem is that Congress gave the Energy Department authority to require local governments and big corporations to buy alternative-fuel vehicles too, but the department has not done so.</p>
        <p>''It was optional,'' said Lisa Cutler, a spokeswoman for the department. ''We only had to do it if it was critical to meet Epact goals,'' she added, using a shorthand name for the law.</p>
        <p>And builders of alternative-fuel vehicles say one reason so few are on the road is that many government agencies that are required to buy them simply do not.</p>
        <p>''It's really a challenge,'' said Art Garner, a spokesman for Honda, who said his company had spent millions of dollars to develop a natural-gas-powered Civic that California says is the cleanest internal combustion car made. ''The letter of the law is not pursued very stringently,'' he said. ''Nobody's complied with it.'' And Ford Motor, which makes the most natural-gas-powered cars, said sales were nowhere near what they would be if everyone were complying. Mr. Reicher said that the shortfall was only about 500 cars and that the Energy Department had written letters to noncompliers.</p>
        <p>As for the public at large, voluntarily buying an alternative-fuel car hardly makes sense on economic grounds. Natural gas has been selling for the equivalent of 75 cents or so a gallon, according to Gilbert P. Sperling of the Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition -- attractive today but less so when gasoline goes for $1 or $1.10. For a typical household car or van, he said, ''you're paying $5,000 more for a vehicle that uses only 500 gallons a year.'' For buses that use thousands of gallons a year, he said, switching is a ''no brainer,'' but for light-duty vehicles, ''we're not seeing much activity.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
