<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Watching The River Freeze Is Half the Fun</title>
    <meta content="23ICE.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1170672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Housatonic River (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kent (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monagan, Jamie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Litchfield County</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D8143DF930A15752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Watching The River Freeze Is Half the Fun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE MONAGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Monagan, Jamie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on declining interest in wagers over when ice on stretch of Housatonic River will break up, 22-year tradition whose proceeds have been split with Kent Volunteer Fire Department; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HELL may freeze over before the Housatonic River does, but the Kent Volunteer Fire Department keeps hoping.</p>
        <p>Despite its location in the supposed ''ice box of Connecticut,'' a paucity of below-freezing days has slowed the Kent Volunteer Fire Department's 22-year-old tradition of taking $2 wagers on when the ice on this stretch of the Housatonic will break up. But until this past week, Kent has not been seeing much ice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HELL may freeze over before the Housatonic River does, but the Kent Volunteer Fire Department keeps hoping.</p>
        <p>Despite its location in the supposed ''ice box of Connecticut,'' a paucity of below-freezing days has slowed the Kent Volunteer Fire Department's 22-year-old tradition of taking $2 wagers on when the ice on this stretch of the Housatonic will break up. But until this past week, Kent has not been seeing much ice.</p>
        <p>Several years of balmy temperatures have put a crimp in the fire company's coffers here in the ''Home of the Famous Ice Watch,'' as proclaims a sign along Route 7 on the western bank of the Housatonic south of Kent village.</p>
        <p>The idea for Kent's ice watch was initially suggested by the late John Greene, a newspaperman and town resident who, according to former Kent Fire Chief Art Seabury, had seen ''some fellows make a brush pile on a river in Alaska, and make book --  a quarter here, a quarter there -- on when the pile would move downstream.''</p>
        <p>In keeping with the tone of this handsome Litchfield County town, Kent has civilized its ice watch a bit. For a $2 ice guess, bettors write their prediction to the day and minute for when a timing device set out on the frozen river just above the Bulls Bridge Dam will begin drifting downstream.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seabury, a vigorous 87-year-old who works full time managing the Kent Water Pollution Control Facility, handles the mechanics of the watch. A brightly painted tripod bolted to a log raft and rigged to a battery-operated clock onshore is set out midstream on the frozen river. Mr. Seabury hauls the raft and tripod onto the river with one helper and no safety gear, relying on judgment gained through a long life lived within sight of the Housatonic.</p>
        <p>''When I feel like walking out there, it goes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Gene Fiengo, a retired volunteer fire fighter who sold the first winning ticket back in 1978, remembers helping Mr. Seabury one winter around 1980.</p>
        <p>''Art and I are out there, I'm near the Route 7 side and Art says 'Don't come back too far,' Mr. Fiengo said. ''I turn around and there's open water there for cripes sake. I said 'Maybe you can walk on water, but I can't.  No more of this stuff for me.' ''</p>
        <p>Tom Ashmore of Ashmore Enterprises, a Brookfield company specializing in training fire and rescue squads in tactical rescues, said each time a person ventures out onto ice on a river, ''it's a dangerous situation.''</p>
        <p>''There's no rule of thumb for ice safety,'' Mr. Ashmore said. ''especially on a river where the water is always moving.''</p>
        <p>The clock is turned on at 12:01 a.m. on Feb. 19, after which no more bets can be wagered. As rising temperatures and fluctuating currents do their work, the tripod is set adrift. At that point, a 75-foot wire connected to the tripod unspools from within a birdhouse-like structure hanging from a cable strung over the river.</p>
        <p>When the wire fully unwinds, it trips a switch, turning off the clock that sits in a small shed about 50 yards off the river bank. The prognosticator whose guess comes closest to the time the clock strikes ''thaw'' splits the proceeds with the fire department.</p>
        <p>A second clock is attached to the rig by a different mechanism for a back-up. ''They might vary a bit so the rule is we go by the first clock to turn off,'' Mr. Seabury said. ''People will argue minutes over this, and enjoy the arguing point, too.''</p>
        <p>''It's a real neat part of the town spirit, a fun way to kick away the winter doldrums,'' said Cathe Mazza, the Kent Volunteer Fire Department's secretary and dean of students at the Kent School, a preparatory school near the town's center. ''I live right next to the river and hear it creak and moan and groan when it's building up ice and then the other way around when it breaks up.''</p>
        <p>But the Housatonic is barely whimpering again this year. If the river isn't frozen on Feb. 19, which has happened four times since 1978, the ice watch turns into a more ordinary raffle drawing.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to sell the ice watch when there's no ice,'' says Bill Tobin, a fire department member and former Kent first selectman. ''If we get a good snow and freeze we'll have ice. But how long it will last with the weather being like it's been all this past winter is kind of doubtful.''</p>
        <p>Bill Kilpatrick is a hydrometeorologist at the National Weather Service Office in Albany. The office provides forecasts for Litchfield County and he doesn't see the recent warm winters as part of an environmental trend, but as aberrations within a norm.</p>
        <p>''I don't buy the global warming theory because there are other places that have stayed very cold,'' he said. ''The way the upper air patterns have persisted for the last several winters just gave us more warm air than usual.''</p>
        <p>The ice watch was canceled altogether in 1998 and 1999 because no fire company member volunteered to organize it, which Mr. Tobin sees as part of another kind of pattern.</p>
        <p>''A lot of volunteer departments, and I'm sad to say, Kent included, are beginning to be subsidized by the local government, because of regulations handed down by the state,'' Mr. Tobin said. ''It takes away the pride and personal interest that the old time fireman had in being self-supporting. Instead of depending on the ice watch and Fireman's Fair to buy equipment, they just say to the town fathers, 'Hey, we need money.' The charm has kind of gone.''</p>
        <p>''We used to have some pretty nice pots,'' Mr. Tobin recalled, explaining that a high pot of $3,650 in 1988 was countered by a low of $662 in 1996, a year when lack of ice required a raffle.</p>
        <p>Those sums are a drop in the bucket compared to the $750,000 department members now need to overhaul a new firehouse purchased on Jan. 7. Only $17,000 has been raised for renovations on the 36,000-square-foot site, which used to be the Kent Manufacturing Building.</p>
        <p>Warmer winters haven't cooled interest in Canada's Ice Guessing Contest in Dawson City. This Yukon Territory town of 2,100 perched at the confluence of the Yukon and Klondike Rivers, 100 miles due east of Chicken, Alaska, has held a contest every year since 1896.</p>
        <p>''When I came out here in 1956 we used to have about six weeks of temperatures around 40 to 60 below zero,'' said Joyce Caley, who organizes the Dawson contest for a Canadian women's charitable group, formerly called the Imperial Order of the Daughters of the Empire, now known simple as IODE. ''The last several years we still get cold spells, but they don't seem to last as long, probably two weeks at the longest.''</p>
        <p>The Dawson fund-raiser parallels Kent's, with a few notable exceptions. The wire atop their tripod is festooned with surveyor's tags to warn ski planes that might want to land on the frozen Yukon River. The marker is set out in mid-March, in advance of an ice floe that finally occurred last year on May 8, well after Connecticut fly-fishers have waded midstream into the Housatonic.</p>
        <p>Given the vagaries of weather, Kent's fire company might take a pointer from neighboring Cornwall's weatherproof Cow Pie Contest. Nancy, a well-fed Holstein, is let to graze on a field adjoining that town's library during the annual Fourth of July festivities. Hundreds of gamblers clutching their $5 tickets ring the field premarked with 500 squares, willing Nancy to heed nature's call on their particular piece of turf.</p>
        <p>The lucky winner splits the proceeds with Cornwall's fire department, and even takes home the plastic-bagged deposit to throw on the compost pile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
