<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. IS PROPOSING NEW WAY TO FIGHT GLOBAL WARMING</title>
    <meta content="02WARM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6D71E3DF931A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. IS PROPOSING NEW WAY TO FIGHT GLOBAL WARMING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States is proposing that efforts to cut levels of heat-trapping gases that may be warming climate give as much credit to countries that use forests and farmers' fields to sop up carbon dioxide, chief greenhouse gas, as for cutting emissions; State Department outlines approach in document filed with United Nations office overseeing talks aimed at carrying out 1997 international accord on averting global warming; Clinton administration officials and some scientists say incentives to plant trees and to farm in ways that lock away carbon are key to stabilizing climate and winning Senate support for any climate treaty; some environmental groups score approach, citing uncertainties about how long plants and soils can continue to absorb carbon; proposal is at odds with European Union stance; 38 other industrialized nations are also set to file proposals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preparing for renewed international negotiations on cutting levels of heat-trapping gases that may be warming the climate, the United States is proposing that countries get just as much credit for using forests and farmers' fields to sop up carbon dioxide, the chief warming gas, as they would for cutting emissions from smokestacks and tail pipes.</p>
        <p>Scientists have known for decades that trees and other plants absorb carbon dioxide as they grow and some soils do as well. In theory, pulling carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere would allow countries to emit some heat-trapping, or greenhouse, gases without adding to the overall problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preparing for renewed international negotiations on cutting levels of heat-trapping gases that may be warming the climate, the United States is proposing that countries get just as much credit for using forests and farmers' fields to sop up carbon dioxide, the chief warming gas, as they would for cutting emissions from smokestacks and tail pipes.</p>
        <p>Scientists have known for decades that trees and other plants absorb carbon dioxide as they grow and some soils do as well. In theory, pulling carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere would allow countries to emit some heat-trapping, or greenhouse, gases without adding to the overall problem.</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials and some scientists said last night that incentives to plant trees and to farm in ways that lock away carbon were essential for stabilizing the climate. In addition, they said, bringing farmers and foresters into the battle is likely to be crucial if the Senate, which has so far firmly opposed ratifying any international climate treaty, is to change its view.</p>
        <p>But the position is being criticized by some private environmental groups, which have pressed to cut the burning of coal and oil, which  caused most of the carbon dioxide buildup in the first place. They point to uncertainties about how long plants and soils could continue to absorb carbon.</p>
        <p>And the proposal is at odds with the stance of the European Union which, given its relative lack of open land for tree-planting, would be at a disadvantage.</p>
        <p>The State Department laid out the United States' approach in documents filed last night with a United Nations office that is overseeing talks aimed at carrying out the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement aimed at averting any dangerous climate warming. Thirty-eight other industrialized countries were scheduled to file their proposals last night, as well.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto agreement has been signed by the United States and more than 100 other countries but has not yet been ratified, and many details remain to be ironed out, with two rounds of negotiations coming in September and again in November.</p>
        <p>If the agreement is ratified, the United States would commit itself to cutting its emissions of carbon dioxide by 2010 to 7 percent below the emissions in 1990. Given the growth in the economy and fuel use since 1990, administration officials say, the only way to come anywhere near that target is by adopting every possible strategy, including the agricultural approach.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore was deeply involved in crafting the Kyoto treaty and any deadlock in talks would be a blow to him. On the other hand, although Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has said he believes global warming is a significant problem, he opposes ratification of the Kyoto Protocol, saying it would unfairly burden the United States.</p>
        <p>White House officials said Mr. Gore was being apprised of the proposed strategy.</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, chief scientist of Environmental Defense, a private group, said that whatever program finally emerges in the next rounds of talks, it must not allow any country to get too much credit for things it is already doing, like, for example, planting trees on land that was clearcut several years ago.</p>
        <p>''Done well, credit for forests and farming could help jumpstart a solution to the global warming problem,'' Dr. Oppenheimer said. ''Done poorly, it could undermine the credibility of the whole Kyoto agreement.''</p>
        <p>David B. Sandalow, the assistant secretary of state for oceans and environmental affairs, said the United States would not want any final climate plan to permit loopholes allowing clearcutting or other bad land practices to get credit.</p>
        <p>But, taking a position at odds with some environmental groups, he added that the country's position would be to try to get credit for most of the carbon dioxide being absorbed by the country's trees and crops -- about 300 million metric tons a year is the projection for that tally by 2010.</p>
        <p>That compares to the projected total emissions of more than 2.1 billion metric tons of carbon dioxide a year from industry, cars and other sources if current energy trends continue, he said.</p>
        <p>He added that keeping some focus on farming and trees would keep the cost of fighting global warming down. Estimates are that it will be much cheaper for a country to absorb pollution than to reduce the output of these gases.</p>
        <p>''We need strong incentives for parties to adopt practices that protect the atmosphere at low cost,'' Mr. Sandalow said last night.</p>
        <p>Canada, Russia, Australia and other countries with lots of forests and farming are all tending to align with the American position. Also, according to several Japanese news services, Japan last night submitted similar plans, anticipating a large role for tree planting. Its focus is probably not so much on current events but on an anticipated round of talks extending actions on global warming to the third world, where Japan and other rich countries could get credit for investing in forest projects.</p>
        <p>Some private environmental groups are vigorously opposing this approach.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Morgan, the director of the climate change campaign at the World Wildlife Fund, an international group, said that forests and soils are, at best, a temporary storehouse for carbon, and one that can be broken open by later changes in practices or by unforseen forces like wildfire, droughts, or insect infestations -- all of which could abruptly unlock millions of tons of banked carbon.</p>
        <p>''Soil can be a great absorber of carbon, but if you plow too deeply two years in a row you can release it all back into the air,'' she said. ''We need to find the most secure way of reaching these goals, and that is to focus on cutting emissions from things like power plants.''</p>
        <p>Last night, a White House official said that some environmental groups -- historically focused on cleaning pollution -- were being too inflexible on the issue. ''Carbon is carbon, right?'' said the official.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
