<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y23BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/23/world/23BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DE133AF930A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Kirk Kraeutler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>SPAIN: FIRST MAD COW CASE  The first case of mad cow disease has been reported in Spain and a second case is under investigation. Government officials said both cows came from the northwest Galicia region. Spanish authorities said they had quarantined the farms where the cows lived and other farms that might have had contact with the animals. The government said all animals that had contact with the cows would be destroyed and tested.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: TROOPS FOR CENTRAL ASIA  The Russian military will dispatch 50,000 troops to form rapid-deployment divisions in Southwest and Central Asia by 2003. The plans include mobilizing defense industries and transport lines to meet threats stemming from the conflict in Chechnya, drug trafficking, Islamic extremism and NATO's expanding military ties on Russia's southern flank, a spokesman for the general staff told the Interfax news agency.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>SPAIN: FIRST MAD COW CASE  The first case of mad cow disease has been reported in Spain and a second case is under investigation. Government officials said both cows came from the northwest Galicia region. Spanish authorities said they had quarantined the farms where the cows lived and other farms that might have had contact with the animals. The government said all animals that had contact with the cows would be destroyed and tested.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: TROOPS FOR CENTRAL ASIA  The Russian military will dispatch 50,000 troops to form rapid-deployment divisions in Southwest and Central Asia by 2003. The plans include mobilizing defense industries and transport lines to meet threats stemming from the conflict in Chechnya, drug trafficking, Islamic extremism and NATO's expanding military ties on Russia's southern flank, a spokesman for the general staff told the Interfax news agency.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: JUDGE STAYS IN SPY TRIAL  Lawyers for the former American naval intelligence officer Edmond Pope failed to win the dismissal of the judge presiding over his espionage trial. The motion followed earlier defense requests to remove the chief prosecutor because his son was a member of the Russian security service team that brought the case. The judge also refused to disqualify contested testimony alleging that Mr. Pope had sought to purchase classified plans for a high-speed torpedo system.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: MORE LAND COMPENSATION DENIED  The Federal Constitutional Court rejected demands for more than $10 billion in further compensation for people whose property had been seized in eastern Germany by the Communists between 1945 and 1949.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: NEW TIES WITH BOSNIA  Yugoslavia and Bosnia said they would establish diplomatic relations in coming weeks, ending nearly a decade of hostility between the two neighbors. Goran Svilanovic, the new Yugoslav foreign minister, made the statement during an official visit to the Bosnian capital, Sarajevo. ''It is time to start producing another kind of history: the history of good neighborly relations,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Carlotta Gall (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>SAUDI ARABIA: ANOTHER ATTACK ON BRITONS  An explosion hit a car carrying three British citizens in Riyadh, injuring two men and one woman, the second such incident involving Britons in one week. Officials said an investigation has started to determine whether the bombing was related to a blast that killed a British man and slightly injured his wife last Friday.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ETHIOPIA: MONEY NEEDED FOR AIDS  Sub-Saharan Africa will need between $2 billion and $10 billion a year in aid to deal with more than 23 million people infected with H.I.V., a United Nations report says. Noting that half the people in the world with AIDS live in Africa, the report called the level of official assistance ''woefully inadequate,'' particularly as the disease is estimated to shave as much as two percent a year off the region's gross domestic product.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>IVORY COAST: RULING ON OUATTARA  The National Election Commission cleared a leading opposition politician, Alassane Ouattara, to run in parliamentary elections on Dec. 10. Saying he had failed to meet strict nationality criteria, a court controlled by the former military ruler had barred Mr. Ouattara from running in presidential elections last month. His exclusion fueled a boycott of the presidential vote and a political crisis after the results were contested.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS</p>
        <p>GRANT TO FIGHT IODINE DEFICIENCY  The U.S. Fund for Unicef, an American support group for the United Nations' Children's Fund, has been given a $15 million grant from the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation for a joint Unicef-Kiwanis International campaign to eliminate iodine deficiency affecting more than 1.5 million people, more than a third of them children. Iodine deficiency is the leading preventable cause of mental retardation.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>BRAZIL: MORE BORDER TROOPS  Brazil announced deployment of a special task force for the Bolivian border in an effort to shut routes to drug trafficking and contraband smuggling. It said 800 troops were being assigned to the remote frontier in a joint military and police operation. The move follows creation of a similar force on the Colombian border.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: ESTRADA FIGHTS IMPEACHMENT  Lawyers defending President Joseph Estrada from impeachment charges are likely to file a motion this week to dismiss the proceeding, on the ground that the full House of Representatives did not vote on the complaint, a presidential aide said. The Senate is expected to begin Mr. Estrada's trial, the first for a Philippine leader, early next month over allegations that he received millions of dollars in illegal gambling profits and tobacco tax kickbacks.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>EVEREST: FEELS WARMING TREND  Global warming is helping shrink Mount Everest, the world's highest peak, according to researchers at China's State Bureau of Surveying and Mapping. The researchers found that the thickness of the snow cap atop the 29,205-foot peak had decreased as temperatures in the Himalayas had increased more than the global average since 1950, the New China News Agency reported. It did not say how much snow had been lost.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
