<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="16DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D61138F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Disappointing Oracle Sales Pummel Technology Sector  Stocks closed sharply lower as disappointing sales from the software maker Oracle led to a technology sell-off while surging oil prices pummeled blue chips. Blue-chip stocks declined on lingering worries that corporate profits will lag because of high energy costs and a weaker euro, the faltering single European currency. But energy stocks, led by Exxon Mobil, rose as oil prices bolted to their highest level since the 1990-91 Persian Gulf crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Disappointing Oracle Sales Pummel Technology Sector  Stocks closed sharply lower as disappointing sales from the software maker Oracle led to a technology sell-off while surging oil prices pummeled blue chips. Blue-chip stocks declined on lingering worries that corporate profits will lag because of high energy costs and a weaker euro, the faltering single European currency. But energy stocks, led by Exxon Mobil, rose as oil prices bolted to their highest level since the 1990-91 Persian Gulf crisis.</p>
        <p>Shares of Oracle fell $6.63, to $78.31, and the Nasdaq composite index declined 78.63 points, or 2 percent, to 3,835.23. The Dow Jones industrial average was down 160.41 points, or 1.5 percent, to 10,927.06. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index was down 15.06 points, or 1 percent, to 1,465.81. [Page C3.]</p>
        <p>Consumer Price Index Fell in August  For the first time in more than 14 years, it cost American consumers a bit less last month to fill their market baskets with goods and services than it did the month before. The Consumer Price Index for August inched down 0.1 percent as the cost of energy skidded 2.9 percent. Gasoline itself dropped 6 percent, but has rebounded this month. In a separate report, the Federal Reserve said that the output of the nation's factories, mines and utilities climbed 0.3 percent last month. [C14.]</p>
        <p>OPEC Seeks Compensation  At the latest round of international talks aimed at shaping a treaty on global warming, delegates from the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries insisted that any accord include a commitment to compensate them if efforts to cut emissions of heat-trapping gases resulted in a drop in the use of oil. [A4.]</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Settles Bias Suit  Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company has settled litigation with a former analyst whose complaints about his firing led to an investigation by the Manhattan district attorney and a public apology from the firm. Christian Curry, a black man who was fired in 1998 after he posed nude in a magazine for gay men, said he had agreed to drop a discrimination lawsuit. In exchange, Morgan Stanley dropped a countersuit against Mr. Curry. [C14.]</p>
        <p>New Media Powerhouse in Canada  The Thomson Corporation, the owner of The Globe and Mail, Canada's leading national newspaper; BCE Inc.; and the Sympatico-Lycos Internet service have announced a $2.7 billion joint venture. BCE will own 70.1 percent of the new company, yet to be named, while Thomson will own 20 percent and the private holding company of Kenneth Thomson, the chairman of Thomson, will put up $275 million for a 9.9 percent stake. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Tennessee Investigating Tire Sales  The Tennessee attorney general is investigating reports that some used tire dealers are selling tires that Firestone has recalled. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Dime Bancorp to Reduce Expenses  Dime Bancorp is planning to cut more than 400 jobs, or about 6 percent of its work force, as part of a series of moves to trim costs. Dime hopes the moves will reduce its annual expenses by $50 million. The cuts come as it is resisting a hostile takeover bid by North Fork Bancorp. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Brewery Joins New York Exchange  American depository receipts of Latin America's leading brewery, Companhia de Bebidas das Americas of Brazil, rose 3.3 percent, to $21.6875, in their debut on the New York Stock Exchange, where company officials generated some publicity by ringing the closing bell with the Brazilian model, Gisele Bundchen, and distributing 6,000 cans of the brewery's Guarana Antarctica tropical soft drink to passers-by outside on Wall Street. Ambev, as the company is known, is the world's fourth-largest beer company. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
