<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Weather Follows Global Warming Trend</title>
    <meta content="Y20WAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/20/science/20WARM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D91039F933A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Weather Follows Global Warming Trend</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Dec. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Overall temperatures in United States continue to run well above average of past century, fitting in with warming trend of past decade; National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration reports that average US temperature in 2000, excluding Hawaii and Alaska, is projected to be about 54.1 degrees, compared with average of 52.8 degrees over previous 106 years; that would make 2000 somewhere between 7th and 12th warmest year on record; worldwide, termperatures are expected to be about 5th warmest on record, and all 10 of warmest years globally have occurred since 1982; chart of US temperatures since 1895 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite a chilly end of the year, temperatures in the United States over all continue to run well above the average of the past century, fitting in with the warming trend of the past decade.</p>
        <p>The average temperature in the United States in 2000, excluding Hawaii and Alaska, is projected to be about 54.1 degrees, compared with an average of 52.8 degrees over the previous 106 years, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration reported. That would make this year somewhere between the 7th and 12th warmest year on record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite a chilly end of the year, temperatures in the United States over all continue to run well above the average of the past century, fitting in with the warming trend of the past decade.</p>
        <p>The average temperature in the United States in 2000, excluding Hawaii and Alaska, is projected to be about 54.1 degrees, compared with an average of 52.8 degrees over the previous 106 years, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration reported. That would make this year somewhere between the 7th and 12th warmest year on record.</p>
        <p>''Certainly a warm year, but not as warm as it looked like through October,'' said Thomas R. Karl, director of the National Climatic Data Center at a news conference today at the American Geophysical Union meeting.</p>
        <p>In the first 10 months of the year, temperatures looked as if they would break the 1998 record of 54.94 degrees. ''But then November came,'' Dr. Karl said.</p>
        <p>Last month was the second coldest November on record in the United States. ''I think this goes to illustrate that even in a warming trend,'' Dr. Karl said, ''one can and should expect an individual month with some very anomalously cold weather.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the cold November, he said, the year included the coolest July on record in Pennsylvania and West Virginia, above-average rainfall in the summer in the Northeast and Midwest and a severe drought in the South.</p>
        <p>Worldwide, temperatures are expected to be about fifth warmest on record, and all 10 of the warmest years globally have occurred since 1982. Temperatures have fallen since the record high average in 1998 in part because the El Nino phenomenon, a warmer-than-normal pool of water in the eastern Pacific Ocean, has faded into the opposite La Nina condition with cooler-than-normal waters. Averaged over the longer term, temperatures have been rising at a rate of about 3 degrees per century.</p>
        <p>Effects of the warmer temperatures have been detected worldwide -- including the melting of Arctic permafrost and sea ice, increased rainfall in the midlatitude regions and warming of the deep oceans -- and scientists are increasingly convinced that emissions of so-called greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide by factories and cars are at least partly to blame.</p>
        <p>Of the natural factors influencing climate, the energy output of the sun has increased, which would tend to lift temperatures, but a larger effect in recent years has been volcanic activity, which spews out gases that change into droplets in the upper atmosphere that reflect sunlight back into space.</p>
        <p>Some computer models predict that without greenhouse gases, global average temperatures would have fallen in the second half of the century. Current temperatures are also well above global temperatures dating back 1,000 years that have been inferred from the thickness of tree rings and other indirect measures.</p>
        <p>''We can say with a fair amount of confidence, this is a very unusual, if not unique, warming,'' said Dr. Thomas J. Crowley, a professor of oceanography at Texas A &amp; M University. ''If it looks like a duck, walks like a duck, quacks like a duck, do you say there is a 95 percent chance it's a duck or do you say it's a duck? This is something that is 95 percent duck.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
