<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reality Took Over But Seemed So Unreal</title>
    <meta content="31JAME$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/31/arts/31JAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO: THE YEAR IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED71338F932A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reality Took Over But Seemed So Unreal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James assesses year in television; cites dominance of politics, reality program and game shows; photos (M)m</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 2000 reality meant game shows, and politics merged with entertainment. Politics dominates this list of the year's most significant television events, but the medium's definition of political became fuzzier than ever.</p>
        <p>BUSH WINS (THIS TIME THEY MEAN IT) -- For an event of flabbergasting incompetence and importance, it's impossible to beat the mistaken projections in the 2000 presidential election, television's longest night. By the time dawn approached, the sleep-deprived anchors on the networks and cable channels had made and retracted three calls (Gore wins Florida, Bush wins Florida, Bush wins the country). When Al Gore heard the news reports that he had lost the presidency, he quickly phoned George W. Bush to concede, then took it back. Why would he have thought there was anything more reliable than television news?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 2000 reality meant game shows, and politics merged with entertainment. Politics dominates this list of the year's most significant television events, but the medium's definition of political became fuzzier than ever.</p>
        <p>BUSH WINS (THIS TIME THEY MEAN IT) -- For an event of flabbergasting incompetence and importance, it's impossible to beat the mistaken projections in the 2000 presidential election, television's longest night. By the time dawn approached, the sleep-deprived anchors on the networks and cable channels had made and retracted three calls (Gore wins Florida, Bush wins Florida, Bush wins the country). When Al Gore heard the news reports that he had lost the presidency, he quickly phoned George W. Bush to concede, then took it back. Why would he have thought there was anything more reliable than television news?</p>
        <p>Television made up for its mistakes by taking the country on an exciting, dizzyingly unpredictable journey into a land of hanging chads and see-saw legal battles. Viewers watched history happen before their eyes, or in the case of the archaically camera-shy Supreme Court, before their ears.</p>
        <p>A minor revelation to emerge from election night: about 3 in the morning, Dan Rather-isms (''If a frog had sidepockets he'd carry a gun'') actually begin to make sense.</p>
        <p>'SATURDAY NIGHT LIVE' AND OTHER POLITICAL POWERS -- On ''SNL,'' Darrell Hammond's scathingly funny impression of Al Gore (the tilted head, the slight drawl, the word ''lockbox'') was matched by Will Ferrell's equally brilliant impression of a dazed and confused George W. Bush, snickering his way toward the presidency. After the show parodied the first Gore-Bush debate, Mr. Gore's advisers made him watch the sketch as a cautionary move.</p>
        <p>On late-night shows, Jay Leno, David Letterman, Jon Stewart and Conan O'Brien shaped the politicians' images more dramatically than the news reporters. And as the candidates made the rounds of talk shows, no theater of the absurd could top the sight of Mr. Bush talking to Susan Hawk, the truck driver from ''Survivor,'' on ''Live with Regis.''</p>
        <p>'SURVIVOR'-MANIA -- It seems so long ago, and faintly embarrassing, but we were so innocent then. For months last summer the nation was obsessed with a group of people CBS had dropped onto an island, as they faced team challenges and kitschy ''tribal councils'' in a game to win a million dollars. How could we not have seen that the scheming Richard Hatch (a.k.a. the ''naked fat guy'') would survive? Not even Rudy Boesch, the crankily lovable ex-Navy Seal, could beat him.</p>
        <p>Here's a reality check: contrary to myth, Richard never ate a rat. The rat-eating came in the show's early weeks, when the contestants were still divided into two teams. The other team ate rats. Maybe that's the secret of winning. We'll all be more jaded when ''Survivor II'' arrives on Jan. 28, after the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>'THE WEST WING' UNITES THE COUNTRY -- Even before the fractured results of this election, NBC was promoting Martin Sheen's ''West Wing'' character, Josiah Bartlet, as ''the president we can all agree on.'' Aaron Sorkin's smart, detailed look at the frenzied, fascinating lives of White House staffers was the year's only television drama that viewers compulsively talked about and taped. The first season ended in May with a cliffhanger about an assassination attempt, returned in the fall with a delicious, witty episode that flashed back to the characters' previous careers, and hasn't slowed down yet.</p>
        <p>DAVID LETTERMAN'S BIG COMEBACK -- You know how you can take people for granted until you almost lose them? That's the way the audience responded to David Letterman's sudden heart surgery last January, an event that landed on tabloid front pages and the network news. After a few weeks, he made an energized return: newly touching, still irreverent and funnier than ever. An account of cutting his finger in the kitchen became an epic, hilarious adventure as he told it; eventually, he had the stitches removed on camera. And he was more relentless than many political reporters in questioning George W. Bush about the death penalty and Al Gore about global warming.</p>
        <p>QUICK CANCELLATIONS: TWO STRIKES, YOU'RE OUT --  After just two weeks, ABC pulled its tough, dazzling but low-rated hospital series, ''Wonderland,'' off the air, part of a trend that makes floundering shows disappear almost before you can learn their names. More deservedly, ''Deadline'' (from Dick Wolf, the producer of the ''Law and Order'' franchise) disappeared after five episodes; the idea of a crusading, crime-solving newspaper columnist was probably irredeemable. And even stardom could not guarantee success. Some of the season's biggest names have been canceled, though they lingered for a while, in effect speaking from the grave: ''The Michael Richards Show,'' John Goodman's ''Normal, Ohio,'' Gabriel Byrne's ''Madigan Men.''.</p>
        <p>UNDER THE RADAR SCREEN -- Some of the year's best shows snuck in with little advance hype. CBS's ''C.S.I.,'' about forensics experts led by William Petersen, became a quick hit. The WB's charming, unsaccharine mother-daughter drama, ''Gilmore Girls,'' held on against ''Friends.'' And HBO's acerbic ''Curb Your Enthusiasm,'' an even darker comedy about nothing from Larry David (the co-creator of ''Seinfeld'') was the funniest, most sophisticated new comedy of the year.</p>
        <p>WHO WANTS TO ADMIT THEY WATCHED 'WHO WANTS TO MARRY A MULTIMILLIONAIRE?'? -- It was a giant step backward for women, game shows, the Fox network and anyone named Darva, but it was a huge ratings success when Rick Rockwell chose Darva Conger to be his bride from among 50 contestants. Then came the embarrassments. The groom was not as rich as he claimed and had had a restraining order filed against him by a former fiancee. The bride entered the land of instant disposable celebrity, insisting on talk shows that she wanted her privacy back, then posing for Playboy.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION LEARNS TO LOVE GAY CHARACTERS -- Gay people became television's trendiest minority, as ''Will and Grace'' won the best comedy Emmy and Showtime's series ''Queer as Folk'' created a minor fuss. The canceled ''Normal, Ohio,'' with John Goodman as a gay man who returns to his hometown, proved that a stale sitcom can't be saved by homosexual trappings. It may be that Richard Hatch, the ''Survivor'' winner, who happened to be openly gay, did more for acceptance on mainstream television than all the other, self-congratulatory fuss.</p>
        <p>'BIG BROTHER,' BIG FLOP -- They were trapped in a house filled with cameras, but we didn't have to watch. CBS's other reality game show was boring and timid. The most volatile and wiliest members (a former member of the New Black Panther party and a former stripper) were the first to be voted out of the house. It's a relief to know that sometimes the best-planned network hype fails miserably.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO: THE YEAR IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
