<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton, Winding Up Trip, Tells Developed Nations Not to Forget the World's Poor</title>
    <meta content="Y15PRE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/15/world/15PREX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1255436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Warwick (England)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elizabeth Ii, Queen of Great Britain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Chelsea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DE163EF936A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton, Winding Up Trip, Tells Developed Nations Not to Forget the World's Poor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>COVENTRY, England, Dec. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton concludes what may be his last overseas trip as president with plea to developed countries not to forget the poor in age of high technology and globalization; speaks at University of Warwick, introduced by his close friend, Prime Min Tony Blair; Clinton, his wife and daughter Chelsea earlier have tea and cookies with Queen Elizabeth at Buckingham Palace (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Laying out some of the challenges that will face the world after he leaves office, President Clinton today wound up what may be his final overseas trip as president with a plea to developed countries not to forget the poor in this era of high technology and globalization.</p>
        <p>''No generation has ever had the opportunity that all of us now have to build a global economy that leaves no one behind and, in the process, to create a new century of peace and prosperity in a world that is more constructively and truly independent,'' Mr. Clinton told several hundred people at the University of Warwick. The university has a special institute that specializes in global issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Laying out some of the challenges that will face the world after he leaves office, President Clinton today wound up what may be his final overseas trip as president with a plea to developed countries not to forget the poor in this era of high technology and globalization.</p>
        <p>''No generation has ever had the opportunity that all of us now have to build a global economy that leaves no one behind and, in the process, to create a new century of peace and prosperity in a world that is more constructively and truly independent,'' Mr. Clinton told several hundred people at the University of Warwick. The university has a special institute that specializes in global issues.</p>
        <p>''It is a wonderful opportunity,'' Mr. Clinton said of the spread of trade, communications and computer technology throughout the globe. ''It is also a profound responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who was to fly back to Washington late tonight, spent the morning in London, where he and Hillary Rodham Clinton had tea, coffee and cookies for about 20 minutes with Queen Elizabeth II at Buckingham Palace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, who has met the royal family before, joked to the queen that after he leaves office he wants a golf rematch with her second son, Prince Andrew, who trounced him when the two last hit the links.</p>
        <p>Presidential aides are still mulling whether Mr. Clinton ought to make a trip to North Korea, but that visit grows more unlikely by the day as his term runs out. So this may have been the final trip beyond the United States borders by a president who has traveled more than any other. It was Mr. Clinton's seventh trip to Britain, where he has established a close bond with Prime Minister Tony Blair.</p>
        <p>''Bill Clinton has been a true leader of the Western world,'' Mr. Blair said in introducing the president, not long after he telephoned congratulations to the next one, President-elect George W. Bush. The prime minister noted that Mr. Clinton had been ''a friend and confidant to me and leaders around the world.</p>
        <p>In his foreign policy speech today, Mr. Clinton urged wealthy countries to consider forgiving the debts of nations in the developing world and to ensure that the ''digital divide'' is reduced between countries connected to computers and those left behind in the computer age.</p>
        <p>''It's fair to ask, I suppose, are computers really an answer for people who are starving or can't yet read?'' Mr. Clinton asked. ''Is e-commerce an answer for villages that don't even have electricity? Of course, I wouldn't say that.</p>
        <p>''We have to begin with the basics. But there should not be a choice between Pentium and penicillin.''</p>
        <p>The president, who often touts rosy statistics showing prosperity spreading throughout the world, focused today on the many problems that will outlast his presidency. He said half the world's people are struggling to survive on less than $2 a day, that nearly one billion live in chronic hunger, that half the children in the poorest countries are not in school and almost a billion adults have never learned to read.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has made globalization a foreign policy mantra, pursuing a free-trade agenda resisted by many. That resistance, he said, does not point out flaws in globalization itself but in a thoughtless approach to breaking down barriers among nations.</p>
        <p>''The great question before us is not whether globalization will proceed, but how,'' the president said. ''And what is our responsibility in the developed world to try to shape this process so that it lifts people in all nations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton largely steered clear of many high-profile issues the world will face in the years to come: the spread of terrorism, the effects of a missile shield, the role of peacekeepers stationed throughout the globe. Today, he focused on matters that often fall below the radar screens of foreign ministries, like the dangers of climate change, the national security threat that AIDS presents, and the importance that education and school lunches can play in stabilizing a country.</p>
        <p>White House aides said that the president's speech was aimed at leaders the world over, not at Mr. Clinton's successor, who comes to the job with modest credentials in foreign affairs.</p>
        <p>''President Clinton made the transition from governor to world leader, and it will be up to President-elect Bush to make that same transition,'' said P. J. Crowley, the president's national security spokesman. ''He will, because the president of the United States has a unique mantle as a world leader. I don't think anyone will question that the United States will stay engaged. The question is how do you handle the challenges we all face?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
