<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Lazio's Acceptance of Nomination</title>
    <meta content="31LTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6D8143CF932A05756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Lazio's Acceptance of Nomination</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Representative Rick A Lazio's acceptance speech after being nominated as candidate for United States Senate by New York State Republican Party (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Representative Rick A. Lazio's acceptance speech yesterday after being nominated as the candidate for the United States Senate by the New York State Republican Party:</p>
        <p>Ladies and gentlemen, I begin this campaign with no illusions. I am the underdog in this race. My opponent is better financed and better known. She comes to New York with the support of every left-wing special interest, from Washington insiders to the Hollywood elite. But as I've said before, ''Bring 'em on.''</p>
        <p>Because when it comes to representing the needs, concerns and values of the people of New York, I have one advantage that she will never have: I can be myself. I am a New Yorker. . . .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Representative Rick A. Lazio's acceptance speech yesterday after being nominated as the candidate for the United States Senate by the New York State Republican Party:</p>
        <p>Ladies and gentlemen, I begin this campaign with no illusions. I am the underdog in this race. My opponent is better financed and better known. She comes to New York with the support of every left-wing special interest, from Washington insiders to the Hollywood elite. But as I've said before, ''Bring 'em on.''</p>
        <p>Because when it comes to representing the needs, concerns and values of the people of New York, I have one advantage that she will never have: I can be myself. I am a New Yorker. . . .</p>
        <p>I have a goal, of course, and it's winning the race for the United States Senate. But more important, more important, I want to be worthy of winning.</p>
        <p>I want to bring New Yorkers together. I want to unite our people. We are a great state. But we are greater still when we work, when we aspire, when we dream as one people. . . .</p>
        <p>Some in the opposition camp have been crisscrossing our country for years, ripping into challengers, doing anything for the sake of political benefit. Well, I reject that political tactic. I reject the partisan idea that you can somehow lead people by dividing people. . . .</p>
        <p>I have a vision which reflects the voice of New York. It is a vision for all of New Yorkers -- from the Battery to Buffalo, from Montauk to Massena -- a vision based on the bedrock values of hope and opportunity and responsibility. A vision guided by mainstream principles and compassionate instincts. . . .</p>
        <p>I've got a record of delivering; you can look it up.</p>
        <p>I've passed legislation to help thousands of low-income women with breast or cervical cancer who were unable to afford treatment.</p>
        <p>I have passed legislation to preserve senior housing, clean up the Long Island Sound and provide tax relief to the small businesses that are the heart and soul of our neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>And there's more. I wrote the law that has reformed our nation's public housing system to unlock the key to home ownership for thousands of New York families. I authored Jennifer's Law to help identify missing children, and was the prime sponsor of landmark law which allows disabled Americans to go back into the work force and become taxpayers without fear of losing their health care coverage. . . .</p>
        <p>I am the candidate of the fair chance for all. I really want to help those who need help make that first tentative step toward the richness of the American dream. I want to help those in poverty reach for opportunity. I want to help build better public schools for our children to learn in. I want to help people train for that first good job, to be able to attend that college, to buy that first house. . . .</p>
        <p>As a proud father of two wonderful girls, both of them students in New York public schools, I know there is no greater imperative than strengthening our New York public school system. I believe in the power of standards because children are the soul of our future, and for millions of our kids, public schools are the place where character is formed, where values are taught, where dreams begin.</p>
        <p>To meet this challenge, I will push for federal policies that provide our local schools the flexibility they need to use their resources to produce real results. . . .</p>
        <p>I've worked hard to give people the opportunity to live in safe, healthy, affordable housing. This is the key to keeping families together and communities intact. . . .</p>
        <p>My friends, the American dream lives. The American dream lives.</p>
        <p>The American dream also means having clean air to breathe and fresh water to drink and fish. . . .</p>
        <p>As your senator, whether it's preserving the Great Lakes, cleaning up the Long Island Sound or reducing acid rain in the Adirondacks, I will fight to preserve New York's precious natural resources.</p>
        <p>My friends, I believe a campaign based on this mainstream vision will unite New York and unite our people. My pledge to you is to work without rest for the next 160 days to bring our message of hope and opportunity and responsibility to every city, every block, throughout our state, to energize our supporters and to appeal to those currently on the other side. . . .</p>
        <p>I will fight for this Senate seat county by county, neighborhood by neighborhood, house by house.</p>
        <p>Because I know I must earn this job.</p>
        <p>I will wage a campaign that reaches across every boundary to every New Yorker, regardless of color, background, belief. . . .</p>
        <p>And I believe this fight will lead to victory in this fall's election.</p>
        <p>My friends, the entire nation will be watching us between now and November. Let's show them who we are. Because when I win, New York will win.</p>
        <p>Thank you and God bless you.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
