<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Legislature, Vulnerable Members of the Majority Get Results</title>
    <meta content="28ALBA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DC1130F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Legislature, Vulnerable Members of the Majority Get Results</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo column notes that in legislative session that wrapped up last week, 'marginal' members, those faced with tough election battles, of Republican Senate Majority and Democratic Assembly Majority gos their bills passed, had money lavished on their districts, got permission to go their own ways on tough votes and have bills that could hurt them tabled; examples cited (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To get what you want as a legislator, it is not always enough to be in the majority party. Sometimes you have to be a threatened member of the majority; then you are cared for like an endangered species.</p>
        <p>The ''marginal'' members of each house's majority -- the Senate Republicans and the Assembly Democrats -- get money lavished on their districts, get permission to go their own way on tough votes and have bills that could hurt them avoided. Best of all, they get their bills passed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To get what you want as a legislator, it is not always enough to be in the majority party. Sometimes you have to be a threatened member of the majority; then you are cared for like an endangered species.</p>
        <p>The ''marginal'' members of each house's majority -- the Senate Republicans and the Assembly Democrats -- get money lavished on their districts, get permission to go their own way on tough votes and have bills that could hurt them avoided. Best of all, they get their bills passed.</p>
        <p>In the legislative session that wrapped up last week, the Republicans who control the Senate, worried about the re-election prospects of their colleagues in swing districts, grudgingly struck deals on an array of important bills that are popular with moderate voters -- from gun controls to restrictions on pesticide use. And on bill after bill, a Republican who is seen as vulnerable in November was listed as sponsor.</p>
        <p>Senator Frank Padavan of Queens sponsored a bill that makes New York the first state to set fire-safety standards for cigarettes, and he sponsored the gun control package. Senator Roy M. Goodman of Manhattan sponsored the first hate-crimes bill to pass the Senate.</p>
        <p>Senator Carl L. Marcellino of Nassau County sponsored a bill that could require neighborhood notification before any commercial use of pesticides. And Senator Kemp Hannon sponsored a bill opening some doctors' malpractice records to public scrutiny.</p>
        <p>In most cases, the sponsor had pushed the bill for years or took a lead role in working out a compromise with the Assembly.</p>
        <p>Several senators could have claimed the gun control bill. But when a deal was struck with Gov. George E. Pataki and the Assembly, the bill was essentially assigned to Mr. Padavan, one of those who would benefit most from being its sponsor.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' one Republican senator said, ''being a marginal's not all bad.''</p>
        <p>Consensual Sodomy Law</p>
        <p>Gay sex will no longer be illegal in New York. Well, it wasn't, anyway, but now it really won't.</p>
        <p>Explanation: a 19th-century statute makes consensual sodomy a crime. It was intended primarily to outlaw gay sex, but sodomy, as in most states, is defined as anal or oral sex, regardless of whether it is homosexual or heterosexual.</p>
        <p>New York State courts long ago struck down that law (though the United States Supreme Court has upheld a similar one in Georgia) and it was widely ignored even before that, but it remains on the books. Not for long.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Legislature and the governor agreed to a wide-ranging overhaul of sex crimes laws that provides tougher sentences for some offenses and a wider range of services for victims. Among other things, the new law, which goes into effect Feb. 1, will eliminate the prohibition on consensual sodomy.</p>
        <p>''It's getting rid of the last vestige of criminalization of homosexual behavior,'' said Matt Foreman, executive director of the Empire State Pride Agenda, a gay rights group.</p>
        <p>It is a sign of the times that repeal of the consensual sodomy law passed the Republican-controlled Senate three years running as a part of Mr. Pataki's sexual assault reform proposal, without a word of protest on the Senate floor. The bill that it was a part of did not pass the Assembly.</p>
        <p>Another sign of the times may be on its way. For decades, New York law has distinguished sexual assault victims by how they were assaulted so that, for instance, penetration with a foreign object is not rape but a lesser crime, sexual abuse.</p>
        <p>The just-approved sexual assault law states that such distinctions are wrong and that the Legislature intends to eliminate them.</p>
        <p>Environmental Groups Gain</p>
        <p>Among the biggest winners of this year's legislative session were environmental groups, starting with one of their top priorities, the pesticide notification bill that passed last week, which the governor has said he views favorably.</p>
        <p>The Legislature approved a bill making New York the first state to prohibit companies from selling ''pollution credits'' to factories in the Midwest that contribute to the Northeast's acid rain problem. It also passed a bill phasing out methyl tertiary butyl ether, a gasoline additive that has polluted ground water supplies. Mr. Pataki has signed both measures into law.</p>
        <p>Both houses have voted to impose tougher air emissions standards on motorized water scooters and similar personal watercraft, and they gave towns and villages the right to ban those vehicles. The Legislature also approved a bill prohibiting Consolidated Edison from recovering from its customers the money it lost from a radiation leak earlier this year. Those bills are awaiting action by the governor.</p>
        <p>''It was a great year,'' said Val Washington, executive director of Environmental Advocates. ''A lot of bills that got passed were things we've been wanting to see for years.''</p>
        <p>So why now? ''It's an election year, and that always helps,'' Ms. Washington said. ''But also, there's been so much talk about the dysfunctional Legislature the last few years that I think they started to get a sense that they had to show the public that instead of just squabbling, they could get some things done.''</p>
        <p>POLITICAL NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
