<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Weeks Starting Today to Argue Fine and Crucial Details of Cutting Greenhouse Gas</title>
    <meta content="13CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/13/world/13CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDF1138F930A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Weeks Starting Today to Argue Fine and Crucial Details of Cutting Greenhouse Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kyoto Protocol, treaty aimed at curtailing global warming, faces its greatest obstacles yet in next two weeks as officials from around world meet in The Hague to tussle over fine print; talks come on heels of new scientific reports providing strongest evidence so far that people, mainly through burning of fossil fuel, have contributed substantially to warming trend that could disrupt weather patterns and ecosystems worldwide; treaty requires industrialized nations to reduce releases of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat in atmosphere; has been signed by more representatives of more than 100 countries, including US, but cannot take effect until substantial number of industrial nations ratify it, which none have so far done; US presidential election may have clouded accord's future; opposition to it by Gov George W Bush and uncertainty that Vice Pres Al Gore could win support in Senate if he is elected noted; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After four years of tortuous negotiations, a treaty aimed at curtailing global warming faces its greatest obstacles yet in the next two weeks as officials from around the world meet in the Netherlands to tussle over the fine print.</p>
        <p>The pivotal talks, which begin today in The Hague, come on the heels of new scientific reports with the strongest evidence so far that people, mainly through the burning of fossil fuels, have contributed substantially to a warming trend that could disrupt weather patterns, ecosystems and agriculture around the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After four years of tortuous negotiations, a treaty aimed at curtailing global warming faces its greatest obstacles yet in the next two weeks as officials from around the world meet in the Netherlands to tussle over the fine print.</p>
        <p>The pivotal talks, which begin today in The Hague, come on the heels of new scientific reports with the strongest evidence so far that people, mainly through the burning of fossil fuels, have contributed substantially to a warming trend that could disrupt weather patterns, ecosystems and agriculture around the world.</p>
        <p>The treaty, called the Kyoto Protocol, requires industrialized nations to reduce releases of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases, which trap heat in the atmosphere. It has been signed by representatives of more than 100 countries, including the United States, but cannot take effect until a substantial number of the industrial nations ratify it.</p>
        <p>So far, none have done so. Most important would be the approval of the United States, far and away the world's largest producer of heat-trapping gases, and without whose participation, specialists say, the effort is bound to falter.</p>
        <p>Even if the details can be worked out over the next two weeks, the presidential election may have further clouded the accord's future.</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush has questioned the science pointing to a warming trend caused by human activity, and he opposes the treaty, which bears the imprint of the Clinton administration -- and particularly of Vice President Al Gore, who flew to the pivotal session in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997 to prod feuding delegates into agreement on key points.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has said, however, that he would support a requirement of some reductions in carbon dioxide emissions from power plants.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Gore wins, some treaty experts say that in a few years he might be able to build sufficient support in the Senate to approve the treaty, but it would be an uphill fight, requiring the consent of 67 of 100 members of the Senate, which with the current election is close to evenly divided.</p>
        <p>In other countries, negotiators say, there is a great enough sense of urgency to give the sessions at The Hague a chance of success.</p>
        <p>Pressure for action in Europe to reduce fuel use has intensified partly because of recent spikes in already high fuel prices and a string of devastating floods and storms that have been cited as a taste of what may lie ahead if the world's climate is disrupted. Other countries are feeling pressure, too, if indirectly.</p>
        <p>''It's the bottom of the ninth, and the bases are truly loaded,'' said John W. Ashe, a negotiator and ambassador to the United Nations from Antigua and Barbuda, a Caribbean country of 67,000. Island nations, which are vulnerable should the melting glaciers and polar icecaps raise sea levels, have been some of the most passionate proponents of the treaty. ''It's time for countries to step up to the plate.''</p>
        <p>If enacted, the treaty would commit industrialized nations over the next 8 to 12 years to reduce their emissions by at least 5 percent below the levels of 1990, the year chosen as the benchmark.</p>
        <p>Developing countries, including giants like China and India, would pledge to seek emissions limits in the future, but would not be legally bound to do so. These countries emit far less greenhouse pollution than industrial nations now, but are expected to surpass many of them within two decades. Many American senators say this lets the developing nations off the hook.</p>
        <p>Even as negotiations over the treaty have dragged on, emission levels of many of the world's big producers of greenhouse gases have continued to rise, particularly as economies have grown. This in turn has increased the pressure on negotiators for cheap solutions that are the least politically risky.</p>
        <p>The United States, for instance, is producing nearly 22 percent more warming emissions now than in 1990, while under the treaty it would be required to reduce those gases by 7 percent below 1990 levels between 2008 and 2012.</p>
        <p>In fact, energy experts say, of the 34 industrial nations involved, only Germany and Britain have a good chance of meeting their emissions targets, and they are likely to do so because of policies that are being pursued in any case. Britain, for instance, is closing obsolete coal mines, and Germany is dismantling the grime-belching factories left behind during Communist rule in the east.</p>
        <p>As a result, private environmental groups say there are many efforts under way to increase loopholes in the proposed treaty. ''They are trying to renegotiate the meaning of the numbers, making it easier to meet the targets,'' said Alden Meyer, director of government relations for the Union of Concerned Scientists, a private environmental group in Washington. ''The result could be we'll have a treaty, but the atmosphere would still be suffering.''</p>
        <p>As it stands, even the current treaty is seen by many climate experts and ecologists as baby steps toward addressing the effects of a century in which fuels were burned with abandon. And much remains to be done before it can take effect.</p>
        <p>The United States disagrees sharply with other countries on central points of the accord -- like how to penalize nations that fail to reach targets and whether to give credit for shifts away from coal and oil that involve alternatives like nuclear plants, hydroelectric dams or new systems that burn a dirty fuel, coal, with fewer emissions.</p>
        <p>The United States, which potentially stands to face the greatest economic cost from cutting emissions, is one of several countries that think nothing should be rejected out of hand. It, for instance, along with Australia and other countries with lots of open space, prefers allowing more credits for efforts to sop up carbon dioxide by planting trees, while more crowded European countries want to limit this option.</p>
        <p>Such disagreements and the politics surrounding the conference, many participants in the negotiations say, are helping to make the forthcoming sessions in The Hague a make-or-break effort.</p>
        <p>The thousands of delegates and observers gathering in the Netherlands represent agendas as varied as the geography, economies and cultures of the countries from which they come.</p>
        <p>There are Washington lobbyists representing oil-producing kingdoms who have succeeded for years in slowing the treaty with challenges aimed in part at compensating their clients once the world begins to wean itself away from petroleum.</p>
        <p>There are European lawyers representing low-lying island nations and those of other poor countries seeking a range of payments to help fend off rising seas and to absorb other effects of climate change.</p>
        <p>There are environmental campaigners who plan to build a dike of sandbags around the conference hall to illustrate the threat of future flooding.</p>
        <p>And in the middle of all this are more than 160 national delegations, many of which have formed negotiating blocs.</p>
        <p>The list of differences over differences and details is enough to dizzy the most seasoned negotiator, participants said.</p>
        <p>The 15 nations of the European Union, pressed by an influential Green movement, are insisting on strict limits on how much credit a country can gain by investing in emissions-cutting projects abroad. Their goal is to have most cuts occur on home soil, through increased energy efficiency or by replacing old coal-fired power plants with clean-energy sources like windmills.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the United States seeks to be able to spend money on emissions reductions wherever they can be done most cheaply, and to harness market forces through a global trading system for carbon dioxide similar to an American system for reducing sulfur pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>Another key dispute is over how much forests can be used to gain credits for absorbing carbon dioxide. Environmental groups and the Europeans oppose large-scale use of this tactic, saying that planting trees where others have been cut down results in no net carbon reduction and that preserving one forest may simply prompt the cutting of another forest somewhere else.</p>
        <p>Also, critics say, forests are not a secure repository because the carbon dioxide can easily be freed up d by fires, assault from pests or as climate shifts occur.</p>
        <p>The United States, in turn, has criticized the European position on penalties for failure to meet targets. Europe proposes a simple cash payment for each ton of carbon dioxide missed. But American negotiators, and some environmental campaigners, say this would allow nations simply to buy their way out of legal obligations.</p>
        <p>''Some rivers in Europe have schemes where you pay to pollute,'' said Fred Krupp, the executive director of Environmental Defense, a private group. ''On this point,'' he said, ''they are for ripping the teeth out of'' the treaty.</p>
        <p>The United States has proposed penalties in the form of larger subsequent cuts in greenhouse gases -- essentially payment with interest. But critics say that this would simply put off the emissions reductions.</p>
        <p>To take effect, the protocol must be ratified by any combination of industrialized countries with combined 1990 greenhouse emissions of 55 percent of the industrial world's total. This could happen without the United States, which accounted for 36 percent of total emissions in 1990.</p>
        <p>The European Union, with 24.2 percent of emissions, has said that it might seek an alliance with Russia, at 17.4 percent, and Japan (8.5 percent), and so reach the threshold for the treaty to go into force. Still, many participants say, the effort is bound to falter if the world's largest source of greenhouse pollutants does not sign on.</p>
        <p>For now, at least, the leader of the American negotiating team, Frank E. Loy, under secretary of state for global affairs, said he is committed to seeking changes in The Hague that produce real cuts in greenhouse gases that are affordable and fair, and thus acceptable to the Senate.</p>
        <p>In an interview last week, Mr. Loy said that the strengthening scientific evidence behind the greenhouse effect will help build support for the treaty in Congress, as will recent decisions by companies like Ford, Shell, Polaroid and DuPont to press ahead with cuts in greenhouse gas emissions and efforts to create new pollution-free technologies.</p>
        <p>''With the increasing clarity of the science and increasing participation of the business community,'' he said, ''it gets clearer and clearer that no administration is going to be able to ignore this issue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
