<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="16DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D7143BF935A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Big Companies Lead Effort To Reduce Medical Errors  A group of 60 of the country's largest companies announced plans to push hospitals to reduce medical errors that cause the deaths of tens of thousands of patients each year.</p>
        <p>Members of the Leapfrog Group, including General Motors, General Electric, AT&amp;T, Boeing and I.B.M., said they would encourage their employees to use hospitals that act to improve patient safety. The companies plan to favor hospitals where prescription drugs and medical services are ordered on computers that reject dangerous mistakes. [Page C19.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Big Companies Lead Effort To Reduce Medical Errors  A group of 60 of the country's largest companies announced plans to push hospitals to reduce medical errors that cause the deaths of tens of thousands of patients each year.</p>
        <p>Members of the Leapfrog Group, including General Motors, General Electric, AT&amp;T, Boeing and I.B.M., said they would encourage their employees to use hospitals that act to improve patient safety. The companies plan to favor hospitals where prescription drugs and medical services are ordered on computers that reject dangerous mistakes. [Page C19.]</p>
        <p>Guest Role on NBC for Cher, the Doll  A doll modeled after the singer and actress Cher plays a prominent role in a plot line of the NBC sitcom ''Will &amp; Grace'' tonight. Mattel plans to begin selling the Cher doll to consumers next spring. The product placement, meanwhile, is part of a stunt for the November ratings sweeps period that the network is calling ''NBC Super Star Thursday.'' Stuart Elliott: Advertising [C10.]</p>
        <p>Willamette Rejects Takeover Offer  Willamette Industries said its board had unanimously rejected a $5.3 billion takeover offer from Weyerhaeuser, saying it did not reflect the value of Willamette. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Technology Shares Bolster Markets  Stocks rose as technology stocks rebounded. The Nasdaq composite index rose 27.22 points, or 0.9 percent, to 3,165.49. Financial shares fell, limiting the gains in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, which climbed 6.86 points, or 0.5 percent, to 1,389.81. The Dow Jones industrial average gained 26.54 points, to 10,707.60. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Prescribing Patterns Duly Noted  Over the last decade, with the advent of sophisticated new computer technology, pharmaceutical companies have been quietly compiling resumes on the prescribing patterns of the nation's health care professionals, many of whom have no idea their decisions are open to commercial scrutiny. These ''prescriber profiles'' are the centerpiece of a vigorous -- and apparently successful -- effort by drug companies to sway doctors' prescribing habits. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Last-Gap Effort to Aid Hyundai Unit  Hyundai said it was turning to its affiliates to sell its headquarters building in Seoul, South Korea, and its in-house trading company, as well as shares in its electronics group. It hopes to raise about $288 million to help one of its big units, Hyundai Engineering and Construction, repay some of its $4.6 billion in debt and avoid bankruptcy. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Sotheby's Reports 9-Month Loss  Sotheby's Holdings reported a ''significant loss'' for the first nine months of 2000, mostly from the third quarter, attributing it largely to the special charges associated with the Justice Department's antitrust investigation into price fixing and pending settlements of lawsuits. Shares of Sotheby's fell $2.06, or 8.5 percent, to $22.25. [C19.]</p>
        <p>Virginia Power Concern Settles Suit  The Virginia Electric Power Company, accused of violating clean air standards and contributing to acid rain and smog in the Northeast, has agreed to the settlement of a landmark lawsuit that would require it to cut emissions from eight coal-burning plants by 70 percent. Officials hope the agreement will set a precedent to be followed by other power companies across the Midwest and the South. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Online Users as Laboratory Rats  Online auctions offer a laboratory for experimental economists to test their theories. Analysis of online auction data has yielded a wealth of insights, and a few puzzles. An intriguing puzzle has been the tendency for ''late bids.'' Hal R. Varian: Economic Scene [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
