<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aftermath of Drought and How to Adjust</title>
    <meta content="CNGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DA1E3EF935A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aftermath of Drought and How to Adjust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MEMORIES might be short this springtime as we become enamored with the new buds and blooms. There is an enthusiastic eagerness to be outside. But, it is time to be serious.</p>
        <p>All may not be peaches and cream  because of last year's drought. It could be the primary reason why so many plants may be looking or reacting quite differently this spring and summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MEMORIES might be short this springtime as we become enamored with the new buds and blooms. There is an enthusiastic eagerness to be outside. But, it is time to be serious.</p>
        <p>All may not be peaches and cream  because of last year's drought. It could be the primary reason why so many plants may be looking or reacting quite differently this spring and summer.</p>
        <p>An excellent explanation of this  appears in a recent issue of ''Frontiers of Plant Science,'' a report published by the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station in New Haven. The lengthy report cautions that the drought of last year may have serious consequences for this and following years.</p>
        <p>To clarify the consequences, the station pointed out that during the months of June, July and August, rainfall totaled 3.69 inches at their research farm in Hamden. This amount was 7.74 inches less than a nearly 30-year average. Or stated another way, the rainfall that occurred was equal to the amount that usually falls for one month. This lack of water was noted nearly everywhere. There were wilting plants, brown or even dead lawns, early fall color on forest and shade trees and even wilting of particularly fine specimen shrubs.</p>
        <p>According to New York City's weather records, the month of June was the second driest on record while July was both the hottest and driest month on record. The results of this soil dryness and heat can be devastating for all green life. The soil pores are deprived of their natural renewal.</p>
        <p>One of the best explanations of this critical development was stated by Paul E. Waggoner in the experiment station's report. In answering what is was that plants needed, Dr. Waggoner explained:, ''In warm weather, well-watered plants can transpire about an inch a week or 4 inches in a month. So the landscape needs, or at least can use, some 16 inches during April-July. Although exactly an inch a week rarely falls, plants draw on the reservoir or bank account of water in soil pores to even out the supply. Six inches of productive soil can store or bank about an inch of water, allowing surplus to drain away.''</p>
        <p>The facts speak for themselves. Wise indeed are those who appreciate the value of good soil moisture. Water in the ground's pore spaces helps any plants, either trees, shrubs or border flowers to grow. Lack thereof of this pore water is critical. Those whose lives depend on well water know how serious a water crisis can be.</p>
        <p>For the gardener, that wise and familiar Boy Scout motto, ''Be prepared'' is a practical thought to keep in mind. Choices of plants to grow can make a big difference.</p>
        <p>The surge of interest in native species will certainly be accented this year. These are the plants that have been around and have survived many vagaries of the seasons. Also, deep-rooted perennials will be in vogue because many of them have been able to come through all kinds of drought and heat with little consequence.</p>
        <p>Nurseries and garden centers may also find that the inquiries they receive may change from ''Does it bloom all summer?'' to ''Does this plant require a great deal of watering to thrive?''</p>
        <p>Lawns may have to be reseeded this spring in certain spots where the turf simply dried out and died. Probably the best time to reseed bare grass patches is this month, provided the soil has been scratched deeply first to make an acceptable place for the tiny grass seed to take hold. Watering these patches, almost daily if it is possible, is important for the young seedlings to catch and take root.</p>
        <p>An alternative to more grass is less grass. Shrinking lawn space is also coming into vogue as many gardeners are learning the merits of smaller, less high-maintenance grass space. Sometimes this is done easily by expanding the space given over to ground covers. Or the property shrub border is stretched out to assume more of the lot line.</p>
        <p>After all this rhetoric about drought and what it does to the soil's pore supply of water, it could be that the year may provide a deluge of water and all precautions will be of no concern. But the continual threat of global warming goes on.</p>
        <p>Many of the weather-predicting experts note that the world is now considered to be somewhere between 5 to 9 degrees warmer than it was during the last ice age that occurred eons ago. Let's hope the cooling rains will come.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
