<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Air-Conditioned Reverie of a Fundamentalist</title>
    <meta content="17MUSC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/17/arts/17MUSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1231066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EED81738F934A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Air-Conditioned Reverie of a Fundamentalist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUMMERTIME in Houston. This is what it's like to be a martyr to city-love. Heat and mugginess drive the body into underground streets and climate-controlled rooms, behind sealed windows and closed doors. The mind feels trapped, too. Intellectually, you know that you're in a great American city. Physically, you feel absent.</p>
        <p>The sensation of absence must be acute for Rafael Moneo, architect of the new Audrey Jones Beck Building at Houston's Museum of Fine Arts. In Moneo's native Spain, builders have been coping with heat for eons. Here in Texas, a one-time Spanish colony, architecture is for all practical purposes a network of sealed membranes, constructed around air-conditioning systems and linked together by cars chilled to bone-rattling discomfort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUMMERTIME in Houston. This is what it's like to be a martyr to city-love. Heat and mugginess drive the body into underground streets and climate-controlled rooms, behind sealed windows and closed doors. The mind feels trapped, too. Intellectually, you know that you're in a great American city. Physically, you feel absent.</p>
        <p>The sensation of absence must be acute for Rafael Moneo, architect of the new Audrey Jones Beck Building at Houston's Museum of Fine Arts. In Moneo's native Spain, builders have been coping with heat for eons. Here in Texas, a one-time Spanish colony, architecture is for all practical purposes a network of sealed membranes, constructed around air-conditioning systems and linked together by cars chilled to bone-rattling discomfort.</p>
        <p>The week I went to Houston, a photograph appeared on the front page of this newspaper depicting the apparent melting of the polar ice cap. Yes, Virginia, Santa's workshop is under water. Compared to this alarming piece of news, the Beck Building is scarcely worth mentioning. Nonetheless, the building is a good one. It deserves a positive story. But so does the link, however remote, between the Beck and our watery top of the world.</p>
        <p>Usually, when I arrive in a city to look at a building, I spend some hours prowling the vicinity to orient myself to the site. In Houston, it was too hot to prowl, or even to inspect the Beck Building's exterior, except from the window of my hotel room across the street. From this perspective, the building's context was the window, the newspaper and a bowl of complimentary fruit. Still life with art museum. Nature morte.</p>
        <p>Still, even a discouraged city-lover would risk dehydration to visit a building by Ludwig Mies van der Rohe. Two previous additions to the Museum of Fine Arts were designed by the great master, in 1958 and 1974. These have now been renovated, to coincide with the Beck Building's opening last May, when the weather may have been more conducive to architectural appreciation.</p>
        <p>Moneo was an excellent choice to build on Miesian precedent. Like Mies, Moneo is a fundamentalist. He believes in essences, architectural values that endure. ''I am committed,'' he said, ''to an architecture that maintains faith in the principles and the mechanisms architecture has always had.''</p>
        <p>Like Mies, who preferred the term ''building art''to architecture, Moneo embraces material construction as architecture's basic fact. He is not a structural expressionist. The stone surfaces of the Beck Building conceal load-bearing steel and concrete construction. But Moneo's forms and volumes do not violate the logic of the materials and methods used to fabricate them.</p>
        <p>The Beck is a square, two-story box. It occupies an entire block in the museum district a few miles from downtown, across the street from the Mies expansion and the museum's original home, a 1924 Beaux Arts temple. All four sides of the Beck are covered with a light pink stone that shimmers with a lustrous, Mediterranean bloom. Only spare geometric cuts are made in the facades: some large windows framed in bronze; a wedge-shape trough that allows the sun to reach a skylight; air grilles. On the west side, a deep reveal shelters the main entrance.</p>
        <p>The Beck's roof can be counted a fifth facade. It supports the building's most conspicuous urbanistic device: a grid of louvered light boxes that illuminate the galleries below. Night photographs taken from above suggest that the lanterns were intended to echo the downtown skyline some miles away. This effect is not apparent from the street. Nonetheless, the roofline makes an elegant night-time apparition.</p>
        <p>Two entrances to the Beck cause anxious indecision, particularly since the main one is concealed in deep shadow beneath an overhang and separated from the street by a driveway. The driveway is partly screened by a thick cement wall that has been molded into scored letters forming the museum's name. The lettering, designed by Massimo Vignelli, is astonishingly unattractive. If the intention was to recall the thick walls of adobe construction, the gesture is hollow here.</p>
        <p>Blast of conditioned air. Ticket lobby. Then, as the body adjusts, a vision of space-on-space: an atrium of an amplitude that you wouldn't believe possible in a two-story building, even with the little penthouse that enables the atrium to punch through the roofline. You are instantly relieved on entering, and not just by the coolness. The atrium's compressed, almost intimate monumentality states that Moneo knows everything there is to know about museum fatigue, including how to spare you from it.</p>
        <p>CLASSICALLY composed yet dynamic, the atrium is animated by two diagonals that slice asymmetrically through it. A staircase to the left, an escalator to the right form two triangles that face each other in reverse -- two flipped halves of a divided square. The length and thinness of the two banks magnify the room's scale. The space is further enlivened by the eclectic array of antique sculptures that face you like a committee welcoming you to the history of art.</p>
        <p>Take the escalator to the permanent collection. You may be halfway through it before your eye is drawn to the Beck's signal detail: a cubic convergence of planes and textures. A narrow strip of stone is set into the floor around the perimeter of each gallery. Playing against the stained, dark oak floor, the strips are light-catchers, horizontal frames that extend the wall's surface into the space of the room. Just above the stone, thin, louvered aluminum air-conditioning grilles are mounted at the base of the wall. The doorways between the classically proportioned galleries are framed with brushed bronze panels.</p>
        <p>It may strike you that the entire building was designed to create a sympathetic environment for this device for framing space and light.  While the skylights, with their louvered light boxes, are formally more assertive, the detailing in the galleries themselves defines the visitor's experience. They helped persuade me that the Museum of Fine Arts has the richest collection I've seen in many years.</p>
        <p>On leaving the Beck, you get another slap in the face. The blast of heat is only part of the shock. There is also the abrupt transition from the visual to the physical, from the sphere of retinal experience to a world where eye and brain are but two organs in a wholly constituted body.</p>
        <p>This is what an art museum is supposed to do, you might say: create a space ruled by the sense of sight. But to become aware of this specialized function is to see that Moneo's building is part of the general fragmentation of culture after all. And this awareness extends to the urban context. Like the Beck, the great majority of our buildings are dedicated to the creation of visual effects. In this sense, the Beck symbolizes architecture's role in the detachment of the eye from the rest of nature.</p>
        <p>The interesting thing about fundamentalists is the many fundamentals that their thinking does not take into account. Architecture's obedience to the eye is a relatively recent phenomenon in the history of building. The ancient Mediterranean sculptures that greet visitors to the Beck building served a religious function. Greek sculpture, for example, was attached to the temple, which itself derived its meaning and value from the sacred earth site on which it stood. Differentiation -- into bodies, selves, disciplines, sites and cities -- was seen by the Greeks as a dreadful if necessary part of life. From it grew tragic theater.</p>
        <p>The differentiation of space into the modern art museum is also wonderful and terrible. For the Greeks, art as well as religion supplied the connective tissue that prevents differentiation from pulling human life to pieces. For us, art is a thing apart. In a modern democracy, it is neither possible nor desirable to return to the Greek model. But it is possible to imagine how, working within the logic of art, the Beck Building might have articulated the tragic as well as the triumphal dimension of the modern art museum.</p>
        <p>The museum's collection is traditionally organized by region, chronology and school. Overall, it traces a narrative of progressive abstraction, from funerary sculpture, created for the body and the earth, to the thin, gorgeous lines of an Agnes Martin painting and spare geometric shapes of the museum's sculpture garden, created in 1986 by Isamu Noguchi. Along the way, we pass through the Italian Renaissance and the modern transition from the sacred to the secular, from the content-laden form of the religious icon to the illusionary device of single-point perspective.</p>
        <p>The museum's architecture tells a similar story. The Beaux Arts building is an abstraction of classical architecture. The Mies expansion pushes neoclassicism to the extreme reduction of glass and steel. The Moneo building, while clad in stone, recapitulates the Miesian ethic of formal reduction and spatial clarity. Even the stone -- a real material that provides the Beck's formal decoration -- represents the earth in abstract form. The story reaches a climax with ''The Inner Light,'' an installation of artificial light created expressly for the Beck by James Turrell. Progressing from earth to sky, physical to ethereal, the story is fundamentally religious in nature, a ritual procession in the temple of art.</p>
        <p>The story is still unfolding. The contemporary informational city is an ethereal zone, held aloft by streams of 0's and 1's generated by rapid electronic impulses. For now, however, its citizens still dwell in bodies, sealed buildings and cars, and these continue to create an invisible but highly unethereal substance: greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Houston is the capital of the oil economy. That economy built the city, defined its shape and makes it habitable. Even the Museum of Fine Arts reminds us of the city's dependence on energy. Across the street from the Beck stands a second new building -- a shadow Beck -- which houses the museum's air-conditioning system and a parking garage. Unfortunately, the shadow Beck has been designed to conceal this infrastructure. It would have been better had Moneo chosen to aestheticize it.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Fine Arts has a nice trove of sculptures by Jean Tinguely, including ''La Bascule VII,'' a work from 1967. It is pictured in the museum's guide book, along with a bold-face quotation from the artist, ''All machines are art.'' This is a fundamental modern tenet, one of the founding beliefs of New York's Museum of Modern Art. If Moneo's thinking were sufficiently elastic to incorporate this idea, the shadow Beck might have gained equal standing with its twin. This could have been achieved in four easy steps: eliminate the walls; install solar panels on the roof (an inverse of the Beck's lanterns); light up the interior (Turrell could have been turned loose on this); and declare the shadow Beck a new museum acquisition -- ''Air-Conditioning, With Cars.''</p>
        <p>Peter Eisenman once said the function of architecture is to ''problematize'' things. That is partly true in the case of the Beck. It is possible to give the building high marks and still come away thinking that something is wrong. Has one toured the wrong building? Perhaps it is a mistake to think of the Beck's concrete walls as its structure. Its deeper structure may lie in the shadow building across the street. Without cars, the museum would be inaccessible. Without air-conditioning, it would be uninhabitable. Compared with this infrastructure, the Beck's structure is almost incidental.</p>
        <p>ART museums traditionally put a fine gloss over the dark side of baron robbery. I see no reason to disparage this civilized practice. But the context of culture has changed dramatically in the quarter century since the Mies expansion was completed. Clients didn't habitually conduct global searches for architects. Before moon landings and satellite photography, the north pole seemed far, far away. It required a stretch to see any connection between an air-conditioning system in Houston and an ecological catastrophe on the polar extremities. Now, it takes a stretch to overlook one.</p>
        <p>The ice caps were once purely natural phenomena. Now they are cultural phenomena as well, the product of an evolving global operating system that has drawn together the producers and consumers of buildings and cars to create what an art historian might reasonably describe as the most ambitious earthwork of historical time. Perhaps the time has come to uncreate this masterpiece. This will require a global effort, too. Cultural institutions have a pivotal role to play in it. We look to them for self-awareness and for traction -- for signs that the operating system can receive sufficient feedback to avoid the self-destructive explosive fate Tinguely sometimes planned for his exploding mechanical sculptures.</p>
        <p>Our Shadow Beck would not reduce oil consumption by one drop. But it could work powerfully on the level of metaphor, the plane on which art museums and their contents communicate. Like Tinguely's sculptures, the Beck Building might have spoken metaphorically about its own civilization. I think it would say: ''Houston, we have a problem.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
