<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exotic Ills Loom Large, But What About the Flu?; Health Experts Fight a Disease Paradox</title>
    <meta content="04DISE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D81F3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exotic Ills Loom Large, But What About the Flu?; Health Experts Fight a Disease Paradox</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public health departments in cities like New York face challenge of remaining alert to illnesses new to region, like West Nile encephalitis, while turning public attention to more mundane health threats; threats include diseases contracted when immigrant residents make visits home, unaware that they have lost and children lack immunity to endemic illnesses; graph of incidence of West Nile and other illnesses; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems as if summer is finally here, and with it the fear of flying insects. It puzzles public health officials, this obsession with mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Although few mosquitoes carry the West Nile virus, which killed 7 people and sickened 62 others in the metropolitan region last year, New Yorkers can be singularly obsessed with the insects. The City Health Department gets frantic calls when they fly into homes. Some New Yorkers have been known to call their local emergency room when bitten. Suburbanites have vowed to spend the entire summer under netting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seems as if summer is finally here, and with it the fear of flying insects. It puzzles public health officials, this obsession with mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Although few mosquitoes carry the West Nile virus, which killed 7 people and sickened 62 others in the metropolitan region last year, New Yorkers can be singularly obsessed with the insects. The City Health Department gets frantic calls when they fly into homes. Some New Yorkers have been known to call their local emergency room when bitten. Suburbanites have vowed to spend the entire summer under netting.</p>
        <p>Consider, if you will, the tick. Ticks carry Lyme disease; Lyme disease is more common in residents of New York State than in those of any other state. Ticks also carry Rocky Mountain spotted fever, a disease not associated with the five boroughs that still sickens a handful of city dwellers each year. Yet that buzz in your ears is from the mosquito, not the tick.</p>
        <p>And don't even get health care workers started on the lack of interest in the vaccine that staves off a wholly preventable seasonal illness that kills roughly 3,000 New Yorkers a year: the flu.</p>
        <p>Still, the West Nile virus, which can cause encephalitis and was unknown in the Western Hemisphere before last year, exemplifies the increasing challenges to public health departments in large cities like New York.</p>
        <p>On one hand, health care workers must be ever alert for diseases new to the region and must find ways to deal with them.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing more exotic diseases,'' said Dr. Marcelle C. Layton, the assistant commissioner for communicable diseases in the City Health Department. ''West Nile is an awakening that although these things are uncommon, they do happen and we need to keep our eyes on them.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, those same workers must turn the public's attention to the seemingly eradicated or more mundane diseases that emerge each year. New York's population, which grows more diverse each year, has its share of both.</p>
        <p>And so an interesting paradox has emerged: while the technology used to identify and treat diseases has become increasingly sophisticated, public health has needed to extend down to the grass roots, penetrating even the most insular communities, one disease at a time.</p>
        <p>''We could create the best and most advanced surveillance system in the world,'' said Dr. Stephen M. Ostroff, an epidemiologist at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta. ''And despite that, I see no scenario where we can replace the front-line public health people.''</p>
        <p>Take malaria. It has grown at a rapid clip in the last decade. In 1997, there were 308 cases in New York City, up 227 percent from 1988. It is not easy to transmit. Unlike West Nile, it is carried by a mosquito that is uncommon in this region. And it needs weeks of hot, dry air to thrive.</p>
        <p>The increase in malaria can be almost completely attributed to people who go back to their home countries, Dr. Layton said.</p>
        <p>''We have to get the message out to people who came from areas where the diseases are endemic but who have been here awhile that their immunity to the illness is lost after a certain number of years,'' she said. African and Indian immigrants are the most common carriers, she said.  ''Children are particularly susceptible, because they were never immune.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the C.D.C. reported three cases in New York City of meningococcal disease among Muslims returning from the hajj, the pilgrimage to Mecca, Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>''There are a number of features that are contributing to the emergence of these pathogens,'' said W. Ian Lipkin, a scientist at the University of California at Irvine who identified the West Nile virus in New York last year. Those include a change in the distribution of disease-carrying insects and animals, global warming, the movement of certain populations into new areas and an increase in global trade and travel.</p>
        <p>''I anticipate that we will see more of these diseases,'' Dr. Lipkin said. ''And we need to have ways that we can rapidly recognize and treat them. H.I.V. came out of jungles and rapidly spread. Hepatitis C had a similar pattern.''</p>
        <p>To find people who may be cut off from the increasingly fragmented health care system, health care workers have begun to work more closely with community groups, religious leaders and tiny advocacy organizations that speak the same language and understand the cultural issues, like distrust of doctors, that prevent people from getting care.  This effort, known as Turning Point, was started in 1998 in large part to find groups on the margins of the health care system.</p>
        <p>''We are really trying to build alliances with organizations who perform a very important function in a very multicultural community,'' said Sandra Mullin, a City Health Department spokeswoman. ''It is in some ways going back to very basic public health.''</p>
        <p>But sometimes, groups are extremely hard to identify. For example, a rise in tuberculosis cases in the 1980's led health care workers to focus intensely on the disease, and the number of cases in New York City fell 33 percent between 1988 and 1998. But this spring, the disease control centers said it had identified an outbreak in New York City and Baltimore among young, gay, black, transgendered men who attend balls organized for their social groups.</p>
        <p>Finding men who acknowledge being among that group is hard enough, health care workers said. ''As we move toward TB elimination, the last cases will be the most difficult,'' said Dr. Peter McElroy, an epidemiologist at the C.D.C.</p>
        <p>In the case of these young men, it was hard for health care workers to insinuate themselves into that world, said Rosalyne Blumenstein, director of the gender identity project at the Lesbian and Gay Community Services Center in Manhattan. It was not enough for workers to seek out gay men in bars, which worked for a hepatitis outbreak in 1997.</p>
        <p>Interestingly enough, the public is often much more agitated about diseases it can do little about, like West Nile, than about preventing those it can. The flu, for instance, which can be fatal to the elderly, can usually be avoided with a shot. But each year, flu cases flood the city's emergency rooms, and doctors lament the number of people who forgo the shot. New York State lags behind the rest of the nation in pneumococcal immunizations; only 30 percent of New York City's residents over 65 get it, according to data from Ipro, a nonprofit group that studies the quality of health care.</p>
        <p>Failing to immunize children results in avoidable outbreaks of other illnesses in the region. Last year, in the upstate county of Chautauqua, a whooping-cough epidemic involved more than 250 cases.</p>
        <p>Back to why the tick is sexier than the mosquito. ''There may be a public perception that you are more at risk for a mosquito than a tick,'' said Kristine Smith, a spokeswoman for the State Health Department. But Culex pipiens, the type of mosquito that government agencies are devoted to wiping out, is far less of a menace than ticks.</p>
        <p>The tick-borne Lyme disease sickened 4,265 New Yorkers last year, not including city dwellers. The ticks also carry ehrlichiosis, a bacterial disease that is fairly new to the United States. The disease sickened more than 70 people in the state last year and can be far more dangerous to elderly patients than West Nile. ''No one really talked about that,'' Ms. Smith said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
