<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Visions of Government</title>
    <meta content="20SUN1$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4D9133EF933A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Visions of Government</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial compares and contrasts ideological differences between platforms of Al Gore and George W Bush</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ralph Nader sees no meaningful difference between the Democratic and Republican parties this year, and at least on a cosmetic level he has a point. Both parties have tried hard to project a centrist image while tranquilizing their activists. In Philadelphia, George W. Bush's inclusiveness pitch required keeping the Republican right wing offstage while throwing it a bone or two in the platform. The Democrats in Los Angeles reversed the process, giving the Kennedy-Jackson wing of the party plenty of air time but little consolation in the platform. Nevertheless, it is clear that there are measurable differences between the two candidates on domestic policy, and that on issue after issue the Democrats would still urge a more vigorous deployment of federal resources to solve national problems. These differences may not be enough to satisfy Mr. Nader's aggressively populist inclinations, but if the election were held now, they would give the voters a real choice.</p>
        <p>The biggest difference, perhaps the defining difference, lies in how the two men would distribute the lion's share of a projected budget surplus of $4.6 trillion over the next 10 years. Mr. Bush, warning that this money should not be hijacked by federal programs, would use about $1.3 trillion to cut taxes, mainly for affluent families. Al Gore would cut taxes by only $500 billion, mostly subsidies of one sort or another for middle-income families. He would also use every penny of the surplus generated by Social Security, about $2.5 trillion, to reduce the national debt. Mr. Bush would use the same money partly to reduce the debt and partly to finance a new system of personal retirement accounts. When all is said and done, Mr. Gore would have about $1 trillion  for new spending, Mr. Bush about $300 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ralph Nader sees no meaningful difference between the Democratic and Republican parties this year, and at least on a cosmetic level he has a point. Both parties have tried hard to project a centrist image while tranquilizing their activists. In Philadelphia, George W. Bush's inclusiveness pitch required keeping the Republican right wing offstage while throwing it a bone or two in the platform. The Democrats in Los Angeles reversed the process, giving the Kennedy-Jackson wing of the party plenty of air time but little consolation in the platform. Nevertheless, it is clear that there are measurable differences between the two candidates on domestic policy, and that on issue after issue the Democrats would still urge a more vigorous deployment of federal resources to solve national problems. These differences may not be enough to satisfy Mr. Nader's aggressively populist inclinations, but if the election were held now, they would give the voters a real choice.</p>
        <p>The biggest difference, perhaps the defining difference, lies in how the two men would distribute the lion's share of a projected budget surplus of $4.6 trillion over the next 10 years. Mr. Bush, warning that this money should not be hijacked by federal programs, would use about $1.3 trillion to cut taxes, mainly for affluent families. Al Gore would cut taxes by only $500 billion, mostly subsidies of one sort or another for middle-income families. He would also use every penny of the surplus generated by Social Security, about $2.5 trillion, to reduce the national debt. Mr. Bush would use the same money partly to reduce the debt and partly to finance a new system of personal retirement accounts. When all is said and done, Mr. Gore would have about $1 trillion  for new spending, Mr. Bush about $300 billion.</p>
        <p>These numbers imply important differences in philosophy. Perhaps oddly, they cast Mr. Gore as the conservative custodian of President Clinton's policies of securing growth by chipping away at the burdensome national debt, and Mr. Bush as the risk-taker who would reverse course on tax policy and divert part of the Social Security payroll tax to private retirement accounts at a time when Social Security's long-term solvency is still very much in doubt. They also reflect Mr. Gore's stronger faith in the remedial powers of the federal government.</p>
        <p>There are also important differences in emphasis when it comes to new spending. Both would use about the same amount, $100 billion, for education, Mr. Bush's signature issue. Mr. Gore, however, would spend $400 billion on health care, mainly to expand insurance coverage and underwrite a prescription drug program under Medicare, while Mr. Bush would spend only $100 billion on health. And Mr. Gore would put as much into environmental programs -- at least $125 billion -- as Mr. Bush would into all other programs combined, defense included. These figures must be treated with caution, since the projected surpluses are iffy. But they do give some indication of priorities.</p>
        <p>Numbers aside, on some issues there are telling ideological differences. The environment is a case in point. Mr. Gore would spend billions to make industry more energy-efficient, thus counteracting global warming. But even more important to conservationists is his gut commitment to preserving the federal government's central role in protecting the environment. Among other things, that means resisting Congressional efforts to destroy the government's regulatory machinery, as the Gingrich Republicans tried to do in 1995, and building on Mr. Clinton's surprisingly strong record of enlarging America's protected wilderness.</p>
        <p>To the extent that Mr. Bush has thought about the issue at all, he has greatly alarmed even moderate Republicans in Congress by suggesting that he would roll back protections of the national forests, open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge for oil exploration and cede greater authority on environmental matters to state and local interests, usually a recipe for disaster.</p>
        <p>Important differences on social issues like gun control and abortion are by now fairly well known. Mr. Gore's proposals for keeping guns out of the wrong hands are stronger, and he unequivocally supports Roe v. Wade, whereas Mr. Bush is generally pro-life. There is also a major difference on a central issue of governance, campaign finance reform. Having engaged in profligate fund-raising himself, Mr. Gore now supports the McCain-Feingold bill eliminating soft money from the American political system, and indeed says he will make it his first order of legislative business. Mr. Bush would abolish corporate and labor soft money but allow unlimited individual contributions to continue, which means that the corrupting flow of soft money that has been so much in evidence at both conventions this year would also continue.</p>
        <p>In time, other differences will emerge. But for now there is plenty of evidence that there are two parties out there -- not, as the Nader people would have it, one big corporate party with a pro-life and a pro-choice wing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
