<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Knack for Controversy Worries ABC News</title>
    <meta content="10MEDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1190881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Westin, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB163EF933A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Knack for Controversy Worries ABC News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moves by ABC News president David Westin stir controversy as he faces increasing pressure to make ABC news coverage distinctive; he says he spurs producers to try new techniques to hold and expand audience, and make it younger; holds standard journalistic lines should not be crossed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day last week, an ABC crew in Miami invested in a crane across the street from the great uncle of Elian Gonzalez, a classic maneuver intended to guarantee clear shots of the child if the authorities sealed the perimeter of the house. It looked like ABC would have a lead on the competition.</p>
        <p>But an ABC news executive ordered the crew to forget the crane. Why risk needless criticism about prying cameras when the perimeter had not yet been sealed?</p>
        <p>In the scheme of things, it was probably a good idea. The last thing that ABC News needed was another controversy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One day last week, an ABC crew in Miami invested in a crane across the street from the great uncle of Elian Gonzalez, a classic maneuver intended to guarantee clear shots of the child if the authorities sealed the perimeter of the house. It looked like ABC would have a lead on the competition.</p>
        <p>But an ABC news executive ordered the crew to forget the crane. Why risk needless criticism about prying cameras when the perimeter had not yet been sealed?</p>
        <p>In the scheme of things, it was probably a good idea. The last thing that ABC News needed was another controversy.</p>
        <p>For the last three weeks, events behind the scene at ABC News have seemed almost as compelling as the news itself. In the process, internal differences have been exposed and the president of ABC News, David Westin, has faced uncomfortable questions about his grip on the division and his mandate to take bold strokes to break through the cluttered marketplace of news.</p>
        <p>First, a staff rebellion quashed a move to make Mark Fuhrman, the detective accused of racism in the O. J. Simpson case, a paid consultant for ''Good Morning America'' on a murder story. Then, critics assailed the division for broadcasting an interview with the 6-year-old Gonzalez boy, which they said violated a rule not to put young children under such a spotlight.</p>
        <p>Then, news broke that the division had employed the actor and teenage idol Leonardo DiCaprio to interview President Clinton for a prime-time special program on global warming -- a move that has been variously described as a new low in celebrity journalism or an inventive move to attract young viewers to news programs.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Westin will decide whether to scrap the DiCaprio interview and how prominently the star should be featured in the special, scheduled for some time next week. The raw footage, which was being edited by producers over the weekend, was said by the White House to include Mr. DiCaprio asking Mr. Clinton about the Kyoto environmental accord.</p>
        <p>In another segment, others say, Mr. DiCaprio, who has been designated chairman of the Earth Day 2000 celebration, was taped sitting on a rock by a pond he used to visit as a boy, discussing the depletion of the frog population there. The production is said to all have an MTV feel and features short segments about global warming and related environmental issues photographed from Alaska to Atlanta. As it stood this weekend, both Mr. DiCaprio and the correspondent Chris Cuomo introduce the segments, basically as co-hosts.</p>
        <p>Seldom has the editing process been so closely watched. Whatever he decides, Mr. Westin will send a signal about what he thinks is appropriate, as the pressure to rise above other media outlets -- to be distinctive -- becomes ever greater.</p>
        <p>That pressure, Mr. Westin acknowledges, is prompting him to encourage his producers to try new techniques to hold their audience, if not expand it, and make it younger.</p>
        <p>''I think in a first-rate news division of any sort, one has to be moving forward,'' Mr. Westin said last week in a telephone interview. ''We can't keep programming news programs just the way we did five or 10 years ago. Society has changed around us; our competition has changed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Westin said he wants his producers to devise programming that will stand out. But, he quickly added, standard journalistic lines should not be crossed.</p>
        <p>Is there a clear understanding at ABC News of exactly what Mr. Westin means? Not consistently, executives acknowledge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Westin was faced with demands for explanations about the DiCaprio affair from Sam Donaldson, Peter Jennings and Ted Koppel, who are said to be uncomfortable with Mr. Westin's edict to try new things, though understanding of it.</p>
        <p>''Yes, it's a changed business and we ought to recognize that,'' Mr. Donaldson said last week. ''But we also all have to recognize that we have to do things according to the standards that will help us retain our credibility.''</p>
        <p>Rudy Bednar, executive producer of the special, said it is causing too much fuss. ''It was truth in advertising from the get-go with Leo's opening line to the president that he's not a journalist,'' Me. Bednar said.</p>
        <p>He said the criticism, both in the organization and outside, has been unfair. ''It's like the Moral Majority condemning a film and you ask them, 'Have you seen it?' and they say 'no,' '' Mr. Bednar remarked.</p>
        <p>ABC News has never walked in lock-step. There have always been fiefs -- of stars and of individual programs. And there have long been two schools of thought about the mixture of news and entertainment.</p>
        <p>But ordering change and managing the various forces is a tall order, especially for Mr. Westin, 47, a corporate lawyer and a relative newcomer to journalism who has had to fill the shoes of his predecessor, Roone Arledge. The inexperience has, at times, put him at a handicap in the news division, and in recent weeks, allies have been placed in the embarrassing position of portraying him as the victim of events.</p>
        <p>In mid-March, some staff members nearly rebelled when it was disclosed that Mr. Fuhrman had been hired by Shelley Ross, the executive producer of ''Good Morning America'' as a paid consultant to win his exclusive insight into the killing in 1975 of Martha Moxley, a Greenwich, Conn., teenager. Some credit Mr. Fuhrman with helping successfully reopen their investigation into Michael Skakel, the Kennedy cousin now charged in her death.</p>
        <p>A news staff member found out about the hiring of Mr. Fuhrman after seeing a guest list. A furor followed, the deal was called off, and it was agreed that he would not be paid for appearances.</p>
        <p>A week later, Diane Sawyer interviewed Elian Gonzalez for ''Good Morning America'' and ''20/20'' in the days leading up to the Justice Department's decision to send him home to Cuba with his father. According to ABC News executives' accounts, they did not want Ms. Sawyer to ask or place emphasis on whether the boy wanted to go back to Cuba. An ABC spokeswoman, Eileen Murphy, insisted that news executives requested only that Elian's desires not be made a focal point.</p>
        <p>When the segment was broadcast, Ms. Sawyer told her audience that the boy said he wanted to return, but said that she would not show him saying it because of the sensitive nature of the case.</p>
        <p>The report was deplored by media critics. Some executives say that if the question about returning to Cuba had not come up, Mr. Westin would not have taken so much heat.</p>
        <p>In the matter of Mr. DiCaprio, executives said Mr. Westin had been misled, though not maliciously.</p>
        <p>After the DiCaprio interview was disclosed in The Washington Post, Mr. Westin sent an e-mail message to staff members saying that no interview had been planned and that Mr. DiCaprio was supposed to do a walk-through at the White House and discuss only the White House's own environmental practices, like how it recycles its trash. He said President Clinton might appear during the tour.</p>
        <p>The White House called this version of events ''rife with inaccuracies,'' and it was disclosed that Mr. DiCaprio did in fact draw up his questions in advance, with some assistance from ABC News producers. This all begged the question of what is the difference between an interview that is conducted while walking or sitting.</p>
        <p>''ABC doesn't know whether Leo and I had an interview, a walk-through or a drive-by,'' Mr. Clinton joked at the annual Radio and Television Correspondents' Association dinner on Thursday. ''Don't you news people ever learn? It isn't the mistake that kills you. It's the cover-up.''</p>
        <p>Paul Friedman, executive vice president of ABC News, said that at the time Mr. Westin wrote the e-mail message, he did believe what he was asserting. He added that Mr. Westin had been given ''incomplete'' information by his own producers, who allowed Mr. DiCaprio to ask the president why global warming did not get the same attention as deficiencies in health care.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Westin said on Friday, ''It is clear to me now that ABC news people worked with Leonardo DiCaprio to prepare him to ask some questions that go beyond what I would have put on the air.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman said Mr. DiCaprio's White House visit ''started out with all the best intentions.''</p>
        <p>''Some mistakes were made,'' he said. ''David was victimized by those mistakes and by incomplete information given to him after the fact.''</p>
        <p>The program's executive producer, Mr. Bednar, said it had not been his intention to mislead Mr. Westin.</p>
        <p>''It was the communicators here miscommunicating,'' he said, adding that in hindsight, he thought he could have been more emphatic in telling Mr. Westin that an interview about general environmental matters had always been planned and that specific questions were prepared for Mr. DiCaprio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Westin knows that criticisms of his leadership are being made and, considering the last three weeks, he said some of that is valid. That is why, he said, he recently reorganized his division and named Mr. Friedman, who has 18 years in the division and the respect of the old guard, as his executive vice president.</p>
        <p>With that done, Mr. Westin and his top executives said they intend to keep pushing for change, even though it might mean ruffling some feathers.</p>
        <p>The reason: Network newscasts generally draw an older audience -- people in their 40's, 50's and 60's. Younger viewers are not drawn to newscasts. The decision to produce the DiCaprio special was to bring these viewers into the ABC fold, Mr. Westin said.</p>
        <p>''If we don't add a younger audience, sooner or later our audience will die,'' Mr. Westin said.</p>
        <p>The tough part is: Can he keep ABC's news practices out of the news, too?</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
