<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Observers Who Just Talk Weather</title>
    <meta content="15CLIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson Valley (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Weather Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Thomas (1743-1826)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollak, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DE143FF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Observers Who Just Talk Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POLLAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollak, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes work of Hudson Valley Weather Observers, chapter of federal government's Cooperative Weather Observers program, which monitors daily weather conditions and sends information to National Weather Service; there are 11,700 Cooperative Weather Observers across US as part of tradition that dates back at least to Thomas Jefferson (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY record their backyards' temperature every day for decades and count inches of snow while others are counting sheep. They swap stories about the storms of '38 and '47 and '50 as if those cyclonic bad dreams were old friendly enemies. They are an integral part of the government's collective finger in the wind, and what the late Tip O'Neill said about politics, they fervently believe about the heavens: all weather is local.</p>
        <p>''If the country wants to know how severe global warming is getting and our temperature region is changing, the only way they're going to get that data is through the cooperative observer program,'' said Dr. Jerome S. Thaler, president of the Hudson Valley Weather Observers, a club whose dozen or so members cover the lower and mid-Hudson Valley.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY record their backyards' temperature every day for decades and count inches of snow while others are counting sheep. They swap stories about the storms of '38 and '47 and '50 as if those cyclonic bad dreams were old friendly enemies. They are an integral part of the government's collective finger in the wind, and what the late Tip O'Neill said about politics, they fervently believe about the heavens: all weather is local.</p>
        <p>''If the country wants to know how severe global warming is getting and our temperature region is changing, the only way they're going to get that data is through the cooperative observer program,'' said Dr. Jerome S. Thaler, president of the Hudson Valley Weather Observers, a club whose dozen or so members cover the lower and mid-Hudson Valley.</p>
        <p>Like most in the group, Dr. Thaler, 70, a semiretired optometrist in Yorktown Heights, is a member of the Cooperative Weather Observers, a federal program, and he has been monitoring daily conditions for 35 years and sending them to the National Weather Service. The Hudson Valley Weather Observers meet every other month in the Mahopac Public Library (the next meeting is Nov. 14), and they publish a monthly newsletter, The Four Seasons. Its editor is Harold G. Schaefer, 11 Old Ludingtonville Court, Carmel, N.Y. 10512.</p>
        <p>''They were much more active in past years, but now with the Internet, they can access a lot of weather data that wasn't there before,'' Dr. Thaler said. ''So the interest has kind of waned, and now you're down to a hard core of observers who want to compare their data with that of other people, and just talk weather.''</p>
        <p>The 11,700 Cooperative Weather Observers across the United States are part of a tradition that goes back at least to Thomas Jefferson, who began a network in Virginia, and Benjamin Franklin, who was perhaps the first person to use observer data to explain continental weather patterns. In New York, people interested in becoming observers can learn more about the program from its Web site, www.nws.noaa.gov/er/ okx, or call Ralph Izzo, the agency employee in charge of the program, at (631) 924-0517, extension 225.</p>
        <p>The notion of nationwide observers might seem archaic, like the Ground Observer Corps watching for Soviet bombers in the 1950's, to generations that have grown used to satellite photography and snazzy television graphics and assume that the government collects everything electronically. Automatic monitors are widely dispersed, and although they are increasing, volunteers are still needed to fill the gaps.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thaler, who has written books on climate in Westchester and the Catskills, explains it this way: ''Supposing one wanted to know, for a specific area in Putnam County, when one should plant one's garden, or how much heating oil you figure you should use during the season, or what's the typical snow depth one could expect.</p>
        <p>''There's no way of knowing anything about that between Albany and the Westchester Airport'' without weather observers and their accumulation of day-to-day local readings, he said. He runs one of the Weather Service's four Westchester weather stations in his backyard in Yorktown Heights; the three others are in Ardsley-on-Hudson, run by John Clear, another Hudson Valley club member; in Granite Springs; and at the Westchester County Airport, he said.</p>
        <p>''I'm not interested in tomorrow's weather,'' said Dr. Thaler, who expects to complete another book this year, ''The Weather History and Climate Guide to the Lower Hudson Valley.'' His real focus is climate trends: ''Climate is what you can normally expect, and what are the extremes, and what is the worst and the best weather that has occurred on a monthly basis for the last 40 years.''</p>
        <p>Besides Dr. Thaler, Hudson Valley club members include an accountant, a horticulturalist, a retired postal worker, a retired priest, a retired New York City teacher and a retired I.B.M. electronics scientist. While not all the members are elderly by any means, the observer program stresses continuity, and many members pride themselves on decades of unbroken daily reporting. If they are ill or out of town, friends or family members keep the record going.</p>
        <p>The handful of members who attended the July meeting had more than 90 years of weather observing among them. John Drohan of White Plains recalled becoming interested when he was 9 or 10, in bed. ''I was sick for a long time,'' he said, so he had nothing better to do than look out the window.</p>
        <p>Weather has never become dull to him. ''It always changes, and we live in a changeable area,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Drohan, 70, has a daily weather map for July 23, 1930, the day he was born. He wrote an article for the first issue of Weatherwise magazine in February 1948 about the 32-inch snowfall in White Plains on Dec. 26, 1947. As he was writing, drifts were four feet high down the middle of the street. ''Where I live, it will be two to three days before the plow will be able to get here,'' he wrote, adding hour-by-hour accumulations, temperatures and wind.</p>
        <p>At meetings, members compare their monthly data sheets. There are daily high and low temperatures, precipitation to the nearest hundredth of an inch, wind speed, maximum gusts and thunderstorm days. There are special remarks like ''smog.''</p>
        <p>Jeff A. Miller of New Windsor, who manages an Internet site for I.B.M., lived in Fort Worth for 10 years and finds the weather up here much more interesting. ''There's the microclimate in this vicinity,'' he said, meaning that the Hudson Valley weather, unlike that in Texas, can be quite different for people who live on opposite sides of town.</p>
        <p>They chatted about Tropical Storm Floyd (they estimated that it was a once-in-200-year occurrence), and a mini-tornado in Cortlandt in June. Mr. Schaefer, the newsletter editor, observed that his property has about a 150-foot altitude difference and that he once saw snow at one end and not at the other.</p>
        <p>''So, Peter, were you below normal or above normal?'' Mr. Drohan suddenly asked.</p>
        <p>Peter C. Jaeger replied, ''I was above normal for May, but less than one degree.'' .</p>
        <p>Mr. Jaeger, 58, a computer operator who lives in Stormville in Dutchess County, has an unbroken record of daily observations there since 1973. He runs a weather station there and, like the other members, he also takes part in the government's Skywarn program, which gives local reports on severe weather conditions. For Tropical Storm Floyd, he called in every hour, he said.</p>
        <p>The government needs more volunteers, Mr. Jaeger said. ''There's a lot of automated equipment these days that can't tell the difference between snow and fog.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
