<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newfound Crater Could Explain Worst Mass Extinction</title>
    <meta content="25CRAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB1530F936A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newfound Crater Could Explain Worst Mass Extinction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists discover a crater some 75 miles wide in Western Australia, and they suggest that the rock from space that created it may have been responsible for sudden disappearance of some 90 percent of all animal species on earth a quarter billion years ago; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A quarter billion years ago, some 90 percent of all animal species, including the trilobites, the three-lobed predators of the sea, suddenly disappeared in the worst of all mass extinctions.</p>
        <p>The killer's identity has long been a mystery. But now scientists in Australia have unearthed evidence that the culprit could have been a speeding rock from outer space that slammed into the planet, carved out a crater some 75 miles wide, and blasted millions of tons of rock and dust into the sky, blotting out the sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A quarter billion years ago, some 90 percent of all animal species, including the trilobites, the three-lobed predators of the sea, suddenly disappeared in the worst of all mass extinctions.</p>
        <p>The killer's identity has long been a mystery. But now scientists in Australia have unearthed evidence that the culprit could have been a speeding rock from outer space that slammed into the planet, carved out a crater some 75 miles wide, and blasted millions of tons of rock and dust into the sky, blotting out the sun.</p>
        <p>A team of four scientists at the Geological Survey of Western Australia and the Australian National University, led by Arthur J. Mory, announced the discovery in the April 15 issue of Earth and Planetary Science Letters, published by Elsevier Science. The structure, now hidden by hundreds of feet of dirt and rock, lies in Western Australia near an arm of the Indian Ocean known as Shark Bay.</p>
        <p>''It's tantalizing,'' Michael R. Rampino, an earth scientist at New York University, said of the discovery. ''It's clearly a big crater. But the age is up for grabs, so a link to extinction remains to be proven.''</p>
        <p>The exact dating of the cosmic scar is uncertain, the discoverers said. But clues suggest its age is roughly between the early Jurassic and early Permian periods, or 200 and 280 million years ago. That distant era, they noted, contained two mass extinctions -- one at the end of the Triassic some 214 million years ago, and one at the end of the Permian 247 million years ago.</p>
        <p>That upheaval saw the disappearance of not only trilobites but hundreds of other marine invertebrates, insects and early reptiles. Their demise was a turning point in earth history that made way for the rise of dinosaurs and widened the niches available for the mammal-like reptiles, the ancestors of humans.</p>
        <p>The Australian blow probably accounts for ''one of the two major extinctions,'' the crater discoverers wrote, ''given the likely environmental consequences of an impact of this magnitude.''</p>
        <p>Named Woodleigh after a station in the Australian outback, the new crater is the largest ever discovered on the Australian geological plate. Globally, it is the fourth largest. The only bigger ones are Vredefort in South Africa (about 185 miles wide), Sudbury in Canada (about 155 miles wide) and Chicxulub in Mexico (about 110 miles wide). In all, scientists have now found some 150 or so impact craters.</p>
        <p>The Australian find was inspired by the scientific detective work that tied the Chicxulub crater (pronounced cheek-soo-LOOB) to the most famous of all mass extinctions. That die-off, 65 million years ago, at the end of the Cretaceous period, killed the dinosaurs, the marine shellfish called ammonites and many other groups of animals.</p>
        <p>The main dinosaur sleuth was Dr. Walter Alvarez, a geologist at the University of California at Berkeley. In 1980, he and his colleagues reported that they had found unusually large amounts of iridium in geological strata laid down when the dinosaurs died out and proposed that the rare metal had come from a giant asteroid that struck the Earth. Iridium, a precious metal belonging to the platinum group of elements, is more abundant in meteorites than in terrestrial rocks.</p>
        <p>The Alvarez theory won wide attention. And in 1990, after long hunts, geologists announced that they had found a candidate crater in Mexico, buried deep under the Yucatan Peninsula. The Chicxulub crater was big enough to account for the dinosaur extinctions, and its age was exactly right.</p>
        <p>The Australian team found an intriguing sample of rock from the Woodleigh region that a company in 1981 had pulled up from a depth of 620 feet. The quartz in this rock was fractured or ''shocked'' in a way that suggested that it had been subject to sudden extreme heat and pressure. In March 1999, the team went back to the site and took 25 core samples from depths ranging from 620 to more than 1,000 feet down.</p>
        <p>Study of the samples with light and electron microscopes revealed multiple signatures of shocked quartz, as well as glassy areas that implied a history of fiery melts.</p>
        <p>The team also obtained government gravity maps, which show variations in the density of the deep rock, and in March 1999 took their own gravity readings as well, the Earth and Planetary Science article said. The maps revealed a buried, multiring structure some 75 miles wide -- the bull's-eye of a cosmic scar.</p>
        <p>The team used an ultraviolet laser to try to date the rocks through mineral analysis, but that effort failed. A minimum age of 200 million years was obtained from geologic deposits that filled in the Woodleigh crater and a maximum age of 280 million from fossils at its base. In addition, the region yielded radiochemical  signs of high heats occurring somewhere from 250 to 280 million years ago -- about the time of the great dying at the end of the Permian.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Ed Boyle, a geochemist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and an editor at Earth and Planetary Science Letters, called the Australian findings ''very interesting'' and predicted other researchers would join the attempt to pin down the crater's date.</p>
        <p>In the years before the Australian find, scientists who pondered the cause of the Permian extinction had suggested a change in the composition of the earth's atmosphere, volcanoes in Siberia and the lowering of global sea levels. Clues have been sparse because the events occurred so long ago. In particular, little remains of the period's fossil record.</p>
        <p>Scientists say a mix of factors may have contributed to the Permian event, with the Australian object providing the killer punch.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rampino at New York University noted that scientists had identified a 25-mile-wide crater in Brazil that also seemed the right age for the Permian extinction.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, he said, it was caused by a pair of cosmic killers, or possibly a barrage of them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
