<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Cooperative to Offer Customers 'Green' Electricity</title>
    <meta content="26GREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Connecticut Energy Cooperative</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Cooperative to Offer Customers 'Green' Electricity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., June 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Energy Cooperative announces that it will begin selling what it calls 'green' electricity, generated not from oil or nuclear reactors but from renewable sources such as wind, water and methane gas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Creating the energy industry's equivalent of an organic food store, a Connecticut company is to announce Monday that it will begin selling what it calls ''green'' electricity, generated not from oil or nuclear reactors, but from renewable sources like wind, water and methane gas captured from garbage dumps.</p>
        <p>Naturally, it will be more expensive -- about $5 to $6 more a month. But the company, the Connecticut Energy Cooperative, is betting that some customers will be willing to pay a premium for it. Those who do not mind fossil fuels can still buy traditional power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Creating the energy industry's equivalent of an organic food store, a Connecticut company is to announce Monday that it will begin selling what it calls ''green'' electricity, generated not from oil or nuclear reactors, but from renewable sources like wind, water and methane gas captured from garbage dumps.</p>
        <p>Naturally, it will be more expensive -- about $5 to $6 more a month. But the company, the Connecticut Energy Cooperative, is betting that some customers will be willing to pay a premium for it. Those who do not mind fossil fuels can still buy traditional power.</p>
        <p>The cooperative plans to begin offering the service on July 1, the day that state legislation deregulating the electricity industry takes full effect. Green power will be available in most parts of the state, including most of Fairfield County. The cooperative, which also sells oil, natural gas and propane and long-distance telephone service, is like a food co-op, operating nonprofit to reduce prices for its members, both homeowners and businesses.</p>
        <p>State Representative Bob Maddox, who is leaving the Legislature after this year to work for the co-op full time as its director of marketing, said he thought people would gladly pay more for the green energy ''for their own health,'' reducing pollution.</p>
        <p>''The monthly pricing difference for the average family in Connecticut will be about the same as the cost of a Big Mac with super-size fries and a Coke,'' said Mr. Maddox, a Republican from Litchfield County, who lives in a solar-powered home in Bethlehem and drives a Honda Insight, a gas-electric hybrid car that gets up to 70 miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>Green electricity is already available in parts of California, Pennsylvania and New Jersey, but not New York State. In New Jersey, it is sold by two companies, Connectiv Power Delivery and Green Mountain Energy.</p>
        <p>The cooperative's electricity will come from wind in upstate New York, landfill gases in New Hampshire and small hydroelectric plants in Connecticut. The co-op will also sell non-green electricity at prices Mr. Maddox says will be lower than rates charged by Connecticut Power and Light and United Illuminating.</p>
        <p>As with organic food, the motives of providers of clean energy can be both environmental and political. Although hydropower is  green energy, the co-op will not do business with Hydro-Quebec, the large government-owned utility in Canada, which has been criticized by environmentalists. Hydro-Quebec, which has long called such criticism unwarranted,  backed off from its most controversial project, called Great Whale, in 1994. Critics said the project would have flooded Indian tribal lands in Canada and destroyed subarctic wilderness.</p>
        <p>Whatever their reasons for choosing green energy, customers who want it will simply be able to call the co-op or visit its Web site, www.energyforme.com. Customers who sign up will not necessarily have green energy going through the outlets in their homes; rather, they are paying to increase the amount of renewable energy on the local power grid, proportional to their monthly usage.</p>
        <p>Because customers have no way of knowing what kind of electricity they are paying for, many companies offering green power, including the Connecticut cooperative, have joined the Green-e Renewable Electricity Certification Program, run by the Center for Resource Solutions, an environmental group in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>To be certified, power providers must disclose their sources of energy and demonstrate that at least 50 percent of the supply comes from renewable sources.</p>
        <p>Ashok Gupta, an economist with the Natural Resources Defense Council, said a cooperative selling both green and traditional energy is ''like a cereal company offering healthy cereal and not-so-healthy cereal.''</p>
        <p>''It's a great thing,'' he said. ''It gives people choices. Avoid coal, nuclear and Hydro-Quebec, and buy green power.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
