<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; ABC Hits (Melting) Iceberg</title>
    <meta content="25COLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicaprio, Leonardo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFDD1230F936A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; ABC Hits (Melting) Iceberg</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column notes that ABC cut over 17 minutes of actor Leonardo DiCaprio's interview with Pres Clinton for its Earth Day special because network felt it was too amateurish (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The time has come to put in a good word for Leonardo DiCaprio.</p>
        <p>The controversial White House interview between the star of ''Titanic'' and President Clinton finally aired last weekend, as part of an ABC Earth Day special. ''Just by changing the lighting in this building we lowered our electric bills by $100,000 a year,'' the Leader of the World's Only Surviving Superpower said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The time has come to put in a good word for Leonardo DiCaprio.</p>
        <p>The controversial White House interview between the star of ''Titanic'' and President Clinton finally aired last weekend, as part of an ABC Earth Day special. ''Just by changing the lighting in this building we lowered our electric bills by $100,000 a year,'' the Leader of the World's Only Surviving Superpower said.</p>
        <p>''Wow,'' replied the Most Famous Actor on the Planet.</p>
        <p>Later Mr. DiCaprio managed to elicit the revelation that environmental concerns were just as important to the president as education or health care. Those were pretty much the high points. More than 17 minutes of the 20-minute interview wound up on the cutting-room floor, allegedly because ABC felt it was too amateurish. Politics has not always been kind to Mr. DiCaprio, the movie star John McCain always enjoyed referring to as ''that androgynous wimp.''</p>
        <p>As an interviewer, Mr. DiCaprio is no Tim Russert, or even the guy who used to ask taste testers whether they prefer Coke to Pepsi. However, the network could have made a worse decision than assigning a 25-year-old actor to talk global warming with the president. For instance, it could have given the job to any of the people responsible for the rest of the show.</p>
        <p>Let's begin with a brief recap of ''Planet Earth 2000,'' since the ratings suggest that you did not get a chance to watch it yourself. In fact, the odds were better that you spent the holiday weekend being abducted by a U.F.O.</p>
        <p>The high point probably came when the ABC correspondent, Christopher Cuomo, delivered a paean to the ancient hunting traditions of the local Eskimos while his subjects buzzed around on snowmobiles, waving high-powered rifles. The actual topic of the segment was thinning ice near the North Pole. But if you waited for Mr. Cuomo to point out that melting of the polar ice cap had a potential effect on anything but the Eskimos' ability to keep their recreational vehicles from falling into the water, you'd still be on the couch.</p>
        <p>The program's resistance to providing context, or making any sort of compelling point, was actually sort of fascinating. A segment on Julia Butterfly Hill, the woman who spent two years living in a tree to save it from the loggers, managed to tell her whole story without once giving any inkling of why cutting down redwoods is undesirable.</p>
        <p>''We were targeting a younger audience,'' said Phyllis McGraddy, an ABC vice president. ''The point of that woman was to bring them to asking: 'Well, why was she in that tree?' ''</p>
        <p>The point of never giving them the answer was somewhat more oblique.</p>
        <p>''It bothers me that nobody seems to be giving us credit for even trying,'' Ms. McGraddy added. ''Whether we failed miserably, well, that's a different debate.''</p>
        <p>Interesting kids in global warming is such a fine goal that you could overlook Mr. DiCaprio, not to mention the ''E.R.''-like camera work, the MTV-type soundtrack and the Foxian way that everything wound up being illustrated by another picture of a hurricane. But out of fear of offending or boring its target audience, ABC also made global warming apolitical, devoid of villains. Even the lumber company that wanted to cut down Ms. Hill's tree seemed nice.</p>
        <p>The White House, possibly hoping to drive ABC nuts, has released a transcript of the entire actor-president conversation, and it turns out that there was one person involved in the project who had a more, ah, global vision of global warming. Mr. DiCaprio wanted to know how the United States could get developing countries to cut pollution when ''we're responsible for a quarter of the greenhouse gases that go into the atmosphere.'' He also asked about requiring automobile manufacturers to make cars cleaner.</p>
        <p>The president's answers were, to use the metaphors of the moment, rather windy and unelectrifying. Even worse, from the producers' point of view, they were delivered from a chair. The network had counted on a walking tour of the energy-efficient White House, and the producers apparently lost interest in Mr. DiCaprio's scoop when they found out the president wanted the interview to be stationary. ''It was supposed to be an hour of everything moving, not sitting down,'' said Ms. McGraddy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
