<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmentalist Gore Gives Salve to Labor</title>
    <meta content="25GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DC103AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmentalist Gore Gives Salve to Labor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, July 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore turns focus to environmentalists and labor unions, two important Democratic constituencies, three weeks before Democratic National Convention; addresses gathering in Grand Rapids, Mich, where he is endorsed by Sierra Club; assures unionized workers that strong environmental policies would not necessarily hurt companies or their employees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With three weeks left before the Democratic National Convention, Vice President Al Gore turned his focus today to uniting two important Democratic constituencies that have sometimes been at odds: environmentalists and labor unions.</p>
        <p>At an event on the tree-lined banks of the Grand River in Grand Rapids, Mich., Mr. Gore picked up the endorsement of the Sierra Club, one of the nation's most politically potent environmental groups. But the crowd of nearly 200 people was filled with unionized workers, and Mr. Gore devoted much of his speech to assuring them that strong environmental policies would not necessarily hurt companies or their employees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With three weeks left before the Democratic National Convention, Vice President Al Gore turned his focus today to uniting two important Democratic constituencies that have sometimes been at odds: environmentalists and labor unions.</p>
        <p>At an event on the tree-lined banks of the Grand River in Grand Rapids, Mich., Mr. Gore picked up the endorsement of the Sierra Club, one of the nation's most politically potent environmental groups. But the crowd of nearly 200 people was filled with unionized workers, and Mr. Gore devoted much of his speech to assuring them that strong environmental policies would not necessarily hurt companies or their employees.</p>
        <p>''We're here today to tell America that as we move toward a cleaner, safer, healthier environment, we are going to create more jobs, not fewer jobs, for American families,'' he said. ''A stronger economy and better environment go together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is trying to win the endorsement of the United Automobile  Workers, a political powerhouse in Michigan, where he and his Republican opponent, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, are in a closely contested race.</p>
        <p>The U.A.W.'s leaders have been angry with the vice president over his strong support for global trade, and some of them worry that administration policies intended to reduce air pollution and slow global warming could drive up the cost of cars and hurt the auto industry.</p>
        <p>But in recent weeks Mr. Gore has had several conversations with Stephen Yokich, the union's president, to try to work out their differences, Democratic officials said. Mr. Gore's aides are hoping that the union's executive committee will vote to endorse him at its next meeting, on Aug. 8, six days before the Democratic convention opens.</p>
        <p>This afternoon Mr. Gore also took a poke at Governor Bush for the  intense media attention that has been attracted to his efforts to choose a running mate. Mr. Gore suggested that the governor had purposely played out his deliberations in public, in an effort to build excitement about his campaign.</p>
        <p>''I've handled my process differently than the Bush campaign has handled theirs,'' the vice president told reporters. ''I've kept it private and, I hope, dignified, out of respect for the individuals, the men and women, who are under consideration. And I am going to continue to approach it that way.''</p>
        <p>But just minutes before, in what seemed like a clear attempt to stoke interest in his own deliberations, Mr. Gore's aides notified reporters that he would be meeting on Tuesday morning with former Secretary of State Warren M. Christopher, who is helping him cull his list of prospective vice-presidential nominees.</p>
        <p>Asked what qualities he was looking for in a running mate, Mr. Gore replied: ''I'm going to pick the person who I believe can become the president on a moment's notice, if necessary; who also has a good working relationship with me, or the prospect of one; and who shares my values, someone who's willing to fight for people and not the powerful.''</p>
        <p>His appearance in Grand Rapids today was hardly the only one this week devoted to his shoring up the Democratic base. Afterward he flew here to Cleveland, where he campaigned among hard-hat workers at a construction site and then met with steelworkers as well as a police union chief. And on Wednesday, he flies to Chicago to address the Rev. Jesse Jackson's Rainbow Coalition.</p>
        <p>Today Robert Cox, president of the Sierra Club, picked up on a theme Mr. Gore has been sounding recently, arguing that Mr. Bush's record as governor of Texas proves that he would support federal policies that would help corporate polluters and ruin the environment.</p>
        <p>''If we fail to elect Al Gore, if George Bush becomes president, we could face a very different America,'' Mr. Cox said. ''We could face what the people of Texas face now: air pollution, water pollution, toxic waste, record numbers of violations of our clean-air and clean-water standards, environmental laws unenforced, and corporate polluters unchecked and out of control.''</p>
        <p>In reply, Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, said the governor had actually reduced air and water pollution in Texas, and he ridiculed the Sierra Club's endorsement of Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing that he's rolling out endorsements from traditionally Democratic groups,'' Mr. Bartlett said. ''This is a campaign that's still trying to solidify its party and its base.''</p>
        <p>In his remarks at the Sierra Club event, Mr. Gore said he had been ahead of his time in understanding environmental problems, having learned about the dangers of pesticides and soil erosion as a boy on his father's Tennessee farm, and about global warming as a college student. In those days, Mr. Gore said, ''if you believed in global warming, people thought you were part of the flat earth society.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
