<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuel Cells: Energy Partners at Odds</title>
    <meta content="09ENER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1190400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookhaven National Laboratory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Plug Power Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Keyspan Energy Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotsalas, Valerie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DB153FF93AA35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuel Cells: Energy Partners at Odds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotsalas, Valerie</byline>
      <dateline>UPTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Sec Bill Richardson recently appeared at Brookhaven National Laboratory to announce joint venture between his department, Long Island Power Authority and Plug Power Inc, manufacturer of fuel cells, to bring cleaner energy technology to Island; Richardson says fuel cell technology, turning natural gas directly into electricity, promises to be cheaper and sounder environmentally; KeySpan Energy, which owns plants that provide electricity to LIPA customers, has announced its own fuel cell program, and is claiming exclusive rights to provide fuel cells on Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was something about the white canopy covering the rows of metal folding chairs -- and about seeing Christie Brinkley perched on one of those chairs -- that lifted the drab surroundings at the Brookhaven National Laboratory into the surreal.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brinkley and her husband, the architect Peter Cook, who are East End homeowners and active environmentalists, recently joined politicians, engineers and reporters to hear Energy Secretary Bill Richardson introduce a cleaner energy technology that seems to have pitted two energy partners against each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was something about the white canopy covering the rows of metal folding chairs -- and about seeing Christie Brinkley perched on one of those chairs -- that lifted the drab surroundings at the Brookhaven National Laboratory into the surreal.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brinkley and her husband, the architect Peter Cook, who are East End homeowners and active environmentalists, recently joined politicians, engineers and reporters to hear Energy Secretary Bill Richardson introduce a cleaner energy technology that seems to have pitted two energy partners against each other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson was joined by Richard M. Kessel, chairman of the Long Island Power Authority, to announce a joint venture between his department, LIPA and a manufacturer, Plug Power Inc., to bring fuel cells to the Island.</p>
        <p>''The rise of heating oil and gas prices has provided the nation with a real challenge,'' Secretary Richardson said. ''This fuel cell technology offers such promise: turning natural gas directly into electricity.''</p>
        <p>Fuel cells are fed a constant supply of natural gas, which is converted to electricity in a chemical process with no combustion. The cells create little pollution: a relatively small amount of carbon dioxide. The major byproducts are water and heat, which can be used for heating.</p>
        <p>A seven-kilowatt fuel cell will power the average home and provide enough heat to keep it warm in winter. Three cells have been installed at a B.N.L. laboratory building in a trial, and tests are planned at the Merchant Marine Academy in Kings Point, Hofstra University in Hempstead and the State University of New York at Stony Brook.</p>
        <p>''We have to have a variety in our engineering mix so that we're not dependent on oil and fossil fuels,'' Mr. Kessel said.</p>
        <p>But life is rarely that simple, as any visitor will learn at the small model of a fuel cell in the Hicksville offices of KeySpan Energy. KeySpan owns the plants that provide electricity to LIPA customers; LIPA maintains the transmission lines.</p>
        <p>More than a week before the Brookhaven ceremony, KeySpan announced its own fuel cell program, with one cell to be installed in late summer at the New York Institute of Technology in Westbury. This cell is also made by Plug Power, of Latham, N.Y., and distributed by GE MicroGen.</p>
        <p>Now KeySpan is claiming exclusive rights to provide fuel cells on the Island.</p>
        <p>''We have an agreement with GE that gives us the opportunity to test 30 of their units on Long Island,'' said David Manning, senior vice president of KeySpan Energy. ''By the end of that testing cycle, we have the right to become the exclusive utility provider of these units.''</p>
        <p>But LIPA also believes it can win an exclusive agreement to distribute the cells after it tests six of the units.</p>
        <p>''We do have an agreement with GE MicroGen for the testing of prototype fuel cell units, and that agreement does contain the possibility of an exclusive commercial relationship in the future,'' said Bert J. Cunningham, LIPA's vice president for communications. He added that any agreement would require approval by the utility's board and the state comptroller.</p>
        <p>Deepening the confusion, GE MicroGen, whose brand name is on the cells, denies having an exclusive agreement with either company.</p>
        <p>''Essentially, what KeySpan has is an agreement to test fuel cell systems,'' said GE MicroGen's president, Barry Glickman. ''During the time they're testing equipment, KeySpan and GE MicroGen will continue discussing KeySpan's role in distributing fuel cell systems. It is similar to the agreement contemplated with LIPA.''</p>
        <p>Two things are at stake: local control of a technology that may replace central power plants and move the source of electricity directly into the home, and the profits that could come from such control.</p>
        <p>While KeySpan pipelines would still be needed to feed household cells with natural gas or some other fuel, the cells themselves are much more reliable than power lines. The efficiency of the cells is also much higher than the turbine-powered plants that supply power now.</p>
        <p>''Our initial unit produces electricity only, so we're not capturing the excess heat, so it operates at only 40 percent efficiency,'' said Plug Power's president and chief executive, Gary Mittleman. ''When combined with a furnace and water heater, we're looking at 80 to 90 percent efficiency. Nowadays, power plants operate at 30 to 50 percent efficiency, but the heat escapes. We can capture that waste heat and put it to use.''</p>
        <p>There is wide agreement that the biggest obstacle to the cells is economic rather than technical. The cost of one seven-kilowatt cell is $7,000 to $10,000, a considerable amount even when weighed against increased efficiency and higher reliability. Mr. Mittleman said that in the next few years, Plug Power expects to bring the cost under $5,000. The key, he added, is mass production, a goal that has not yet been reached.</p>
        <p>Still, the increased demand for power and the recently highlighted dependency on foreign oil have created an urgency for alternative fuel sources. The reliability of a cell installed directly in the home is also appealing.</p>
        <p>Last winter, a power failure in New York City exposed the fallibility of backup generators in hospitals and other institutions. At Columbia Presbyterian Hospital, for example, AIDS research experiments were lost when the hospital lost power.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups like Standing for Truth About Radiation, which has rallied to shut down nuclear research reactors at Brookhaven, are pleased with the fuel cell trials, which explains the presence of Ms. Brinkley and Mr. Cook at Mr. Richardson's ceremony: They are members of STAR.</p>
        <p>''The future is now,'' Ms. Brinkley said from her folding chair. ''It's here. This is a cure for energy needs and for a clean environment for future generations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
