<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bewitching Barks, Huggable Trunks</title>
    <meta content="17CUT.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1256178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyle, Eileen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDA163EF934A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bewitching Barks, Huggable Trunks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Raver Cuttings column in appreciation of variegated tree barks, best seen on winter walks; Eileen Boyle of New York Botanical Garden describes different species; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I GET the same secret pleasure out of winter walks as I do getting up before anyone else in the morning. No one knows how good this is, I say to myself, and I hope it stays that way. There's an openness to the landscape after the leaves fall and the vines die back. You notice the architecture of the place as a whole: the dark gray outcroppings of schist, for example, as it courses through the woods; the tall mastlike trunks of poplars and oaks; how the land rolls.</p>
        <p>And it's an excellent time to look at the architecture of the trees themselves, whether they have single or multiple trunks, if they hold their branches aloft or arching downward, what kinds of catkins or seedpods dangle like ornaments, what their bark looks like on a rosy dawn or in the golden light of the setting sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I GET the same secret pleasure out of winter walks as I do getting up before anyone else in the morning. No one knows how good this is, I say to myself, and I hope it stays that way. There's an openness to the landscape after the leaves fall and the vines die back. You notice the architecture of the place as a whole: the dark gray outcroppings of schist, for example, as it courses through the woods; the tall mastlike trunks of poplars and oaks; how the land rolls.</p>
        <p>And it's an excellent time to look at the architecture of the trees themselves, whether they have single or multiple trunks, if they hold their branches aloft or arching downward, what kinds of catkins or seedpods dangle like ornaments, what their bark looks like on a rosy dawn or in the golden light of the setting sun.</p>
        <p>''Flowers come and go, and so do the leaves, but bark is sort of eternal,'' said Eileen Boyle, the director of horticulture at the New York Botanical Garden.</p>
        <p>The self-proclaimed barkophile was showing me some of her favorite trees in the bark department one recent chilly day in the garden. We worshiped first in the grove of six Tanyosho pines (Pinus densiflora Umbraculifera), whose multi stemmed trunks were flaming orange-red in the late afternoon light. These trees, planted in 1908, have a spreading form, their green needles and little cones held high up in the branches like a big generous umbrella. But it's the bark that entrances: big scaly pieces, like gold-embossed paper, peeling away to reveal smooth wood in shades of yellow, green and deep orange, like an aerial view of a tropical river delta. One tree, unbelievably, had eight trunks.</p>
        <p>''But don't think your tree will look like these when they're young,'' Ms. Boyle warned. The first 20 years, they're just shrubby little pine trees. And that shimmering, exfoliating bark comes only with age, as the tree expands from within.</p>
        <p>''It reminds me of the Incredible Hulk bursting out of his shirt,'' Ms. Boyle said. ''A tree grows up and down, but it also grows toward the inside and toward the outside, which is what makes it push out of its bark, which is like its skin.''</p>
        <p>Another venerable specimen grows behind this grove: the lacebark pine, Pinus bungeana, whose bark looks like a jigsaw puzzle of amoeba shapes in gray, ivory, olive and bronze. Really ancient trees in China turn bone-white and are planted near temples and in other sacred sites.</p>
        <p>Farther on, across from the conservatory, is a striking paperbark maple, Acer griseum, which, as Ms. Boyle says, has the Cadillac of bark.  ''It's like a copper tea kettle in this light,'' she said, as we stared at its exfoliating bark, which gleamed in multiple shades of bronze, deep orange, eggplant, peach and olive.</p>
        <p>On toward a yellow birch, we were stopped dead in our tracks by a massed planting of winterberry holly (Ilex verticillata), whose clusters of Chinese red berries were in elegant contrast to their gray-black stems. It was like a woman of style choosing just the right stockings for the dress.</p>
        <p>The yellow birch (Betula alleghaniensis) is a huge granddaddy of a tree, its fat trunk fanning out into four trunklike branches that spread a good 60 feet across. Its slate-gray bark is a patchwork of exfoliating papery sheaves, riddled with horizontal rows of little pin-size holes.</p>
        <p>''Those are the lenticels for the exchange of gases,'' Ms. Boyle said. ''That's how the tree lets oxygen in and carbon dioxide out.''</p>
        <p>A native witch hazel, Hamamelis virginiana, was blooming nearby, and I noticed its gracefully spreading branches with their smooth, silver-gray bark and the little ribbonlike yellow flowers, which are fragrant on a sunny day.</p>
        <p>Stewartia pseudocamellia is another knockout. A small graceful tree, suitable for a small garden, it has multiple trunks, which form a vaselike shape, and its smooth bark is like pink satin. Its camellialike white flowers bloom in July and August, and in winter, the split seedpods dangle from bare branches.</p>
        <p>Another day, I happened upon Todd Forrest, the garden's curator of woody plants. He showed off his favorite tree, a 300-year-old oak, which soars over the administration building. ''I've measured the trunk, which is 53 inches in diameter,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''You can tell it grew for a long time in the open.'' Its swirling branches, 60 feet across, were the tip-off. Trees in the forest can't stretch out like that. Its corky bark is thick and platy, as botanists say, and I hugged it for a minute. We need more big trees in our lives.</p>
        <p>Tall persimmon trees (Diospyros virginiana) also grow here, and their checkered bark, so like alligator skin, is just one more reason to grow this American beauty, which produces soft orange fruit, and yellow to bronze leaves in the fall.</p>
        <p>''Do you like beech trees?'' Mr. Forrest asked as we passed a great old beech with gray elephantine skin. Its branches must have spanned 80 feet. ''If you like beech bark but don't have room, yellow wood, Cladrastis lutea, is a beautiful tree.'' We stopped by a graceful little tree with a low trunk that quickly spread into five uplifted trunks, its bark the same dove gray as the beech. This tree blooms in June, with fragrant wisterialike flowers.</p>
        <p>We headed to the Montgomery collection to see the grove of dawn redwoods, 11 soaring metasequoias, aglow in the late afternoon light as the sun hit their rust-colored trunks and golden needles, which shed in the fall. They must have been 80 feet tall.  ''You'd have to have a lot of space to plant a grove of them,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''Well, you could plant three,'' Mr. Forrest said. ''They grow like weeds.'' And to think this tree was thought extinct until 1945, when it was found growing happily in China.</p>
        <p>So see, there are a lot more things going on in this garden than the celebrated miniature train show at the conservatory. And these trees are not just standing still. They're growing. They're bursting out of their skins. So keep an eye on them.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
