<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trail Leads to a Transformed State</title>
    <meta content="Y15MIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1176711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: MICHIGAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDE1531F936A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trail Leads to a Transformed State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>TROY, Mich., Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New economy, in which auto workers wear white collars, has generated new electorate in Michigan whose party affiliations are loose and whose votes are hard to predict; new voters have changed state's politics in recent years, and could be crucial in determining who wins Republican presidential primary on February 22; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The popular perception that Michigan elections are still dominated by legions of auto workers toting lunch pails is as dated as a Chevrolet Citation.</p>
        <p>Here, as in New Hampshire and South Carolina, a new economy, in which auto workers wear white collars, has generated a new electorate, whose party affiliations are loose and whose votes are hard to predict. Those voters have already helped change Michigan politics in recent years, and, according to the latest polls, they could be crucial in determining who wins the state's Republican presidential primary on Tuesday of next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The popular perception that Michigan elections are still dominated by legions of auto workers toting lunch pails is as dated as a Chevrolet Citation.</p>
        <p>Here, as in New Hampshire and South Carolina, a new economy, in which auto workers wear white collars, has generated a new electorate, whose party affiliations are loose and whose votes are hard to predict. Those voters have already helped change Michigan politics in recent years, and, according to the latest polls, they could be crucial in determining who wins the state's Republican presidential primary on Tuesday of next week.</p>
        <p>The new, high-tech professionals are people like Joel Gibson, a 26-year-old car-engine software programmer whose father, grandfather and great-grandmother were all auto factory workers and staunch Democrats.</p>
        <p>''I lean Republican, but I like to look at each individual candidate,'' said Mr. Gibson, who is taken with  former Senator Bill Bradley and Senator John McCain.</p>
        <p>The new workers tend to vote Republican in state and local elections, but they have proved unpredictable in contests for national office.</p>
        <p>''They may identify themselves as Republicans, but when they pull that curtain, the independent streak kicks in, much to my chagrin,'' said one Republican officeholder, L. Brooks Patterson, the Oakland County executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson knows those voters well, because it is here in Oakland County, in Detroit's northwestern suburbs, that they tend to make their homes. Macomb County, which lies along Oakland's eastern boundary  and is characterized by strip malls and small ranch-style houses, remains the home of the so-called Reagan Democrats -- union workers attracted to the Republicans' appeal to traditional values. But Oakland County has dozens of auto engineering centers that have sprung up in rows of new, tinted-glass office towers as starkly anonymous as any in Silicon Valley, and tens of thousands of the new workers live here.</p>
        <p>Dotted with small lakes surrounded by beautiful homes, crisscrossed by freeways increasingly lined by those engineering centers, Oakland County has 1.2 million people to Macomb's 770,000, and is growing twice as fast.</p>
        <p>''Oakland is where many of these people live, and is going to be a battleground going into the future,'' said Jennifer Granholm, a Democrat who won election as state attorney general in 1998, partly by doing well in the county.</p>
        <p>Ms. Granholm is a fairly recent arrival, having grown up in San Francisco. Other recent arrivals, including many engineers, have more than offset the constant stream of retirees moving south and have raised the state's population to almost 10 million, from 9.3 million in 1990.</p>
        <p>Politicians and pollsters from across the political spectrum describe the new workers similarly:  conservative on economic issues, particularly in their skepticism about government regulation, but moderate on social policy. They have helped Republicans take control of both houses of the Legislature as well as the governor's mansion.</p>
        <p>But they have also been willing to vote for some Democrats in national elections: Bill Clinton beat former Senator Bob Dole in Oakland County in 1996, and nearly beat President George Bush here in 1992. That inclination has increasingly made them the swing voters in a state that is among the nation's most evenly divided between Democrats and Republicans.</p>
        <p>''They're the ones who come across and vote for the Democrats who win in Michigan,'' said Robert Teeter, a Republican pollster in Ann Arbor.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Macomb County, with its Reagan Democrats, was once regarded as the capital of Michigan's swing voter. But the changing face of the work force has brought a changing face to the electorate. The number of unionized industrial workers as a proportion of all voters in the state has dropped by nearly half in  the last two decades, to between 6 and 9 percent, pollsters say.</p>
        <p>Auto production remains the state's dominant industry, but auto makers and auto parts companies are changing the way they do business. For instance, while much of the actual manufacturing has either been automated or moved to Southern states and overseas, to take advantage of lower wages elsewhere,  all but 8 of the nation's 200 auto parts engineering centers are now in Michigan instead of being scattered across the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The nation's long economic expansion has been particularly good to the highly cyclical auto industry, like a prolonged return to the early 1960's, before auto makers' profits were crippled by foreign competition and, arguably, government safety and environmental regulations. The arts are flourishing in Detroit, with the opening of a cavernous opera house and the restoration of a magnificent symphony hall. Housing prices have been rising faster across this metropolitan area than almost anywhere else in the country.</p>
        <p>Further, an acute shortage of skilled labor has kept Michigan's unemployment rate below the national average since 1995. The state's rate was just 3.6 percent in December, and the state government plans to start spending as much money advertising for engineers to move here from other states as it previously spent persuading businesses to locate here.</p>
        <p>Michigan's shift in employment toward white-collar jobs has occurred on a massive scale. The number of unionized auto workers in Michigan has plunged to fewer than 250,000 now from 479,000 in 1980. But total employment in the auto industry, the state says, has only inched down, to 471,000 from 507,000 two decades ago, and actually grew in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>In Pontiac, several miles west of here, General Motors recently gutted and remodeled two assembly plants with the combined floor space of the Empire State Building, turning them into offices and laboratories for 8,500 engineers. G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler can afford such grandiose undertakings: they were the world's three largest companies in 1998, in terms of sales and share of global economic output.</p>
        <p>A statewide poll by The Detroit Free Press a week ago found that in the race for the Republican primary next week -- the Democrats are holding presidential nominating caucuses in March -- Senator McCain and Gov. George W. Bush were evenly matched if Democrats and independents voted in fairly large numbers, while Governor Bush was ahead among Republicans alone.</p>
        <p>The poll also showed that Senator McCain enjoyed a sizable advantage in Macomb County, partly because of  Reagan Democrats, while Governor Bush commanded strong support in western Michigan, where abortion opponents are numerous and active and have been leery of the senator. Oakland County was a tossup if Democrats and independents were included, while Governor Bush prevailed if only Republicans were counted.</p>
        <p>One issue on which Mr. Bush could ultimately prove vulnerable here is government regulation. Michigan Republicans regularly deride Vice President Al Gore for saying in his book, ''Earth in the Balance,'' that the internal combustion engine's contribution to global warming is ''a mortal threat to the security of every nation that is more deadly than that of any military enemy we are ever again likely to confront.'' The Republicans are eager to attack Mr. Gore relentlessly on the issue should he win the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>But whether they would be much able to do so with Mr. Bush as the Republican nominee is uncertain.  Criticized by environmentalists in New England television advertisements this autumn, Mr. Bush announced in New Hampshire in December that he had asked Texas regulators to consider adopting California's new auto pollution rules, which are stricter than the federal government's and are particularly tough on high-profit sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks.</p>
        <p>The regulators held hearings on the idea during the week of the New Hampshire primary, and the conservative Detroit News sent a reporter to Texas to cover them. The resulting article emphasized that G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler sold 90 percent of Texas' sport utilities and pickup trucks, and ran under a big headline that said, ''Bush Cleanup Plan to Cut Truck Sales.''</p>
        <p>But beyond environmental regulation lies the broader landscape of a  changing work force and changing politics here. Dwayne F. Davidson, a 41-year-old G.M. manager of computer-aided design, is a Republican leaning toward Governor Bush, trusting him to keep government small. Mr. Davidson agrees on few political issues with his father, a lifelong Democrat who spent 30 years welding car body panels in the same giant building in Pontiac where the son now oversees the design of sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks.</p>
        <p>''I've hung out with Republicans, I golf with Republicans,'' Mr. Davidson said. ''It has kind of rubbed off.''  THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: MICHIGAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
