<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="22OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uranus (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uranus (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D6113EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Observatory column on measuing sea levels at time of earth's ice age, on Shakespearean names for recently discovered moons of Uranus and on safe disposal of old pressure-treated wood (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ice Cubes and Ice Ages</p>
        <p>A tray of ice cubes is something of a closed system. Left on the kitchen counter on a hot summer day, the ice turns to liquid water. Put back in the freezer, the liquid water turns back to ice. But the number of water molecules in the tray remains more or less constant (unless, of course, a couple of cubes are plopped into a drink).</p>
        <p>This basic fact is a key to understanding how icy the earth got in the last ice age 200 centuries ago. As the earth got colder, the ice thickened and spread, with a corresponding drop in the amount of water in the oceans. While how far the ice sheet extended is fairly well known, a reliable measurement of the sea level at that time would allow calculation of just how thick it got, and when.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ice Cubes and Ice Ages</p>
        <p>A tray of ice cubes is something of a closed system. Left on the kitchen counter on a hot summer day, the ice turns to liquid water. Put back in the freezer, the liquid water turns back to ice. But the number of water molecules in the tray remains more or less constant (unless, of course, a couple of cubes are plopped into a drink).</p>
        <p>This basic fact is a key to understanding how icy the earth got in the last ice age 200 centuries ago. As the earth got colder, the ice thickened and spread, with a corresponding drop in the amount of water in the oceans. While how far the ice sheet extended is fairly well known, a reliable measurement of the sea level at that time would allow calculation of just how thick it got, and when.</p>
        <p>Now researchers from the Australian National University in Canberra, analyzing sediment cores from an area off the continent's northern coast that was partly exposed back then, have made what is considered the first such reliable measurement. The sea level, they report in the journal Nature, reached its low point of 425 to 440 feet below the present level from about 22,000 to 19,000 years ago. That means that the volume of land-based ice at the time was at its maximum -- roughly 12 million cubic miles more ice than exists now.</p>
        <p>While the research does not show how all that ice was distributed, it does indicate that the ice sheets reached some level of equilibrium and stability. But the data also show that 19,000 years ago, the ice lost its stability rather quickly, perhaps because of major climate change. About 10 percent of the ice melted away in just a few hundred years.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare in the Sky</p>
        <p>Astronomers can get as excited as first-time parents when they discover new objects in the solar system. It just takes a lot longer to name them. The International Astronomical Union this month approved names for several moons of Uranus, some of which were discovered in 1997. The union is the international authority for names, and only offers approvals every three years.</p>
        <p>Unlike moons of other planets, which are named for characters from classical mythology, most of the names from Uranus's moons have been taken from Shakespeare. The new names continue this tradition, with Caliban, Prospero and Stephano, among others, joining Ariel, Oberon, Titania and others in the cast.</p>
        <p>The astronomical union also approved names for various other bodies and features in the solar system, including Petit-Prince for the tiny satellite orbiting the asteroid Eugenia and Lolita, Cupid, Don Quixote and other love-struck names for features on Eros, the asteroid that is currently being studied by the Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous spacecraft. The group also approved the naming of a 60-mile-wide crater on Mars for Carl Sagan.</p>
        <p>Arsenic and Old Wood</p>
        <p>The use of pressure-treated lumber for decks, playground equipment and other structures has become widespread, and with good reason. The chemicals added to the lumber, often chromated copper arsenate, or C.C.A., help it withstand the effects of insects and fungi far longer than untreated wood.</p>
        <p>But C.C.A. contains, among other things, chromium and arsenic, both of which are toxic. So one concern is what happens when old pressure-treated wood is disposed of. Manufacturers warn against burning it, but undoubtedly some old wood makes its way to incinerators where the arsenic, in particular, forms very small particles that may not be trapped by pollution control equipment.</p>
        <p>Now, researchers at the University of Florida say they have come up with a technique that may make the incineration of treated lumber less of a problem. By introducing limestone into the incineration process, the researchers say, the arsenic forms much larger particles, which wind up in waste ash.</p>
        <p>The researchers note that their work is only in the laboratory phase, and much more research must be done.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
