<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q &amp; A/Daniel C. Esty; Long-Term Optimist for the Environment</title>
    <meta content="13QNA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Esty, Daniel C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFD6163FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q &amp; A/Daniel C. Esty; Long-Term Optimist for the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN BISBORT</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yale Center for Environmental Law and Policy director Daniel C Esty answers questions on Pilot Enviromental Sustainability Index, which is meant to measure ability of economies to achieve environmentally sustainable development; photo (Q&amp;A column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DANIEL C. ESTY, director of the Yale Center for Environmental Law and Policy, thinks the environment will not be taken seriously around the world, until it is given a number. ''What is important gets measured,'' Mr. Esty said, but that kind of analytical approach is rarely focused on the natural world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Esty proposed to change all that to include the environment in the equation and the result is called the Pilot Environmental Sustainability Index. The purpose of the index, which grew out of a February workshop at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, is to ''measure the ability of economies to achieve environmentally sustainable development,'' Mr. Esty said. In other words, it is a report card on the state of the environment in a number of countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DANIEL C. ESTY, director of the Yale Center for Environmental Law and Policy, thinks the environment will not be taken seriously around the world, until it is given a number. ''What is important gets measured,'' Mr. Esty said, but that kind of analytical approach is rarely focused on the natural world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Esty proposed to change all that to include the environment in the equation and the result is called the Pilot Environmental Sustainability Index. The purpose of the index, which grew out of a February workshop at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, is to ''measure the ability of economies to achieve environmentally sustainable development,'' Mr. Esty said. In other words, it is a report card on the state of the environment in a number of countries.</p>
        <p>The numbers he has crunched, obtained through the Center for International Earth Science Information Network at Columbia University, have already generated the sort of heated but healthy dialogue he had anticipated.</p>
        <p>To create the index, Mr. Esty, his Yale colleagues, and members of the World Economic Forum's Global Leaders of Tomorrow (a select group of promising young people who, in the past, have included Bill Gates, the Treasury Secretary Larry Summers and Mr. Esty), took data from 57 countries and looked at 65 variables. The countries who were graded and then ranked were those for which reliable data existed. .</p>
        <p>The resultis what Mr. Esty calls ''something like a batting average or cumulative grade- point average.''</p>
        <p>The index hasn't been perfected, which is why it's a ''pilot,'' said Mr. Esty, who plans to expand the survey next year to 100 countries.</p>
        <p>A one-time administrator at the Environmental Protection Agency, Mr. Esty has put his global perspective to work locally, having served on Cheshire's Planning and Zoning Commission for five years. Describing s himself as a ''short-term pessimist but long-term optimist,'' he said he was committed to the long haul of reversing the havoc of the ''experiment'' on the earth. Mr. Esty was interviewed at his New Haven office. Here are excerpts from that conversation.</p>
        <p>Q.  Your index has the United States ranked 16th. Why isn't it closer to the top?</p>
        <p>A. If there was a direct correlation between economic wealth and environmental health, the U.S. would be tops in both. A significant percentage of reaction is ''Oh my goodness, the U.S. is doing so poorly, what's going on?'' But there's another reaction, particularly from Europeans who perceive us as foot-dragging on critical issues like climate change, that we are ranked as high as we are. Both myths get burst. The U.S. is riding high and everything is fine is not true, and this puts numbers to that reality. But, also the perception that the U.S. is abominable is also unveiled as not true.</p>
        <p>Q. Were there any surprises in the results things you never suspected?</p>
        <p>A. The biggest single surprise is how high Russia ranks at 22. We know their performance is terrible, and yet what has saved them is that they have a vast open space in Siberia. So that on certain criteria they rank high simply as a function of having Siberia. But if one looked at pollution control in Russia's cities, it's horrible. They rank at the bottom. The opposite is true in Singapore, a country we know is sophisticated in its environmental management. But Singapore is a city state that sits at the edge of sustainability on a number of issues. It has no place to put garbage, it doesn't have adequate water, it's up against critical limits. So, even excellent management does not produce a high score on the index.</p>
        <p>Q. Can't a number of these countries with low scores be said to have  inherited their problems, in that much of the worldwide environmental awareness rose only after the damage was done?</p>
        <p>A. Some countries are still on the industrialized trajectory. One wants to get to China, Thailand, Vietnam, before they deepen their hole. One chart in the index plots competitiveness against environmental performance and what you see is that there is no trade-off; countries doing well economically take necessary environmental steps. But the chart also shows, clearly, that you don't get rich by getting dirty. That whole theory of development is strongly disproved.</p>
        <p>Look at Sweden and Belgium. They're roughly the same on competitiveness, but look how much better Sweden does than Belgium on the environment. Given an equal economic success, a country can do different things to their environment. Belgium is riddled with dioxins, and it shows up on the index. Sweden is fifth, Belgium 23rd, below Russia.</p>
        <p>Q. Isn't this is one of the more optimistic aspects of the index, that it is an ongoing thing?</p>
        <p>A. Exactly. The truth is that as we move forward this can only improve, because we discard shaky data sets and replace them with more systematically gathered data. And we broaden the number of countries included as these countries develop the data we need. One of the positive things that came out of this were the number of countries that called, mailed, or e-mailed, saying ''Why didn't you include us?'' Our answer was simple: ''We just don't have enough data from you.'' People are upset about being ranked low but it's worse to not be ranked at all, because it takes you off the list of countries taken seriously.</p>
        <p>Q. Doesn't it sometimes feel like the human genome project of the environment?</p>
        <p>A. It's very complex, and there's a tendency in politics and media to simplify. We're saying go the other way, accept the complexity. This index only begins to tell the story. The question it doesn't answer, yet, is ''which policies matter?''</p>
        <p>Q. What is the reaction to the index from business leaders around the world?</p>
        <p>A. We know that a significant percent of business community takes the environment seriously. For those who do, the index is not a surprise. The brighter companies today understand that investing in the environment does not undermine their economic position. One of the things we hope to do with this index is to show that those old attitudes are not in touch with the current wisdom about how you want to promote economic development.</p>
        <p>Think about what the developing countries' representatives were saying at the World Trade Organization meeting in Seattle: ''Don't hold us to environmental standards, it'll hold us back.'' That's based on old, disproved economic misconceptions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
