<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>America in the World</title>
    <meta content="07MON1$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D8133CF934A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>America in the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial in series, Campaign 2000, on issues in 2000 presidential campaign, focuses on foreign policy; says there should be vigorous debate on America's role in world, starting with assessment of critical national interests; argues that less than decade after demise of Soviet Union, US is military and economic colossus that seems uncertain about its role and perplexed by changing array of threats it faces (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are heady yet baffling times for the world's sole superpower. Less than a decade after the demise of the Soviet Union, the United States is a military and economic colossus. No nation in history has possessed the wealth, military might or technological edge over its rivals that America has today. Yet as the presidential campaign enters its final months, the country seems uncertain about its role and perplexed by the changing array of threats that it faces. There should be vigorous debate about these matters in the days ahead, starting with an assessment of America's critical national interests.</p>
        <p>There are clear and important differences between Gov. George W. Bush and and Vice President Al Gore on Russia, China, missile defenses and other pressing issues. We intend to return to some of these matters as the campaign unfolds. But specific policies cannot be developed or evaluated in isolation. They should flow from principles that reflect the nation's core values and interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These are heady yet baffling times for the world's sole superpower. Less than a decade after the demise of the Soviet Union, the United States is a military and economic colossus. No nation in history has possessed the wealth, military might or technological edge over its rivals that America has today. Yet as the presidential campaign enters its final months, the country seems uncertain about its role and perplexed by the changing array of threats that it faces. There should be vigorous debate about these matters in the days ahead, starting with an assessment of America's critical national interests.</p>
        <p>There are clear and important differences between Gov. George W. Bush and and Vice President Al Gore on Russia, China, missile defenses and other pressing issues. We intend to return to some of these matters as the campaign unfolds. But specific policies cannot be developed or evaluated in isolation. They should flow from principles that reflect the nation's core values and interests.</p>
        <p>It is harder today than during the cold war to define American interests and to determine how best to defend them. Contamination of the world's air and water or a currency crisis in Asia can threaten American security as much as a fleet of Russian bombers. The free flow of information across national borders may be a more potent force for advancing democracy than dispatch of American aircraft carriers to a distant sea.</p>
        <p>Still, some core national interests remain unchanged. The physical defense of America's territory, people and economic lifelines is paramount. The Pentagon can safely eliminate thousands of nuclear weapons left over from the cold war, but must maintain enough to discourage attack. America also needs highly trained and mobile military forces, adequately paid and equipped with advanced weaponry. Washington must also guard against international terrorist groups. Effective intelligence gathering is an essential first line of defense. Washington should provide adequate financing for these purposes, but spending must be based on realistic needs, not inflated threat assessments or parochial Congressional interests.</p>
        <p>In the absence of a powerful enemy like the Soviet Union, the country has found itself with few established guidelines to decide when military intervention abroad is warranted. Clearly, self-defense and the protection of allies and economic lifelines are reasons to use force, as Washington did when oil supplies were endangered by the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>But as recent upheavals in Africa and the Balkans have shown, ethnic conflicts can escalate to imperil the stability of an entire region, and genocidal attacks on civilians sometimes can be stopped only by outside force. Washington should consider intervening in such conflicts if it is clear that force can make a difference and sufficient military resources are available to assure success, the case in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>As the last decades of the 20th century showed, the defense of American security is no longer primarily defined by sending military forces into combat. The United States is uniquely suited to encourage peacemaking in troubled regions like the Middle East. President Clinton has used American influence constructively in the Middle East and Northern Ireland, and his successor should continue the work he has begun. It may also be appropriate, as in Bosnia, to send American troops overseas to serve as peacekeepers once warring parties have laid down their arms and agreed to a peace accord.</p>
        <p>Today, the country's security and prosperity are connected to the global movement of goods, capital, information and people. Keeping these channels of commerce and technology open can be as important as defending a foreign border. Washington should advance these interests through trade agreements that lower barriers to imports and investment. But the preservation of a stable global economic order, a vital American interest, cannot be accomplished without spreading prosperity's benefits more fairly. Three billion people, or half the world's population, live on less than $2 a day. Bettering their lives requires more effective governance, increased private investment and expanded access to education and health care.</p>
        <p>America also makes its own democracy more secure by promoting democracy elsewhere. The evolution of Russia and China into enduring democratic states would make the world a far safer place and erase two of the greatest potential threats to American security. Encouraging democracy and the rule of law in these nations should be among the primary goals of the next president.</p>
        <p>Protecting health and the environment are central American interests. Epidemics and climate change know no borders. Strong environmental treaties and efforts to make medicines more widely available must be a high priority for Washington.</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore engage foreign policy, they should spell out their thoughts about these broad national interests. Mr. Bush has so far taken the more creative approach to the question of nuclear weapons reductions. Mr. Gore has been more forward looking on environmental issues and has shown a more nuanced appreciation of the role American troops could play in halting regional conflicts. But the debate between them has not moved much beyond rhetorical flourishes. Voters deserve a serious discussion of how this country's power should be used to advance the global interests of its people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
