<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABC's Earth Day Special Culls Hour's Lowest Rating</title>
    <meta content="24LEO.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nielsen Media Research</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Planet Earth 2000 (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DC1430F937A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABC's Earth Day Special Culls Hour's Lowest Rating</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Premliminary Nielsen Media Research data show Planet Earth 2000, ABC Earth Day special that included controversial Leonardo DiCaprio interview with Pres Clinton, came in last in ratings among its major network competitors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As one of Hollywood's biggest stars, Leonardo DiCaprio is used to being in projects that draw a lot of attention.</p>
        <p>He probably was not expecting that ''Planet Earth 2000,'' the hourlong ABC Earth Day special in which he participated, would garner similar attention, and he was right.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As one of Hollywood's biggest stars, Leonardo DiCaprio is used to being in projects that draw a lot of attention.</p>
        <p>He probably was not expecting that ''Planet Earth 2000,'' the hourlong ABC Earth Day special in which he participated, would garner similar attention, and he was right.</p>
        <p>Despite a spate of unintended preshow publicity surrounding his participation, the show did not qualify as a box office smash when it was broadcast at 8 p.m. on Saturday.</p>
        <p>According to preliminary Nielsen Media Research figures -- which are based on viewing in the 47 largest television markets and are subject to change -- the special came in last among its major network competitors. It was watched in an average of 3.6 million homes during its first half-hour. That number fell to 3.1 million during its second half-hour.</p>
        <p>Far more households tuned in to watch ''Early Edition'' on CBS (5.8 million), a repeat of ''Pretender'' on NBC (5.3 million) and two episodes of ''Cops'' on Fox (5.7 million). Each of those networks gained viewers as the hour progressed.</p>
        <p>ABC News executives said they were standing behind the program despite its ratings. ''We produced a special we are proud of,'' said Su-Lin Nichols, a spokeswoman for ABC News. She said the program would have a broader reach in May, when it would be distributed to 12,000 high schools and middle schools.</p>
        <p>In the days leading up to its airing, top ABC executives said they were less than satisfied with its production values. Its producers were still working on it as of Friday.</p>
        <p>The news division originally agreed to produce the special with Mr. DiCaprio -- chairman of the Earth Day 2000 celebration committee -- in an attempt to draw younger viewers, who have proved elusive for network news divisions. The program featured a production style similar to one often used on MTV, with sped-up video footage, sporadic camera angles and fast dance music. Mr. DiCaprio traded off with Elizabeth Vargas of ABC News in introducing segments about steps being taken to reduce pollution in Atlanta, the effects of global warming on the coral reefs in Florida and thinning ice in Alaska. The ABC correspondent Chris Cuomo, a friend of Mr. DiCaprio's, reported those segments.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiCaprio's involvement in the production, especially an interview he conducted with President Clinton, angered some ABC News staff members. It set off debate within the division over what level of celebrity participation is appropriate in a news program and caused embarrassment for David Westin, the president of ABC News.</p>
        <p>When he was first questioned about Mr. DiCaprio's role, Mr. Westin said the actor was not sent to the White House to interview the president. Rather, he said, Mr. DiCaprio was to be given a tour of the White House, which would focus on energy efficiencies there, and that it was only a possibility that the president would be present during that tour.</p>
        <p>The White House called his version of events inaccurate. Mr. Westin then confirmed that Mr. DiCaprio arrived at the White House with specific, written questions for the president. He said that he had not been given all of the facts from the outset.</p>
        <p>In the end, the segment showing Mr. DiCaprio's interview of the president lasted for 2 minutes, 40 seconds. Mr. DiCaprio, who had spoken with the president for about 20 minutes, seemed nervous as he lobbed questions at the president on whether the environment was as important to him as health care or education and whether the United States could act as a role model in environmental responsibility. Mr. Clinton answered yes to both questions.</p>
        <p>Although producers filmed him asking the same questions later that day -- out of the presence of the president so that he would seem calmer -- those retakes were not used, Ms. Nichols said.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiCaprio began his interview by telling the president that he was ''neither a politician, nor a journalist,'' but, rather, ''a concerned citizen.''</p>
        <p>Reaction to the program was muted yesterday. Many ABC staff members were apparently too busy covering the Elian Gonzalez story or enjoying the Easter holiday to watch it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
