<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6D7123AF930A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-20</p>
        <p>Russia to Sell Arms to Iran, Breaking Treaty's Limits  Russia has notified the Clinton administration that it intends to withdraw from a 1995 agreement negotiated by Vice President Al Gore limiting Russian sales of tanks and other conventional weapons to Iran, officials said. Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright has warned Foreign Minister Igor S. Ivanov that new sales of advanced conventional weaponry to Tehran could lead to American economic sanctions against Russia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Retaliatory Violence in Mideast  A powerful car bomb killed two Israelis and wounded scores of others during rush hour in the coastal city of Hadera. Prime Minister Ehud Barak pledged that Israel would get even for what he called a barbaric attack. Earlier, Israeli soldiers killed four Palestinians at a roadblock in southern Gaza that had been set up to ambush one of them, wanted for a previous attack.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-20</p>
        <p>Russia to Sell Arms to Iran, Breaking Treaty's Limits  Russia has notified the Clinton administration that it intends to withdraw from a 1995 agreement negotiated by Vice President Al Gore limiting Russian sales of tanks and other conventional weapons to Iran, officials said. Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright has warned Foreign Minister Igor S. Ivanov that new sales of advanced conventional weaponry to Tehran could lead to American economic sanctions against Russia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Retaliatory Violence in Mideast  A powerful car bomb killed two Israelis and wounded scores of others during rush hour in the coastal city of Hadera. Prime Minister Ehud Barak pledged that Israel would get even for what he called a barbaric attack. Earlier, Israeli soldiers killed four Palestinians at a roadblock in southern Gaza that had been set up to ambush one of them, wanted for a previous attack.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Yemen Names Cole Bombers  Yemen's prime minister said that investigators of the bombing of the United States destroyer Cole have identified the bombers as two Saudi Arabian citizens with Yemeni family roots who fought Soviet forces in Afghanistan. The two men have personal profiles that run closely parallel with that of Osama bin Laden, wanted by the F.B.I. on terrorism charges.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Interim Leader in Peru  Veteran legislator Valentin Paniagua was sworn in as interim president of Peru. So ended a decade of authoritarian rule by Alberto K. Fujimori that defeated two terrorist rebellions but failed to repair the country's endemic instability. The inauguration came after six months of extreme turmoil during which Mr. Fujimori struggled to hold on to power through corruption scandals, riots and a small military rebellion.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Conflict Warnings in Yugoslavia  Yugoslav authorities warned that the region could be facing the risk of a new war after a large bomb exploded in Pristina, half demolishing the home of the Serbian government's representative in Kosovo, killing one man and injuring several others.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A24-41</p>
        <p>Presidential Vote Dispute Enters Third Tangled Week  It was a day of intense legal and political jockeying, brinkmanship and drama, from South Florida to north Florida to Texas to Washington, as Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas struggled to settle their race for the White House and the nation entered its third week since Election Day without a president-elect. There was new turmoil as Miami-Dade County, the largest Florida Democratic enclave still recounting votes by hand, abruptly decided to stop, and a state court judge ordered election officials in Palm Beach County to expand their review of disputed ballots.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign urgently sought the intervention of the United States Supreme Court to stop what his lawyers called a capricious vote-counting process that ''now borders on anarchy.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Republican vice presidential nominee Dick Cheney suffered a mild heart attack. Mr. Bush said the hospitalization of Mr. Cheney for chest pains was a ''precautionary measure.'' Aides later said that Mr. Bush was unaware that the diagnosis was a heart attack when he made his remarks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Openly contemptuous of the Florida Supreme Court, senior Republican legislators in the state searched for a legislative stroke that would deliver the White House to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Florida Supreme Court ruling in favor of hand recounts in three Democratic counties was denounced by Republicans in Congress, with the House majority leader urging the Florida Legislature to step in.</p>
        <p>A33</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush sued election officials in 13 Florida counties for rejecting the absentee ballots of members of the military serving abroad. A36</p>
        <p>Nurse Could Face Execution  Prosecutors in Massachusetts say they will seek the death penalty if Kristen Gilbert, a former nurse accused of killing patients, is convicted. If they succeed, she will be the first woman executed by the federal government since 1953.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Giving Thanks For Getting There  Congestion was the order of the day across America as millions of Americans tried to get home to family and friends for Thanksgiving.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-14</p>
        <p>A New Yorker's Kindness Helps to Turn a Life Around  Raymond Lawrence, a homeless man, was reunited with his mother in October 1999 after being befriended by Vincent Jones, a bighearted New Yorker who passed Mr. Lawrence on the street daily. A year later he is still off the streets, going to Alcoholics Anonymous meetings and living in his mother's home in Portsmouth, Va. And his family says he has secured a hold on life that goes far beyond sobriety.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>Mountains of Cyberjunk  The average life span of a computer bought today is three years and shrinking, and the pace of computer obsolescence has created a backlog of equipment with nowhere to go. It has also raised questions about who is responsible for the expensive collection, transportation, dismantling and recycling of old computers. In 1998 alone, 20 million computers were taken out of service; only 2.3 million were recycled. If the right systems were in place, all obsolete computers could be reused or recycled, and governments and industry are trying to solve the problem.</p>
        <p>G1</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-18</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-18</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Fracas at Global Warming Talks  Protests at the talks in the Hague on a climate treaty reached a high pitch, with demonstrators climbing into the rafters of a central room, blockading doorways and splattering the top American negotiator with a cream pie.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>Renewed Looks at Quaker Oats  The collapse of Coca-Cola's $16 billion bid to acquire Quaker Oats prompted rival bidders to re-evaluate their acquisition strategies and aroused a discussion about the implications for Coke's chief executive, Douglas N. Daft. Danone of France, the maker of Evian bottled water, issued a statement signaling renewed interest in acquiring Quaker Oats and its most prized brand, Gatorade. Danone submitted an offer for Quaker Oats last week.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Markets Twitch Over Florida  Stocks resumed their broad slide in a session marked by sudden shifts in response to the legal battle over Florida's presidential vote, and weighed down by concern over the profits of technology companies. The Nasdaq composite fell 116.11 points, or 4 percent, its fifth straight loss and the 11th in 13 trading days since since the Friday before Election Day. Dow Jones industrial average fell 95.18 points, to 10,399.32.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Auto Plants to Be Idled  DaimlerChrysler and Ford said they would idle some North American plants next week as the automakers try to reduce the number of unsold cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A42-43</p>
        <p>Editorials: Reckless Republican rhetoric; the Thanksgiving call; politics of the teachers' contract.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E14  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E18  Crossword</p>
        <p>E18  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
