<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lavender Begins to Find New Areas to Conquer</title>
    <meta content="02CUT.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lavender</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DB1739F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lavender Begins to Find New Areas to Conquer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on various types of lavendar plants and growing techniques; photos (Cuttings column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE there's an up side to the climate change that spells warmer, drier weather for the East Coast: lavender.</p>
        <p>Everybody wants to grow sweeps of it in front of the beach house, the roses, the pool, the old chicken house. Even people with clay are growing it -- in sandy raised beds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE there's an up side to the climate change that spells warmer, drier weather for the East Coast: lavender.</p>
        <p>Everybody wants to grow sweeps of it in front of the beach house, the roses, the pool, the old chicken house. Even people with clay are growing it -- in sandy raised beds.</p>
        <p>''We always think of lavender as a Mediterranean plant, or something that would thrive in the California desert,'' said Fabienne Audette, the assistant director of horticulture at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx. ''New York used to be too cold and cloudy to sustain subtropical plants, but now, if we provide a little protection, the climate change is allowing us to grow them.''</p>
        <p>She did her master's thesis on the effects of water and pH on lavender, in greenhouse conditions and clay fields. ''Sandy soil and good drainage are key to growing lavender,'' said Ms. Audette, who was born in Switzerland, lived in southern France (where lavender grows in fields) and now gardens in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''The biggest difference between Mediterranean and American soil is that the Mediterranean has been cultivated for thousands of years,'' she said. ''The soil structure is very loose and tends to be more alkaline or neutral, and the nutrients have been leached out.''</p>
        <p>So if you have clay soil, grow lavender in raised beds, with plenty of organic matter. Plant in full sun, on high ground, on a south-facing slope. Some growers use mushroom compost to help protect plants from root rot. And if you live in a humid area, growing lavender in pots will improve air circulation. Go easy on nitrogen fertilizer, which will promote soft green growth, not flowers. Ms. Audette suggests mulching with a one-inch layer of white or light-colored sand, grit or gravel.</p>
        <p>The blooms range in color from white and pink to green to all shades of blue. The foliage can be from very silvery to gray blue or green.</p>
        <p>Ms. Audette found that lavender, like most desert plants, responds quickly to water. ''They are very tomentose or leathery, with little water,'' she said. ''Once they get it, the cells elongate and divide. The leaves are larger, the stems extended, with seven or eight whorls of flowers.''</p>
        <p>In the Mediterranean, plants may go three months without water, but as soon as there's a storm, they quickly take up as much as possible.</p>
        <p>Lavenders belong to the Labiatae family, which has square-stemmed plants like thyme and mint. The genus, Lavandula, contains 28 species, including L. angustifolia, commonly known as English lavender.</p>
        <p>The oldest description dates to A.D. 46, when Dioscorides described a plant called stoechas, used as a wine and medicinal herb. ''He found it on Stochade Island, which is now called Ile d'Hyeres on the Cote d'Azur,'' Ms. Audette said.</p>
        <p>In A.D. 76, Pliny described a plant called nard, which sounded like stoechas, but it came from India. ''The plant had a wonderful fragrance, and the Romans were so crazy about it for their baths, they depleted it,'' Ms. Audette said. ''So they went to stoechas and called it false nard.''</p>
        <p>Two species of lavender -- angustifoloia and latifolia -- have long been grown in southern Europe for perfume. And bees or other pollinators crossed these two species, producing a hybrid called lavandin, first discovered around 1850.</p>
        <p>''Because L. angustifolia and latifolia were so highly cultivated, a fungus came through Europe in the 1930's and wiped out the monocultures,'' Ms. Audette said. Then a farmer noticed one survivor: lavandin, which he started propagating.</p>
        <p>Lavandin is more disease-resistant than lavandula and produces 300 percent more essential oil, Ms. Audette said, but it has a high camphor content. ''About 85 percent of the lavender grown in France is lavandin,'' she said. And it's probably lavandin in soaps, sprays and toilet  water. ''But for the true perfume -- much sweeter and mellow -- the essential oil should be angustifolia.''</p>
        <p>Among the most popular English lavenders are Hidcote, Munstead, Sharon Roberts and Twickle Purple.</p>
        <p>L. stoechas, also called Spanish, French or Italian lavender, is the adorable fat flower with the purple rabbit ear. L. viridis, also called green or yellow lavender, has yellow-cream flowers on two-foot stems. And don't forget lavandin, 30 inches tall, with narrow spikes ranging from lavender and pink to blue and deep violet. And its fragrance is strong, from that camphor.</p>
        <p>Like other lavender experts, Ms. Audette advises buying cuttings. Seed-grown lavender is highly variable, which can be interesting for adventurous types, but you will have a hodge-podge of plants with different growth habits, shapes and colors.</p>
        <p>There are so many different kinds of lavenders, and two recent books go into explanations: ''Lavender, the Grower's Guide'' (Timber Press, 2000; $30) by Virginia McNaughton and ''The Lavender Garden, Beautiful Varieties to Grow and Gather'' (Chronicle, 1998; $19) by Robert Kourik.</p>
        <p>Sources for lavender include: Digging Dog Nursery, Albion, Calif., (707) 937-1130, free catalog; Sandy Mush Herb Nursery, Leicester, N.C., (828) 683-2014, catalog $4; and Well-Sweep Herb Farm, Port Murray, N.J., (908) 852-5390; catalog, $2.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
