<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frantic Russian Effort To Rescue Crew of Sub</title>
    <meta content="15RUSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kursk (Submarine)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Barents Sea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drew, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5D8113FF936A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frantic Russian Effort To Rescue Crew of Sub</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE with CHRISTOPHER DREW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina; Drew, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian nuclear submarine Kursk plunges to seabed in Barents Sea during naval exercises, possibly after explosion on board, trapping more than 100 crew members 450 feet below surface; officials say vessel is badly damaged; are unsure how many of crew are alive or how long they can survive; Russian navy begins desperate rescue attempt; says odds of saving crew are slim; says submarine carried no nuclear weapons and that nuclear reactors were turned off, calming fears of possible radioactive contamination; Pres Clinton is briefed about accident and offers US help; American experts say vessel, unlike most Russian submarines, was probably not equipped with pressurized escape chambers that could have carried crew to surface; Russia's loss of at least four nuclear submarines from 1960's through 1989, and crippling of others by reactor malfunctions, fires or other problems recalled; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Russian submarine plunged to the seabed in the Barents Sea on Sunday during a naval exercise, possibly after an explosion on board, officials said today.</p>
        <p>They said the submarine was badly damaged, and was trapped at least 450 feet below the surface. They said they did not know how many of the more than 100 crew members on board were alive or how long they could survive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Russian submarine plunged to the seabed in the Barents Sea on Sunday during a naval exercise, possibly after an explosion on board, officials said today.</p>
        <p>They said the submarine was badly damaged, and was trapped at least 450 feet below the surface. They said they did not know how many of the more than 100 crew members on board were alive or how long they could survive.</p>
        <p>Tonight the navy began preparing a desperate attempt to rescue the crew. But navy officials said the odds of saving the men were slim.</p>
        <p>The submarine, called the Kursk, was not carrying nuclear weapons, the navy said, but was powered by two nuclear reactors, raising concerns about possible radioactive contamination. But Russian officials said the reactors had been turned off, and officials in Norway said a scientific vessel in the area had detected no signs of a radioactive leak.</p>
        <p>A flotilla of ships and rescue vessels was on the scene off Russia's northern coast in rough weather tonight, frantically searching for ways to reach the men. Navy officials said they intended to mount a rescue attempt on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>News reports said rescue workers had been trying to hook lines to the submarine to bring it air and fuel. If the sub lost power, the men could suffocate and the submarine's compartments could turn unbearably cold in the frigid waters.</p>
        <p>The navy's commander, Adm. Vladimir Kuroyedov, said, ''Despite all the efforts being taken, the probability of a successful outcome from the situation with the Kursk is not very high.''</p>
        <p>The White House spokesman, Joe Lockhart, said that President Clinton had been briefed about the accident, and that his national security adviser, Samuel R. Berger, had told Foreign Minister Igor S. Ivanov that the United States was willing to help. Mr. Lockhart said the Russians had not followed up on the offer.</p>
        <p>The Russians initially said the sub appeared to have sunk after a collision, possible with a foreign submarine. During the cold war, one or two American subs were always on reconnaissance missions in the Barents Sea. But those missions have become much rarer since the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991, and Pentagon officials denied today that any American sub had been involved.</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials said a Navy electronic surveillance ship was operating in or near the Barents Sea at the time of the accident. They said the ship was monitoring Russian submarine movements but was far from the scene of the accident.</p>
        <p>Unlike most Russian submarines, American naval experts said, the Kursk apparently was not equipped with pressurized escape chambers that could have carried the crew to the surface.</p>
        <p>One military expert, A. D. Baker III, said Russia's Northern Fleet once had deep-diving minisubs that could have undertaken such a rescue, just as the United States Navy does. But, he said, that ability was ''allowed to dwindle away'' during budget cuts that have turned the once-powerful Russian Navy into a shadow of what it was during the cold war.</p>
        <p>He said it was doubtful that American rescue vessels could be brought to the site of the stricken submarine in time, adding that the Russian crew members would probably be lost ''unless a miracle occurs.''</p>
        <p>Frequent television news updates galvanized viewers in Moscow and stood in sharp contrast to the secrecy that surrounded submarine operations during most of the cold war.</p>
        <p>American experts say Russia lost at least four nuclear submarines in accidents from the 1960's through 1989, while others were crippled by reactor malfunctions, fires or other problems. American and Russian submarines used to track one another at close quarters, seeking information and advantage in a dangerous effort to control the ocean depths.</p>
        <p>But since the cold war ended, the Russian submarine force has stayed close to home, cut in size by a third.  It has had little money for training and maintenance, and many of its submarines and ships are rusting at their piers.</p>
        <p>The Russian Navy provided few details of the Kursk accident, and the information available in Moscow today was sketchy and even contradictory. One news report said crew members could be heard pounding on the hull.</p>
        <p>If the submarine still had battery power to run air-cleansing equipment, crew members who survived the sinking might be able to live for several more days, said Thomas Nilsen, a researcher in Oslo and co-author of a report on the Russian fleet. But even if the air was still breathable, the carbon dioxide exhaled by any survivors could gradually make the air toxic.</p>
        <p>The Kursk, an Oscar II-class submarine that was completed in 1994, sank on Sunday in international waters, about 35 miles from the coast. Besides torpedoes, it normally carries 24 missiles intended to destroy ships. It usually has a crew of 107 men, though some reports said 116 were on this cruise.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said the Kursk had been taking part in a naval exercise when it lost radio contact with its base.</p>
        <p>The Itar-Tass news agency reported that a preliminary underwater investigation showed that an explosion had probably damaged the bow of the submarine, causing the torpedo room to flood.</p>
        <p>The grim efforts to reach the men illustrate the difficult calculus behind any submarine rescue mission.</p>
        <p>The United States lost two nuclear submarines, the Thresher and the Scorpion, in accidents during the 1960's. After the Thresher sank in 1963, the Navy built two minisubs that can dive to 2,000 feet, connect their hatches to those of stricken subs and ferry 24 men at a time to the surface.</p>
        <p>The minisubs can be flown to a port near a submarine disaster and then ferried to the scene by one of eight specially configured mother submarines.</p>
        <p>Both of the Navy's minisubs are in San Diego. One of them, the Avalon, is ready for immediate deployment; the other, the Mystic, is being certified for a return to activity.</p>
        <p>But experts said it was not clear whether either vessel would be compatible with the hatch design of the Russian sub. And it could take a week or more for one of the mother submarines to reach Russian waters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, the editor of Combat Fleets of the World, published by the United States Naval Institute Press, said Russia's Northern Fleet had a similar mother sub with smaller rescue vessels. But he said those vessels had not operated since 1990 and were no longer usable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker said Russia's best hope for rescuing any sailors on the Kursk would probably be through the use of pressurized diving bells, either from its own fleet or borrowed from oil-drilling companies.</p>
        <p>In the late 1930's, 32 men were rescued from a primitive American sub, the Squalus, in four trips with a diving bell in 240 feet of water. But Mr. Baker said the water in the Barents Sea was much more treacherous.</p>
        <p>And some reports said the Kursk had listed nearly 60 degrees to one side, which could make it hard to secure a diving bell to one of its hatches.</p>
        <p>The latest accident comes at a critical time for Russia's Navy, which has been under strict budget constraints since the fall of the Soviet Union. As recently as May, the navy owed officers as much as six months of back wages, while even the temperatures in schools at the naval bases plunged last winter because of lack of money for heating.</p>
        <p>Russia's record in nuclear safety has also been troubling, with some areas of the Barents Sea contaminated with radiation from discarded nuclear reactors. Russia's last major submarine accident occurred in 1989, when the Komsomolets sank off the coast of Norway, killing most of its crew.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
