<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping Mosquitoes At Bay</title>
    <meta content="26HOME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0DC143DF935A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping Mosquitoes At Bay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column advises on warding off mosquitoes that spread West Nile encephalitis (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE mosquitoes are generally not a high-priority item at this time of year -- in the New York City area, the insects do not become active until late spring -- some recent announcements by the city's Health Department may inspire homeowners to launch a pre-emptive strike against the pests even before they take their first flight.</p>
        <p>On March 9, the Health Department reported that a study by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention confirmed that hibernating mosquitoes collected in Fort Totten, Queens, had low levels of the West Nile virus genetic material. And while no live viruses were recovered, officials said, the discovery raises the possibility of a repeat of last year's outbreak. The virus can cause encephalitis and meningitis. Seven people died last year, and 62 others became seriously ill as a result of being bitten by infected mosquitoes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE mosquitoes are generally not a high-priority item at this time of year -- in the New York City area, the insects do not become active until late spring -- some recent announcements by the city's Health Department may inspire homeowners to launch a pre-emptive strike against the pests even before they take their first flight.</p>
        <p>On March 9, the Health Department reported that a study by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention confirmed that hibernating mosquitoes collected in Fort Totten, Queens, had low levels of the West Nile virus genetic material. And while no live viruses were recovered, officials said, the discovery raises the possibility of a repeat of last year's outbreak. The virus can cause encephalitis and meningitis. Seven people died last year, and 62 others became seriously ill as a result of being bitten by infected mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>And while health officials have developed a surveillance and control plan to prevent a repeat of last year's outbreak, there are steps that homeowners can take to keep the number of new mosquitoes at a minimum.</p>
        <p>''This may not be the time of year you expect to be see mosquitoes,'' said John Gadd, a spokesman for the Health Department.  ''But it's not too early for homeowners to start their mosquito prevention efforts.''</p>
        <p>Pest control authorities say that the best way to reduce the number of mosquitoes around a home is to remove any standing water.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Potter, an urban entomologist at the University of Kentucky in Lexington, said that the kind of mosquito identified by health officials as the carrier of the West Nile virus -- Culex pipiens, the common household mosquito -- typically lays its eggs on the surface of standing water.</p>
        <p>''Homeowners often don't realize that there are a whole bunch of places where water might be accumulating,'' Dr. Potter said, adding that while it is unlikely that there are any mosquitoes flying around right now, it is only a matter of a short time before egg-bearing females take flight.</p>
        <p>''As soon as the conditions are right they'll start laying eggs,'' Dr. Potter said. ''And any eggs they lay will hatch in a matter of days.''</p>
        <p>Among the likely -- or perhaps unlikely -- places that eggs will be laid, Dr. Potter said,  are in buckets, birdbaths, pool covers, discarded tin cans, old tires, cisterns, recycling bins, inverted trash-can tops and saucers for flowerpots; in water that has collected on top of pool covers and tarpaulins and  even in small pockets on children's toys.  And one of the most common breeding areas, he said, is a leaf-clogged rain gutter.</p>
        <p>''Mosquitoes develop rapidly,'' Dr. Potter said, and they can go from tiny water-bound wrigglers to flying, biting adults in as little as one week. ''That means that a single neglected roof gutter can produce hundreds of new mosquitoes each day,'' he added.</p>
        <p>But what can homeowners do if they have  an ornamental pond or a swampy area that is impossible to drain?</p>
        <p>''One thing to consider might be to stock the pond with mosquito fish,'' Dr. Potter said, referring to what are called predacious minnows, about an inch to an inch and a half long, that dine quite happily on mosquito larvae.</p>
        <p>Another alternative, he said, is to treat the pond or swampy area with a ''biorational'' insecticide that will kill mosquito larvae while leaving pets, plants and people unharmed. Products that will accomplish this, he said, include Bactimos, Vectobac and Altosid, all of which can be purchased from the Clarke Mosquito Control Products in Roselle, Ill., (800) 323-5727; and Mosquito Dunks, manufactured by March Biological Control in Sherwood, Ore.</p>
        <p>''They're all essentially harmless to other aquatic organisms,'' Dr. Potter said.</p>
        <p>Brad Ross, the owner of March Biological Control, said that Mosquito Dunks are similar in size and shape to small doughnuts and float on the surface of standing water.  ''Each dunk will treat 100 square feet of surface water for 30 days,'' Mr. Ross said, adding that the product will remain effective for that period even if the area in which it has been placed -- a swampy area, for example, or in pools that may form along the banks of a brook or stream -- dries up and then refloods.</p>
        <p>Mosquito Dunks are sold in six-packs for about $8.25 and can be bought from March Biological's Web site: www.marchbiological.com.</p>
        <p>For those who have not been able to eradicate mosquito larvae, there are various products on the market that can be used on adult insects.</p>
        <p>''Most of the products that can be purchased by consumers are reasonably safe,'' said Timothy Deschamps, a member of the executive board of the Northeastern Mosquito Control Association, a nonprofit organization in Northborough, Mass.  ''But be sure to follow the label directions. More is not necessarily better, and if you use too much, you could end up killing beneficial insects along with the mosquitoes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deschamps recommends spraying around the bases of shrubs and high plants because that is where mosquitoes are likely to rest during the day. And since most mosquito sprays have little residual effect, he said, it is typically necessary to find the mosquitoes and execute a frontal assault.</p>
        <p>One product that does not work very well with mosquitoes, Mr. Deschamps said, is the electronic bug zapper.</p>
        <p>''We've found that a typical backyard bug zapper might get 1 percent of the mosquito population in a backyard,'' he said. Instead, they attract harmless or beneficial insects like  moths and ladybugs.</p>
        <p>But there is one ''zapper-like'' product now being marketed that claims to increase its mosquito-killing power considerably by using heat and even carbon dioxide to lure its prey.</p>
        <p>''Our machine actually mimics the body temperatures of humans, cattle and pets, all the things that mosquitoes like to bite,'' said Alvin Wilbanks, the president of Environmental Products and Research in Blytheville, Ark.</p>
        <p>And while the device may look like an aluminum wastebasket with a hat to a human, Mr. Wilbanks said, it looks like a human to a mosquito.</p>
        <p>Janice Chandler, the town treasurer of Pollard, Ark., said, the town bought five last year and has bought five more for this summer. ''The machines are being used as an alternative to using airplanes to spray insecticide in public parks. They've really done the job for us.''</p>
        <p>The technology does not come cheap: the basic Mosquito Killer unit costs $399. A $120 add-on that emits carbon dioxide, mimicking exhaled breath, increases the kill rate, Mr. Wilbanks said.</p>
        <p>Additional information about the Mosquito Killer can be found at www.epar-mosquito.com.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
