<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Agency Details Plans For Electric Turbines in City</title>
    <meta content="22TURB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/22/nyregion/22TURB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Power Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD143AF931A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Agency Details Plans For Electric Turbines in City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Power Authority explains plans to install fleet of small electricity generators around New York City to prevent summer blackouts; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stepping in to reduce the threat of blackouts next summer, the New York Power Authority is detailing its plans to install a fleet of small electricity generators around Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx and on Long Island and possibly in Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Not only do officials hope to avert blackouts with the generators, but they also hope to hold down the price of electricity on hot summer afternoons, when high demand pushes up power rates in the newly deregulated market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stepping in to reduce the threat of blackouts next summer, the New York Power Authority is detailing its plans to install a fleet of small electricity generators around Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx and on Long Island and possibly in Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Not only do officials hope to avert blackouts with the generators, but they also hope to hold down the price of electricity on hot summer afternoons, when high demand pushes up power rates in the newly deregulated market.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to increase reliability here in this city,'' said Clarence D. Rappleyea, the chairman and chief executive of the power authority, which plans to make the announcement of the new plants today. ''We're trying to keep the lights on in the city of New York, and I think everybody knows what happens when we have a problem with that.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the decision by the state-owned agency to install the generators was a sign that deregulation of the utility industry is not working as was anticipated, at least not yet. The idea behind deregulation was that entrepreneurs would rush to build new power generators to meet high demand, as occurs in other parts of the economy.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of going back into the old regime,'' said John W. Dax, a lawyer for NYC Energy, a company that is trying to win permission from various state and federal agencies to build a 79-megawatt power plant at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. The plant would be built on a barge and could be put in place quickly, Mr. Dax said, but the Power Authority's action was making it difficult to win financing.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is saying, do I want to invest in a project that has had the economic legs kicked out from under it by the state,'' Mr. Dax said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rappleyea, in a telephone interview, said that the generators would probably not be a good business proposition and that his agency was spending an extra $50 million for additional pollution controls, something that he said a private entity would probably not do.</p>
        <p>The Power Authority generators, built by General Electric, will burn natural gas and are to be equipped with acoustic muffling and with devices called selective catalytic converters. Akin to the catalytic converters on cars, they sharply reduce nitrogen oxides, which are a cause of smog, acid rain and particulate pollution. All locations chosen by the Power Authority are in industrial areas, except for one, on Staten Island, which is adjacent to a Con Edison substation but which has housing in the area. That one is still under study.</p>
        <p>In a regulatory shortcut, the generators are slightly smaller than the size that would require approval by the state bureaucracy that regulates power plants, although they will need approvals from the Department of Environmental Conservation. There will be 10 of them, or 11, if the site on Staten Island is used. The Power Authority announced in September that it planned to add plants for peak days; it will say today that it has found places to put them.</p>
        <p>New York City entered the summer of 2000 with too little capacity for comfort, according to the commission's staff, but made it through because the weather was relatively cool. Demand is growing by 1.5 percent a year, the commission said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the area is short of transmission capacity. That has led the organization that arranges power sales in the state to order that companies selling power in New York City have enough generating capacity within its borders to meet 80 percent of their load, a criterion that the Power Authority does not now meet. The generators, shipped in 14 segments and looking like a series of grey metal boxes, are about 140 feet long and 40 to 55 feet high, with a 100-foot stack on the end. Each occupies about an acre. Gas comes in from under ground, and electricity leaves that way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
