<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Recap Of the Next 100 Years</title>
    <meta content="02ORDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUT OF ORDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bouchier, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DC1638F931A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Recap Of the Next 100 Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BOUCHIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bouchier, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tongue-in-cheek look back at great events of 21st century; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG ISLAND was a pretty dull place back in the 1900's. The most notable events were the opening of the Long Island Expressway in 1955, and the first Amy Fisher made-for-television movie in 1993. Fortunately, the 21st century has been much more dramatic. What's left of the Island has been transformed beyond Robert Moses's wildest dreams. Let's look back on some of the great events of the past hundred years.</p>
        <p>2000: The Y2K fiasco was justifiably labeled the anticlimax of the century. Hundreds of thousands of Long Islanders filled their basements with survival supplies. Absolutely nothing happened, and they spent most of the following year feeling foolish, and trying to use up their stocks of bottled water, packet soups, candles and cat food.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG ISLAND was a pretty dull place back in the 1900's. The most notable events were the opening of the Long Island Expressway in 1955, and the first Amy Fisher made-for-television movie in 1993. Fortunately, the 21st century has been much more dramatic. What's left of the Island has been transformed beyond Robert Moses's wildest dreams. Let's look back on some of the great events of the past hundred years.</p>
        <p>2000: The Y2K fiasco was justifiably labeled the anticlimax of the century. Hundreds of thousands of Long Islanders filled their basements with survival supplies. Absolutely nothing happened, and they spent most of the following year feeling foolish, and trying to use up their stocks of bottled water, packet soups, candles and cat food.</p>
        <p>2001: The true beginning of the 21st century arrived with no fanfare. After the excesses of the previous year, everyone preferred to ignore it. The totally unexpected collapse of all computers on Jan. 1 (later known as Y2K1) took everyone by surprise. After two or three days of chaos, things ran much more smoothly. The elderly found that they could sell their archaic skills at premium prices and no longer needed to feel inferior to their grandchildren. Those who could run a filing or accounting system, using nothing but paper, or write grammatical, properly spelled English on a manual typewriter, became the new technological elite.</p>
        <p>2009: By this time, everyone had learned to live very happily without computers. The art of letter writing had revived, and people began to talk to their families and colleagues again instead of sending e-mails. A visit to the post office or the library became a simple and quick transaction, instead of a losing battle with the newest computer system. Late in the year, software engineers, who had been living like refugees in their obsolete high-tech offices, declared that the mysterious Y2K1 problem had been solved, and computers would soon be back in action. This news sparked off the first full-scale citizen's rebellion in American history. The slogan ''Just Say No!'' swept the country, and all computer experts were humanely exiled to a closed compound near Seattle.</p>
        <p>2030: By a happy coincidence, the Dow Jones Industrial Index hit 30,000. Some economists puzzled over the fact that the endless boom was based on no apparent economic activity except the buying and selling of stocks.</p>
        <p>2036: Long Island real-estate brokers announced that the average new home now offered 10,000 square feet of living area, with garage space for five cars. At the same time, traffic experts noted that a perfect balance had been achieved between homes, highways, retail stores and parking lots. Not one more house or car could be fitted into the available space. Frustrated developers suggested building on the sacred golf courses, which by then occupied 80 percent of land on the East End. This was dismissed as too radical, and the Island was declared closed.</p>
        <p>2069: Enormous excitement was created by the crash landing of an alien spacecraft on the site of the old Grumman facility in Bethpage. Unfortunately, for those who had long been waiting for contact with beings of superior intelligence, the aliens were the galactic equivalent of a bunch of teenagers out cruising who had collided with Long Island because they weren't paying attention. After being provided with baseball caps and instructed to wear them backward, the alienswere absorbed into the local school system with no further fuss.</p>
        <p>2076: Peconic County seceded from the rest of Suffolk on the 300th anniversary of the first American Revolution. Shelter Island immediately seceded from Peconic County, and the Hamptons declared their independence from absolutely everything. This set off a chain reaction. By year's end, Long Island was divided into 76 tiny nations, each with its own passport and frontiers, its own flag, currency, postage stamps, traffic laws, national song, national prejudices and all the other things that make independence such fun. Long Island gained a reputation as the Balkans of the West, and troops from the United Nations were stationed here to keep the peace</p>
        <p>2094: The unforgettable year of the Great Inundation (later called the Great Flood because nobody could spell inundation). A combination of global warming, a high tide, a heavy population, a planetary conjunction and a hurricane brought the sea surging over the whole length and breadth of the Island. At the height of the flood, nothing could be seen except a line of expressway signs just above the water, reading ''Long Delays Ahead, Exits 1 to 73.'' Residents of Middle Island and Hicksville found that they owned valuable beachfront properties. Nothing was left of the Hamptons but a few designer clothes floating on the waves.</p>
        <p>2099: By this time, the only significant industry in the world was tourism, and New York was a favorite destination for visitors from all over the planet. The narrow strip of the Island that remained after the flood was chosen as an ideal landing place for the huge supersonic aircraft that converged on the city. Displaced residents were moved to an artificial island in the middle of Salamonie Lake, Montana, where the intensive construction of highways, tract houses and strip malls soon created an almost exact replica of historic 20th-century Long Island. Everyone agreed it was almost as good as than the real thing.</p>
        <p>OUT OF ORDER E-mail address: liorder@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: liorder@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
