<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Dies of Suffocation After Locking Herself in a Vault</title>
    <meta content="29VAUL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asphyxiation and Suffocation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Depository Trust Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Penn, Esther</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DD153DF93AA15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Dies of Suffocation After Locking Herself in a Vault</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Esther Penn, 35-year-old employee of Depository Trust in lower Manhattan, dies of suffocation after accidentally locking herself in vault and triggering fire extinguishing system that filled chamber with carbon dioxide (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman working at a financial services company died Thursday night after accidentally locking herself in a vault and triggering a fire extinguishing system that filled the chamber with carbon dioxide, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The authorities are investigating what went wrong around 9 o'clock, when the woman, Esther Penn, 35, became trapped in the 10,000-square-foot vault while storing stock receipts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A woman working at a financial services company died Thursday night after accidentally locking herself in a vault and triggering a fire extinguishing system that filled the chamber with carbon dioxide, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The authorities are investigating what went wrong around 9 o'clock, when the woman, Esther Penn, 35, became trapped in the 10,000-square-foot vault while storing stock receipts.</p>
        <p>Before pulling the fire alarm, Ms. Penn used an in-house telephone in the vault to call her supervisor, leaving a message on his voice mail that she was trapped, the police said.</p>
        <p>She then apparently panicked, pulling a lever marked ''fire suppression'' and unwittingly activating the extinguisher system instead of merely summoning help.</p>
        <p>She was found by firefighters and pronounced dead on arrival at New York University Downtown Hospital.</p>
        <p>During the two years that Ms. Penn worked at the company, Depository Trust, at 55 Water Street in Lower Manhattan, she would regularly descend to the basement vaults, said Stuart Z. Goldstein, a spokesman for the Depository Trust and Clearing Corporation, the overseeing holding company.</p>
        <p>''The depository has been around for 25-plus years,'' Mr. Goldstein said, ''and I don't know of a single incident to my knowledge where something like this has occurred.'' He added that at least 20 employees entered the vault each day.</p>
        <p>A Fire Department spokesman, L. Frank Gribbon, said that a preliminary application to change the fire suppression system from a Halon gas system to the carbon dioxide system, which displaces oxygen in closed spaces, had been filed in 1976 but never followed up, and that the department had not found any records indicating approval of the current system.</p>
        <p>While Lieutenant Gribbon would not comment on the specifics of the system, he did say that ''one of the key features of any system is the ability for prompt evacuation.'' He added, ''They make these systems with the intentions that they will be used properly. This was used improperly.''</p>
        <p>The lieutenant said that when the alarm sounded and firefighters arrived at the site, security guards assured them several times that nobody was in the vault and that they had video surveillance of the area. ''Eventually when we got it open she was found inside,'' the lieutenant said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein of Depository Trust said that Fire Department officials had assured heads of his company that the system was approved. ''The D.T.C. would never put in a system like this if it was not authorized by the Fire Department,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The woman's death has left fellow employees baffled. ''It's just like a mystery,'' said a man who has worked at the Depository Trust Company for more than 10 years but declined to give his name, saying he feared he might lose his job. The employee said that he entered the vault every night and that it had to be locked from the outside, by at least two employees.</p>
        <p>Ms. Penn, who had a teenage daughter and a younger son, lived in an apartment at 1199 East 53rd Street in East Flatbush, Brooklyn, until about a month ago, said Colleen Corridon, a neighbor. ''She's someone like myself,'' Ms. Corridon said. ''She goes from work straight upstairs. This is a very shocking experience.''</p>
        <p>The general manager of the Kings Village Corporation, Dennis Fermaint, said that early this month Ms. Penn came to his office with her mother and signed a lease to rent a three-bedroom apartment on East 51st Street in Brooklyn with a view of the Manhattan skyline. She was scheduled to move into her new apartment, a $95,000 co-op with a rent-to-own option, on Aug. 3.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
