<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seas and Soils Emerge as Keys to Climate</title>
    <meta content="16CARB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0D6103BF935A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seas and Soils Emerge as Keys to Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers explore ways to reduce atmospheric carbon dioxide by expanding plant and soil carbon reservoirs, or 'sinks,' on land; these sinks could be expanded by such practices as no-till agriculture, conversion of cropland into grassland and maximizing forestation; environmentalists prefer limiting emission of heat-trapping gases to finding ways to absorb them in the terrestrial biosphere, but proponents of carbon sink idea argue that it could be a valuable interim alternative; photos; diagrams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last 150 years, the burning of coal, oil and natural gas has released some 270 billion tons of carbon into the air in the form of heat-trapping carbon dioxide. If all that had stayed in the atmosphere, much of the substantial global warming predicted for a century from now might have already taken place.</p>
        <p>Luckily, more than half the carbon dioxide emitted by fossil-fuel burning is absorbed from the air by the oceans, by plants (which use it in converting sunlight to chemical energy) and by soils. Fewer than half the emissions, scientists believe, remain airborne to warm the earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last 150 years, the burning of coal, oil and natural gas has released some 270 billion tons of carbon into the air in the form of heat-trapping carbon dioxide. If all that had stayed in the atmosphere, much of the substantial global warming predicted for a century from now might have already taken place.</p>
        <p>Luckily, more than half the carbon dioxide emitted by fossil-fuel burning is absorbed from the air by the oceans, by plants (which use it in converting sunlight to chemical energy) and by soils. Fewer than half the emissions, scientists believe, remain airborne to warm the earth.</p>
        <p>All of this is part of one of nature's grand and endlessly complicated global recycling networks. In it, carbon is constantly exchanged among the air, the terrestrial biosphere, the oceans and the solid rock of the earth at varying rates on time scales ranging from hours to millions of years.</p>
        <p>Now, as the economic and political difficulty of reducing carbon dioxide emissions at the source becomes ever more obvious, a broad-based move is under way to manipulate the carbon cycle so that it will remove more of the heat-trapping gases from the air. It is an ambitious idea, but on closer inspection one surrounded by questions, potential risks and obstacles.</p>
        <p>In one approach, researchers are investigating ways to remove carbon chemically from industrial and automotive emissions before they are released to the atmosphere, then to sequester it at some other way station in the natural carbon cycle -- by injecting the removed carbon back into underground reservoirs or into the ocean, for instance.</p>
        <p>The United States Department of Energy has expanded research into carbon-removal technologies at eight of its national laboratories. But this option, the department said in a recent study, is ''truly radical'' and most experts believe it is some distance from providing a practical alternative.</p>
        <p>More promising in the near term, many scientists believe, are prospects for increasing the absorption of atmospheric carbon dioxide by what is called the terrestrial biosphere: that is, the whole complex of living things on land, mainly plants and various tiny inhabitants and detritus of the soil.</p>
        <p>Every time a plant sprouts and grows to maturity, it absorbs carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, breaks it down chemically and uses carbon as construction material for roots, stem, branches, flowers and leaves. When the plant dies, some of the carbon goes back into the atmosphere, but some is also released into the soil as the dead plant decays. Decomposing animals, including people, further add to the carbon reservoir in the soil. Globally, soil contains about five times as much carbon as vegetation.</p>
        <p>The expansion of these carbon reservoirs, or ''sinks,'' in vegetation and soil has been sanctioned as one way industrialized countries might meet their obligations  under the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, which is aimed at reducing emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Lately, intense argument has developed over the degree to which countries like the United States, which may have great potential for expanding its carbon sinks, ought to be allowed to meet their emissions reduction targets under the protocol by means like planting trees, improving forest management and conserving soils rather than reducing carbon dioxide emissions from cars, factories and power generating stations.</p>
        <p>Delegates from more than 100 countries are to grapple with the issue when they meet in November in The Hague for what is widely seen as a make-or-break effort to make the Kyoto Protocol operational.</p>
        <p>The rules governing carbon sinks are among the many sets of yet-to-be adopted regulations necessary to put the protocol into effect, and only a few countries have ratified the agreement pending action on them.  The United States, where the protocol has encountered strong opposition in Congress on several grounds, is one of those holding back.</p>
        <p>In preparation for the critical November meeting, scientists of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, created by the United Nations more than a decade ago to advise the world's governments, issued a report on the carbon issue at a meeting last week in Montreal. The analysis suggested that expansion of terrestrial carbon sinks in the industrialized countries could potentially more than enable them to meet their entire combined emissions reduction quota under the protocol.</p>
        <p>But experts associated with the report questioned how much of that potential could be achieved, given the difficulty of actually expanding the world's carbon sinks in practice.</p>
        <p>''Judging the technical potential is easy,'' said Dr. Robert T. Watson, chairman of the intergovernmental panel, who is also the chief atmospheric scientist and environmental adviser of the World Bank. ''The real question is, what is the likelihood of realizing that technical potential?''</p>
        <p>Under the Kyoto Protocol, the rich industrial countries as a group are obligated to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions 5 percent below 1990 levels by about 2010. The reductions are widely seen as a first step in eventually stabilizing atmospheric concentrations. If emissions are not reduced, prominent scientists say, the average global temperature will rise by about 3.5 degrees Fahrenheit by the year 2100. (By comparison, the world is now 5 to 9 degrees warmer than in the depths of the last ice age 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.)</p>
        <p>This much warming, the experts say, would bring rising seas, more severe droughts, rainstorms, heat waves and floods, along with broad shifts in climatic and agricultural zones that would benefit some regions but seriously harm others.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and some parties to the Kyoto Protocol, especially the European Union, strenuously object to allowing any country to meet all or most of its emissions reduction goal by expanding carbon sinks.</p>
        <p>''Sucking carbon out of the atmosphere is not the same as preventing it permanently from leaving the exhaust pipe or power plant,'' said Jennifer Morgan, director of the World Wildlife Fund's climate change campaign.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that since forests can always be cut down as well as planted, and soils can always be plowed up as well as conserved, the terrestrial biosphere is not nearly as secure a carbon reservoir as the underground reservoirs where coal, oil and gas are contained. So, they say, why remove them from that secure spot in the first place?</p>
        <p>They also fear that reliance on sinks to meet the Kyoto targets could delay the adoption of measures to reduce fossil fuel use and replace it with other energy technologies.</p>
        <p>In any event, scientists say, carbon sinks will eventually probably reach a saturation point, at which they will be unable to absorb any more carbon dioxide. The dominant view therefore remains that if the world is serious about reducing and stabilizing the atmospheric concentrations, emissions must be cut at the source by burning fossil fuels more efficiently, switching from relatively high-carbon fuels like coal to lower-carbon natural gas, and replacing fossil fuels altogether by alternatives like hydrogen fuel cells.</p>
        <p>Given the slow progress in that direction, though, proponents of the carbon sink idea argue that it could be a valuable interim measure.</p>
        <p>In many ways, however, human activity has been shrinking carbon sinks rather than expanding them.  Deforestation and farming have obliterated great stretches of forest and grassland that once absorbed carbon dioxide. Farming has also chopped up soils in ways that cause them to give off carbon dioxide rather than to sequester it.</p>
        <p>In fact, said the scientific report issued in Montreal, human use of the terrestrial biosphere, including the burning of wood, has released some 135 billion tons of carbon into the air since 1850 -- about half as much as has been emitted by fossil fuel burning.</p>
        <p>The net result of all this is that overall atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide are about 30 percent higher now than at the start of the industrial revolution.</p>
        <p>A de facto counterattack has been under way for some time in the Northern Hemisphere, where the replanting of forests on deforested lands has made headway in recent decades. One provision of the Kyoto Protocol allows for industrialized countries to gain credit toward their reduction targets for tree planting since 1990 -- but also to incur debits for any deforestation since then. To reap meaningful credit, a country would have to show a net gain.</p>
        <p>The protocol also allows countries to gain credit for reductions through a variety of other ways of expanding terrestrial carbon stocks should the parties to the agreement so decide.  These include, for instance, expanding carbon stores in soil through no-till agriculture, in which no plowing takes place and seeds are sown in the carbon-rich detritus of the previous year's harvest.</p>
        <p>Other possibilities include conversion of cropland into grassland, fertilization of pastureland and forest management practices designed to increase carbon stocks -- for example, lengthening the period between harvests of a forest's timber, or promoting faster tree growth and thicker stands of trees, plantation-style.</p>
        <p>Estimates suggest that these kinds of measures might allow some countries to achieve large cuts in net carbon dioxide emissions. The potential of such measures in the United States, Canada and Russia is great, according to a recent calculation made for the World Wildlife Fund by Kevin Gurney, an atmospheric researcher at Colorado State University who studies the carbon cycle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurney estimated, for example, that without planting any trees, the measures would potentially enable the United States to remove about 150 million tons of carbon a year from the atmosphere. This exceeds its Kyoto emissions reduction target by tens of millions of tons.  ''They're pretty big,'' Mr. Gurney said of the estimates.</p>
        <p>The Montreal report estimated that in theory, measures other than tree-planting by the industrialized countries could remove nearly 290 million more tons of carbon a year from the atmosphere by about 2010 than are removed by such measures now. By comparison, the Kyoto Protocol would require the rich countries to cut emissions by about 200 million tons a year below 1990 levels by about 2010.</p>
        <p>The report also raised caveats about how much of this estimated potential might be achieved. Even with ''an ambitious policy agenda,'' it said, the estimates were ''likely to be on the high side.''</p>
        <p>Far smaller gains could be achieved by the rich countries by planting trees and slowing deforestation, the report concluded. It said that a 20 percent increase in forest planting would probably offset no more than 3 million tons of carbon emissions a year, while slowing deforestation by 20 percent could offset about 18 million tons.</p>
        <p>Even if the potential for carbon sequestration can be realized to a substantial degree, many headaches still present themselves. For instance, forest growth is spurred -- and terrestrial carbon stocks are increased -- by a warming climate, and by rising levels of carbon dioxide and of atmospheric nitrogen deposited on forests as a result of industrial emissions.</p>
        <p>In assessing a country's carbon stocks for purposes of assigning credit, how can these effects of human activity be separated from the growth in carbon stocks brought about by tree-planting efforts alone?  It is almost impossible to make such a separation, Dr. Watson said.</p>
        <p>Another difficulty for some kinds of carbon sequestration efforts is that of monitoring and accounting for carbon stocks. Although there are well-established means of measuring the increase of carbon in a stand of growing trees, other sinks may present problems. One way to get around the difficulty in the case of agricultural soils might be to set up a business-as-usual control plot, in which conventional farming methods are used, against which to measure the change in carbon stocks as a result of no-till farming.</p>
        <p>Then there are ecological concerns. For instance, managers of carbon-sequestration projects might be tempted to replace naturally functioning forests with tree plantations, which in biological terms are comparatively poor and sterile, with little of the biological richness and variety of the wild woods. Likewise, managers might be tempted to cut down mature forests so as to plant new, faster-growing ones that sequester carbon at a higher rate.</p>
        <p>It is on questions of detail like these that the success or failure of the Kyoto Protocol may ultimately hinge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
