<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protests Distract Global Finance Meeting</title>
    <meta content="Y27FUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/world/27FUND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfensohn, James D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2DA133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protests Distract Global Finance Meeting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Masked protesters hurl cobblestones and attack police with homemade gasoline bombs in unsuccessful bid to shut down joint World Bank-International Monetary Fund meeting, Prague; riot police escort government ministers into special subway cars to whisk them from meetings at end of session, restoring normal access by evening; police and many protesters say squadrons of European anarchists and communists provoked violence; many of financial leaders pledge to rededicate selves to fighting poverty; World Bank president James D Wolfensohn cites need to make globalization instrument of opportunity and inclusion, not fear; police prepared for siege, with 11,000 officers outnumbering demonstrators; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Black-masked protesters hurled cobblestones ripped from Prague's medieval streets and attacked the police with homemade gasoline bombs today, trying desperately -- but unsuccessfully -- to shut down the global finance meeting here.</p>
        <p>The riot police had to escort government ministers attending the annual conference of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank into special subways cars to whisk them away from their meeting at the end of the session, though by evening, normal access had been fully restored.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Black-masked protesters hurled cobblestones ripped from Prague's medieval streets and attacked the police with homemade gasoline bombs today, trying desperately -- but unsuccessfully -- to shut down the global finance meeting here.</p>
        <p>The riot police had to escort government ministers attending the annual conference of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank into special subways cars to whisk them away from their meeting at the end of the session, though by evening, normal access had been fully restored.</p>
        <p>The violence, which both the police and many protesters said was provoked by squadrons of European anarchists and communists, did not stop the meetings.</p>
        <p>But it did steal the media spotlight, giving it to protesters who had vowed to re-create the blockade of the trade talks last year in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Inside the halls, financial leaders who are here to discuss aid policies tried to show that they are at least as passionate about the poor as the protesters are. Many pledged to rededicate themselves to fighting poverty, even to inspiring a new spirituality.</p>
        <p>Everyone seemed to cite the statistic that 3 billion people live on $2 or less a day.</p>
        <p>''Something is wrong when the richest 20 percent of the global population receive more than 80 percent of the global income,'' James D. Wolfensohn, the president of the World Bank, said in his keynote address. ''Our challenge is to make globalization an instrument of opportunity and inclusion -- not fear.''</p>
        <p>The leaders of the World Bank and the I.M.F., and finance ministers from some rich nations that back them, said they would speed up debt relief, allow poor countries to have more say in planning loan programs and consider replacing some loans with grants.</p>
        <p>But by afternoon, protesters had stolen the show, at least as far as the television cameras were concerned. The demonstrators included Czech anarchists, Italian Communists, British schoolteachers and German truck drivers, many of whom contended that the lending agencies are the problem, not the solution.</p>
        <p>The Prague police had prepared for a siege, with 11,000 officers around the city. In the end, the police estimated that there were 6,000 demonstrators. The protesters, who once expected 20,000, claimed that they actually had 10,000. Even if they were right, they still failed to match the police one for one, and they fell short of the tally in Seattle and at other recent protests.</p>
        <p>Early in the day, in what has become the signature vandalism, several people smashed the windows and tore up the interior of a McDonald's in Wenceslas Square, the site of the peaceful protests during Czechoslovakia's Velvet Revolution in 1989.</p>
        <p>Near the hilltop Congress Center, where the meetings were held, a small group of demonstrators provoked the police by hurling fist-sized stones that later littered the street behind police lines. Some protesters wore black masks and carried the red-and-black flag of anarchists. Several threw Molotov cocktails, igniting the uniforms of officers stretched in a line across the street.</p>
        <p>The police responded with repeated shots of tear gas. They sprayed water from cannons to disperse the crowd, while armored personnel carriers raced into position to close off the streets.</p>
        <p>The police said as many as 65 people were taken to hospitals with injuries, most of them officers involved in the melee. There were dozens of arrests. A few demonstrators were hurt by the police who seized them, with one man bleeding from the face after four officers threw him to the ground.</p>
        <p>The skirmishes spread to the valley below the meeting hall, where demonstrators burned barricades of wood and tires to keep the police back, then smashed windows and destroyed a car. An American flag was burned, while protesters yelled, ''No new world order.''</p>
        <p>Tomas, a 19-year-old from the Moravia region of the Czech Republic with orange hair and a rooster cut, was there throwing plastic bottles at the police. ''I hate the police and they hate me,'' he said. ''I would like some real fighting to happen.''</p>
        <p>A 23-year-old man from Berlin who refused to give his name carried several cobblestones as he prepared to rush police lines. He removed his black mask to reveal his face, seared red from pepper gas.</p>
        <p>''To fight them for me is symbolic of fighting the I.M.F., which will never change on its own,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Today's protests did succeed in blocking access to the conference center for several hours in the afternoon. But by that time meeting participants had already arrived, and their sessions continued uninterrupted, though delegates surrounded television monitors to get the latest news from the barricades.</p>
        <p>By late afternoon, some people at the meeting were complaining to guards that they had planes to catch and had to leave the center immediately, prompting authorities to open a subway station to officials only.</p>
        <p>Protesters had been gathering in Prague for a week, with many of them vowing to turn this session into a repeat of Seattle, when demonstrators briefly kept delegates away from their meetings.</p>
        <p>Many protesters decried the violence.</p>
        <p>''We're really disappointed,'' said Chelsea Mosen, an organizer. ''We were really hoping for a nonviolent protest on the basic issues of the I.M.F. and the World Bank, but instead now the focus has shifted to the streets of Prague.''</p>
        <p>Catherine Devon, 38, a teacher who traveled from Birmingham, England, by train for 24 hours to reach Prague this morning, said, ''This is not what I came for.'' She said she decided to join the demonstrations because her son often woke up in the middle of the night, frightened about global warming.</p>
        <p>''I want to tell him I am doing something about it,'' she said. ''We must show up every time these people meet. Someday, they will get the message.''</p>
        <p>Though they attracted less attention, delegates at the meetings from developing countries also challenged the lending agencies and wealthier governments to improve their policies.</p>
        <p>Trevor A. Manuel, South Africa's finance minister and the honorary chairman of this year's meetings, scolded the representatives of wealthy nations for pressing poor nations to embrace free markets while often protecting their own markets from the goods that developing countries produce.</p>
        <p>''The robust state of the global economy is due in no small measure to the success of the fundamental reforms undertaken by developing countries,'' Mr. Manuel said. ''Their boldness needs to be matched by the richer countries.''</p>
        <p>The United States treasury secretary, Lawrence H. Summers, who addressed the opening ceremonies early in the day, prodded the World Bank to spend more on human development projects, including education. Such proposals have met some resistance on the bank's board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers also called on the bank to provide some grants as well as its traditional loans, echoing a recommendation first made by a Congressional review panel that was highly critical of the bank's practices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers said the grants would go to programs like those that help prevent the spread of AIDS, whose benefits cannot be measured in money.</p>
        <p>It was left to Vaclav Havel, the Czech president and former dissident, to try to reconcile the demands of protesters with the money controlled by the ministers. He asked whether all the proposals to increase material well-being had obscured the task of improving spiritual health.</p>
        <p>''We often hear about the need to restructure the economies of the poorer countries and about the wealthier nations being duty bound to help them accomplish this,'' Mr. Havel said. ''But I deem it even more important that we should begin also to think about another restructuring -- a restructuring of the entire system of values that forms the basis of our civilization today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
