<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Have You Hugged Your Tree Today?</title>
    <meta content="08MOBILIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mobilio, Albert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyle, T Coraghessan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Friend of the Earth, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3D91E3AF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Have You Hugged Your Tree Today?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Albert Mobilio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mobilio, Albert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Albert Mobilio reviews book A Friend of the Earth by T Coraghessan Boyle (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Friend of the Earth</p>
        <p>By T. Coraghessan Boyle.</p>
        <p>271 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Friend of the Earth</p>
        <p>By T. Coraghessan Boyle.</p>
        <p>271 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>IT'S no slight feat for a writer to make you laugh out loud, and T. Coraghessan Boyle does it often. He handily mimics in prose the rhythmic interplay of voice, hands and limbs that stage comedians rely upon. Yet it has always been a wonder that this talent didn't make him a better novelist. In a peripatetic series of novels set among Mexican immigrants, Old Dutch New Yorkers, marijuana growers and turn-of-the-century health nuts, Boyle has unreeled wiry, jitterbugging sentences that never failed to delight. His topic hopping and hyperactive prose reveal him to be a consummate showman -- the Robin Williams of writers -- but like that actor he rarely leaves you wanting more.</p>
        <p>The common complaint about Boyle -- that his quirky characters are about as deep as the page on which we meet them -- is true enough. His impulse toward satiric exaggeration routinely overwhelms the bounds of verisimilitude. In his early novels, where the kinetic storytelling took readers by storm, this literary cuteness didn't seem quite the defect it has become in recent books. Like a motormouth entertainer who relentlessly seeks to dazzle, Boyle has wearied readers -- and perhaps himself -- for whom the tricks have grown stale and the dazzle has dimmed. This exhaustion is nowhere more apparent than in his eighth novel, ''A Friend of the Earth.''</p>
        <p>The setting is Southern California in 2025. The environment has been ravaged by pollution, plunder and global warming. (Apparently Al Gore lost the 2000 election.) Meat and fish are rarities, the forests have been leveled, and the climate careers between drought and unending, vicious rainstorms. A handful of nearly extinct animal species are kept on the sprawling estate of Maclovio Pulchris, a pop star modeled on Michael Jackson, while Tyrone O'Shaughnessy Tierwater, onetime heroic eco-warrior and now aged ex-con, manages the motley menagerie of hyenas, wart hogs, foxes and lions. A call from his former comrade in arms (and ex-wife), Andrea Knowles Cotton Tierwater, prompts in Tierwater memories of the heyday of Earth Forever!, an environmental action group modeled on Earth First!, in the late 1980's and 1990's. Flipping back and forth between the present and past, Boyle fills us in bit by bit on Tierwater's back story, which, in fact, provides the novel's slim narrative momentum save for some ''Bringing Up Baby'' high jinks with animals.</p>
        <p>Characters with oddball monikers are a much-worn 60's trope, one that hardly furthers their believability, yet Boyle can't let go of the gimmick. (Then again, what can you expect from a writer once named Tom Boyle, who reinvented himself, via a relative's name, as T. Coraghessan Boyle?) Likewise, we learn that Tierwater is ''half an Irish Catholic and half a Jew,'' but this lineage in no way informs the story; it's just evidence of clever confection. This wrapped-with-a-ribbon quality wouldn't matter if Boyle delivered the tactile presence of an actual person in his prose. But as a narrator, Tierwater's a simile-besotted show-off.</p>
        <p>In the space of two paragraphs, he describes storms ''stacked up out over the Pacific like pool balls on a billiard table,'' slamming a roof around ''like a giant Frisbee'' and picking up a fox ''like Dorothy'' while the rain snaps in his face ''like a wet towel.'' After prolonged exposure, this prose ends up flying like a Frisbee wrapped in a wet towel. Boyle won't let up enough to give Tierwater a mind of his own.</p>
        <p>That's a shame because the setup is provocative; Boyle wants to probe the barbed contradiction at the heart of environmental activism: ''To be a friend of the earth, you have to be an enemy of the people.''</p>
        <p>The son of a tract-home and shopping-center builder, Tierwater is destined for an ordinary suburban life, tooling around in a gas guzzler, furthering suburban sprawl. On a camping trip, his wife, Jane (yes, plain old Jane), is stung by a bee and dies from an allergic reaction. After several years of single-fatherhood, he falls in love with Andrea, an Earth Forever! campaigner, and soon he is cementing himself and his teenage daughter, Sierra, into a logging road to save the trees.</p>
        <p>After their arrest, the girl is taken away and placed in a foster home. Having lost both Jane and Sierra to nature, Tierwater becomes an eco-terrorist, famous as ''the human hyena,'' whose destructive exploits -- he sets fire to a forest planted for timber harvesting -- are fueled at least as much by vengeance as by love for birds and flowers.</p>
        <p>Andrea reappears just as epic rainstorms flood Pulchris's compound and the animals are herded into the basement of the mansion. She's accompanied by a young eco-advocate, April Wind, who's writing a book about Sierra, now viewed as an environmental martyr. This stirs painful memories for Tierwater; he recalls kidnapping Sierra from foster parents, the two of them living under fake identities, and how, as a young woman reared as an eco-radical, she climbed a giant redwood and lived in the branches for three years before she slipped and fell dead at Tierwater's feet. All this sadness, loss and futile struggle might have undergirded this satire with some genuine emotion, but Boyle won't repress his inner jokester: ''I'm in love all over again. I am,'' Tierwater declares about Andrea. ''Standing there in the dark, the silence so profound it's beating in my veins with an unconquerable force . . . I'm almost sure of it. On the other hand, it could just be indigestion.'' Leaving aside the fact that this quip requires carbon dating, one wonders: if Boyle's characters don't take their inner lives seriously, why should readers?</p>
        <p>Boyle not only pulls the rug out from under his characters but occasionally does so to his own overboiled prose. Just a few pages earlier, we have read: ''We're in the James Brown Room, surrounded by images of the godfather of soul, his sunken eyes, glistening pompadour and thrusting chin replicated over and over till the walls seem to shift like the walls of a planetarium and his multiplied eyes become the stars in the sky. It's quite a trope, I know, but then I'm suffering from indigestion.'' Yes, it is ''quite a trope,'' but this self-parody doesn't exculpate him from descriptive assault, a crime that too readily communicates the narrator's frequently invoked stomach troubles. This kind of self-reflexive wisecracking provides a tonic jolt in some novels, but in a story this thin it only reminds us how little we care, how slight the tether is to any larger drama. An eco-stunt in which Tierwater and Andrea go naked, without supplies, into the woods for a month is meant to be the novel's defining set piece. Ravenously hungry, the environmentalists end up trying to club marmots and devouring whole colonies of mussels, as facile ironies proliferate around them. Quickly the comedy becomes a burlesque that flattens out potentially spiky questions about humanity's presence in the wild. But nuance never had a chance here; Boyle's high-concept, game-show-like conceit -- nude tree-huggers against the forest -- foreclosed that possibility.</p>
        <p>BOYLE can put his nimble mind to honest work. He endows the awkward, if slightly ridiculous, scene of a father and daughter shouting up and down a redwood tree with elegance and pathos: ''A gust shook the treetops, and Sierra's tree quaked till I could feel the recoil of it in my feet. I looked up and there she was, her face a distant, drawn-down splash of white in a welter of rocketing green needles. And then her voice, buffeted by the winds and assaulted by the rain, came drifting down like a leaf: 'Dad!' she called. 'Dad!' ''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, with its slack plotting, motiveless characters and unfruitful time shifting, ''A Friend of the Earth'' is a ragged, uninspired effort from this gifted writer. Although tricked out in fancy prose, both global catastrophe and one family's painful struggle remain unaffecting. There has always been a toylike quality to Boyle's work. In boisterous, joyously comic novels such as ''Water Music'' and ''World's End,'' he made the wheels spin and lights flash and we were taken by his fresh spirits and ability to conjure a circus within a sentence. But Boyle's special-effects humor has proved less durable than the work of sly comic masters like P. G. Wodehouse, Evelyn Waugh and Nathanael West. It's hard not to feel disappointed about the direction -- or lack of one -- this prolific author's talent has taken; he's writing the same kind of books he did nearly 20 years ago, to ever-diminishing laughter. The best hope may be that ''A Friend of the Earth'' marks a low point from which Boyle -- less desperate to wring giggles from his readers -- will rebound.</p>
        <p>Albert Mobilio writes for The Village Voice, Harper's Magazine and Newsday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Albert Mobilio writes for The Village Voice, Harper's Magazine and Newsday.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
