<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Gas Fireplace For Heat</title>
    <meta content="05HOME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fireplaces</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fireplaces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0D91E30F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Gas Fireplace For Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article offers advice on heating with gas fireplaces; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH energy prices rising and with real wood as tedious as ever to chop, stack and carry, growing numbers of homeowners are using increasingly efficient gas logs and gas-fueled fireplaces as a supplemental source of heat.</p>
        <p>Gas fireplaces come in three categories: B-vented, the oldest and least efficient; direct vented, which is much more efficient, and vent-free, the most efficient of all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH energy prices rising and with real wood as tedious as ever to chop, stack and carry, growing numbers of homeowners are using increasingly efficient gas logs and gas-fueled fireplaces as a supplemental source of heat.</p>
        <p>Gas fireplaces come in three categories: B-vented, the oldest and least efficient; direct vented, which is much more efficient, and vent-free, the most efficient of all.</p>
        <p>The vent-free fireplace is ''the fastest-growing gas appliance on the market today,'' said Ed Hahn, sales manager for DESA, a gas-fireplace manufacturer in Bowling Green, Ky. Mr. Hahn said that about 8 million vent-free heating appliances have been sold in the last 20 years.</p>
        <p>Vent-free fireplaces are accepted in 47 states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, said Mary S. Carson, program director for the Vent-Free Gas Products Alliance, an industry organization based in Arlington, Va. But the vent-free fireplace is not approved for use in New York City, which has more stringent requirements. Direct-vent and B-vent gas fireplaces can be used in the city as long as proper venting is provided in accordance with city codes.</p>
        <p>In a B-vented unit, the most commonly used in homes and apartments with existing fireplaces, the air used for combustion comes from inside the house while exhaust gases are vented outside through a pipe run up an existing chimney or installed as a stand-alone vent stack. ''With a B-vent system, most of the heat goes out the vent,'' Mr. Hahn said, adding that such systems are typically 30 to 40 percent efficient and are more often used ornamentally. ''If you want to use your fireplace as a heat source, you have to get a minimum of 70 percent efficiency. And that's where a direct vent system comes in.''</p>
        <p>Direct-vent systems are from 75 to 80 percent efficient, Mr. Hahn said. In such a system, he said, two vent pipes are connected to the fireplace -- an intake vent that brings combustion air in from the outside and an exhaust vent that directs the products of combustion from the inside out. That leaves warmed, indoor air indoors where it belongs. The system can be vented straight through an exterior wall, eliminating the need for an existing chimney.</p>
        <p>With a vent-free or ventless fireplace, he said, air from inside the house is taken into the firebox, where it is used to support combustion, and the byproducts are exhausted back into the house. The recycling of combustion air allows ventless fireplaces -- which do not need chimneys -- to achieve efficiency ratings of more than 99 percent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carson said that the combustion gases that are pumped back into living space are not a problem. While any fire that uses gas as a fuel will produce carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide, nitrogen dioxide, oxygen and water vapor, today's technology ensures that emissions fall well within nationally recognized safety standards. Even the largest vent-free gas fireplace, she said, produces about the same level of emissions as a four-burner gas stove with all four burners lit.</p>
        <p>Ilyse Fink, a spokeswoman for the New York City Department of Buildings, said that although vent-free gas fireplaces may be legal elsewhere in New York, they cannot be used in the city because they violate the city's Administrative Code.</p>
        <p>''The code currently provides that any gas-fueled heater must get its combustion air from outside the building,'' Ms. Fink said, adding that for such appliances to be legal the City Council would have to amend the code. Ms. Carson said the alliance was working with city officials in an attempt to do so.</p>
        <p>She said vent-free fireplaces are safe primarily because they are fitted with an oxygen detection safety-pilot, or O.D.S.</p>
        <p>The O.D.S., she said, is a simple $7 device whose sole function is to shut off the gas supply when oxygen levels in the room fall below a certain level. ''The amount of oxygen in the air we breath is about 20.9 percent,'' she said. ''So the O.D.S. is designed to shut off the gas supply to the fireplace when the oxygen level falls to 18.5 percent.''</p>
        <p>That is accomplished, she said, by placing what is known as a thermocouple -- a switch turned on or off by heat -- at the base of the flame produced by the fireplace's pilot light.  Under ordinary circumstances -- when oxygen levels are within the acceptable range -- the pilot light burns steadily and keeps the thermocouple hot. When oxygen levels fall below 18.5 percent, Ms. Carson said, the ignition flame ''jumps off the pilot light looking for a fuel source.'' When that happens, she said, the flame no longer heats the thermocouple evenly, causing the device to shut down the gas supply.</p>
        <p>''There has never been a death attributed to the use of a vent-free product since the O.D.S. was introduced in 1980,'' she said. While gas fireplaces can burn either natural gas or propane, she said, it is necessary to make sure the appropriate burner nozzle is installed for the fuel being used.</p>
        <p>Steve Plaff, a product manager for Lennox Hearth Products, a gas-fireplace manufacturer in Fullerton, Calif., said that a minor drawback to vent-free fireplaces is that they burn so cleanly the flame they produce is usually an uninspiring deep blue.</p>
        <p>''We saw that as an opportunity to create a better flame,'' Mr. Plaff said, explaining that his company now manufacturers a catalytic vent-free appliance that uses a ceramic-based substance inside the combustion chamber to produce a bright yellow flame.</p>
        <p>''You end up with a clean-burning but more lively flame,'' he said, adding that a catalytic vent-free fireplace costs from $1,500 to $3,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hahn, the sales manager for DESA, said that a standard vent-free fireplace sells for from $800 to $2,400, including the logs, a mantle, some wood trim and a base.</p>
        <p>Direct vent appliances, he said, sell for $600 to $1,000, while B-vent fireplaces generally cost from $350 to $500, excluding the cost of the necessary venting. Most gas-fireplace manufacturers make both stand-alone units and inserts that can be installed in an existing fireplace.</p>
        <p>Ernie Johnson, director of marketing for Varsity Plumbing &amp; Heating in Flushing, Queens, said that running a gas line to the fireplace or stand-alone unit could cost $500 or more, depending on the complexity of the work.</p>
        <p>''And make sure you hire a licensed plumber,'' he said. ''You don't want an amateur messing around with gas lines in your house.''</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
