<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Global Milestone for U.N., Local Chaos for New Yorkers</title>
    <meta content="02UN.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/02/nyregion/02UN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Jo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE2DD1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Global Milestone for U.N., Local Chaos for New Yorkers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Millennium Summit at United Nations, billed as biggest gathering of heads of state and government, is expected to spawn huge traffic snarls, numerous demonstrations and heavy security measures in New York City; UN has spent $700,000 on public relations campaign to inform New Yorkers about importance of meeting; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forget, just for a moment, that some of the weightiest world issues are up for discussion next week during the Millennium Summit at the United Nations, the biggest gathering of heads of state and government ''in human history,'' as the United Nations says. Poverty. Global warming. AIDS. Illiteracy. Urban decay.</p>
        <p>Let's talk New York weighty -- in-your-backyard weighty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forget, just for a moment, that some of the weightiest world issues are up for discussion next week during the Millennium Summit at the United Nations, the biggest gathering of heads of state and government ''in human history,'' as the United Nations says. Poverty. Global warming. AIDS. Illiteracy. Urban decay.</p>
        <p>Let's talk New York weighty -- in-your-backyard weighty.</p>
        <p>Unspeakable traffic snarls and about 175 curb-skipping motorcades near Kennedy Airport in Queens and the United Nations Plaza on the East Side. Thousands of Secret Service agents elbowing their way through 36 hotels and countless restaurants in pursuit of 245 ''protectees,'' from President Clinton to Prime Minister Ionatana Ionatana of Tuvalu.</p>
        <p>Police lookouts at major bridges and tunnels in Manhattan, 6,000 additional officers patrolling the streets and a knot of road closings mostly between 30th and 63rd Streets and between Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive and Seventh Avenue. Ninety-one scheduled public protests with a crush of demonstrators. Even mountains of garbage, piled on barges destined for the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island, left rotting upstream because of precautions against terrorism on the East River.</p>
        <p>All this will be dumped on a testy citizenry slogging back to work after the Labor Day finale to a summer that mostly never was, and on a city already besieged by the crowds at the United States Open in Queens.</p>
        <p>''Let me thank in advance the good people of New York, our neighbors in New York, for their patience,'' Louise Frechette, the deputy secretary general of the United Nations, said the other day in announcing the details of the three-day summit meeting, which begins on Wednesday. ''We know their patience will be tried in the course of the summit week, but we would like to invite them to be patient and to reassure them that this is really for a good cause.''</p>
        <p>Patience is not a characteristic generally associated with New Yorkers. Add an expected 159 world leaders and 86 first spouses to the seven million or so people here who already consider themselves very important, and the United Nations is looking at a titanic clash of egos and schedules.</p>
        <p>Ms. Frechette knows that. So does Secretary General Kofi Annan and almost everyone else who works at the United Nations headquarters. (After all, they live here as well, one official pointed out.) That is why New Yorkers are witnessing what the United Nations calls another first in human history: the world organization's effort to sell itself to the city as a worthy neighbor through a $700,000 promotional campaign.</p>
        <p>It has been 49 years since the 39-story Secretariat building on First Avenue opened as the United Nations' official home, but it seems it is never too late for an introduction.</p>
        <p>''We have always cared, but this is part of the new U.N., trying to be more inclusive and transparent and reaching out to everyone,'' said Susan Markham, chief of promotion and planning for the United Nations' department of public information. ''The public relations campaign is trying to get across to people the importance of this millennium meeting so that they won't feel so bad sitting in traffic jams.''</p>
        <p>It is also the closest the United Nations will come to apologizing for the world-class mess coming New York's way. ''It is hard getting around on a regular day, let alone when something like this is happening,'' Ms. Markham said. ''Saying, 'Sorry you are in a traffic jam' doesn't really help very much. Hopefully, New Yorkers will realize what is going on at the summit will affect their lives, too.''</p>
        <p>In televised public service announcements, Harry Belafonte talks about the serious tasks facing the United Nations gathering. Advertisements in subway trains, on Metropolitan Transportation Authority maps and at bus shelters pronounce, ''History will be made here.'' There will even be a Batman-style beacon of light, flashing a still-undisclosed message near the United Nations Plaza, to remind the vexed and vanquished that good shall prevail (starting, presumably, in some meeting room along the East River).</p>
        <p>The campaign is being donated by Brand Buzz, a division of Young &amp; Rubicam Inc. John Partilla, managing director of Brand Buzz, says the United Nations has ''an overall positioning and identity'' problem in New York that is only going to get worse with the anticipated fallout from the Millennium Summit.</p>
        <p>''People are quick to judge and say, 'We are inconvenienced,' '' Mr. Partilla said. ''We need to remind people that they are not selling shoes or soda pop over at the U.N. They are really working to solve problems.''</p>
        <p>Once that connection is made, he said, the strategy calls for New Yorkers to spontaneously proclaim their affection for the United Nations: ''Yes, there is some inconvenience, but I am proud to be in this city,'' the imagined self pep talk goes, Mr. Partilla said. Brand Buzz intentionally avoided direct references to traffic and other problems because that would ''just play up the negative,'' he said. (''Yes, there is some inconvenience, and curse this blasted place'' is not the monologue Mr. Partilla has in mind.)</p>
        <p>The test may be in how difficult things really get next week. New York is a place where the extraordinary can seem ordinary, but this time, the authorities say, the disruption will really be one of a kind. The upheaval is expected to begin tomorrow, when the first foreign dignitaries arrive; reach its worst stage on Thursday, when the biggest United Nations meetings are held; and ease sometime next weekend as everyone skips town.</p>
        <p>The three days of meetings are being described as a working summit meeting, not a celebration or commemoration. There will be no formal banquets or ceremonial toasts; the only ''nod to tradition,'' Ms. Frechette said, will be a group photograph. The heart of the gathering will be a series of small, informal discussions, which are intended to encourage the world's leaders to speak frankly about many problems. At the end, they are expected to adopt a declaration renewing their commitment to goals like preventing conflicts and expanding the Internet in poor countries.</p>
        <p>At its simplest, the problem New Yorkers will face next week can be explained with arithmetic: the larger the number of heads of state and government in attendance, the larger the number of possible threats. The larger the number of possible threats, the larger the number of security people. The larger the number of security people, the larger . . .</p>
        <p>''It is one thing when the president comes into town and you have one motorcade,'' said Lt. Stephen Biegel, a spokesman for the Police Department, which started planning for the summit meeting a year ago. ''But now you are talking about having all of the major players in the world coming into New York. It is going to be a difficult week.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that the city had budgeted $8 million in police overtime for the week. He said the 6,000 extra officers on the street were enough to deal with any chaos.</p>
        <p>Groups including adherents of the Chinese spiritual movement Falun Gong and Iranians living in exile have announced plans to join the spectacle. The authorities have identified the Cuban Mission on Lexington Avenue as a particular place to avoid for those who do not like their toes stomped or the contents of their handbags thoroughly scrutinized. Fidel Castro is expected there, with noisy crowds to follow.</p>
        <p>The mayor, who has made no secret of his distaste for Mr. Castro and the United Nations, reiterated his views at a news conference yesterday, calling Mr. Castro a ''murderer.''</p>
        <p>In addition to providing special security, Mr. Giuliani is not taking any chances with the West Nile virus. He said the United Nations Plaza and the rest of Manhattan north of 23rd Street would be sprayed for mosquitoes before the summit meeting began. Mr. Giuliani announced yesterday that a dead bird infected with the virus was discovered at the United Nations' doorstep at 42nd Street and First Avenue.</p>
        <p>''You have to remember, this illness is potentially the most dangerous for elderly people, and some of the people coming are elderly,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''So we want to make sure the U.N. is clear and safe.''</p>
        <p>Danny Spriggs, the assistant director for protective operations at the Secret Service, said the only event that compared to the Millennium Summit in terms of V.I.P. protection was the 50th anniversary celebration at the United Nations in 1995. But even then, only about 150 people needed Secret Service protection, compared with the 245 now on the agency's roster, he said. Eighteen have been classified as particularly high security risks, according to the police, and Mr. Clinton is scheduled to stay for three days, a visit that on its own is enough to turn much of Manhattan inside out.</p>
        <p>The Secret Service would not disclose details of its security arrangements. Mr. Spriggs said the demand for agents was so great that vacations had been canceled and personnel were being drawn from most of the service's 100 field offices and from the Internal Revenue Service, the Customs Service and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms.</p>
        <p>''It is an overwhelming challenge to say the least,'' Mr. Spriggs said.</p>
        <p>On the East River, the Coast Guard will be bogged down in debris, not diplomacy. With a watchful eye on the river-facing rooms of the United Nations complex, the Coast Guard will regulate the downstream flow of city trash toward Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Normally, the City Department of Sanitation sends four barges, each loaded with 620 tons of waste, from a transfer station in College Point, Queens, to the Fresh Kills landfill every day. But the river will be off-limits for such deliveries when summit meeting participants are using riverfront rooms because of vulnerability to a possible terrorist attack. (Untidy views are a less pressing issue.)</p>
        <p>The city has added a tugboat and three barges to its garbage fleet to handle the expected backup, but no one can say for sure how much trash will be affected and for how long.</p>
        <p>''We work on tides, so if the window of opportunity is available at the time when the tide is low, we won't be able to navigate the waters,'' said Peter Fenty, deputy commissioner of sanitation. ''If the material can't be shipped down the river, it will be held there until it can be shipped. We've added the extra barges because we might have to stack.''</p>
        <p>Lt. Cmdr. Michael McAllister, chief of the Coast Guard's marine response division, said the Coast Guard would also limit access to the river for pleasure boats from East 35th Street to the Queensboro Bridge. No boats will be allowed within 175 yards of the eastern Manhattan shoreline throughout the summit meeting, and at particular times, the entire width of the river will be closed.</p>
        <p>About three dozen boats from the Coast Guard and the New York Police Department will patrol the river and its bridges, as well as the waterways near Kennedy Airport, where most of the gathering's dignitaries are scheduled to arrive and depart. A floating command center will be set up on the Coast Guard cutter Bainbridge Island.</p>
        <p>What happens if, Hollywood style, an errant garbage barge crashes through the barriers and sets course for the United Nations?</p>
        <p>''All of our Coast Guard units have crew members armed and trained with general law enforcement procedures,'' Commander McAllister said.</p>
        <p>And the hoped-for marketing response? Yes, there is some inconvenience, but New Yorkers always enjoy a good show.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
