<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore, the Earnest Student and Natural Teacher, With a Sweet Tooth</title>
    <meta content="Y25GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Macomb (Mich)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D6123DF936A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore, the Earnest Student and Natural Teacher, With a Sweet Tooth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>MACOMB, Mich., March 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gore, the Earnest Student and Nato</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore was sitting around with a group of students when Sally Hannert, the drama teacher, plucked him out to participate in a theatrical exercise. A look of mild panic froze his face, but he gamely plunged in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore and Stephanie White, 12, were to play a father and daughter discussing her bad report card. But they could not use words, just gibberish, while another student, Rachel Burke, 11, had to guess the plot through their gestures and tone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore was sitting around with a group of students when Sally Hannert, the drama teacher, plucked him out to participate in a theatrical exercise. A look of mild panic froze his face, but he gamely plunged in.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore and Stephanie White, 12, were to play a father and daughter discussing her bad report card. But they could not use words, just gibberish, while another student, Rachel Burke, 11, had to guess the plot through their gestures and tone.</p>
        <p>''NNNNAAAARRRRVOOOO,'' the vice president said. Rachel interpreted the indistinct slur of vowels and choked consonants as the plight of a girl afraid of being attacked by a bear. Still, she perceived Mr. Gore as a benevolent figure and decided what he was saying was this: ''Everything will be O.K. I'll take care of it. I'm the vice president.''</p>
        <p>Stephanie rated him later as clueless, but a great success.</p>
        <p>''He didn't know what was going on,'' she told a reporter. ''But it was really fun to play with him.''</p>
        <p>From the drama class to a discussion on the Industrial Revolution to the cafeteria, where he wolfed down two slices of pepperoni pizza, two chocolate chip cookies and half a brownie, the vice president delved into suburban school life today, showing himself off as dutiful student and natural pedagogue -- and, his campaign hoped, in touch with ordinary Americans and more concerned about education than his Republican rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas.</p>
        <p>In the first ''school days'' of his campaign -- he promises one every couple of weeks and pledges to continue them if he is elected president -- Mr. Gore is using the novelty of a presidential candidate's spending an entire day in school to draw attention to his commitment to education.</p>
        <p>In a recent Pew survey, voters said Mr. Bush cared more about this vital issue than did Mr. Gore. But Gore aides believe that as Mr. Gore and his proposals become better known, he will catch up.</p>
        <p>''I think I can demonstrate to you during the course of this campaign that I have the perspective and heart to do the job,'' the vice president told a group of students, teachers and parents in the course of his day, which ran from a 7:45 a.m. hallway chat with school custodians to a 2 p.m. rally in the gym.</p>
        <p>The site was not random. The school, L'Anse Creuse Middle School North, sits smack in Macomb County, a landmark bellwether electoral district northeast of Detroit where Reagan Democrats first emerged and were then coaxed back to the Democratic fold by Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>Voters here -- many of them white, Roman Catholic, blue-collar and socially conservative -- represent one of Mr. Gore's greatest challenges. They voted for John McCain in the Republican primary this year and are being wooed by Mr. Bush, whose father won them over in 1988 and 1992. Mr. Gore needs to keep them and sought his way to their hearts today through their children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore uttered nary a word about the Bush family today, trying to focus instead on the concerns especially of suburban mothers here, from stopping school violence to nurturing their inner selves. He emphasized the importance of parental involvement and used the day as he used his town meetings in the primary season -- to convey that he is not a scripted politician but a real person, and a sensitive one at that.</p>
        <p>In a soft-focus, FM-radio voice, he told students at every opportunity to be focused and disciplined, as if sharing a campaign secret from his advisers.</p>
        <p>''Be true to yourself, be honest, keep a good sense of what's important in your life, set priorities, and if it is important enough for you to reach a goal, you can reach a goal,'' he said in response to a student who asked him how to succeed.</p>
        <p>The day was given over also to small revelations about the vice president, who, many people here said, once seemed cold and remote but now seemed like one of them.</p>
        <p>His day began after a sleepover on Thursday night at the home of a teacher, Claudia Amboyer, 52, and her husband, Donald, a former sheriff.</p>
        <p>Last night, Mrs. Amboyer fed the vice president chocolate cake (''Don't most men like chocolate cake?'' she asked later) and this morning cooked him scrambled eggs and bacon. She told him that she sold antiques and was interested to hear that Mr. Gore's father also sold antiques. She described the experience as ''wonderful and unnerving,'' telling reporters that she did not see any Secret Service agents but that a Winnebago mysteriously arrived in her driveway and stayed the night.</p>
        <p>She and the vice president rode to school together this morning in a cavalcade of suburban vans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore helped guide a civics discussion that moved from the Industrial Revolution to global warming to child labor laws.</p>
        <p>The parents of some students work in the auto industry, but as Mr. Gore questioned the students, he found few who were interested in doing work like their parents.</p>
        <p>Their aspirations, they told him as he toured a technical-education room, were different -- veterinarian, lawyer, marine biologist. One girl said she wanted to be an author, to which Mr. Gore responded: ''You must be a good writer. Do you know Annie Proulx? Get a book called 'Shipping News' and look at the way she writes.''</p>
        <p>But mostly, he wanted his listeners to know that he came as a student.</p>
        <p>''I learned in my work setting up the reinventing government program,'' he said, ''that the most important insights and lessons by far actually come from the people who are doing the hands-on work.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
