<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming Moves From Impassioned Words to Modest Deeds</title>
    <meta content="19CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/19/science/19CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DA113BF93AA25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming Moves From Impassioned Words to Modest Deeds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preparations are under way in New York metropolitan area for future in which climate and geography may be different because of global warming; on Long Island, Army Corps of Engineers is looking at how communities might protect themselves from rising sea levels; in New Jersey, state has begun program of buying out property owners whose homes or businesses are in vulnerable flood plains; New Jersey has adopted no-surrender policy, vowing to protect waterfront communities and tourism dollars they represent; because global warming does not mean simply hotter climate, but rather altering planet's heat and precipitation, wide array of futures may exist that include increased disease and contamination of water supply (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forget the diplomats dithering over protocols and the scientists agonizing over equations. The next wave of the global warming debate is about nuts and bolts. In the New York metropolitan area and in other cities and states, ordinary people in corporations and government -- engineers, teachers and bureaucrats -- are quietly beginning to plan for a future in which climate and geography may be decidedly different.</p>
        <p>Many steps are tiny and incremental and uncertain. Many are also self-contained, in some cases the result of a single individual in a city or state agency who has taken up the issue. But environmentalists and politicians say that early steps, in a field where the time horizon stretches into decades, are often the most crucial because they set the patterns and precedents that future generations in the region are likely to have to build upon if the full potential of global warming becomes real.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forget the diplomats dithering over protocols and the scientists agonizing over equations. The next wave of the global warming debate is about nuts and bolts. In the New York metropolitan area and in other cities and states, ordinary people in corporations and government -- engineers, teachers and bureaucrats -- are quietly beginning to plan for a future in which climate and geography may be decidedly different.</p>
        <p>Many steps are tiny and incremental and uncertain. Many are also self-contained, in some cases the result of a single individual in a city or state agency who has taken up the issue. But environmentalists and politicians say that early steps, in a field where the time horizon stretches into decades, are often the most crucial because they set the patterns and precedents that future generations in the region are likely to have to build upon if the full potential of global warming becomes real.</p>
        <p>''There's still scientific uncertainty, without a doubt, about what climate change will bring,'' said William D. Solecki, a professor in the earth and environmental studies department at Montclair State University in New Jersey and a director of a recent federal study on the effects of planetary warming on the New York metropolitan region. ''But there's a growing recognition that the future will be different from today.''</p>
        <p>On Long Island, the Army Corps of Engineers is looking at how to help communities protect themselves from rising sea levels that could bring storm surges miles inland. On Wall Street, El Nino seminars and weather-risk financing have become hallmarks of the newly climate-conscious. In some New York City public schools, complex fluid-dynamic equations of global warming are used to teach math and environmental consciousness.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, which environmentalists say is one of the most active states in coordinating climate-change policies, the state government has begun an aggressive program of buying out property owners whose homes or businesses are in vulnerable flood plains. State economic development officials have been enlisted to promote the idea that global warming defenses can even encourage economic growth, through an energy-efficiency program that helps businesses reduce emissions of greenhouse gases and save money on utility bills.</p>
        <p>''It's a balance -- you have to look out in 50- and 100-year increments, but you also have to grapple up front, what your preventative measures can result in now,'' said  New Jersey's commissioner of environmental protection, Robert C. Shinn Jr.</p>
        <p>Some experts say the new activity is a product of the region's reservoir of intellectual and financial capital, some of which is finding an outlet in climate-change work and tapping specialties as diverse as energy, oceanography and risk management.</p>
        <p>The United Nations, for instance, has become a leading research center on global climate issues. Columbia University's Earth Institute has taken the lead in examining local climate consequences, and the financial district is expected to become a global player in the climate-change economics that are involved in such systems as international trade in greenhouse gas emissions credits. How such a trading system should work is a main agenda item at the international global warming conference now under way in The Hague.</p>
        <p>''The metro area is a powerhouse of global warming stuff,'' said Michael Glantz, a senior scientist at the environmental and societal impact group within the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo. ''There's a lot of innovation, awareness, intellect and knowledge.''  What's missing, he said, are coordination and communication. ''People are still working in their own worlds and not crossing lines,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is also a sharp disagreement about what the region's approach should be, particularly whether governments should focus on adapting to an inevitable future, or on efforts to mitigate greenhouse gas emissions and thus to try to change that future, if only in a marginal way.</p>
        <p>Some groups, like Environmental Defense, a private conservation group, argue that local and state governments in the region should be actively preparing people for a significantly altered terrain in which some coastal areas may have to be surrendered to the rising seas. Scientists at Columbia have projected a worst-case scenario in which the sea rises nearly four feet in the metropolitan area over the next 100 years,  an increase that researchers said would pose particular risk to river estuaries.</p>
        <p>Most politicians, on the other hand, especially in New Jersey, have adopted what they call a no-surrender policy, vowing to protect at all costs waterfront communities and the millions of dollars in tourism and tax dollars they represent.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists have criticized New York City for declining to join an international federation of cities coordinating efforts to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. Members include Los Angeles and Chicago and, more locally, Bridgeport, Conn., and Newark and Maplewood, N.J.</p>
        <p>New York's defenders, including Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, say the city already has the lowest per capita emissions rate of greenhouse gases of any large city in the nation because its reliance on mass transit reduces automobile use, a main source of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The city, the mayor has said, is working on the problem in its own way. The Department of Design and Construction, for example, which oversees development and renovation of city government buildings, issued guidelines last year focusing especially on energy-saving technology, from fiber optic lighting to geothermal heating and cooling. The guidelines are being incorporated in 15 pilot projects, from the Queens Botanical Garden to Bronx Criminal Court.</p>
        <p>The broader plan, though, is to lead by example and hope that the designs catch on in the booming private construction trades, said Hillary Brown, an assistant commissioner at the department's office of sustainable energy. After electricity and natural gas and heating oil prices began climbing this year, she said, private contractors' and owners' interest in the new techniques has climbed, judging from the jump in requests for copies of the guidelines.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, private corporations with large international operations are working with the state to cut greenhouse gas emissions. Johnson &amp; Johnson, the pharmaceutical giant in New Brunswick, signed up with the state's greenhouse gas plan this summer and is putting it into action at its corporate units within the state. The next step: taking the plan to its worldwide corporate operations. ''In New Jersey, we will lead and the rest will follow,'' said Johnson &amp; Johnson's corporate energy director, Harry Kauffman.</p>
        <p>In many ways there is no single future to prepare for but rather a wide array of possible futures, because global warming does not necessarily mean simply a hotter climate. Altering the planet's system of heat and precipitation -- the result, many scientists say, of burning fossil fuels that release gases like carbon dioxide into the atmosphere -- is also expected to increase weather variability and heighten storm damage.</p>
        <p>Climate also varies and evolves naturally over time, aside from human influence. Average global temperatures were warmer at the last millennium, the year 1000, than they are today. But the ''Medieval warm period'' was then followed by nearly 500 years of sharply colder temperatures, ''the little ice age.'' Temperatures began rising again in the mid-1800's, at the same time that the Industrial Revolution, with its reliance on the burning of fossil fuels, was developing.</p>
        <p>A group studying the effect of altered weather conditions on New York City's water supply is considering one scenario in which the region is hotter and wetter in 2050 than today, and another scenario in which it is hotter and drier. Some researchers are looking at how rising salt water could contaminate underground aquifers on Long Island, and others are looking at whether alternative distribution systems like new aqueducts or water tunnels might be necessary once the rainfall pattern changes.</p>
        <p>Other effects of a new climate are completely unknowable. Doctors at the New York State Department of Health say that a warmer weather pattern in the 21st century could make the region more hospitable to foreign diseases like the West Nile virus, which was first detected locally last year. But human factors like an increasingly older population with weaker immune systems and the growth of international travel to exotic locales make the ebb and flow of the biosphere so complex that there is no way to prepare for a specific climate-induced health threat.</p>
        <p>''You have to anticipate the potential that there could be an introduction of some new diseases related to this,'' said Dr. Dale L. Morse, the director of the division of infectious disease at the New York State Department of Health. ''But climate is only one of several factors we are looking at, and it's hard to say what weight one factor may have over others.''</p>
        <p>Some planners are also afraid to share ideas, apparently out of concern about alarming the public. Scientists and environmental groups say that the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey has begun a comprehensive internal examination of how climate change could affect the region's transportation network, especially how runways at low-lying airports like La Guardia and Kennedy International could be protected from rising waters.</p>
        <p>Port Authority officials declined repeated requests to discuss their analysis or research. A spokesman, Steve Coleman, said researchers were concerned that preliminary ideas would be misconstrued as definitive plans.</p>
        <p>In other cases, climate goals are bumping against old-fashioned reality. In Brooklyn, a pilot science curriculum using sustainable energy as the thread to teach concepts about fossil fuels, gas emissions and climate has been tested in a few high schools over the last several years. But experts in environmental education say the program's future is in question because the State Regents exam, which all students must pass to graduate, still relies on traditional science.</p>
        <p>And some researchers are looking backward for possible lessons about climatic future. Energy conservation is considered one of the prime ways in which institutions and individuals can reduce greenhouse gas emissions. But Dr. Morse said that energy-saving efforts in the 1970's could have been partly to blame for the spread of Legionella pneumophila, or Legionnaires' disease. To conserve energy, Dr. Morse said, many hospitals reduced the temperature of their hot water by a few degrees, and that slight difference was apparently enough to allow the disease to propagate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
