<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Officials Devise a Plan to Rescue Coral Reefs</title>
    <meta content="28CORA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coral Reefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Files, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DB1E3DF93BA15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Officials Devise a Plan to Rescue Coral Reefs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN FILES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Files, John</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal government issues long-term plan to save coral reefs along coast of United States and its territories, setting aside many sites as ecological preserves over next 10 years; plan calls for 20 percent of all coral reefs in American-controlled waters to be designated ecological preserves by 2010, protecting them from pollution, fishing and other activity that could harm reefs; corals are tiny plantlike amnimals that thrive only in clean, clear water with plenty of sunlight; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal government has issued a long-term plan to save coral reefs along the coast of the United States and its territories, setting aside many sites as ecological preserves over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for 20 percent of all coral reefs in American-controlled waters to be designated ecological preserves by 2010, protecting them from pollution, fishing and other activity that could harm the reefs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal government has issued a long-term plan to save coral reefs along the coast of the United States and its territories, setting aside many sites as ecological preserves over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for 20 percent of all coral reefs in American-controlled waters to be designated ecological preserves by 2010, protecting them from pollution, fishing and other activity that could harm the reefs.</p>
        <p>''Protecting 20 percent of all U.S. reefs and other decisive actions called for in the new plan is crucial because two-thirds of the world's reefs may be dying,'' said D. James Baker, the under secretary for oceans and atmosphere at the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>''If current conditions continue,'' Mr. Baker said, ''an alarming 70 percent of the world's reefs may be gone by 2050. This rapid decline represents a serious threat to businesses, consumers, communities and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Corals are tiny plantlike animals that thrive only in clean, clear water with plenty of sunlight. They gradually build coral skeletons that form the elaborate reefs that then become home to thousands of fish, lobsters, sea turtles and other species.</p>
        <p>The United States has about 6,500 square miles of coral reefs, mostly off Florida, Texas, Hawaii and around American territories in the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>The reefs are particularly vulnerable because they prosper in shallow water near shore, which exposes them to pollution from marine debris and chemicals, overfishing and destructive actions like fishing with cyanide and dynamite, vessel grounding and anchoring, and even global climate change.</p>
        <p>This year's budget contains the first federal money directed toward saving the coral reefs: $6 million to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and $5 million to the Interior Department. President Clinton has requested $25 million for the 2001 budget.</p>
        <p>In a separate effort, the National Park Foundation, a nonprofit partner of the National Park Service, is studying the effectiveness of transplanting healthy fragments of coral to damaged reefs in the waters of the Virgin Island National Park.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to jump-start reef recovery by transplanting healthy, naturally occurring, broken-off pieces of fast-growing coral species to new locations where they are more likely to survive,'' said Ginger Garrison, the project's principle researcher.</p>
        <p>Coral reefs and their ecosystems support billions of dollars of tourism each year, federal officials said, with over a billion dollars generated in the Florida Keys alone. The reefs' value for commercial and recreational fishing is nearly $200 million a year. In all, reef-related activities generate as much as $375 billion annually, the Commerce Department says.</p>
        <p>They are also considered as possible sources of new medicines.</p>
        <p>And, they are natural buffers along shorelines protecting against erosion and property damage.</p>
        <p>In addition to the ecological preserves, the plan sets goals for mapping all coral reefs in the United States by 2009. The oceanic administration also wants to create a national monitoring system.</p>
        <p>But commercial and recreational fishing interests, concerned about fishing bans, are seeking alternatives, possibly including catch-and-release policies in protected areas.</p>
        <p>Eddie Cameron, a tournament fisherman from Morehead City, N.C.,  said a ban on fishing and other activities would be too extreme.</p>
        <p>''There is a need to protect the resources,'' said Mr. Cameron, who fishes extensively along the coasts of Virginia, North Carolina, Florida and Texas. ''But a ban would be devastating for the people who fish and dive on the reefs. It would absolutely devastate the Keys.''</p>
        <p>Roger T. Rufe, president of the Center for Marine Conservation in Washington, applauded the action, but he said that more needed to be done to combat water pollution, including legislation that would provide sufficient money for a plan ''to insure complete protection and conservation'' of coral reefs.</p>
        <p>Jack Sobel, a program director at the center, pointed out that for a resource that provides many billions of dollars of revenue, the money proposed in the plan was ''limited and shortsighted,'' only a first step towardappreciating ''the real value of the coral reefs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
