<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rare Plant Community Is Vanishing</title>
    <meta content="25HAMM$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Everglades (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Derr, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Everglades National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDD133AF936A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rare Plant Community Is Vanishing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK DERR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Derr, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>EVERGLADES NATIONAL PARK, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The few surviving hardwood forests rising on elevated ground in Florida Everglades contain unusual collection of tropical plant species important to regional biodiversity; forests, or hammocks, face threats from hurricanes and storm surges, fire, invasion by exotic plants, sudden freezes and rising sea level; scientists say proposal to restore freshwater Everglades will do little to save coastal hammocks; diagram; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a clear, warm day recently, Dr. Thomas Armentano picked his way through a stand of red mangroves near the southern edge of the Florida peninsula and stepped into a bone dry stretch of marl prairie littered with scores of uprooted, sun-bleached buttonwood trees.</p>
        <p>With tangled roots spanning six feet and trunks approaching three feet in diameter, the weathered relicts were of a size seldom found among living South Florida buttonwood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a clear, warm day recently, Dr. Thomas Armentano picked his way through a stand of red mangroves near the southern edge of the Florida peninsula and stepped into a bone dry stretch of marl prairie littered with scores of uprooted, sun-bleached buttonwood trees.</p>
        <p>With tangled roots spanning six feet and trunks approaching three feet in diameter, the weathered relicts were of a size seldom found among living South Florida buttonwood.</p>
        <p>Not more than a hundred yards from where he stood, the desiccated trees faded into a tropical hardwood hammock, one of a vanishing few coastal hammocks that exist only around Florida Bay in Everglades National Park and parts of the Caribbean, including the Yucatan.</p>
        <p>This particular hammock is unique in the United States because of its size, its marl substrate and its orchids, said Dr. Armentano, chief biologist for the South Florida Natural Resources Center, located in Everglades National Park. Marl is a clay-like limestone.</p>
        <p>Covering just over 200 acres and lying less than a mile north of Florida Bay, the hammock hosts a mind-numbing profusion of wild bromeliads and orchids, some of breathtaking dimensions.</p>
        <p>To protect them from plant thieves, who have nearly stripped other areas bare, Dr. Armentano asked that the hammock's precise location be kept secret.</p>
        <p>Hammocks -- basically forests of hardwoods rising on elevated ground from among pines, marshes and old shorelines -- were once common throughout South Florida, especially along the coasts. For much of the past century, they fell to loggers, developers and charcoal makers, who leveled vast stands of buttonwood. Nearly all of the remaining hammocks are now found only in the region's parks and preserves.</p>
        <p>Covered head to toe to guard against the sun, poison plants, thorns and mosquitoes that define walking in the Everglades, Dr. Armentano led a reporter and photographer on a tour of the fallen buttonwood forest and its neighboring hammock to illustrate the forces that threaten the survival of some of the nation's rarest plant communities.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most significant of those threats, he said, pointing to the bleached buttonwoods, are hurricanes that can remake whole landscapes. ''These coastal hardwood communities are uniquely tied to tropical storms,'' Dr. Armentano said. ''Storm effects in Florida Bay have helped create them, and yet extremely violent storms can also destroy them.''</p>
        <p>This buttonwood forest was toppled by the 1935 Labor Day hurricane, a Category 5 monster with winds estimated at 200 to 250 miles an hour. That storm battered the Florida Keys, killing an estimated 800 workers on the Overseas Highway, before churning across Florida Bay into the Everglades. Hurricanes Donna in 1960 and Betsy in 1965 uprooted the trees left standing. Mature buttonwood is so hard and dense it does not rot in the hot, wet South Florida climate, and so the dried-out trees remain, dotting what in the aftermath of those storms became a low-lying prairie of cactuses and other succulents growing precariously from salty ground and inundated for much of the rainy season.</p>
        <p>In addition to hurricanes and their storm surges that can drive saltwater, sand and mud far inland, other threats to coastal hammocks are fire, invasion by exotic plants, sudden freezes and rising sea level, Dr. Armentano said.</p>
        <p>Scientists agree that the $7.8 billion plan to restore what remains of the freshwater Everglades, the historic ''river of grass,'' now under consideration in Congress, will do little to save coastal hammocks. ''It's hard to put a finger on something, like hydrological restoration, you can do to preserve them,'' Dr. Armentano said.</p>
        <p>Everglades hammocks are the region's uplands, standing high enough that they escape flooding for much, if not all of the year. In this flat and subtle land, high enough means anywhere from several inches to about six feet for those on Indian middens, or refuse heaps.</p>
        <p>Of the 164 woody species native to these forests, Dr. Armentano said, 135 are tropical, of West Indian origin. The rest are temperate North American trees and shrubs at the southern end of their range. Many of the 14 distinct types of hammocks that botanists have identified are named for their dominant vegetation, like thatch palm, mahogany, gumbo limbo, live oak (a temperate tree) or tropical hardwood.</p>
        <p>Most biologists believe that the Caribbean plants were brought to the North American mainland by migrating birds, winds and tides. They took root in the last 5,000 years, when the Florida peninsula became warmer and wetter, and the Everglades were formed.</p>
        <p>The precious hammocks bordering Florida Bay occupy old sand ridges, marine marl deposits, or dead coral that seldom stand more than three-feet above sea level.  ''Hammocks like this are only found in Caribbean areas where the soils and moisture conditions are similar,'' Dr. Armentano said. ''But the islands are overdeveloped and there have been quite a few hurricanes in those areas in recent years, so we don't know their condition.''</p>
        <p>Leading the way into the hammock, he pointed out that as the land rose barely more than an inch, the vegetation began to change from ground-hugging succulents to grasses growing under scrub buttonwood and manchineel, a plant considered more noxious than poison ivy. In the dappled shade also grew wild hibiscus, wild cotton, wild cinnamon, limber caper and three types of rangy cactuses.</p>
        <p>After a rise of another few inches, that vegetation faded into full hammock, a nearly impenetrable, multilayered forest with vines reaching high into the tree tops. A riot of Spanish stopper, blolly, and various hardwood saplings formed a thick understory beneath a canopy of Jamaica dogwood, mastic, sabal palm, mahogany, gumbo limbo, pigeon plum and wild lime, including one Dr. Armentano called the largest he had seen. The presence of many of these plants, he said, showed that the hammock was free of the salt permeating the marl prairie.</p>
        <p>Tropical hardwoods usually have short trunks and vast canopies, the better to shed limbs while remaining upright in hurricanes, Dr. Armentano said, but here, because of past storms, there was a lack of such big trees. Instead young trees rose straight for 20 feet or more through the riotous tangle, seeking sunlight.</p>
        <p>Dr. Armentano said that there were about a dozen canopy species represented in the hammock, with another 20 or so found in the understory and among the epiphytes, or air plants. The plants put down horizontal roots, reaching no deeper than a foot, in the thin, nutrient-poor soil, created from decaying hammock vegetation.</p>
        <p>Plants grew on top of and around other plants. A strangler fig entombed a tall sabal palm, leaving only the fronds visible. On an ancient buttonwood, its outstretched limbs covered with epiphytes, a cactus grew out of a bromeliad. A shriveled resurrection fern lay waiting for rain to revive it on a 20-foot-long limb of a Jamaica dogwood.</p>
        <p>Bromeliads and orchids -- cow horn, mule ear, dollar, ghost and butterfly -- crowded dead and weathered but still living buttonwoods, their favorite host, and spilled onto other trees. Some of those epiphytes were three to four feet in diameter. The flowers had dropped from most of the orchids, but after a search, Dr. Armentano found a large mule-ear orchid with a long cascade of gold and rust colored blossoms.</p>
        <p>This tropical hardwood hammock has remained remarkably free of destructive exotics, like Brazilian pepper, a shrub that grows so densely it crowds out all other vegetation, and Colubrina asiatica, a vine that covers the canopy, shading out all plants beneath it. But colubrina has already invaded nearby hammocks, and park biologists fear its advance.</p>
        <p>For 35 years the hammock has also escaped freezes, like the two in the 1980's that destroyed orchids in much of the park. But this and other coastal hammocks that are already rare may ultimately fall to hurricanes and rising tides, especially if, as many scientists believe, global warming is accelerating sea level rise, while intensifying hurricanes.</p>
        <p>Already, saltwater is undercutting sand ridges holding thatch palm hammocks on the north shore of Florida Bay and has destroyed mangrove and hardwood forests on several islands in the bay itself, Dr. Armentano said.</p>
        <p>''Tidal gauges in Key West have recorded a nine-inch rise in sea level, since 1930,'' said Dr. Harold Wanless, professor of geological sciences at the University of Miami. ''Even if you add just one foot in the next century to what we have already -- and I think that is a ridiculously conservative estimate -- you see that these coastal hammocks are pretty well doomed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
