<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="05OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soybeans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caffeine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">landec corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">vyn, tony j (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDB1330F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Tony J Vyn is testing whether seeds coated with thin polymer developed by Landec Corp can be used to help farmers overlap winter wheat and soybeans in same field; researchers clone gene responsible for enzyme that plays key role in caffeine production; suggest transgenic plant, with this gene sequence inactivated, could produce decaffinated coffee beans or tea leaves; die-offs of frogs and other amphibians are still occurring in parts of United States; phenomenon remains something of mystery, although researchers have pinpointed cause of some die-offs; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coated Seeds for Farming</p>
        <p>M&amp;M's melt in your mouth (and not in your hands!) because, as the old TV commercial said, they are covered by a thin candy shell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coated Seeds for Farming</p>
        <p>M&amp;M's melt in your mouth (and not in your hands!) because, as the old TV commercial said, they are covered by a thin candy shell.</p>
        <p>A Purdue University agronomist is testing whether a similar idea will work for seeds as a means of increasing farm efficiency. Using a thin polymer coating developed by the Landec Corporation of Menlo Park, Calif., the agronomist, Dr. Tony J. Vyn, is testing whether coated seeds can be used to help farmers overlap winter wheat and soybeans in the same field.</p>
        <p>Relay planting, as the technique is known, is practiced with wheat and soybeans in southerly parts of the Midwest. The problem in more northerly parts, like Wisconsin and northern parts of Indiana and Illinois, is that planting the soybeans early enough so that the existing wheat stalks are not damaged by the planting machinery often results in soybean plants that are too spindly and high when the wheat harvest takes place. Thus much of the soybean crop is destroyed in harvesting the wheat.</p>
        <p>The polymer-coated seeds, which should be on the market in a few years, work like a time-release aspirin, delaying seed germination by about two weeks until heat and moisture in the soil break down the coating. That would allow farmers to plant soybeans early, without damaging the wheat, and yet produce soybean plants that are short enough to be missed when the wheat combine cuts through the field.</p>
        <p>Dr. Vyn said that the coating could also include a fungicide to ward off mold that can rot seeds. Fungicides maintain their activity longer in colder soil, so putting a coated seed into the ground earlier would have the added advantage of protecting it longer.</p>
        <p>Natural Decaffeination</p>
        <p>Decaffeinated coffee usually gets that way through an industrial process that uses a solvent, commonly ethyl acetate, to remove the caffeine from the bean. But what if coffee (and tea) could be grown without caffeine in the first place?</p>
        <p>That is the prospect of new research by scientists in Japan and Scotland who have cloned the gene responsible for an enzyme that plays an important role in caffeine production. Their work was reported in Nature.</p>
        <p>The enzyme, called caffeine synthase, acts as a catalyst in the final two steps in the caffeine-making pathway in the coffee or tea plant. So the researchers suggest that a transgenic plant, with this gene sequence inactivated, could produce decaf coffee beans or tea leaves. That is one genetically modified plant that might actually find favor among some members of the public.</p>
        <p>Dying Amphibians</p>
        <p>Die-offs of frogs and other amphibians are still occurring in parts of the United States, and although researchers in some cases have been able to pinpoint a cause, the phenomenon remains something of a mystery.</p>
        <p>One of the most recent die-offs involved tiger salamanders at a lake in North Dakota. Researchers from the United States Geological Survey first noticed sick salamanders in May; by July, population counts were far below the previous years.</p>
        <p>Geological service researchers have blamed a type of virus called an iridovirus for most of the deaths in North Dakota. Iridoviruses have also been linked to other salamander die-offs in recent years, and the researchers say that they are probably the cause of other die-offs this summer, including the deaths in late June of hundreds of spring peeper frogs at Acadia National Park in Maine and of wood frogs, bullfrogs and salamanders in North Carolina.</p>
        <p>What is still not known is whether the die-offs, which are not limited to this country, are short-term events or a part of a longer-term phenomenon that is only now coming to light. Among theories being investigated to help explain the population declines are increased exposure to ultraviolet radiation (due to thinning of the ozone layer), pesticide contamination and rising temperatures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
