<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y21BRI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/21/world/21BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DE163AF932A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>KASHMIR: INDIAN OVERTURE SNUBBED -- An Indian peace overture in Kashmir -- a unilateral cease fire in the Muslim holy month of Ramadan -- was snubbed by militant groups and Pakistan with reactions ranging from skepticism to contempt. ''This is typical Indian politics based on fraud,'' said the hard-line group Lashkar-i-Toiba. Pakistan, which has strongly backed the 11-year insurgency, said that as ''a test of its sincerity'' India must offer to include Pakistan in any talks or expose the gesture as a ruse. This year, Ramadan is to begin at sundown on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>KASHMIR: INDIAN OVERTURE SNUBBED -- An Indian peace overture in Kashmir -- a unilateral cease fire in the Muslim holy month of Ramadan -- was snubbed by militant groups and Pakistan with reactions ranging from skepticism to contempt. ''This is typical Indian politics based on fraud,'' said the hard-line group Lashkar-i-Toiba. Pakistan, which has strongly backed the 11-year insurgency, said that as ''a test of its sincerity'' India must offer to include Pakistan in any talks or expose the gesture as a ruse. This year, Ramadan is to begin at sundown on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDIA: WORKERS RAMPAGE -- Tens of thousands of workers facing job losses rampaged across New Delhi to protest a court order closing polluting factories, witnesses and the police said. Scores of people were wounded, many with gunshot wounds, as the protesters randomly attacked shopping malls, government buildings and private vehicles, they said. Twenty-six police officers were hospitalized and at least five rioters were shot and seriously wounded.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>BANGLADESH: EX-DICTATOR SURRENDERS -- The deposed president and former dictator Hussain Muhammad Ershad turned himself in to begin a five-year jail term for corruption. Mr. Ershad, 70, leader of the main faction of the opposition Jatiya Party, had refused to surrender until the Supreme Court upheld the verdict, handed down in August. Mr. Ershad seized power in a coup in 1982 and was deposed in a 1990 mass pro-democracy uprising.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>GERMANY: CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATS' No. 2 -- The Christian Democrats overwhelmingly elected Laurenz Meyer, 52, as their new deputy leader, confirming him in an office he took over in October. Still haunted by former Chancellor Helmut Kohl's slush funds scandal and divided on the issue of immigration, the conservative opposition party is trying to take the political offensive in view of the next general election in 2002.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>NETHERLANDS: FRANCE AND U.S. CLASH -- France and the United States clashed at the United Nations climate conference in The Hague on reducing greenhouse gas emissions. President Jacques Chirac of France began the conference's second and last week by implying that the United States was trying to get out of its promised reductions under the 1997 Kyoto protocol. The United States wants unlimited ability to buy carbon credits from countries that will easily meet their own targets and have credits to spare. The Europeans want a cap on credit trading.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CZECH REPUBLIC: CENTER-RIGHT VICTORY -- The center-right opposition Quad-Coalition swept the second round of voting for a third of the Senate, dealing a blow to the governing Social Democrats. That result from the election on Sunday effectively killed plans by the minority government and its parliamentary ally, the Civic Democrats, to cut the powers of President Vaclav Havel through constitutional reform. The outcome stripped the Social Democrats and their ally of their majority in the 81-seat house.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: OCALAN HEARING -- The European Court of Human Rights was due to hear claims today by the Kurdish leader Abdullah Ocalan that his rights had been violated by his trial and imprisonment in Turkey. Mr. Ocalan was convicted of separatist activities and sentenced to death. The Strasbourg-based court asked Turkey to stay the death penalty until it had a chance to review the case, which is being closely watched because Turkey has applied for membership in the European Union, which forbids capital punishment.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Olson (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: FORMER BASQUE LEADER EXTRADITED -- France extradited a former armed Basque separatist leader, Jose Maria Arregui Erostarbe, to Spain where he faces charges of being involved in 14 attacks by the E.T.A. group, including a 1987 car bombing in which 11 people died. Mr. Arregui, 54, was the last of three E.T.A. chiefs arrested in 1992 in southwestern France to be handed over to Spain after serving French jail sentences.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Jones (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: EUROPE URGES MEAT BAN -- A team of European Union scientists is urging Europe to ban all meat imports from Canada until it complies with European regulations on the use of hormones, antibiotics and other chemicals in cattle. The recommendation was made public by the Canadian Health Coalition, a group that says the chemicals cause cancer.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>CUBA: SEEKING EXTRADITION -- Cuba and Venezuela are seeking the extradition of Luis Posada Carriles, a Cuban exile who Fidel Castro says planned to kill him during the weekend's Ibero-American summit meeting in Panama City. Mr. Castro's government has asked that Mr. Posada and three others detained in Panama be sent to Cuba. Venezuela also seeks the extradition of Mr. Posada, who in 1985 escaped from a Venezuelan prison where he was awaiting trial on charges of bombing a Cuban jetliner.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>TANZANIA: NEW PARLIAMENT OPENS -- President Benjamin Mkapa opened Tanzania's new Parliament with a promise to fight corruption and take action to save the troubled union between the mainland and semiautonomous Zanzibar. Mr. Mkapa, left, pledged to tackle poverty and corruption in his second five-year term and also said a special committee would be formed to confront the Zanzibar issue. Mr. Mkapa won re-election in the general election last month, but voting was marred by accusations that the governing Party for the Revolution cheated in Zanzibar.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
