<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Countries Resist Cutting Fuel Taxes</title>
    <meta content="Y14EUR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/14/world/14EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6D91238F937A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Countries Resist Cutting Fuel Taxes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Truckers and farmers around continental Europe continue their protests, but political leaders dug in their heels against cuts in gasoline tax; acts of defiance in Belgium and Germany described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Truckers and farmers around continental Europe continued their protests today, but political leaders dug in their heels against cuts in the gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>In the eastern German city of Schwerin, about 400 truckers and farmers heckled Chancellor Gerhard Schroder as he visited the city, and they drowned out much of his speech with whistles and horns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Truckers and farmers around continental Europe continued their protests today, but political leaders dug in their heels against cuts in the gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>In the eastern German city of Schwerin, about 400 truckers and farmers heckled Chancellor Gerhard Schroder as he visited the city, and they drowned out much of his speech with whistles and horns.</p>
        <p>In Belgium, truck drivers blocked fuel deliveries to express their anger at the rising prices and tied up streets in Brussels and the port city of Antwerp.</p>
        <p>Oil and gasoline prices have soared, and in Germany gasoline is fetching about $4 a gallon. That has fomented public ire at fuel taxes, which make up as much as three-quarters of the cost.</p>
        <p>But mindful of the huge contribution to government coffers, political leaders have ruled out a cut in fuel taxes and have proposed narrower and often temporary reductions on other taxes.</p>
        <p>''Drop this dangerous game, because it could threaten the growth and employment prospects we currently have,'' Chancellor Schroder warned protesting truckers in Schwerin today.</p>
        <p>And he told ARD television, ''We have to make the use of our resources, especially energy, more costly. The money we get will go immediately to cut pension insurance costs. This policy has been a success, and we can't change it.''</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Guy Verhofstadt of Belgium refused demands for a fuel tax rebate for the trucking industry, offering instead reductions in taxes on truckers' insurance and a postponement on paying next year's road taxes.</p>
        <p>Belgian truckers seized the inner ring road in Brussels, but outside the view of television cameras, the mood was surprisingly tranquil, with some protesters even sipping beer at an outdoor cafe near the Transportation Ministry.</p>
        <p>Alain Gerlache, a spokesman for the Belgian government, said officials simply were not willing to offer a permanent reduction in gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>''The truckers are asking for a structural reduction in the price of fuel,'' Mr. Gerlache said today. ''We don't agree to that. European Union rules don't allow it.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, France agreed last week to cut its fuel tax by 15 percent, a move that largely calmed protests that had gathered force there.</p>
        <p>Though gasoline taxes are sky-high across most of Europe, they have become a particularly sore topic among Germans because Mr. Schroder's government has pushed through two gasoline tax increases in the last year, with another one to take effect in January.</p>
        <p>Germany's center-right opposition party, the Christian Democratic Union, has begun an advertising and petitioning campaign aimed at blaming Mr. Schroder's Social Democratic Party and its coalition partner, the Green Party, for the gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>The German federation of truckers announced plans to hold a four-hour slowdown on Sept. 26. As envisioned, the truckers will creep along at 40 miles an hour on the autobahns and well below the speed limits on smaller roads as well.</p>
        <p>Among other protests today, truckers blocked many of the roads in and around the Belgian port of Antwerp, and they succeeded in blocking many if not most of the gasoline trucks.</p>
        <p>Total Fina Elf S.A., Belgium's leading gasoline supplier, said it was able to deliver only about 20 percent of the gasoline its customers needed. ''If it lasts for a couple more days, the damage could be catastrophic,'' a company spokesman told Reuters today.</p>
        <p>For the most part, highway traffic and gasoline supplies were normal in most countries and did not come close to the paralysis this week in Britain.</p>
        <p>Italy, where strikes are common, remained tranquil and free of gasoline shortages as trucking leaders and government officials negotiated over competing proposals for relief.</p>
        <p>The eruption of widespread anger about high gasoline prices poses a problems for many European political leaders.</p>
        <p>Most of the governments are now controlled by left-of-center parties, most of which support high fuel taxes as a method of reducing gasoline consumption and reducing the production of ''greenhouse'' gases that trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Gasoline taxes also represent an important and simple way for governments to raise revenue. And under rules restricting budget deficits for countries that have adopted the euro as a common currency, most governments would have to offset any reductions in gasoline taxes by increasing other taxes or by cutting spending.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
