<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1223623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DC133EF93AA2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Explosions Damaged Sub, Russian Admiral Says  The Northern Fleet's commander acknowledged that an internal explosion devastated the nuclear submarine Kursk before it sank last Saturday, confirming Western intelligence reports of underwater explosions. A Russian rescue vehicle finally docked with the sub, but its crew said damage to the sub had made it impossible to make the watertight connection needed to enter the sub.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Bid to Resurrect the Concorde  British and French aviation regulators formed a committee to examine ways to return the Concorde to service ''in safe conditions'' that would protect it against the flaws behind last month's crash near Paris.</p>
        <p>A2</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Explosions Damaged Sub, Russian Admiral Says  The Northern Fleet's commander acknowledged that an internal explosion devastated the nuclear submarine Kursk before it sank last Saturday, confirming Western intelligence reports of underwater explosions. A Russian rescue vehicle finally docked with the sub, but its crew said damage to the sub had made it impossible to make the watertight connection needed to enter the sub.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Bid to Resurrect the Concorde  British and French aviation regulators formed a committee to examine ways to return the Concorde to service ''in safe conditions'' that would protect it against the flaws behind last month's crash near Paris.</p>
        <p>A2</p>
        <p>Bittersweet Farewells in Korea  The four-day reunions in Seoul and Pyongyang ended, as planned, with 200 North and South Koreans returning to their homes on the divided peninsula. More exchanges are planned under a recent accord signed by the two Koreas' leaders.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>U.S. Delays Asylum Decision  Immigration officials were said to have delayed until next month a decision on whether to grant asylum to Zhang Hongbao, the leader of a Chinese spiritual movement, after Chinese officials appealed for his return and submitted detailed charges that he had raped followers.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>U.N. Sending Nigerian to Congo  General Abdulsalami Abubakar, left, who presided over Nigeria's return to democracy last year, is being sent to Congo by Secretary General Kofi Annan to try to salvage the peacekeeping operation there.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>U.S. Effort on Mideast Peace  The State Department's special envoy, Dennis Ross, met in Jerusalem with Prime Minister Ehud Barak in an effort to break an impasse in the negotiations for an Israeli-Palestinian peace agreement.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Kurds Hopeful on Rights Policy  Turkey's Kurdish population expressed tempered enthusiasm at the government's decision to end a 34-year holdout and sign two United Nations conventions on the social and political rights of minorities.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-13, 16</p>
        <p>Bush Says Gore Uses A Divisive Strategy  Gov. George W. Bush, campaigning in Tennessee, Vice President Al Gore's home state, said Mr. Gore's convention speech sought to sow division and foment class warfare.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, campaigning by riverboat on the Mississippi, said some people strove harder and less successfully than others and that he was seeking to be their champion.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Leaders at a Democratic National Committee meeting turned to how to attack the Republicans and Mr. Bush on a variety of issues, with a heavy emphasis on abortion.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>The Democrats' convention, which received greater prime-time network television coverage, did slightly better in the prime-time ratings than the Republicans' did, though audiences for both events were down over all compared with 1996.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The role, and performance, of political Web sites at the conventions was less than some had expected.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Skin Cancer Surgery for McCain  Senator John McCain said he would have two malignant melanomas removed this morning in Arizona.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Judge Disclosed Grand Jury  Richard D. Cudahy, a federal appeals court judge in Chicago appointed to the bench by President Jimmy Carter in 1979, said he was the source of a report that a new grand jury had been impaneled by the independent counsel investigating President Clinton's relationship with a former White House intern.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Tripp Lawsuit Reassigned  A lawsuit brought by Linda R. Tripp against the government has been taken away from a judge who has been critical of the Clinton administration and given to a judge appointed by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Scientist Portrayed as Spy  Prosecutors sought to bolster their case against Wen Ho Lee, a former Los Alamos scientist accused of mishandling nuclear weapons secrets, by arguing that a visit to Beijing in 1988 transformed him into a virtual spy for China. Dr. Lee is seeking bail before his trial.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Pessimism on Wildfires  Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt said that western wildfires were likely to get worse and that little could be done to slow their progress.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>U.S. Says Mobs Smuggle Fake Vodka to Europe  A federal inquiry into organized crime in the ports of Newark and Elizabeth, N.J., found a loose-knit web of companies smuggling millions of gallons of American-made grain alcohol to Eastern Europe that, with some tinkering, was peddled on the black market as vodka.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Surviving West Nile Illness  Most people made ill by the West Nile virus last year say they have not recovered their strength and have been forced to give up activities like tennis and dancing. Others remain so traumatized that they are afraid to venture outdoors and are unwilling to discuss their experiences.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Groom-to-Be in Fatal Fall  Peter Seligman, a 30-year-old public relations executive, fell to his death from between two subway cars as he and his fiancee were on their way to get their marriage license.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Mayor Mum on Police Choice  Mayor Giuliani has chosen a new police commissioner, but he was putting off the announcement until this morning to give Howard Safir a final day of recognition.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Melting at the North Pole  An ice-free patch of ocean about a mile wide has opened atop the world, a sight presumably never before seen by humans and more evidence that global warming may be real.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Dr. James E. Hansen of NASA's Goddard Institute for Space Studies, an expert on global warming, said that the emphasis on carbon dioxide emissions might be misplaced.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Cuba's Hard Line on Defectors  Cuba is refusing to give waivers for athletes who have defected and now want to compete in the Olympics for other countries.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Woods Takes Lead at PGA  Tiger Woods held a one-stroke lead in the second round of the PGA Championship, as he bid for a third major title this year.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-15</p>
        <p>Corporate Raider Eyes G.M.  Carl C. Icahn has begun accumulating a stake in General Motors, the world's largest company, in a move that will increase pressure on the automaker to spin off its most valuable asset, Hughes Electronics.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Datek to Buy Out 2 Principals  The fast-growing online brokerage firm was said to have agreed to raise about $500 million to buy out the company's two majority shareholders, Jeffrey A. Citron and Sheldon Maschler. Datek is the subject of criminal and regulatory investigations into its day-trading operations during the 1990's.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Fallout From Wireless Auction  Hutchison Whampoa of Hong Kong withdrew from one of the six groups that won wireless licenses in Germany's $46 billion auction, citing costs. Standard &amp; Poor's said it would reduce the credit ratings for most of the big phone companies in the bidding, and investors continued to sell stocks in the winning companies.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Progress in Phone Strike  Negotiators for Verizon and more than 86,000 striking telephone workers reached tentative agreement on several critical issues, but an overall settlement to the 13-day walkout was bogged down in the details.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Reviving the Mideast summit; phantom rogues at the I.R.S.; misguided aid for Colombia; Steven R. Weisman on power in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B14  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>B6  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
