<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; By Bread Alone</title>
    <meta content="23FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="89" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pray, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Molly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DC1231F930A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; By Bread Alone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Molly O'Neill</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Neill, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Molly O'Neill article on gentle kneading technique favored by 'artisan' bread bakers Alison Pray and Matt James; recipes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How the modern epicure swoons for the yeasty aroma, firm crust and dense honeycomb texture of a good loaf of bread. But is it the full wheat flavor or what the loaf represents that has made ''old-fashioned'' or ''artisan'' bread the rallying point of good taste?</p>
        <p>The real stuff, after all, requires what real people have the least amount of -- time. Along with flour, water and salt, it takes time -- as well as patience and the gentleness that comes from an unhurried hand -- to make the great bread that's appearing in large cities and remote backwaters across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How the modern epicure swoons for the yeasty aroma, firm crust and dense honeycomb texture of a good loaf of bread. But is it the full wheat flavor or what the loaf represents that has made ''old-fashioned'' or ''artisan'' bread the rallying point of good taste?</p>
        <p>The real stuff, after all, requires what real people have the least amount of -- time. Along with flour, water and salt, it takes time -- as well as patience and the gentleness that comes from an unhurried hand -- to make the great bread that's appearing in large cities and remote backwaters across the country.</p>
        <p>By choosing to spend rather than save time, artisan bakers like Alison Pray and Matt James of the Standard Baking Company in Portland, Me., have built a better loaf. Along the way they also reversed some long-held bread-baking truths and developed a mind-set that any bread-obsessed home-baker might want to acquire.</p>
        <p>''Our generation was taught that very warm temperatures helped the yeast or starter to act,'' Pray says. ''In fact, making great bread is like making great wine: the slower the fermentation, the better the flavor.'' The process can take days. ''If we begin the starter or 'poolish' on Sunday night, we bake the bread on Tuesday,'' Pray says. ''That long, slow development is key to flavor.''</p>
        <p>Like most modern bakers, the duo had also been taught to knead dough like a boxer, to form it in loaves and imprison it in metal holders. But violence, like expediency, is antithetical to great bread. Pray and James, like many of the new bakers, advocate ''autolyse'' (pronounced aw-toe-leez), a technique that entails a rest during kneading.</p>
        <p>''Autolyse minimizes the stress of kneading,'' James says. Gentle kneading, they've found, creates a cream-colored interior, more moisture and irregular pockets of air that give an open texture. A tender touch also preserves the carotene, the element that accounts for the wheat flavor, which overly enthusiastic kneading will destroy.</p>
        <p>The gluten content of the flour also determines the texture of bread. Gluten is the elastic substance in flour that captures bubbles of carbon dioxide from the yeast and helps the bread to rise.</p>
        <p>Rather than use high-gluten hard wheat flour (containing up to 14 percent protein), which is standard in American bread, artisan bakers favor hard wheat flour with a lower protein content -- between 11 and 12 percent (bakers find the lower-protein flour easier to work with).</p>
        <p>In their squat, former warehouse on Portland's waterfront, slowness is next to godliness. Instead of being scooped quickly from a bin, the flour is carefully weighed and poured. The loaves are shaped by hand and allowed to rise not in conventional metal frames but in canvas. ''It is porous and allows the dough to continue to develop organically and retain moisture,'' Pray says.</p>
        <p>Each of these little, time-lavishing habits is a key to creating flavorful, crusty loaves. It's an effort that can turn the ordinary into a luxury.</p>
        <p>Poolish</p>
        <p>1cup minus 2 tablespoons room-temperature water</p>
        <p>3/4teaspoon crumbled cake yeast</p>
        <p>2cups organic white flour with retained germ.</p>
        <p>In a 1-gallon plastic container, combine the water and yeast and stir until the mixture is milky and foamy and the yeast is fairly dissolved. Stir in the flour until just combined. Cover and leave at room temperature for 5 hours. May be refrigerated for up to 48 hours before using. Bring to room temperature before using.</p>
        <p>Yield: About 1 1/2 cups.</p>
        <p>Baguettes</p>
        <p>1 cup plus 1 tablespoon water at 85 degrees (just a little warmer than room temperature)</p>
        <p>2/3 cup poolish (see recipe)</p>
        <p>3/4 teaspoon crumbled cake yeast</p>
        <p>3 cups minus 2 tablespoons all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>1 3/4 teaspoons fine sea salt.</p>
        <p>1. Place the water in a large mixing bowl. Break the poolish into small pieces with your hands or a wooden spoon and add it to the bowl along with the yeast. Stir until fairly dissolved. Add the flour and salt and stir until combined. Cover the bowl with a tea towel and set aside 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Begin kneading the bread; the dough will be sticky, but keep the surface and your hands only lightly floured and incorporate as little excess flour as possible. Knead for 10 minutes. Rinse out and dry the bowl and return dough to the bowl. Cover with the tea towel and leave at room temperature for 1 hour.</p>
        <p>3. Gently turn the dough out onto a very lightly floured surface. Fold the dough in half and return it gently to the bowl. (Don't deflate it by punching or pressing on it.) Cover. Allow dough to rise 1 more hour, or until it holds the impression of your finger when lightly pressed.</p>
        <p>4. Gently turn the dough out again on a lightly floured surface. Cut dough into thirds. Gently shape each into a loose, fat log. Place on a lightly floured sheet pan, cover loosely and let rest for 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>5. Shape one piece of dough into a long snake by folding the long sides of the dough into the center 4 times, and then rolling it with your palms, applying pressure until it is approximately 13 inches long. Transfer the dough to a large sheet pan covered with parchment paper. Allow to rise until it just holds a fingerprint when lightly pressed but the dough still springs back slightly, 1 to 2 hours.</p>
        <p>6. When ready to bake, preheat the oven to 450 degrees and have a plant sprayer full of fresh water ready. Using a single-sided razor held at a 30-degree angle, slash the surface of the loaves vertically with 4 3-inch slashes. When the oven is hot, spray it 2 to 3 times with water and immediately put the bread in and close the door. Spray the oven (not the bread) again 2 more times during the first 6 minutes of baking. Bake until the bread is a deep, golden brown and sounds hollow in the center when it is tapped, about 14 to 16 minutes. Remove from the oven and cool the loaves on a wire rack.</p>
        <p>Yield: 3 loaves.</p>
        <p>Rustica</p>
        <p>1cup plus 6 tablespoons water just slightly warmer than room temperature</p>
        <p>3/4 cup poolish (see recipe)</p>
        <p>3/4 teaspoon cake yeast</p>
        <p>3 cups minus 2 tablespoons unbleached all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons raw wheat germ</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon fine sea salt.</p>
        <p>1. Place the water in a large mixing bowl. Break the poolish into small pieces with your hands or a wooden spoon and add it to the bowl along with the yeast. Stir until fairly dissolved. Stir in the flour, wheat germ and salt and stir until combined. Continue stirring for 5 minutes. Cover the bowl and let sit for 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Turn the dough out onto a lightly floured surface. Gently fold the dough in half lengthwise and then fold it in half again crosswise. Return the dough to the bowl with its smooth side up. Repeat the folding process 2 more times over the next 40 minutes. After the last turning, let the dough rest for 20 to 30 more minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Gently turn the dough out onto a lightly floured surface. Loosely form it into a square on the table, taking care not to deflate it. Using a knife or bench scraper, cut the dough into 4 equal squares. Gently move the pieces to a sheet pan lined with a well-floured heavy tea towel, and cover loosely with plastic wrap. Let rest until the dough just holds the imprint of your finger when you press it gently, 1 to 1 1/2 hours.</p>
        <p>4. Preheat oven to 450 degrees and have a plant sprayer full of fresh water ready. Very gently transfer the dough pieces to 2 sheet pans lined with parchment paper, putting the side of the dough that came in contact with the floured tea towel up and leaving plenty of space between the pieces. When the oven is hot, spray it thoroughly with water and immediately put the bread in and close the door. Spray the oven (not the bread) again 3 more times during the first 5 minutes of baking. Bake until the bread is golden brown and sounds hollow in the center when tapped, 15 to 20 minutes more.</p>
        <p>5. Remove the loaves from the oven and cool them on a wire rack.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 small loaves.</p>
        <p>Raisin-Pecan Bread</p>
        <p>2 cups raisins</p>
        <p>2 cups boiling water</p>
        <p>3 cups lightly toasted pecan halves</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons turbinado (raw) sugar</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cups water just slightly warmer than room temperature</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon fresh cake yeast</p>
        <p>1/2 cup poolish (see recipe)</p>
        <p>4 1/4 cups unbleached all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons finely ground sea salt.</p>
        <p>1. Combine the raisins and boiling water in a bowl and set aside for 10 minutes. In the container of a food processor, combine  1/2cup of the pecan halves and sugar and pulse until the pecans are very finely ground. Set aside. Thoroughly drain the raisins and set them aside.</p>
        <p>2. Place the warm water and yeast in a large bowl. Break the poolish into small pieces with your hands or a wooden spoon and add it to the bowl. Stir until fairly dissolved. Stir in the flour, ground pecans and sugar and salt. Stir until combined.</p>
        <p>3. Turn the mixture out onto a lightly floured surface and knead for 10 minutes. Slowly begin to fold in the raisins and the remaining pecan halves a little at a time. Return the dough to the bowl, cover with a tea towel and let rise until doubled in bulk, 1 to 2 hours.</p>
        <p>4. Gently turn the dough out onto a lightly floured surface and cut into 3 equal pieces. Leave the pieces on your work surface and cover them with a tea towel. Let them rest for 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>5. Gently shape each piece into a short log and place the logs on a sheet pan lined with parchment paper. Cover with the tea towel and let rise until the loaves just hold a fingerprint when lightly pressed, 30 minutes to 1 hour.</p>
        <p>6. When ready to bake, preheat oven to 375 degrees and have a plant sprayer full of fresh water ready. Using a single-sided razor at a 30-degree angle, slash the loaves diagonally with 2 3-inch slashes each. When the oven is hot, spray it thoroughly with water and immediately put the bread in and close the door. Spray the oven (not the bread) again 2 more times during the first 5 minutes of baking. Bake until bread is very brown and sounds hollow when the bottom is tapped, 25 to 30 minutes more.</p>
        <p>7. Remove the loaves from the oven and cool them on a wire rack.</p>
        <p>Yield: 3 loaves.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
