<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hate the Weather? This Man Doesn't</title>
    <meta content="06PERS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">David A. Robinson</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, David a (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDF103FF935A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hate the Weather? This Man Doesn't</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New Jersey's official climatologist and global snow expert David A Robinson, who comments on his fascination with weather ever since grade school; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID A. ROBINSON was in the fourth grade at MacKay elementary school in Tenafly when he made his first weather chart.</p>
        <p>By the time he was in the sixth grade, he was giving a daily weather report to his class. (A friend looked out the window and followed with the cloud report.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID A. ROBINSON was in the fourth grade at MacKay elementary school in Tenafly when he made his first weather chart.</p>
        <p>By the time he was in the sixth grade, he was giving a daily weather report to his class. (A friend looked out the window and followed with the cloud report.)</p>
        <p>These are the origins of New Jersey's official climatologist, whose duties include researching the state's climate, collecting  data and providing information to the public.</p>
        <p>''I love it; this is a wonderful career,'' Dr. Robinson said the other day from his data-crammed office in Lucy Stone Hall here on the Livingston College campus of Rutgers University, where he is also a professor of geography. ''As a kid growing up in Tenafly, if you had told me there was a state climatologist, this is what I would have wanted to be when I grew up.''</p>
        <p>In his enthusiasm for weather, and especially snow cover, a subject in which he is considered a global expert, Dr. Robinson comes off as still a young boy. He looks much younger than his 44 years, especially this day in jeans, striped button-down shirt and ski sweater as he removes a battered folder from a shelf and pulls out a paper that happens to be a weather observer's record for this very day in 1894.</p>
        <p>''It was 34 degrees with a low of 10,'' he says. ''And just the day before they had four inches of snow. Isn't that interesting? And it had been so mild.''</p>
        <p>Just like January 2000.</p>
        <p>''Listen to this,'' he says. ''This is what I love about these records.''</p>
        <p>And he quotes a passage: ''On the evening of the 24th I picked from the surface of the ground a box of earth worms or night walkers as our piscatorial friends call them . . .''</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson laughs. '' 'Piscatorial friends','' he says with delight. ''I just love the way you get these anecdotal remarks.''</p>
        <p>When Dr. Robinson took over the job in 1991, he got occasional calls from lawyers who needed data to be used in litigation. Now he gets a thousand inquiries a year, only now they come from companies that plow snow, condominium managers, state officials, police departments, prosecutors' offices, journalists and curious citizens.</p>
        <p>''A couple of years ago, I sent data to some department of environmental protection people who were studying a turtle migration'' he says. ''I get calls from people asking me what the weather is going to be on Sunday, June 11, this year because 'My daughter is getting married and we want to know if we have to get a tent for the reception in our backyard.' ''</p>
        <p>Last year, Dr. Robinson answered more than 360 queries from the news media. (Last month alone he got 92 because of unusually high and low temperatures.) And he gives as many as two dozen lectures a year, including many in schools where he drags out his old fourth-grade weather chart.</p>
        <p>The position of state climatologist was created by the federal governement in the 1950's and then abolished in the early 70's for budgetary reasons. The states kept the positions, however, usually administering them through the state universities.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the state climatologist is appointed by the dean of Cook College at Rutgers, who is also executive dean of the Agricultural Experimental Station.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's climate office is a ''fairly active'' one, says Dr. Robinson, who in his other capacity teaches courses in physical geography, remote sensing, climate dynamics and a multi-disciplinary course on global and regional climate change. He has served as dean of the geography department and will again next year.</p>
        <p>In the early 1990's, the state climate office had only one observation station of its own and relied on data from four dozen stations operated by the National Weather Service, the majority of which reported once a day.</p>
        <p>Within the last few months, the weather service has added a network of two dozen stations that it operates, mostly in central and northern New Jersey, and polls electronically every hour. Now Dr. Robinson is  working to create a  network of as many as a hundred stations.</p>
        <p>An hourly data page is under development and is expected to be linked in a few months to the state climate home page: http://climate.rutgers.edu/stateclim/.</p>
        <p>Each year, he also raises from $150,000 to $200,000 for his own global research program focusing on snow cover.</p>
        <p>''He's known as one of the top climatologists in the country and he's known internationally for his work in large-scale snow cover,'' said Dan Leathers, the climatologist for Delaware who is a close friend and who has collaborated on some of Dr. Robinson's 130 published articles.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson says he didn't get his interest in the weather from his parents. His father, Thomas, was a high school guidance counselor, and his mother, Lois, a fourth grade teacher. His older sister, Lynne, is a high school math teacher.</p>
        <p>He thinks it was Donna -- as in the hurricane. When it roared up the East Coast in September 1960, he had just begun kindergarten and it left a vivid impression.</p>
        <p>What struck him as he spent the afternoon looking out the window, he said, was ''just the whole specter of the storm -- the winds. You know, sometimes you wonder if it's because it disrupts life a little differently like a snowfall does. But more than that, it's just the fascination with the power of nature and the changes.''</p>
        <p>Snow especially fascinates him.</p>
        <p>''I think what it is, again, it's the power of the storm and the way it can change the world right in front of your eyes.''</p>
        <p>That interest in snow goes back to the winter of 1960-61: a major snowstorm in December, ''the Kennedy inauguration snowstorm in January'' and ''an even bigger one in February.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I remember the snow over my head in drifts out my window and along the driveway. Now is that why I started liking snow? I don't know. But I volunteered to take those observations in the fourth grade as part of the science assignment and after that two-week assignment ended I kept taking records and I still keep them today.''</p>
        <p>At Dickinson College, a liberal arts school in Carlisle, Pa., he majored in geology, getting his bachelor's degree in 1977. After receiving his master's degree and Ph.D. in geology from Columbia University in 1981 and 1984, he worked four years as an associate research scientist at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia and spent a year as a visiting scientist at the National Climatic Data Center. He joined the Rutgers faculty in 1989.</p>
        <p>In high school, he played junior varsity basketball but discovered he had a singing voice -- a baritone -- and abandoned basketball to sing in the high school choir and act in musicals. That interest carried over to college choirs and a stint as singer in a rock and roll band, ''Waldo and the Geeks.'' He was one of the Geeks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson lives with his wife, Keating, and their two sons, Douglas, 14, and Drew, 10, in Hillsborough. An avid sports fan, he coached little league for about 10 years as well as soccer and now is a scoutmaster.</p>
        <p>Drew, he says, is interested in being a baseball historian, and they have visited the Hall of Fame in Cooperstown. Douglas, on the other hand, has accompanied him to to a half-dozen meetings on the weather in New Jersey, New Hampshire and Washington,  and plans to study meteorology in college.</p>
        <p>''He is willing to let me retire,'' Dr. Robinson only half-joked, ''before he assumes my present duties as state climatologist.''</p>
        <p>It's Not the Heat. It's the Lack of Water.</p>
        <p>WITHOUT question, said David Robinson, ''the decade of the 90's was the warmest of the century in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Citing records dating to 1895, Dr. Robinson, the state climatologist, said temperatures had increased by about two degrees Fahrenheit over the last 100 years. ''We're not becoming Jacksonville, Florida,'' he said, ''but there are signs of warming.''</p>
        <p>The first two decades were cold, followed by a stable period in the 1930's through the 1980's, with some warming in the 80's, he said. But in the 1990's only one year was below the mean and every other year was in the upper 50 percentile.</p>
        <p>He attributed this to an active sun, minimal volcanic activity, a great number of El Nino years, the natural variability of weather -- plus the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>''The question is now: Is the climate changing due to at least the partial influence of humans? And that's a different kind of change,'' Dr. Robinson said.</p>
        <p>New Jersey has been wetter in the last three decades, but there have also been brief but influential droughts, a condition that is of concern, he said</p>
        <p>''We have been blessed with a number of years of abundant rain and four situations where the rains came right on the heels of a 12-month drought,'' he said of the droughts of 1980, 1985, 1995 and 1999.''</p>
        <p>But these paled in comparison with the drought of the mid-1960's, which was a far more serious event of longer duration.</p>
        <p>''We've grown in population since the drought of the 60's,'' he said. ''If we have a drought like the mid-60's we're going to be faced with very severe problems.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson said he believes that temperatures will continue to get warmer in New Jersey, though that is not the most important issue. ''Water is the issue,'' he said. ''What is the future going to bring in New Jersey and elsewhere around the world in terms of our precipitation patterns?''</p>
        <p>GEORGE JAMES</p>
        <p>IN PERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
