<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Megadrought Appears to Loom in Africa</title>
    <meta content="08PREC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174785"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verschuren, Dirk (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DD173EF93BA35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1317" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Megadrought Appears to Loom in Africa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New study finds decades-long droughts far longer and more severe than any in recorded weather history alternated in equatorial East Africa over last millennium with periods when rainfall was heavier than today; finds long droughts sometimes caused collapse of entire ancient civilizations and force large-scale human migrations; sees high probability of devastating drought hitting tropical Africa again in next 50 to 100 years, affecting human population that has doubled in last 25 years and is increasing its water use even faster; Dr Dirk Verschuren, who headed study, urges preparations for catastrophic drought; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lately, it has become increasingly clear to scientists that in the 10,000 years since the last ice age ended, the world's climate has often served up droughts far surpassing anything seen in the last 150 years, resulting in some cases in the collapse of entire ancient civilizations.</p>
        <p>Now a new study has found that over the last millennium in equatorial East Africa, decades-long droughts far longer and more severe than any in recorded weather history have alternated with periods when rainfall was heavier than today. The droughts dwarfed any experienced by humans in the 20th century, including the American Dust Bowl of the 1930's and the African Sahel drought of the 1970's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lately, it has become increasingly clear to scientists that in the 10,000 years since the last ice age ended, the world's climate has often served up droughts far surpassing anything seen in the last 150 years, resulting in some cases in the collapse of entire ancient civilizations.</p>
        <p>Now a new study has found that over the last millennium in equatorial East Africa, decades-long droughts far longer and more severe than any in recorded weather history have alternated with periods when rainfall was heavier than today. The droughts dwarfed any experienced by humans in the 20th century, including the American Dust Bowl of the 1930's and the African Sahel drought of the 1970's.</p>
        <p>In each of the earlier droughts, some of which lasted as long as 80 years, according to oral traditions cited in the study, famine ravaged the land, provoking social and political upheaval and forcing large-scale migrations of people.</p>
        <p>Given this pattern of naturally occurring, long-term variability in precipitation, say the scientists who performed the study, there is a ''very high probability'' that a devastating dry period, possibly lasting decades, will visit tropical Africa again in the next 50 to 100 years. This time, it would affect a human population that has doubled in the last 25 years and is increasing its use of water even faster.</p>
        <p>''We have to anticipate that a major catastrophic drought will happen sooner or later, and we must prepare for such an event,'' said Dr. Dirk Verschuren, a scientist at the University of Minnesota and the University of Ghent, in Belgium, who headed the study. While such a drought would not necessarily be unremitting, he said, it could result in large-scale crop failures lasting 10 to 15 years at a stretch.</p>
        <p>The study by Dr. Verschuren and Dr. Kathleen R. Laird and Dr. Brian F. Cumming of Queens University in Kingston, Ontario, appeared in a recent issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Natural long-term variations in precipitation, especially dry periods, have long had a major impact on human societies. Researchers have linked a 300-year drought starting about 4,200 years ago to the collapse of the world's first great empire, that of the Akkadians in Mesopotamia. Drought is also believed responsible for the collapse of several pre-Inca civilizations in South America, and to have been a major contributor to the disappearance of the Mayan civilization in Central America.</p>
        <p>Over the last 3,500 years, according to one study, drought has been the rule in what is now California, with some dry periods lasting as much as two centuries; today's California climate, despite occasional dry spells, is a relatively wet exception.</p>
        <p>Droughts as severe as that of the 1930's Dust Bowl, according to a recent study by federal scientists, have occurred once or twice a century over the last 300 to 400 years. And even more severe dry periods have in the past periodically converted big stretches of the Great Plains to Sahara-like conditions.</p>
        <p>Scientists draw such conclusions on the basis of indirect evidence, since widespread direct measurements of weather and climate have been in use only since the mid-19th century.</p>
        <p>In the recent African study, Dr. Verschuren and two associates examined clues contained in sediments in Lake Naivasha, Kenya. Over the centuries, the shallow lake has collected runoff from its immediate surroundings. In the middle of the lake is a deeper depression formed by the rim of an ancient volcano. Sediment in the runoff has been deposited there in such a way that it has been protected from disturbance.</p>
        <p>Dr. Verschuren and his colleagues extracted a 20-foot core from the protected sediments. The strata of sediment preserved in the core reached back 1,100 years. The scientists analyzed the core for three types of indicators of wetness and dryness: varying kinds of soils, the pattern of different species of algae (some thrive in low, saltier water, others in high, fresher water), and patterns of different species of tiny insects called midges, which are also sensitive to salinity.</p>
        <p>The analysis enabled the researchers to reconstruct the climatic history of the region, and all three indicators told the same story: over the last millenniums, the region has experienced a constant succession of wetter and drier periods. Most recently, there were serious droughts in the 1870's, just before Europeans colonized the region, and in the late 18th and early 19th centuries. Both of these were much longer and more severe than the Dust Bowl and the 1970's Sahel drought, which threatened millions with starvation.</p>
        <p>On the other end of the precipitation scale, rainfall was found to have been significantly higher than today in the 17th and early 18th centuries. This coincides with some of the colder periods of what was called, in Europe, the little ice age, a five-century span in which unusual cold afflicted parts of the Northern Hemisphere from time to time. Conversely, one of the major drought periods coincided with a relatively warm time in Europe, which lasted from about A.D. 1000 to 1270.</p>
        <p>The practical question raised by the findings, Dr. Verschuren said, is that of how to plan for the eventuality of a future megadrought in Africa, where the survival of the populace depends mostly on rain-fed agriculture.</p>
        <p>''These emerging agricultural economies all do their best in trying to feed their populations, but they do so at a major cost of water use,'' Dr. Verschuren said. ''In many cases, there is serious overexploitation of available water resources.''</p>
        <p>In countries where water availability is chancy and directly dependent on climate, he said, ''you're basically setting yourself up for a catastrophe.''</p>
        <p>One way to prepare for a coming megadrought, he said, would be to switch to drought-resistant crops. Another would be to reduce dependence on irrigation, which requires large quantities of water.</p>
        <p>A broader lesson to be drawn from the findings, he said, is that irrespective of any human impact on the world's climate, there is great natural variability in rainfall, and this variability may swamp the effects of any global warming produced by industrial emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The average surface temperature of the globe is rising, and the dominant view among scientists is that it will increase by 2 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit by 2100 if emissions of the greenhouse gases are not reduced. While attention in the global warming debate has focused mostly on temperature, many experts say the warming's effect on precipitation may be more striking.</p>
        <p>Even in the absence of any impact by greenhouse gases, precipitation is often of greater concern than temperature. ''Human societies suffer much more from declining or irregular water resources than from changes in temperature,'' Dr. Frank Oldfield, director of the international Past Global Changes project in Bern, Switzerland, wrote in a commentary in Nature.</p>
        <p>In general, a warmer atmosphere causes more water to evaporate from the earth's surface. This phenomenon can produce heavier rains, but it can also make droughts worse. Scientists expect both of these to happen in the future, but they are at a loss to predict where and when it will rain less or more.</p>
        <p>In any case, Dr. Verschuren said, the effect of global warming on rainfall will probably be small in comparison with the natural variations reported in the new study. Warming in theory could either exacerbate an African drought or alleviate it. ''But even if it does alleviate the problem,'' he said, ''it is not going to solve it, because the beneficial effects might be relatively minor compared to the natural variability.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
