<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada Port Gains as Ice Diminishes</title>
    <meta content="03SHIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/03/business/03SHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stevedoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freight Forwarding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wheat</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Churchill (Manitoba)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Omnitrax Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E2DE1F30F930A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada Port Gains as Ice Diminishes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>CHURCHILL, Manitoba</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some shippers are quietly shifting marine routes to Churchill, Manitoba, Canada's northernmost industrial harbor, now that ice hazards that kept them from using it have disappeared as a result of global warming; by docking at Churchill, oceangoing ships benefit from rail links to prairie heartlands of Canada and US, world's largest wheat-exporting nations; new routes benefit of Omnitrax Inc that bought port and access railroad in 1997; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here on the edge of Canada's tree line, where polar bears prowl the tundra under the dancing lights of the northern sky, a Barbadian flag vessel was at port one recent evening, its crew sweeping aside snow to fill its holds with grain for shipment direct to Europe.</p>
        <p>While politicians debate the validity of global warming, some shippers are voting with their boats, quietly shifting marine routes to Churchill, Canada's northernmost industrial harbor. After decades of ignoring the only major port on the Hudson Bay because of ice hazards, shippers are finding that the retreating ice cover is putting Churchill on the map. By docking at this sub-Arctic outpost of 1,100 residents, oceangoing ships benefit from rail links to the prairie heartlands of Canada and the United States, the world's largest wheat exporting nations. And their business is much to the benefit of Omnitrax Inc., the Denver-based company that bought the port and access railroad in 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here on the edge of Canada's tree line, where polar bears prowl the tundra under the dancing lights of the northern sky, a Barbadian flag vessel was at port one recent evening, its crew sweeping aside snow to fill its holds with grain for shipment direct to Europe.</p>
        <p>While politicians debate the validity of global warming, some shippers are voting with their boats, quietly shifting marine routes to Churchill, Canada's northernmost industrial harbor. After decades of ignoring the only major port on the Hudson Bay because of ice hazards, shippers are finding that the retreating ice cover is putting Churchill on the map. By docking at this sub-Arctic outpost of 1,100 residents, oceangoing ships benefit from rail links to the prairie heartlands of Canada and the United States, the world's largest wheat exporting nations. And their business is much to the benefit of Omnitrax Inc., the Denver-based company that bought the port and access railroad in 1997.</p>
        <p>''Omnitrax are aggressive, and they are enticing cargo through the Port of Churchill, and if it's going through the Port of Churchill, we want to ship it,'' said Thomas Paterson, a vice president of Fednav Ltd., an international shipping company based in Montreal.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 9, when grain chutes are to swivel away from the last grain ship here, 27 ships, nearly double last season's flotilla of 14, are expected to have been loaded. With wheat and peas leaving here this fall for Africa, Europe and Mexico, total tonnage is forecast to hit 710,000, more than double the average annual shipments of the last five years. This year's shipping season began with the arrival of Fednav's M.V. Federal Rhine on July 11, the earliest port opening since international shipping started here in 1931.</p>
        <p>''If we are going to have global warming, then the only way for Churchill to go is up,'' David M. Collenette, Canada's Minister of Transport, said on a visit here last month to inaugurate $25 million worth of federal investments in the port, largely for dredging and dust control in the towering grain elevators. ''Churchill could have a five-month season, instead of the current four-month season.''</p>
        <p>The Canadian Ice Service, a federal agency, has measured ice extent on July 15, the benchmark date for the annual start of shipping in Hudson Bay, for every year since 1971. Although years vary, the trend is that over the last three decades the expanse of Hudson Bay ice on that date has decreased by about one-third, according to John Falkingham, chief of the service's Ice Forecasting unit.</p>
        <p>Citing this study, Omnitrax hopes to persuade Lloyd's, the London-based insurer, to drop a longstanding 15 percent insurance surcharge on Churchill shipments and is seeking to expand the standard insured shipping season from three months to five months, from July 1 to the end of November. Currently, this season is from July 21 to Oct. 21. Ice-class vessels with reinforced hulls can operate outside those dates.</p>
        <p>Neil Smith, a spokesman for Lloyd's Underwriters' Association, said that company officials have toured the port and are reviewing ice data and other statistics, and hope to make a decision before shipping begins next summer. In one setback, a Greek-owned ship hit ice in the bay this August, punching a 20-square foot hole that was repaired in Churchill.</p>
        <p>Still, said Gary D. Rennick, chief operating officer of Omnitrax Canada Inc., ''The fact is the ice is gone from the port earlier and forms in the port later.''</p>
        <p>Omnitrax officials say that in addition to climate change, increased shipping here is a result of better ice mapping by the government, better ice detection equipment on ships and aggressive port marketing. The port, which was to be closed in 1995 because of a lack of business, is expected to turn a profit next year.</p>
        <p>The company's pitch to world grain buyers is that shipping prairie grains through Churchill saves as much as $20 a ton in shipping costs compared with the cost of sending grain through its competitor, Thunder Bay, Ontario, the starting point for the Great Lakes and St. Lawrence Seaway system. Noting that Churchill is the closest port for one-quarter of Canada's prairie farmers, Omnitrax officials say they saved farmers $10 million in international shipping costs this season.</p>
        <p>''In many cases, Churchill is proving to be the least-cost alternative,'' said Bill Drew, transportation adviser for the Canadian Wheat Board, a government agency that accounts for 75 percent of grain shipments through here.</p>
        <p>Although Thunder Bay's season is twice as long as Churchill's, shipping through here is often cheaper because there are no seaway fees and grain does not have to be transferred from lake boats to oceangoing vessels. Recent dredging has increased this port's navigable depth, allowing it to handle vessels loaded with 50,000 tons of grain, double the loads oceangoing boats at Thunder Bay can carry.</p>
        <p>With some shippers shifting to Hudson Bay, an amount equal to about one third of Thunder Bay's grain tonnage will ship through Churchill this year, double the average share in the 1990's. Pat Broe, president of the Broe Companies, which owns Omnitrax, hopes to triple Churchill's annual export volume to two million tons in 2002, equal to Thunder Bay's annual average of the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>A key to Churchill's revival has been the joining of the port and the 530-mile access railroad. Long-term residents accuse the previous owner, Canadian National, of trying to kill the Hudson Bay line by saying that only old-fashioned box cars could run on the rails, which are laid on unstable permafrost.</p>
        <p>Omnitrax proved that theory wrong, regularly running 100-car trains of tube-shaped hopper cars filled with grain. Believing that the railroad will eventually handle cargo from the American prairies, Omnitrax is investing millions of dollars to lay new ties and new ballast to shore up the prairies' outlet to the sea.</p>
        <p>For now, almost all ships arrive here empty. But Mr. Broe hopes traders will start to see Churchill as a port of entry to the North American heartland, perhaps starting with Russian phosphate fertilizer for American and Canadian farmers.</p>
        <p>As ice increasingly retreats in summer throughout the Arctic, Russia is developing its own northern shipping route. A Finnish company, Kvaerner Masa-Yards Inc., is building ice-resistant tankers, and shippers hope to soon send cargo ships with reinforced hulls across the top of Siberia, following the Northern Sea Route, between Murmansk and the Bering Strait.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
