<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Sets Another Record for Winter Warmth</title>
    <meta content="Y11WAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1182921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Climatic Data Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3DB143BF932A25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Sets Another Record for Winter Warmth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal scientists at National Climatic Data Center report that for third year in a row, United States set record for winter warmth; say that with an average temperature of 38.4 degrees Fahrenheit, three-month period of December 1999 through February 2000 was warmest winter season in contiguous 48 states in 105 years that such data has been recorded; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the third year in a row, the United States has set a record for winter warmth, federal scientists reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>With an average temperature of 38.4 degrees Fahrenheit, the three-month period of December 1999 through February 2000 was the warmest winter season in the contiguous 48 states in the 105 years that such data has been recorded, the scientists said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the third year in a row, the United States has set a record for winter warmth, federal scientists reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>With an average temperature of 38.4 degrees Fahrenheit, the three-month period of December 1999 through February 2000 was the warmest winter season in the contiguous 48 states in the 105 years that such data has been recorded, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>That mark slightly surpassed the previous record of 37.8 degrees, set a year ago. The third-warmest winter was that of 1997-1998, when the average temperature for the same three-month period was 37.5 degrees.</p>
        <p>''Winter has shortened on both ends'' this year, said Mike Changery, a climatologist at the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., which issued the report made public yesterday.</p>
        <p>This fits in with a previously detected trend toward later freezes in the fall and earlier departures of frost in the spring, Mr. Changery said.</p>
        <p>Put another way, according to yesterday's report, two-thirds of the winter seasons of the last 20 years have been warmer than the long-term national average.</p>
        <p>Shorter and milder winters are consistent with a century-long global warming trend that mainstream scientists believe has been at least partly caused by emissions of heat-trapping waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The warming has been especially significant in the last quarter-century, amounting to more than three times the century-long warming rate of about 1 degree Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Computer models predict that the temperature rise will continue at that accelerated pace if emissions of heat-trapping gases are not reduced, and also predict that warming will be especially pronounced in the winter.</p>
        <p>''We are beginning to approximate the kind of warming you should see in the winter season'' based on the model projections, especially over the land masses of the Northern Hemisphere, Mr. Changery said.</p>
        <p>But while the winter warming trend is consistent with the projections, he added, ''the jury is still out'' on just what has caused the especially warm winters of the last three years.</p>
        <p>Global warming aside, scientists said prime suspects were the natural phenomena known as El Nino and La Nina. These are sea-surface temperature oscillations in the tropical Pacific that touch off changes in wintertime atmospheric circulation.</p>
        <p>In different ways, El Nino in 1997-98 and La Nina in the last two winters influenced circulation patterns that kept most of the United States relatively warm most of the time.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Changery said, true winter cold visited the East this winter only in a three-week period that started in mid-January.</p>
        <p>This winter, according to the climatic data center, every state in the contiguous United States was warmer than its long-term average, with 21 states from California to the Midwest ranking well above average.</p>
        <p>In many places from the Northern Plains to New England, the first snowfall came later than ever, as did the first freeze. Other places experienced their longest periods between episodes of sub-zero temperatures.  In February, hundreds of daily maximum temperature records were established. Numerous places across the northern tier of states set or tied their high temperature records for the month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
