<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Third Moon Of Jupiter May Have Sea Under Its Ice</title>
    <meta content="17MOON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/17/science/17MOON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1255841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Calisto (Jovian Moon)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Europa (Moon of Jupiter)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ganymede (Moon)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Galileo (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4D91439F934A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Third Moon Of Jupiter May Have Sea Under Its Ice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Dec. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA's Galileo spacecraft finds evidence of an ocean on Ganymede, moon of Jupiter; oceans have already been detected on two of its sister moons, Europa and Calisto (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have found evidence that Ganymede, a moon of Jupiter, has an ocean. That is the third Jupiter moon that shows signs of water sloshing beneath its frozen exterior.</p>
        <p>NASA's Galileo spacecraft has detected telltale undulations in Ganymede's magnetic field. Planetary scientists had previously found indications of under-ice oceans on Europa and Callisto, two other moons. Water is considered a necessary ingredient for the development of life, although no signs of life have yet been seen on any of the moons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists have found evidence that Ganymede, a moon of Jupiter, has an ocean. That is the third Jupiter moon that shows signs of water sloshing beneath its frozen exterior.</p>
        <p>NASA's Galileo spacecraft has detected telltale undulations in Ganymede's magnetic field. Planetary scientists had previously found indications of under-ice oceans on Europa and Callisto, two other moons. Water is considered a necessary ingredient for the development of life, although no signs of life have yet been seen on any of the moons.</p>
        <p>''It looks pretty persuasive to us,'' said Dr. Margaret Kivelson, a professor of space physics at the University of California at Los Angeles, who led the research. She was to present her Ganymede findings Sunday at the fall meeting of the American Geophysical Union here.</p>
        <p>''I think it's an exciting result,'' said Dr. Robert Pappalardo, of Brown University. ''It makes sense if Callisto has really retained a liquid water layer over the age of the solar system, that Ganymede should, too.''</p>
        <p>In recent years, planetary scientists have found much evidence of an under-ice ocean on Europa, including its fractured surface and areas that look as if water had erupted from below the surface. In 1998, Dr. Kivelson and her collaborators offered additional evidence by looking at how the direction and strength of Jupiter's magnetic field shifted somewhat each time the Galileo spacecraft, in orbit around Jupiter, passed near Europa.</p>
        <p>The moon, the researchers said, was generating electrical currents as it swept through Jupiter's powerful field. The new electrical currents, in turn, generated magnetic fields that altered Jupiter's field.</p>
        <p>For electrical current to flow on Europa, some part of Europa must conduct electricity, and ice is not a good conductor. But salty liquid water is, and the magnetic-field fluctuations therefore pointed to an ocean 5 to 10 miles below the surface. To their surprise, the researchers also found swings in the magnetic field around Callisto, smaller and farther away from Jupiter than Europa.</p>
        <p>The new findings, based on data from two visits by Galileo to Ganymede in 1996 and one in May, found similar magnetic fluctuations. At 3,270 miles in diameter, Ganymede is the largest moon in the solar system, three-quarters the width of Mars.</p>
        <p>Photos of Ganymede have shown channels of smooth ice that might have flowed out of ''ice volcanoes'' billions of years ago. Dr. Kivelson's findings are the first evidence that liquid water might still exist on Ganymede, although it would now be tens of miles beneath the surface.</p>
        <p>The data indicates either a thin ocean -- about half a mile thick -- within 30 miles of the surface or a thicker ocean deeper down, perhaps about 100 miles below the surface. The temperature of the water would probably a few degrees below zero.</p>
        <p>Complicating the analysis is that Ganymede, unlike Europa and Callisto, still possesses a molten core that generates its own permanent magnetic field similar to Earth's. With Europa and Callisto, the researchers only had to figure out if the moons were producing any magnetic fields. With Ganymede, they had to detect whether the moon's existing permanent fields were changing direction by a few degrees.</p>
        <p>''It just rocks back and forth,'' Dr. Kivelson said. ''You can see that is much more difficult to be confident about.''</p>
        <p>It was possible that irregularities in Ganymede's permanent field could mimic the effect, but it was ''unlikely nature has conspired'' that effect, Dr. Kivelson said.</p>
        <p>Other researchers are presenting evidence that Ganymede is more like Europa than previously thought. In the latest photos from Galileo, scientists have spotted geological features  like craters that broke and moved apart, as if on two sides of an earthquake fault.</p>
        <p>The photos indicate that most of the bright areas seen on Ganymede are not ice floes from volcanic eruptions, but were instead formed by a process similar to how new ocean floor is created on Earth when two tectonic plates pull apart and molten material wells up. On Ganymede, two ice sheets would have pulled apart, and more malleable ice would have risen to fill the gap.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
