<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Balancing Hybrids vs. Electrics on the Environmental Scale</title>
    <meta content="04HYBR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">American Tour De Sol (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DF113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Balancing Hybrids vs. Electrics on the Environmental Scale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article compares hybrid gas-electric cars with battery-electric cars using criteria measured at 12th running of alternative-vehicle race, American Tour de Sol, where cars are ranked by energy efficiency and contribution to global warming; race shows that cars are improving in aspects such as range, reliability and handling, that hybrids had better fuel economy than electrics, but emitted more gases believed to cause climate change; Honda Insight is overall winner with high fuel economy but global warming potential is double that of second-place finisher, General Motors EV1 electric car, and better than most cars in use today; hybrids technology is second-best from greenhouse-gas standpoint, but costs less and travels farther than battery-powered cars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HYBRID gas-electric cars can be clean and very fuel-efficient, and may, if automakers persuade regulators, be used to fill the quota for battery-electric cars that California, New York and Massachusetts plan to require. But engineers are learning that hybrids cannot accomplish everything that environmentalists want.</p>
        <p>That point was demonstrated at the end of the 12th running of an alternative-vehicle race, the American Tour de Sol, here on May 18, when race organizers set out to rank the competing cars on a variety of scales. One criterion was energy efficiency, which was measured on a miles-per-gallon basis for the hybrid vehicles that used gasoline or diesel fuel; for battery-electric vehicles, organizers came up with an equivalent measure based on how much fuel an electric utility would need at its power plant to make the electricity the vehicle consumed. Another criterion was the cars' potential contribution to global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HYBRID gas-electric cars can be clean and very fuel-efficient, and may, if automakers persuade regulators, be used to fill the quota for battery-electric cars that California, New York and Massachusetts plan to require. But engineers are learning that hybrids cannot accomplish everything that environmentalists want.</p>
        <p>That point was demonstrated at the end of the 12th running of an alternative-vehicle race, the American Tour de Sol, here on May 18, when race organizers set out to rank the competing cars on a variety of scales. One criterion was energy efficiency, which was measured on a miles-per-gallon basis for the hybrid vehicles that used gasoline or diesel fuel; for battery-electric vehicles, organizers came up with an equivalent measure based on how much fuel an electric utility would need at its power plant to make the electricity the vehicle consumed. Another criterion was the cars' potential contribution to global warming.</p>
        <p>The race showed that all the cars were improving in many aspects, like range, reliability and handling. The numbers also showed that hybrids had better fuel economy than some electrics, but emitted more gases believed to cause climate change.</p>
        <p>For example, in the race's ''production category,'' for vehicles commercially available today, the overall winner was the Honda Insight hybrid. It had a fuel economy average of 92 miles a gallon in the race. In second place over all was General Motors' two-seat EV1 electric car. It had the equivalent fuel economy of 68 m.p.g.</p>
        <p>But the ''global warming potential'' of the Insight -- a number that includes carbon dioxide and two much more potent tailpipe gases, methane and nitrous oxide -- was roughly double the EV1's level. A big reason is that even a very good gasoline engine is only about 18 percent efficient in turning the gas into usable energy; the rest of the fuel is consumed by friction or expelled as exhaust. In contrast, an inefficient power station using the same amount of fuel is closer to 33 percent effective at turning fuel into electricity; an efficient one can reach 50 percent. Tour de Sol organizers had the Argonne National Laboratory, part of the Energy Department, perform the calculation using the mix of power plants in the Northeast, since the race ran from New York City to Washington. That includes nuclear and hydroelectric plants that do not emit carbon dioxide and related gases.</p>
        <p>Nancy Hazard, who organizes the race for the Northeast Sustainable Energy Association, a nonprofit environmental group, said the result was ''something that I was not actually expecting.''</p>
        <p>But even if the Insight gave off twice as much greenhouse gas as the EV1, it was still a huge improvement over most cars on the road. It had only a quarter of the emissions of a conventional gasoline-powered Saturn driven on the same route.</p>
        <p>In the near term, at least, hybrid cars are more likely than battery-electrics to be a solution to the problems of air pollution and dependence on imported oil. Toyota, which has produced both types of vehicles, told California regulators last week that the public was not ready to accept electrics; indeed, Toyota said it could not sell the cars and would have to pay customers to take them.</p>
        <p>Hybrid technology is second-best from a greenhouse-gas standpoint, and hybrids have a brighter future than battery-powered cars because they cost comparatively less and travel much farther without needing to stop for recharging.</p>
        <p>The idea of trading off one environmental value against another is not new. Controlling acid rain by taking sulfur out of power-plant emissions means using some of the plants' electric output for anti-pollution equipment, which means more carbon dioxide for each kilowatt-hour delivered to customers. The Environmental Protection Agency is belatedly trying to ban methyl tertiary butyl ether, or M.T.B.E., a gasoline additive it once favored to clean the air. When gas leaks into the soil, M.T.B.E. contaminates water supplies. And catalytic converters, the basic pollution-control equipment of ordinary gasoline cars, have been found to produce nitrous oxide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
