<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Absolut Zero</title>
    <meta content="06KALFUST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1174099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Siberia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thubron, Colin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalfus, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In Siberia (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Siberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DF133CF935A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Absolut Zero</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ken Kalfus</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kalfus, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Kalfus reviews book In Siberia, by Colin Thubron (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN SIBERIA</p>
        <p>By Colin Thubron.</p>
        <p>287 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN SIBERIA</p>
        <p>By Colin Thubron.</p>
        <p>287 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $26.</p>
        <p>THE standard wall map of Russia will mislead the unwary traveler, who may not notice the faint, fatal north latitude lines sweeping down toward the middle of the map. For example, on National Geographic's familiar transverse polyconic projection, the relatively temperate capital, Moscow, is tucked into the map's upper left-hand corner, apparently well above the country's center, when in fact it lies considerably south of it. To fully appreciate Russia, you must peer from above the North Pole down onto the frozen wastes that make up much of its land mass. More than half of Russia lies north of the 60-degree mark, the latitude of St. Petersburg and roughly the latitude of Juneau.</p>
        <p>''In Siberia'' demonstrates Colin Thubron's intimacy with these cold facts. Thubron, the British author of two previous travel books about the former Soviet Union, as well as books about the Middle East and China and several novels, recently returned to Russia to explore its bleak northern plains in an era of pervasive misery. His first journey, made in European Russia in the early 1980's and recorded in ''Where Nights Are Longest,'' had been dominated by his latent fear of the police state; in the early 90's he traveled to the newly independent countries of central Asia, producing ''The Lost Heart of Asia.'' During that time he giddily and compulsively gazed northward, at maps of Siberia: ''I was subverted by the sudden falling open of a vast area of the forbidden world,'' he tells us here.</p>
        <p>From the beginning of summer through the onset of winter he travels alone, mostly by train and bus but also by way of airplane and thumb (paying the drivers small fares, as was the custom for hitchhikers even in Socialist times). Above and below the Arctic Circle, he visits frigid outposts languishing in neglect, emptied prison camps, misplanned planned cities, cities built by Cossacks and others built by convicts. He takes a steamship north on the Yenisei River to the Arctic village of Potalovo, where he allows himself to be stranded for weeks. In Magadan, ''the capital of sorrow,'' he crawls under barred windows to explore a former detention center, where the walls of the unheated punishment cells are sheathed in ice.</p>
        <p>Thubron estimates that Siberia, whose borders have not been precisely fixed by geographers, occupies one-twelfth of the earth's land mass. It's probably the worst twelfth. His book opens ominously: ''The ice fields are crossed forever by a man in chains.'' Siberia has always served as Russia's continent-sized prison, the killing cold and inhuman distances effectively preventing escape. But Siberia has also been large enough to provide safe haven for free men and women, notably the Cossacks, ethnic Russians unbound by the claims of serfdom. This contradiction haunts contemporary Russian society, beckoning and repelling at once: as Thubron remarks, Siberia ''impends through the darkness as the ultimate, unearthly Abroad.'' At the same time, the Russian East represents for many Russians the real Russia, the one uncontaminated by the West.</p>
        <p>European civilizers, most recently the Communists, have generally come to grief on the permafrost. ''Even a century ago people were speaking of Siberia as the land of the future,'' Thubron says, ''but despite its vast western oil and gas deposits, and the mineral and lumber riches of its east, Siberia has proved too harsh, too guarded, too inaccessible, to comply.'' Wherever he travels in Siberia, Thubron finds ruins. Sometimes failure is represented by indigence and environmental devastation; other times he encounters blackly comic dissonance.</p>
        <p>Tramping through Akademgorodok, the science city built by Khrushchev, Thubron passes laboratories shuttered by the lack of funds and the collapse of Russia's once proud scientific enterprise. At the Institute of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, he is shown around by a scientist named Sasha who is preposterously evangelical on the subject of magnetic fields. Sasha invites him into his ''hypomagnetic chamber,'' which is supposed to remove all ''natural magnetic waves'' for healthful effect. Going along, as all good travelers must, Thubron lies down in the chamber while Sasha revs it up -- generating power from an exercise bicycle. Nothing happens, and Thubron must sadly reflect that he is what Sasha calls ''cosmophobic,'' and that Sasha is wasting what's left of the institute's funds.</p>
        <p>From the capital of pseudoscience he journeys to Kyzyl, the capital of Tuva, and the realms of pseudoshamanism, where the elaborate animist rituals of the Tuvans seem to have degenerated into run-of-the-mill 10-minute seances. But Thubron persists -- as a favor to an acquaintance, he's brought to Kyzyl the receipts from the sale of a yak -- and finally meets the former yak owner, Kunga-Boo, an old-time shaman who wears his raven-feathered headdress and bangs a drum for him. Kunga-Boo asks only that the next time he comes from London, Thubron bring him a vial of that transcendent substance, ''essence of walrus.''</p>
        <p>Thubron is a sensitive and observant traveler who clearly respects the Siberians for the hardships they have endured. Charming and amusing scenes, with shamans, madmen and Old Believers, dependably relieve his book's underlying grimness. But the author cannot hide his anger and grief at the tragedies that have been imposed on the Siberian landscape by the human will.</p>
        <p>Laced through the narrative is that notorious archipelago of prisons, most of them out of operation yet still palpable scars on the landscape and the conscience. Near Lake Baikal, Thubron hikes to a labor camp where in Stalin's time mica was excavated. He is shaken by this artifact of repression and, waxing philosophical, poses questions at the heart of Russia's moral reality: the labor camp's ''time seemed neither yesterday nor yet in any reconciled past. It had not been destroyed in shame, but left to decay. Why, I wondered, was there so little Russian outrage at the Gulag? Why did its perpetrators live on unpunished? I became dogged by the idea of a helpless national collusion, in which everyone was guilty, everyone innocent.''</p>
        <p>In this account, Potalovo, the Arctic village on the Yenisei, stands as the emblem of failed Soviet development efforts. The former fur-trading village and reindeer collective has become a squalid and depressed slum-in-an-icebox. Acid rain from the nearby Norilsk nickel processing factories has destroyed the reindeer pastures, and wild reindeer won't cross the gas pipelines. The human cost among the native Entsy people is made tangible by the coal-black local pond glistening with discarded vodka bottles.</p>
        <p>As Thubron knows, Siberia also has its gorgeous side -- mostly inaccessible, to be glimpsed through the windows of his conveyances. Flying north of the Arctic Circle, he gazes upon ''a treeless tundra whose earth was a silvery maze of lichen and fungi. No road or railway crossed it. For thousands of square miles the wilderness shattered into a jigsaw of ponds and streams, as if the whole continent had flattened to sponge, where the rivers wound fantastically upon one another, and splintered 10 or 20 ways.'' Alas, planes, buses and trains usually deposit him in utterly prosaic built-up places.</p>
        <p>''In Siberia'' places the region in its historical context, but Thubron's history is never didactic or potted. Above all, Thubron is never a travel bore. With minimal complaint about traveling inconveniences, he keeps his focus on Siberia. Readers may derive a great deal of travel envy from this account of his adventures. Thubron covered a lot of ground. Many of us, though, will be glad that he was the one who made the trip, so that we won't have to.</p>
        <p>Ken Kalfus is the author of two short story collections, ''Thirst'' and ''Pu-239: And Other Russian Fantasies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ken Kalfus is the author of two short story collections, ''Thirst'' and ''Pu-239: And Other Russian Fantasies.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
