<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking the Big Tepee From the Bronx to Maryland</title>
    <meta content="23LORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CITY LORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smithsonian Institution (Washington, DC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Museum of the American Indian</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merritt, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD9173AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking the Big Tepee From the Bronx to Maryland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD STAMLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of Scott Merritt, who is in charge of moving more than 800,000 objects and artifacts comprising bulk of one million items in Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of the American Indian from warehouse in Bronx, NYC, to new building in Maryland; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you've ever wondered how museums move their collections back and forth, Scott Merritt has the answer: very, very carefully.</p>
        <p>He should know. Mr. Merritt is in charge of moving the more than 800,000 objects and artifacts that comprise the bulk of the one million items in the permanent collection of the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of the American Indian, from arrowheads and clay jars to canoes, masks and totem poles, ''fascinating, beautiful objects,'' said Elizabeth Gaston, one of those working on the move. After decades in an overcrowded, run-down brick warehouse off Interstate 95 in the Pelham Bay section of the Bronx, the items are now headed south, to a new building in Maryland. And it is Mr. Merritt's job to make sure they get there safely. The work, which began last year, is going into high gear this summer and will continue for two more years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you've ever wondered how museums move their collections back and forth, Scott Merritt has the answer: very, very carefully.</p>
        <p>He should know. Mr. Merritt is in charge of moving the more than 800,000 objects and artifacts that comprise the bulk of the one million items in the permanent collection of the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of the American Indian, from arrowheads and clay jars to canoes, masks and totem poles, ''fascinating, beautiful objects,'' said Elizabeth Gaston, one of those working on the move. After decades in an overcrowded, run-down brick warehouse off Interstate 95 in the Pelham Bay section of the Bronx, the items are now headed south, to a new building in Maryland. And it is Mr. Merritt's job to make sure they get there safely. The work, which began last year, is going into high gear this summer and will continue for two more years.</p>
        <p>The move is the last stage of the federal takeover of what was once an independent New York museum, founded by Gustave Heye, a financier. Mr. Heye spent his life acquiring as many Indian items as he could, and single-handedly amassed most of the collection.</p>
        <p>In 1922, he opened the Museum of the American Indian at 155th Street and Broadway. But it was too far away from Manhattan's other museums, and off the tourist track, and so despite the breadth of its holdings, few visitors came. After Mr. Heye died in 1957, the museum slowly fell into disuse and disrepair.</p>
        <p>During the 1980's, many proposals were made to rescue the museum, including one that would have merged it into the American Museum of Natural History on Central Park West. In 1989, after that plan fell through, the Heye Foundation, which Mr. Heye established to run the museum, agreed to transfer its collection to the Smithsonian. The institution agreed to create a permanent home for the collection on the Mall in Washington, and to open a satellite museum at the old Custom House on Bowling Green in Manhattan. The Smithsonian also promised to build a new storage and research centerin Suitland, Md., for the bulk of the collection, which previously had been warehoused in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The Bowling Green museum opened in 1994. Ground for the Washington branch, to open in 2002, was broken last year. And the Suitland building, called the Cultural Resource Center, also opened last year. That's when the move from the Bronx began.</p>
        <p>The items are of great historic and religious significance, said Russ Tall Chief, a museum spokesman who is an Osage from Oklahoma, and so religious ceremonies  must occasionally be performed before they are moved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Merritt explained that the ceremonies might involve ''smudging,'' or the burning of small amounts of cedar or grass, accompanied by a prayer and sometimes by the serving of wine or food. Sometimes, the proceedings were even more elaborate. One group painted red dots on participants' foreheads and crosses on their wrists. An Indian  consultant advises Mr. Merritt on the need for ceremonies, he said.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Merritt said, workers have moved only ''28,000 ethnology objects and about 18,000 archaeological objects.'' The process is taking so long in part because Mr.  Heye's original catalog, which he did himself, by hand, must be updated and computerized. Also, each object must be tagged with a bar-coded label and digitally photographed before it leaves the Bronx, so that it can become part of what Mr. Merritt called the ''new museum database.''</p>
        <p>Many require restoration, too, because of their age and, sometimes, because of deterioration suffered in the Bronx warehouse, which has stored items since 1926 and long suffered from leaks and inadequate ventilation. Some items are infested with insects and their larva.</p>
        <p>To make sure that no unwanted visitors accompany the objects on their trip, most are frozen first for at least seven days at 35 degrees below zero. Others, too fragile for freezing, are fumigated or placed in carbon dioxide chambers. And, infested or not, items that are broken or dirty are fixed and cleaned by workers experienced in preservation.</p>
        <p>Once the objects are ready for transfer, they are loaded into tractor-trailer trucks. Unmarked vehicles are used, for fear of hijacking. Security is tight throughout the process.</p>
        <p>The move will cost between $15 million and $18 million, Mr. Merritt said, which includes restoration and improving the physical condition of the Bronx warehouse, as well as paying a staff of 28 people.</p>
        <p>On a recent rainy afternoon, Abby Sohn and Angela Yvarra, museum conservation technicians clad in laboratory coats, carefully vacuumed a Sioux buffalo robe before packing it. It had been infested with insect casings, Ms. Yvarra said. Down the hall, Dorothy Morris and Ms. Gaston examined numbers scratched by Mr. Heye on the bottoms of pots, and cross-checked them with computer printouts before affixing labels and packing them in bubble wrap. A computer technician worked nearby with a digital camera, photographing each item with its catalog number conspicuously displayed alongside.</p>
        <p>All four had worked for other museums or on other conservation projects. But they agreed that this experience was special.</p>
        <p>''It's been such a gift to be able to come here and see these things every day,'' Ms. Yvarra said.</p>
        <p>CITY LORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
