<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detroit Plays Catch-Up In Race for Hybrid Car; With Fewer Subsidies, Japan Is Ahead</title>
    <meta content="Y01GAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81338F932A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detroit Plays Catch-Up In Race for Hybrid Car; With Fewer Subsidies, Japan Is Ahead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experimental vehicles are being built by General Motors, Ford Motor Co and DaimlerChrysler under umbrella of government-sponsored Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles; they face huge obstacles; Big Three are all focusing on diesel-electric hybrid cars, even though federal and state environmental regulators are adopting new rules for tailpipe emissions that will make it difficult after 2003 to sell cars with diesel engines; Honda Motor and Toyota Motor, operating with much smaller government subsidies, are already mass producing small high-mileage cars that combine gasoline engines and electric motors; manufacturing costs for all hybrid cars, including Japanese models, are steep; selling them at competitive prices remains money-losing proposition; and there is little sign that Americans want high-mileage cars in era of relatively low gasoline prices and rising national prosperity; photos; diagrams (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With hundreds of millions of dollars of private and federal research work behind it, the General Motors Precept, an experimental model to be introduced here on Jan. 9, is probably the most expensive single car ever built. Yet it is still a lot of car for the money.</p>
        <p>In place of side-view mirrors, which cause a lot of wind resistance, it has tiny cameras, mounted on the front doors, that send images to the dashboard. Rather than the smooth, rounded contours commonly associated with aerodynamic design, carefully angled body panels are designed to give the six-passenger Precept far less wind resistance than a Corvette sports car. And instead of a gasoline engine, the car has two electric motors, batteries under the seats and a rear diesel engine to charge the batteries and provide additional power and range.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With hundreds of millions of dollars of private and federal research work behind it, the General Motors Precept, an experimental model to be introduced here on Jan. 9, is probably the most expensive single car ever built. Yet it is still a lot of car for the money.</p>
        <p>In place of side-view mirrors, which cause a lot of wind resistance, it has tiny cameras, mounted on the front doors, that send images to the dashboard. Rather than the smooth, rounded contours commonly associated with aerodynamic design, carefully angled body panels are designed to give the six-passenger Precept far less wind resistance than a Corvette sports car. And instead of a gasoline engine, the car has two electric motors, batteries under the seats and a rear diesel engine to charge the batteries and provide additional power and range.</p>
        <p>These features, which produce remarkable fuel economy of almost 80 miles a gallon, are expected to influence what Americans will drive early in this new century. But the Precept and similar experimental vehicles from Ford Motor and DaimlerChrysler being built under the umbrella of the government-sponsored Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles face huge obstacles that raise serious questions about the costly partnership between Detroit and Washington.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the Big Three have all focused on diesel-electric hybrid cars. Yet federal and state environmental regulators have just adopted new rules for tailpipe emissions that will make it very difficult after 2003 to sell automobiles with diesel engines. Meanwhile, Honda Motor and Toyota Motor, operating with much smaller government subsidies, have already begun mass production of small high-mileage cars that combine gasoline engines and electric motors, leaving Detroit scrambling to catch up.</p>
        <p>Manufacturing costs for all hybrid cars, including the Japanese models, are steep, so selling them at competitive prices remains a money-losing proposition. Perhaps most daunting of all, there is little sign that Americans want high-mileage cars in an era of relatively low gasoline prices and rising national prosperity.</p>
        <p>The combination has left Detroit executives alarmed by a new competitive threat from Japan, frustrated by what they see as conflicting strategies among government agencies and struggling to justify further investments in cars like the Precept. But auto industry leaders here say that despite the problems, they intend to continue pouring money into high-technology cars, mainly to protect themselves in case gasoline prices soar again someday.</p>
        <p>''We'd better be prepared to deal with it,'' said Harry Pearce, G.M.'s vice chairman. ''You don't revolutionize your industry overnight.''</p>
        <p>The biggest embarrassment for G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler is that Honda and Toyota have beaten them to the market for hybrids. The Clinton administration has given $1.4 billion over the last five years to national laboratories, universities, auto parts manufacturers and Detroit automakers to help in the building of a few experimental models. Yet Japanese automakers, who were excluded from the program, have been able to put working hybrids on sale first.</p>
        <p>The Honda Insight, which went on sale on Dec. 15, starts at $19,295, and gets 61 miles to the gallon in the city and 70 on the highway. Toyota plans to start selling its bigger Prius next summer for a little over $20,000, and predicts that its car will approach a combined 50 miles to the gallon.</p>
        <p>Honda and Toyota officials don't mind rubbing it in. ''We always see our competitors talking about their projects as soon as we hit the market with a real product,'' said Robert Bienenfeld, Honda's manager of sales and marketing of alternative-fuel vehicles.</p>
        <p>The Japanese government has provided a small subsidy for the cars. Japanese car buyers who choose the new-technology automobiles receive a $3,000 rebate from the government. The Clinton administration proposed a similar program in the United States last winter. It was combined with tax-cut proposals in Congress and never made it into law, but is expected to pass once G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler have cars that can use such subsidies.</p>
        <p>While Honda and Toyota executives refuse to discuss their costs, auto analysts say that both automakers will be losing money on every car they sell. But with Honda planning to sell only 4,000 Insights in the United States next year and Toyota expecting to offer just 12,000 Prius cars in the 2001 model year, neither company's costs will be exorbitant.</p>
        <p>Yet as Detroit executives have been quick to point out, the Insight and Prius fall far short of the roomy, high-performance sedans that G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler hope to produce someday. The Insight, for example, is essentially a two-seat, very lightweight aluminum car with a small gasoline engine that does most of the work. As in most hybrid cars, the engine shuts off when the vehicle stops; once the driver touches the accelerator, a small electric motor and modest batteries get the car moving again while the gasoline engine turns back on.</p>
        <p>Toyota has taken a different approach with the Prius, which closely resembles a Corolla from the outside. Compared with the Insight, the electric motor and batteries provide a much greater proportion of the car's overall power. But the Prius, because it is heavier, manages to achieve only slightly better mileage than the smaller Chevrolet Metro. The Prius, in essence, is a compact car with fuel economy a little better than a subcompact's.</p>
        <p>Despite these cars' shortcomings, Detroit automakers, particularly G.M., still feel pressure to match the Japanese entrants. G.M., which marketed the all-electric EV-1 with little success from 1996 to 1998, is already studying ways to introduce a small gasoline-electric hybrid vehicle, using its technical partnership with Toyota, Mr. Pearce acknowledged. While G.M. and Toyota officials refuse to elaborate, environmentalists say that the companies are working on a gasoline-electric car that would look like a sport utility vehicle and would probably be manufactured at their joint operation in Fremont, Calif.</p>
        <p>But there are engineering limits to the fuel efficiency of gasoline engines, and automakers appear to be approaching those limits. So G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler have been working with the government on diesel-electric hybrids instead. Diesel engines can be up to 30 percent more efficient than gasoline engines. However, even though today's diesels are far cleaner and quieter than earlier versions, they may still  run afoul of the new and unexpectedly tough state and federal air pollution regulations.</p>
        <p>The auto industry's problems began a year ago, when the California Air Resources Board met to approve a staff proposal to require sport utility vehicles and other light trucks to meet the far more stringent air pollution standards for cars. One of the board members, who are political appointees, noted that the staff proposal did not change the rules on diesel-powered light trucks. Yet the board had voted the month before to classify diesel emissions as a toxic air contaminant. Automakers had been laying plans for years to build more sport utility vehicles with conventional diesel engines so as to meet Federal fuel economy rules.</p>
        <p>After less than half an hour of discussion, and with no staff analysis, the board amended the staff's proposal to eliminate the agency's longstanding separate regulations for diesel-powered family vehicles. Even though diesels offer better fuel economy and produce lower quantities of gases associated with global warming, they will be subject to the same strict standards as gasoline-powered cars, beginning with the 2004 model year. Effectively, that will mean new cars with diesel engines will be banned from California.</p>
        <p>''Fuel economy is strictly a federal area; we don't deal with it, we don't have the mandate to deal with it,'' Richard Varenchik, a spokesman for the board, said. Prodded by a national lobbying effort by environmentalists against pollution by sport utility vehicles, New York and Massachusetts are now moving to adopt California's emissions rules, including the diesel provisions.</p>
        <p>President Clinton gave final approval last week to strict new federal regulations on tailpipe emissions that will also take effect with the 2004 model year. The federal rules are slightly less stringent than California's standards; Gary Guzy, the general counsel of the Environmental Protection Agency, said that with further research, it should be possible to develop diesel engines clean enough to comply with the least stringent category.</p>
        <p>But automakers will only be allowed to sell a limited number of vehicles in that category, which they already plan to use for large sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks. As a result, automakers will face a choice between selling high-mileage, diesel-electric hybrid cars or selling large, high-profit sport utility vehicles and pickups.</p>
        <p>Automakers once hoped that the Republicans who control Congress would rescue them from their environmental predicament, but that hope is evaporating like a puddle of spilled gasoline. Stung by environmentalists' television advertisements in New Hampshire criticizing air pollution in Texas, Gov. George W. Bush, a leading candidate for the Republican presidential nomination, said in a debate in New Hampshire in early December that he favored the federal air quality rules that President Clinton was about to approve. Two weeks later, Mr. Bush asked the Texas Natural Resources Commission to consider adopting California's auto emissions rules.</p>
        <p>Even if an unexpected technological breakthrough allows automakers to address the emissions problems of diesel engines, a bigger question looms: How many Americans will want very high-mileage cars? New automobile buyers these days rank fuel economy down with the quality of seat fabrics and interior carpeting, behind two dozen other considerations, according to recent surveys by Auto Pacific, a market research firm in Santa Ana, Calif.</p>
        <p>Americans pay so little attention to gasoline these days because it is so cheap, even after a run-up in prices over the last year. The United States has the lowest gasoline taxes of any large industrialized country. In Europe and Japan, where high taxes push the price to $4 or $5 a gallon, small cars are much more popular, which is why their citizens are expected to buy large numbers of hybrids long before Americans do.</p>
        <p>Hybrid cars also have a few nuisances that may irritate Americans spoiled by the power of gasoline-powered cars. For instance, most models -- including the Precept, Insight and Prius -- have fuel-efficient manual transmissions, which are becoming almost extinct in the American auto market.</p>
        <p>The hybrids also have less power to spare for accessories. The Prodigy, an experimental, diesel-electric car that Ford also plans to display at the North American International Auto show early in January where the G.M. car will be introduced, has an air-conditioning system that shuts down whenever the car stops. The car's electric motor is not strong enough to run the air-conditioning by itself.</p>
        <p>Rescuing the occupants of hybrid vehicles after crashes could also prove tricky. While the hybrids meet Federal safety standards when crashed into concrete barriers, their batteries and high-voltage cables pose special risks for rescuers who must cut into vehicles to save trapped motorists.</p>
        <p>The auto industry and federal officials say that they plan to continue working on all these problems, and will hope for breakthroughs in their research.</p>
        <p>The United States still needs to keep working on high-technology cars, Bill Richardson, the energy secretary, said, because ''getting a highly fuel-efficient car that can meet the demands of U.S. consumers in the market will reduce pollution and enhance our energy security.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
