<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY; Whitman Seen as Strong Choice for E.P.A.</title>
    <meta content="21ENVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/21/politics/21ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3D61E39F932A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY; Whitman Seen as Strong Choice for E.P.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER with ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C; Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Gov Christine Todd Whitman is rumored choice to head Environmental Protection Agency in new Bush administration; environmental scientists and advocates react warmly to anticipated announcement; say she is best that liberal conservation groups can hope for in Republican administration; say she is strong choice to head agency because of stature she would bring as first governor to hold post and as one of best-known women in Republican politics; Whitman says she is very pleased with her stewardship of state's environment; leaders of few of state's environmental watchdog groups harshly criticize her record (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Republicans spread the word that she was President-elect George W. Bush's choice to head the Environmental Protection Agency, Gov. Christie Whitman of New Jersey proudly defended her environmental record in interviews this week, refusing to confirm reports that she had been selected while seeming already to be practicing for the national stage.</p>
        <p>Environmental scientists and advocates generally reacted warmly to the anticipated announcement, which several officials here said would come by week's end, calling her the best that liberal conservation groups could hope for in a Republican administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Republicans spread the word that she was President-elect George W. Bush's choice to head the Environmental Protection Agency, Gov. Christie Whitman of New Jersey proudly defended her environmental record in interviews this week, refusing to confirm reports that she had been selected while seeming already to be practicing for the national stage.</p>
        <p>Environmental scientists and advocates generally reacted warmly to the anticipated announcement, which several officials here said would come by week's end, calling her the best that liberal conservation groups could hope for in a Republican administration.</p>
        <p>Leaders of a few New Jersey environmental watchdog groups harshly criticized the governor's record on regulation and enforcement of air and water quality standards, which make up much of the purview of the E.P.A. But advocates and experts outside the state described Mrs. Whitman as a strong choice to head the agency, in part because of the stature she would bring as the first governor to hold the job and as one of the best-known women in Republican politics.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Tuesday night,  Governor Whitman said she was ''very pleased'' with her stewardship of the environment in New Jersey, which she said had produced cleaner air and water, state money to preserve a million acres of open space and an aggressive approach to cleaning up old industrial sites.</p>
        <p>''Nationally, New Jersey is looked on as being in the forefront of environmental policy,'' she said. ''Is there more to do? Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>The governor, who has a year remaining in her second and last term, said one of her main pieces of unfinished business was an ambitious set of water quality and watershed management rules, which would go a long way toward determining how New Jersey distributes the million new residents expected over the next two decades. The state is revising its proposal after an earlier version met with widespread opposition from lawmakers in both parties, builders and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>''I would love to be further along in those, but I'm not surprised to be where we are today, simply because these are the big megillahs,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''The dialogue has started, the dialogue is real. I think the public is ready for some kind of constraint on new septic permits and on water quality. And so we are moving forward.</p>
        <p>''The fact that we're being attacked by both sides leads me to believe that we're probably right where we need to be, which is in the middle, to find some kind of common ground.''</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, Mrs. Whitman's critics on the environment still bitterly recall her first term, when she cut enforcement and spending over all, abolished an environmental prosecutor's office, and eased right-to-know reporting rules for companies that handle toxic materials.</p>
        <p>David S. Pringle, campaign director of the New Jersey Environmental Federation, commended the governor's open-space program and other initiatives in her second term.</p>
        <p>''She's gone from bad to better, and hopefully it'll go to good'' at the E.P.A., Mr. Pringle said.</p>
        <p>But from a distance, and in comparison with other Republican governors -- including Mr. Bush -- Mrs. Whitman is seen far more favorably.</p>
        <p>Fred Krupp, executive director of Environmental Defense, one of the nation's largest environmental groups, said Mrs. Whitman would be a ''very positive'' appointment, if not because of her efforts to combat air pollution and to protect New Jersey's coast, then because of her credibility as a governor.</p>
        <p>''In every administration, there are always voices on the other sides of these issues,'' Mr. Krupp said. ''Given the stature that she walks in with, and her record in New Jersey, we're hopeful that she would not be afraid to be an independent voice to make the environmental case.''</p>
        <p>But on one of the most salient  issues -- climate change -- Mrs. Whitman's statements this week left some scientists and environmental advocates perplexed, especially since her administration has been a leader among the states in addressing the problem. For example, New Jersey was the first states to set a target for reducing emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>But when asked to discuss her views on the science behind global warming on Tuesday, Governor Whitman responded by citing her doubts about the causes of the hole in the protective ozone layer high in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>She was asked: ''Global warming, what is your thought on what the state of science is and what can be done to address it?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman said: ''Still somewhat uncertain. Clearly there's a hole in the ozone, that has been identified. But I saw a study the other day that showed that that was closing. It's not as clear, the cause and effect, as we would like it to be.''</p>
        <p>When some experts on the atmosphere and pollution read a transcript of Mrs. Whitman's statements, they said the governor had clearly confused two distinct, important global environmental problems: global warming and the ozone hole.</p>
        <p>Today, asked to clarify her views, the governor said she might have misunderstood the question, but added that she did not think the two issues were ''not interrelated.''</p>
        <p>''In both of those instances, I'm not sure that there's a scientific consensus on how to deal with them,'' Governor Whitman said today. ''There seems to be good enough evidence that both are occurring. But I am not aware of a uniformly agreed to scientific response, on either the causes or the solutions here.''</p>
        <p>The governor added, ''Those are the kinds of questions that I'm going to be answering in a Senate confirmation hearing, if this comes to pass, if I'm ever nominated, and if I'm going to be taking this position.''</p>
        <p>Told of the governor's remarks, some scientists expressed mild concern.</p>
        <p>''We in the scientific community understand that to deal with these issues involves not just science but also a value judgment on policy, but it's very important to get the science right,'' said Mario J. Molina, a professor of chemistry at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Dr. Molina shared a Nobel Prize in 1995 for work that identified the link between certain synthetic industrial chemicals, chlorofluorocarbons, and damage to the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>''With that in mind,'' he said, ''we'd be happy to help advise her and help her get things right.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
