<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="03FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDF103DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Peace Talks Are Shelved As Mideast Death Toll Rises  Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel said peace talks were now ''on the shelf'' and Yasir Arafat called for an emergency Arab summit meeting, as violence tore through Israel and the Palestinian territories for the fifth straight day, leaving at least 15 dead and scores more severely wounded. President Clinton and other foreign leaders called for a halt to the violence and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright said she would meet with Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat in Paris on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Peace Talks Are Shelved As Mideast Death Toll Rises  Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel said peace talks were now ''on the shelf'' and Yasir Arafat called for an emergency Arab summit meeting, as violence tore through Israel and the Palestinian territories for the fifth straight day, leaving at least 15 dead and scores more severely wounded. President Clinton and other foreign leaders called for a halt to the violence and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright said she would meet with Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat in Paris on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Milosevic Denounces Opponent  President Slobodan Milosevic went on Yugoslav national television to implore citizens to re-elect him in a runoff and reject efforts by what he called a traitorous opposition to organize a general strike. His challenger, Vojislav Kostunica, who says he won the presidency outright in elections on Sept. 24, reiterated to striking miners that he would not participate in a second round.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Russia Bolsters Tajik Border  Russia is laying antipersonnel mines and reinforcing positions along the border between Tajikistan and Afghanistan. Taliban fighters have moved within artillery range of the Russian Army, which protects the gateway to Central Asia, but a senior Russian official said Moscow did not expect an attack.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The worst drought in 50 years has followed a decade of industrial collapse and civil war and threatens half of Tajikistan's population.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Rebuffed on U.N. Dues  The European Union rebuffed an American request to have Washington's dues to the United Nations lowered, as a review began of each country's contributions.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Hurricane Batters Caribbean  Hurricane Keith tore up buildings and caused flooding throughout Central America and Mexico, causing at least three deaths. The storm swirled just off the coast of Belize and was drifiting north.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Reggie Kray  The last survivor of the three-brother gang of ruthless enforcers who ran London's underworld in the 1950's and 1960's was 66.</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-25</p>
        <p>Poll Finds Both Candidates Faring Well on Leadership  A New York Times/CBS News Poll shows that most Americans regard Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore as strong leaders, but they consider Mr. Gore far more prepared for the White House and better qualified to deal with world leaders and members of both parties in Congress. But when voters are asked to assess each man on the broader question of his potential to be ''an effective president,'' both candidates receive high marks. The poll also found that Mr. Bush's personal popularity had eroded slightly as Mr. Gore's continued to improve. In terms of voter preferences, Mr. Gore held a narrow lead over Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gore is leading in California, Mr. Bush is far outpacing him in contributions in Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>On the day before their first debate, Mr. Bush campaigned in West Virginia and Mr. Gore was sequestered with advisers in Florida.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman prepared for their debate on Thursday.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>An independent analysis of the Bush and Gore tax proposals.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Senate Fight Over River Wildlife  The Senate, ignoring the threat of a veto and voting 57 to 37, approved a measure barring the Army Corps of Engineers from altering the Missouri River's flow to protect two birds and a fish, the piping plover, the least tern and the pallid sturgeon.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Execution Delayed in Texas  A state judge delayed the execution of Stacey Lawton, convicted of murdering a man in 1992, because his court-appointed lawyer had missed the deadline for filing a clemency petition on his behalf.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>New Efficiency Standards  Central air-conditioning and heat pumps would have to do the same amount of work on 20 to 30 percent less electricity under standards to be proposed today by the Energy Department. They are part of an effort to reduce consumption by appliances to cut air pollution, fuel use and strain on the electric system.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>New Strategy Against Drinking  Colleges across the country say a new tactic to discourage binge drinking -- simply saying students don't drink so much, after all -- has surprised many by producing notable declines in the number of students who say they drink heavily.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>State Monitors Fault Nassau Financial Plan  A state board monitoring Nassau County's fiscal crisis said the county executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, had failed to balance the budget in his new four-year rescue plan. The report urged county officials to devise a sound proposal by the end of the month or face a state takeover.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A Car and Its Owner Reunited  Pavel Grinberg, who lost his car 19 months ago in the first criminal case resulting from a citywide crackdown on drunken driving, got his car back, though the case was dropped in January. The Acura had to be towed home because its engine was dead.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Church Embezzlement Inquiry  Queens investigators said some questions might never be answered about sizable sums reported missing at Our Lady Queen of Martyrs Church in Forest Hills, including precisely how much was missing and how many people were involved.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>New Debate on Warming  A sharp new debate has sprung up among atmospheric scientists over where to focus efforts against global warming: carbon dioxide, the most common greenhouse gas, or less common but more powerful substances, like methane, ozone and soot. The debate comes as international negotiators prepare for talks on the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, a treaty governing greenhouse emissions.</p>
        <p>F1  Digging Into Syria  A 4,300-year-old tomb excavated this summer is the oldest unplundered elite tomb to be found in Syria, its American-Dutch discovery team said, and promises new insights into a little-known urban culture.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Ravenous Threat to Fisheries  Swarms of jellyfish consumed so many fish eggs and larvae in the Gulf of Mexico this summer that some scientists are talking about the potential for serious future threats to commercial and recreational fisheries in the northern Gulf.</p>
        <p>F2</p>
        <p>Nothing to Cheer About  Some experts worry that cheerleading has become nearly as dangerous as the sports the cheerleaders root for. The most recent estimate showed 21,096 injuries associated with cheerleading last year.</p>
        <p>F8</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Hearing on Music Industry Suit  A federal appeals court in San Francisco heard arguments on whether to reinstate a lower-court injunction, pending trial, barring the online music service Napster from facilitating exchanges of copyrighted music.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Profit Warning From Xerox  Xerox, citing lower sales at a time of rising costs, warned after the close that it would report a third-quarter loss of 15 to 20 cents a share.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>2-Year Manufacturing Low  Manufacturing fell in September for the second straight month, a sign that higher borrowing and energy costs caused factory cutbacks.</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>New Encryption Standard  The Commerce Department chose the Rijndael encryption technique, developed by two Belgian computer scientists, as the new standard for protecting sensitive information on government computers and for computers of organizations doing business with the government.</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1-10</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Baseball Playoffs Begin  The Yankees play the A's at Oakland today, the Seattle Mariners play the White Sox in Chicago and the Atlanta Braves face the Cardinals in St. Louis. The Mets face the Giants tomorrow in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Conflagration in the Middle East; Congressional dos and don'ts; playoff time.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
