<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winter in New York: Something's Missing; Absence of Snow Upsets Rhythms Of Urban Life and Natural World</title>
    <meta content="15SNOW$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1168731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED8103AF936A25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winter in New York: Something's Missing; Absence of Snow Upsets Rhythms Of Urban Life and Natural World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dearth of snow in New York City area this winterupsets rhythms of urban life and natural world, depriving trees of snow cover and children of sledding opportunities; photos; graph; arrival of bit of old winter, white dusting and cold temperatures, finally gives radio and television announcers chance at some exciting moments, however fleeting (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once, and not so many years ago, no New Yorker would have dignified a January with three chilly days in a row and a soggy spurt of whitish precipitation as winter. Winter in New York was a season of single-digit temperatures, icy winds whipping off the Hudson and snow forts that did not begin to melt until March.</p>
        <p>That chilly stuff Thursday that melted as soon as it touched asphalt -- snow? A sunny Friday afternoon in the 20's -- bitter cold? In Yazoo City, Miss., or Mobile, Ala., maybe. But not in New York City.  Until now. Years of mild, rainy winters seem to be making New Yorkers hungry for the freezing winds and snow they deplored when it was plentiful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once, and not so many years ago, no New Yorker would have dignified a January with three chilly days in a row and a soggy spurt of whitish precipitation as winter. Winter in New York was a season of single-digit temperatures, icy winds whipping off the Hudson and snow forts that did not begin to melt until March.</p>
        <p>That chilly stuff Thursday that melted as soon as it touched asphalt -- snow? A sunny Friday afternoon in the 20's -- bitter cold? In Yazoo City, Miss., or Mobile, Ala., maybe. But not in New York City.  Until now. Years of mild, rainy winters seem to be making New Yorkers hungry for the freezing winds and snow they deplored when it was plentiful.</p>
        <p>So the arrival of a bit of real winter -- of Thursday's flurries in the city, of yesterday's lows in the teens, of foot-deep snow in Albany and the Catskills -- created the kind of excitement once reserved for much more extreme meteorological episodes. Radio and television announcers warned listeners about frostbite, and news writers dusted off adjectives like ''blustery.''</p>
        <p>''It's good, the snow,'' said Glen Cooper, a telephone technician, standing on Eighth Avenue near Times Square, smiling, as the evanescent flakes melted on his face on Thursday. ''Snow slows people down. It makes people happy. It's natural.''</p>
        <p>Freezing, snowy winters are not only natural for New York's trees and greenery, they are entwined in the lore and arts of the city. They influence moods, they inspire poetry and painting, they drive advertising and appetites, they build childhood memories. So the mild winters of the last few years have caused a major ripple effect, from ecology to gastronomy.</p>
        <p>To gardeners, one of the most troubling aspects of an April-like January is that it causes many flowering plants and trees to bloom prematurely, including bulbs and fruit trees. Tricked into thinking that spring is approaching, the early buds leave themselves vulnerable to cold snaps, like this one.</p>
        <p>Like a quilt on a bed, a blanket of snow keeps the organisms beneath the surface of the soil warm. Without this covering, the insects, bacteria and tree roots underground are left to the mercy of sudden freezes. That could mean there will be fewer ladybird beetles and other useful insects in the spring, said Maurice J. and Catherine A. Tauber, entomologists at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>And a complex biological chain reaction, beginning with bacteria living in the soil, could result in high-acid soil, which could run off into the streams and rivers and harm the fish, said Gary M. Lovett, a scientist at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in Millbrook, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Without their warm snow cover, birches and sugar and red maples, too, are vulnerable to freeze damage, said Allan Auclair, a scientist at the RAND Corporation, a nonprofit research and policy organization in Washington. Sugar maples in Vermont are showing damage, which is probably at least partly the result of the lack of snow, he said.</p>
        <p>The already overabundant deer, mice and squirrel populations are likely to increase even more because food supplies are more plentiful and accessible in mild weather. (Luckily, the even more dreaded rats and cockroaches should not proliferate any more than usual.)</p>
        <p>But it does not take a scientist to size up the effects of snowless winters on the children too young to remember the record-setting blizzards of 1996. For them, the pleasures of sledding and snowball fights are as out-of-date as hoop-rolling, and the delight of a snow day off from school is unknown.</p>
        <p>''I bought a sled in '96 for my daughter,'' said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a scientist at the nonprofit Environmental Defense Fund. ''It's been sitting in the stairwell, and hasn't been used. I used to go sledding all the time. It's one of my most vivid and pleasant memories as a kid, hauling the sled out to Cunningham Park in Queens.''</p>
        <p>Marcella Durand, 32, a poet at the St. Marks Poetry Project in the East Village, remembers burrowing through tunnels and building igloos and snowmen in a snow-buried TriBeCa. ''I really miss the snow,'' she said. ''I miss the peace. I miss looking out the windows onto streets with snow falling around the lights, like a special halo. It brought a little bit of peace to the city. It's the only thing that seems to quiet the city down.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it is easy on a 50-degree day in January to wax nostalgic about the glories of a hard freeze. Even people who moved to Miami to escape the cold have been overtaken by a craving for the coziness of a warm fire in a snowstorm. Some even crank up the air-conditioning so they can huddle by a fake-log fire with a hot whiskey or a cup of cocoa.</p>
        <p>Another result of the succession of warm winters is the emergence of a cause of clinical depression. These are bad times for the tiny group of people who become depressed in the summer and cheerful in the winter. ''Some people are energized by winter,'' said Dr. Thomas Wehr, a psychiatrist at the National Institutes of Mental Health. ''They look forward to summer with dread.'' The mild weather is cheating them of the cold they crave, he said.</p>
        <p>At least part of the reason for the recent warm winter is La Nina, the chilly air in the equatorial Pacific that has been pushing the vast stream of cold air north along the border of the United States and Canada. This has been allowing space for warm winds from the south to expand into the Northeast, including New York. And Dr. Oppenheimer, among other ecologists, points to global warming as perhaps the most significant long-term factor.</p>
        <p>Nearly everybody has an occasional craving for an icy, snowy day. What use are beautiful wool sweaters, high leather boots, thick stews and hot toddies when it's warm? At Cashmere, Cashmere on the Upper East Side, sales of sweaters and sweatsuits have been slow, though they picked up during yesterday's cold, said Jan Mehalick, the owner. At Judson Grill in Midtown, customers are ordering fish at lunch instead of the hearty winter cassoulet, Bill Telepan, the chef, said.</p>
        <p>And snowstorms make the city beautiful, at least for a day or two. From an aesthetic point of view, drab light and rain cannot compare with the glistening white and pristine silence of snow. Snow makes events vivid. Who could forget the familiar Currier &amp; Ives images and E. B. White's rendition of stoic Maine farmers and their camaraderie during deep snowfalls.</p>
        <p>Who could forget the sight of people cross-country skiing down Broadway during the blizzards of 1996? During the Great Blizzard in 1947, jazz fans created an urban legend when they turned out in force to hear Duke Ellington and his musicians play the ''Liberian Suite'' in Carnegie Hall.</p>
        <p>Despite global warming and La Nina, New Yorkers who are hungry for snow and ice may still find some satisfaction in the months ahead. Snow is predicted for Tuesday -- and that could well mean a snowfall that sticks, rather than mere flurries. Over the next 10 weeks, there are plenty of ''snow opportunities,'' said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>''All it takes is one or two good snowstorms and you've got yourself a winter,'' he said. ''If I were a betting man -- and I'm not -- but if I were, I'd say there's a good chance there'll be a good old-fashioned snowstorm some time this winter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
