<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Ozone Hole Refuels Debate on Climate</title>
    <meta content="10OZON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/10/science/10OZON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chlorofluorocarbons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D6103CF933A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Ozone Hole Refuels Debate on Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists report that hole that opens in ozone layer over Antarctica each southern spring formed earlier and grew bigger this year than at any time since satellites have been monitoring polar atmosphere; finding renews suspicions among atmospheric scientists that global warming could be indirectly abetting chemical reactions that destroy ozone, but many still say growth of hole could also be result of natural, albeit unusual, variations in Antarctic weather and other conditions; illustrations of satellite images (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hole that opens in the ozone layer over Antarctica each southern spring formed earlier and grew bigger this year than at any time since satellites have been monitoring the polar atmosphere, scientists have reported.</p>
        <p>The finding renewed suspicions among atmospheric scientists that global warming could be indirectly abetting the chemical reactions that destroy ozone, but many still say the growth of the hole could also be the result of natural, albeit unusual, variations in Antarctic weather and other conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hole that opens in the ozone layer over Antarctica each southern spring formed earlier and grew bigger this year than at any time since satellites have been monitoring the polar atmosphere, scientists have reported.</p>
        <p>The finding renewed suspicions among atmospheric scientists that global warming could be indirectly abetting the chemical reactions that destroy ozone, but many still say the growth of the hole could also be the result of natural, albeit unusual, variations in Antarctic weather and other conditions.</p>
        <p>In early September, several weeks before it normally reaches its peak, the hole expanded to a record 17.1 million square miles, an expanse larger than North America, according to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. By comparison, in 1981, according to the atmospheric agency, it covered just 900,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>Since its peak in September, the hole, which changes shape day by day as it is molded by globe-spanning winds, has extended several times over the southern tip of South America, as it has in a few years over the last decade.</p>
        <p>With this year's record following records in 1996 and 1998, some atmospheric scientists are beginning to express surprise at the persistence of the phenomenon, which is caused largely by reactions between ozone and a group of synthetic chemicals that have been banned and whose concentrations are starting to decline in the air.</p>
        <p>''I've been very much expecting to see a turnaround, a leveling off,'' said Dr. Michael H. Proffitt, the senior scientific officer at the World Meteorological Organization in Geneva, which issues a series of bulletins each fall tracking the progress of the ozone hole.</p>
        <p>The hole is closely watched because the stratosphere's diaphanous layer of ozone -- molecules consisting of three oxygen atoms -- absorbs  ultraviolet rays, which could contribute to skin cancers and cataracts and threaten agriculture and ecosystems if they reached the surface.</p>
        <p>The annual ozone hole is the legacy of decades of emissions of a group of synthetic chemicals, mainly chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, that destroy ozone in the presence of sunlight. The chemicals were once popular in aerosol sprays, plastic foams, refrigerants and firefighting equipment, but have nearly all been phased out under voluntary moves by industry and the 1987 Montreal Protocol.</p>
        <p>In the early 1970's, when scientists first reported that CFC's could destroy ozone, some theorized that the effect would be most discernible in the highest reaches of the atmosphere over the tropics, partly because of the abundance of sunlight.</p>
        <p>But in 1985 British scientists found the huge loss of ozone each spring and summer over the South Pole.</p>
        <p>''That was the surprise of the century,'' Dr. Proffitt said.</p>
        <p>Subsequent research determined that the effect is focused mainly high over Antarctica, and to a smaller degree the North Pole, because ozone destruction is most vigorous when extremely frigid temperatures create clouds of ice particles in the stratosphere, generally 9 to 12 miles above the surface, that intensify the chemical reaction.</p>
        <p>The putative link with global warming, Dr. Proffitt and other scientists say, comes because it is thought that a buildup of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping industrial gases, while warming the lower atmosphere, actually acts in the opposite way in the stratosphere, causing it to radiate more heat to space and grow colder than it would otherwise be.</p>
        <p>Another cause of stratospheric cooling is simply the loss of ozone itself. Without ozone, this layer of the atmosphere does not absorb the energy arriving from the sun as ultraviolet radiation, making the thin air even cooler.</p>
        <p>The more cold high air, the more ice clouds, Dr. Proffitt said. More ice clouds mean CFC's and other ozone-destroying chemicals can more efficiently do their work.</p>
        <p>Over the last five years, Dr. Proffitt said, measurements of stratospheric temperatures in October over Antarctica have shown an unusually large area cold enough to form ozone-destroying clouds. In the latest ozone bulletin, issued last week, Dr. Proffitt noted that the average expanse of extremely cold stratospheric air from 1995 to 2000 has been double that seen in any other five-year period.</p>
        <p>Even so, he said, it is too soon to say definitively that a general global warming trend is responsible for this high-altitude cold snap, and the resulting growth in the ozone hole.</p>
        <p>Other atmospheric scientists agree that, for several decades to come, the ozone hole will probably exhibit a lot of variability, and possibly more growth, before the global ban on CFC's and other ozone-destroying chemicals finally reduces concentrations enough to see the layer repair itself at the poles.</p>
        <p>Through this span, unpredictable variations in polar weather will probably have more influence on the condition of the ozone layer than anything else, said Dr. Michael J. Kurylo, the manager of upper atmosphere research for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>''What we get in any one season is going to be driven by meteorological circumstances from year to year,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For residents of Punta Arenas, Chile, and Ushuaia, Argentina, ports that sporadically have been visited by the edge of the ozone hole, there is little to worry about one way or the other, said Dr. Paul A. Newman, an atmospheric physicist at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md.</p>
        <p>In September and October, the peak months for the ozone hole, the sun is too low in the sky to pose much of a sunburn or cancer threat, he said.</p>
        <p>''When the hole passed over Punta Arenas this time, it was 35 degrees that day,'' Dr. Newman said. ''Nobody was really out there getting a suntan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
