<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; All That's Bare Is Fit to Wear, So Why the Stares?</title>
    <meta content="02BADE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bader, Jenny Lyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DE1439F931A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; All That's Bare Is Fit to Wear, So Why the Stares?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY LYN BADER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bader, Jenny Lyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women's clothing is skimpier, with many lingerie and handkerchief items now classifying as 'clothes'; women of all sizes, shapes and ages are wearing tie-backs and halters once seen only on young and slim, partly thanks to better self-image and increased acceptance of different body types; clothing makers profit from skimpy fashions: they can charge more and more for items that are tinier and tinier; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BLAME HBO's ''Sex and the City'' or blame the decline of the ozone layer, but skin is in. American women are showing more of it than ever before.</p>
        <p>Summer itself is hotter. And over the last decade, the proliferation of the Wonderbra coincided with global warming so that just as cleavages became more pronounced, shorts became shorter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BLAME HBO's ''Sex and the City'' or blame the decline of the ozone layer, but skin is in. American women are showing more of it than ever before.</p>
        <p>Summer itself is hotter. And over the last decade, the proliferation of the Wonderbra coincided with global warming so that just as cleavages became more pronounced, shorts became shorter.</p>
        <p>The stock market, always synchronized with hemlines, has reached crazy new heights and so has the slip dress. Some of the skirts, like some of the stocks, have since plunged down again. Other skirts, like other stocks, have reached these new heights without having much to them in the way of visible material: They're so sheer, they're almost transparent.</p>
        <p>With the triumph of minimalism, the handkerchief has returned, not as a decoration in a man's pocket but as an entire piece of women's clothing, featured in handkerchief tops and hanky hemlines. Sleeves, once a staple of the workplace, have become optional. MTV's official anthem for its Spring Break 2000 was the ''Thong Song,'' the R-and-B artist Sisqo's ode to revealing apparel.</p>
        <p>A brief history of skimpy: When things from the lingerie or handkerchief category first became  ''clothes,'' they seemed like mistakes. The model wearing the bra top down the runway looked as if she had been interrupted while getting dressed. The woman arriving at the party in the camisole looked as if she had been awakened from a nap. Backless shoes and shirts appeared incomplete. But now everyone can tell that these things are not mistakes, because it has become O.K. to wear what was formerly considered underwear or handkerchiefs in most situations.</p>
        <p>They're not fashion mistakes, at least. But following fashions can lead to other mistakes. Just as tight corsets put Victorian women into severe physical discomfort, so today's scarf tops and cropped tanks can bring stylish dressers to new levels of personal discomfort. As women have embraced the empowerment and comfort of wearing less, they have also been punished by those who can't see past naked skin. As Erin Brockovich discovered, and as Julia Roberts learned when she played Ms. Brockovich in the recent movie, if women need to work twice as hard as men to prove they're as good, scantily clad women need to work three times as hard.</p>
        <p>FEMALE exposure has been attacked by the puritanical and the macho alike. At the George Washington Middle School in Alexandria, Va., 12-year-old girls wearing shorts of the lengths recommended by Seventeen magazine were accused of violating the school dress code, lined up and subjected to humiliating inspections. Last season, even the trend-setting sitcom character Ally McBeal was held in contempt of court for wearing a micro-mini.</p>
        <p>On the day of the recent Puerto Rican Day parade in New York City's Central Park, women wearing the latest fashions were mauled by young men less interested in the pages of Vogue than in the violent imagery of traditional skin magazines.</p>
        <p>It's a shame that plunging necklines and ascending midriffs have become identified with pornographic fantasies, because they do reflect an improved reality. Women of all sizes, shapes and ages wear the tie-backs and halters once seen only on the young and slim, partly thanks to better self-image and the increased acceptance of different body types. Designers have even made tube tops for the visibly pregnant.</p>
        <p>While it seems generous of designers to want women to feel better about themselves, clothing makers do profit from skimpy fashions: they can charge more and more for items that are tinier and tinier.</p>
        <p>Less is simple, and simplicity especially delights the low-end retailers who copy and mass-produce couture. The popularity of the George label sold in England's Asda chain, which was just purchased by Wal-Mart, demonstrates that consumers like cheap versions of designer fashions so much that they will buy them in the supermarket. The American  discount warehouse Sam's Club now sells clothes. Why go elsewhere? these non-clothing clothing stores seem to be asking. Wouldn't it be nice to wear less, pay less and think about the whole thing less?</p>
        <p>It would be nice, if the judgments and gazes that followed weren't quite so judgmental and gazing. Those who dare to show the flesh and the confidence celebrated by current styles may find themselves in a zone of discomfort. Women who dress provocatively have traditionally been accused of sending a mixed message. But now that provocative is chic, women are the ones receiving the mixed message: Everyone's wearing it, but wear it at your own risk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
