<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artful Echoes, In Parks And Porches; Patterns in Modern Life Reflect Hudson Aesthetic</title>
    <meta content="02HUDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/02/nyregion/02HUDS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <meta content="IN ART'S FOOTSTEPS: What's Left Behind" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1322017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="In Art's Footsteps"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cole, Thomas (1801-1848)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Cole, Thomas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6DC1E30F931A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="2028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artful Echoes, In Parks And Porches; Patterns in Modern Life Reflect Hudson Aesthetic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Patterns in Modern Life Reflect Hudson Aesthetic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>CATSKILL, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses effect of nature on art, as depicted in paintings by Thomas Cole and other artists of Hudson River School; suggests places people might go to see views Cole saw and turned into spectacular paintings; also describes influence of nature on more abstract styles of art; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To get a glimpse of the artistic vision that gripped Thomas Cole when he climbed down into a cavern under a waterfall here 175 years ago, people can go to the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, where his painting of Kaaterskill Falls hangs today.</p>
        <p>Or they can simply take a walk in New York City's Central Park, which was deliberately designed to mimic the art of the Hudson River School that Cole launched from this place. Tiring of that, they might stroll to the nearby art galleries on Madison Avenue that owe their roots to the 19th-century bull market in landscape imagery that made New York the nation's first art capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In parks and on porches, the Hudson River School's romantic embrace of the wilderness continues to have an impact</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To get a glimpse of the artistic vision that gripped Thomas Cole when he climbed down into a cavern under a waterfall here 175 years ago, people can go to the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, where his painting of Kaaterskill Falls hangs today.</p>
        <p>Or they can simply take a walk in New York City's Central Park, which was deliberately designed to mimic the art of the Hudson River School that Cole launched from this place. Tiring of that, they might stroll to the nearby art galleries on Madison Avenue that owe their roots to the 19th-century bull market in landscape imagery that made New York the nation's first art capital.</p>
        <p>Going for a drive instead? The Blue Ridge Parkway in Virginia was built in the 1930's to offer just the kind of landscape perspectives that Cole and his followers turned into formula: foreground, middle ground, distance.</p>
        <p>Feel like just sitting around on the front porch? Even here, scholars say, the old ideas still resonate. Front porches on American homes were first popularized about the time that Hudson River School art was at its peak of popularity before the Civil War -- porches were considered perfect perches for looking at the landscape.</p>
        <p>''The impact went everywhere,'' said Hal K. Rothman, a professor of history at the University of Nevada at Las Vegas, who edits the the journal, Environmental History. ''If kids put posters on their walls in those days, it would have been Hudson River School art.''</p>
        <p>Cole certainly did not invent the idea that a relationship with nature was important. America's debate over wilderness -- what it meant and how people should relate to it -- is at least as old as the first encampments of the Puritans in New England. But the specific vocabulary and mechanics of the relationship between humans and the wild that he and other artists and writers perfected between about 1820 and 1875 is still very much a part of modern life.</p>
        <p>Some elements of the pattern are fuzzy -- as cracked and begrimed with age as any old painting. Landscape architects might know, for example, that walking down Central Park's Promenade to Bethesda Terrace at the rowboat lake was designed to deliver three traditional landscape art perspectives -- formal, pastoral and picturesque -- in sequential order. Most people wouldn't even care.</p>
        <p>Other threads of Cole's tapestry, especially the elements of spirituality in nature, are as vibrant as ever, in issues like  ecology and global warming. Over the last decade, ordinary people and experts in fields ranging from theology to evolutionary biology have found common ground to argue that a deeper human connection to the earth -- a page that seems taken directly from the Hudson River sketchbook -- should be the foundation for protecting it.</p>
        <p>But there was also an element of pure chance in the unfolding of the Hudson River School. New York City, in Cole's time, was mainly a commercial center, just beginning to boom as new transportation routes opened to the Midwest. What happened after Cole is that the ''national vision,'' as the art historian Angela Miller called it, came to be associated -- permanently, as it turned out -- with a city that had mostly before that been about money-grubbing. The news media capital in America was christened with a paintbrush.</p>
        <p>''There was a convergence of different factors -- writers, artists, patrons, wealth, people who collected art -- and then the art itself was marketed by New York institutions,'' said Dr. Miller, an associate professor of art history and American studies at Washington University in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Other cities that might have claimed the art-leadership mantle, specifically Boston and Philadelphia, as each had beautiful regions nearby -- notably New Hampshire's White Mountains north of Boston and the Delaware River Valley outside Philadelphia. But New York had the Hudson Valley, which had already attained an aura of grandeur, and it had Cole and the acolytes who came after him, and that made all the difference. The Catskills, where Cole first made his name, was also only a few hours north by steamboat -- an accessible Outward Bound kind of experience for the rising Victorian-era middle classes.</p>
        <p>The lingering mystery of the artist's eye -- what Cole really saw when he gazed out from the cavern of the Kaaterskill -- remains unsolved. But people still search. Judy A. Abbott, a 55-year-old artist from Lake Hill, N.Y., has hiked to the falls more than two dozen times with her paints and easel over the last year working on a single painting. She said she has perhaps a dozen more trips -- each timed to catch the light falling on the falls just so -- before the piece is done.</p>
        <p>''There's something very compelling,'' she said of the view, which still stops her in her tracks. ''The water seems to come out of the sky. It gives you a feeling of being a very small part of something very magnificent.''</p>
        <p>Mixing Preservation and Profit</p>
        <p>The mostly unspoken assumption behind the rise of American landscape painting was that nature -- supposedly so wild and untamed -- could be framed and composed by artists for consumption and purchase. Wilderness became a commodity, however high-toned the rhetoric about its edifying qualities.</p>
        <p>Some historians say that America never quite recovered from that paradox: the wilds were there to be controlled and manipulated, and the wilder they were, the more valuable. Awe and arrogance, preservation and profit became deeply mixed.</p>
        <p>It was a combination that led to at least a few disastrous mistakes, according to a new book by Stephen J. Pyne, a historian at Arizona State University who has studied the birth of the conservation movement.</p>
        <p>The first head of the United States Forest Service, for example, Gifford Pinchot, whose family had been deeply influenced by the Hudson River School painters, set down the policy under President Theodore Roosevelt that all forest fires were to be fought, no matter what the size, and his rule quickly became conservation dogma. That made giant fires unavoidable, Professor Pyne writes in his book, ''Year of the Fires: The Story of the Great Fires of 1910'' (Viking, 2001), because it short-circuited the natural cycle of small fires that clear out the most flammable underbrush. Only in the 1990's was Mr. Pinchot's policy laid to rest.</p>
        <p>The Hudson River School also imprinted a kind of duality into American thought -- that some vistas were more worthy of protection than others. The places celebrated by the painters -- the Catskills, the Adirondacks, and later, parts of the west like Yosemite Valley in California and the Yellowstone basin in Wyoming -- came to be considered holy. The national parks movement arose specifically to protect these places.</p>
        <p>But the places that weren't as sublime didn't get that kind of protection. The nation became a patchwork of the pristine and the polluted, the sacred and the profane.</p>
        <p>''Walling off areas in the west and later in the east as national parks was driven by the aesthetics of the Hudson River painters,'' said Alan B. Howard, director of American studies programs at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. ''What kinds of places do we want to set apart? By and large they were areas similar to the wilderness of a Cole painting.''</p>
        <p>By the time that work on Central Park was begun in 1858, the notion that nature -- like art -- could be manipulated for human enjoyment or moral improvement had become unquestioned. The rocky swamp designated for the park was torn up and rebuilt from scratch. Every angle and pathway, and even the size of the leaves on the trees -- kept deliberately small in some areas to heighten the illusion of distance -- were composed, said Sara Cedar Miller, a photographer and historian for the Central Park Conservancy, who is writing a book about the park as an artwork.</p>
        <p>''This is an illusion,'' she said on a recent walk through the park's north end. ''It's naturalistic, but it's not nature.''</p>
        <p>Believing Through Ecology</p>
        <p>The Hudson River School's romantic embrace of the wilderness as a tonic for the ailments of civilization came to seem naïve after the Civil War, and through most of the 20th century. The idea that landscape could unite a nation of immigrants -- or that it could reveal the hand of God -- was largely dismissed.</p>
        <p>But over the last few decades, many environmentalists and religious seekers have begun finding their way back to the notion that nature may be, after all, the binding ring of life, just as Cole imagined.</p>
        <p>Deep ecology, which stresses the interrelated nature of life on earth, the Gaia hypothesis, which considers the planet itself to be, in effect, a life form, and multinational efforts like Earth Charter, which pushes nations and corporations to embrace a sense of ethical responsibility to the earth, have all gained ground, environmentalists say.</p>
        <p>Some mainstream religious groups have waded into these waters as well.</p>
        <p>''There's a hunger for the transcendent,'' said E. Calvin Beisner, an associate professor of historical theology and social ethics at Knox Theological Seminary in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., and the author of the book, ''Where Garden Meets Wilderness: Evangelical Entry Into the Environmental Debate'' (Eerdmans Publishing, 1997).</p>
        <p>Professor Beisner said that many churches have given up on the hard doctrinal discussions about the human relationship to God, pushing instead a more practical message about ethical behavior and responsibility.</p>
        <p>That has also led some believers toward spiritual environmentalism because the conflict with traditional religion is no longer as apparent, he said.</p>
        <p>Other experts say that people are simply looking for meaning. Some of the spiritual values of the Hudson River School have returned, they say, because in a deeply cynical age, other things have become even harder for people to accept.</p>
        <p>''More and more, people are skeptical of ultimate value systems where holy is above and beyond the world -- they're increasingly looking for meaning more in their immediate surroundings,'' said Bron Taylor, a professor of religion and environmental studies at the University of Wisconsin at Oshkosh.</p>
        <p>He added, ''Many people have the sense that there's something sacred to their lives here, something sacred to this fecund living planet.''</p>
        <p>What Really Matters</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon in Central Park, Paloma Baez, 6, and her friends Mariah Dueño, also 6, and Mariah's brother Matthew, 4, who all live in Manhattan, were peering down into a stream.</p>
        <p>The stream was artificial. It ran with regular city water and had been stocked with wildlife. The bridge had only been made to look rustic.</p>
        <p>The view extending into the distance had perspectives that Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux -- the park's designers -- had created for aesthetic effect.</p>
        <p>None of that seemed to matter very much.</p>
        <p>''Tadpoles!'' the children shrieked, pointing down into the water.</p>
        <p>In Art's Footsteps</p>
        <p>The paintings of the Hudson River School are portraits of the Northeast, captured at a time when 19th-century America was re-examining its ideas about nature. The landscapes helped spur tourism and environmentalism.</p>
        <p>This is the last of 10 summer articles in which The New York Times returned to the places illuminated by Hudson River School artists.</p>
        <p>The previous articles and additional materials are available on the Web:  www.nytimes.com/nyregion</p>
        <p>In Art's Footsteps</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
