<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AS STOCKS TUMBLE, PRESIDENT SOUNDS A NOTE OF CONCERN</title>
    <meta content="15BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/15/business/15BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nasdaq</org>
        <org class="online_producer">church</org>
        <org class="online_producer">aid</org>
        <org class="online_producer">American University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1D9163DF936A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1266" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AS STOCKS TUMBLE, PRESIDENT SOUNDS A NOTE OF CONCERN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER with RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>EAST BRUNSWICK, N.J., March 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush says he is 'concerned' that many Americans' stock portfolios are being affected by steep sell-off in first two months of his presidency; speaks only minutes after market opens with 300-point plunge in Dow Jones industrial average; he seems intent on conveying at least glancing sense of optimism after months in which Democrats have accused him of talking down the economy as way of building support for his $1.6 trillion tax cut; declines in Dow and in Nasdaq composite index make Bush and his advisers increasingly aware that his political standing is likely to be affected by his economic management skills over next few months; during presidential campaign he insisted that economic boom was product of entrepreneurship rather than policy decisions in Washington; now he argues that 'good public policy' is path to 'second wind for economic growth'; Bush justifies on economic grounds his decision to back off campaign pledge to regulate levels of carbon dioxide emitted by power plants; he suggests that such regulations would add to burden on consumers at time of economic downturn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the stock market tumbling again and fears growing about economic problems at home and abroad, President Bush said today that he was ''concerned that a lot of Americans' portfolios have been affected'' by the steep sell-off in the first two months of his presidency.</p>
        <p>In his comments, first to reporters and then in a speech to several chambers of commerce here, Mr. Bush seemed intent on conveying at least a glancing sense of optimism after months in which Democrats have accused him of talking down the economy as a way of building support for his $1.6 trillion tax cut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the stock market tumbling again and fears growing about economic problems at home and abroad, President Bush said today that he was ''concerned that a lot of Americans' portfolios have been affected'' by the steep sell-off in the first two months of his presidency.</p>
        <p>In his comments, first to reporters and then in a speech to several chambers of commerce here, Mr. Bush seemed intent on conveying at least a glancing sense of optimism after months in which Democrats have accused him of talking down the economy as a way of building support for his $1.6 trillion tax cut.</p>
        <p>''I've got great faith in our economy,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>A senior aide to the president said today that if Mr. Bush's tone had changed, it was ''because he has a direct understanding that what is happening in the markets affects real lives.''</p>
        <p>The president first spoke only minutes after the market opened with a 300-point plunge in the Dow Jones industrial average, as investors reacted to a deteriorating corporate earnings outlook in the United States and growing questions about financial stability in Japan. Although prices fluctuated throughout the day, the Dow lost 317.34 to close at 9,973.46, the first time since October that the bellwether index finished a day below 10,000. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index continued its long decline, dropping 42.69 to close at 1,972.09. It has fallen 20.18 percent this year, and 60.9 percent from its all-time high just over a year ago.</p>
        <p>Those declines have made Mr. Bush and his advisers increasingly aware that the president's political standing is likely to be affected by his economic management skills over the next few months. During the presidential campaign Mr. Bush had insisted that the economic boom was the product of entrepreneurship rather than policy decisions in Washington.</p>
        <p>Today he argued that ''good public policy'' was the path to a ''second wind for economic growth.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Bush justified on economic grounds his decision on Tuesday to back off a campaign pledge to regulate levels of carbon dioxide emitted by power plants. He suggested that such regulations would add to the burden on consumers at a time of economic downturn.</p>
        <p>The president also said that the country faced a long-term ''energy crisis,'' a comment he repeated four times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's comments here came in a trip that took him to a church that provides after-school care for children, part of his effort to promote aid to what he calls faith-based organizations, and then to a lunch of four New Jersey chambers of commerce. As he has for months, he made the case that the best medicine for what ails the economy is his tax cut, and he tried to win over Senator Jon Corzine, a newly elected Democrat, who traveled here with the president. Also along were several members of the House and New Jersey's other Democratic senator, Robert G. Torricelli, who has been more sympathetic to a large tax cut, though he has urged reshaping it to provide more help to low-income and middle-class families.</p>
        <p>''Senator Corzine and I on the plane talked about how we make sure money gets into the economy as quickly as possible,'' Mr. Bush said, again backing moves to speed the tax cuts, an action that would cost considerably more than the money Mr. Bush has allocated in the budget proposal he has sent to Congress.</p>
        <p>In flavoring his blunt talk about the bad news with a morsel of optimism, Mr. Bush was tweaking but not fundamentally altering a strategy he and members of his administration have maintained since before the election was settled late last year.</p>
        <p>They say they are upbeat about the economy's long-term prospects. But they emphasize that the new president inherited a deteriorating situation from his predecessor, and they suggest that to oppose the tax cut is to risk recession.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry people are losing value in their portfolios,'' Mr. Bush said in his speech. ''But with the right policies, I'm confident our economy will recover. The right policies, fiscal policies. And that means giving people money back, in plain language.''</p>
        <p>Reacting to criticism from former members of the Clinton administration that Mr. Bush's comments have fed the market's pessimism, Mr. Bush's aides say he is doing nothing more than being realistic.</p>
        <p>''He is a straight shooter,'' one of the aides traveling with him said today, ''and he can be sympathetic without sugarcoating the reality.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Bush team's forecasting record has been better than that of many Wall Street firms. In early December, when the political battle in Florida was still raging and most economists were sanguine about the economic outlook, Dick Cheney predicted, more or less accurately as it turned out, that the nation might be ''on the front edge of a recession.''</p>
        <p>But in speaking so openly and frequently about economic problems, Mr. Bush has also opened himself to accusations that he is talking down the economy for short-run political gain.</p>
        <p>He has also created some longer term risks for himself. Should his tax cut pass but do little to help the economy rebound -- an outcome that analysts and members of both parties say is possible, if not likely -- it could backfire on the president. What this White House has subtly tried to position as the ''Clinton downturn'' could quickly become the Bush downturn, or the Bush recession, regardless of when it technically began.</p>
        <p>There are other risks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan to add private investment accounts to Social Security seemed like an easier sell when the market was rising. Now, he may well have to defend the idea against critics who will point out how those accounts would have declined in the past year. And in his speech today, Mr. Bush promoted the plan, saying, ''We need to think differently and let younger workers manage some of their own money in the private markets, to make sure there is a Social Security system around tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>However Mr. Bush adjusts his tone these days, experts say his influence on the markets may be marginal.</p>
        <p>''Presidents have very little impact on economic performance,'' said James A. Thurber, the director of the Center for Congressional and Presidential Studies at American University in Washington. ''But to have a president talk down the economy during a historic drop in the market since last March -- and certainly the last couple of days -- is unique. And it may in fact be not wise.''</p>
        <p>Saying that Mr. Bush could not have it both ways, Democrats said they did not understand how he could talk about the economic pitfalls ahead in one breath and then promote his Social Security privatization plan in the next, as he did today.</p>
        <p>''When the market was going from 3,000 to 10,000, people were saying, 'Why not allow us to invest in the stock market?' '' said Representative Robert T. Matsui, Democrat of California. ''Now, with the market dipping, it's a reality check, particularly for the middle class that has invested in the market and is now seeing their portfolios diminish or their returns fall.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
