<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moves on Environment Disappoint Industry</title>
    <meta content="11ENVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/11/science/11ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1277174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Admr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Utah</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Defense Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <org class="online_producer">firm on Arctic</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House Resources Committee</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Conservation Fund</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reagan, Ronald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDC123AF932A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moves on Environment Disappoint Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>While environmentalists sound anxious alarm over Pres Bush's agenda, it it his allies in industry who are expressing concern that his administration is falling short of their expectations; several surprising first moves, particularly on clean air, have put environmental orgns in unexpected role of offering guarded praise for administration they fought hard to defeat; industry representatives, especially oil and mining, who see themselves as early losers, circulate view that Bush's presidency might not be as much of a departure from his predecessor as hoped; photo of Christie Whitman, admr of Environmental Protection Agency, with several of her counterparts at G8 Environmental Summit in Trieste, Italy (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While environmentalists have sounded an anxious alarm over President Bush's agenda, it is his allies in industry who are expressing concern that his administration is falling short of their expectations.</p>
        <p>Several surprising first moves, particularly on clean air, have put environmental organizations in the unexpected role of offering guarded praise for an administration they fought hard to defeat. The industry representatives, who see themselves as early losers, have circulated a view that Mr. Bush's presidency might not be as much of a departure from his predecessor's as hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While environmentalists have sounded an anxious alarm over President Bush's agenda, it is his allies in industry who are expressing concern that his administration is falling short of their expectations.</p>
        <p>Several surprising first moves, particularly on clean air, have put environmental organizations in the unexpected role of offering guarded praise for an administration they fought hard to defeat. The industry representatives, who see themselves as early losers, have circulated a view that Mr. Bush's presidency might not be as much of a departure from his predecessor's as hoped.</p>
        <p>Beginning with word of a decision not to try to overturn President Bill Clinton's declaration of nearly two dozen national monuments, the new administration has gone on to uphold a Clinton-backed plan to rein in diesel emissions and signaled support for a plan to begin regulating carbon dioxide emissions to combat global warming -- steps seen as anathema by oil and mining interests.</p>
        <p>''It may be just too early to tell, but we're not seeing a difference of philosophy from the Clinton days,'' said a leading industry lobbyist who insisted that neither his name nor that of his organization be published. ''If their goal is to keep on sticking it in the eye of business, they've done a good job.''</p>
        <p>Each side said it suspected that the timing and substance of the administration's initial steps might have been motivated by a desire to be seen early on as a friend of the environment. Certainly, the careful way in which the Bush allies have begun to register their discontent -- almost always under the cover of anonymity -- has served to give voice to criticisms while reinforcing the politically useful impression that the White House might not be as bad as the environmentalists made out.</p>
        <p>It is nonetheless striking, each sidesays, that business interests seem to have lost out to environmental ones in most early big decisions, particularly when the administration has been sounding a distinctly conservative note on other issues, like tax cuts and labor.</p>
        <p>''There have been some encouraging signs,'' said Gregory Wetstone, program director of the Natural Resources Defense Council, which fought hard in the unsuccessful effort to block the nomination of Gale A. Norton as interior secretary.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most unexpected overture from the new administration to the environmentalists has come in signs that it may be prepared to embrace a stance on global warming not too far from the one Al Gore championed in the presidential campaign. Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, has said that the administration was sufficiently concerned about the problem that it might regulate emissions of carbon dioxide. That stance was attacked last week in an article on the editorial page of The Wall Street Journal (another target was Treasury Secretary Paul H. O'Neill, who has expressed concern about global warming) and has prompted loud protests from industry representatives.</p>
        <p>''They don't want to do anything that will set the environmentalists off,'' John Grasser, a spokesman for the National Mining Association, said of the administration's tentative embrace of a plan that the energy industry has long said would amount to a new tax on fossil fuels. ''We've got to talk to the Bush administration and let them know that the political wind blows our way, too.''</p>
        <p>The real test, each side says, will be the battle over Mr. Bush's plan to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration. Environmental groups have highlighted the issue in appeals that leaders say have paid dividends in increased membership and fund-raising.</p>
        <p>Business groups expect the Bush administration to stand firm on Arctic drilling, and they are counting on the White House to try to reverse or scale back regulations that in many cases were imposed in the last days of the Clinton presidency.</p>
        <p>Some Bush allies say any complaining is overwrought.</p>
        <p>''I think it's premature to start talking in terms of wins and losses,'' Representative James V. Hansen, the Utah Republican who is chairman of the House Resources Committee, said today. ''I'd tell these people to keep their powder dry. Most of the administrative offices don't even have their staffs put together yet.''</p>
        <p>Among major rulings still being reviewed by the White House six weeks into Mr. Bush's term is one that would permanently ban road building on about 60 million acres of national forest land, a move supported by environmentalists as a barrier to development of about one-third of forest land. Industry groups, including snowmobile dealers and mining conglomerates, and officials in Western states oppose the ban, saying it will unfairly curb their activities.</p>
        <p>Another ruling would drastically lower the limit for arsenic in drinking water, a move opposed by the mining industry, which said it would add significantly to their costs.</p>
        <p>A third, part of a legal settlement approved on Mr. Clinton's last day in office, would require the Environmental Protection Agency to set new standards for pesticide use that would take into account any health risks to children. The agriculture industry and pesticide manufacturers have complained that their views were ignored in the decision.</p>
        <p>On these issues and others, Republicans in Congress have made tentative moves toward overturning the rules, even as they wait for the White House to make its position clear.</p>
        <p>But the first sign of the Bush administration's intentions is more likely to emerge in the courts, as the Justice Department must decide beginning this week whether to defend the Clinton administration's positions against what have become a number of challenges by business groups and states.</p>
        <p>On Mr. Bush's first full day in office, his chief of staff, Andrew H. Card Jr., issued a memorandum imposing a 60-day moratorium on Clinton administration rules that had not yet taken effect, prompting hopes from their foes that Mr. Bush planned to reverse them.</p>
        <p>But so far, the only rules on which the new administration has announced a decision have been limits on diesel emissions and the new national monuments, both of which have strong public support. Some people who have close ties to the new administration said that the White House might have concluded it would be a mistake to pick too many fights. And in the case of the monuments, Ms. Norton, the interior secretary, has broad discretion over how they are administered.</p>
        <p>''I think what we have in the administration is a bunch of thoughtful people trying to make good decisions, and that doesn't mean taking on willy-nilly a bunch of environmental regulations in ways that wouldn't be responsible policy and wouldn't be politically responsible,'' said Doug Crandall, a top Republican aide to the House Resources Committee.</p>
        <p>In its few staff and budget decisions in environmental matters, the new administration seems to have tried to bow to conservatives and business interests. As Ms. Norton's top deputy at the Interior Department, the White House on Thursday said it would nominate J. Steven Griles, an assistant interior secretary under President Ronald Reagan who now works as a lobbyist for the mining industry.</p>
        <p>Among those passed over for the post was John Turner, a director of the federal Fish and Wildlife Service in President Bush's father's administration. As the head of the Conservation Fund, an environmental organization, he has a reputation as a moderate and was reportedly recommended by Vice President Dick Cheney. Administration officials said Mr. Turner lost out in large part because conservative property rights advocates tarred him as being too closely aligned with environmental interests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's new budget calls for cuts of 4 percent or more at the Interior and Agriculture Departments and the Environmental Protection Agency, the main agencies with environmental responsibilities. In his budget address to Congress, Mr. Bush heaped attention on the $4.9 billion he is seeking for the national parks. Critics said that too much of the money, to be spent over five years, would go for road building and tourist buildings, and too little to preservation and research.</p>
        <p>The decision to let stand the limits on diesel emissions might also have been timed to divert attention from the budget cuts. Although it was announced by Mrs. Whitman, the decision had been directed in large part by top aides to Mr. Bush, administration officials said today. They said oil industry warnings that the strict new emissions standards could lead to fuel shortages had been outweighed by the health-based arguments made by the rule's proponents, which included the automobile industry as well as environmental groups, and by evidence of broad popular support for the regulation.</p>
        <p>When she announced the administration's decision to retain the monument designations, Ms. Norton made clear that the new administration would be open to plans that might shrink their boundaries or allow more commercial and recreational use.</p>
        <p>But some in the oil industry in particular still saw the announcement as a bad sign, mostly because Ms. Norton did not voice a specific commitment to keeping the new lands open to energy exploration.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
