<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senator Clinton Settling In as Just One of 100</title>
    <meta content="13HILL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/13/politics/13HILL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Baltimore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Beijing</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Plattsburgh</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">edgar</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Maryland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Baltimore</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Philadelphia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Utica</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Rome</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Watervliet</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">West Nile</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic fund</org>
        <org class="online_producer">attorney general</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cantwell, Maria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ashcroft, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hutchison, Kay Bailey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moynihan, Daniel Patrick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DA1231F930A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senator Clinton Settling In as Just One of 100</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton, who arrived in United States Senate 100 days ago, seeks to be seen as just another freshman lawmaker; she and her advisers promote message that she is not too big for her new job; her daily schedule on Capitol Hill is as mundane as any other junior senator's, and she says she is satisifed with decidedly smaller goals than she had in White House; says she appreciates good commmittee assignment, pasage of amendment here and there, and support from her colleagues, even Republicans, on issues dear to her; she has reached out to colleagues, quietly joining prayer group led by Republican senators and telling fellow Democrats, in closed-door meeting, that she intends to be 'a workhorse, not a show horse'; her attendance record has been perfect so far; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton once wrote a book depicting the world as a global village. Now she issues press releases seeking to rename a courthouse in Manhattan and protect apple farmers.</p>
        <p>She once traveled to places like Beijing to denounce human rights abuses around the world. Now she  finds herself visiting the Holiday Inn on Route 3 in Plattsburgh, N.Y., to talk about job growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton once wrote a book depicting the world as a global village. Now she issues press releases seeking to rename a courthouse in Manhattan and protect apple farmers.</p>
        <p>She once traveled to places like Beijing to denounce human rights abuses around the world. Now she  finds herself visiting the Holiday Inn on Route 3 in Plattsburgh, N.Y., to talk about job growth.</p>
        <p>She once spoke of a right-wing conspiracy in the nation. Now she is forging alliances with some of the fiercest critics of the Clinton White House, like Senators Arlen Specter and Orrin Hatch.</p>
        <p>One hundred days after her splashy arrival in the United States Senate, when her friends and foes alike predicted that she would loom large over Capitol Hill, Mrs. Clinton is doing her best to be seen as just another freshman lawmaker.</p>
        <p>Even as scandal continues to follow her, Mrs. Clinton and her advisers have set out to gradually remake her image to convey a very simple message: the former first lady is not too big for her new job. It is the same message she tried to get out when she was a candidate.</p>
        <p>''I'm a measured kind of person,'' she said playfully. ''I carry around a little measuring cup, a little measuring spoon.''</p>
        <p>These days, the woman who once sought to overhaul the nation's health care system says she is satisfied with decidedly smaller goals: a good committee assignment, passage of an amendment here and there, and support from her colleagues, even Republicans, on issues dear to her.</p>
        <p>Her daily schedule on Capitol Hill is as mundane as any other junior senator's. There are meetings and photo opportunities with constituents, like the members of the Veterans of Foreign Wars of western and southern New York who showed up at her office the other day. There are also news conferences, committee hearings and press releases on matters of national importance (global warming, acid rain and immigration) and local concerns (Governors Island, West Nile virus and renovating the port of entry on Lake Champlain).</p>
        <p>In public gatherings on Capitol Hill, she is now often the last to speak, waiting her turn in deference to ranking members of the Senate.  Mrs. Clinton has reached out to her colleagues in other ways, from quietly joining a prayer group led by Republican senators (she's a churchgoing Methodist) to telling her fellow Democrats, in a closed-door meeting with them, that she intends to be ''a workhorse, not a show horse.''</p>
        <p>Her attendance record has been perfect so far, with Mrs. Clinton voting all 86 times that the Senate has held floor votes. Mrs. Clinton has also introduced 10 bills, most of them part of an economic package intended to help upstate New York.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton stays in Washington during the week at her new home near Embassy Row, where she usually ends her days reading reports, memos and correspondence. Weekends are usually spent in Chappaqua, N.Y., with her husband, former President Bill Clinton. Her advisers say she continues to rely on him for advice on matters from the wording of a minor speech to the interpretation of poll numbers. But Mr. Clinton has visited their home in Washington only a few times, possibly because he is trying to abide by the tradition former presidents have of living outside the capital. For the most part, the two lead separate lives, people who know them say.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's new Senate Web site is telling, as well. It features photos of her giving her first floor speech, meeting with constituents in her office in the Senate Dirksen Building and reciting Edgar Allan Poe's ''The Raven'' in a Capitol Hill pressroom after losing a Super Bowl bet to her colleagues from Maryland who wagered on the Baltimore Ravens.</p>
        <p>For all that, Mrs. Clinton can't easily escape her fame. The other day, as she walked out of the Senate chamber, a group of high school girls from Philadelphia spotted her and yelped with delight. ''There's Hillary Clinton,'' shouted one girl. ''Give me the camera!''</p>
        <p>Her celebrity profile is still considered a big draw at Democratic fund-raising events, despite the investigations into her involvement in the pardons granted by her husband. Mrs. Clinton agreed to play host at a fundraiser in her Washington home later this month on behalf of another Democratic freshman senator, Maria Cantwell of Washington State.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's debut on Capitol Hill was unusually bumpy. Her attempts to get down to work were overshadowed by the disclosures over her last days in the White House: the furniture and other gifts that were later returned; her brothers' involvement in getting presidential pardons for their clients; and so on.</p>
        <p>But none of it -- not even chatter about her possible presidential ambitions for 2004 or beyond -- has deterred her from reminding people what she is doing in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Recently, for example, she sent an e-mail press release to dozens of reporters boasting that she had pushed through a relatively minor measure that would have been overlooked: money to help communities upgrade their water treatment systems. She made sure to share credit with Republicans, the sort of gesture that goes a long way in the clubby world of the Senate.</p>
        <p>More striking was when Mrs. Clinton agreed to team up with Mr. Specter, a Republican from Pennsylvania, on a bill he introduced that seeks to tighten the rules on presidential pardons. Mr. Specter, who this winter raised the possibility of trying to impeach Mr. Clinton again, this time out of office, said the bill was a response to the controversial pardons. But Mrs. Clinton made no mention of that when she offered her support, saying only that it was ''sensible bipartisan'' legislation.</p>
        <p>Even her occasional jabs at Republicans are couched in cautious terms, confounding some of her most ardent supporters. Many of them had hoped that she would be more outspoken, particularly about President Bush's pick for attorney general, John Ashcroft, a man with a conservative record on abortion rights and school desegregation. Mrs. Clinton did not criticize the Ashcroft nomination for weeks, until it was about to go to the floor of the Senate. Then she did so in a news conference in New York, not Washington, so as not to draw national attention to herself and still address the concerns of liberal groups in her state, her advisers say.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, Mrs. Clinton has pleasantly surprised many people who were initially wary, most notably Republicans in the Senate, whose support she needs if she hopes to get anything done legislatively.</p>
        <p>''She has handled herself well, being collegial and getting to know the system,'' said Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison, a Texas Republican. Mrs. Hutchison added that her colleague ''is doing what a new thoughtful senator should do, and that is learning the ropes before you jump out.''</p>
        <p>With Congress in recess this week, Mrs. Clinton returned to New York, where she has been traveling the state and criticizing the budget President Bush released on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Her aides say that as much as anything, Mrs. Clinton wants to be known as a lawmaker who delivers for her fellow New Yorkers. She has, in fact, made several swings across the state since being sworn into office, hitting just about every available media market to drive home that message. And when she is back on Capitol Hill, she threads her speeches with homespun references to average folks she has met in places like Utica and Rome.</p>
        <p>Much of her legislative record has been tailored with an eye toward her constituents, too. Her first major bill, for example, seeks to revive the economy of upstate New York. And the other bills that she has helped introduce include one that would secure more defense contracts for the Army's Watervliet Arsenal near Albany, and another that would require the federal government to turn Governors Island over to New York.</p>
        <p>But it would be a mistake to think that she has abandoned the bigger picture. Asked about the failed health care initiative she pushed in 1993, Mrs. Clinton said her goal was valid; the problem, she said, was the way she went about trying to achieve it. Nor has Mrs. Clinton shied away from using her new elected power to advance an agenda that reflects her deeply held positions on child care,  education and health care. She has also shown a willingness to use blistering oratory to defend those goals.</p>
        <p>Recently discussing the dangers she believes President Bush's tax cuts pose to social programs, Mrs. Clinton posed this question to her audience: ''Will we meet the challenges of our time or will we squander this moment on a budget that puts politics first and people last?''</p>
        <p>It is still too early to say what kind of senator Mrs. Clinton will be once she establishes herself. Will she have enough stature to shape her party's national agenda, in the tradition of Edward M. Kennedy and Daniel Patrick Moynihan? Or will the kind of troubles she has run into over the last few months prevent her from leaving a legacy?</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton knows that there is plenty of time for such questions to be resolved. ''My life has been kind of an unfolding drama, to me as well as everybody else,'' she said while standing outside the Senate chamber. Then, she concluded, ''I have six years, and I am somebody who does take the long view.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
