<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuel Economy for New Cars Is at Lowest Level Since '80</title>
    <meta content="Y18FUE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/18/politics/18FUEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE ENERGY PLAN: THE STANDARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit (Michigan)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">transportation department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Light</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DaimlerChrysler AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">BMW</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sierra Club</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0D6113AF93BA25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuel Economy for New Cars Is at Lowest Level Since '80</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transportation Department report finds overall fuel economy of new cars and light trucks sold in United States, after improving slightly a year ago, has dropped back to lowest levels since 1980; estimates average of 24.5 miles per gallon in 2001 model year; chart of fuel economy since 1980 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The overall fuel economy of new cars and trucks sold in America, after improving slightly a year ago, has dropped back to the lowest levels since 1980, a new government report indicates.</p>
        <p>President Bush's energy plan called today for improving fuel efficiency, so the report, from the Transportation Department, served to underscore that the auto industry is moving in the opposite direction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The overall fuel economy of new cars and trucks sold in America, after improving slightly a year ago, has dropped back to the lowest levels since 1980, a new government report indicates.</p>
        <p>President Bush's energy plan called today for improving fuel efficiency, so the report, from the Transportation Department, served to underscore that the auto industry is moving in the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>The report estimates that the average fuel economy of all cars and light trucks sold in the 2001 model year will be 24.5 miles a gallon, the same as in 1999 and slightly below the 24.7 miles a gallon in the 2000 model year. The peak was 26.2 miles a gallon in 1987, before automakers began selling large numbers of gas-guzzling sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>And those numbers exaggerate fuel economy, because automakers get extra credit for manufacturing vehicles that can run on either gasoline or nearly pure ethanol, even though few of those vehicles are thought to be fueled with ethanol by drivers.</p>
        <p>Ford Motor and General Motors have increased their output of the so-called duel-fuel vehicles since 1999, though fewer than one service station in 1,000 sells the ethanol fuel.</p>
        <p>Excluding the ethanol credit, the average gas mileage is now lower than in 1999 and at its lowest level since 1980.</p>
        <p>Federal regulations require each automaker to produce cars with an average fuel economy of 27.5 miles a gallon. Light trucks -- a category that includes sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans -- must achieve an average of 20.7 miles a gallon. The lower standard for light trucks dates to the 1970's, when it mainly applied to pickups used by farmers and merchants.</p>
        <p>According to the Transportation Department report, light trucks from G.M. and DaimlerChrysler were unable to meet even the more lenient standard. The average fuel economy of G.M.'s 2001 light trucks is 20.6 miles a gallon; DaimlerChrysler's average is 20.5 miles agallon.</p>
        <p>Both companies planned to use credits from exceeding the standards in past years to avoid paying millions of dollars in fines for falling short in 2001.</p>
        <p>Ford matched the government standard for light trucks, with an overall fuel economy of 20.7 miles a gallon. Most foreign automakers met the regulatory standards by comfortable margins. A few fairly low-volume foreign automakers, like BMW and Ferrari, missed the standards, as they do consistently, and will pay fines as part of the cost of doing business in the United States.</p>
        <p>All the automakers' fuel economy figures are calculated using a special methodology that the government allows for regulatory purposes. This methodology produces results that are 18 percent higher than the gas mileage estimates posted on the window stickers of new automobiles. Many drivers complain that they have trouble matching even the window-sticker estimates.</p>
        <p>G.M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler are producing close to a million dual-fuel minivans, pickup trucks and cars this year, at an extra cost of up to $200 a vehicle for the fuel sensors and stainless-steel fuel lines needed for ethanol.</p>
        <p>The government counts these vehicles as getting roughly triple the fuel economy that they achieve when burning gasoline. The automakers have used the extra mileage credits to sell more full-size sport utilities and pickups while meeting the federal standards for average fuel economy.</p>
        <p>David Barthmuss, a General Motors spokesman, said the automaker wanted oil companies to sell more ethanol at service stations. Oil companies have resisted doing so, contending that ethanol can cause problems in their pipelines and is expensive to distribute by tanker truck.</p>
        <p>Ford pledged last July to improve the average gas mileage of its sport utilities by 25 percent by 2005, without relying on extra ethanol credits. G.M. responded a week later by vowing to exceed Ford in the average fuel economy of sport utilities and of light trucks over all, also without ethanol credits. DaimlerChrysler said last month that it would keep pace with its main rivals in overall light truck fuel economy, but it had not taken a position on the use of ethanol credits to do so.</p>
        <p>In the energy report he released today, President Bush called for improving fuel efficiency through the pursuit of new technologies and subsidies for the sale of hybrid vehicles that use a combination of gasoline and electric propulsion.</p>
        <p>The report acknowledged that few dual-fuel vehicles were actually using ethanol, a type of alcohol produced from corn. The report praised the production of these vehicles, and said without elaboration that further study on ways to increase the actual use of ethanol was needed.</p>
        <p>''Reforms to the federal alternative fuels program could promote alternative fuels use instead of mandating purchase of vehicles that ultimately run on petroleum fuels,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The administration report said the president would review fuel-economy standards in light of a report by the National Academy of Sciences that is due on July 1. Environmentalists have dismissed that report as unlikely to recommend significantly stiffer standards, because its authors include several people who have worked for the auto and oil industries but no environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Told of the contents of today's Transportation Department report, Dan Becker, the energy and global warming director of the Sierra Club, said, ''It's bad news for the environment that fuel economy has dropped, and it's now up to the president to raise fuel-economy standards that have languished for 12 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker also expressed skepticism whether subsidies for hybrid vehicles would do any good, pointing out that automakers could just use hybrid sales to offset the sale of other gas-guzzlers while still meeting federal standards.</p>
        <p>The auto industry has been lobbying heavily in recent months for an extension of the ethanol credits, which are currently scheduled to expire in 2004. The legislation that authorized the credits a decade ago, which was strongly backed by farm-state lawmakers, called for the Transportation Department to send a report to Congress on the program by September 2000. The Clinton administration did not finish work on the report before leaving office, however, and the Bush administration has not yet named a new administrator for the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, the Transportation Department agency that must produce the report.</p>
        <p>A department official who insisted on anonymity said the report would not be completed until after an administrator had been chosen and confirmed by the Senate.</p>
        <p>THE ENERGY PLAN: THE STANDARDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
