<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Green Revolution: It's Also the Color of Money</title>
    <meta content="18OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/18/sports/othersports/18OUTD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1344120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Business for Wilderness</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Outdoor Industry Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bodo, Pete</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DC133BF93BA25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Green Revolution: It's Also the Color of Money</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Green Revolution: It's Also the Color of Money</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pete Bodo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bodo, Pete</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pete Bodo Outdoors column discusses economic benefits of protecting wilderness areas and promoting environmentalism; cites examples from study conducted by Business for Wilderness, program of Outdoor Industry Assn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Advocates for roadless wilderness and similar conservation issues have traditionally emphasized the ethical imperatives and aesthetic rewards of promoting environmentalism. But, perhaps noticing that money is green, too, a growing, hardnosed component in the environmental community, often led by constituents in the outdoor industry, is hammering out a different kind of message: that there are great practical, economic benefits to protecting the environment, and in promoting outdoor recreation.</p>
        <p>In a study that will be released next week, ''The Bottom Line: Protecting the Value of America's Public Lands,'' Business for Wilderness, a program of the Outdoor Industry Association, quantifies the economic impact visitors have on a wide range of communities near recreation areas. These are not all A-list areas, like Montana's Glacier National Park or Florida's Everglades, either. Yet many of them generate significant, steady revenue, often for distressed rural communities. The report also identifies the prime threats posed to such areas by proposed activities such as mining, development and acid rain pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing, hardnosed component in the environmental community is hammering out a new message: There are practical economic benefits to protecting the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Advocates for roadless wilderness and similar conservation issues have traditionally emphasized the ethical imperatives and aesthetic rewards of promoting environmentalism. But, perhaps noticing that money is green, too, a growing, hardnosed component in the environmental community, often led by constituents in the outdoor industry, is hammering out a different kind of message: that there are great practical, economic benefits to protecting the environment, and in promoting outdoor recreation.</p>
        <p>In a study that will be released next week, ''The Bottom Line: Protecting the Value of America's Public Lands,'' Business for Wilderness, a program of the Outdoor Industry Association, quantifies the economic impact visitors have on a wide range of communities near recreation areas. These are not all A-list areas, like Montana's Glacier National Park or Florida's Everglades, either. Yet many of them generate significant, steady revenue, often for distressed rural communities. The report also identifies the prime threats posed to such areas by proposed activities such as mining, development and acid rain pollution.</p>
        <p>The Business for Wilderness program ultimately seeks to increase the recreation industry's profile and its involvement in decisions about United States public land. Its goals include protecting wilderness (and roadless) areas, expanding the number of national recreation destinations and protecting public access.</p>
        <p>''We want to get the public to understand the economic benefits as well as the simple joys of getting out, perhaps with the family, to enjoy the outdoors,'' said Tom Adams, executive director of Business for Wilderness. ''In doing that, we'd also like to lay to rest the damaging myth that the only thing environmentalists contribute to society is lawsuits. If we can connect and coordinate our efforts with like-minded companies out there, we'll be that much more effective in getting that message out.''</p>
        <p>In the past, conservation groups have made similar attempts to demonstrate the dollars-and-cents value of activities and places whose primary values are anything but material (in a 1995 study, Trout Unlimited estimated that the Beaverkill watershed generated $10.1 million for the local economy). And individual companies, including industry giants like Orvis, Patagonia and REI, have made significant contributions to conservation causes (for example, Orvis's corporate mission statement includes a specific, economic and ethical mandate to support conservation projects and organizations).</p>
        <p>Along similar lines, Business for Wilderness hopes to consolidate various resources of the self-interested parties in ''human-powered'' recreation, an industry that includes activities as diverse as kayaking and rock climbing but not fishing and hunting. Still, even excluding those vastly popular pursuits, the industry generated more than $18 billion in revenues in 2000 -- $213 million from the sale of hiking boots alone.</p>
        <p>It is easy to understand that whitewater enthusiasts on Idaho's famed Salmon River helped to earn $120 million and contributed heavily to the creation of 5,980 jobs in rural Blaine County, Ore. But it's also true that whitewater recreation and tourism around -- among other places -- the Ocoee and Chattooga Rivers generated $51.62 million annually for rural Polk County, Tenn., and Swain County, N.C.</p>
        <p>And in Southern California's Arc of Wilderness, an area easily accessible to the dense population nearby, the Cleveland, San Bernardino and Angeles National Forests annually attract 32 million visitors; the average visitor spends $52.15. All told, visitors spend more than $1.6 billion annually within 50 miles of the park.</p>
        <p>Currently, the Salmon is threatened by mining, the Ocoee and Chattooga are threatened by restrictions on river access, poor water quality and the loss of old growth forest, and the Arc of Wilderness is subject to pollution, rapid urbanization and user conflicts.</p>
        <p>The 150 constituents of Business for Wilderness range from small boutique companies like Black Diamond, which manufactures high-quality climbing gear, to large businesses like the backpack maker Jansport. Tom Adams estimates that the human-powered recreation industry consists of some 4,000 businesses, and the program's target is to get 1,500 on board by the end of 2002. Unlike the Conservation Alliance, an Outdoor Industry Association program that has contributed more than $3 million to grass roots environmental groups since its inception in 1989, members of Business for Wilderness will not be required to make financial commitments to the organization.</p>
        <p>''We mostly want the time, interest and energy of people,'' Adams said, ''so they can advise and help us expand the environmental ethic in the industry, and help us publicize the economics of recreation.''</p>
        <p>Adams said one of the more beneficial aspects of the recreation industry is that it adds components of diversity and slow but reliable and sometimes recession-proof growth to local economies. ''Newspapers have noted how people have been flocking to national parks and other outdoor areas in the wake of the terrorist attacks,'' Adams said. ''So I think we're also providing or taking part in a service that helps people get through tough times. It's hard to publicize this, but the outdoors are always there, through good times and bad. And a lot of us go there to seek silent reflection and spiritual renewal, especially in troubled times.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, the bottom line is -- but is not always -- about money.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
