<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing the Rain Forest Into a Boardwalk Battle</title>
    <meta content="21BOAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DOWN THE SHORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boardwalks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Asbury Park (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amazon River Basin</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Circle-a Construction Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sucato, Kirsty</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E0DD173CF932A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing the Rain Forest Into a Boardwalk Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRSTY SUCATO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sucato, Kirsty</byline>
      <dateline>ASBURY PARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental groups succeed in temporarily halting contract awarded to Circle-A Construction Co to rebuild section of boardwalk in Asbury Park, NJ, using lumber of ipe tree from Brazilian rain forest that is not certified as meeting forestry industry practices; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The boardwalk here  its southern yellow pine and Douglas fir warped and splintered  -- as much as anything else reflects the dilapidated condition of much of this city.</p>
        <p>But so far, a plan to fix up the walkway, four-tenths of a mile long and a generous 60 feet wide, that is intended to draw redevelopment along the oceanfront has drawn only an outcry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The boardwalk here  its southern yellow pine and Douglas fir warped and splintered  -- as much as anything else reflects the dilapidated condition of much of this city.</p>
        <p>But so far, a plan to fix up the walkway, four-tenths of a mile long and a generous 60 feet wide, that is intended to draw redevelopment along the oceanfront has drawn only an outcry.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups have halted, at least temporarily, a plan by Asbury Park to rebuild a section of the boardwalk using  lumber from the Brazilian rain forest that has not been certified as meeting forestry industry practices.</p>
        <p>The city had accepted a $686,000 bid on Jan. 3 from Circle-A Construction Company  of Neptune to replace about 700 feet of the boardwalk using the lumber of the ipe (pronounced ee-PAY) tree the tropical hardwood also used on boardwalks in Coney Island, Atlantic City and Avon-by-the-Sea.</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, after the threat of legal action from Rainforest Relief and the New Jersey Chapter of the Sierra Club, city council members agreed to postpone the project for ''two or three weeks'' to investigate other options with help from the State Department of Environmental Protection.</p>
        <p>The state Green Acres Program, which is financing the work through $1 million in grants and loans, will review the choice of materials, said Terance D. Weldon, the acting city manager.</p>
        <p>''This governing body wants to explore all possibilities, all alternatives, and if the D.E.P. with their review can make a recommendation to us that would be suitable for the needs in Asbury Park then we certainly  are going to listen and explore,'' Mr. Weldon said.</p>
        <p>The project, part of the city's attempt to spur redevelopment of the blighted waterfront, is the first phase of a planned $3.6 million replacement of the entire boardwalk, a once-impressive resort attraction that is more than 20 years old in some sections, said the city's assistant engineer, Donald J. Norbut.</p>
        <p>Asbury Park officials chose ipe because it is durable, he said. At $11.20 per square foot installed, it costs more than the traditional boardwalk material, southern yellow pine, at $8, but it lasts longer: from 25 to 40 years, against 10 to 15 years for the pine.</p>
        <p>City officials opted for uncertified ipe because certified wood is more expensive and harder to obtain, he said. They also rejected several other materials, including a recycled plastic material called TriMax, which is guaranteed for 50 years and is considerably more expensive than wood.</p>
        <p>But conservationists argued that the city was striking a fool's bargain by using tropical wood.</p>
        <p>''It is a process that ultimately leads to costs that we can't even guess at,'' said Timothy D. Keating, the executive director of Rainforest Relief, a New-York based conservation group that has opposed the project along with the Sierra Club and the Monmouth County Friends of Clearwater.  ''One of these is that Asbury Park will in the future spend massive amounts of money because of global warming. I can't imagine  anything more myopic than building a boardwalk of rain forest hardwoods.''</p>
        <p>The group successfully protested the use of ipe for boardwalks in Wildwood, Ocean City and Long Beach, N.Y. It threatened to sue Asbury Park under a 1993 state executive order that requires government agencies to use recycled material wherever possible as long as the cost does not exceed 10 percent of virgin material.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists strongly favor a boardwalk made from recycled plastic but would settle for hardwood that is certified, Mr. Keating said.</p>
        <p>Ipe trees, usually harvested when they are 150 to 200 years old, do not grow together in stands, and so cutting them can cause extensive damage to the rain forest, he said.</p>
        <p>Brigid M. Shea, the manager of government and environmental affairs for the International Wood Products Association, a trade organization for wood importers, said the certification issue was not clear-cut.</p>
        <p>''A lack of certification doesn't necessarily mean that there isn't good forestry practices in place in these developing countries,'' she said. ''We think that if people are really interested in saving the rain forest, they should buy tropical wood, because if the forests are going to be managed, there has to be value there.''</p>
        <p>DOWN THE SHORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
