<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Faces New Dispute Over Payment Of U.N. Dues</title>
    <meta content="Y17NAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/17/international/17NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1317814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D6153EF934A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Faces New Dispute Over Payment Of U.N. Dues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Faces New Dispute Over Payment of U.N. Dues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration officials and House Republican leaders work to resolve new dispute over United States' payment of millions of dollars in back dues to United Nations, one month before Bush's planned first visit; dispute centers on legislation that seeks to exempt Americans from jurisdiction of International Criminal Court; Bush is said to oppose measure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With President Bush's first visit to the United Nations just one month away, administration officials and House Republican leaders are working to resolve a new dispute over the United States' payment of millions of dollars in back dues to the organization.</p>
        <p>The dispute, first reported by The Washington Post, is no longer over whether the United States should pay money it owes the United Nations; that was worked out by the House and Senate earlier this year, after years of contentious debate. Instead, it centers on legislation that seeks to exempt Americans from the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court, the first permanent tribunal now being created at The Hague to prosecute war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republican leaders are working to resolve a new dispute over the United States' payment of millions of dollars in back dues to the United Nations</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With President Bush's first visit to the United Nations just one month away, administration officials and House Republican leaders are working to resolve a new dispute over the United States' payment of millions of dollars in back dues to the organization.</p>
        <p>The dispute, first reported by The Washington Post, is no longer over whether the United States should pay money it owes the United Nations; that was worked out by the House and Senate earlier this year, after years of contentious debate. Instead, it centers on legislation that seeks to exempt Americans from the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court, the first permanent tribunal now being created at The Hague to prosecute war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity.</p>
        <p>The exemption passed the House in May with broad bipartisan support as an amendment to a bill to operate State Department programs, which included repayment of $826 million in back dues to the United Nations. At the time, many lawmakers expressed suspicion of a permanent tribunal, fearing its power could be easily misused to make capricious arrests of American officials or military personnel abroad.  Just before this, the United States  had been voted off the United National Human Rights Commission, a move that infuriated House members.</p>
        <p>The White House has stressed the need to resolve the thorny issue of back dues before Mr. Bush goes to the United Nations in late September. Mr. Bush has already angered several allies with his plan to create a national missile defense system and his stance on global warming, and is not eager to exacerbate tensions with other United Nations members.</p>
        <p>''The administration does not support the attachment of any additional conditions to the payment of these arrears,'' Philip Reeker, a State Department spokesman, said today.</p>
        <p>Republican leaders are working on a compromise to help release the money, House Republican leadership aides said today.</p>
        <p>''No one wants to embarrass the president,'' said one aide. ''We are just looking at all options and working with the administration.''</p>
        <p>Another aide added, ''There is no question this will be resolved before the president goes to the United Nations.''</p>
        <p>While the Bush administration opposes the creation of a permanent court at The Hague, it is reluctant to relinquish control over foreign policy matters to Congress, an administration official said.</p>
        <p>Still, the official added, ''we understand that the servicemen and women need some protection.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the Senate passed a stand-alone bill, called Helms-Biden, that frees up $582 million in back dues, with no conditions regarding the tribunal. This sum, unlike the House figure, excludes peacekeeping costs. Now the House and the Senate must reconcile their differences.</p>
        <p>In doing this, however, Republican leaders face their own quandary, aides say. If they ignore the House vote for the amendment, which was written by Representative Tom DeLay, the powerful majority whip from Texas, they risk losing support from conservatives for the entire bill, including for the repayment of dues.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay's provision would cut off military aid to any non-NATO countries that ratify the International Criminal Court treaty. In addition, it would bar American soldiers from participating in United Nations peacekeeping efforts unless the soldiers first received immunity from the court's jurisdiction.</p>
        <p>The United States has long supported individual tribunals, like the ones created to deal with crimes in Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia, but the idea of a permanent court is problematic to many House members.</p>
        <p>''The problem with the International Criminal Court is that it is so subject to being hijacked,'' said one Republican leadership aide. ''It is a court without a mandate, without a specific mission. It's like an independent counsel for the world.''</p>
        <p>President Bill Clinton signed the treaty to create the court on Dec. 31, even while acknowledging that he found aspects of it problematic. The Bush administration has said it will not submit the treaty to the Senate for ratification.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
