<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Quick, Henry, the emollient!</title>
    <meta content="WLN100929" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/01/magazine/01ONLANGUAGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DA1130F932A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: On Language; Quick, Henry, the emollient!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Language: Quick, Henry, the Emollient!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column on word 'unilateralist' to characterize Bush administration's foreign policy and the use of nomenclature to put the best light on policy positions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'I hope the notion of a unilateral approach died in some people's minds here today,'' President George W. Bush told a NATO news conference in Brussels, bridling at having been saddled with the dirty diplomatic word. ''Unilateralists don't come around the table to listen to others. . . . Unilateralists don't ask opinions of world leaders.'' In case anybody didn't get his point, he gave a definition: ''A unilateralist is one that doesn't understand the role of NATO.'' Were it not for the ghost of the Nixonian ''I am not a crook,'' he would surely have added, ''I am not a unilateralist.''</p>
        <p>Why the revulsion at this word? Because the adjective means ''undertaken by one,'' which is diplomatically quite incorrect, or ''one-sided,'' which carries an overtone of arrogance. Born in botany to describe a cluster of flowers growing on one side of a stalk, it bloomed in diplolingo a half century ago: ''Unilateralism, to coin one more gobbledygook term,'' wrote Arthur Schlesinger Jr. in 1951 in its disparagement, ''has become the new isolationism. Go it alone; meet force with maximum force; there is no substitute for victory . . . these are the tenets of the new faith.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'I hope the notion of a unilateral approach died in some people's minds here today,'' President George W. Bush told a NATO news conference in Brussels, bridling at having been saddled with the dirty diplomatic word. ''Unilateralists don't come around the table to listen to others. . . . Unilateralists don't ask opinions of world leaders.'' In case anybody didn't get his point, he gave a definition: ''A unilateralist is one that doesn't understand the role of NATO.'' Were it not for the ghost of the Nixonian ''I am not a crook,'' he would surely have added, ''I am not a unilateralist.''</p>
        <p>Why the revulsion at this word? Because the adjective means ''undertaken by one,'' which is diplomatically quite incorrect, or ''one-sided,'' which carries an overtone of arrogance. Born in botany to describe a cluster of flowers growing on one side of a stalk, it bloomed in diplolingo a half century ago: ''Unilateralism, to coin one more gobbledygook term,'' wrote Arthur Schlesinger Jr. in 1951 in its disparagement, ''has become the new isolationism. Go it alone; meet force with maximum force; there is no substitute for victory . . . these are the tenets of the new faith.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, Senator Joseph Biden, now the Democratic chairman of foreign relations, tagged the G.O.P. ticket as ''unilateralists if not isolationists.'' That was the theme that France's prime minister, Lionel Jospin, picked up this spring: ''This is not an isolationist administration as has been the case before in the Republican tradition,'' he noted. ''This is more like a unilateralist administration.''</p>
        <p>Uni means ''one''; multi means ''many.'' A few years ago, Republicans were criticizing the Clinton administration for being too multilateral, following the lead of the U.N. and other groups of nations. Just as the uni prefix implies arrogance, multi implies meekness, requiring Clinton's secretary of state, Madeleine Albright, to come up with a toughening modifier: ''assertive multilateralism.''</p>
        <p>Rather than reaching for a softening qualifier (''acquiescent unilateralism'' leaps to mind) and despite an opening offered by the European trade commissioner, Pascal Lamy (''One man's unilateralism is another's determined leadership''), the Bush team decided to deny it flatly. Its preferred self-description is neither isolationist nor interventionist, but ''internationalist.''</p>
        <p>As the smoothing-over was decided on, one word muscled its way into vogue: emollient. In The New York Times in December, R.W. Apple Jr. and Steven Erlanger separately wrote of ''emollient words'' used by Bush to soften hard lines. Last month, British analysts became entranced with the word: ''At his first major meeting with skeptical European leaders,'' wrote Anton La Guardia in The Daily Telegraph, ''Mr. Bush struck an emollient note.'' My colleague in columny, Anthony Lewis, who I suspect reads the British press, noted that ''the emollient Bush words about loving the environment did not match the reality of the administration's destructive actions.''</p>
        <p>Get to know this soothing locution, both noun and adjective, which is not nearly as stinging as ''astringent'' and is the opposite of ''abrasive.'' The Latin molli is ''soft''; Alexander Pope wrote in 1727 of poetry's ''emollients and opiates.'' Pour it over your unilateralism, rub it in and cozy the world along.</p>
        <p>NOMENCLATURE WARS</p>
        <p>When did the inheritance tax (a pro-taxing term) become the estate tax (a neutral term)? And who changed it to the death tax, which has a built-in anti-tax message?</p>
        <p>In the same way, who abolished most favored nation? M.F.N., as it used to be initialized, was a trade status equal to that of the most favored nation -- which was denied to certain countries, often for human rights reasons. But the phrase made it seem as if China, for example, would become the most favored nation -- and most people did not favor that. So the name was changed to nondiscriminatory trade practices -- and who was in favor of discrimination? The name was changed further to normal trade relations, leaving opponents to espouse abnormal relations, a loser. The name changes helped change the policy.</p>
        <p>The classic example was pro-life, adopted by those who were anti-abortion. This not only put the case in positive terms (which anti-abortion did not) but also suggested that the opposition was pro-death. In their defense, people who opposed restrictions on abortion adopted the term pro-choice. Thus a right to abort was presented in the more favorable light of a right to choose.</p>
        <p>In the war of words in the Middle East, the Palestinians won. Israel referred to the land gained after it repelled invasions as Judea and Samaria, the ancient names of the land. The Arab world preferred the West Bank, situated on the west bank of the Jordan river in what had been Trans-Jordan. For a time, the Israelis fell back to the administered territories and later to the disputed territories, but almost all the media adopted West Bank as distinct from Israel proper, and any traditionalist reference to Judea and Samaria is now considered quaint or slanted.</p>
        <p>Remember when global warming was a hotly disputed phrase? At the sudden order of the Great Namechanger, global warming was iced and global climate change took its place. No explanation; no argument; the order came down, and everybody on both sides of that argument marched off in lock step.</p>
        <p>''The latest semantic fashion in Congress,'' reports The Hill, Martin Tolchin's lively Washington weekly, ''is renaming fast track trade authority as trade promotion authority, or T.P.A.'' Fast track apparently reminds too many Republicans of the Clinton era.</p>
        <p>Representative David Dreier, a California Republican, requires his staff to put a dollar in a jar every time one of them uses the taboo term fast track. It's the same jar he used to coerce his minions into using normal trade relations when they blurted out most favored nation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
