<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Eco-Terrorism,' And Nary a Redwood In Sight; Is Suburban Sprawl Debate So Fevered That It Encourages the Torching of Homes?</title>
    <meta content="14VAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010211T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1262616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East End (Li)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Earth Liberation Front</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3D7113AF937A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Eco-Terrorism,' And Nary a Redwood In Sight; Is Suburban Sprawl Debate So Fevered That It Encourages the Torching of Homes?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT SINAI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 'urban terrorist exploits' against developers on Long Island's East End; Earth Liberation Front has taken responsibility for actions; officials from local and national environmental groups are puzzled over why group would target Long Island, not known as hotbed for environmental issues, and agree that any criminal activity aimed at halting suburban sprawl, including firebombing, should not be tolerated; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN an underground environmental group sought credit for ruining a Cold Spring Harbor cornfield last summer, it left behind a graffiti message denouncing genetic engineering. But the crops, it turned out, were never genetically altered.</p>
        <p>When the elusive group, the Earth Liberation Front, announced on New Year's Eve that it had firebombed some luxury houses under construction on old farmland in Mount Sinai, it used more graffiti messages: ''Stop Urban Sprawl'' and ''If You Build It We Will Burn It.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN an underground environmental group sought credit for ruining a Cold Spring Harbor cornfield last summer, it left behind a graffiti message denouncing genetic engineering. But the crops, it turned out, were never genetically altered.</p>
        <p>When the elusive group, the Earth Liberation Front, announced on New Year's Eve that it had firebombed some luxury houses under construction on old farmland in Mount Sinai, it used more graffiti messages: ''Stop Urban Sprawl'' and ''If You Build It We Will Burn It.''</p>
        <p>But Lennard Axinn, the builder who was targeted that snowy Dec. 30 morning, played a role in saving nearly 18 acres of land across the street from the upscale subdivision for a park, a model use of open space. Mr. Axinn is considered by mainstream East End environmentalists to be a gem among developers for his friendly dealings with the greens.</p>
        <p>''He was conscious of the environment,'' said Lori Baldassare, president of the Mount Sinai Civic Association, said of Mr. Axinn. ''He wanted to work with the community, which is always a welcome change for a developer. I am not really sure why they picked that development to target. We have been trying to figure it out ourselves.''</p>
        <p>It has not gone unnoticed by federal and local authorities tracking the group that news bulletins about Long Island actions released by an Earth Liberation Front spokesman in Portland, Ore., are chock-full of errors.</p>
        <p>Those bulletins have miscalculated the scope of damage (fire gutted one unit in one building in a Middle Island condominium complex, not 16 nearly completed luxury homes, as claimed); overestimated the economic value of their destruction ($200,000 worth of fire and smoke damage in Middle Island, rather than the $3.5 million claimed); and gotten simple facts wrong (the communique claimed the Mount Sinai attack was on Dec. 29, when in fact it was a day later).</p>
        <p>Tactically, there have been mistakes too. The crude incendiary devices used in a Dec. 9 arson at an upscale subdivision in Middle Island malfunctioned in three of four cases when slow-burning punks affixed to plastic jugs of gasoline did not ignite a blaze. The group replaced the punks with birthday candles in the Mount Sinai arson, but even then one device malfunctioned, the police said.</p>
        <p>Rather than all-knowing defenders of the earth who strike with pinpoint precision and then vanish, the group known by the acronym ELF is beginning to emerge as the gang of militant environmentalists that could not shoot straight.</p>
        <p>Some people are even wondering why ELF has targeted Long Island, a place whose gentle hills and heaving surf have long been a magnet for people looking to live far enough but not too far from the city.</p>
        <p>Long Island would not make it on a mainstream environmentalist's Top 10 list of national causes, said Eric A. Goldstein, an attorney with the Natural Resources Defense Council. And Daniel F. Becker of the Sierra Club said: ''Long Island's environmental problems are not radically better nor radically worse than many other suburban areas in the United States.''</p>
        <p>Long Island is in no great distress from a major industrial contaminant. It is not some poverty-stricken community living in the shadow of a gigantic oil refinery. And it does not have any crown jewels of the national park system that might be perceived as threatened.</p>
        <p>Its farms are vanishing in a cloud of developers' dust, but they are farms, after all, not pristine wilderness. The Island's wildest area, the Pine Barrens, is mostly protected from development.</p>
        <p>''I'm baffled,'' Richard L. Amper, Jr., executive director of the Long Island Pine Barrens Society, said when asked why he thought the Earth Liberation Front has turned up in Suffolk County.</p>
        <p>''They may have picked a place that is a paradigm for overdevelopment, but the audience didn't need the message,'' Mr. Amper said. ''It is like bringing us a telegram saying, 'World War II is over.' We know!''</p>
        <p>But in many ways, Long Island may be the perfect place to gain attention for such a movement. A quintessential suburb, it has been host to a long-running debate on land use: preservationists against developers is an old story. But in recent years that debate has grown hotter. Today, there is not one town on the East End that does not have some land dispute.</p>
        <p>Robert S. DeLuca, president of the Group for the South Fork, described the Island as ''a perfect laboratory for anarchy.''</p>
        <p>For the last 50 years, farmland has been disappearing at the rate of 1,200 acres per year as the population of eastern Long Island has tripled since 1960, Mr. DeLuca said. He added that the number of farms in Suffolk has gone from 2,200 to 600 in the last decade.</p>
        <p>''We invented suburbia,'' said Steven Englebright, a Democratic state Assemblyman from Setauket. ''Long Island has been a crucible for environmental issues resulting from our society's confrontation with crowding, transportation problems, air quality and water quality. None of which is new.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Englebright first ran for Suffolk County legislator on the issue of preserving open space back in 1983. Now, nearly 20 years later, the issue is bigger than ever.</p>
        <p>''I think they are exploiting us,'' Mr. Englebright said of ELF. ''It appears that what they are doing is trying to take advantage of Long Island's struggles for their own notoriety and to try to get some coverage that would benefit their operation.''</p>
        <p>With the biggest media center in the world a mere bumper-to-bumper ride west on the Long Island Expressway, the region can be attractive for anyone craving attention. Craig S. Rosebraugh, the ELF spokesman in Portland, said he had received about 70 calls from reporters around the country and the world in the past weeks.</p>
        <p>It is a classic case of what is called ''propaganda of the deed,'' said Chip Berlet, the senior analyst at Political Research Associates, a think tank in Somerville, Mass., that studies authoritarian and anti-democratic social movements.</p>
        <p>''What they are trying to say to one side is, 'You need to be more radical,' '' Mr. Berlet said. ''Overwhelmingly, as a tactic, this fails because people are repulsed by the violence.''</p>
        <p>That is what happened after ELF took credit for a $12 million arson at a new ski resort in Vail, Colo., in 1998, said Michael Roselle, who works for Greenpeace, which over the years has had many confrontations with whalers, loggers and builders but says it has never destroyed property.</p>
        <p>''They came back stronger and they got a better facility and they wiped out the local opposition to their expansion,'' Mr. Roselle said of those pushing for the Vail project. ''So it was lose-lose'' for the environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Already in Suffolk, some developers have begun to paint all environmentalists with the same broad brush -- an injustice akin to painting all members of the media as unscrupulous paparazzi, Mr. Englebright said.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Wieboldt, executive vice president of the Long Island Builders Institute, said the invective over land use on the East End has actually provided a toehold for violence. He has urged all political and governmental leaders in the area to denounce the violence and has offered a $10,000 reward.</p>
        <p>''The key question in my mind is 'Why Long Island?' '' Mr. Wieboldt said. ''And the thing that first comes to mind is, the level of rhetoric on this island about preservation and development has been so extreme. The extreme rhetoric is essentially almost sort of a prior cause for this thing. I can just see soft minds being led, and I think the whole tone of the rhetoric has been so extreme that that is why it is hitting here.''</p>
        <p>Local and national environmentalists reject that notion as preposterous. The politics of environmentalism on Long Island, no matter how divisive, cannot be blamed for criminality, they say. But they do not shrink from the issue of overdevelopment of Long Island as a valid concern.</p>
        <p>''Violence should have no place whatsoever in political discourse, and the means employed by these few kooks are repugnant,'' said Mr. Goldstein of the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''But the concerns that prompted their action are reality-based. The environment is a major reason why people want to live on Long Island in the first place and you don't want to kill the goose that laid the golden egg by destroying it for short-sighted reasons.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker, director of the global warming and energy program at the Sierra Club's Washington headquarters, argued that it was not worth discussing what may have driven the ELF actions because there could be no justification for criminal activity. And whatever their motivation, he said, it had nothing to do with the environment.</p>
        <p>''I would be very surprised if, in the fullness of time, someone found out there was a specific operation to target Long Island,'' Mr. Becker said. ''These are either disturbed people or criminals. I have no respect for people who resort to violence, no matter what their political goals.''</p>
        <p>And when they get the underlying set of facts about their target wrong, it further muddies the picture, many said.</p>
        <p>''They don't consider the facts to be as important as the overall mission. They feel there is an excuse for this total-warfare attitude, and they don't necessarily need to do any kind of research,'' said Mr. Roselle, who was a founder of Earth First, an environmental group whose members held a gathering in England in the early 1990's where the ELF movement is said to have gotten its start.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh said he could not speak to the tactical errors because he was not member of the group. He attributes the informational glitches to the difficulty of corroborating the claims of an anonymous band of radicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh, who said he merely shared the information forwarded to him through means he declined to reveal, said his attempts to verify the details before releasing them were often hindered because local authorities would not speak freely.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh said he trusted the information from the communiques more than he did any account by officials or the media, because the ELF members were present for the action. But details aside, he said, ''the key importance is to let the public know what went on and why it went on.''</p>
        <p>''The question is, 'How do I know that the actions I receive communications for are the ELF?' Well, truthfully, there is no way to know because the ELF is an anonymous group,'' Mr. Rosebraugh said recently. ''But we do as much checking as we can. We try to contact the media, for them to contact the authorities.''</p>
        <p>But even the authorities have questions about who is behind the destruction and how connected they may (or may not) be to a national movement that emerged publicly in 1997, in a wave of illegal and extreme environmentalism mostly in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>A local debate has begun about whether those who caused the Suffolk damage are part of a small traveling band of ELF nomads that crisscross the nation or some local residents sympathetic to the ELF cause but entirely divorced from any organized leadership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh describes the group as a series of cells across the country with no hierarchy, no membership roll and a decentralized philosophy for direct action. It claims allegiance only to the cause of opposing those judged to be destroying the environment to make a profit.</p>
        <p>Or, as the group itself said in a 1997 Internet posting: ''ELF works to speed up the collapse of industry, to scare the rich and to undermine the foundations of the state.'' The posting gave directions to cut power lines, blow up transformers and ''smash, burn or flood'' buildings.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation refers to such acts eco-terrorism.</p>
        <p>''We are aware of them as a special-interest group,'' Steven Berry, a supervisory special agent for the F.B.I. in Washington, said of ELF. ''Some members of the group emphasize violence and other illegal activities to support their cause. We consider any act of eco-terrorism as serious, and we investigate these matters fully and thoroughly.''</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. is working with the Suffolk District Attorney, James M. Catterson Jr., and the local police. Samples of the red paint used to scrawl graffiti on the nearly completed houses have been sent to a forensics laboratory, said Detective Sgt. Dodd R. Amrhein of the Suffolk County Police arson squad. The police are examining other evidence, including a claw hammer hurled through a window, for the trace of any fingerprints, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roselle, like others, is at a loss to explain who is behind the acts. Mr. Rosebraugh said it was impossible to put reporters in touch with actual ELF members. But Federal officials yearning to know more about ELF have hauled him before a grand jury six times, Mr. Rosebraugh said.</p>
        <p>He has always invoked his Fifth Amendment right to remain silent under questioning, he said, except for once last year when he was placed under an order compelling testimony about a fire at the Monmouth, Ore., offices of the Boise Cascade lumber company that ELF took responsibility for.</p>
        <p>''I, to the best of my ability, told the truth,'' Mr. Rosebraugh said of his testimony on that occasion. ''I, to a number of questions, said, 'I do not recall.' ''</p>
        <p>Back in July, officials at Cold Spring Harbor Lab who surveyed the damage to the trampled corn at the Uplands Farm facility in Huntington, said the vandalism provided few clues about why ELF chose the site. It was not only misguided, they said, but misdirected.</p>
        <p>The land was where Dr. Barbara McClintock studied Indian corn in the 1940's to learn about transposable elements -- work that won her a Nobel Prize in 1983, said Jeffrey J. Picarello, a lab spokesman. It was not the kind of site to make a statement denouncing genetic engineering of a popular American food.</p>
        <p>Even a cursory search of the Internet could tell people that, Mr. Picarello said.</p>
        <p>''They attacked a field of natural corn,'' Mr. Picarello said. ''It set our research back two years, but they made a mistake. We were using it to study natural plant breeding, so I assume they thought they were targeting a genetically modified field of corn. But we don't have genetically modified crops here. I mean, it is not even a food crop.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 11, 2001, Sunday  A picture caption on Jan. 14 about vandalism by the Earth Liberation Front misstated the slogan spray-painted on a garage door in a Mount Sinai housing development. It was: ''If You Build It We Will Burn It. E.L.F.'' (''Stop Urban Sprawl'' had been painted on another facade of the house.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 11, 2001, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Jan. 14 about vandalism by the Earth Liberation Front misstated the slogan spray-painted on a garage door in a Mount Sinai housing development. It was: ''If You Build It We Will Burn It. E.L.F.'' (''Stop Urban Sprawl'' had been painted on another facade of the house.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
