<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gas-Rich Desert Will Test Bush Resolve</title>
    <meta content="04LAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/04/politics/04LAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1268327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jack Morrow Hills (Wyo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wyoming</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Land Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7D6133EF937A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gas-Rich Desert Will Test Bush Resolve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>ROCK SPRINGS, Wyo., Jan. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Enormous, unfenced gas-rich swath of high desert in Wyoming known as Jack Morrow Hills will be first test of new approach Pres Bush has pledged on public lands; land, rich in natural gas, has been off limits to energy exploration while Bureau of Land Management works on plan to balance conservation and development; Clinton administration rejected one proposal and ordered that new plan give top priority to conservation goals; Bush administration is giving top priority to closing what it contends is big gap in nation's energy supply; people living in region hope Bush will reverse wave of government action in Clinton's final month that put scores of millions of acres of federal land out of reach to mining, logging and drilling; experts expect Bush to make his stand in places like Jack Morrow Hills, where development could serve energy needs; environmentalists contend that any benefits of exploration in hills will be outweighed by certain costs of interfering with fragile habitat; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a test of the new approach that President Bush has pledged on public lands, a good gauge will be what happens north of here, across an enormous, unfenced swath of high desert prized both for its rugged beauty and for the natural gas that lies beneath.</p>
        <p>For four years, the land, known as the Jack Morrow Hills, has been off limits to energy exploration, while the Bureau of Land Management tried to come up with a plan to balance conservation and development. Just before leaving office, the Clinton administration rejected one proposal and, in an extraordinary step, ordered that a new plan give top priority to conservation goals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a test of the new approach that President Bush has pledged on public lands, a good gauge will be what happens north of here, across an enormous, unfenced swath of high desert prized both for its rugged beauty and for the natural gas that lies beneath.</p>
        <p>For four years, the land, known as the Jack Morrow Hills, has been off limits to energy exploration, while the Bureau of Land Management tried to come up with a plan to balance conservation and development. Just before leaving office, the Clinton administration rejected one proposal and, in an extraordinary step, ordered that a new plan give top priority to conservation goals.</p>
        <p>But now the fate of the Jack Morrow Hills is in the hands of a Bush administration that is giving top priority to closing what it contends is a big gap in the nation's energy supply. And in a region where most people live off what is pulled from the ground, many people say they hope the final decision will help to reverse a wave of government action that, in President Bill Clinton's final month, put scores of millions of acres of federal land out of reach to mining, logging and drilling.</p>
        <p>''To just lock up the land and have it for the sake of saying it's out there doesn't make a lot of sense to me,'' John W. Hay III, president of the Rock Springs National Bank and head of the local cattlemen's association, said. ''But we have a change in administrations, and my guess is that we will have some rational people who see that there is room for multiple use.'' Across the West, many of Mr. Bush's allies have disparaged Mr. Clinton's approach as amounting to a land grab, and the new president himself has made plain his view that his predecessor overreached. At least some of the land that Mr. Clinton ordered protected, Mr. Bush said in a pre-inauguration interview, should be reassigned to allow development if it could be done in an environmentally sensitive way.</p>
        <p>With an eye toward possible reversals, the new administration is reviewing all of Mr. Clinton's last-minute actions, including rules that banned logging and road building across nearly a third of the nation's national forest land and orders that created more than a dozen national monuments.</p>
        <p>But rather than mount an across-the-board challenge, people who have been watching the process say, Mr. Bush is most likely to make his stand in places like the Jack Morrow Hills, where overturning the Clinton approach would be relatively easy and where development could clearly serve energy needs.</p>
        <p>''A former secretary of the interior told the B.L.M. to go back to the drawing board, and the new secretary of the interior can say heck no,'' said Johanna Wald, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, which is among the organizations campaigning to keep the Clinton protections in place.</p>
        <p>At stake in the Jack Morrow Hills, Ms. Wald and others contend, is not just energy, but the fate of a vast habitat that environmental groups prefer to call the red desert, an area of shifting sand dunes, red rocks and soaring buttes that is home to some of North America's largest herds of desert elk, antelope and wild horses.</p>
        <p>A substantial part of the area's 600,000 acres has a high likelihood of containing significant natural gas supplies, the Bureau of Land Management study concluded last June.  But many nearby areas are already being drilled, and environmental advocates contend that any benefits of  exploration in the hills will be outweighed by the certain costs of interfering with a fragile habitat.</p>
        <p>''It's an oxymoron to say that you can make an oil well environmentally sensitive,'' said Tom Bell, a local historian who is a leader among those who have fought for years to gain better protection for the area.</p>
        <p>Only six weeks ago, one of the Clinton administration's final actions had environmental campaigners who believe the land should be permanently protected from development hoping that they had finally won their battle. In contravening a draft plan by the federal Bureau of Land Management, which recommended that the Jack Morrow Hills be reopened to limited oil and gas exploration, the departing interior secretary, Bruce Babbitt, ordered in a Dec. 22 memorandum that the top priority in a revised proposal should be conservation.</p>
        <p>''The presence of finite mineral resources should not deprive future generations of the natural and aesthetic wonders of the Great Divide Basin,'' Mr. Babbitt wrote in the directive, in which he instructed that ''an appropriate decision will be made to protect this unique area and its outstanding resources.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has not signaled whether it intends to overrule that directive. But Mr. Bush and his deputies, including Vice President Dick Cheney, a Wyoming native, have said that decisions about public lands should keep in mind the need to meet a surge in the demand for natural gas, the cleanest of the fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>At least 95 percent of the power plants under construction will be fueled by natural gas, and in large part for that reason a 1999 study by the National Petroleum Council predicted that American demand for natural gas would increase by about 30 percent by 2010, with much of the new supply to come from the Rocky Mountain regions like Wyoming, which is soon to outpace Texas as the country's leading producer of natural gas.</p>
        <p>As across the West, a vast majority of Wyoming land believed to shelter new reserves of oil and gas is owned by the federal government, so the Bush administration's decisions about access are bound to have a direct impact on energy supplies. In the Rockies, according to the 1999 study -- which was commissioned by the Energy Department -- about 137 trillion cubic feet of natural gas, or 10 percent of the country's total reserves, is available only subject to federal restrictions.</p>
        <p>And in Rock Springs, a city of 20,000 whose economy is almost entirely dependent on oil, gas, coal and a mineral known as trona, the dominant view is that any costs of energy development will be far outweighed by the benefits. ''You can keep the habitat and you can go after the resources without affecting people's livelihood,'' said Shane Heavin, a roughneck who was driving over the frozen sand dunes one recent morning to check on some of the few dozen oil and gas wells in in operation.</p>
        <p>Those who believe that energy development and the natural habitat can coexist point to the desert elk herd that is at least five times bigger now than when oil and gas exploration began about 1950. Now, scattered pipelines are visible across the desert sands and isolated wells stand out as industrial islands in the landscape, but advocates of renewed drilling say that goal and nature can easily coexist.</p>
        <p>''Our analysis has basically shown that we can balance oil and gas production and providing habitat for elk,'' said John S. McKee, the director of the local Bureau of Land Management office, whose analysis was overruled by Mr. Babbitt. With an air of criticism, Mr. McKee described Mr. Babbitt's memo as ''not normal,'' but added: ''That was an order from the secretary, and whether it can be undone, I won't speculate on.''</p>
        <p>Others in Wyoming have been more vehement in their denunciations. ''He was telling us what the outcome should be before anyone had done the analysis, and that's not scientific,'' Dru Brower, a vice president of the Petroleum Association of Wyoming, said.</p>
        <p>For the oil and gas industry, the history of decisions on public lands in the Rockies under the Clinton administration was mostly a chronicle of defeat.</p>
        <p>An effort by the Marathon Oil Company to develop gas reserves on federal lands across a vast area of northern Colorado was rejected at the last minute by the Bureau of Land Management, whose decision was upheld in 1999 by the Supreme Court. In 1997, a local forest service official put off limits the entire Lewis and Clark National Forest in Montana, along an energy-rich area known as the Rocky Mountain Front.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton went a big step further with the forest-protection plan, made final in early January, that barred new road building and logging across nearly 60 million acres of national forest. That plan did not prohibit new drilling, and it allowed energy operations to stay in place, but industry officials say that its effect in terms of access will be to all but prevent new oil and gas operations.</p>
        <p>Even more severe in its impact, the officials say, has been Mr. Clinton's decision to use his executive power to establish national monuments in states like Utah, Colorado, Idaho and Montana, giving those areas a status that carries with it a virtual prohibition on oil and gas exploration.</p>
        <p>An unusual deal struck in the 1950's, in negotiations surrounding the establishment of Grand Teton National Park, has established Wyoming as one of only two states (the other is Alaska) in which a president cannot use his power under the Antiquities Act of 1906 to unilaterally designate a national monument. If it were not for that prohibition, people close to Mr. Babbitt say, the interior secretary would have almost certainly recommended that Mr. Clinton protect the Jack Morrow Hills by making it a monument, just as he did in his final weeks in office in protecting places like the Missouri Breaks in Montana, along a 149-mile stretch of the Missouri River, giving them a status that can be reversed only by a Congressional vote. Without that power in Wyoming, Mr. Babbitt and the Clinton administration resorted to an authority that can be much more easily overturned, leaving the door open for a possible reversal by Gale A. Norton, the new interior secretary.</p>
        <p>''You can't have Wyoming be a pristine, untouched area and still be a major natural gas producer,'' said Russell L. Kirlin, the regional manager for Questar, a natural gas company. ''You have to decide what you want.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
