<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aurora Trout: One of Fishing's Best-Kept Secrets</title>
    <meta content="18OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/18/sports/18OUTD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trout</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ontario Province (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karas, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDD1130F93BA25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aurora Trout: One of Fishing's Best-Kept Secrets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nicholas Karas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Karas, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nicholas Karas Outdoors column describes fishing for aurora trout in Ontario, where there is a three-month season for them; (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 50 years of fishing, probably the toughest challenge I ever faced was trying to catch a brook trout without spots. And if that wasn't difficult enough, the fish had been extinct for 30 years. So it was with some disbelief that I questioned Larry Sorochan of Timmins, Ontario, when he called and told me that aurora trout, believed by some to be the only subspecies of brook trout, were alive and well in a dozen small lakes around Timmins.</p>
        <p>On a crisp, sunny, windless October day, I pushed my small aluminum canoe onto the sparkling blue waters of Semple Lake and followed Sorochan as he paddled in his canoe to the far side. We had just driven 20 miles on a dirt logging road, through a dense black-spruce forest to reach the lake. No more than a half-mile across and maybe a mile wide, the lake showed brilliantly against the colorful maples and poplars that lined its edges. The lake's depth plummeted to nearly 70 feet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 50 years of fishing, probably the toughest challenge I ever faced was trying to catch a brook trout without spots. And if that wasn't difficult enough, the fish had been extinct for 30 years. So it was with some disbelief that I questioned Larry Sorochan of Timmins, Ontario, when he called and told me that aurora trout, believed by some to be the only subspecies of brook trout, were alive and well in a dozen small lakes around Timmins.</p>
        <p>On a crisp, sunny, windless October day, I pushed my small aluminum canoe onto the sparkling blue waters of Semple Lake and followed Sorochan as he paddled in his canoe to the far side. We had just driven 20 miles on a dirt logging road, through a dense black-spruce forest to reach the lake. No more than a half-mile across and maybe a mile wide, the lake showed brilliantly against the colorful maples and poplars that lined its edges. The lake's depth plummeted to nearly 70 feet.</p>
        <p>Sorochan, an engineer for a smelting plant outside of Timmins -- located in northeastern Ontario, about midway between Lake Huron and James Bay -- is a dedicated fly fisherman who has become obsessed with catching spotless brook trout. He converted an upstairs bedrooms into a walk-in fly-tying bench. It has the slight aroma of mothballs, used to protect his vast hoard of feathers and fur. His library has almost every book written on tying flies and fly-fishing. On one wall, in a shrinelike setting, is a mounted four-pound female brook trout, one without spots.</p>
        <p>For a few minutes I lost Sorochan in the cover of a mist rising out of the pond. It was giving up its heat to the approaching winter. Only Sorochan's head, arms and fly rod stood above it as he began casting toward shore.</p>
        <p>''They're not like regular brook trout,'' he said as I watched him cast a homemade streamer into the shallows. His most productive pattern is the Mickey Finn, but he is always changing flies. ''Throughout most of the season they stay deep during the day and feed on the surface only early in the morning or between sunset and dark. This late in the season they stay on top longer.''</p>
        <p>Just as he finished his sentence, a fish hit and Sorochan leaned back on the rod, setting the barbless hook. The battle was short-lived when he saw it was a ''regular'' brook trout. ''It's best not to fight them too long,'' he said. ''That decreases their chances of surviving.'' His left hand quickly followed the taunt leader to the hook in the water. Deftly, with a simple twist of the wrist, he released a one-pound spotted brook trout.</p>
        <p>Sorochan has chased these spotless fish ever since Ontario opened a three-month season on them a decade ago. It has been one of fishing's best-kept secrets.</p>
        <p>Once, in the high country of northeastern Ontario, in three little lakes, there lived a population of brook trout that did not look like brook trout. They were shaped like brook trout but their coloration was like Arctic char. They lacked wormlike markings on their backs, and their sides were devoid of crimson spots set in baby-blue halos usually found on brook trout. Their bodies were colored a brassy orange with a dark, olive-drab back.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 1, 1923, a party of American anglers from Pittsburgh took the North Bay-Timmins train north to Earlton Junction. From the village of Elk Lake, they canoed up the East Branch Montreal River to Smoothwater Lake. There the land rises in a series of high hills, some more than 1,000 feet above the lake. On the east side, a dozen small lakes, drained by an interconnecting stream, flow into Smoothwater. It is these lakelets they fished.</p>
        <p>They caught plenty of brook trout but only one without spots. William H. Rinkenbach, a physicist, recognized how unusual the fish was and took it back to Pittsburgh. He named it aurora borealis because the fish's appearance reminded him of the Northern Lights.</p>
        <p>The following July he returned with Dr. Arthur W. Henn, who was an ichthyologist at the Carnegie Museum. They caught aurora trout in Whirligig as well as Whitepine Lake. Henn concluded that it was a new, distinct species unrelated to brook trout, but still a member of the char family. He gave it its scientific name, Salvelinus temagarniensis.</p>
        <p>The search for minerals rang the death knell for many waters in the area. Seventy miles southwest of the ponds, a new smelter's belching smokestacks were loaded with noxious particles that wafted in the wind. When washed from the clouds by rain or snow, they turned into deadly nitric and sulfuric acids.</p>
        <p>They affected all fishes in the Montreal River's headwaters. Aurora, along with brook trout, were the first to decline. In 1950, fishing was closed and the aurora was placed on the endangered species list. By 1971, they were thought to be extinct from the lakes in their natural realm.</p>
        <p>In 1958, Paul Graf, a supervisor at the Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources' Hills Lake Hatchery, which was out of range of acid deposition, netted nine aurora trout and successfully spawned them in his hatchery. That is about as close as it can come to the complete annihilation of a type of fish. Their progeny were retained in the hatchery until a decade ago. When acid rain production in the area was sufficiently reduced, auroras were reintroduced to their original ponds and a dozen others.</p>
        <p>When we fished in October, I used an 8-weight fly rod and a full-length sinking 8-weight fly line to get down where the fish were. We alternated six days of fishing on two waters near Timmins, Semple and Wynn lakes. It wasn't until the fourth day on Wynn Lake, just before sunset, that I caught my first aurora, a 2.25-pound female. I did find one faint blue halo on her side.</p>
        <p>The next day we returned to Wynn Lake. Near sunset, Sorochan boated a duplicate of my fish and immediately released it. The brilliantly colored female on his wall is the only one he has kept. ''I won't kill a aurora unless it's bigger than my four-pounder,'' he said.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
