<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 9-16-01: Questions for Bill Ayers; Forever Rad</title>
    <meta content="WLN135334" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/16/magazine/16QUESTIONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1325331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Weather Underground (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayers, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reeves, Hope</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fugitive Days (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">weathermen</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reeves, Hope</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED61238F935A2575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 9-16-01: Questions for Bill Ayers; Forever Rad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Questions for Bill Ayers, ex-Weatherman, on Which Way the Wind Is Blowing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hope Reeves</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reeves, Hope</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Bill Ayers, former leader of Weathermen, who comments on his new memoir, Fugitive Days, and state of America today; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: You're calling from a pay phone? You still pick up a receiver and think, ''My phone might be tapped''?</p>
        <p>I think anybody in America who doesn't think that is off his rocker. Is there such a thing as a Big Brother? Absolutely. I mean, our worst paranoid fantasies about what the government was capable of in the mid-60's turned out to be mild by comparison to what it did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former leader of the Weathermen defends his new memoir, 'Fugitive Days,' and his partly cloudy forecast for today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: You're calling from a pay phone? You still pick up a receiver and think, ''My phone might be tapped''?</p>
        <p>I think anybody in America who doesn't think that is off his rocker. Is there such a thing as a Big Brother? Absolutely. I mean, our worst paranoid fantasies about what the government was capable of in the mid-60's turned out to be mild by comparison to what it did.</p>
        <p>But you're living a normal life now, with a job and a family and a book to sell, while at least one former comrade, like Kathy Boudin, who was just denied parole, is still in prison. Does that mean you've come to place a certain trust in society?</p>
        <p>I don't trust it. You can't live in a society like this in equilibrium and not sell your soul. This society is not a just and fair and decent place.</p>
        <p>So you're living troubled?</p>
        <p>Oh, I'm troubled, troubled. We're living in a country where the election was stolen, and we didn't have a mass uprising. It's incredible. We're all asleep. The pundits all pat themselves on the back: ''God, what a great country. You know, we could have had a constitutional crisis, but instead, we let him steal the election. Isn't that great. What a country.'' It makes me want to puke.</p>
        <p>So if things are as bad as ever, was it worth it, all the struggling?</p>
        <p>Without a doubt. And the reason is that we really did play a role in destroying the old system of segregation and in destroying the conquest of Indochina by the Americans.</p>
        <p>My parents were also Weathermen. Whenever they refer to their ''revolution,'' I can't help rolling my eyes. I mean, isn't there something a little absurd about thinking you would overthrow the United States government?</p>
        <p>It's a funny word, and people use it for a million different reasons. Mainly, these days, to sell products -- a ''revolutionary'' deodorant. We used the word to mean that we should create a society more equal, more fair, more just, more loving than the society that we have. It was a huge kind of hope. And it does seem, looking back, naïve and absurd. But if we are guilty of a kind of grandiose innocence, what we should not fall into in reaction is a kind of arch cynicism.</p>
        <p>Yes, my parents have often accused me of being in what you would call ''a deep American sleep.'' Is there something wrong with my generation for not being obsessed with world injustice?</p>
        <p>Well, I'm going to disagree with you. There are all kinds of signs now of a wonderful activism going on internationally -- Seattle and Genoa, young people objecting to global capitalism getting to make all the decisions about everybody's life without any consultation or any democratic process at all, let alone any sharing of the wealth. People are demanding that the world come to its senses about things like global warming and environmental degradation and the pollution of water and air. It's not all quiet.</p>
        <p>You were quoted as urging the young to ''kill all the rich people, break up their cars and apartments, bring the revolution home, kill your parents, that's where it's at.'' Did you actually mean for people to do that?</p>
        <p>Many things were said in a kind of a humor. They were excessive and extreme and a joke. They were taken literally mainly by the for-profit media to show how crazy we were.</p>
        <p>Well, my mom took it seriously, as a directive from you.</p>
        <p>She killed her parents?</p>
        <p>No, but it took years to heal the wounds. She and the other foot soldiers, as she calls them, looked to you and the Weather Bureau for direction.</p>
        <p>Well, if there's a lesson, it's to never surrender your own mind. People being betrayed by leaders -- well, that's the cautionary tale.</p>
        <p>Lots of folks are still around who lived through the time you're writing about. What will you say to those who say that's not how it happened, that you're lying?</p>
        <p>That it's a memoir, it's not a history. It's a story of one person and should be read as a story. Reading it as anything else is a distorted reading. Memoirs are not records of events; they are memories.</p>
        <p>But you spend a lot of your book discussing how hazy memory is.</p>
        <p>How can you write a memoir if you, as you note in the opening, remember almost nothing?</p>
        <p>I have a little disclaimer that says, ''This is one version of events, not authoritative, not authorized, but one boy's story.'' Did I make things look a certain way that they weren't or purposely leave things out? Not consciously, but perhaps unconsciously. Someone else could say, ''No, no, it was like this.'' And it's not like one of us has a purchase on the truth. I'm writing a story about how it felt to me, and I invite everyone to write the story about how it felt to them. It's the clash of stories that's the true story. It's collective memory that matters.</p>
        <p>Hope Reeves</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
