<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Plans Incentives for Energy Conservation</title>
    <meta content="13RADI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/13/politics/13RADI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5D91F3BF930A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Plans Incentives for Energy Conservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed new tax incentives today to encourage energy conservation, including assistance for people who buy fuel-efficient cars and for companies that  install more efficient power generating systems.</p>
        <p>President Bush, in his weekly radio address, said the proposals would be part of a broad review of energy policy that the administration is about to unveil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed new tax incentives today to encourage energy conservation, including assistance for people who buy fuel-efficient cars and for companies that  install more efficient power generating systems.</p>
        <p>President Bush, in his weekly radio address, said the proposals would be part of a broad review of energy policy that the administration is about to unveil.</p>
        <p>''Pushing conservation forward will require investment in new energy technology, and that will be part of my administration's energy plan,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's remarks provided the latest example of his growing willingness to incorporate at least modest conservation measures into his energy planning. In recent weeks, the administration has been sharply criticized for focusing on fossil fuel exploration and power plant construction, more than conservation, as the solutions to energy shortages.</p>
        <p>This month, the president ordered all federal facilities in California to keep thermostats at 78 degrees and shut down escalators during electricity shortages this summer. He also told managers of the government's 500,000 buildings nationwide to devise plans to reduce their energy use as much as possible.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has in the past warned that the nation ''can't conserve our way to energy independence.'' But today, he sought to distinguish between traditional conservation policies and ''a 21st-century conservation'' that uses new technology to make efficiency less painful.</p>
        <p>''Some think that conservation means doing without,'' Mr. Bush said in his address. ''That does not have to be the case.''</p>
        <p>''It can mean building sensors into new buildings to shut the lights off as soon as people leave a room,'' he continued. ''It can mean upgrading the transmission lines that deliver electricity to your home so less is wasted on the way.''</p>
        <p>The new proposals outlined by the White House today would allow companies to write off the costs of new, more efficient generators at a faster rate. The proposal is intended to encourage businesses to replace inefficient boilers with systems that make use of both the heat and the electrical power that they produce.</p>
        <p>The plan would also give tax credits to people who buy electric or gas-electric hybrid cars between 2002 and 2007. The White House did not specify the value of those credits.</p>
        <p>Hybrid cars, which are currently being sold in the United States only by Honda and Toyota, can typically travel 50 miles or more on a gallon of gasoline.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also proposed expanding a variety of federal energy awareness programs, including the voluntary Energy Star program that is intended to help consumers pick out more energy efficient appliances.</p>
        <p>Daniel Becker, director of the Sierra Club's global warming and energy program, described Mr. Bush's initiatives as extremely modest and said he expects the final plan to focus on drilling for oil and gas or building nuclear and coal-fired power plants.</p>
        <p>''They seem to be constructing a Potemkin village of energy efficiency,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
