<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="08FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2D81E39F93BA35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Taiwan Moves to Build Commercial Links to China  Taiwan lifted longtime restrictions on direct investment in China, bowing to the reality of living next door to a fast-rising political and economic power. But some analysts worry that the move will make Taiwan overly dependent on China and threaten its political independence. Others say it will accelerate the commercial integration of Taiwan and China.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Taiwan Moves to Build Commercial Links to China  Taiwan lifted longtime restrictions on direct investment in China, bowing to the reality of living next door to a fast-rising political and economic power. But some analysts worry that the move will make Taiwan overly dependent on China and threaten its political independence. Others say it will accelerate the commercial integration of Taiwan and China.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>The Concorde Flies Again  The world's only supersonic airliner resumed passenger service with an Air France flight from Paris to New York followed by a British Airways flight from London. The planes have been modified since a Concorde crashed outside Paris 15 months ago.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Spanish Judge Is Slain  A judge was shot dead as he left home near Bilbao, in northern Spain, in the first fatal attack linked to the Basque separatist group E.T.A. since the Sept. 11 terror attacks in the United States. Officials speculated that the shooting was a response to the arrest of two people suspected of planting a car bomb in Madrid that injured 95 people on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Greek Elite Is Accused  Tensions between Greece and the United States increased after Thomas Niles, a former American ambassador to Athens, asserted that there were links between Greece's political elite and the Revolutionary Organization 17 November, a terror group held responsible for a series of assassinations of Americans and others.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>German Response to Sept. 11  The German cabinet adopted plans for major changes in security and immigration laws and approved the deployment of up to 3,900 troops for up to a year to support the American-led war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Global Warming Talks  Government ministers from around the world meeting in Morocco were encouraged by a breakthrough in lower-level talks that put in place a system to ensure that countries comply with their pollution targets -- an issue that has been a stumbling block.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-24</p>
        <p>Oregon Sues U.S. to Keep Its Assisted-Suicide Law  Oregon's attorney general, joined by four patients, went to court seeking a stay of a Justice Department order authorizing federal drug agents to take action against any doctor who prescribes lethal drugs for terminally ill patients wishing to end their lives under provisions of Oregon's assisted-suicide law.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>$5 Billion Valdez Penalty Voided  A federal appeals court in San Francisco struck the $5.3 billion in punitive damages assessed for the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska in 1989, the worst in the nation's history. The court agreed with Exxon Mobil that the award was excessive, and it ordered a judge to reduce it.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Defining Disabilities  The Supreme Court heard arguments on just what it means when the Americans With Disabilities Act defines a disability as an impairment that ''substantially limits'' someone from engaging in one or more ''major life activities.''</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>New Atlanta Mayor  Unofficial results indicate that Shirley Clarke Franklin has become the first woman to be elected mayor of Atlanta and the first black woman to lead a major Southern city.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Bush Pushes His Faith Initiative  President Bush asked Senate leaders to pass a slimmed-down version of his plan to give federal money to religious charities, saying all charities were hard-pressed to provide relief to victims of the Sept. 11 terror attack while helping the needy.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>D1-13</p>
        <p>Democrats Squabble After Bloomberg Victory  New York Democrats dissolved in recriminations over who was to blame for Mark Green's loss to Michael R. Bloomberg, the novice Republican elected mayor. The state Democratic Party leader suggested that either Andrew M. Cuomo or H. Carl McCall quit the governor's race to avoid a reprise of the racially charged mayoral primary campaign.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>With the notable exception of New York City, Democrats did well throughout the New York region.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Mayor-elect Bloomberg indicated he would form his own team for a new administration, and not necessarily by retaining top Giuliani aides.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Warning in New Jersey  Governor-elect James E. McGreevey warned about the tough fiscal situation facing the state and newly elected legislators, who include a new majority of his fellow Democrats in the State Assembly.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Baby's Killing  Julie Herrnkind gave a written statement to the police describing how she and her husband killed their 3-year-old daughter in a fit of rage. Child welfare officials sought to determine whether caseworkers and others who visited the Staten Island home in the last year or so had missed signs that the girl was in danger.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>D12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Change Atop Science Academy  Rodney W. Nichols resigned as president and chief executive of the New York Academy of Sciences after months of turmoil over his efforts to reshape the academy.</p>
        <p>D9</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Sotheby's Ex-Chief on Trial  Sotheby's former chairman, A. Alfred Taubman, 76, goes on trial today on charges involving price-fixing at his auction house and Christie's.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Enron Close to Being Acquired  The board of Dynegy Inc. tentatively approved a deal to acquire the Enron Corporation, the once-mighty energy-trading company laid low by a financial crisis.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Pakistan Seeks Tariff Relief  A big decline in business from American companies is forcing apparel and textile concerns in Pakistan to lay off thousands of people and could soon close numerous factories.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Suit Over Missing Millions  A lawsuit accused three executives of Evergreen International Spot Trading and First Equity Enterprises, a currency firm, of plotting to cover up $105 million that was missing after the trade center attack.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>S1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: The C.E.O. of N.Y.C.; coalition maintenance; Verlyn Klinkenborg on Kathy Nguyen.  Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>S2  Public Lives</p>
        <p>D2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
