<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fun for Children And the Childish</title>
    <meta content="13BIER$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/13/weekinreview/13BIER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biersdorfer, J D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Greece</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Decades</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D61E3BF930A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fun for Children And the Childish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY J. D. BIERSDORFER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Biersdorfer, J D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on computer games that are marketed specifically to adults; there is seen an interesting commerical paradox at work; sometimes software designed specifically for children is a lot smarter than what is being peddled to adults; it is grownups, often, who seem drawn to threadbare plots that serve as pretext for violence and sexual innuendo; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT first glance, the computer game that lets the player create a city-state in ancient Greece (down to setting up tax and trade policies and propitiating the gods) may seem like the sort of entertainment only a middle-aged historian would love. On the other hand, the game featuring a cute little squirrel seems meant for kids.</p>
        <p>Wrong. Zeus, Master of Olympus, a richly illustrated and complex adventure, was created for players of all ages and has found a market among children. Conker's Bad Fur Day, on the other hand, is little more than a chaotic stew of scatological humor -- usually from the mouth of a squirrel named Conker -- that is marketed specifically to adults.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT first glance, the computer game that lets the player create a city-state in ancient Greece (down to setting up tax and trade policies and propitiating the gods) may seem like the sort of entertainment only a middle-aged historian would love. On the other hand, the game featuring a cute little squirrel seems meant for kids.</p>
        <p>Wrong. Zeus, Master of Olympus, a richly illustrated and complex adventure, was created for players of all ages and has found a market among children. Conker's Bad Fur Day, on the other hand, is little more than a chaotic stew of scatological humor -- usually from the mouth of a squirrel named Conker -- that is marketed specifically to adults.</p>
        <p>There is an interesting commercial paradox at work here. Sometimes the software designed specifically for children is a lot smarter than what is being peddled to adults. It is the grown-ups, often, who seem drawn to threadbare plots that serve as the pretext for violence and sexual innuendo.</p>
        <p>Of course, the entertainment software industry, which took in more than $6 billion dollars domestically last year, offers plenty of dreadful material for children, as well as some terrific titles for adults.</p>
        <p>The whole wonderful-to-awful gamut will be on display this week at the Electronic Entertainment Expo in Los Angeles, the world's largest trade show for game software, where hundreds of new games will be unveiled. Still, a certain pattern will be observable: adults play games to escape reality, while kids are game for anything.</p>
        <p>When it comes to their computer screens, observed Steve Koenig, senior analyst with NPD Intellect, a research firm in Reston, Va., ''kids are a little bit more open-minded.''</p>
        <p>In SPY Fox: Operation Ozone, a game for preteen children, the eponymous protagonist must save the world from a giant can of hair spray shot into space by the villain to destroy the Earth's ozone layer. The game, considered complex for its intended age group, 5 to 8,  with its use of subtle clues and need for sturdy logic skills, combines a compelling adventure scenario with witty characters and a socially conscious message.</p>
        <p>In contrast, one of the best-selling games for adults last year, Diablo 2, is a violent sword-and-sorcery epic with heroes battling evil monsters. The game is challenging and vivid, but one cannot help enjoying the irony that while little girls are saving the ozone layer in SPY Fox, the grown men are off fighting their way through dungeons full of imaginary monsters in Diablo 2.</p>
        <p>Video games in any form have had a reputation for violence, repetition and plots mired in galactic struggles between good and evil. The first video game, Spacewar -- created in 1962 on M.I.T.'s hefty PDP-1 computer, which was the size of three refrigerators with a control panel full of switches and light -- featured two rudimentary spaceships firing torpedoes at each other. Decades later, there are still games like Wing Commander that boil down to the same thing, albeit with glorious full-color animation.</p>
        <p>One hundred and forty-five million Americans play computer and video games, the Interactive Digital Software Association estimates. Their average age is 28, and 43 percent of them are women. While shooting and quest games (or those that, like the Tomb Raider series,  combine shooting and questing with curvaceous female protagonists) appeal more to men, simulation-and-strategy games, which tend to be more complex, various and subtle, are growing rapidly in popularity. According to figures supplied by Mr. Koenig at NPD Intellect, the top-selling game last year was The Sims. In the game, which is designed for players 13 and older, one gets to create and control a detailed neighborhood and all the neighbors. Another recent release for teens, Black &amp; White, also lets players literally play God, represented onscreen by a disembodied hand. Games that allow for behavioral ambiguity, logic and elaborate role-playing are currently outpacing programs in which good and bad slug it out.</p>
        <p>The old-fashioned hack-'em-ups will always be around, but as players and software designers alike mature, more new games like The Sims, which stimulate creativity and community, could lead the gaming world out of the Dark Ages and into a new age in which it's not just the children who are playing like grown-ups.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
