<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; Raising His Megaphone, Bush Says, I'm in Charge</title>
    <meta content="30MEMO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/30/politics/30MEMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Arizona</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reed, Scott</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gillespie, Ed</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DB153FF933A05750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; Raising His Megaphone, Bush Says, I'm in Charge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo on Pres Bush's second news conference; says Bush projected image of engaged leader, not just a witness (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At his White House news conference today, the president put forward the persona of the jocular Bush, ribbing a television news reporter for a salary that was undoubtedly in ''the top 1 percent.'' He presented the self-deprecating Bush, making fun of his own tendency to mispronounce words.</p>
        <p>But perhaps most important, he promoted the image of the engaged Bush, who was not merely a detached witness to the campaign finance debate in the Senate or the bloodshed in the Middle East, but rather a leader with a role in these events, opinions about them and a lot more on his mind and his plate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At his White House news conference today, the president put forward the persona of the jocular Bush, ribbing a television news reporter for a salary that was undoubtedly in ''the top 1 percent.'' He presented the self-deprecating Bush, making fun of his own tendency to mispronounce words.</p>
        <p>But perhaps most important, he promoted the image of the engaged Bush, who was not merely a detached witness to the campaign finance debate in the Senate or the bloodshed in the Middle East, but rather a leader with a role in these events, opinions about them and a lot more on his mind and his plate.</p>
        <p>After several weeks in which President Bush was at times an almost peripheral figure in the news of the day, which veered in directions different than his administration desired, he seemed to be trying to take both center stage and control. Some political analysts said that the news conference was interestingly timed.</p>
        <p>''John McCain has dominated the news for two full weeks,'' noted Scott Reed, a Republican strategist here, referring to campaign finance, an issue that was not one of the administration's priorities. ''The economy has slowed down. Next week is a big week in the Senate with the budget resolution. Now's when you have to have all 12 cylinders pumping.''</p>
        <p>Kenneth M. Duberstein, the former chief of staff in the Reagan White House, offered a similar assessment.</p>
        <p>''Bush is staying focused on the economy and tax cuts on a day when the Senate is considering campaign finance reform,'' Mr. Duberstein said, noting that the president's ''megaphone is bigger than anybody else's -- including 100 senators.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush is not always quick to use it, and just as his first news conference followed a period of time when another politician, former President Clinton, was getting more coverage than he was, this White House news conference -- Mr. Bush's second -- followed a period of dominance by Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's news conference also came at a time of growing apprehensions about the economy, reflected in several recent polls by Republican officials and independent organizations that showed either signs of jitters in the electorate or possible seeds of doubt about Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that they and Mr. Bush had started talking late last week about having a news conference late this week, and that it fit within their general goal of having at least one every month.</p>
        <p>''The president wants to be accessible to the press, and there are a lot of issues right now that the press had not had a chance to talk to the president about,'' said Karen P. Hughes, the counselor to the president.</p>
        <p>Those included campaign finance, the Middle East, carbon dioxide emissions and reports of tension with Mr. McCain, and as Mr. Bush took an array of questions about these predictable topics, it seemed as if he was trying to quiet all the extraneous noise, so that Americans would better hear his pitch for his tax cut.</p>
        <p>It was telling that he opened his news conference by drawing attention to a House vote on Wednesday in favor of his budget resolution, a development that was crucial to the passage of his tax plan, but that was given only limited attention.</p>
        <p>''He's used his megaphone very well to sell his tax cut on the road,'' said Ed Gillespie, a Republican strategist who talks frequently with administration officials. ''It's helpful, when he's back here in town, to use it here as well.''</p>
        <p>And so he did, in a merry-cum-mischievous manner that may not be conventionally presidential but is quintessentially Bush, a part of the upbeat, unfussy, informal aura he relishes. As he did last month, he held the news conference not in the gilded East Room but in the press briefing room, a less stilted setting.</p>
        <p>And he cracked jokes. ''Those who think that they can say, 'We're only going to have a stimulus package, but let's forget tax relief,' misunderestimate -- or excuse me -- underestimate,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>''Just making sure you were paying attention,'' he laughed.</p>
        <p>(Mr. Bush continued his recent habit of poking such generous fun at himself at a dinner tonight for television and radio correspondents, where he read aloud from a book that catalogued his most ridiculous and comical misstatements.)</p>
        <p>During the press conference, he told a reporter with a raised hand that of the remaining two people who would get to ask questions before the end, the reporter would be ''next to next. Let me rephrase that -- you're last.''</p>
        <p>And when a beeper went off, he did not repeat his reaction last week when the ringing of a reporter's cell phone interrupted his remarks and he gently chastised an aide for failing to patrol the situation. (Mr. Bush abhors such aural intrusions.)</p>
        <p>He simply said, with a smile: ''Don't worry about the beeper violation. It's a new approach.''</p>
        <p>Today's news conference was all about adjustments -- in what reporters were focusing on, in what people were perceiving or misperceiving about the president's intentions, positions or degrees of involvement. Mr. Bush was fine-tuning, and he was trying to be nimble about it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
