<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Misguided Energy Proposal</title>
    <meta content="18FRI1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/18/opinion/18FRI1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California (USA)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Rocky Mountains</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Carter, Jimmy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D9113AF93BA25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Misguided Energy Proposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Pres Bush's long-awaited energy plan is unbalanced effort whose main objective seems to be to satisfy ambitions of oil, gas and coal industries, either by easing environmental rules or by opening public lands for aggressive exploration, while doing little for efficiency or renewable energy; says, on more fundamental level, that plan fails to make case that energy crisis even exists; says it will be up to an attentive Congress to ensure that some good ideas survive while bad ones disappear</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's long-awaited energy plan is as flawed and one-sided as its advance notices suggested it would be. Its 105 separate provisions include several potentially useful proposals aimed at improving energy efficiency and modernizing the country's power grid and pipelines. It also challenges Congress and the country to a long-overdue debate about nuclear power. But on the whole it is an alarmingly unbalanced piece of work whose main objective seems to be to satisfy the ambitions of the oil, gas and coal industries, either by easing environmental rules or by opening public lands for aggressive exploration.</p>
        <p>The plan fails on an even more fundamental level. It warns that the nation is in the midst of an energy crisis that ''will inevitably undermine our economy, our standard of living and our national security'' -- a point repeated yesterday by Mr. Bush as he took his energy campaign on the road. But nowhere does the report persuasively make the case that such a crisis exists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's long-awaited energy plan is as flawed and one-sided as its advance notices suggested it would be. Its 105 separate provisions include several potentially useful proposals aimed at improving energy efficiency and modernizing the country's power grid and pipelines. It also challenges Congress and the country to a long-overdue debate about nuclear power. But on the whole it is an alarmingly unbalanced piece of work whose main objective seems to be to satisfy the ambitions of the oil, gas and coal industries, either by easing environmental rules or by opening public lands for aggressive exploration.</p>
        <p>The plan fails on an even more fundamental level. It warns that the nation is in the midst of an energy crisis that ''will inevitably undermine our economy, our standard of living and our national security'' -- a point repeated yesterday by Mr. Bush as he took his energy campaign on the road. But nowhere does the report persuasively make the case that such a crisis exists.</p>
        <p>True, California is in obvious trouble, and rising gasoline prices at the pump are discomfiting. But that is not by any stretch a ''crisis'' like those confronted by Richard Nixon and Jimmy Carter. California's problems arise mainly from a deregulation plan gone awry, and gasoline prices are actually lower, in real terms, than they were in the early 1980's. The acute shortage of natural gas that the report complains of is beginning to disappear as more wells are drilled in response to rising prices. Finally, the report's alarming estimates of the growing gap between consumption and production of oil and natural gas over the next 20 years -- bedrock data on which Mr. Bush's drilling strategy depends -- do not take into account any important new programs aimed at increasing efficiency, even though such programs have confounded official predictions in the past by greatly reducing the country's energy use.</p>
        <p>The report is not without value. Though the document was hatched in secret, it could well stimulate an open debate on the country's energy future. More specifically, it proposes some long-overdue capital spending on the country's transmission lines and natural-gas pipeline system. In a nod to the conservationists whom Vice President Dick Cheney has been belittling, it offers hefty tax credits for hybrid cars that run on gasoline and electricity. In addition, the report promises to study possible increases in the fuel economy of the nation's fleet of cars and light trucks -- though nobody really expects Mr. Bush to risk any political capital on changes that the automobile industry opposes and Congress itself has refused to make.</p>
        <p>The plan also urges a new look at the potential value of nuclear power, which currently generates about 20 percent of the country's electricity but whose growth has been stalled for decades by legitimate safety concerns over waste disposal as well as by the high cost of building new plants. The plan makes a case for increasing nuclear power to diversify the country's energy base and to reduce the emission of global warming gases, which are a byproduct of plants burning fossil fuels but not of nuclear energy. But it ducks for now the troublesome issue of waste disposal, and it seems almost cavalier in calling for the reconsideration of a quarter-century ban on reprocessing the spent fuel from nuclear plants, a technique that can simplify waste disposal but produces plutonium that can be used to make bombs.</p>
        <p>Apart from the tax credits for hybrid cars, however, the plan does little for efficiency or renewable energy. But by far the most controversial of Mr. Bush's proposals are those that would ease environmental regulations and open public lands for more drilling. Although Congress is unlikely to approve his misguided plan to drill in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, the president has asked his Interior secretary, Gale Norton, to inventory other federal lands that can be made available for exploration. These include ecologically significant wilderness areas in the Rocky Mountains and part of the outer continental shelf that has been off-limits to the oil companies for a decade. Meanwhile, Mr. Bush has asked his Environmental Protection Agency to review clean air rules that, in his view, have placed undue burdens on coal-fired power plants.</p>
        <p>The history of most overarching energy strategies is that a few good ideas survive and most of the bad ones disappear. One can only hope that the same fate will befall the Bush program. But it will be up to an attentive Congress to make sure that happens.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
