<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Like a Film Script, From Jobless to Genius</title>
    <meta content="23CONV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/23/science/23CONV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1265072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A CONVERSATION WITH: SHAWN CARLSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Society for Amateur Scientists</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreifus, Claudia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carlson, Shawn (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Conversations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED6133CF930A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Like a Film Script, From Jobless to Genius</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA DREIFUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dreifus, Claudia</byline>
      <dateline>PROVIDENCE, R.I.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Shawn Carlson, founder of Society for Amateur Scientists; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Shawn Carlson's biography reads like a mutant graft of Mr. Wizard meets Horatio Alger: an unhappy physicist working in a mainstream laboratory decides to quit his job and start a nonprofit organization aimed at encouraging the projects of backyard tinkerers and garage experimenters.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Carlson devotes himself to organizing his Society for Amateur Scientists, he drives his family to near-penury. Just as he is about to go broke, the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation comes to the rescue with a ''genius grant,'' and nearly $300,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Shawn Carlson's biography reads like a mutant graft of Mr. Wizard meets Horatio Alger: an unhappy physicist working in a mainstream laboratory decides to quit his job and start a nonprofit organization aimed at encouraging the projects of backyard tinkerers and garage experimenters.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Carlson devotes himself to organizing his Society for Amateur Scientists, he drives his family to near-penury. Just as he is about to go broke, the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation comes to the rescue with a ''genius grant,'' and nearly $300,000.</p>
        <p>''After MacArthur, I was a certified 'genius'; the day before I was just certifiable,'' Dr. Carlson, 40, said over coffee one morning in Providence, where he and his family have recently moved. Stocky, with sandy-blond hair, he has an open face and an easy laugh.</p>
        <p>In addition to his organizational work, Dr. Carlson has written the ''Amateur Scientist'' column in Scientific American magazine for the past five and a half years.</p>
        <p>The column, however, is to be suspended in March to make room for ''other good ideas for columns,'' said John Rennie, the magazine's editor in chief. ''Amateur Scientist'' had been a regular feature of the periodical since 1928.  Q. Define ''amateur scientist.''  A. We think of amateur scientists as anyone who is engaged in scientific inquiry for the sheer joy of it. If you include all the home tinkerers and amateur naturalists, there must be several million in the country.  Q. How American is the movement?  A. As American as apple pie. Many of the founding fathers were amateur scientists -- Benjamin Franklin.</p>
        <p>Since the mid-1800's, farmers and everyday folk have been organized to make weather observations with the Smithsonian Institution. Thomas Jefferson organized weather-watchers in Virginia and gave them instrumentation to study climate change.  Q. Aside from the occasional eclectic discovery, are there areas where amateurs can make a discernible difference to the general body of scientific knowledge?  A. Most scientists don't really realize the tremendous contributions that amateurs have made over the decades. For instance, most of the global warming debate hinges on data collected by amateurs before the 1950's -- farmers, people like that.</p>
        <p>Bird watchers have done incredible work on calculating the fate of various species. On environmental questions, I see a situation where amateurs could became a vast data collection army, measuring all kinds of things -- thickness of birds' eggs, magnetic field fluctuations.  Q. What exactly does the Society for Amateur Scientists do?  A. Democratize science. We hope we help encourage the scientific creativity in the everyday citizen. We believe that you don't just have to be a Ph.D. to do interesting science. S.A.S. serves as a switchboard for amateurs to trade ideas. In addition to publishing our bulletin, we print how-to information for projects and provide access to inexpensive equipment and chemicals. We also have mentors to help with projects, and a Web site: www.sas.org.</p>
        <p>The Amateur Society has just opened up an observatory with a 16-inch telescope inside New Milford High School in Connecticut. Now the question is, What is the mission going to be? We're still having meetings about that.</p>
        <p>First, we want to get the students in there, but there is going to be a tremendous lot of open time available on the thing. I'd love to link this to the Internet, so that amateurs around the world could use it, for a small fee. The idea is, If we can get the amateur astronomy community on it, we could maybe make $1,000 a night and then have the money to constantly upgrade the telescope.  Q. Name a few amateur projects that have come across your desk and that have intrigued you.</p>
        <p>A. There's a guy named Roger Baker, and he has a design for a magnetometer that allows you to measure changes in the earth's magnetic fields. He uses materials bought at Radio Shack for about $10.</p>
        <p>A wonderful project was done by two dear friends: George Schmermund and Greg Schmidt. They have developed a system to measure extremely tiny masses with very high precision.</p>
        <p>The secret is to go to a surplus store and to buy one of those old analog meters. George invented a way of taking an old discarded galvanometer and turning it into a device that can measure a millionth of a gram. And then, my friend Greg computerized that device for a couple of dollars and turned it into a really powerful instrument so that now any amateur can measure tens of micrograms.  Q. Tell us about your grandfather, the late George Donald Graham.  A. Grandpa Don was a free-spirited wild man, a person with incredible scientific creativity. But he was one of those personalities who couldn't go through the standard course of instruction.</p>
        <p>So he pursued his passion for mathematics and geology and biology on his own and he would frequently write really interesting papers that he couldn't get published because he didn't have ''Ph.D.'' after his name.</p>
        <p>My grandfather would produce a brilliant paper on gravity and corn -- and it just killed me that someone of this kind of talent would be excluded from the discussion just because he didn't have the credentials. Grandfather wore these rejections like a badge of honor on his sleeve. The only place that would publish him was the ''Amateur Scientist'' column of the Scientific American, a column which I authored for five and a half years.  Q. How much are you your grandfather's boy?  A. I'm very much like him. I've got his scientific talents. But as a younger man, I didn't want to make his mistakes -- so I got myself a Ph.D. in nuclear physics from U.C.L.A. and worked as an astrophysicist at Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory from 1991 to 1993. There, I discovered I was like him in another way: I couldn't work on someone else's project and I couldn't keep a job. I drifted more and more toward involvement with the amateur scientific community.</p>
        <p>Then in 1994, my wife and I left the Bay Area. She was about to enter graduate school in San Diego. I decided to use this change and take a huge chance to try to make a contribution as an amateur scientist.</p>
        <p>I took the little savings we had and put it toward starting an organization for people like me -- a society for amateur scientists. I had dreamed about doing this for 10 years. It was a way of paying tribute to my grandfather.  Q. How does an unemployed astrophysicist get to be an organizational entrepreneur?  A. It was hard. I never took a salary. Mostly, my wife, Michelle Tetreault, and I ran up credit card debts and put our own money into it. We had a child, eventually two -- and we lived on my wife's graduate student stipend.</p>
        <p>In 1995, I was asked to take over the ''Amateur Scientist'' column in the Scientific American and that provided $1,000 a month, later $1,500. You can imagine the difference that money made.  Q. Why were you so poor? Did your organization have difficulty finding funding?  A. Oh, yeah. We fell outside the normal funding guidelines. We couldn't get research dollars because -- guess what -- our investigators didn't have Ph.D.'s after their names. We couldn't get educational money because we weren't focusing on children.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, we got a lot of moral support from prestigious science professionals. People like Kip Thorne, Douglas Osheroff and Robert G. Coleman were our advisory board.</p>
        <p>The financial problems all came to a head in June of 1999, when Michelle was about to finish up her Ph.D. and have our second child. One day, she sat me down and said, ''You may have to close S.A.S. down because you have to take care of your family.''</p>
        <p>And just like in the movies, as I stood there shaking my head, saying, ''no, no, no,'' at that very minute, the phone rang with the news that the MacArthur people had granted me a ''genius'' fellowship -- $290,000! Once the MacArthur prize hit, we were legitimate.  Q. Next month, the Scientific American will cease publication of the ''Amateur Scientist'' column -- a feature that magazine has run with different authors since 1928. What are your feelings about the demise of a column that has meant so much to you?  A. Well, of course, I'm heartbroken.  Q. On a lighter subject, when you want to shop till you drop, where do you go?  A. I would like to say Radio Shack, but I would have to say that my favorite place is Hyatt's Electronics in San Diego. It's this little hole in the wall run by this guy named Dick Hyatt. In there, you can find -- anything. I go and say, ''Dick, I need 250 resistors.'' And he'll say, ''Fine, I've got six million. What values do you want?''</p>
        <p>A CONVERSATION WITH: SHAWN CARLSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
