<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DF113DF937A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Taliban Ban on Drug Crops Is Working, U.S. Concludes  American narcotics officials who visited Afghanistan confirmed earlier United Nations reports that the authoritarian Taliban had, in one growing season, managed a rare triumph in the drug war with their ban on the growing of poppies. Without any multimillion-dollar aid packages, they have managed to empty the fields that once accounted for 75 percent of the world's opium crop.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Indian Overture to Pakistan  India said it was ending its six-month unilateral cease-fire in Kashmir, acknowledging that it had failed to bring about peace there, but it also said Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee would invite Pakistan's military ruler, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, to restart talks on peace and cooperation between the two hostile nuclear powers. Pakistani officials said the general would accept the invitation.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Taliban Ban on Drug Crops Is Working, U.S. Concludes  American narcotics officials who visited Afghanistan confirmed earlier United Nations reports that the authoritarian Taliban had, in one growing season, managed a rare triumph in the drug war with their ban on the growing of poppies. Without any multimillion-dollar aid packages, they have managed to empty the fields that once accounted for 75 percent of the world's opium crop.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Indian Overture to Pakistan  India said it was ending its six-month unilateral cease-fire in Kashmir, acknowledging that it had failed to bring about peace there, but it also said Prime Minister Atal Behari Vajpayee would invite Pakistan's military ruler, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, to restart talks on peace and cooperation between the two hostile nuclear powers. Pakistani officials said the general would accept the invitation.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Calm After Israeli Cease-Fire  A fragile, partial cease-fire instituted unilaterally by Israel's army brought some calm to the region and a quickening of diplomatic activity, as foreign emissaries sought to persuade Israelis and Palestinians to turn the lull into a negotiated truce.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Powell Rebuffed on Choice  The White House has overruled Secretary of State Colin L. Powell on his choice to head an important refugee bureau at the State Department, Alan Kreczko, and has instead insisted on John M. Klink, who represents the Vatican's diplomatic mission at the United Nations.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell began a weeklong visit to Africa with a stop in one of West Africa's zones of stability, Mali, a fledgling democracy that welcomed him enthusiastically.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Diplomatic Mission to Congo  Twelve Security Council ambassadors visiting Congo and neighboring countries to encourage a peaceful resolution of Africa's widest war are finding positive developments across the region, said the leader of the group, Ambassador Jean-David Levitte of France.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Cardinals' Meeting in Rome  The four-day gathering of cardinals to discuss the future of the Roman Catholic Church wound down, with some calls for more openness, power-sharing and frank discussion at the top of the church.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>New Feud in House of Windsor  Prince Charles is so upset at reports that his father, Prince Philip, regards him as delicate, wasteful and unlikely to be an effective king that he has scrapped plans to write a warm tribute for his father's gala 80th birthday next month.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Father's Essays Put Son in Jail  The Chinese government, in an effort to control political views on the Internet, has detained Hu Dalin, a man whose only apparent trespass was to help his father maintain a Web site featuring the father's obscure, left-wing writings.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-27</p>
        <p>Expected G.O.P. Defection Sparks Turmoil in Capitol  Senator James M. Jeffords of Vermont told aides that he would leave the Republican Party and become an independent, a move that would vault Democrats into control of the Senate and complicate President Bush's effort to gain approval of his legislative agenda and judicial nominees. Mr. Jeffords scheduled an announcement for today. Republicans feverishly sought to dissuade him.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Senate Passes Tax Cut  The Senate approved a sweeping, $1.3 trillion tax-cut bill containing all the main elements that President Bush proposed. The vote was 62 to 38, with 12 Democrats joining all 50 Republicans in favor. House and Senate negotiators immediately began meeting to reconcile differences between their respective bills.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Religious Plan Wanes  Senators spearheading President Bush's initiative to finance social programs of religious charities said they were indefinitely delaying the legislation, citing an array of factors that had dampened support.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Ashcroft Enters Gun Debate  Attorney General John Ashcroft, writing to an N.R.A. lobbyist, said the Constitution protects the right of individuals to keep and bear firearms. That view appeared to conflict with a 1939 Supreme Court opinion and with eight years of Justice Department policy under Janet Reno.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Labor Forms Retiree Lobby  The A.F.L.-C.I.O. said it had formed the Alliance for Retired Americans, an advocacy group of 2.5 million retired union members that labor leaders hope will add a powerful new liberal voice on Social Security, Medicare and many other issues.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Deadly Journey Out of Mexico  Twelve illegal immigrants died in the Arizona desert after crossing the border from Mexico, and rescuers were searching for others who might be stranded in temperatures that climbed as high as 115 degrees, the Border Patrol said.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Broad Support for School Bill  The House overwhelmingly passed a bill to reshape the government's role in education by requiring states to conduct annual math and reading tests for students in grades 3 to 8 and holding accountable those schools that fail to make progress.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK\REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Sharpton and 3 Others Are Jailed for Navy Protests  A federal judge in San Juan sent the Rev. Al Sharpton to jail for 90 days and ordered three prominent Puerto Rican politicians from New York to serve 40 days, all for misdemeanor trespassing charges involving protests near the Navy bombing range on Vieques island. Each will seek immediate release pending appeal.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bid to Aid Pregnant Immigrants  State lawmakers and others, reacting to a federal appeals court ruling limiting Medicaid benefits to women in the United States illegally, studied options for restoring medical coverage by using only state money.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Child Welfare Agency Plans  Nicholas Scoppetta, the commissioner of the city's Administration for Children's Services, unveiled a five-year child welfare plan and stepped up efforts to secure permanent status for his revamped agency.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE\HEALTH</p>
        <p>Disputing the Placebo Effect  Danish researchers say an analysis of medical studies found no support for the notion that a third of patients generally improve if they are given a dummy pill and told it is real.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Caution on Transplants Urged  The use of healthy people as organ donors for adults who need livers is expanding too quickly and without adequate study, a medical ethicist and two liver surgeons wrote in the New England Journal of Medicine.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Anti-Greenhouse Plan Doubted  Two studies challenged the idea that planting forests could be a cheap way to absorb emissions of carbon dioxide, the main heat-trapping gas released by human activities.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>An Image of Shakespeare  A Canadian claiming an ancestral link to 17th Century English theater has roiled the world of Shakespeare scholarship with a 1603 portrait of a coy man of 39 bearing a full head of hair and a Mona Lisa smile.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Streamlining at Bowman  Bowman Capital, one of the nation's largest hedge fund groups, is shutting the $2 billion Bowman Technology fund, which declined 22 percent this year, and will return more than $1 billion in cash to investors.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Confusion on Hybrid Tax Credit  Car dealers, buyers and even the I.R.S. expressed confusion over whether there was already a tax credit of the sort proposed by Vice President Dick Cheney last week for vehicles powered mainly by electricity.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Technology Stocks Step Back  The Nasdaq, which had six straight days of gains, dropped 70.37 points, or 3 percent, to 2,243.48. The Dow fell 151.73 points, or 1.4 percent, to 11,105.51, and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 20.33 points, or 1.6 percent, to 1,289.05. Analysts cited profit-taking.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Shoe Designer Pleads Guilty  Steven Madden, 44, the designer and retailer of footwear for young women and the founder of the company that bears his name, pleaded guilty to federal charges of securities fraud and money-laundering.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: If Mr. Jeffords jumps; Kerouac on the block; flacking for Governor Pataki.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  Weather</p>
        <p>D9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
