<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doctors Say Artificial-Heart Patient Is Improving</title>
    <meta content="Y17HEA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/17/health/17HEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1310076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Artificial Heart</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Louisville</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDE1E3BF934A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doctors Say Artificial-Heart Patient Is Improving</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Doctors See Improvements in Artificial-Heart Patient</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky., July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Doctors report unidentified man who recently became first recipient of self-contained artificial heart has positive mental outlook and has shown some signs of improvement; say he remains on ventilator and has only minor complications (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The unidentified man who became the first recipient of a self-contained artificial heart two weeks ago has a positive mental outlook and has shown some signs of improvement, his surgeons said here today.</p>
        <p>But the man, who received the AbioCor device on July 2, remains on a ventilator because he becomes tired while breathing on his own, and he has experienced minor complications like bleeding into his stomach, the surgeons said. They attributed the man's extreme weakness to the severe malnourishment and inactivity brought on by his months experiencing end-stage heart failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The man who became the first recipient of a self-contained artificial heart two weeks ago has shown some signs of improvement</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The unidentified man who became the first recipient of a self-contained artificial heart two weeks ago has a positive mental outlook and has shown some signs of improvement, his surgeons said here today.</p>
        <p>But the man, who received the AbioCor device on July 2, remains on a ventilator because he becomes tired while breathing on his own, and he has experienced minor complications like bleeding into his stomach, the surgeons said. They attributed the man's extreme weakness to the severe malnourishment and inactivity brought on by his months experiencing end-stage heart failure.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the surgeons expressed cautious optimism at a news conference about the man's long-term recovery. They said the man's course so far was similar to that of other patients who ultimately recovered after receiving a different kind of heart-assist device.</p>
        <p>As for the AbioCor device, the surgeons said, it appears to have functioned flawlessly in the 1.5 million times it has beat in the man.</p>
        <p>In the months before the implant, the man lost about 60 pounds from his normal weight of 200 pounds, surgeons said. People with end-stage heart failure commonly lose the energy to eat and the ability to digest.</p>
        <p>Although the man has sat in a chair since the implant, he has not walked and ''he does not have the energy to function normally,'' said Dr. Laman A. Gray Jr., one of the surgeons who implanted the device at Jewish Hospital.</p>
        <p>''He is extremely sick, has been, and he is going to be sick for a very, very long time,'' Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Malnourishment is the man's chief problem, ''and it will not be corrected in days or weeks, but months,'' Dr. Gray said in an interview. He added,  ''If we could fix it, the guy would walk out of the hospital.''</p>
        <p>To help make that a reality, the doctors are now feeding the man 2,600 calories a day through a tube, and he seems to be responding. ''As he regains calories, his energy will return to normal'' because the weakness is not permanent, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>A blood test shows the severity of malnutrition; the man's albumin level, a measure of protein in the body, is 2.1 compared with a normal level of 3.6, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray and his partner, Dr. Robert D. Dowling, said the man had a type of lung problem known as interstitial edema that they attributed to the malnutrition. Otherwise, they said, tests show that the man's lungs are exchanging oxygen and carbon dioxide well. The man's liver function is near normal, and a blood test for creatinine, a standard measure of kidney function, shows improvement to 2.2 today compared with about 3 before the implant, the doctors said. A normal creatinine is less than about 1, and the man's lowest creatinine in the last two years was 1.9 as his kidneys also failed.</p>
        <p>''We're very encouraged by'' the improved kidney function and by tests that have shown no evidence of a stroke or other neurological abnormality, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Debilitating strokes plagued recipients of the Jarvik-7 artificial heart when it was tested in the 1980's. The strokes resulted from blood clots that formed in the Jarvik-7.</p>
        <p>To prevent such clots, the man is receiving heparin and other anticoagulant drugs. But determining the amount of such medication has been difficult, Dr. Gray said. The doctors have started and stopped heparin because the man bled around the implanted device and in his stomach. But Dr. Dowling said the stomach bleeding was a common problem after major surgery.</p>
        <p>The man has received an unspecified number of blood transfusions. But tests have shown no evidence that the AbioCor has chewed up many red cells, a problem with some previous artificial hearts.</p>
        <p>The AbioCor is much quieter than the Jarvik-7 and ventricular assist devices and makes a soft swishing sound as it beats, Dr. Gray said. The man's AbioCor is pumping about seven liters a minute, in the range of a normal heart's but four times the amount the patient's failing heart could pump before the implant.</p>
        <p>The man's temperature is normal and cultures have shown no evidence of infection so far, Dr. Dowling said. He also said that during the day, physical therapists encourage the man to squeeze a rubber ball and lift 1 1/2-pound weights to regain strength in his arms and legs.</p>
        <p>Earlier, the man was disconnected from a ventilator for brief periods but had to be reconnected. ''We probably took him off a little prematurely because we were enthusiastic and things were going well,'' Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Now Dr. Gray said he expected that the man would probably stay on a ventilator for another two weeks or so. To improve the man's comfort and allow him to get up in that period, Dr. Gray said, surgeons might soon cut a hole in the man's windpipe (a tracheotomy) to avoid keeping a breathing tube in his throat.</p>
        <p>The risk of keeping a breathing tube in place is a narrowing of the windpipe. But performing a tracheotomy increases the risk of the man's developing a dangerous type of infection known as mediastinitis.</p>
        <p>Jewish Hospital held the news conference after it and Abiomed, the maker of the device, were criticized by leading ethicists and cardiologists for putting a clamp on news about the patient. The doctors and hospital officials were reluctant to discuss details of the financial arrangements for the man's medical care. Dr. Gray said Abiomed and Jewish Hospital were paying the costs, without any input from health insurance policies, but in proportions that he did not know. No Abiomed representative spoke at the news conference.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
