<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats See Gold in Environment</title>
    <meta content="22ENVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/22/politics/22ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Princeton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Massachusetts</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Colorado</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Princeton</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">elmendorf</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Campaign Committee</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congressional Committee</org>
        <org class="online_producer">international Kyoto</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Gallup Poll</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Inslee, Jay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lake, Celinda</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDC1130F931A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats See Gold in Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional Democrats have found rallying cry and gone on offensive against Pres Bush for early environmental rollbacks; concerted public relations campaign, amplified in television advertising by environmental advocacy groups, is expected to reach crescendo on Apr 22, 31st anniversary of Earth Day; Democrats with eye on 2002 House and Senate elections say several of Bush's environmental actions and proposals have given them way to appeal to swing voters who will matter most: suburban mothers and independents whom Bush courted with his emphasis on education (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Let the Bush administration restudy what concentration of arsenic is acceptable in drinking water. One thing is clear: the issue has been very good for Democrats.</p>
        <p>After three months of uncertainty over where to draw bright lines of opposition, Congressional Democrats have found a rallying cry and gone on the offensive against President Bush for early environmental rollbacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Let the Bush administration restudy what concentration of arsenic is acceptable in drinking water. One thing is clear: the issue has been very good for Democrats.</p>
        <p>After three months of uncertainty over where to draw bright lines of opposition, Congressional Democrats have found a rallying cry and gone on the offensive against President Bush for early environmental rollbacks.</p>
        <p>Throughout the Congressional recess, Democrats, from the party's  presidential hopefuls to the most politically vulnerable House members, have struck the same themes, trying to use Mr. Bush's actions -- including the decision to delay carrying out the Clinton administration's tougher arsenic standard -- to undercut the president's image with moderates.</p>
        <p>It is a concerted public relations campaign, amplified in television advertising by environmental advocacy groups, that is expected to reach a crescendo on Sunday, the 31st anniversary of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>Some of the publicity is intended to put pressure on Republican moderates in Congress to help defeat such Bush efforts as his call to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil and gas exploration.</p>
        <p>But Democrats also have their eye on 2002, when control of the House and Senate is at stake. And gleeful party strategists say Mr. Bush has given them a way to appeal to the swing voters who will matter most: the suburban mothers and independents whom Mr. Bush courted with his emphasis on education .</p>
        <p>''Republicans did make some progress in the last cycle in talking like Democrats,'' said James M. Jordan, the executive director of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee. ''This is an issue where we can get some clear, obvious, verifiable separation from the Republicans,'' Mr. Jordan said.</p>
        <p>The Democratic assault has been building for weeks.</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, a possible presidential contender, told the Colorado Democratic Party late last month, ''It is hard to accept that the Supreme Court has given us an administration that is content to allow one in every 100 Americans with certainty to get cancer from drinking water they have a right to believe is safe.''</p>
        <p>Representative Jay Inslee of Washington plans to remind runners racing on Sunday to protest global warming that Mr. Bush has reversed himself on a pledge to regulate carbon dioxide emissions. ''It's stunning to me how rapidly the president has caused folks in suburban areas to focus on this issue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And ground zero in the environmental wars may have been the pump house of a closed arsenic-plagued well in Hopewell Borough, N.J., where Representatives Rush D. Holt and Frank Pallone Jr. spoke out on Wednesday against the arsenic rule rollback.</p>
        <p>The well, after all, is in a swing state, not just any swing state but the home state of former Gov. Christie Whitman of New Jersey, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency. And it is in Mr. Holt's Congressional district -- one of the most competitive House districts in the nation, encompassing Princeton University, new office complexes, farmland and suburban sprawl.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holt, a former assistant director of the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, said he considered the environment and related concerns about suburban sprawl and open space part of a cluster of issues that had helped him prevail in an area long considered safely Republican.</p>
        <p>And he said his constituents, including many Republicans, had taken notice of events in Washington.  ''Arsenic,'' he said. ''That hit a nerve because arsenic sounds like poison.'' He added that a number of people who had voted for Mr. Bush had told him, ''If I had known,'' or ''I should have known.''</p>
        <p>And on Wednesday, he was stoking those sentiments at a news conference, expounding on arsenic. ''When the old standards were devised years ago, no one knew about the cancer-causing effects of arsenic,'' he told reporters. ''They only knew about acute arsenic poisoning.''</p>
        <p>Republican strategists say that issues like tax cuts, education and energy will prove more important to voters in the long run than the environment, and that in those districts where environmental concerns run high, moderate Republicans will have voting records that suit their constituents</p>
        <p>''I think where it really matters, the Republicans won't cede the issue,'' said Jim McLaughlin, a pollster for the National Republican Congressional Committee.</p>
        <p>The White House has also moved fast to try to repair any political damage from a string of actions in March that included the rejection of the international Kyoto treaty on global warming.</p>
        <p>Every day this week, senior administration officials participated in showy White House announcements to soften the president's environmental image. In rapid succession, Mr. Bush agreed to Clinton administration regulations on wetlands preservation and allowed Clinton rules on lead emissions to go forward.</p>
        <p>The administration said it would sign a treaty negotiated in the Clinton presidency phasing out persistent toxic chemicals that are already banned in many developed nations. And Ms. Whitman indicated the administration would eventually toughen arsenic rules after further study.</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, a deputy assistant to the president, said that over time,  ''Americans will say that this president has taken a very reasonable way'' on the environment. ''The president is committed to funding programs that work and making sure local stakeholders have a voice in the process,'' he said. ''That is a departure from some on the left who would prefer that everything be controlled and dictated out of Washington.''</p>
        <p>Democrats are not relenting. Senator Barbara Boxer of California simply dismissed the week's White House announcements. ''What he did this week was nothing,'' she said. ''He didn't overturn a regulation on lead. That's hardly a clarion call on the environment when you don't repeal something.''</p>
        <p>One question is whether the environment really galvanizes voters. Steve Elmendorf, chief of staff to Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House Democratic leader, says the environment works better as a campaign theme ''when voters who care about these issues feel they are threatened.''</p>
        <p>The Gallup Poll, in a survey taken for Earth Day, found the environment ranks 16th on Americans' list of most important problems facing the country today. But it is their top concern for 25 years from now.</p>
        <p>Celinda Lake, a Democratic pollster who recently briefed Senate Democratic aides on her findings, said that the issue appealed most to independents, and that it resonated most particularly when it was tied to the idea of favors for special interests. ''They're antipolitical feelings as well as pro-environment feelings,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
