<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: How Many Miles Per Gallon?; It's Easy: Add Safety, Mileage, Pollution. Divide by Dollars.</title>
    <meta content="29BRAD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/29/weekinreview/29BRAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="How Many Miles Per Gallon?"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Sciences</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC123DF93AA15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: How Many Miles Per Gallon?; It's Easy: Add Safety, Mileage, Pollution. Divide by Dollars.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Add Safety, Mileage, Pollution. Divide by Dollars.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on National Academy of Sciences report that recommends higher fuel-economy standards, plays down safety concerns related to SUVs and gives little heed to Detroit industry's interests; photo; complex interplay of issues discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a panel of the National Academy of Sciences was asked a decade ago to assess federal fuel-economy regulations, it warned that higher gas-mileage standards for cars would make the nation's roads less safe and threaten the financial survival of Detroit's automakers and their workers.</p>
        <p>But a new panel of the same academy has drafted a completely different report this summer, recommending higher standards, playing down most safety concerns and giving little heed to Detroit's interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new report is still likely to create problems for the auto industry when the House takes up legislation this week to raise fuel-economy standards</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a panel of the National Academy of Sciences was asked a decade ago to assess federal fuel-economy regulations, it warned that higher gas-mileage standards for cars would make the nation's roads less safe and threaten the financial survival of Detroit's automakers and their workers.</p>
        <p>But a new panel of the same academy has drafted a completely different report this summer, recommending higher standards, playing down most safety concerns and giving little heed to Detroit's interests.</p>
        <p>The report is due to be made public on Monday, and while some of its language has been toned down after industry lobbyists objected to a draft copy that was leaked July 17, the final document is still likely to create problems for the industry when the House takes up legislation this week to raise fuel-economy standards.</p>
        <p>The report -- and the industry's objections to the first draft -- present an object lesson in the trade-offs facing politicians and auto executives alike. Deciding how many miles a family vehicle should get to a gallon of gasoline affects the environment, public safety, the economy, the nation's trade deficit and even national security -- to the extent that America's dependence on imported oil influences its policies in the Mideast.</p>
        <p>The findings of this year's panel show how much perceptions of the trade-offs have changed over the last ten years.</p>
        <p>For example, a decade ago global warming had barely begun to be seen as an automotive issue, but the new report cites global warming as the single most important reason for regulating the fuel economy of new vehicles. When a car engine burns gasoline, it is basically combining carbon from the gasoline with oxygen from the air coming through the grille, producing a remarkable 19.5 pounds of carbon dioxide, an important global-warming gas, for each gallon of gasoline consumed. A full-sized sport utility vehicle belches nearly 11 tons of carbon dioxide a year, almost twice as much as the midsized cars that have long dominated the American road.</p>
        <p>The automotive safety debate has also been transformed since the last report was written in 1991 (and released in 1992). It focused on research suggesting that when automakers reduced the size of cars in the early 1980's to improve gas mileage, the lighter cars provided less protection for occupants during crashes, with deadly results.</p>
        <p>But the report paid little attention to sport utility vehicles, even though lenient gas-mileage rules for the tall vehicles were already contributing to soaring sales. It briefly mentioned that research was needed to determine whether the taller vehicles were exacting a heavy toll in crashes with cars. And the report predicted that the problem of rollover crashes of sport utility vehicles would be solved by new rules that federal regulators had just drafted.</p>
        <p>The new report takes a much more complex look at safety, with an emphasis on S.U.V.'s and other so-called light trucks, although the final version has been softened somewhat following industry objections. It mentions that lighter vehicles provide less protection, but looks at other problems at the same time.</p>
        <p>The rollover regulations drafted in 1992 were never put into force; automakers complained that they were so strict that they would essentially outlaw S.U.V.'s. Insurers warn, however, that lighter sport utility vehicles are the most likely to roll over, so higher mileage standards for them might actually increase the rollover problem.</p>
        <p>A study last month by a Transportation Department researcher found that as the percentage of light trucks on the roads increases, traffic deaths also rise. Light trucks have higher death rates than cars in single-vehicle crashes, but do nothing to make multiple-vehicle crashes less deadly (though they do tend to shift the deaths in multivehicle crashes to car occupants).</p>
        <p>The question now is how Congress will balance issues like safety and global warming with consumer choice. Americans have been telling pollsters for years that they want better fuel economy. But upper-income families increasingly dominate the market for new vehicles, especially sport utility vehicles. (Middle-class families now tend to buy reliable late-model cars coming off leases instead.) And upper-income families consistently tell the auto industry's market researchers that gas mileage ranks no higher among vehicle attributes than the quality of the carpets.</p>
        <p>THE interplay of all these issues is so complex that, while this year's panel recommends that mileage standards be raised and provides statistics on what increases are feasible, it has steered clear of recommending specific increases in mileage standards, saying that must be left to elected officials.</p>
        <p>Paul R. Portney, the economist who is the panel's chairman, said that it might cost $800 to substantially increase the fuel economy of a new car or sport utility with better engine technology, money many consumers might rather spend on making their vehicle fancier. And no scientific panel, he said, should be expected to decide how to balance consumer choice with all the other issues involved in fuel economy.</p>
        <p>How Many Miles Per Gallon?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
