<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interior Dept. Halting Plan For Grizzlies In 2 States</title>
    <meta content="Y21BEA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/21/science/21BEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Idaho</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interior Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norton, Gale (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Montana (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Interior Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DE1630F932A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interior Dept. Halting Plan For Grizzlies In 2 States</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interior Department abandons Clinton administration plan to reintroduce grizzly bears into isolated wilds of Idaho and Montana to help threatened species toward recovery; Interior Sec Gale A Norton defers to concerns in West, where plan was highly controversial, and in particular to lawsuit by State of Idaho; says while she is fully committed to recovery of bears, threatened species in lower 48 states where they have been driven off 98 percent of their range, building support from state leaders is important element in any such undertaking; supporters of Clinton plan score decision as potentially backward step for bears; say it seems to reflect lack of commitment to requirement under Endangered Species Act that calls for government to play active role in promoting bears' recovery; department's reversal of other Clinton administration environmental policies noted; Clinton plan called for release of 25 grizzlies over five years, beginning in summer 2002, in Bitterroot wilderness of central Idaho and western Montana (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Interior Department said today that it was abandoning a Clinton administration plan to reintroduce grizzly bears into the isolated wilds of Idaho and Montana, in what was to have been a bid to help grizzlies, a threatened species, toward recovery.</p>
        <p>The plan had been highly controversial in the West, and the decision by Interior Secretary Gale A. Norton comes in deference to those concerns, in particular to a lawsuit by the State of Idaho. Gov. Dirk Kempthorne of Idaho, a Republican, sharply attacked the plan for what he called ''massive, flesh-eating carnivores.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Interior Department said today that it was abandoning a Clinton administration plan to reintroduce grizzly bears into the isolated wilds of Idaho and Montana, in what was to have been a bid to help grizzlies, a threatened species, toward recovery.</p>
        <p>The plan had been highly controversial in the West, and the decision by Interior Secretary Gale A. Norton comes in deference to those concerns, in particular to a lawsuit by the State of Idaho. Gov. Dirk Kempthorne of Idaho, a Republican, sharply attacked the plan for what he called ''massive, flesh-eating carnivores.''</p>
        <p>In a written statement tonight, Ms. Norton pronounced herself ''fully committed'' to the recovery of the bears, a threatened species in the lower 48 states, where they have been driven off 98 percent of their range. But, she added, ''Building support from state leaders is an important element to any potential partnership of this size and scope.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the Clinton plan said Ms. Norton's reversal could be a step backward for the bears and seemed to reflect a lack of commitment to requirements under the Endangered Species Act that call for the government to play an active role in promoting those species' recovery.</p>
        <p>''Secretary Norton is essentially allowing a governor to veto a major conservation initiative in a way that undermines the Endangered Species Act and that sets a very dangerous precedent,'' said Jamie Clark, who headed the Fish and Wildlife Service in the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>The decision is the latest in a series of reversals of Clinton-era environmental policies. Among other steps, the new administration has ended American support for the international treaty on climate change, has said it will review new standards for arsenic in drinking water, and has made clear its intention to scale back a plan to put about one-third of the national forests off limits to development.</p>
        <p>In 1995 and 1996, the Clinton administration pushed through another controversial plan, the reintroduction of gray wolves to central Idaho and in Yellowstone National Park, which is now widely seen as a success. But President Bush promised before the election to be sensitive to local sentiment, particularly in the intermountain West, a region that felt slighted by Mr. Clinton and his team and has long been a solid base of Republican political support.</p>
        <p>The Clinton plan called for the release of 25 grizzlies over five years, beginning next summer, in the Bitterroot wilderness of central Idaho and western Montana. The last grizzly there was shot in the 1950's, and the area is regarded by wildlife biologists as prime range for grizzlies, which weigh 300 to 800 pounds.</p>
        <p>The plan to reintroduce the bears had been assembled over the last seven years in negotiations between state, federal and local officials, conservationists, timber industry representatives and other interested parties. It was approved by the wildlife service last November, with the service's grizzly bear coordinator, Chris Servheen, saying it ''maximizes the probability that grizzlies will be around in 100, 200, 300 years.''</p>
        <p>But the idea of reintroduction had always raised hackles in communities like Dixie, Idaho, and Hamilton, Mont., on the fringes of the wilderness areas. Some have also voiced worries about potential dangers to hikers and others in the back country. Timber companies and state officials in Idaho have also expressed concerns that reintroducing the bears could lead to restrictions on their own use of state and federal forests.</p>
        <p>Governor Kempthorne filed suit to block the plan in January, in Federal District Court here, saying the plan  usurped the state's right to regulate land use and interfered with its duty to protect its citizens.</p>
        <p>There are now about 1,100 grizzly bears in the lower 48 states, in Montana, Idaho, Wyoming and Washington. This compares with about 50,000 believed to have lived there before European settlement.</p>
        <p>In its announcement today, the Interior Department said the wildlife service intended now to ''concentrate recovery efforts and resources'' on the existing grizzly bear populations, including the largest, in the Yellowstone area and in the area of Glacier National Park.</p>
        <p>Technically, the decision will be cast in terms of a new proposal by the wildlife service for the grizzly bear recovery plan, and the public will have 60 days to comment on the proposal before a final decision is reached. But administration officials said they saw the issue as settled, and conservationists said the withdrawal of administration support for the plan meant it was dead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
