<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Center Is Round-the-Clock Guard for Chemical Threats</title>
    <meta content="29TRUC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/29/national/29TRUC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: CHEMICAL HAZARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Halons (Chemical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chemical Transportation Emergency Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DD173DF93AA1575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Center Is Round-the-Clock Guard for Chemical Threats</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Center Is Round-the-Clock Guard for Chemical Threats</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chemical Transportation Emergency Center in Washington, a kind of 911 line for chemical questions, takes two calls on Sept 11 attacks, one from New York City officials about several large cylinders of Freon that were found at World Trade Center site and another about origin of tank of Halon found in Pentagon wreckage; Halon is used in airplanes and in buildings as fire suppressant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the nation on edge about whether terrorists' next attack will be chemical, a chemical industry emergency center here is, as always, staffed around the clock. But it is already focused on the chemical hazards at the World Trade Center and the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>The Chemical Transportation Emergency Center, set up 30 years ago as a kind of 911 line for chemical questions, has taken two calls on the Sept. 11 attacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chemical Transportation Emergency Center, set up 30 years ago as a kind of 911 line for chemical questions, has taken two calls on the Sept. 11 attacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the nation on edge about whether terrorists' next attack will be chemical, a chemical industry emergency center here is, as always, staffed around the clock. But it is already focused on the chemical hazards at the World Trade Center and the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>The Chemical Transportation Emergency Center, set up 30 years ago as a kind of 911 line for chemical questions, has taken two calls on the Sept. 11 attacks.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the New York City Police Hazardous Materials Team called to say that officers had found several large cylinders filled with Freon, which is used in air conditioning systems, in an area that was still smoldering, according to the chemical center, known as Chemtrec. Freon, although it damages the earth's ozone layer, is not toxic and does not burn, but the police were concerned about whether the heat could break it  down into something more dangerous.</p>
        <p>That was at 11:50 a.m.; by 12:03 p.m., the center had contacted DuPont, which makes Freon, and shortly after, DuPont spoke to the police. DuPont said they were right to worry; Freon breaks down into two poisons, hydrofluoric acid and hydrochloric acid. The center followed up with DuPont 90 minutes later to determine that the company had advised the team on what precautions to take.</p>
        <p>A few days earlier, investigators had called seeking the origin of a tank of Halon, used on airplanes and in buildings as a fire suppressant, that they found in the wreckage at the Pentagon; was it from the Boeing 767 that hit the building, or from the Pentagon itself? The center did not answer the question, but found a company to sample the material and determine its origin.</p>
        <p>Now, with reports that federal authorities have arrested 20 men who may have fraudulently sought driver's licenses to transport hazardous materials, the center is preparing for calls that might come from a chemical attack.</p>
        <p>It is what Carl Reynolds, the managing director of Chemtrec, calls the third leg of the triad of counter-terrorism; not prevention or discovery, but response.</p>
        <p>With thousands of chemicals in common use around the country, and with emergency personnel and even managers of industrial plants not knowing their precise composition or characteristics, Chemtrec has emerged as a quick point of contact, matching firefighters with chemists and emergency room doctors with highly specialized toxicologists.</p>
        <p>''We run the gamut here,'' said Tom Flores, a recently retired firefighter and paramedic from Fairfax County, Va., who answers calls. If called upon to determine what the proper remedial step would be in the event of attack, said Mr. Flores, ''I'm pretty confident we can handle it.''</p>
        <p>Two to four ''communicators'' answer Chemtrec's phones around the clock. Each desk has three phones; black ones, which are normally the only ones to ring; white ones, which connect if the local system that runs the black ones should fail; and red phones that are connected to a different long-distance carrier, in case the carrier serving the red and black ones goes down.</p>
        <p>Each workstation is connected to a computer system with data on thousands of chemicals, and that data is updated each workday to a laptop that each communicator takes home at night; the whole set-up is duplicated in backup locations in case of a problem at the main office. Lately, executives have asked that the location of the main office not be precisely described.</p>
        <p>Even without the threat of terrorism, Chemtrec has a growing workload. When the American Chemistry Council founded Chemtrec in 1971, partly to stave off government regulation, it took in 8,000 calls a year; last year there were 78,400.</p>
        <p>The classic emergency call here is from a police officer or firefighter who is watching an overturned tanker truck burn, its driver dead or unconscious, its shipping manifest missing and its hazardous materials placard, required by the Department of Transportation, burned beyond recognition. If the emergency worker can identify the company that owns the truck, Chemtrec can track  down the carrier and then the shipper. If all that is available is the truck's license plate, it will call the state police from that state.</p>
        <p>The center was founded by a handful of chemical companies including Pfizer, Eli Lilly, Quaker Oats Chemical Division and Elizabeth Arden; now it has more than 20,000 member companies.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: CHEMICAL HAZARDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
