<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain and Lieberman Urge Emission Limit</title>
    <meta content="Y04MCC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/04/politics/04MCCA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <person class="online_producer">McCain, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E6D9133CF937A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain and Lieberman Urge Emission Limit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">McCain and Lieberman Urge Emission Limit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sens John McCain and Joseph I Lieberman join forces to warn that nation's isolation from global warming pact could hurt American businesses as well as environment and say they want to guide nation toward limits on greenhouse gases; two would set limits on carbon dioxide emissions, much like those Pres Bush rejected; administration officials say they are working on position on global warming but have not made commitment to present proposal at next international meeting on subject, in Oct (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of President Bush's onetime and possibly future political rivals joined forces today to warn that the nation's isolation from a global warming pact could hurt American businesses as well as the environment and said that they wanted to guide the nation toward limits on greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The two, Senators John McCain, Republican of Arizona, and Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, said the United States should set  limits on carbon dioxide emissions, much like those Mr. Bush rejected. They also said they would work with all sectors of industry to develop such a plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senators John McCain and Joseph I. Lieberman warned that the nation's isolation from a global warming pact could hurt business as well as the environment</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two of President Bush's onetime and possibly future political rivals joined forces today to warn that the nation's isolation from a global warming pact could hurt American businesses as well as the environment and said that they wanted to guide the nation toward limits on greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The two, Senators John McCain, Republican of Arizona, and Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, said the United States should set  limits on carbon dioxide emissions, much like those Mr. Bush rejected. They also said they would work with all sectors of industry to develop such a plan.</p>
        <p>''Voluntary programs unfortunately do not work,'' Mr. Lieberman said.</p>
        <p>Businesses, Mr. McCain said, ''are increasingly recognizing that purely voluntary approaches will not be enough'' to stop global warming. ''It is time to take action,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's comments were an unusually explicit endorsement of controls and a break with Republican orthodoxy, although Mr. McCain  sought to underscore the political viability of his argument by citing an editorial in The Wall Street Journal that advocated the same thing.</p>
        <p>Senator Lieberman, who ran for vice president on the Democratic ticket against Mr. Bush, said, ''I have been extremely troubled by the failure of our government to engage on this crucial issue.''</p>
        <p>The joint statement, placed in the Congressional Record as the Senate left town today for the August recess, was the third sign this week of growing bipartisan sentiment in the Senate that the Bush administration erred in rejecting a global climate accord.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the Senate Foreign Relations Committee unanimously approved a nonbinding resolution that called on the administration to develop a plan to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and get involved in international negotiations. On Thursday, the Senate Governmental Affairs Committee unanimously approved a bipartisan resolution to establish a White House office dedicated to developing a national strategy on climate change within a year and to spend nearly $5 billion over the next 10 years to develop technology to control global warming.</p>
        <p>Today's comments from Senators McCain and Lieberman suggest the political power that both parties sense in the issue.</p>
        <p>The approach they called for would enforce a nationwide limit on emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases that mainstream scientists have warned are warming the earth's atmosphere. Companies that emit these gases, mainly when they burn fossil fuels, would be able to buy and sell emissions permits, an approach called ''cap-and-trade'' that reward those who find cheap ways to control pollution.</p>
        <p>Companies could also earn and trade credits for actions like growing trees, which remove carbon dioxide from the air, and could trade permits and credits internationally under the Kyoto Protocol, the agreement to fight global warming that Mr. Bush rejected.</p>
        <p>Fred Krupp, executive director of Environmental Defense, said, ''To have two senators like John McCain and Joe Lieberman joining across the aisle to say that voluntary methods haven't been enough and that they're going to work to develop a comprehensive cap-and-trade system is very significant.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials have said they are working on a position on global warming but have not made a commitment to present a proposal at the next international meeting on the subject, in October.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
