<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Stadium With an Aura All Its Own</title>
    <meta content="30ARAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/30/sports/baseball/30ARAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DC1430F933A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Stadium With an Aura All Its Own</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Stadium With an Aura</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses aura of Yankee Stadium as New York Yankees prepare for Game 3 of World Series against Arizona Diamondbacks down 0-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years ago this month, the Yankees returned home from Cincinnati, down two games in the World Series on their way to being swept. It was 1976 and Yankee Stadium, remodeled and reopened that very season, was back after a 12-year absence in the World Series business.</p>
        <p>''For me, as a young player in my first World Series, I remember it feeling so different from anything during the regular season and even in the playoffs against Kansas City,'' Willie Randolph said yesterday in the doorway of the coaches' room in the Yankees' clubhouse. ''Everything felt different. It even smelled different. There was that fall crispness. In fact, I remember it was cold, really cold. These last few years, October doesn't seem as cold as it did back then.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It didn't feel much like fall in Phoenix and it was hard to tap into karma at a place called the Bob. On Tuesday night, though, the Series returns to the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years ago this month, the Yankees returned home from Cincinnati, down two games in the World Series on their way to being swept. It was 1976 and Yankee Stadium, remodeled and reopened that very season, was back after a 12-year absence in the World Series business.</p>
        <p>''For me, as a young player in my first World Series, I remember it feeling so different from anything during the regular season and even in the playoffs against Kansas City,'' Willie Randolph said yesterday in the doorway of the coaches' room in the Yankees' clubhouse. ''Everything felt different. It even smelled different. There was that fall crispness. In fact, I remember it was cold, really cold. These last few years, October doesn't seem as cold as it did back then.''</p>
        <p>Global warming hit the Bronx, and maybe Randolph's chilled memory has something to do with wintry tingles running down the spine of a rookie second baseman getting his baptism of Fall Classic fire against the Big Red Machine of Morgan and Bench, of Perez and Rose.</p>
        <p>History instructs us that the Yankees used that Series as a learning tool, acquiring more power and ego in the person of Reggie Jackson and beating the Dodgers the next two years. Since 1996, Randolph has added four championship rings to his collection as the Yankees' third-base coach. He has spent most of a quarter-century in pinstripes after a childhood in Brooklyn, a Mets fan conditioned in the early 1960's to believe that the World Series had the permanent address of Bronx, N.Y., much like kids around these parts now.</p>
        <p>He and the Yankees came home early yesterday morning after a couple of nights in Phoenix that, for Randolph, were virtual nights off. He sent one runner home to score against Curt Shilling and none against Randy Johnson in Games 1 and 2 of the 2001 World Series. The Yankees looked as overmatched in the Arizona desert at the Bank One Ballpark -- one of those new luxury-laden, tax-funded fun houses -- against the Diamondbacks as they did against the Reds in 1976.</p>
        <p>Tonight, as they attempt to make this a series, the Yankees play their last ace, and we're not talking about their Game 3 starter, Roger Clemens. Tonight the scene shifts to a cooler place, weather-wise and otherwise. Tonight they play the World Series at Yankee Stadium, where, as Manager Joe Torre said yesterday, ''you really feel it.''</p>
        <p>Forgive these Yankee bluebloods, for they cannot help themselves. To them, Yankee Stadium is to the World Series what Harvard is to academia. Even Randolph, who made it to the Series with the Oakland A's in 1990 against Paul O'Neill and another Cincinnati team, admitted to his wife, Gretchen: it didn't feel much like fall in Phoenix and he just couldn't tap into Classic karma at a place called the Bob.</p>
        <p>''It was noisy and the park is beautiful but, I don't know, it didn't feel the same,'' he said. ''I can't really explain why. It's just a special feeling I've always gotten when we play a World Series game at home.''</p>
        <p>For obvious reasons, Yankee Stadium will be more fortified than ever tonight. In terms of public address pollution, it sure is a lot louder than in 1976 when, after a two-year renovation, the Stadium was hailed as a modernized monument to itself. Otherwise, Yankee Stadium hasn't changed; only the expectations of George Steinbrenner, who has alternately been lobbying and threatening New York City for a new park, preferably in Manhattan, in order to maximize his earning potential.</p>
        <p>With four championships in five years, soaring attendance and ticket prices and mammoth television deals, Steinbrenner deserves no sports owner welfare. A Metro-North Stadium stop? For sure. Improved parking and ramp access? Why not? A few more luxury boxes? Go ahead, keep up with the Joneses and Jacobses. But after Sept. 11, with the hole in the city's downtown skyline still smoldering, who is going to so much as dare suggest we pull down yet another New York City landmark for more leg room and a couple of sushi bar concession stands?</p>
        <p>More than ever we ought to understand why Major League Baseball should be preserved in the Bronx and realize that Yankee Stadium is even more entwined with New York culture than it is with the World Series. As Randolph said, it's about connecting the years, about familiar sights and smell.</p>
        <p>The Stadium itself will not beat Arizona tonight. The night will be chilly, though. The feelings will be old. ''I'll know where I am when I step out there,'' Randolph said. He'll be at home in the World Series, at Yankee Stadium, Bronx, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
