<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frustrated Europeans Set to Battle U.S. on Climate</title>
    <meta content="Y16CLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/16/science/16CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1309852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto (Japan)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D9103BF935A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frustrated Europeans Set to Battle U.S. on Climate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Frustrated Europeans Set to Battle U.S. on Climate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>ESCHWEILER, Germany, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US and Europe will face off as principal antagonists in Bonn, Germany, on July 16 at talks over Kyoto Protocol to combat global warming; representatives from 170 nations will make last-ditch effort to salvage treaty in face of US opposition, that has all but scuttled it; mood toward US among Europeans is one of anger and bewilderment, with European Union showing unusual display of solidarity among 15 members; Europeans insist treaty is crucial to preventing catastrophe; hope to persuade Japan to ratify it; Japanese leaders explicitly say they will not do so if US remains opposed; Pres Bush's outright rejection of accord, arguing that it would place unfair burden on US economy and excuse developing countries from obligations, noted; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This used to be a gritty and dirty little town, surrounded by coal mines and factories and overshadowed by a power plant that spewed soot everywhere.</p>
        <p>But as representatives from more than 170 nations meet in Bonn Monday to begin last-ditch talks to save a treaty to combat global warming, this town provides one tiny slice of the anger and bewilderment that people across Europe now feel toward the United States, whose opposition has all but scuttled the accord.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beginning Monday, the United States and the European Union will face off as the principal antagonists over the climate treaty, called the Kyoto Protocol</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This used to be a gritty and dirty little town, surrounded by coal mines and factories and overshadowed by a power plant that spewed soot everywhere.</p>
        <p>But as representatives from more than 170 nations meet in Bonn Monday to begin last-ditch talks to save a treaty to combat global warming, this town provides one tiny slice of the anger and bewilderment that people across Europe now feel toward the United States, whose opposition has all but scuttled the accord.</p>
        <p>Almost nobody here complains that environmental regulations are killing jobs. Instead, they point with relief to the elaborate filters that have cleaned up the power plant's exhaust. They hike beneath windmills that now provide the city with supplemental electricity.</p>
        <p>And like almost all Germans today, they meticulously sort their garbage for recycling: paper, glass, plastic packaging, aluminum cans and plastic bottles.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to the United States, which produces 25 percent of the world's greenhouse gases, they express incomprehension.</p>
        <p>''It seems to me that the only thing American politicians care about is money,'' said Heinz Kutschker, a retired electrician, as he hiked through the woods here. ''You have one country that is telling everybody else what to do, without any concern for what it means for our grandchildren.''</p>
        <p>For up to two weeks beginning Monday, the United States and the European Union face off as the principal antagonists over the climate treaty, called the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>Saying it would place an unfair burden on the American economy and excuse developing countries from obligations, President Bush has flatly rejected the accord, which would require industrialized countries to sharply reduce their emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>The European Union, in an unusual display of solidarity among its 15 members, insists that the treaty is crucial to preventing catastrophe. And in what increasingly looks like a doomed effort, they are trying to save it.</p>
        <p>To do that, they must persuade Japan to ratify the treaty. But Japanese leaders have almost explicitly said they will not do so if the United States is not on board.</p>
        <p>And the United States has repeated that it has no intention of changing its mind. ''We very much appreciate that others are reaching out to the United States and are thinking of ways of engaging us, but we do truly believe the protocol is fundamentally flawed,'' said Paula J. Dobriansky, the under secretary of state for global affairs and leader of the American delegation heading to Bonn. ''We will not be coming back to the protocol.''</p>
        <p>European leaders are furious, charging that the United States has not only undermined the treaty by rejecting it but also tried to kill it by persuading others to back away.</p>
        <p>''Why should we let the least ambitious countries define the pace and the content?'' said Margot Wallstrom, the European Union's commissioner in charge of environmental issues. ''It is important to show the public that we can reach an agreement, even without the United States.''</p>
        <p>That may be easier said than done. The treaty can come into force only if 55 countries ratify it, including a group responsible for at least 55 percent of the 1990 emissions from industrialized countries. But if the world's two biggest economies fail to ratify, the treaty is doomed.</p>
        <p>For Europeans, that prospect has stoked frustration and anger in ordinary citizens as well as political leaders.</p>
        <p>At a time when Europeans increasingly embrace American notions of open markets and shareholder capitalism, attitudes on environmental issues and energy by political leaders and the public appear starkly different from those in the United States.</p>
        <p>And not just in Germany. Denmark imposes a staggering minimum registration tax of 105 percent on new cars. Most countries impose heavy taxes on gasoline, which make it three times as expensive as in the United States. Intense recycling is now common in most countries.</p>
        <p>''We have in the European community a consensus in favor of climate protection,'' said Jürgen Trittin, Germany's minister of the environment and a member of the Green Party. ''It is not just a Green position,'' he added. ''It goes across the political spectrum, from conservative to liberals.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trittin has evidence to back him up. In a recent survey by Emnid, a polling company, 86 percent of Germans said that Chancellor Gerhard Schröder should demand that President Bush adhere to the support for the Kyoto accord pledged three years ago by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>But even in the United States, there appears to be a broad gap between Mr. Bush's position and that of the public. A recent New York Times/CBS News Poll found that 72 percent of the public believed that it was necessary to take immediate steps to counter global warming, with more than half saying that the United States should abide by the Kyoto accord.</p>
        <p>But even as they are remarkably unified in their approach to fighting the United States, European leaders and industry groups are still wrestling among themselves over scores of internal issues.</p>
        <p>The European Union under the Kyoto accord has pledged to reduce its emissions to 8 percent below the levels in 1990. To meet that target, the 15 member countries have hammered out a plan that leaves countries with different burdens, and not everyone is happy about it.</p>
        <p>Germany, Europe's biggest economy by far, is expected to reduce its emissions by 21 percent. The Netherlands, by contrast, is supposed to cut its emissions by 6 percent. And Portugal, which is trying to catch up to its wealthier neighbors, is actually allowed to increase its emissions.</p>
        <p>This has left German industry leaders fuming that they have to shoulder too much of Europe's overall burden. They also argue that their burden is disproportionate because the plan does not rely heavily enough on reductions in automobile traffic or household-generated emissions.</p>
        <p>''Our problem is not with the Kyoto Protocol,'' said Joachim Hein, the top environmental policy expert at the German Federation of Industry. ''What bothers us is that, within the European Union, German industry is being held responsible for so much of the reduction.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trittin worries about that as well. ''One thing we want to avoid is that European countries harshly criticize the 'bad guys' on the other side of the Atlantic, the people in the White House, but then behind that criticism essentially behave the same way,'' he said. ''That cannot be in Germany's interest, or in the interest of Great Britain.''</p>
        <p>There have also been fights within the European Union about the best way to accomplish reductions, like the use of ''emissions trading'' that would allow countries to acquire pollution credits from countries that have room to increase emissions.</p>
        <p>The disagreements are such that last month the European Commission was forced to shelve a plan to start emissions-trading because European manufacturers and power companies opposed a part of the plan that would have imposed absolute limits on total emissions.</p>
        <p>There is also argument over how much credit should be given for forest lands that can serve as carbon-absorbing ''sinks.'' In particular, Russia, which is not a European Union member, is hoping to cash in these sinks by selling emission credits to Western companies.</p>
        <p>But those battles are mainly within Europe. For all the uncertainties, European leaders have shown little disagreement about how to confront the United States.</p>
        <p>In an interview at her office in Brussels last week, Ms. Wallstrom said Europe was ready to offer Japan sweeteners that would make its own targets easier to reach. She also suggested that the United States was trying to sabotage the treaty by persuading Japan not to sign it.</p>
        <p>''They are putting pretty heavy pressure on their partners,'' Ms. Wallstrom said, but added that the United States had promised not to ''obstruct'' the Bonn negotiations.</p>
        <p>Some European industrial companies are openly calling on the United States to support the Kyoto Protocol. Earlier this month, Germany's Federation of Chemical Industry, which includes conglomerates like BASF A.G. and Bayer A.G., urged the United States to rejoin the process.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wallstrom, Europe's commissioner for the environment, who is Swedish, captured the difference between American and European attitudes toward tougher rules.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it is too difficult for American politicians,'' she mused. ''Is it possible for political leaders in the U.S. to say you can't have two or three cars or that you can't drive to the post office box?''</p>
        <p>In Eschweiler, which is in the Ruhr Valley and the heart of heavy industry, Mayor Rudolf Bertram said he had seen a profound transformation during the past 20 years.</p>
        <p>''Twenty years ago, this city didn't have anybody who dealt with environmental issues,'' he said. ''Today, we have a whole department and they get involved in everything -- construction, industrial development, noise abatement.''</p>
        <p>Recycling is mandatory, and residents have to sort their waste into at least four categories. Indeed, Germany's ''green dot'' program for recycling paper and plastic packaging has become a $2 billion enterprise.</p>
        <p>''But what has changed even more intensively is the attitudes of the people,'' Mr. Bertram said. ''They want something done for environmental protection, and they know environmental protection doesn't stop at the border.''</p>
        <p>Peter Hüllen, a retired coal-mine engineer, hardly considers himself a radical environmentalist. But as he hiked through the woods, he found it hard to hold back his bewilderment about the United States.</p>
        <p>''How much do the Americans really know about climate problems?'' he asked. ''Do they know anything about these issues? Do they have any interest in them? What are they thinking?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
