<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>150th Anniversary: 1851-2001; When Newspapers Were Newsmakers</title>
    <meta content="20WILF$20" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Special Section" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/14/specials/onefifty/20WILF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1342999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Into the Wild"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bennett, James Gordon Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ochs, Adolph S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0DF1F38F937A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>150th Anniversary: 1851-2001; When Newspapers Were Newsmakers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Newspapers Were Newsmakers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I MAKE news,'' boasted James Gordon Bennett Jr. He was full of himself, as usual. But make news he did, with deep pockets and commanding zeal. As owner of The New York Herald after the Civil War, Bennett would not wait for news to just happen. He dispatched reporters far and wide with orders to send back sensational copy of adventure and discovery, anything to capture the essence of a time of expanding horizons and, not incidentally, to win readers away from the competition.</p>
        <p>It was what editors did in the rough-and-tumble of journalism when The New-York Times was striving to secure a foothold: when they went out of their way to ''make'' news, the papers became participants in what they were reporting. The practice continues to this day, though rarely with the showmanship of a Bennett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In journalism's rough-and-tumble days, The Times looked for its own adventures, even in Loch Ness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I MAKE news,'' boasted James Gordon Bennett Jr. He was full of himself, as usual. But make news he did, with deep pockets and commanding zeal. As owner of The New York Herald after the Civil War, Bennett would not wait for news to just happen. He dispatched reporters far and wide with orders to send back sensational copy of adventure and discovery, anything to capture the essence of a time of expanding horizons and, not incidentally, to win readers away from the competition.</p>
        <p>It was what editors did in the rough-and-tumble of journalism when The New-York Times was striving to secure a foothold: when they went out of their way to ''make'' news, the papers became participants in what they were reporting. The practice continues to this day, though rarely with the showmanship of a Bennett.</p>
        <p>Only purists with blinkers would argue that journalists do not have an impact on the news they write about -- or that they could avoid it. A decision to cover one thing and not another makes news of one and non-news of the other.</p>
        <p>Over time, The Times found its own niche. It made news, but in a way that proved adaptable to the changes in exploration and adventure brought about by advances in science, aviation and technology.</p>
        <p>No paper, of course, could have matched Bennett's first and greatest exploit. In 1869, a century before the moon landings, he summoned a reporter, Henry M. Stanley, and ordered him, ''Find Livingstone.'' For three years, there had been no direct word from David Livingstone, the British missionary lost in deepest Africa.</p>
        <p>Stanley, heading a search party, became the leading participant in the story. When he finally found his man in 1871, it was his own words -- not anything the missionary said -- that left an indelible mark: ''Dr. Livingstone, I presume?''</p>
        <p>Near the end of the 19th century, another titan of journalism, William Randolph Hearst,  whipped up a frenzy of support for war with Spain over Cuba and deployed his crack correspondent, Richard Harding Davis, and the artist Frederic Remington to Havana to file on the first shots. But Washington and Madrid seemed less eager for combat than Hearst. After a long wait, Remington cabled: ''There is no trouble here. There will be no war. Wish to return.'' To which the bellicose Hearst supposedly responded: ''Please remain. You furnish the pictures and I'll furnish the war.''</p>
        <p>Whether or not Hearst actually used those words, they were in the spirit of the man and of journalism in those years. This may not be how journalists see themselves today, but that was not the last time they took an active role in the dialogue of war, politics or domestic security. Think of The Washington Post bringing down a president with its Watergate reporting, or The Times (followed by The Washington Post), in defiance of White House pressure, publishing the Pentagon Papers on the conduct of the war in Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>In the last decades of the 19th century, The Times remained for the most part on the sidelines as the more colorful press engaged in journalistic adventuring. The paper had emerged from the Civil War with a reputation for sober, thorough reporting. The paper's one serious foray into Bennett-style adventurism was a series of exclusive accounts by an Army explorer in Alaska in 1886, billed as ''The Times' Alaska Expedition.'' But this paled in comparison with Bennett's three-year search about the same time for remnants of the ill-fated John Franklin expedition in northern Canada.</p>
        <p>The appeal of the remote unexplored corners of the world eventually drew The Times into the game of expedition exclusives with increasing vigor and success. The man largely responsible was Carr Van Anda, the managing editor in the early 20th century and a gifted mathematician fascinated with science and exploration.</p>
        <p>With the backing of his publisher, Adolph S. Ochs, Van Anda lined up, over 25 years, the polar explorers Robert E. Peary and Richard E. Byrd, as well as the aviator Charles A. Lindbergh. In the 1930's, editors signed up William Beebe for the report of his descent in a bathysphere to the seafloor, and Auguste Piccard for the account of his balloon ascent into the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>The paper's practice was not to mount its own expeditions, but if someone had organized and secured substantial financing for a project, then The Times would invest modestly in return for exclusive rights to publish a first-person account. The paper was not so much making news as collaborating in spreading it.</p>
        <p>In the first of these arrangements, Peary accepted the paper's offer of $4,000 for New York rights to an account of his 1909 expedition, trumpeted as the ''discovery of the North Pole.'' His first message, triumphant if not necessarily quite accurate, was sent part of the way by wireless, itself a notable achievement.</p>
        <p>The Flipper in the Loch</p>
        <p>Aviation was the rage in the 20's, and Times reporters kept busy with accounts of record-setting flights and disastrous failures. Byrd's flight in 1926 with Floyd Bennett, to a point close to the North Pole if not actually over it, was described in another Times exclusive. When Lindbergh made his trans-Atlantic flight to Paris from Long Island, The Times had a $5,000 contract for his own detailed story.</p>
        <p>The reporter as adventurer, in the Stanley mold, lives only in memory. The Spirit of St. Louis rests in the Smithsonian, and Paris is only a drink, meal and movie away on a jumbo jet. Scientists and reporters, even tourists, regularly fly in and out of Antarctica. A man in California recently paid for a trip to the International Space Station. Where are the sensations of yesteryear?</p>
        <p>There is, of course, the occasional throwback. In 1976, an editor on the foreign desk of The Times read an article of mine about a picture purporting to show the flipper of a large creature in Loch Ness, Scotland. In an earlier time, the editor said, a newspaper would send an expedition to find Nessie. So began what became known as the New York Times Loch Ness Expedition.</p>
        <p>Waste no time seeking parallels between this and Stanley's search for Livingstone. The pier from which we put out in boats to sweep the deep waters with sonar and the little house where we monitored video from submerged cameras were just down the road from a comfortable hotel with a well-stocked pub, where the Nessie legend was refueled nightly. Every few days I transmitted an article filled with the excitement of anticipated discovery, but Nessie was a no-show. Still, The Times and I had made news. Reporters descended on the lochside village, and where there is a critical mass of journalists, there is news.</p>
        <p>On returning from Scotland, I covered the spacecraft landings on Mars, where Martian microbes proved as elusive as Nessie. Here was an example of the new exploration. Only governments can afford expeditions into space and investigations of cosmic origins, and all but a few ventures to the poles and the seafloor. These are national and international endeavors, driven by science and a perceived political and economic need to be at the front of modern technology.</p>
        <p>In exploration today, no publication can buy exclusive rights to a government project. Yet reporters are still making news, though with a difference. For science journalists in particular, the difference is in bringing research from the lab and the field to the front page, rescuing it from obscurity in language accessible to the public.</p>
        <p>This may not match finding Livingstone, but the implications can be greater. The Times has taken a leading role in this type of journalism, from the time of Van Anda through the introduction of the weekly Science Times in 1978. At Van Anda's instigation, the reporter Alva Johnston spent three days in 1922 at a wide-ranging science conference, listening to reports, interviewing scientists and writing a number of well-informed articles about research that probably would not otherwise have reached public attention. They were exclusives because no reporter had before deemed such science to be news. Johnston was the first science reporter to win a Pulitzer Prize.</p>
        <p>In the late 30's, William L. Laurence, a Times science reporter, put two and two together and came so close to recognizing the possibilities of an atomic bomb that in the midst of World War II the government asked that he be detached from the newspaper for a secret assignment. Laurence was given the only inside story of the Manhattan Project, on the condition that nothing be published until the bomb had been dropped.</p>
        <p>Walter Sullivan once wrote an article about the first detection of radiation from the birth of the universe in the Big Bang; the scientists themselves later said they had not fully appreciated the significance of their research until they read the report in The Times.</p>
        <p>So it is today, with issues like cloning, genome mapping, clinical trials for drugs, global warming and prospects for biological warfare -- subjects already in the news but crying out for interpretation on a newsmaking scale. Every science reporter here fields calls from bewildered but pleased scientists whose research has been the subject of a Times article. They have been besieged for days with requests for other newspaper and magazine interviews, television appearances and sometimes book contracts. That's making news, reverberating news, today's way.</p>
        <p>Into the Wild John Noble Wilford is a senior science writer for The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Noble Wilford is a senior science writer for The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
