<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Detroit May Face Pressure To Reduce Carbon Dioxide</title>
    <meta content="Y16AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/16/business/16AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Michigan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DaimlerChrysler AG</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Halliburton Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Abraham, Spencer</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D7173DF935A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Detroit May Face Pressure To Reduce Carbon Dioxide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, March 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's decision not to regulate carbon dioxide emissions by electric utilities is mixed blessing for automakers, which oppose any regulation of such emissions, which are linked to global warming; administration is expected to find itself under even more pressure from environmentalists to reduce such emissions from automobiles since administration has decided not to regulate such emissions by electric utilties industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's decision this week not to regulate carbon dioxide emissions by electric utilities is a mixed blessing for automakers, which oppose any regulation of such emissions.</p>
        <p>Automakers have been increasingly alarmed by public attention to carbon dioxide, a gas linked to global warming. Whether carbon dioxide emissions from electric utilities should be regulated has implications for a far more politically acrimonious issue: federal fuel-economy regulations for new automobiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's decision this week not to regulate carbon dioxide emissions by electric utilities is a mixed blessing for automakers, which oppose any regulation of such emissions.</p>
        <p>Automakers have been increasingly alarmed by public attention to carbon dioxide, a gas linked to global warming. Whether carbon dioxide emissions from electric utilities should be regulated has implications for a far more politically acrimonious issue: federal fuel-economy regulations for new automobiles.</p>
        <p>Automobile engines produce almost 20 pounds of carbon dioxide for each gallon of gasoline they burn. The catalytic converters in cars slightly increase these emissions, by turning dangerous carbon monoxide in engine exhaust into yet more carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>In deciding not to regulate electric utilities' emissions, President Bush questioned the scientific research that has tied man-made carbon dioxide emissions to global warming. Automakers have also questioned the research.</p>
        <p>But having told electric utilities that their carbon dioxide emissions will not be regulated, the administration will find itself under even more pressure from environmentalists to reduce such emissions from automobiles to address global warming concerns, said Dan Becker, the energy policy director at the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>Josephine Cooper, the president of the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, a Washington-based trade group, said that the auto industry had been watching the electric utilities' issue closely but had not weighed in. ''Clearly, it is an issue that resonates with our members,'' she said, adding that the automakers did not support any increase in the gas mileage requirements currently set by federal law.</p>
        <p>Each automaker is required to produce cars that get an average of 27.5 miles a gallon. Light trucks -- sport utility vehicles, minivans and pickups -- must get an average of 20.7 miles a gallon. Overall fuel efficiency has been declining as manufacturers produce more light trucks instead of cars.</p>
        <p>When gasoline prices soared last spring, there was a push for more stringent light truck standards by Democratic and Republican senators from Western states where people drive long distances. In a compromise, the National Academy of Sciences was asked to produce a report, due on July 1.</p>
        <p>Officials at General Motors, Ford Motor and DaimlerChrysler said this week that they had not lobbied on the electric utilities issue. But environmentalists contend that the auto industry did not need to explain its views to top administration officials, some of whom are veterans of the auto and oil industry's battles against fuel-economy regulations over the last quarter of a century.</p>
        <p>Spencer Abraham, the energy secretary, and Vice President Dick Cheney helped persuade President Bush to retreat on Tuesday from a campaign pledge to limit electric utilities' carbon dioxide emissions. Mr. Abraham spent the last six years as a Republican senator from Michigan and opposed global warming initiatives while leading successful efforts to freeze fuel-economy regulations. Mr. Cheney was the chief executive until last year of the Halliburton Company, an oil drilling company.</p>
        <p>As president of the American Automobile Manufacturers Association, and then as G.M.'s top lobbyist until last autumn, Andrew H. Card Jr., now the White House chief of staff, fought Clinton administration initiatives on global warming.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cooper said that she had not tried to lobby Mr. Card because of his previous ties to the auto industry. ''I've tried to maintain decorum and distance from Andy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Transportation-related carbon dioxide emissions increased at a faster rate from 1997 to 1999 than any other large category of emissions, according to the Energy Department. But electric utilities still emit twice as much carbon dioxide as automobiles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
