<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Debates Fate Of Pollution-Control Suits</title>
    <meta content="Y07POL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/07/politics/07POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">null</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED81F38F934A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Debates Fate Of Pollution-Control Suits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration is considering pleas from coal and electric companies to drop series of government lawsuits initiated by Clinton administration to require utilities to install modern pollution controls on old coal-fired power plants; request touches off debate within administration; Christie Whitman, administrator of Environmental Protection Agency, is resisting industry's plea, while Vice Pres Dick Cheney and Energy Sec Spencer Abraham are more sympathetic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration is considering pleas from coal and electric companies to drop a series of government lawsuits initiated by the Clinton administration to require the utilities to install modern pollution controls on old coal-fired power plants.</p>
        <p>The request, which the coal industry says would let it quickly increase its output of power, has touched off a debate within the administration. Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, which initiated the litigation, is resisting the industry's suggestion, while Vice President Dick Cheney and Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham are more sympathetic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration is considering pleas from coal and electric companies to drop a series of government lawsuits initiated by the Clinton administration to require the utilities to install modern pollution controls on old coal-fired power plants.</p>
        <p>The request, which the coal industry says would let it quickly increase its output of power, has touched off a debate within the administration. Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, which initiated the litigation, is resisting the industry's suggestion, while Vice President Dick Cheney and Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham are more sympathetic.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration is determined to increase the nation's use of fossil fuels to produce power in response to what it deems an energy crisis.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman appears in a relatively strong position in this case, since her agency has reached agreements with some of the defendants, while the Bush Justice Department has recently filed court documents strongly defending the agency's stance.</p>
        <p>As governor of New Jersey, Mrs. Whitman had joined some of the E.P.A.'s suits, most of which were brought against plants in the Midwest and South with pollutants that drifted to the East Coast.</p>
        <p>The coal industry says that the Environmental Protection Agency's enforcement of the Clean Air Act is preventing investments that would generate tens of thousands of megawatts of electricity from existing coal-fired plants and that the cost of new pollution controls would have to be paid by consumers.</p>
        <p>''There is a recognition that plants aren't modernizing because the burden is too onerous,'' a White House official said today.</p>
        <p>Discussions in the administration about the lawsuits have intensified in recent days, with many of the talks taking place in Mr. Cheney's office as the White House completes the report by his energy task force, which is to be printed Monday night.</p>
        <p>''The coal industry is pushing very hard to lock this in and make it part of the report,'' said an environmentalist who has been following the case closely.</p>
        <p>Some administration officials said the report might sidestep the environmental controversy and instead include a broad recommendation to overhaul how plants are treated.</p>
        <p>The administration is especially concerned with what signals it sends the industry on how it will handle the regulatory process. ''Most of industry wants a commitment out of the administration to reform the review process,'' said an administration official.</p>
        <p>At stake are emissions that would cost millions of dollars to control and that account for a significant share of the nation's air pollution.</p>
        <p>In court papers filed in February  against the Tennessee Valley Authority, government lawyers said: ''The coal-fired electric utility industry as a whole remains by far the nation's largest industrial-sector polluter, in 1998 emitting approximately one quarter of all nitrogen oxides and two-thirds of all sulfur dioxide emissions in this country.''</p>
        <p>Since 1988, the E.P.A. has sued 11 companies over controls at 49 power plants.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act exempted many older plants from strict emissions controls but required modern controls when owners modified plants in ways that increased emissions.</p>
        <p>For years, the agency says, plants evaded the requirements by insisting that certain modifications were merely ''routine maintenance.'' But the agency found that a number of major electric utilities had been modernizing their plants with projects that increased emissions.</p>
        <p>The National Coal Council, a federally chartered advisory group made up mainly of industry officials, argues in a report delivered to the administration that the agency's tough new stance on enforcement ''has had a direct and chilling effect on all maintenance and efficiency improvements.''</p>
        <p>If the administration dropped these lawsuits and otherwise softened regulations, the council argues, coal-fired plants could provide an increased capacity of 40,000 megawatts within three years, almost twice the capacity of all new power plants built last year, and 5 percent of the total generating capacity available nationwide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
