<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dick Cheney, Energy Czar</title>
    <meta content="14MON1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/14/opinion/14MON1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cnn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD7163AF937A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dick Cheney, Energy Czar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial criticizes Bush administration's energy policies, notably Vice Pres Dick's Cheney's downplaying of conservation and his insistence that only way to address energy shortage is to move more aggressively to increase supplies with more exploration and building of new infrastructure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soaring gasoline prices have landed President Bush in the middle of a political storm, and to some extent he has only himself to blame. Mr. Bush did not cause gas prices to rise, any more than President Bill Clinton did when prices jumped above $2 a gallon last summer. As with Mr. Clinton, there is little he can do in the short term to bring prices down. However, he set himself up, but good, for the lashing he is getting from the Democrats.</p>
        <p>First, he instructed Vice President Dick Cheney, a fellow oilman, to develop a national energy strategy, thus adding to Mr. Cheney's growing portfolio of important tasks. Mr. Cheney then plunged into three months of secret meetings reminiscent of Hillary Clinton's closed-door plotting on health care, and embarked on a series of tough-guy speeches in which he derided conservationists as virtuous wimps and said that only a strategy weighted toward extraction could meet the nation's energy needs. Add to all this the oil industry's huge contributions to Mr. Bush's campaign, and it has not been difficult for the Democrats to portray the president as a captive of big oil and an enemy of the little guy at the pump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soaring gasoline prices have landed President Bush in the middle of a political storm, and to some extent he has only himself to blame. Mr. Bush did not cause gas prices to rise, any more than President Bill Clinton did when prices jumped above $2 a gallon last summer. As with Mr. Clinton, there is little he can do in the short term to bring prices down. However, he set himself up, but good, for the lashing he is getting from the Democrats.</p>
        <p>First, he instructed Vice President Dick Cheney, a fellow oilman, to develop a national energy strategy, thus adding to Mr. Cheney's growing portfolio of important tasks. Mr. Cheney then plunged into three months of secret meetings reminiscent of Hillary Clinton's closed-door plotting on health care, and embarked on a series of tough-guy speeches in which he derided conservationists as virtuous wimps and said that only a strategy weighted toward extraction could meet the nation's energy needs. Add to all this the oil industry's huge contributions to Mr. Bush's campaign, and it has not been difficult for the Democrats to portray the president as a captive of big oil and an enemy of the little guy at the pump.</p>
        <p>One ironic element here is that Americans  might not be nearly as traumatized by gas prices if Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney had not spent so much time scaring them about the country's energy future. Mr. Bush is constantly engaging in careless talk about how ''we're running out of energy,'' while Mr. Cheney has been forecasting a bleak future unless we start punching holes in the Arctic tundra and building 1,300 power plants. Little wonder, then, that when a spike in gas prices occurred, some people saw it as confirmation of the very apocalypse the Bush team has been predicting.</p>
        <p>In addition, the administration seems to have largely ignored the curative forces of the marketplace, which even now may be working to increase supplies and stabilize prices of both natural gas and gasoline. The rise in natural gas prices over the last few years, for example, has more than tripled the number of drilling rigs in operation, and this in turn is likely to alleviate the shortages that underlie the administration's calls for urgent government action.</p>
        <p>Market forces also explain the recent spike in prices at the gas pump. Mr. Cheney attributes the spike to industry's failure to build any new refineries for 25 years. A more important reason is industry's failure to anticipate changes in American buying habits. When Americans were buying smaller, more fuel-efficient cars in the 1970's and 80's, oil refining became a depressed business, and refiners made only incremental additions to capacity. When Americans turned to S.U.V.'s and other gas-guzzlers in the 90's, refiners were caught short.</p>
        <p>Expanding refining capacity and upgrading pipelines will, in time, get more gasoline to market and help lower prices at the pump. But the larger, more important lesson from the current spike in gasoline prices is that conservation and efficiency -- the very responses Mr. Cheney has dismissed -- are in fact vital components of any rational strategy aimed at bringing supply and demand into better balance and thus moderating prices.</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mr. Cheney has been softening his tone a bit, and on CNN last Tuesday he sounded as if he had been up all night reading Al Gore's ''Earth in the Balance.'' He asked the various combatants in the debate to stop stereotyping one another. He all but conceded that improved efficiency had been the cornerstone of America's energy successes since the gasoline shortages of the early 1970's, noting that the American economy had managed to grow fivefold with only a 25 percent increase in energy. He spoke glowingly of how new technologies had made it possible to produce more energy with less pollution. He said the administration would offer tax incentives for renewable energy sources and more fuel-efficient cars, and would at least examine the idea of strengthening fuel economy standards for cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cheney's basic message remained the same. The country, he continued to insist, is in the grips of an energy shortage, and the only sure way to address it is to move aggressively to increase supplies of oil and natural gas, remove impediments to the increased burning of coal and build new infrastructure, including refineries, pipelines and electrical transmission lines. If that is the main message of Mr. Bush's forthcoming energy plan, then the lesson of the current gasoline shortage, that conservation has to be a prominent part of any new policy, will have been missed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
