<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 02-04-01; Here Comes The Sun</title>
    <meta content="WLN091947" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1268029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burdick, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DB1E3FF937A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 02-04-01; Here Comes The Sun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Burdick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burdick, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>here comes the sun*</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I was a kid in upstate New York, I wanted to be a weatherman. I suppose I liked the idea of controlling the elements. Sure, predicting the weather wasn't the same as changing it, but at least I'd know before my friends did when we were going to have a snow day. Also, I liked our local weatherman, a young guy named Al Roker. I liked that his name was my name and that if I joined Big Al's Fan Club (he was big back then too), I'd get a free Celsius-Fahrenheit conversion chart. The way Al presented it, the weather was an anodyne, a salve for the self-inflicted wounds of crime and football.</p>
        <p>Those were the days. In the decades since, the weather has acquired a vaguely sinister cast: more political in nature, more intricate and convoluted. First came acid rain, then nuclear winter (or the threat of it), then the ozone hole, then El Nino -- a pattern generated in part by plankton on the other side of the world. The 1990's brought a dawning awareness that the climate overhead could indeed be altered by the humans below. It was perfect weather for postmodernists: inescapably self-referential, painfully meta.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I was a kid in upstate New York, I wanted to be a weatherman. I suppose I liked the idea of controlling the elements. Sure, predicting the weather wasn't the same as changing it, but at least I'd know before my friends did when we were going to have a snow day. Also, I liked our local weatherman, a young guy named Al Roker. I liked that his name was my name and that if I joined Big Al's Fan Club (he was big back then too), I'd get a free Celsius-Fahrenheit conversion chart. The way Al presented it, the weather was an anodyne, a salve for the self-inflicted wounds of crime and football.</p>
        <p>Those were the days. In the decades since, the weather has acquired a vaguely sinister cast: more political in nature, more intricate and convoluted. First came acid rain, then nuclear winter (or the threat of it), then the ozone hole, then El Nino -- a pattern generated in part by plankton on the other side of the world. The 1990's brought a dawning awareness that the climate overhead could indeed be altered by the humans below. It was perfect weather for postmodernists: inescapably self-referential, painfully meta.</p>
        <p>Maybe every age gets the weather it deserves. No sooner have we arrived (truly) in the third millennium than we have a new brand of weather. It's the biggest, baddest weather so far: space weather. It's like planetwide sunburn. Every day, the Sun blows a steady ''solar wind'' of charged particles. But from time to time, storms on the Sun's surface -- visible to scientists as sunspots, solar flares and those high, looping coronas -- spew extra-big wads of ions. That's space weather. You thought the New Year's snowstorm was bad? Wait till you've been slapped with a coronal mass ejection.</p>
        <p>Actually, our planet's magnetic field shields us from the worst of it. But enough solar ions rain down to wreak havoc on our electronic devices: between 1994 and 1999, space weather caused an estimated $500 million in damage to radio, navigation, telecommunications and other satellites. Space weather also can blow out industrial power grids. (In 1989, it blacked out all of Quebec for several hours.) It's a solar assault on the information age, a stellar kibosh on our global-village designs.</p>
        <p>That assault is raging. The Sun is at the peak of an 11-year cycle of storminess that, thanks to new NASA satellites, is being studied in unprecedented detail. Space weather has a Web site (www.spaceweather.com), calendar real estate (Space Weather Week in May), even a movie deal (''Solarmax,'' playing at an Imax theater near you). Space weather is a celebrity, a true phenomenon.</p>
        <p>Of course, it's not really a new phenomenon. Space weather was always out there, like Antarctica before 1820 or the far side of the moon before 1957. What changed is us. We keep pressing outward, from stratosphere to troposphere to magnetosphere, filling the space with our emissaries: satellites, space stations, the bits and bytes of our transglobal dialogue. With information technology, we've made the atmospheric fringe as integral to our pedestrian lives as the soil our cities are built on. Space weather didn't find us: we found it.</p>
        <p>In effect, space weather is a product of our ego, as well as a check against it. Slowly, we are worming our way into the substance of the universe. Yet, it seems, no matter how big our big ideas get, no matter how advanced our civilization becomes, the elements stay one step ahead of us. Tomorrow's explorers may colonize Mars or plumb the seas on Jupiter's moons. There, no doubt, they will find yet more exotic weather, forces that scientists so far have detected only in the abstract, if at all.</p>
        <p>I take solace in that realization. The past few decades have grown fraught with weather angst. Were the floods in Mozambique induced by global warming or were they an El Nino anomaly? If it's warm in January, can I enjoy the day, or should I fear for future generations? Is the summer too hot; is the winter too cold; is it raining too much or not enough?</p>
        <p>Simply looking out the window prompts a wave of anxiety. And rightly so. For all of our upward, outward mobility, our physical selves are still firmly rooted to the same Earth we sprouted from four million years ago. However far our influence may spread, we aren't going anywhere soon, except maybe to hell in a handbasket; it's about time we dealt with it.</p>
        <p>Still, it is precisely at such moments that we seek relief, something beyond us, some brief opportunity to once again be an unqualified victim of a natural phenomenon rather than its accomplice. A dozen years ago, Bill McKibben declared that we had reached ''the end of nature,'' for even the weather was now marked with the human footprint. Space weather is a welcome, if harsh, reminder to the contrary. Humans may yet be the end-all, but we're still far from the be-all.</p>
        <p>We will, of course, master space weather. We'll never control it (unless we devise a way to disrupt the Sun), but we'll learn to get around it. Until then, I say just sit back and enjoy the show. Isn't that the appeal of an old-fashioned snowstorm, after all? A whiteness descends; silence befalls us; the mad rush is momentarily stilled. Snow is a veil we treasure, a fig leaf we clutch to our naked ambition -- good for a little while, anyway, until the rays of April lay bare our sins once more.</p>
        <p>Alan Burdick is writing a book about nature, to be published next year by Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Burdick is writing a book about nature, to be published next year by Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
