<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford's 70-Year Itch Could Be Relieved; As G.M. Stumbles, Its Perch at the Top Is Within Reach</title>
    <meta content="Y03FOR0AI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/03/business/03FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1290268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0DE1238F930A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2223" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford's 70-Year Itch Could Be Relieved; As G.M. Stumbles, Its Perch at the Top Is Within Reach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co is closing sales gap with General Motors Co, which has been biggest automaker in US and world since 1931, and is expected to become largest automaker in world in next few years; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time Ford Motor was the world's biggest automaker was 1930, when Henry Ford, the founder, was still in charge, the Model A had finally replaced the Model T and Margaret Mitchell was still writing ''Gone With the Wind.''</p>
        <p>General Motors -- led by Alfred P. Sloan Jr., who organized a half-dozen separate car lines under one corporate umbrella and introduced the concept of the annual model change -- surpassed Ford the following year. It remained the nation's largest company, and at times, the world's largest, through most of the rest of the 20th century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time Ford Motor was the world's biggest automaker was 1930, when Henry Ford, the founder, was still in charge, the Model A had finally replaced the Model T and Margaret Mitchell was still writing ''Gone With the Wind.''</p>
        <p>General Motors -- led by Alfred P. Sloan Jr., who organized a half-dozen separate car lines under one corporate umbrella and introduced the concept of the annual model change -- surpassed Ford the following year. It remained the nation's largest company, and at times, the world's largest, through most of the rest of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>But now, to the amazement of many in Motor City, Ford seems increasingly likely to take from G.M. the top spot in the auto industry. Ford came within half a day's sales of passing G.M. in total revenue in the first quarter. And Ford actually surpassed G.M. in automotive revenue, although this was partly because G.M. cut production more deeply than Ford in response to the slowing economy. Many people in the industry expect Ford to edge ahead of G.M. in total revenue and automotive revenue within two or three years.</p>
        <p>The short-term reasons G.M.'s lead is likely to evaporate are simple. G.M. is phasing out its Oldsmobile division and is trying to sell its Hughes Electronics subsidiary or spin it off to shareholders as a separate company.  And Ford will pick up additional sales from its acquisition of Land Rover.</p>
        <p>But G.M.'s lost mastery has much deeper roots: an inability to respond to market trends quickly. G.M. missed the growth of the small-car market in the late 1970's and early 1980's, the move to more aerodynamic midsize cars in the late 1980's and the rise of sport utility vehicles based on pickup truck designs in the 1990's. And now it is stumbling in its response to the popularity of sport utilities based on car designs.</p>
        <p>For most people in the auto industry, the question is no longer if Ford will overtake G.M., but when. ''Their market share is going to continue to decline,'' said Chris Cedergren, the managing director of Nextrend Inc., an automotive consulting company. ''The new generation can't relate to G.M. brands.''</p>
        <p>G.M. executives say that although their share of the United States market has been falling for 22 years, the trend is about to reverse itself. They are pinning their hopes on expanded production of full-size pickup trucks and sport utilities based on pickup designs, and on sport utilities based on car designs that Saturn, Buick and Pontiac will introduce this year and next.</p>
        <p>The executives are nonetheless surprised to find Ford so close behind and gaining fast. ''Most of us didn't anticipate we'd see this, but we have to be careful -- we don't expect these trends will continue,'' said Paul Ballew, G.M.'s executive director of market analysis, whose grandfather was making factory tools in a Chrysler plant here the last time Ford was ahead.</p>
        <p>The most recent setback for G.M. has been in its initial effort to tap into the market for sport utilities based on car designs, like Honda Motor's Honda CR-V and Toyota Motor's Lexus RX 300 and Toyota Highlander. The car-based models offer a smoother ride and better fuel economy than traditional sport utilities. They are also less likely than pickup-based models to inflict major damage on cars during collisions, and they typically emit less of the gases linked to smog and global warming.</p>
        <p>Sales of sport utilities based on car designs have tripled in the last year even as sales of sport utilities based on pickups have dropped 8.5 percent and the overall auto market has fallen 5.7 percent, according to Ward's Auto Info Bank, a market data service in Southfield, Mich.</p>
        <p>G.M. and Ford jumped into the market for car-based sport utilities at almost the same time late last summer, with the Pontiac Aztek and the Ford Escape.</p>
        <p>But the Aztek has been dubbed one of the ugliest automobiles in years by many auto reviewers, and has sold so poorly that G.M. has ordered hundreds of its engineers to start borrowing them from the company fleet so that at least some Aztek would be seen on Detroit roads.</p>
        <p>The Escape is now the best-selling vehicle in the segment by a wide margin, and outsold the Aztek in April by 14,025 to 2,394.</p>
        <p>G.M. also missed the boom in pickup-based sport utilities in the 1990's, particularly full-size models, even though it had been making them longer than any other company, beginning in April 1935 with the Chevrolet Carryall Suburban. When Ford introduced the Expedition in 1996, it swiftly raised production to meet soaring demand. Its Expedition factory in Wayne, Mich., quickly generated more in overall profits than any factory in any industry, reaching an estimated $3.7 billion in pretax profits by 1998.</p>
        <p>Only in the last year, as high gasoline prices, foreign competition and declining consumer interest have begun eroding the profitability of the market segment, has G.M. finally stepped up production significantly.</p>
        <p>Ford led the move to aerodynamic styling in midsize cars in 1986 with the Taurus, which has been one of the nation's best-selling cars ever since. In the late 1970's and early 1980's, Ford paid more attention to attractive designs than G.M., which became so distracted with meeting new safety, emissions and fuel-economy regulations that it produced too many look-alike cars.</p>
        <p>During the two recessions of the early 1980's, some questioned whether Ford could even survive. But because Ford came much closer to the brink of financial collapse then than G.M., the United Automobile Workers union let it lay off or push into retirement tens of thousands of workers, and allowed some restrictive work rules to be rewritten. G.M. was not as aggressive then in cutting its work force, and is only now coming close to matching Ford in factory productivity.</p>
        <p>The decline of G.M. is the fading not just of an automotive giant but of a national institution that once wielded enormous influence. In 1928, when G.M.'s profits and market share were already soaring, there was a huge controversy when John Raskob, the chairman of the finance committee of G.M. board, was elected chairman of the National Democratic Committee and promptly moved its offices into the General Motors Building in New York. In the 1930's, G.M. bought up much of the nation's aircraft manufacturing and airline industries, as well as a big bank, although it has long since sold those investments.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s vast corporate reach gave rise to the myth that one of its presidents, Charles E. Wilson, said in 1953 that ''what's good for General Motors is good for the country.'' Mr. Wilson's actual words to a Senate committee, after he was nominated by President Dwight D. Eisenhower to become defense secretary, were somewhat different.</p>
        <p>Asked by a senator if he could make a decision adverse to G.M.'s interests, Mr. Wilson replied, ''I cannot conceive of one because for years I thought that what was good for our country was good for General Motors, and vice versa.''</p>
        <p>''Our company is too big, it goes with the welfare of the country,'' he added.</p>
        <p>That dominance has gone the way of poodle skirts and outdoor waitresses on roller skates. Because of G.M.'s poor sense of the market, its share of auto sales in the United States has slumped to just 28 percent from 48 percent in 1978.</p>
        <p>Ford has stayed remarkably steady at 23 percent, although partly by investing its profits over the last decade in the outright purchase of Jaguar, Aston Martin, Volvo and Land Rover. This has also raised the average price of Ford's vehicles, increasing total revenue. G.M. has instead purchased minority stakes in Fiat Auto and Fuji Heavy Industries, which makes Subarus, and has increased its minority stakes in Isuzu Motors and Suzuki Motor, but these companies remain independent and G.M. does not count them in its own sales.</p>
        <p>Ford has surpassed G.M. on other criteria, like operating earnings and market capitalization. But in terms of revenue, Ford finished last year with $170.1 billion to G.M.'s $184.6 billion. That gap is closing and Ford will take the lead within the next several years unless G.M. makes a big acquisition or finally stabilizes its market share.</p>
        <p>Last summer, Ford bought Land Rover, which has about $6 billion in annual sales, but only Land Rover's sales from July through December were included in last year's results. At the same time, G.M. plans to phase out its unprofitable Oldsmobile division, with $8 billion in sales, over the next several years. G.M. hopes to hold on to all of these revenues, said Darwin Clark, G.M.'s vice president for dealer relations.</p>
        <p>But auto consultants say that G.M. will lose at least half of Oldsmobile's customers to rivals, so the loss of Oldsmobile could shave perhaps $4 billion from G.M.'s lead. Finally, G.M.'s board approved further talks with the News Corporation to dispose of Hughes Electronics, which had $8.7 billion in revenue last year. Add up these changes and it equals more than enough to wipe out the sales gap with Ford, even without further market-share deterioration by G.M.</p>
        <p>Ford will not catch G.M. in overall sales this year, acknowledged Henry D. G. Wallace, Ford's chief financial officer. Like G.M. executives, Mr. Wallace contended that his priority was profits, not sales.</p>
        <p>''With virtually the same revenues, our profitability was four times what theirs was,'' in the first quarter, Mr. Wallace said, keeping up the old Detroit tradition of chiding rival manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Many in Detroit attribute G.M.'s persistent slowness in coming up with attractive car designs to a corporate culture in which executives are rotated from job to job without ever being punished for failure. By contrast, Ford has had a long history of pushing out unsuccessful managers as part of an often ruthless corporate culture.</p>
        <p>G.M. executives acknowledge the criticism and say that changing the company's bureaucratic mind-set has been a top priority in recent years. ''I don't think we can get done what we have to get done at this company without continued cultural change,'' said John Devine, G.M.'s vice chairman and chief financial officer and a former chief financial officer of Ford.</p>
        <p>But few doubt that G.M. has a long way to go. ''I don't think the G.M. people consider themselves to be a business,'' said Gerald Meyers, a former chairman of American Motors who remains active in the auto industry as a consultant. ''Every G.M. executive I've met has considered himself as part of an institution.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
