<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Names an Environmental Conservation Commissioner</title>
    <meta content="06DEC.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/06/nyregion/06DEC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1275798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Conservation Department (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crotty, Erin M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">erin</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Albany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Troy</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Conservation Committee</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Washington, Val</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DE103BF935A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Names an Environmental Conservation Commissioner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, March 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov George E Pataki names Erin M Crotty, former deputy commissioner who helped devise his policy on toxic waste cleanup, to head State Department of Environmental Conservation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki today named a former deputy commissioner who helped devise his policy on toxic waste cleanup to head the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>If confirmed by the Senate, the former official, Erin M. Crotty, will take over the department in two weeks, succeeding John P. Cahill. She would be the first woman to hold the job. Mr. Cahill, who headed the department for four years, was promoted last month to become a senior policy adviser to the governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki today named a former deputy commissioner who helped devise his policy on toxic waste cleanup to head the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>If confirmed by the Senate, the former official, Erin M. Crotty, will take over the department in two weeks, succeeding John P. Cahill. She would be the first woman to hold the job. Mr. Cahill, who headed the department for four years, was promoted last month to become a senior policy adviser to the governor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crotty is now a lobbyist for Plug Power, a joint venture near Albany that is trying to develop methods of using fossil fuels or hydrogen to produce electricity through a chemical reaction, rather than through combustion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who sees himself as a committed environmentalist, expressed confidence that Ms. Crotty has the expertise to be a fine commissioner. She was his first choice, he said, once he decided to bring Mr. Cahill into his inner circle of advisers.</p>
        <p>''The first person I thought of was this person, but we didn't know if we would be able to entice her back into public service,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Reactions to Ms. Crotty's nomination were mixed among environmentalists and lawmakers. Ms. Crotty headed a group that developed Mr. Pataki's policy on state Superfund sites, which favors weakening cleanup standards for sites that will used by industry in the future. That policy has drawn fire from some environmentalists and Democratic lawmakers who favor keeping stricter standards.</p>
        <p>''The administration has again passed over the environmental community and gone to industry for the head to lead this department,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester County Democrat who heads the Assembly's Environmental Conservation Committee. ''She's the person who ran the attempt to weaken Superfund and to reduce business responsibility to clean up its own mess.''</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists, however, praised Ms. Crotty's grasp of the issues and said she was not a rigid ideologue.</p>
        <p>''I didn't like what came out of the governor's Superfund working group, but I think Erin Crotty is one of a handful of people that really understand the issues,'' said Val Washington, the executive director of Environmental Advocates, a lobbying group. ''I see her as someone who can continue to work on it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Crotty, who is 34 and grew up in Troy, N.Y., said that she agreed with the governor on most issues.</p>
        <p>''The priorities of mine are the priorities of the governor,'' she said. ''My job is to implement them.''</p>
        <p>Before joining Plug Power in October 1999, Ms. Crotty served for two years as a deputy state environmental commissioner in charge of cleaning up contaminated sites and ensuring water quality.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crotty first joined the administration as an aide to the governor's counsel, Michael Finnegan, in 1995. She played an important role in negotiating a historic agreement between New York City and upstate communities that protects the city's watersheds without resorting to a filtration plant. The agreement imposes development restrictions around the reservoirs.</p>
        <p>Before Mr. Pataki's election in 1994, Ms. Crotty worked as a policy analyst for the New York State Senate Commission on Toxic Substances and Hazardous Wastes.</p>
        <p>The Republican-controlled Senate must vote on Ms. Crotty's nomination, , but aides to the majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, said they did not foresee much opposition.</p>
        <p>Among the first issues Ms. Crotty will have to deal with are a proposal to develop industrial wastelands in the cities, the federal government's plan to dredge contaminated soil from the Hudson River and questions surrounding the emergency use of diesel generators to provide power this summer, environmentalists said.</p>
        <p>After the governor announced her nomination at a news conference today, she said her parents were naturalists and anglers. They had instilled in her, she said, a deep commitment to protecting the environment from a young age.</p>
        <p>''This is one of those life-changing moments,'' she said, as she took the podium in front of the cameras.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
