<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watchful Eyes On a Violent Giant</title>
    <meta content="02POPO$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/02/science/02POPO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Popocatepetl Volcano (Mex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Geological Survey, US</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDD123BF931A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watchful Eyes On a Violent Giant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Jan. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Popocatepetl, Mexican volcano that erupted Dec 18, has become world's most elaborately monitored volcano; Mexican scientists and experts from United State Geological Survey's Volcano Disaster Assistance Program worked together to provide early warning; maps; diagram; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Popocatepetl, Mexico's magnificent and mystical 17,945-foot peak, has been called the world's most dangerous volcano. Nearly 30 million people live within view of it, most of them in Mexico City, 40 miles west, and Puebla, 30 miles east.  More than 300,000 people living in the danger zone directly under the volcano regard it as a living thing, a magical man-mountain, a geological god giving rain and rich land. On Dec. 18, when it erupted in what some scientists said was its biggest explosion in a millennium, they came to regard it with a little more fear than awe.</p>
        <p>But they now have more than a little science to mix with their magic. Since 1994, when it awakened from a seven-decade slumber, Popocatepetl (which is pronounced poh-poh-kah-TEH-peh-til and means ''smoking mountain'' in Nahuatl, the indigenous language of Mexico) has become the world's most elaborately monitored volcano. Seismologists, geologists, volcanologists and mathematicians have been watching and recording its every tremor. As a result, scientists were able to predict within hours that it was about to blow on Dec. 18, and officials evacuated more than half of the people in the valleys below.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Popocatepetl, Mexico's magnificent and mystical 17,945-foot peak, has been called the world's most dangerous volcano. Nearly 30 million people live within view of it, most of them in Mexico City, 40 miles west, and Puebla, 30 miles east.  More than 300,000 people living in the danger zone directly under the volcano regard it as a living thing, a magical man-mountain, a geological god giving rain and rich land. On Dec. 18, when it erupted in what some scientists said was its biggest explosion in a millennium, they came to regard it with a little more fear than awe.</p>
        <p>But they now have more than a little science to mix with their magic. Since 1994, when it awakened from a seven-decade slumber, Popocatepetl (which is pronounced poh-poh-kah-TEH-peh-til and means ''smoking mountain'' in Nahuatl, the indigenous language of Mexico) has become the world's most elaborately monitored volcano. Seismologists, geologists, volcanologists and mathematicians have been watching and recording its every tremor. As a result, scientists were able to predict within hours that it was about to blow on Dec. 18, and officials evacuated more than half of the people in the valleys below.</p>
        <p>And therein lies a tale.</p>
        <p>On average, a volcano erupts somewhere about once a week. Ten or 12 eruptions a year have the potential to kill people. Two or three a decade threaten mass death and destruction. And 75 percent of the biggest eruptions in the past two centuries came from volcanoes never known, in human history, to have erupted before.</p>
        <p>Scientists understand a lot about volcanoes. They know the earth has three layers: its dense core, its partly molten mantle and its crust, broken into 16 major tectonic plates, moving almost imperceptibly, a few inches a year.</p>
        <p>And they know that all along the Pacific coast, from Alaska to Chile, the plates that underlie the ocean are scraping under the land. At the edges of these plates, rivers of molten rock, called magma, bubble toward the surface of the earth. Magma that reaches the surface is called lava, and volcanoes are built from accumulated lava, rock, ash and dust. In hot spots along rifts in the plates, the magma can erupt with volcanic force.</p>
        <p>But there is much they do not know about why volcanoes erupt when they do, and as a result volcanoes remain a lethal threat to those who live around them.</p>
        <p>Since May 18, 1980, when Mount St. Helens erupted in Washington State, causing 57 deaths, volcanoes have killed nearly 30,000 people, driven more than one million people from their homes, and caused billions of dollars of damage. More than 25,000 people were killed in 1985, when the Nevado del Ruiz volcano in Colombia erupted after months of restless rumbling, sending rivers of mud and ash called lahars down on the town of Armero.</p>
        <p>The deaths could have been prevented, scientists say, if the volcano's warning signs could have been  detected, analyzed and transmitted in time.</p>
        <p>Volcano monitoring systems do exist. After Mount St. Helens, scientists from the United States Geological Survey began devising portable volcano monitoring instruments that could be set up together in 70-pound early-warning systems. They could chart changes in sulphur dioxide and carbon dioxide in the air, the tilt and temperature of the ground, the most minor earthquakes and tremors, and debris flows that would otherwise go undetected. Transmitters to send the data -- with radio, antenna and a year's power supply -- were packed into nine-gallon steel drums. The system provided a continuous, real-time history of seismic activity.</p>
        <p>The system was originally intended for the Pacific Coast ranges of California, Oregon and Washington, but after Nevado del Ruiz, the United States Office of Foreign Disaster Assistance, an arm of the Agency for International Development, asked the geological survey to set up a global program. The result was the world's only rapid-response team of its kind, the Volcano Disaster Assistance Program.</p>
        <p>''The truth of the matter with volcanoes is that no one knows what will happen next,'' said Dan Miller, a research geologist who is the chief of the program, which has headquarters in Vancouver, Wash. ''Volcanoes are not that consistent and not that well understood. But what happened at Nevado del Ruiz didn't need to have happened.''</p>
        <p>When a volcano becomes active, the team can move quickly (though only when invited by another nation's government, through a formal request to the State Department). It now has worked at 19 volcanoes in 15 nations. Within days, it can install monitoring equipment, detect magma flowing to the surface and forecast eruptions with reasonable accuracy.</p>
        <p>''Forecasting exactly when an eruption will occur is very difficult,'' Dr. Miller said. ''And eruptions can go on for months and even years.''</p>
        <p>When Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines reawakened on April 2, 1991, after lying dormant for more than 500 years, Philippine scientists called in the disaster assistance program to install a monitoring network. The sensors gave clear warning of a catastrophic explosion, which came two months later. By that time, 75,000 people, including 18,000 members of the American military, had been evacuated.</p>
        <p>''We were lucky,'' Dr. Miller said. ''The volcano was threatening big, destructive eruptions and it produced them a few days after the signs were clear and accurately interpreted. Tens of thousands of lives were saved. And the entire effort cost less than $1.5 million.''</p>
        <p>Things went less well at Montserrat, in the British West Indies, in 1995. The team installed its monitoring network at the Soufriere volcano, watched magma moving up to surface and transmitted the danger signs. But it was more than two years before the volcano truly exploded, by which time the force of the warnings had dwindled. At least 19 people died and the capital, Plymouth, was destroyed by lava and ash.</p>
        <p>In December 1994, Popocatepetl, which is geologically similar to the volcanoes in the Cascade Range in Washington and Oregon that the United States geological team knew best, became active with a series of eruptions after lying dormant since 1927.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the National University of Mexico and the National Disaster Prevention Center (known by its Spanish acronym, Cenapred) already had installed four seismic sensing stations on the volcano's flanks. But they asked for help. The result has been, by most volcanologists' accounts, one of the world's best volcano monitoring networks.</p>
        <p>Working together, the Mexican and United States scientists set up a device called a tiltmeter to detect infinitesimal shifts in the slope of the volcano, which becomes swollen when magma rises into it. A tiltmeter works like a carpenter's level, with a bubble in the middle that sets off an electrical impulse when it shifts. The one at Popocatepetl is so sensitive that if you had a 3,000-foot bar of steel, and slipped a nickel under one end, the tiltmeter at the other end would detect it.</p>
        <p>The Mexicans and the United States team installed a special seismometer, an acoustic-flow monitor, that could pick up a small lahar flowing by. They had specially equipped surveyors' rods, enhanced by lasers, to detect bulges in the volcano.</p>
        <p>They deployed other sensors to pick up ground movements along with shifts in gases, electrical and magnetic fields that flow from subterranean movements of magma. They had special detectors to listen for the phenomena called harmonic tremors, earth vibrations set off by moving magma for reasons no one really understands. They also had, it should go without saying, a network of Popocams, or video cameras hooked up to the Internet, watching over the smoking mountain.</p>
        <p>All of this was woven together at Popocatepetl in a system called Earthworm, which allows instant acquisition and sharing of data over the Internet. Two weeks ago, as the volcano began showing signs of a big eruption, Cenapred scientists could sit in a control room on the southern edge of Mexico City and watch it.</p>
        <p>''These guys are operating at the state of the art,'' said Jim Luhr, director of the Smithsonian Institution's Global Volcanism Program.</p>
        <p>But their work would mean nothing if the people who live under the volcano did not get their message or ignored it.</p>
        <p>When a warning goes from Cenapred through radio and television it reaches most of the 217 towns in the danger zone within minutes. And in the 24 towns that radio cannot reach, a satellite telephone alerts local leaders, who ring church bells to sound the alarm.</p>
        <p>Alejandro Rivera Dominguez, a seismologist affiliated with the Center for Disaster Prevention at Puebla University, described the 300,000 people around Popocatepetl as mostly poor, many of them farmers who are especially reluctant to leave their fields and herds behind. To them, he said, the volcano is a sacred symbol that cannot be fathomed by science, a rain god and a giver of good harvests.</p>
        <p>The authorities, he said, have learned to speak and think of Popocatepetl with a more folkloric, more magical language in order to better communicate warnings to the villagers, Mr. Rivera said.</p>
        <p>That may be. For nearly a week before Popocatepetl's spectacular nighttime explosion on Dec. 18, the alarms had gone out from Cenapred to the countryside, the church bells had rung. Thousands heeded the warnings, but thousands resisted, saying they were less fearful of lava and ash than the possibility that soldiers and policemen sent to protect them would loot their homes instead.</p>
        <p>''We've been holding out for a week now,'' said Jose Felipe Pacheco, 26, a farmer from Santiago Xanitzintla, one of the communities closest to the crater, as he left his home reluctantly, under pressure from army officers, more than eight hours after the first huge eruption. ''Our belongings, all that we have, and have earned through such sacrifice -- and to think that we could come back to an empty home, losing  everything you've worked for.</p>
        <p>''Leaving is in my best interest,'' he said. ''But staying is also in my  best interest.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
