<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1350761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DE153FF931A25751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>U.S. to Abandon ABM Pact, Clearing Way for Testing  President Bush will announce this week that Washington will withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty in six months. It would be the first time in modern history that the United States renounced a major international accord, administration officials said. The decision came after Secretary of State Colin L. Powell was unable to bridge differences with Russia's president, Vladimir V. Putin, on an arms control accord.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Poisons in Suicide Bombs  An examination of bomb fragments left by Palestinian suicide bombers at a pedestrian mall in Jerusalem 10 days ago turned up traces of a toxic chemical, perhaps a pesticide or rat poison. There have been six or seven such incidents in the last five years, the police commissioner said.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>U.S. to Abandon ABM Pact, Clearing Way for Testing  President Bush will announce this week that Washington will withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty in six months. It would be the first time in modern history that the United States renounced a major international accord, administration officials said. The decision came after Secretary of State Colin L. Powell was unable to bridge differences with Russia's president, Vladimir V. Putin, on an arms control accord.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Poisons in Suicide Bombs  An examination of bomb fragments left by Palestinian suicide bombers at a pedestrian mall in Jerusalem 10 days ago turned up traces of a toxic chemical, perhaps a pesticide or rat poison. There have been six or seven such incidents in the last five years, the police commissioner said.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Separate Trials for Serb Leader  Slobodan Milosevic appeared before the international war crimes tribunal in The Hague and was told that he would face two separate trials for the crimes of which he stood accused. The unexpected decision was a setback for the chief prosecutor, Carla Del Ponte, who sought one trial for all three indictments she had issued.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Racial Rifts in Britain  A British government report said that whites and ethnic minorities had become deeply divided and were leading separate lives with no social or cultural contact and no sense of belonging to the same nation.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Guilty in Adventurers' Deaths  A Swiss judge convicted six employees of an adventure company of negligent manslaughter in the deaths of 18 tourists and 3 guides in a flash flood in a narrow Alpine gorge during an expedition two years ago.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Italy Will Not Block Warrants  Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi gave in to pressure from critics and said Italy would not, after all, block establishment of a European arrest warrant, which prosecutors consider crucial in fighting terrorism.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-28</p>
        <p>Bush Aide Bemoans Losses Among White Evangelicals  President Bush's top political adviser, Karl Rove, said Republicans did not rally enough religious conservatives to the polls in last year's presidential race, and he suggested that the administration would do more to reach out to those white evangelicals who are among the Republicans' most ardent supporters.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Maneuvering in House  Tom DeLay, the Republican whip, is expected to seek the majority leader's post, the No. 2 position in the House Republican hierarchy, if its current holder, Dick Armey, announces his retirement today.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>School Prayer Law Struck Down  A federal appeals court struck down a Louisiana law allowing vocal classroom prayer, believed to be the only such law remaining in the nation.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Drug's Marketing Assailed  The head of the D.E.A., Asa Hutchinson, said aggressive promotion of the painkiller OxyContin by its maker, Purdue Pharma, had played a role in its widespread abuse by people seeking a heroin-like high.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Warning on Climate Change  A report issued by the National Research Council warned that the vast reshaping of the environment by modern civilization raised the chances of sudden and drastic upheavals in the climate.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>New Jersey Transit Plans to Raise Fares  New Jersey Transit, facing a daunting deficit and falling government aid, proposed its first fare increases in more than a decade. Fares would rise 10 percent on buses, commuter trains and the Newark subway in the coming year, and additional increases would be pegged to inflation in each of the next five years.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>D8</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-18</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>D9</p>
        <p>Deal Struck on Schools Bill  House and Senate conferees agreed on President Bush's education bill, giving him his first domestic legislative victory since Democrats took over the Senate and giving poor children a big increase in federal aid.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Custodians Arrested  Eleven school custodians in New York City were arrested on charges of taking kickbacks from companies given contracts to wash school windows without going through an authentic bidding process.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>S1-7</p>
        <p>Mets Get Roberto Alomar  The Mets acquired the 12-time All-Star second baseman in an eight-player trade with Cleveland.</p>
        <p>S1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Wendell Gauthier  A lawyer who won billions for victims in suits over silicone breast implants and hotel fires before taking on the tobacco industry, he was 58.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>11th Rate Cut of the Year  The Fed reduced its main lending rate by a quarter of a percentage point, to 1.75 percent, as President Bush and Congress made progress in reviving negotiations on an economic stimulus package.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Software Piracy on Campus  Federal law-enforcement agents seized computers and raided computer networks at M.I.T., U.C.L.A. and other big universities, shutting down what they called one of the Internet's largest software-piracy networks.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Kickback Case May Be Settled  Credit Suisse First Boston may pay $100 million to securities regulators to end an inquiry into whether it received kickbacks from buyers of hot stock offerings in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: Betraying the helpless; another rate cut from the Fed; food for Afghanistan; the battle over special education.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>D2  Weather</p>
        <p>A26</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
