<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Test Driving Heating Unit Before Frost</title>
    <meta content="23HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/23/realestate/23HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1327355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DC133BF930A1575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Test Driving Heating Unit Before Frost</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Test Driving Heating Unit Before Frost</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Your Home column on testing and preparing home heating unit before upcoming winter heating season; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH winter approaching, and the prospect of higher energy prices a distinct possibility, now is the time, plumbing and heating experts say, for building owners and managers to make sure that the heating systems in their buildings are operating as efficiently as possible.</p>
        <p>''My standard advice for every property owner is to take their heating system on a test drive right now instead of waiting for the first cold day of winter,'' said Dan Holohan, a Bethpage, N.Y., consultant and expert on steam heating systems. ''Unfortunately, very few people actually take that advice.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now is the time for building owners and managers to make sure that the heating systems in their buildings are operating efficiently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH winter approaching, and the prospect of higher energy prices a distinct possibility, now is the time, plumbing and heating experts say, for building owners and managers to make sure that the heating systems in their buildings are operating as efficiently as possible.</p>
        <p>''My standard advice for every property owner is to take their heating system on a test drive right now instead of waiting for the first cold day of winter,'' said Dan Holohan, a Bethpage, N.Y., consultant and expert on steam heating systems. ''Unfortunately, very few people actually take that advice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holohan, who maintains a Web site providing advice and information about heating systems (www.heatinghelp.com), stressed the importance of taking the time now -- before the system is needed to actually deliver heat -- to make sure that the boiler or furnace is running as well as it can.  And while energy efficiency is important to any homeowner, it is critical in multifamily buildings, in which a number of relatively minor problems can add up to a significant waste of money and energy.</p>
        <p>Fredric Goldner, president of Energy Management and Research Associates, an energy consulting company in Brooklyn, said that the first thing that every property owner -- and particularly owners of multifamily dwellings -- should do is to have an annual combustion efficiency test performed on their heating system.</p>
        <p>''And now is the time to do it,'' Mr. Goldner said, pointing out that plumbing and heating contractors are much more likely to be available now than they will be next month -- a factor that becomes even more important if repairs are necessary.</p>
        <p>The combustion efficiency test is made up of four separate tests, he said, adding that all four tests can typically be completed in one short visit and should cost $150 to $300.  The four tests include a measure of the ''stack temperature,'' or the temperature of the combustion gas just after it leaves the boiler or furnace; a measure of the amount of carbon dioxide present in the exhaust gas, which indicates the richness or leanness of the air-fuel mixture; the so-called draft, or the amount of exhaust gas being produced by combustion; and, for oil burners, a smoke test, or, particularly for gas-fueled systems, a test of the amount of carbon monoxide produced by the burning of natural gas.</p>
        <p>''By taking those four readings, a professional can determine the efficiency of the heating plant,'' Mr. Goldner said, defining efficiency as basically a measurement of how good the system is at turning fuel into usable heat.''Every system should be at least 80 percent efficient. If you're below 80 percent, your boiler almost certainly needs to be tuned and cleaned.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Goldner said, raising the efficiency of a boiler from 70 percent to 80 percent will result in approximately a 12.5 percent savings on fuel costs. ''And we find many buildings running at 70 percent efficiency,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another thing that can significantly affect the efficiency of the boiler, Mr. Goldner said, is soot that accumulates in the combustion chamber. ''Just one-sixteenth of an inch of soot will reduce combustion efficiency by 4 percent,'' he said. ''And it's not unusual for us to see soot deposits of a quarter of an inch or more.''</p>
        <p>Henry Gifford, who owns Gifford Fuel Saving Inc., a Manhattan heating and ventilation design and consulting company, said that building owners who wanted a fairly simple way of determining whether their heating system was functioning properly could invest as little as $100 for a thermometer that could be used to monitor the exhaust stack temperature after the boiler had been tuned and cleaned by an expert.</p>
        <p>''The thermometer should be mounted in the exhaust pipe just after the boiler,'' Mr. Gifford said. ''If the temperature rises more than about 50 degrees Fahrenheit above what it was after the tuneup, there's definitely something wrong.''</p>
        <p>It also makes sense, he said, for building owners to contact the manufacturer of the heating system and its components for instructions and specifications for the system being used. ''Every burner has certain adjustments that are critical,'' he said. ''And it's unreasonable to expect a boiler mechanic to memorize all the settings for every piece of equipment they are asked to work on.''</p>
        <p>Just ensuring that the boiler is operating efficiently, however, is no guarantee that fuel is not being wasted elsewhere. ''Uneven heating in a building wastes energy,'' Mr. Gifford said. ''But the waste is so far away from the boiler that it will not always be obvious to someone working on the system in the basement.''</p>
        <p>In fact, he said, one of the most effective ways of determining whether there is uneven heating in a building is to stand outside the building on a cold day and look for open windows.</p>
        <p>''What happens in a lot of big buildings is that people in some of the apartments call the superintendent and tell him they're not getting enough heat,'' Mr. Gifford said. ''So the super goes down to the basement and sends up more heat building-wide.''</p>
        <p>And while doing that might make the people who were cold a little more comfortable, he said, it will also make the people who were comfortable a little too hot. And when that happens, Mr. Gifford said, people in the hot apartments open their windows and the fuel dollars go sailing out.</p>
        <p>In most cases, he said, the reason that some residents have too much heat while others do not have enough has little to do with the amount of heat being produced by the boiler but is instead attributable to an imbalance in the heat distribution system.</p>
        <p>Multifamily buildings that are heated by steam, he said, use either a one-pipe or a two-pipe system. With a one-pipe system, Mr. Gifford said, steam generated by the boiler travels through pipes in the building to radiators in individual apartments.  A vent on each radiator allows air in the system to escape, making room for steam to enter the radiator, where it then condenses and returns as liquid through the same pipes that delivered it.</p>
        <p>With such a system, Mr. Gifford said, apartments that are not getting enough heat can usually be made comfortable by installing vents with larger openings in those apartments or preferably by installing vents with smaller openings in rooms that are getting too hot or by installing master vents at the end points of the supply lines to the colder parts of the building.</p>
        <p>Balancing heat in a building with a two-pipe system, on the other hand, is a bit more complicated. With such a system, Mr. Gifford explained, condensate returns to the boiler through a second set of pipes at the outlet of each radiator.</p>
        <p>At each outlet, however, there is a what is known as a steam trap, which, when it is working properly, allows air and water to pass into the return lines while keeping steam out of those lines. However, Mr. Gifford said, steam traps often fail, allowing the steam to enter the return lines, where it then prevents the venting of air from radiators in nearby apartments, thereby making it impossible for steam to enter those radiators and heat them as it should.</p>
        <p>''And that creates a lot of banging and clanging and uneven heating in the building,'' he said, adding that the only way to rectify that situation was to identify and replace the defective traps or, better yet, to replace all the traps in the building at the same time. That can be an expensive proposition, however, he said, adding that the cost for each radiator would be about $100, including labor.</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
