<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y03BRI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/03/world/03BRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1267893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDD133EF930A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: ADOPTIVE PARENTS SUED  The British couple who adopted American-born twin girls have been ordered to appear in American courts by lawyers for a California couple who had been caring for the girls. Vickie and Richard Allen of San Bernardino, Calif., are contesting the legality of the adoption by Judith and Alan Kilshaw. The Britons were served in Chicago after they appeared with the Allens on Wednesday at a taping of the Oprah Winfrey show. The twins are staying with a British social service agency while the legal struggle goes on.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: ADOPTIVE PARENTS SUED  The British couple who adopted American-born twin girls have been ordered to appear in American courts by lawyers for a California couple who had been caring for the girls. Vickie and Richard Allen of San Bernardino, Calif., are contesting the legality of the adoption by Judith and Alan Kilshaw. The Britons were served in Chicago after they appeared with the Allens on Wednesday at a taping of the Oprah Winfrey show. The twins are staying with a British social service agency while the legal struggle goes on.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: AMERICAN REPORTED ALIVE  Interior Minister Vladimir Rushailo said Kenneth Gluck, the American aid worker kidnapped in Chechnya last month, was still alive, the Interfax news agency reported. Mr. Gluck, left, a native of New York City, was seized south of the capital, Grozny, while on a mission for Doctors Without Borders. Russian officials say Mr. Gluck is being held by unidentified rebels, possibly for ransom.</p>
        <p>Patrick E. Tyler (NYT)</p>
        <p>SCOTLAND: LOCKERBIE SUIT  The American families of victims of the Lockerbie bombing will sue Libya for up to $10 billion in damages, said Lee Kreindler, lead counsel for 150 families. He said a New York judge would meet family representatives to draw up a timetable, but no trial date could be set before an expected appeal was heard. A Libyan secret agent, Abdelbaset Ali Mohmed al-Megrahi, was convicted Wednesday of the bombing, which killed 270 people, including 189 Americans.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>ECUADOR: STATE OF EMERGENCY  President Gustavo Noboa declared a state of national emergency after the breakdown of talks with Indian leaders over price increases that have brought violent protests nationwide. The action allows the government to limit meetings and travel, inspect homes, and dispatch military and police forces as it deems necessary. After talks aimed at heading off a crisis broke down, Indian leaders, who led an uprising last year that forced out President Jamil Mahuad, threatened to intensify their protests.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: FOX FIRM ON PULLOUT  The administration of President Vicente Fox said it would not continue to withdraw troops from bases in the State of Chiapas until leaders of the Zapatista National Liberation Army agreed to meet with the peace commissioner, Luis H. Álvarez. Among conditions for restarting talks, the rebels demanded that troops be withdrawn from seven bases. So far troops have been pulled from four positions.</p>
        <p>Ginger Thompson (NYT)</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: SWITCHING ROLES  In a completely unanticipated move, President Hugo Chávez has named his minister of foreign affairs, José Vicente Rangel, to be the new minister of defense. Mr. Rangel, 71, becomes the first civilian to head the armed forces since the 1920's, and will replace Gen. Ismael Hurtado. General Hurtado shifts to the Infrastructure Ministry after coming under fire from conservative critics for what they say is his role in politicizing the military.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: WAHID APOLOGY  After being censured by Parliament for misconduct, President Abdurrahman Wahid went on television to apologize for the political turmoil that has plagued Indonesia since he was implicated in two financial scandals. But Mr. Wahid ruled out resigning, despite growing calls for him to step down. He also dismissed speculation that he planned to fire key officials and generals.</p>
        <p>Calvin Sims (NYT)</p>
        <p>TAIWAN: NUCLEAR COMPROMISE  Leaders in Taiwan have moved closer to breaking a political deadlock over a partly built nuclear power plant. Prime Minister Chang Chun-hsiung, who halted the $5.5 billion project over the objections of the opposition Nationalist Party, offered to put the matter to a referendum. A senior Nationalist official said his party was ready to resolve the dispute.</p>
        <p>Mark Landler (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>LEBANON: U.N. WARNING TO ISRAEL  The United Nations special envoy for southern Lebanon, Staffan de Mistura, flew over Lebanon's border with Israel by helicopter and reported that the Israelis appeared to be building a fence extending into Lebanon beyond the divided border village of Ghajar. Mr. de Mistura said he expressed concern to the Israelis, who promised the construction would stop.</p>
        <p>Christopher S. Wren (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>GUINEA: 130 REBELS REPORTED SLAIN  Guinean troops have killed more than 130 rebels in clashes near the border with Liberia, the state radio said. About 60 rebels were killed in the area of Tanangue Zezou, and the rest in separate clashes in four other villages, all in the district of Macenta, the radio said, adding that the villages had been totally destroyed. The radio did not mention government casualties, but a security official said four soldiers were killed.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING ALERT  Global warming could cost the world billions of dollars a year unless emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases are curtailed soon, the United Nations Environment Program reported in its magazine, Our Planet. The report cites estimates by Munich Re, a German reinsurance company, that the cost of more frequent tropical cyclones, rising sea levels and damage to farming and fishing could eventually exceed $300 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Christopher S. Wren (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
