<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 6 Months, Bush Says, He's Doing Pretty Well</title>
    <meta content="Y04BUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/04/politics/04BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="White House Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DE133CF937A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 6 Months, Bush Says, He's Doing Pretty Well</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At 6 Months, Bush Says, He's Doing Pretty Well</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush, on eve of summer vacation, gives his first six months in office positive review; cites legislative successes and portrays his own actions as wholly principled and his opponents' reservations as mostly partisan; he hopes to use that tactic to push legislation he favors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Filling out his own report card just before his summer vacation, President Bush said today that he had proved, through the enactment of a tax cut and the increased possibility of a patients' bill of rights, that he could end ''deadlock and drift'' in the nation's capital.</p>
        <p>''Together with Congress, we're proving that a new tone, a clear agenda and active leadership can bring significant progress to the nation's capital,'' Mr. Bush said as he stood at the edge of the Rose Garden, his entire cabinet arrayed like an exultant team around him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush gave his administration high marks for making "significant progress" in his first six months in office</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Filling out his own report card just before his summer vacation, President Bush said today that he had proved, through the enactment of a tax cut and the increased possibility of a patients' bill of rights, that he could end ''deadlock and drift'' in the nation's capital.</p>
        <p>''Together with Congress, we're proving that a new tone, a clear agenda and active leadership can bring significant progress to the nation's capital,'' Mr. Bush said as he stood at the edge of the Rose Garden, his entire cabinet arrayed like an exultant team around him.</p>
        <p>''On this path, we're headed for a year of strong, meaningful legislative achievements,'' Mr. Bush later added, essentially giving himself and his deputies straight A's. ''And I want to express my thanks for every legislator who made tough decisions, every legislator who chose long-term progress over short-term political gain.''</p>
        <p>That last sentence captured the crux of Mr. Bush's legislative and oratorical strategy as he looks toward what could be a difficult fall. He will have to try to romance a Senate that will not be as easily wooed as the House, where he won big victories this week on patients' rights and his energy program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is portraying his own actions as wholly principled and his opponents' reservations as mostly partisan, and he hopes to use that tactic to push education legislation and health insurance protections through committees that will try to reconcile very different House and Senate bills.</p>
        <p>Americans, Mr. Bush said, ''want us to be principled, not partisan.''</p>
        <p>''They want us to look for agreement instead of looking for fights and arguments,'' he continued. ''Americans know obstructionism when they see it, and when necessary, I will point it out.''</p>
        <p>Some Democrats complained that Mr. Bush was talking out of both sides of his mouth -- and that his words were not being matched by truly conciliatory deeds. His suggestion that people with different opinions were obstructionists, they noted, was its own kind of partisan sniping.</p>
        <p>''He says, 'When you agree with me, you're bipartisan, but if you disagree with me, you're partisan,' '' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York. ''That statement is an inherent contradiction.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer offered a less flattering report card for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''Bipartisanship in terms of pictures and language -- B+,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''Bipartisanship in terms of action -- D.''</p>
        <p>As an example, Mr. Schumer cited Mr. Bush's opposition to the level of education financing that the Senate approved -- even before it shifted to Democratic control from Republican.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's remarks today hewed to his fondness for brevity, lasting less than six minutes.</p>
        <p>Even at that length, they amounted to a kind of official review at a distinct juncture. He recently passed the six-month mark of his presidency. Congress just began its August recess. And Mr. Bush is set to leave on Saturday for four weeks on his beloved Texas ranch, with its spacious pool and private fishing pond.</p>
        <p>He referred to that trip as a journey ''home to the heartland,'' a rubric that aides have created for his vacation, which will be interrupted with short trips to states like Colorado, New Mexico, Wisconsin, Pennsylvania -- all between the coasts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said his goal was to ''listen to the American people and to talk about the values that unite and sustain our country.''</p>
        <p>Aides said he would visit at least one school, stroll through a national park and, in Waco, Tex., next week, help hammer some nails into a home being built by Habitat for Humanity.</p>
        <p>Once he returns to Washington in early September, the predictably divisive appropriations process will begin in earnest, and Mr. Bush used his comments today as a sort of pre-emptive strike against lawmakers who seek more spending than he has recommended.</p>
        <p>''The Congress must live within the generous limits of our budget,'' Mr. Bush said, adding that ''within a limited budget,'' he will begin to propose and promote programs intended to help parents ''raise responsible, motivated and moral children''; to help immigrants; and to encourage private citizens to help solve public problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was clearly buoyed by several recent successes in Congress, including the House's vote on Thursday for a patients' bill of rights that bent significantly to the president's desires, and Senate Democrats' approval today of a farm-aid bill that met Mr. Bush's specifications. In his remarks, Mr. Bush also mentioned the House's passage earlier this week of his energy bill.</p>
        <p>''We're ending deadlock and drift and making our system work on behalf of the American people,'' Mr. Bush said near the start of his remarks.</p>
        <p>His self-critique of the past six months was selective. When he reviewed his administration's record on foreign policy, he made no acknowledgment of the divide between the United States and some of its most important allies on key treaties and issues like global warming and missile defense.</p>
        <p>''We have put our foreign policy on sound footing,'' he said. ''We're strengthening our relationships with our allies and moving to build a world that trades more freely.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps his most consistent assertion was that he was sailing high above politics-as-usual, just as he had said he would.</p>
        <p>''My administration pledged to bring civility and high standards to Washington, and to lead for the sake of all Americans,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>By his own grading system, he was making good on that promise.</p>
        <p>White House Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
