<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1272105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D91E30F93AA25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Refugee Workers in Kenya Accused of Extorting Fees  United Nations investigators are sifting through evidence that corrupt workers with the U.N. high commissioner for refugees in Kenya extorted fees. The amounts are rumored to range from a few dollars for an appointment to up to $5,000 for a new life in the United States, Canada or Australia.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Refugee Workers in Kenya Accused of Extorting Fees  United Nations investigators are sifting through evidence that corrupt workers with the U.N. high commissioner for refugees in Kenya extorted fees. The amounts are rumored to range from a few dollars for an appointment to up to $5,000 for a new life in the United States, Canada or Australia.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Kurds Recall Horrors at Sea  Kurdish migrants who were rescued off the coast of the French Riviera spoke about their horrifying journey from northern Iraq to France.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Taliban Accused of Killings  Taliban commanders have been involved over the last year in the massacres of several hundred civilians in northern Afghanistan, Human Rights Watch said.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>New Tape of Ukraine Leader  A newly released secret recording of President Leonid D. Kuchma of Ukraine indicated that he ordered a broad campaign of threats and intimidation in 1999 to ensure his re-election.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Yeltsin Aide Awaits Trial  Pavel Pavlovich Borodin, who was Boris Yeltsin's lieutenant, finds his quarters in a federal detention center in Brooklyn a world apart from the Moscow high-rise where he was Mr. Yeltsin's neighbor. He is being held on Swiss charges of money laundering.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe Expulsions Delayed  A court delayed for five days the expulsions from Zimbabwe of two journalists, Joseph Winter, a BBC correspondent, and Mercedes Sayagues, who writes for a South African newspaper.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Kilimanjaro's Ice Melting  New studies show that the icecap atop Mt. Kilimanjaro is retreating at such a pace that it will disappear in less than 15 years, new studies show -- one of the clearest signs that a global warming trend has exceeded typical climate shifts.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Global warming is expected to increase crop yields in temperate regions while harming agriculture in the tropics, scientists said.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-13</p>
        <p>Clinton Defense of Pardon Draws Storm of Criticism  Leaders of House and Senate committees examining former President Bill Clinton's decision to pardon Marc Rich, the fugitive financier, said that Mr. Clinton's latest and most detailed defense of his decision raised fresh questions that need to be investigated. The defense at issue was an Op-Ed article Mr. Clinton wrote that was published in The New York Times on Sunday. The article listed reasons for the pardon.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Hard Time Being Charitable  Philanthropy, one of the nation's most spectacular growth industries for the last decade, is feeling the pinch of the market turnaround, several indicators suggest. Many foundations report that assets have shrunk, and some nonprofit organizations have had a drop in donors.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Social Security Woes Cited  The quality of service provided to the public by the Social Security Administration has deteriorated in recent years, and the problems are likely to grow as millions of baby boomers retire, a federal advisory panel has told the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Cold War Legacy in Idaho  Buried in tanks and dumped into trenches at the Idaho National Engineering and Environmental Laboratory northwest of Idaho Falls is a witches' brew of deadly chemicals and radioactive waste left over from the cold war. The area was designated a Superfund site in 1989, and the government started trying to clean it up. Now two men who audited that effort say in a federal lawsuit that government contractors who were paid hundreds of millions of dollars made the contamination worse.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Dire Warning From Labor Boss  John J. Sweeney, the A.F.L.-C.I.O.'s president, gave an unusual do-or-die warning to labor leaders at a meeting in Los Angeles, telling them that unless unions did far more to increase their ranks, organized labor could drift into irrelevance.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Church Recasts Its Image  The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints will step up efforts to discourage use of the term Mormon Church, and emphasize the name Jesus Christ in references to the church, a Mormon official said.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Specter of Losing Seats Spurs Intense Politicking  Congressional redistricting in New York has always set off waves of intrigue and political brawling. But this year, the process has become even more intense because New York is poised to lose two of its 31 seats in the House of Representatives as a result of the nation's shifting populations. The task of deciding which two districts must go falls to the State Legislature in Albany, and members of the state's Congressional delegation are doing everything from hiring well-connected lobbyists to contributing to the campaign coffers of Albany leaders in hopes of saving their seats.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>New Fees at Pharmacies  New York City's Health and Hospitals Corporation, strapped for cash and desperate to find new income, has begun charging a universal fee for prescription drugs at the pharmacies of all its public hospitals and community clinics.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>First Dysfunctional Family  Suffering dominates ''Abraham and Mary: A House Divided,'' a six-hour documentary starting tonight on PBS that offers a brooding, emotional vision of President Lincoln and his wife. He was a depressive who was able to transform private grief into monumental political courage. She was a depressive who tried to forget her troubles by shopping on a monumental scale. The program casts the Lincolns as First Dysfunctional Family, using them as a central metaphor for a ruptured nation.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Daytona Crash Kills Driver  Dale Earnhardt Sr., 49, was killed in a crash on the last turn of the last lap at the Daytona 500, the Nascar season opener. The race was won by Michael Waltrip. Dale Earnhardt Jr. finished second.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7-8</p>
        <p>William H. Masters  The doctor who, with his co-researcher, Virginia E. Johnson, revolutionized the way sex is studied, taught and enjoyed, was 85.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Eddie Mathews  The Hall of Fame third baseman who hit 512 home runs and teamed with Hank Aaron to form the most productive power-hitting combination in baseball history was 69.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Balthus  The artist whose proper name was Balthasar Klossowski was among the most widely admired of European painters for the last 30 years, excelling as a portraitist, as a painter of French landscapes and as a stage designer. He was 92.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Layoffs in Perspective  Goodyear Tire and Rubber, Dell Computer and Nortel Networks are the latest to announce plans to lay off thousands of employees, joining companies like DaimlerChrysler, Lucent Technologies, Sara Lee and Whirlpool. But in many cases, only a fraction as many Americans will find themselves unemployed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Glimmer of Hope in Hollywood  Talks between the Writers Guild of America and the major studios and television networks have extended into a fourth week, stirring hope in Hollywood that a settlement may yet be reached to forestall dreaded dual strikes this summer by the industry's writers and actors.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Deal Seen for Unilever Unit  George Weston, the Canadian food conglomerate, is expected to buy Unilever's bakery division for about $1.7 million, adding Thomas' English muffins to its brands, which include Girl Scout cookies, executives close to the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Shootout at the 'ER' Corral  A new round in the battle for prime-time television's most lucrative night, Thursday, will begin on March 1 when CBS challenges television's most popular show, ''ER'' on NBC, with ''Big Apple,'' a show about turf wars between the F.B.I. and the police department in New York.</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Workers Seize Daewoo Plant  Hundreds of workers at the Daewoo Motor Company seized the company's huge manufacturing plant in Inchon, South Korea, pledging to hold it until the financially troubled company gives up plans to lay off more than a third of its work force and reinstates those already dismissed.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Giant Cable Deal Altered  The Liberty Media Corporation and UnitedGlobalCom Inc. have made changes in their intended merger plan after bondholders rejected the transaction.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>U.S. Markets Closed Today  The financial markets in the United States are closed for Presidents' Day. The markets in other countries will be open.</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Clinton's explanation; auditing the poor; the world champs go global.  Columns: William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E9  Weather</p>
        <p>D10  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
