<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commerce Designate Has Easy Going at Senate Hearing</title>
    <meta content="Y05COM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/05/politics/05COMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1260409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Donald L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Census</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDF163AF936A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commerce Designate Has Easy Going at Senate Hearing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Donald L Evans, Pres-elect George W Bush's choice for commerce secretary, receives cordial reception from Senate Commerce Committee; he tells senators at his confirmation hearing that he has no position yet on how to handle politically touchy census, but promises to enforce trade laws vigorously and to keep his department free of political influence peddling; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Donald L. Evans, President-elect George W. Bush's choice for commerce secretary, told senators at his confirmation hearing today that he had no position yet on how to handle the politically touchy census, but promised to enforce trade laws vigorously and to keep his department free of political influence peddling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, a Texas oilman who served as Mr. Bush's campaign chairman and is a longtime friend of the president-elect, was the first cabinet selection to undergo the required Senate scrutiny, and he received a cordial reception. Several senators predicted during and after the hearing, conducted by the Senate Commerce Committee, that Mr. Evans would face little or no opposition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Donald L. Evans, President-elect George W. Bush's choice for commerce secretary, told senators at his confirmation hearing today that he had no position yet on how to handle the politically touchy census, but promised to enforce trade laws vigorously and to keep his department free of political influence peddling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, a Texas oilman who served as Mr. Bush's campaign chairman and is a longtime friend of the president-elect, was the first cabinet selection to undergo the required Senate scrutiny, and he received a cordial reception. Several senators predicted during and after the hearing, conducted by the Senate Commerce Committee, that Mr. Evans would face little or no opposition.</p>
        <p>Senator Ernest F. Hollings of South Carolina, the committee's senior Democrat, was chairman of the hearing, because Democrats control the Senate until Dick Cheney succeeds Al Gore as vice president in two weeks. Mr. Hollings said at the end of the two-hour hearing that the committee hoped to send the Evans nomination to the Senate floor, with a recommendation that it be confirmed, in the first week after the inauguration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans seemed to have charmed most committee members with visits to their offices in recent days, and he was asked relatively soft questions about how he would manage the department's many functions. The department promotes American companies, enforces trade agreements, reviews patents, researches the oceans, oversees the fishing industry, conducts the census and helps set standards and regulations for the technology industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans, who spent the last 25 years as a senior executive at Tom Brown Inc., an oil exploration company based in Midland, Tex., has never held a government position, though he did head the Board of Regents at the University of Texas, his alma mater.</p>
        <p>Still, speaking in a soft Texas twang, he deflected the most sensitive queries with the deftness of an old Washington hand.</p>
        <p>He expressed a strong interest in everything from the plight of the steel industry and rural access to high-speed Internet connections to research into global warming. He promised to work closely with senators in addressing each of those issues.</p>
        <p>Some of the most pointed questions came from Senator John McCain of Arizona, who will resume the committee's chairmanship when the Republicans regain Senate control.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain ran against Mr. Bush for the Republican presidential nomination and has spearheaded a drive to overhaul campaign finance laws. Today he pressed Mr. Evans, who raised a record $100 million for the Bush campaign, on what he would do to make sure that the Commerce Department did not use its powers to reward major campaign contributors.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain warned him to avoid the kind of cloud that dogged Ronald H. Brown, President Clinton's first commerce secretary, who faced accusations that he had in effect sold seats on foreign trade trips to campaign contributors and allowed Commerce Department officials to raise political funds. The senator asked Mr. Evans to submit in writing within 30 days details of how he would prevent that sort of political activity, and he agreed to do so.</p>
        <p>Several Democrats, especially Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, sought to elicit a commitment from Mr. Evans to allow statistical sampling to supplement last year's decennial count of the population if Census Bureau experts find that  achieving an accurate tally requires it.</p>
        <p>In November, the Clinton administration shifted the power to adjust the census from the commerce secretary to the director of the Census Bureau, arguing that the nonpolitical professionals at the bureau would be a fairer judge of whether such an adjustment was needed to correct for an undercount. Under the regulation, the director could adjust the count only if a panel of experts within the bureau so recommended. Democrats are happy with that arrangement, and would like assurances that the new administration will do nothing to overturn it.</p>
        <p>Many Republicans, though, citing the Constitution's requirement that the census be an ''actual enumeration,'' have argued that such an adjustment would be illegal. Some also worry that since minorities, who tend to live in Democratic areas, are the people most likely to be missed by conventional counting methods, such an adjustment might aid Democrats when new Congressional and state legislative districts are drawn.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Hollings teasingly urged Mr. Evans to apply the standard that the senator suggested had been adopted by the Bush camp in the long battle over the Florida election outcome.</p>
        <p>''Our hope,'' Mr. Hollings said, ''is that you stick with Mr. Bush's position supporting sampling and opposing hand counts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans expressed no firm stand on the issue but agreed to come back before the committee when he decided what to do.</p>
        <p>Senators of both parties were critical of the Clinton administration's record on trade law enforcement, and urged Mr. Evans to do more.</p>
        <p>Senator John D. Rockefeller IV, Democrat of West Virginia, pushed Mr. Evans to help protect the steel industry. Mr. Rockefeller, whose state is home to several of the largest steel makers, said the industry was on the verge of extinction because of what he called unfair competition from abroad. He said Mr. Gore had failed to carry West Virginia, long a Democratic state, largely because the Clinton administration had done little to help ailing steel companies and workers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans promised to examine whether to impose sweeping measures to protect the industry under existing trade law.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of talk about the information economy,'' he said. ''But I am not one who believes that means you turn your back on the industrial base of this economy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
