<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rich Nations Offer a Hand, But the Poor Hope for More</title>
    <meta content="Y21SUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/21/international/21SUMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1310988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="GENOA SUMMIT MEETING: THE HAVES AND THE HAVE-NOTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Group of Eight</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Genoa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Genoa (Italy)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED9123AF932A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rich Nations Offer a Hand, But the Poor Hope for More</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rich Nations Offer a Hand, but the Poor Hope for More</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>GENOA, Italy, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of Eight leaders sit down for first time to discuss health, debt and the poor, topics that demonstrators have complained are ignored by rich countries, but progress is incremental and unlikely to defuse criticism; announce that $1.2 billion has been committed to United Nations global health fund, primarily to fight AIDS; United Nations Sec Gen Kofi Annan says more is needed; Group of Eight leaders also meet with leaders of several poor and developing nations to discuss debt relief and other economic programs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After growing protests, world leaders sat down today for the first time to discuss health, debt and the poor -- exactly the topics that demonstrators have complained are ignored by rich countries.</p>
        <p>But progress was incremental and unlikely to defuse the criticism that the wealthy nations worry about trade first, their own wealth second and everything else third.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>World leaders at the summit meeting in Genoa, Italy, discussed health, debt and the poor  the same topics that demonstrators complain that rich countries ignore</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After growing protests, world leaders sat down today for the first time to discuss health, debt and the poor -- exactly the topics that demonstrators have complained are ignored by rich countries.</p>
        <p>But progress was incremental and unlikely to defuse the criticism that the wealthy nations worry about trade first, their own wealth second and everything else third.</p>
        <p>On the opening day of their summit meeting here, the leaders of the world's biggest economies announced that about $1.2 billion had been committed to a United Nations ''Global Health Fund'' that would primarily fight AIDS, following through on a commitment made at the summit meeting last year in Okinawa, Japan.</p>
        <p>President Bush announced the American contribution of $200 million two months ago and called it ''seed money,'' suggesting more might flow.</p>
        <p>Britain and Japan have both matched that amount. Germany pledged $150 million, France $120 million and African nations about $12 million. The Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, created by the chairman of Microsoft, and the Credit Suisse Group, the large banking company, have been among the major private donors who have committed $101 million.</p>
        <p>While the figures may seem large, Secretary General Kofi Annan of the United Nations has said that $7 billion to $10 billion a year is needed to truly make a difference.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Annan called the donations ''laudable,'' but, he added, ''it is not enough.''</p>
        <p>''Much, much more is needed,'' Mr. Annan said, a message that several of the leaders, facing increasingly slow economic times and tight budgets, would rather not have heard.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the Group of 8 also met tonight with the leaders of several poor and developing nations, including Nigeria, Mali, Bangladesh and El Salvador. It was the first time that leaders of smaller nations were invited to the summit meeting; less than a decade ago, President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia was invited but was not permitted to act as a full participant for several years.</p>
        <p>The discussion focused on how  poor, deeply indebted nations could move beyond debt relief. Already, in return for debt forgiveness, poor countries are required to use loans for education or health care, or measures to ensure greater labor productivity. Mr. Bush is now pressing the World Bank to focus its programs on making poor countries more economically competitive.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Bush's senior aides said tonight that the president had ''gone beyond the debt relief program'' by proposing that up to half of the new money spent on the poorest nations be distributed as grants, not loans. Mr. Bush promoted that idea earlier this week at a speech in Washington by recognizing that many countries do not repay their loans.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's idea failed to win the endorsement of his colleagues, and he committed no new cash for debt relief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides noted that 23 countries have qualified for debt relief, from Benin to Zambia. The program was originally pushed by President Bill Clinton, though Mr. Bush endorsed it -- in muted tones -- during his election campaign. But many of those countries have only begun to be released from their payments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush pressed for and received a lengthy passage in the economic communiqué today that praised the United States for its tax cuts and budget restraint -- essentially an international endorsement of his domestic strategy. He also predicted that the American economy would recover in the second half of the year. But the communiqué released today -- the kind of document that is little-read, but much argued about before summit meetings like this one -- pressed for ''tax cuts, as well as structural reforms aimed at further increasing employment'' in Europe.</p>
        <p>No country was harshly criticized, even though many of the reforms the group talked about today have languished for years. That situation underscores one of the objections to these summit meetings: all the leaders want praise for their policies for use back home. The result is that criticisms are so muted that they have little effect. The closest the leaders came to a critical tone was noting that prices had continued to spiral down in Japan, a worrisome deflationary trend, and hinting that structural reforms had been slow.</p>
        <p>The leaders also carefully avoided the question of which nation should lead the world out of an economic slowdown.</p>
        <p>''Everyone says it should be us,'' one White House official said recently, ''because we are the biggest. We say that we led for most of the 90's, and now it's time for Japan to get back in the game. And the Europeans are looking at both of us.''</p>
        <p>The leaders also urged a quick launching of a new, global round of trade talks -- exactly what Mr. Clinton failed to achieve at the World Trade Organization meeting in Seattle in December 1999. Violent street protests erupted there, and demonstrations at subsequent meetings have steadily escalated, culminating in the death of a protester here today. The summit meeting's communiqué suggests that Europe and the United States have begun to settle the many rifts that undercut the Seattle talks. But Mr. Bush has yet to answer the main concern of developing nations: that the United States, Japan and Europe are attempting to force open the markets of poorer nations before they have the ability to compete. Meanwhile, the small nations argue that the West continues to protect its own farmers and textile makers from cheap imports. It is a subject Mr. Bush has never addressed in detail, beyond describing himself as an advocate of free markets.</p>
        <p>On the sidelines of the meeting, Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi of Japan told Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany that he was continuing his efforts to persuade Mr. Bush to accept the Kyoto Protocol to control greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>''Koizumi's been under great pressure from Germany and France,'' one Japanese official said here today. ''They need Japan to win passage of the protocol over American objections.''</p>
        <p>France's president, Jacques Chirac, was far more critical of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''There is no alternative to the Kyoto protocol and to the efforts to reduce greenhouse gas emissions,'' he told Prime Minister Jean Chrétien of Canada, French officials said.</p>
        <p>GENOA SUMMIT MEETING: THE HAVES AND THE HAVE-NOTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
