<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1310633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1D8173AF93AA25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Bush Setting Limits On Reworking of ABM Pact  The Bush administration has decided that in seeking to work out a new understanding with Moscow to replace the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972 the United States will not accept any agreement that limits the development of antimissile defenses, an official said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and the Russian foreign minister held talks in Rome. In Moscow, Mr. Putin said he was open to negotiating an accord over a limited missile defense without discarding decades of arms control agreements.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Bush Setting Limits On Reworking of ABM Pact  The Bush administration has decided that in seeking to work out a new understanding with Moscow to replace the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972 the United States will not accept any agreement that limits the development of antimissile defenses, an official said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and the Russian foreign minister held talks in Rome. In Moscow, Mr. Putin said he was open to negotiating an accord over a limited missile defense without discarding decades of arms control agreements.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Police officers in Genoa, Italy, secured a six-square-mile area where world leaders will meet; some anti-globalization groups pledged to penetrate it. Mr. Bush arrived in London to begin his weeklong trip to Britain, Italy and Kosovo.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Charge in Okinawa Rape  Air Force Staff Sgt. Timothy Woodland was charged with rape in connection with an attack on a 20-year-old Japanese woman on Okinawa.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Egypt Cracks Down on Gays  Fifty-two men were charged in a state security court with engaging in immoral acts or religious offenses in a high-profile crackdown on suspected homosexual activity that has been condemned by some legal activists and human rights groups.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Pardon for Assassin's Friend  President Moshe Katsav of Israel pardoned Margalit Har-Shefia, 25, left, who was jailed for not telling what she knew about the intentions of her friend Yigal Amir, the right-wing religious extremist who killed Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin in 1995.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Macedonia Peace Hopes Dim  Macedonian Slav and Albanian leaders appeared unable to reach a political agreement to end a five-month-old conflict, after nearly two weeks of intensive Western-brokered negotiations.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-22</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Dissension Delays Voting on Charities Plan  House Republican leaders, faced with a threatened rebellion by moderates in their party, abruptly delayed voting on President Bush's initiative to funnel more federal money to religious groups to deliver social services. The moderates questioned whether the bill would override local and state laws protecting gays from discrimination.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Ally Backs Cell Studies  Senator Bill Frist, a Tennessee Republican who is also a transplant surgeon, abortion opponent and close ally of President Bush, said he supported federal financing for stem cell research under certain conditions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cheney Panel's Records Sought  The General Accounting Office demanded that Vice President Dick Cheney turn over records relating to the development of his energy task force's policies.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Action on Fuel Efficiency  The House Energy and Commerce Committee moved to require slightly higher fuel economy from sport utility vehicles, minivans and light trucks, but it voted against calls for major economy increases. Environmentalists promised to take the fight to the House floor.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Children's Lot Found to Improve  A federal report said that by many social, financial, educational and health measures, the well-being of America's children was improving, though children remain more likely than adults to live in poverty.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>California Turnaround  A cool July and effective conservation efforts have taken the state out from under the specter of blackouts and shortages and into a position from which it is able to sell surplus electrical power back to a glutted market, though at a loss.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Police Back Off After Protests  Three months after Cincinnati was traumatized by street clashes and vandalism, the police have retreated from ''pro-active'' patrols in black neighborhoods, saying they fear fresh charges of racism.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Third-Party Fund-Raising Is Boon to Hevesi Campaign  Alan G. Hevesi's mayoral campaign received donations bundled by lawyers, executives, bankers and other intermediaries at a rate that far exceeded those of his Democratic rivals in the last six months, campaign finance reports show. But his campaign also led all others in returning donations for ethical considerations. The data also confirm that the real estate industry is hedging its bets by spreading dollars among the candidates.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Big Admen on Campus  Two enterprising New Jersey high school seniors have persuaded a credit card company to underwrite their college educations for $40,000 each in exchange for their wearing of the company's logo and being its ''spokesguys'' among their peers.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Naming Rights for a Donation  The Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of American History has offered to let General Motors name a new hall of transportation in exchange for a $10 million gift.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>A Retreat on Pitch Counts  Baseball officials backed off a plan to use the number of pitches in a game as a measure of an umpire's performance, a tactic that umpires construed as an effort to expand the strike zone to speed up the game.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Fed Chief Hints at More Cuts  Alan Greenspan said the economy remained weak and susceptible to bad news, and he hinted that more rate cuts could be coming.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Amex Paring Down Labor Force  American Express will cut as many as 5,000 jobs, on top of 1,600 already cut this year, and take more than $1 billion in charges this quarter.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Mixed Report From AOL  AOL Time Warner had higher profit margins in crucial units and a lower loss than in the same quarter a year ago, but revenue growth lagged.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T Holding On to Cable Unit  AT&amp;T's board rejected Comcast's unsolicited bid to acquire AT&amp;T's cable operation, but the board also delayed its own plan to spin off the cable unit as an independent company.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Offshore Tax Havens Popular  Tax evasion by Americans using offshore accounts is rising, Treasury Secretary Paul H. O'Neill said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Clueless on global warming; the tuberculosis threat; cleaning up stock market research.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
