<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and Putin: Words That Tell of Common Ground</title>
    <meta content="Y23STE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="GENOA SUMMIT MEETING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D8103AF930A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and Putin: Words That Tell of Common Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from news conference by Pres Bush and Pres Vladimir V Putin of Russia at close of summit Genoa, Italy, at which they addressed missile defense and arms control (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the news conference by President Bush and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia at the close of the summit meeting in Genoa, as provided by The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>President Putin</p>
        <p>. . . The differences in approaches on a couple of topics is still there. However, what is more important is that we are aimed, both of us are aiming at partnership to look forward, well reasoned, well balanced, carefully weighed approaches and solutions. Naturally, we discussed issues of strategic stability. There we spent a lot of time. We talked in great detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the news conference by President Bush and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia at the close of the summit meeting in Genoa, as provided by The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>President Putin</p>
        <p>. . . The differences in approaches on a couple of topics is still there. However, what is more important is that we are aimed, both of us are aiming at partnership to look forward, well reasoned, well balanced, carefully weighed approaches and solutions. Naturally, we discussed issues of strategic stability. There we spent a lot of time. We talked in great detail.</p>
        <p>I have to say that, to some extent, what was unexpected both for me, and I think for President Bush as well, was the understanding that was reached today between us on the issue that the offensive arms and issue of defensive arms will be discussed as a set. . . .</p>
        <p>President Bush</p>
        <p>. . . As the president said, we are going to have open and honest dialogue about defensive systems, as well as reduction of offensive systems. The two go hand-in-hand in order to set up a new strategic framework for peace.</p>
        <p>And along these lines, as the president mentioned, my national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, will be visiting in Moscow, the purpose of which is to lay out a specific timetable of discussions between our defense ministers and our foreign ministers.</p>
        <p>So as we can continue progress to find common ground to make the world more peaceful, both of us want to seize the moment and lead, and I appreciate this attitude so very much with President Putin. Secondly, we did talk, spent time discussing economic cooperation. There will be a statement put out after the meeting on both, by the way, the strategic framework discussions, as well as the economic cooperation along these lines. Secretary Evans and Secretary O'Neill will be in Moscow next week to discuss a wide range of topics.</p>
        <p>But one of the things that is clear and evident is that the president understands the need to create a framework for entrepreneurial activity. As I mentioned in my last press conference -- I will mention this again -- I am impressed by the fact that he has instituted tax reform, a flat tax. And as he pointed out to me, it is one of the lowest tax rates in Europe. He and I share something in common. We both proudly stand here as tax reformers. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. To (Mr. Putin), your proposal on holding a conference in Moscow on the environment. How were the other G-8 partners receiving your invitation to Moscow?</p>
        <p>MR. PUTIN . . . The Kyoto Protocol is simply not sufficient to substantially improve the ecology in the world, although the movement that we're moving in is in the right direction. But I want to say that Russia is still for the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>But what's important is that the scientists themselves, political leaders, ecologists, people in society, government leaders, never, ever got together once. Each of these groups sits there alone, and out of their own corner reviews this issue. And the thought was to get everybody together on one common platform. This was supported very energetically by the president of the United States and by other colleagues. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. A question to both presidents: Please tell us how you assess the Genoa summit results from the point of view of the future G-8's, because you've got all these anti-globalist demonstrators and others.</p>
        <p>MR. BUSH -- Well, I'm looking forward to future G-8 summits. People should be allowed to protest in a peaceful way. The great thing about freedom is that it provides an outlet for people to express their differences. Having said that, I  believe that which we discussed today and in the last couple of days will make the world a heck of a lot more prosperous and peaceful place. . . .</p>
        <p>MR. PUTIN -- I have to tell you that the people who are out on the streets and talked about the issues of the poor countries and their problems and those who gathered within the framework of the eight were all taken by one and the same series of issues. In this sense, we can say that we're all of the same mind. But unlike those who chose the extremist ways of expressing their minds, those who worked here tried to find solutions, ways to get to the end solution, specific kinds of solutions which realistically could affect -- I hope will affect -- the condition in which the very poorest countries are living in the world today. . . .</p>
        <p>GENOA SUMMIT MEETING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
