<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Politics as Usual Has An Unusually Ominous Ring</title>
    <meta content="08POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1284027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EEDD153EF93BA35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Politics as Usual Has An Unusually Ominous Ring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David M. Halbfinger</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe the millenial purists were right when they said the end of the world would come this year, not in 2000. New Jersey politics is starting to feel like a passage from Revelations.</p>
        <p>The sea isn't exactly boiling, but the Environmental Protection Agency is suddenly acting as if a little arsenic in the water will put hair on your chest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe the millenial purists were right when they said the end of the world would come this year, not in 2000. New Jersey politics is starting to feel like a passage from Revelations.</p>
        <p>The sea isn't exactly boiling, but the Environmental Protection Agency is suddenly acting as if a little arsenic in the water will put hair on your chest.</p>
        <p>Peter Verniero may not be wearing the mark of the beast, but it certainly seems as if he's had a few concentric circles painted on the back of his black robe.</p>
        <p>And the four horsemen have not been spotted, but any reporter worth his salt can get four or more Republican county chairmen to warn of plague, pestilence, famine and disease if Acting Gov. Donald T. DiFrancesco fails to rally as a candidate and drags his party down to defeat in November.</p>
        <p>''It hasn't seemed this chaotic around here since a woman drove up on the State House steps and threw her mother's head out the car window,'' said Jim Manion, a spokesman for Democrats in the State Senate, who recalled the grisly disposal from his days here as a reporter for The Associated Press in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>Reporters around this State House had gotten used to a somewhat leisurely pace. Beat reporters covered sleepy state agencies. Political writers were considered enterprising if they showed up at political fund-raisers in the off-season and spent more time asking questions than sampling the free food and drinks.</p>
        <p>Now it's all hands on deck.</p>
        <p>''You have a governor who left town to become the administrator of the E.P.A., and immediately got caught contradicting her president, twice,'' said one highly placed Republican official who would rather be caught dead than be quoted by name, referring to Christie Whitman's recent embarrassments on global warming policy and arsenic-in-the-water standards.</p>
        <p>''You have an acting governor who is by virtue of the state constitution, the leader of both the legislative and executive branch,'' the official continued. ''And you've got his judiciary chairman calling for the resignation, and rattling the saber of impeachment over, the E.P.A. administrator's political protégé and former chief of staff. On the side sits Jack Collins, and his last political role was dropping out of a governor's race that he never really had a high-profile campaign for in the first place.</p>
        <p>''It's just a new level of soap opera with tremendously high stakes,'' the official added.</p>
        <p>Soap opera certainly describes the direction the governor's race is headed.</p>
        <p>Not long ago it looked as if the Republican primary would be the political equivalent of a spring training game for Mr. DiFrancesco, the newly promoted acting governor who enjoyed the nearly monolithic support of the party's rank and file. His conservative opponent, Bret D. Schundler, the mayor of Jersey City, had won high praise from the National Review set but seemed a bit far to the right for a state that has been walking briskly, if not running, to the left, to tell from a decades worth of polls.</p>
        <p>But for the last two months, Mr. DiFrancesco has been running against himself -- and losing. While Senate President DiFrancesco was a well-known and well-liked figure around the State House after 25 years in the Legislature, his law practice and business interests had never been examined. So reporters who went digging into the background of the new most powerful person in New Jersey found a lengthy paper trail replete with loans, and lawsuits, and legal judgments, and accusations of ethical lapses.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiFrancesco released a pile of documents in a savvy bid to air everything at once and move on. But he also stumbled badly by nominating for state treasurer someone who had been fired from a bank a few years ago after being accused of abusing her expense account to pay for personal travel. And when that was reported, Mr. DiFrancesco still tried to push her confirmation through the Senate Judiciary Committee.</p>
        <p>''For those of us who have been honored to serve in the State Senate,'' Mr. DiFrancesco was saying on Thursday, ''we believe that it is not just our right, but our responsibility to review thoroughly the nominations submitted for our consideration.''</p>
        <p>He was talking now about Mr. Verniero, the associate State Supreme Court justice whom Mr. DiFrancesco accused of misleading senators about racial profiling during his confirmation hearing two years ago. In a room filled with 15 cameras, he forcefully -- even gubernatorially -- made the case for Mr. Verniero to resign.</p>
        <p>Just a while earlier, however, one of Mr. DiFrancesco's political aides had passed out a tip sheet for reporters, with bullet points and backup documents detailing the unsavory pasts and presents of 13 people appointed by Mr. Schundler or connected to his administration. They ranged from two deputy mayors accused of being nasty landlords to the stepdaughter of another deputy mayor and an investigator employed by a law firm that contributed to Mr. Schundler's campaign.</p>
        <p>His political aides said the tip sheet was meant to encourage the  media to be as scrupulous in vetting Mr. Schundler as Mr. DiFrancesco. A more irreverent interpretation would be a plea for payback.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiFrancesco, after all, had reacted a few weeks ago to reports about his real estate deals by describing them as a ''smear campaign that Bret Schundler, nasty sleazy guy that he is, that he's doing.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS David M. Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David M. Halbfinger is Trenton bureau chief of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
