<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Invasion of the Soil Snatchers; Newcomers Push Out Native Plants</title>
    <meta content="24FLOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/24/nyregion/24FLOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Monmouth</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Delaware</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Moses, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDD1639F937A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Invasion of the Soil Snatchers; Newcomers Push Out Native Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses how native plants in New York metropolitan region are becoming increasingly pushed out of their soil by development and aggressive nonnative plants; several botanists comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The survey is not even halfway done, yet it has already revealed a disturbing trend: immigrants are forcing old-timers out of their homes.</p>
        <p>''The native plants that used to be here are being pushed out by development and aggressive nonnative plants,'' said Gerry Moore, a botanist with the Brooklyn Botanic Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The survey is not even halfway done, yet it has already revealed a disturbing trend: immigrants are forcing old-timers out of their homes.</p>
        <p>''The native plants that used to be here are being pushed out by development and aggressive nonnative plants,'' said Gerry Moore, a botanist with the Brooklyn Botanic Garden.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn garden is cataloging every variety of plant life in the New York metropolitan area. That flora project, a comprehensive effort to determine what plants exist in a 7,650-square-mile area of New York City, northern New Jersey, Long Island and Westchester and Orange Counties, is 10 years old. It is expected to take another 10 to 20 years to complete.</p>
        <p>After finding and identifying the plants, the researchers compare them with 100 years of historical records to see what is new, extinct, declining or increasing.</p>
        <p>The results so far do not bode well for many native plants.</p>
        <p>At a ditch next to Hurley Pond Road in Howell Township, in a rural section of Monmouth County, N.J., Steve Glenn, a project botanist, stepped over beer cans and into the scraggly scrub, his eyes trained on the ground. Across the road, Mr. Moore pushed through the bushes with seven wild cranberries in his hand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glenn bent over a thin-stemmed reed with blue-green leaves and brown-and-yellow tips. ''A Carex barattii,  Steve!'' Mr. Moore said. ''That's a rare one. Amazing. Plants like this are just hanging on by their toenails.''</p>
        <p>The first category of the study -- trees, shrubs and vines -- has been completed. A handful of botanists and scores of volunteers have cataloged about 450 species in the metropolitan area. Now they are working on wetlands and aquatic varieties, which number about 1,200. Next are the 2,700 types of grasses, and then ferns, wildflowers and miscellaneous weeds. When it has concluded, the project will start over from the beginning, cataloging the same places to see what has changed.</p>
        <p>Researchers hope that the survey will help them answer questions: Is it possible to track the decline in native species? How many Southern plants are spreading north, perhaps  as a result of global warming? Most important, how can native species be brought back to the city and the region?</p>
        <p>The survey has already documented the growing dominance of imported plants. The ditches by Hurley Pond Road in Howell Township provided a good example. On one side, dark green patches of Asian pachysandra flourished; on the other, Japanese honeysuckle was entwined with the shrubs and trees. Along the road were several swaths of land that had been cleared for construction.</p>
        <p>Throughout the region, many varieties of exotic trees, shrubs and vines that have taken root over the years are proliferating. Unlike the native species, which tend to grow more slowly and in one kind of habitat, the alien plants grow rapidly and thrive in varied habitats. About one-third of the plants in the New York area are nonnative, and some are spreading so rapidly that they are squeezing out and nearly annihilating the native ones, botanists say.</p>
        <p>One newcomer, Oriental bittersweet, was first raised in private gardens and botanical gardens in the late 1800's. Now that vine, with its brilliant orange fruit, is everywhere. It twists around trees and strangles them, in parks and forests and along highways.</p>
        <p>The multiflora rose, an Asian import with delicate white blossoms, was once a flower of choice for many gardeners, and was used for erosion control. Now, it blankets summer meadows that used to be yellow, pink and blue with goldenrod and asters, and it pushes up through asphalt cracks. ''Everywhere,'' Mr. Moore said. ''A terrible weed.''</p>
        <p>Phragmites and its smaller cousin, stiltgrass, have become a horror story for park managers and environmentalists. Nearly every waterbank and marsh in the region is surrounded by towering phragmites. The phragmites reeds choke ponds and lakes. They are extremely difficult to eradicate, with roots that extend six to eight feet into the ground.</p>
        <p>Robert Moses, the New York City parks commissioner from 1934 to 1960, was among those who planted tough foreign strains of phragmites in wetlands, which were considered disease-ridden swamps.</p>
        <p>''It grows so aggressively that nothing can take it on,'' Mr. Moore said. Wetlands where orchids once grew and lakes that had wild rice and cardinal flowers are clogged with phragmites and stiltgrass.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Glenn pushed through chest-high reeds, he said disgustedly,  ''This phragmites has become nothing but a monoculture.''</p>
        <p>There are more invaders. Black locust trees, which were imported for ship masts, and tree of heaven, intended as food for silkworms, are all over, pushing their way through concrete and thriving in poor soil. Floating water chestnut is taking over the Hudson and Delaware Rivers, and flashy purple loosestrife is crowding out native wildflowers in wetlands and meadows.</p>
        <p>A few native plants seem to have disappeared. The researchers could find no trace of micranthemum, a delicate plant with minute white flowers that once grew abundantly along riverbanks. They could only find a patch or two of bog rosemary. And they are scratching their heads over the near demise of pipsissewa, with lovely, fragrant white flowers, when a cousin, spotted wintergreen, is thriving in oak and pine forests.</p>
        <p>Blueberries, cranberries, huckleberries and wild azaleas have disappeared from the city and declined throughout the region, Mr. Glenn said.</p>
        <p>Once, pipsissewa, with shiny green leaves, dotted the pine and oak forests of New York, New Jersey and Long Island. ''Now it's gone, just gone,'' Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>But spotted wintergreen is doing quite well. Researchers suspect that deer are eating the pipsissewa, but avoiding the wintergreen because of its astringency.</p>
        <p>But it is the speed with which the invasive plants spread that has researchers shaking their heads. ''It only took the multiflora rose 40 years to spread,'' said Steve Clements, director of the project.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, tea viburnum, a tall ornamental shrub from China, was rarely seen even in private gardens. Now researchers have found it in 22 woodland and forest sites.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing it more and more,''  Mr. Moore said. ''It's definitely an established part of the wild flora. It's on the cusp. We're watching it. The red flags are up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
