<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Noxious Landfill to a Nurturing Colony for Artisans</title>
    <meta content="Y24CRA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/24/national/24CRAF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Blue Ridge</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DA113AF937A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Noxious Landfill to a Nurturing Colony for Artisans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From a Noxious Landfill to a Nurturing Colony for Artisans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PENLAND, N.C.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lush peaks and valleys of this Blue Ridge community have long been home to some of the nation's finest craft workshops.</p>
        <p>But Penland, about 50 miles northeast of Asheville, N.C., is also home to a much less welcome landmark: the former Mitchell County and Yancey County dump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The noxious fumes that once befouled a Blue Ridge landfill now create power and incubate the careers of a small colony of artists in energy-intensive fields</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lush peaks and valleys of this Blue Ridge community have long been home to some of the nation's finest craft workshops.</p>
        <p>But Penland, about 50 miles northeast of Asheville, N.C., is also home to a much less welcome landmark: the former Mitchell County and Yancey County dump.</p>
        <p>''It always seemed a scary place to me,'' said Jon Ellenbogen, a potter who for 30 years hauled his trash up the winding roads to the six-acre landfill before it closed in 1994. ''Without fail, whenever I ventured up there, my wheels would get stuck in the muck, forcing me to remain until one of the bulldozers pulled me out.''</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Ellenbogen and other artisans look forward to going to the old landfill site. In fact, they hope tour groups will visit.</p>
        <p>Since May, the noxious fumes that once befouled the landfill have been creating power and incubating the careers of a small colony of artists in energy-intensive fields. The power project uses methane gas, a flammable pollutant and byproduct of decomposing trash, to fuel furnaces for glass blowers and metal workers, and potters' kilns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellenbogen, board president of the nonprofit project, called EnergyXchange, estimated that the artists would save $1 million in energy costs during the 12 to 20 years the gas is expected to last.</p>
        <p>John Geci, a glass blower at the site and a former student at the Penland School of Crafts, said he was grateful for that.</p>
        <p>''Even though my work had begun selling,'' Mr. Geci said, ''there was no way I could afford the $1,000 per month it would have cost just to run the furnace.''</p>
        <p>The artists, two glass blowers and three potters, will pay $200 to $350 a month during their three-year fellowships to work in two Quonset huts on a six-acre site on top of the old landfill, which has one of the best views in the area. A third building will be used as a gallery and visitors' center, and another will be used for offices and business classes that will be offered free to the artists.</p>
        <p>''My perception of what it takes to be a successful artist has changed dramatically in the last five years,'' Mr. Geci said. ''Initially, I thought all that was required was the ability to make nice forms. Now, I recognize the business skills I'm going to need to survive, and I'm glad it's part of the program.''</p>
        <p>In a greenhouse, heated by methane, seedlings of native plants like rhododendrons and azaleas are grown for sale to local farmers.</p>
        <p>The project began when a Yancey County official read about a landfill recovery plan in Florida, said Terry Woodruff, the site's project manager and an employee of the Blue Ridge Resource Conservation and Development Council. Officials contacted the development council, an arm of the federal Agriculture Department, which set up EnergyXchange with Mayland Community College and HandMade in America, a nonprofit organization that fosters economic development with crafts. Organizers received several grants to start the project but are now trying to make it self-supporting with money from plant sales.</p>
        <p>In addition to nurturing artists and the local economy, the project helps the environment, Mr. Woodruff said.</p>
        <p>''If the gas weren't captured,'' he said, ''an estimated 7,500 tons of methane gas would be released into the atmosphere over the next 10 years here and on a neighboring landfill in Avery County.'' The greenhouse gases captured by the project are ''the equivalent of removing 21,002 cars from North Carolina roads,'' he said. ''That's a pretty substantial figure.''</p>
        <p>More projects are planned, said Becky Anderson, executive director of HandMade in America.</p>
        <p>''Once the buildings are finished, we'll be planting a heritage craft garden with plants that can be used for papermaking, basketry, dye and broom-making,'' Ms. Anderson said. ''Ours is in large part a creative economy in Western North Carolina, which is why it's so important to show people just how creative we can get in enhancing our own economic situation in an environmentally friendly manner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellenbogen, too, said he hoped EnergyXchange could be a model.</p>
        <p>''There are some 900 small landfills around the nation like ours,'' he said. ''We're the perfect example of how individual talents can be pooled for the greater good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
