<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Energy-Saving Rules Are Getting a Second Look</title>
    <meta content="Y31POWE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/31/politics/31POWE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Washing Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Heaters</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Heaters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Refrigeration Institute</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Association of Home Appliance</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D7123FF932A05750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Energy-Saving Rules Are Getting a Second Look</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Department is reviewing energy efficiency standards, issued in last weeks of Clinton administration, for new clothes washers, central air-conditioners and water heaters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department is reviewing energy efficiency standards, issued in the last weeks of the Clinton administration, that would require new clothes washers, water heaters and central air-conditioners to use less electricity and natural gas.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the department, Joseph H. Davis, confirmed that the new standards were under review, as part of an effort ordered by the White House to look at all regulations published in the last 60 days of the Clinton administration. People involved in the review said the standard under closest scrutiny was the one governing air-conditioners; if left standing, it would save the most electricity and reduce pollution from power plants the most, but would also impose the greatest costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department is reviewing energy efficiency standards, issued in the last weeks of the Clinton administration, that would require new clothes washers, water heaters and central air-conditioners to use less electricity and natural gas.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the department, Joseph H. Davis, confirmed that the new standards were under review, as part of an effort ordered by the White House to look at all regulations published in the last 60 days of the Clinton administration. People involved in the review said the standard under closest scrutiny was the one governing air-conditioners; if left standing, it would save the most electricity and reduce pollution from power plants the most, but would also impose the greatest costs.</p>
        <p>The rule requires that beginning in 2006, new central air-conditioners (and also central heat pumps, which can heat or cool) run on 30 percent less electricity than under current  minimum standards of efficiency. In negotiations that led to the rule, the manufacturers had pressed for improvement of only 20 percent. A lawsuit against the new standard has been filed by their trade association,  the Air Conditioning and Refrigeration Institute, which calls the extra cost of building more efficient machines a ''cruel penalty'' on consumers, to whom those costs would be passed on.</p>
        <p>When the rule was written last year, however, its backers called it a bargain for consumers, and they are even more strongly in support now that the price of electricity has been rising.</p>
        <p>The new standards for washers, water heaters and air-conditioners  were adopted to meet the requirements of a federal law. That legislation was adopted by Congress fully 14 years ago, but, as the Energy Department sat down to work out the details, Congress blocked the regulations in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>When the air-conditioner rule was finally issued this Jan. 17, Bill Richardson, the departing energy secretary, said the resulting reduction in energy bills and in pollution from power plants would be ''one of the biggest environmental achievements of the Clinton administration.''</p>
        <p>Now, though, that rule and the others are getting a second look. Staff members at the Energy Department say the agency's acting general counsel has asked them to prepare memorandums addressing whether the benefits of each of the rules might have been overstated or the costs understated, whether they could be considered an ''overreach'' and whether they pose a potential for litigation. The staff is also looking into whether any procedural errors were made in the rules' adoption.</p>
        <p>Bush administration officials say they can rescind any rule not yet in force.</p>
        <p>''It would be irresponsible and wrong,'' said Mr. Davis, the Energy Department spokesman, ''if the administration, newly elected and sworn into office, couldn't review regulations that have yet to take effect.''</p>
        <p>Some opponents, however, maintain that with the rules' publication in the Federal Register, the procedure would be more complicated. They also point to President Bush's depiction of ''an energy crisis'' in  defense of his decision to oppose limiting power plants' emissions of carbon dioxide, and to his call for more energy drilling and more use of ''clean coal'' technologies.</p>
        <p>Dan W. Reicher, who was assistant secretary for energy efficiency and renewable energy in the Clinton administration, said, ''It's stunning that at the very moment the new administration is telling us there's an energy crisis, they would be looking at rolling back standards that will save us more energy than virtually anything else we've done in 20 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reicher said the economics of the regulations looked even more favorable now, after a period of rising  prices for natural gas and electricity, than when the rules were drafted last year.</p>
        <p>Efficiency experts say that in California, air-conditioning consumes 28 percent of the electricity used during peak hours in summer, and that a standard that takes the low-efficiency models off the market would gradually reduce the need for new power plants.</p>
        <p>But the industry argues that the cost could exceed $5 billion and that  the pay-back period for consumers -- the length of time it would take for  their cumulative electricity savings to equal the additional cost of a higher-efficiency air-conditioner --  would be 9 to 14 years.</p>
        <p>The politics of the clothes-washer standard is more complicated. The manufacturers' trade group, the Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers, is pleading to keep the rule in place.</p>
        <p>''The whole rationale'' behind negotiations that led to that rule was that ''the members wanted a standard which they could plan towards,'' said Edward C. Foley Jr., director of the group's major-appliance and supplier division. ''Certainty is always better than uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>Under this rule, the improvements are to come in two stages, in 2004 and in 2007. The improvement in efficiency is put at 35 percent.</p>
        <p>As for the water-heater standard, which applies to both electric and gas models, the Gas Appliance Manufacturers Association petitioned the Energy Department earlier this month to revise it. If it is left to stand, water heaters will need more insulation and may require a U-shaped trap to stop hot water from rising up the pipe when no faucet is turned on, keeping the water in the heater until it is needed. Efficiency improvement is put at 5 to 9 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
