<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Coal and Climates</title>
    <meta content="Y16CAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/16/science/16CARB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Utica</location>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DD143DF935A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Coal and Climates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis: Pres Bush's reversal on campaign pledge to cut power plant emissions highlights difficulty of controlling carbon dioxide, which many scientists say is chief cause of global warming; chief sticking point is that carbon dioxide, unlike more familiar forms of pollution, is unavoidable byprodict of burning fuels (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's reversal this week on a pledge to cut power plant emissions highlights the difficulty of controlling carbon dioxide, a seemingly benign ingredient of the air people exhale, but also, many scientists say, a chief cause of global warming.</p>
        <p>A growing body of research has concluded that carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping greenhouse gases appear responsible for at least half of a warming trend over the last 50 years and pose a threat to ecosystems, water supplies, coastlines and tropical agriculture in the new century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's reversal this week on a pledge to cut power plant emissions highlights the difficulty of controlling carbon dioxide, a seemingly benign ingredient of the air people exhale, but also, many scientists say, a chief cause of global warming.</p>
        <p>A growing body of research has concluded that carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping greenhouse gases appear responsible for at least half of a warming trend over the last 50 years and pose a threat to ecosystems, water supplies, coastlines and tropical agriculture in the new century.</p>
        <p>Advocates on each side of the issue point to a long, varied list of factors  that have stalled efforts to control carbon dioxide in the United States and worldwide.</p>
        <p>These vary from the political influence of industries and energy companies that have plants that release the gas to the lack of any clear and present harm from the increase in carbon dioxide that has already occurred: a 25 percent gain since the late 1800's, almost all of it from smokestacks and tailpipes.</p>
        <p>But the chief sticking point is simply that carbon dioxide -- unlike more familiar forms of pollution, which can be filtered -- is for the moment an unavoidable byproduct of burning fuels, particularly fossil fuels, and especially the biggest source, coal.</p>
        <p>That means, as Mr. Bush stated this week in reversing his campaign promise, almost any effort to cut emissions must curtail the use of coal, which now supplies 56 percent of the country's electricity. And that means it would cost a lot of money.</p>
        <p>The cost is important not only to the domestic debate over the need for a law cleaning up power plants, but also to negotiations over the Kyoto Protocol, a 1997 treaty that would, if ratified, commit 38 industrialized countries to reduce greenhouse emissions. Each country, in calculating the merits of reductions, has a different estimate of how it would affect the economy.</p>
        <p>Those dependent on coal -- the United States, for example -- see mainly economic peril in a binding treaty. Those that generate most of their electricity with carbonless nuclear power -- France, for example -- are less likely to resist.</p>
        <p>But the cost is only one side of the calculus that leads either to action or inaction to blunt climate change, environmental experts say.</p>
        <p>The other is weighing risk: risk to health, ecosystems, agriculture and the like. Countries or communities generally have to perceive some definable threat on a clear timetable to be prompted to act to repel the threat or at least to invest in an insurance policy.</p>
        <p>In the past, pollution problems were almost always attacked only after those two conditions were satisfied. Lead was removed from gasoline because levels in blood were high. As unleaded gasoline became the norm, lead levels in blood sharply dropped.</p>
        <p>Other air pollutants -- like soot, sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides -- leave discernible fingerprints: grimy windows, sterilized mountain lakes downwind from power plants or eye-burning clouds of smog.</p>
        <p>In contrast, carbon dioxide, as opponents of cuts like to point out, is harder to cast as a villain. In fact, the skeptics say, no clear evidence exists that a crime has been committed.</p>
        <p>The gas is, after all, the substance that plants transform through photosynthesis into corn, pansies and rosewood.</p>
        <p>Finally, in instances where scientists say they have measured its effects, they are always secondary, indirect, and often far, far away from where most of the earth's human population is located.</p>
        <p>The most recent findings have come from melting mountain glaciers and satellites monitoring an increase in the amount of heat trapped in the upper atmosphere as greenhouse gases build.</p>
        <p>These are hardly the kinds of effects that are quick to generate a call for new laws or global treaties that could raise energy costs.</p>
        <p>A lack of urgency and a focus on costs both contributed to the breakdown of talks on the Kyoto in The Hague last November. The shift this week by Mr. Bush has, according to a variety of battle-worn veterans of the climate wars, threatened prospects for the next round of treaty talks, which are scheduled to take place in Bonn in July.</p>
        <p>The White House action left opponents of controls on carbon dioxide doing the e-mail equivalent of high-fives. On Tuesday night, the Cooler Heads Coalition, an informal network of groups opposing cuts in greenhouse gases, sent an urgent Internet alert from its chairman, Myron Ebell. ''We have won a famous victory, and everyone should congratulate themselves,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Still, some supporters of controlling carbon dioxide say they are confident that momentum will eventually swing their way, though perhaps slower than they would like.</p>
        <p>Sherwood L. Boehlert, a moderate Republican congressman who was first elected to represent Utica, N.Y., in 1982, said it took eight years of fighting for acid rain controls to be added to the Clean Air Act in 1990. Power plant emissions of the offending compounds, nitrogen oxides, have dropped but remain too high, Mr. Boehlert said.</p>
        <p>''And I still have some colleagues in the House telling me it's a figment of my imagination,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The same timetable is likely to hold true for actions to curtail global warming, said Mr. Boehlert, one of a small but growing minority of Republican officials seeking limits on carbon dioxide along with other air kinds of air pollution.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, undeterred by Mr. Bush's decision and a near certain prospect of failure, Mr. Boehlert and a bipartisan group of colleagues introduced House and Senate bills calling for exactly what the president rejected -- adding carbon dioxide to the list of power plant emissions to be cut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
