<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Industry Gives Nuclear Power A Second Look</title>
    <meta content="Y24NUK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/24/business/24NUKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1288114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D61F30F937A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Industry Gives Nuclear Power A Second Look</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass., April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time may be drawing near for building new nuclear power plants in US; reactors are so desirable that when old ones go on sale, bidding wars have broken out; Bush administration's energy plan is expected to include strong support for new reactor construction; supporters say that with improved reliability and design, new generation of reactors will be less expensive to operate than competing sources of electricity; nuclear waste remains an obstacle, but supporters believe that either a burial spot will be found or plants will be built to break down waste or reuse it; photos; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some regions of the country are short of electric power, and the price of natural gas, the most popular fuel for new power plants, has doubled. Windmills look promising but still produce only a tiny amount of power; solar power is even less significant.</p>
        <p>Nuclear reactors are now so desirable that when old ones go on sale, bidding wars have broken out. And the Bush administration's energy plan, scheduled for release soon, is expected to include strong support for new reactor construction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some regions of the country are short of electric power, and the price of natural gas, the most popular fuel for new power plants, has doubled. Windmills look promising but still produce only a tiny amount of power; solar power is even less significant.</p>
        <p>Nuclear reactors are now so desirable that when old ones go on sale, bidding wars have broken out. And the Bush administration's energy plan, scheduled for release soon, is expected to include strong support for new reactor construction.</p>
        <p>Does that mean it is time to order new ones?</p>
        <p>Not quite, according to a number of experts gathered at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology here to talk about the role of technology in a time of growing electric demand and increased concern about pollution. But after a 30-year hiatus, the time may be drawing closer.</p>
        <p>''There's some change in the wind,'' said Charles M. Vest, president of M.I.T., helping to open a two-day International Symposium on the Role of Nuclear Energy in a Sustainable Environment, sponsored by the university's Center for Advanced Nuclear Systems. Experts from France, Japan, Russia and the United States discussed designs that might be feasible in 30 years, or in 3 years.</p>
        <p>The group acknowledged obvious problems, like the fact that this country has still not decided what to do with reactor waste, but presumed that either a burial spot would be found or plants would be built to break down the waste or reuse it.</p>
        <p>The industry's trade association, the Nuclear Energy Institute, has assembled a task force on new nuclear deployment, which has met four times to draw up a business plan for new reactors. Participants include five companies that either operate or have recently bought plants -- Dominion Resources of Virginia, Entergy of New Orleans, Exelon of Chicago, Constellation Energy of Maryland and the Southern Company of Georgia.</p>
        <p>Industry executives say that the first new order for a reactor, if it comes, is likely to be at a site where other plants are already operating and the neighbors are used to a nuclear installation.</p>
        <p>As for what a new plant might look like, a great deal has changed since 1973, when the last plant that was not later canceled was ordered, and even since 1996, when the last one was finished. Experts say the designs or construction techniques of the 1970's are no more likely to return than other wonders of that era, like the Boeing 727 or the Saturn V rocket.</p>
        <p>One possibility is the ''pebble bed'' design, which circulates uranium fuel pellets shaped like billiard balls through the reactor and generates only about one-tenth as much heat per square foot as a conventional reactor. As a result, supporters assert that it cannot have a meltdown. The fuel balls in the pebble bed design are replaced as needed, but the reactor never has to shut down for refueling.</p>
        <p>The Exelon Corporation, which owns 17 reactors in this country, joined a partnership with a South African utility, Eskom, another South African company and BNFL, formerly known as British Nuclear Fuels, to build one in South Africa.  Exelon has asked the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to look at this design, but has not announced plans to build one in the United States.</p>
        <p>Other possible new designs range from simplified, refined versions of the Westinghouse and General Electric models in service today to the pebble bed. The regulatory commission approved new Westinghouse and General Electric designs in the late 1990's, and that, in itself, is a change; designs for the current generation of plants were not approved until the plants were built, sometimes leading to licensing delays.</p>
        <p>The nuclear division of Westinghouse, now owned by BNFL, says that its design has 60 percent fewer moving parts -- with fewer pumps, wires and pipes -- and that there is less to build and less to go wrong. It also has stairs in places where older designs had ladders, to accommodate an aging nuclear power plant work force.</p>
        <p>A new General Electric design is also meant to be simpler and safer. In 1996 a utility in Japan completed a reactor that resembled the design approved by American regulators.</p>
        <p>But other changes since the 1970's do not bode well for new reactor construction. In those days, the utilities that built generating stations were regulated monopolies that could take on large projects with the assurance that their customers would pay the price almost no matter what it was.</p>
        <p>''Somebody else was paying for your mistakes,'' said David Lochbaum, a nuclear reactor expert at the Union of Concerned Scientists, a nonprofit safety group, who did not attend the meeting here. Now, most power plants are built by unregulated suppliers that could be bankrupted by the cost overruns that were common when the last of the 103 reactors still running were completed.</p>
        <p>The unregulated companies prefer plants that can be put up quickly, with less financial risk.</p>
        <p>Nuclear waste is a more pressing problem than when the first plants were built. California, for example, has made it illegal to begin new reactors until the waste problem is solved. In every state, that will be an argument. The Energy Department was supposed to begin accepting spent fuel from reactors in 1998, but work on its proposed permanent repository, Yucca Mountain, near Las Vegas, has been slow. So far scientists have not ruled on its suitability.</p>
        <p>In addition, there are promising competitors, including windmills and fuel cells. Even though President Bush's budget proposes cuts in money available to research alternative forms of energy, many researchers are pursuing new technologies. And energy planners have been wrong for decades in prematurely predicting the end of oil, gas and coal.</p>
        <p>''When everybody in this room dies, fossil fuels are going to be abundant and inexpensive,'' said Michael W. Golay, a nuclear engineering professor here, to a gathering of about 40 nuclear experts.</p>
        <p>Supporters say that with improved reliability and design, the new generation of reactors will be less expensive to operate than the competing sources of electricity, coal and natural gas. But the numbers remain somewhat speculative.</p>
        <p>Still, the industry is getting a second look, for some of the same reasons nuclear power seemed attractive in the 1960's and 70's. Supporters argue that fossil fuel supplies are limited, that the United States should be developing technology to help the world electrify, and that pollution, especially emissions linked to global climate change, is a concern.</p>
        <p>Still, the industry was not helped by Mr. Bush's decision to drop the Kyoto accord on limiting carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>But another recent development has helped: the rise in the price of natural gas. About 90 percent of the plants built in the last 10 years use natural gas, but in California last winter, the price of that fuel reached $60 per million British thermal units, equivalent to oil at about $350 a barrel, or about seven times the current price, and some analysts expect it to stay in the range of $4 to $6 per million B.T.U., up from $2 to $3 a year ago.</p>
        <p>In response, some companies have announced plans to build coal-burning plants, but these require costly pollution controls, and even then, they will emit sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides, which cause acid rain and smog. The plants also produce carbon dioxide, which may eventually be regulated as a contributor to global climate change.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates call for investments in efficiency, and in ''renewable'' sources like wind and solar, but so far those sources are tiny compared with demand. The Chernobyl nuclear accident in Ukraine was 15 years ago, and Three Mile Island was 22 years ago; meanwhile, American reactors are operating with a record low level of minor incidents, and producing more power than ever. Plants are having their 40-year licenses extended for 20 years.</p>
        <p>The result, said Paul Jaskow, a former chairman of the economics department at M.I.T. and an expert on regulated industries, is that ''there has not been a better time for nuclear power in the last 25 years.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Jaskow, analyzing the recent power plant sales and separating the components, like long-term power purchase agreements, trust funds for reactor decommissioning, and sale of nuclear fuel, concluded, that ''none of these deals even comes close to covering the book costs.''</p>
        <p>''You couldn't justify paying $2,000 or $3,000 per kilowatt for those plants,'' he said, referring to the price per unit capacity.</p>
        <p>Supporters say they could build plants for about $1,000 per kilowatt of capacity, but similar claims in the 1960's and 70's were way off, and nearly bankrupted some utilities.</p>
        <p>The regulatory commission has simplified the licensing procedure, to reduce the possibility of lengthy delays, but industry experts are skeptical because the new procedure has not been used.</p>
        <p>Investors would have to expect a huge competitive benefit from nuclear plants to risk putting money in a new one, Mr. Jaskow said, ''because of the significant possibility of coming up with a dry hole.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 2001, Saturday  An article in Business Day on Tuesday about a resurgence of interest in nuclear power included a company erroneously among members of a task force on new nuclear deployment set up by the industry's trade association, the Nuclear Energy Institute. Constellation Energy of Maryland is not a member.</p>
        <p>The article also misspelled the surname of a former economics chairman at M.I.T. who said this was a good time for nuclear power. He is Paul L. Joskow, not Jaskow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 2001, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Tuesday about a resurgence of interest in nuclear power included a company erroneously among members of a task force on new nuclear deployment set up by the industry's trade association, the Nuclear Energy Institute. Constellation Energy of Maryland is not a member.</p>
        <p>The article also misspelled the surname of a former economics chairman at M.I.T. who said this was a good time for nuclear power. He is Paul L. Joskow, not Jaskow.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
