<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; The Route to Real Safety May Be the Open Road</title>
    <meta content="05DEPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/05/weekinreview/05DEPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mexico</location>
        <org class="online_producer">North American Free Trade Agreement</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3DE133CF936A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; The Route to Real Safety May Be the Open Road</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Route to Real Safety May Be the Open Road</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Issue of Mexican truck access to US highways, intertwined with Nafta free trade agreement, discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICAN truck drivers and their union, along with a number of Democrats and Republicans, have been battling to keep Mexican trucks in Mexico. In doing so, they have shaped the debate so that it seems to be about safety and not protectionism. But another way to think about it is as a fight over economic power and how to use it in a rapidly globalizing world.</p>
        <p>The fundamental premise behind international trade pacts like the North American Free Trade Agreement is that when countries work together, the result of their combined efforts is greater than what any of them could deliver to their people by controlling their economies alone. In other words, under this theory, the best way to stronger, more equitable economies is not by relying on traditional methods of sovereign control, in which strong powers dictate to weak ones, often sowing resentment, resistance and retribution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the controversy over Mexican truckers continues, it is becoming clearer that power is not shared equally in the North American Free Trade Agreement</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICAN truck drivers and their union, along with a number of Democrats and Republicans, have been battling to keep Mexican trucks in Mexico. In doing so, they have shaped the debate so that it seems to be about safety and not protectionism. But another way to think about it is as a fight over economic power and how to use it in a rapidly globalizing world.</p>
        <p>The fundamental premise behind international trade pacts like the North American Free Trade Agreement is that when countries work together, the result of their combined efforts is greater than what any of them could deliver to their people by controlling their economies alone. In other words, under this theory, the best way to stronger, more equitable economies is not by relying on traditional methods of sovereign control, in which strong powers dictate to weak ones, often sowing resentment, resistance and retribution.</p>
        <p>Rather, nations in cross-border compacts knowingly cede some control over how their economies work in exchange for advantages like open access and equality of treatment that are supposed to level the playing field for everyone. And that, in turn, increases trade and spreads the wealth.</p>
        <p>That's been the theory, anyway. Now, as the agreements begin to mature, it is becoming clearer that power is not shared equally. And so the strongest members, when they worry about surrendering sovereignty, may be worrying for nothing. Their economic might, it turns out, is often not diminished at all, but simply transformed into a kind of stealth power, enabling them to exert even greater influence and achieve broader goals.</p>
        <p>Take the border ban. The truckers want the United States to use power in the old way to keep out Mexicans drivers and their rigs, requiring them to undergo special safety inspections on the premise that many are unsafe. Underlying this is a calculation that this gives the American trucking industry, and its drivers, a more secure future. The decision by the United States, dating to the Clinton administration, to ignore the provisions of Nafta that would have freed long-haul trucks from Mexico, the United States and Canada -- the third leg of the Nafta trinity -- to cross the borders unhindered, clearly violates the agreement that took effect in 1994. And, in the minds of many experts, it is also likely to hurt the American trucking fleet more than it helps it.</p>
        <p>What often gets overlooked, these experts say, is that the border ban is reciprocal -- and that the American trucking industry is in a position to play that to its own advantage. Aaron Dichter, Mexico's under secretary for transportation, said American trucks operating in Mexico face the same restriction as Mexican trucks in the United States. They can cross the border but cannot leave a narrow commercial zone that extends no more than 20 miles. Like Mexican drivers on the other side, they drop loads at transfer points, from which domestic trucks and drivers complete the delivery.</p>
        <p>Mexican trucking executives say that even if border blockades are lifted by the end of this year, as President Bush has promised, only a few of the biggest Mexican rigs could make deliveries deep into the United States. The patchwork of regulations, including a requirement that trucks be licensed in every state where they operate, intimidates most truckers.</p>
        <p>WHAT is most likely to happen, say Mexico experts like George W. Grayson of the College of William and Mary, is that the better-financed and more competitive American trucking outfits will enter the growing Mexican market either through joint ventures or in head-to-head competition. ''I'd be surprised if, two or three years after the border was opened, 80 to 85 percent of long hauls from Mexico weren't handled by the U.S. trucking fleet,'' Professor Grayson said.</p>
        <p>Of course, this example echoes the basic argument for the efficiencies of global trade that have been put forward by all recent American presidents, from Ronald Reagan to George W. Bush. ''If you relax your total control, you can more effectively enhance your economy and your development,'' said Robert A. Pastor, an Emory University political scientist and former member of the National Security Council.</p>
        <p>In the old days, when bashing the United States was a stock in trade for many Latin American populists, Mexico built walls around its economy to keep from being smothered by the United States. But those walls didn't feed their people. However much that protectionism gratified Mexican nationalists, ''they found themselves deteriorating behind the walls and eventually had to dismantle them,'' Professor Pastor said. As a result, since Nafta came into effect in 1994, exports from Mexico have grown faster than from any other nation. But in the same period, American investments in almost every sector of the Mexican economy have grown too.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Canada has long resented American arrogance and for many years tried to keep the United States out. In the 1970's, the nationalist government of Pierre Trudeau severely limited foreign investment in Canadian oil and controlled prices. Exploration and drilling all but stopped, and the industry stagnated.</p>
        <p>After entering free trade agreements with the United States, Canada lost the power to erect such obstacles. But its energy exports have boomed, and it is now the United States' No. 1 foreign supplier of oil and natural gas.</p>
        <p>Pierre S. Pettigrew, Canada's minister of international trade, sees the growth of American power and  accepts it because of the benefits it brings Canada. ''There are certain things that can no longer be legislated because we've signed international agreements,'' he said. ''But in so doing, the U.S. ends up being even more powerful because you have another kind of relationship that is growing, that is developing, that is strengthening all elements of the three countries.''</p>
        <p>While such a system produces winners in all three countries, it also produces friction, especially when it seems that a state's sovereignty has been compromised. Mr. Pettigrew was in Washington last week to meet with his American and Mexican counterparts to tinker with the part of Nafta that gives unelected tribunals the power to secretly resolve disputes between international investors and governments.</p>
        <p>Still, most nations -- including the United States under President Bush -- are eager to join international trade agreements, if only as a measure of self-protection against the growing power of competing trade blocs in other areas, like the European Union.</p>
        <p>THAT doesn't mean, however, that the Bush administration likes all international agreements to the same degree, especially compacts that are not about trade. President Bush has steadfastly refused to submit to international agreements like the Kyoto protocol on greenhouse gases, the small-arms control pact and other treaties. The inconsistency has angered allies and given opponents issues to focus on.</p>
        <p>''The White House should follow its own advice consistently,'' said one, Thomas F. McLarty III, who was President Clinton's chief of staff. ''It's pretty clear that in an interconnected world, the U.S. is going to have to engage with, and not dictate, to our partners.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to the Clinton administration's approach to international agreements, the current administration clearly prefers to pick only those compacts where surrendering control may actually increase American economic power, while passing on those that simply acknowledge the globe's interconnectedness.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
