<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buffalo Journal; A Striped Parade Comes for the Chicken</title>
    <meta content="20JOUR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/20/nyregion/20JOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1295073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Day Care Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Buffalo (New York)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Black Rock</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Riverside</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DF173DF933A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buffalo Journal; A Striped Parade Comes for the Chicken</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theories abound as to why skunks are suddenly sweet on Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The skunks arrived after being displaced from once-pastoral towns in the grip of a building boom at the city's border. They started pawing garbage cans when railroad tracks in the city were torn up to make way for housing -- or was it when a former dog food plant was torn down? Others say it's the raccoons, stupid, arguing that a recent drop in the raccoon population cleared the way for skunks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theories abound as to why skunks are suddenly sweet on Buffalo.</p>
        <p>The skunks arrived after being displaced from once-pastoral towns in the grip of a building boom at the city's border. They started pawing garbage cans when railroad tracks in the city were torn up to make way for housing -- or was it when a former dog food plant was torn down? Others say it's the raccoons, stupid, arguing that a recent drop in the raccoon population cleared the way for skunks.</p>
        <p>Frank L. Poincelot, the head pest control and wildlife officer for the City of Buffalo, who once had a pet skunk named Herbie (more on that later), acknowledges all of the above. But he offers a more whimsical hypothesis. He insists that skunks are drawn to the same finger food that put Buffalo on the culinary map.</p>
        <p>''A skunk will eat anything from mice to rats to bugs, but they love chicken wings,'' he said, with just a trace of facetiousness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poincelot should know. In what has been the worst skunk season in modern memory, he has trapped and destroyed 45 skunks since Feb. 1, using mainly chicken meat and chicken fat for bait. (One skunk would come only for strawberry shortcake.)</p>
        <p>Buffalo does not need this now. The city is already smarting from a population drain, and the Buffalo area has one of the highest unemployment rates among major metropolitan regions in the country. But New York State's second-largest city is nonetheless wearing an unmistakably musky cologne these days, particularly in the more modest neighborhoods on the city's west side.</p>
        <p>It is a searing aroma, pleasantly associated, in some minds anyway, with balmy nighttime drives through an inky countryside. But in the scrappy neighborhoods where chain-link fences delineate postage-stamp yards, and people plop upholstered couches on listing front porches, the smell is not fleeting, and residents wish it would go away.</p>
        <p>Nursing a beer in a corner bar on a recent weekday morning, Martha Benjamin, 55, who lives in the Black Rock neighborhood, said she had armed herself with a can of lilac air freshener, kept by her bedside. ''I see the skunks at least three times a week in my backyard,'' she said, ''and the smell goes right into the bedroom.''</p>
        <p>Kimberly Hall, 23, who also lives in Black Rock and works in a local day care center, had another, but less effective, weapon: tomato soup. After her German shepherd got into a dust-up with a skunk, she maneuvered him into the bathtub and doused him with 12 cans of tomato soup. ''It really didn't work,'' she recalled. (Mr. Poincelot and other experts say a solution of hydrogen peroxide, baking soda and liquid detergent is, if not a magic bullet, more effective than tomatoes.)</p>
        <p>Like other Black Rock residents, James F. Strach noticed an uptick in the number of skunks after the demolition of a nearby dog food plant a few years back. Since November, when an abandoned house across the street from his home began attracting illegal dumpers, Mr. Strach has seen even more.</p>
        <p>''I've been here 57 years, and I intend to die here,'' said Mr. Strach, a retired store-window designer. ''It's not that I dislike skunks. But I don't like them hanging around my neighborhood because it indicates decay and decline.''</p>
        <p>Other sections of Buffalo that have proved attractive to skunks include the University and Riverside neighborhoods. ''Skunk complaints are outnumbering rat complaints by 3 to 1,'' bemoaned Betty Jean Grant, a city councilwoman who represents the University district. ''People see them at 5 in the morning walking across the street, lined up according to size. It's like a parade.''</p>
        <p>What most people fear is the spray, an oily, yellowish liquid squirted by the skunk when provoked. ''It's toxic,'' Mr. Poincelot said. ''It can take your breath away and burn your skin and eyes. Skunks have excellent aim. When that tail comes up and they look at you, you're already hit.''</p>
        <p>Skunks, like rats, are attracted to garbage, whether piled in vacant lots or tied up in flimsy plastic bags left at the curb. The three neighborhoods with the worst skunk problem are also among the last to benefit from a city program to blanket Buffalo with special vermin-proof garbage cans: 95-gallon containers on wheels, with tight-fitting lids.</p>
        <p>Mr. Poincelot said the city would finally distribute cans to residents in those areas by July 1. ''It will make a huge difference for the entire city of Buffalo,'' he said. In the meantime, Mr. Poincelot and the nine people on his rodent-control team are bracing for late June, when the recent breeding season comes to fruition.</p>
        <p>The baby skunks will pose a quandary for Mr. Poincelot, a former zoo keeper at the Buffalo Zoo who says it pains him to kill anything. After trapping adult skunks, he gasses them with carbon dioxide. But he takes a more humane approach with the young. ''Most of the time,'' he said, ''I release the little kids 20 or 30 miles out of Buffalo on state lands.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Poincelot may be the only rodent-control officer in the country with a soft spot for skunks. He owned Herbie, a pet skunk whose scent glands had been removed, for four years in the early 1970's. ''They're really cute and make damn good pets,'' he said. ''He used to sleep in bed with me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
