<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Gets What Slice of the President's First Federal Budget Pie</title>
    <meta content="MB002430" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1284645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT'S BUDGET: THE BREAKDOWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norton, Gale (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DA1F3EF933A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Gets What Slice of the President's First Federal Budget Pie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Breakdown of Pres Bush's proposed 3.9 percent cut in Interior Department spending, to about $10 million, and proposed 6.4 percent cut in Environmental Protection Agency spending, to $7.3 billion; Interior Sec Gale A Norton and EPA head Christie Whitman defend cuts; table (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environment</p>
        <p>Officials at the Interior Department and the Environmental Protection Agency defended President Bush's requests for a combined 5 percent cut from this year's spending levels, saying they represented reversions to historically normal levels after an unusual surge in environmental spending this year that was due in part to pork-barrel Congressional appropriations and to emergency spending on wildfires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Environment</p>
        <p>Officials at the Interior Department and the Environmental Protection Agency defended President Bush's requests for a combined 5 percent cut from this year's spending levels, saying they represented reversions to historically normal levels after an unusual surge in environmental spending this year that was due in part to pork-barrel Congressional appropriations and to emergency spending on wildfires.</p>
        <p>Interior Secretary Gale A. Norton said the request of about $10 billion for her department, a reduction of 3.9 percent, was ''compassionate in the way it protects our environment and conservative in how it spends taxpayers' money.''</p>
        <p>In terms of new spending, some of the biggest increases proposed by the administration would try to give the states a bigger role in land conservation programs and in the enforcement of environmental laws. A grant of $450 million, up from $90 million this year, would go to states for programs designed to enhance recreation and conserve wildlife habitat as part of the Land and Water Conservation Fund. A separate grant of $25 million would help to finance state efforts to enforce environmental laws, as part of an E.P.A. effort to shift some of that responsibility from the federal government to the states.</p>
        <p>Other big increases would help support initiatives that have alarmed environmentalists: the stepped-up energy exploration the administration is proposing on federal lands, both onshore and offshore. Some $5 million would be set aside for studies intended to make preparations for oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge by 2004, a goal that is supported by the administration but faces an uphill battle in Congress. At the Bureau of Land Management and the Marine Minerals Management Service, spending related to oil, gas and coal exploration would increase by 19 percent and 12 percent, respectively.</p>
        <p>But even those agencies would face significant overall cuts, as would others including the United States Geological Service, whose budget would drop by 8 percent. Overall spending on clean air, clean water, safe food, waste management and other environmental goals would also decline, as would, though only slightly, the money set aside for the reduction of heat-trapping gases that are believed to contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>For one program, a Treasury Department fund designed to promote conservation of tropical forests, the administration is proposing $13 million in spending, the same as this year's level. But the figure is considerably less than the $100 million President Bush promised in his fall campaign.</p>
        <p>At the E.P.A., whose $7.3 billion budget request includes a 6.4 percent spending cut, Christie Whitman, the agency's administrator, noted that the new figure was still $56 million higher than the Clinton administration's last budget request. For the most part, Mrs. Whitman said, the cuts reflected a carving of Congressionally mandated programs that had ''not necessarily been a priority of the agency.''</p>
        <p>DOUGLAS JEHL</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT'S BUDGET: THE BREAKDOWN  Correction:  April 11, 2001, Wednesday  A chart yesterday with an article about President Bush's budget proposal for federal agencies misstated the sum the Interior Department would provide to states for land conservation. It is $450 million, not billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2001, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A chart yesterday with an article about President Bush's budget proposal for federal agencies misstated the sum the Interior Department would provide to states for land conservation. It is $450 million, not billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
