<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DF103EF931A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1205" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bush Maintains Opposition To Global Warming Accord  President Bush made clear that he had no intention of reversing his opposition to the Kyoto climate accord supported by the European leaders he is to meet with this week. And he strongly suggested that any new accord must also bind developing nations, especially China and India, to the kind of commitments that would be made by the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bush Maintains Opposition To Global Warming Accord  President Bush made clear that he had no intention of reversing his opposition to the Kyoto climate accord supported by the European leaders he is to meet with this week. And he strongly suggested that any new accord must also bind developing nations, especially China and India, to the kind of commitments that would be made by the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israeli-Palestinian Talks  Security officials from both sides met for four hours but failed to reach an agreement on an American proposal that would extend the fragile and partial 10-day-old cease-fire, according to a Palestinian official involved. The official also said that C.I.A. Director George J. Tenet, who mediated, had told negotiators that he was uncertain that he would be willing to continue the talks. The toll of the violence rose with the death of a 5-month-old Israeli, Yehuda Haim Shoham, who was injured last week by Palestinian stone throwers.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATO Detentions in Kosovo  International peacekeepers said they detained 19 men over the weekend on suspicion of belonging to the ethnic Albanian rebel army fighting government forces in Macedonia.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.N. Drug Director Faulted  Internal investigations of the United Nations Office of Drug Control and Crime Prevention in Vienna found that poor management by the program's executive director, Pino Arlacchi, was costing the office money and talent, leaving the staff demoralized and in the dark.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Filipino Rebels Report Execution  Muslim rebels said they had killed an American hostage, Guillermo Sobero of Corona, Calif., one of the three dozen foreign and Filipino captives whom they hold. The military cautioned that the group had lied about such killings in the past.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Australian to Visit U.S.  Prime Minister John Howard, who has backed the Bush administration on Taiwan, the environment and missile defense, will visit Washington in September.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A22-30</p>
        <p>Death Sentence Is Fulfilled For Oklahoma City Bomber  Timothy J. McVeigh, 33, was put to death by injection in the federal prison in Terre Haute, Ind., in a procedure watched in person and on closed-circuit television by some survivors and relatives of victims. He made no final remarks but issued a statement quoting the 1875 poem ''Invictus.'' He was the first federal prisoner executed since 1963.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>High-Tech Snooping Barred  The Supreme Court ruled, 5 to 4, that police use of a thermal imaging device to detect patterns of heat coming from a private home is a search that requires a warrant. The court said the requirement would also apply to any systems that let the police gain knowledge that in the past would have required physical entry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Forecast for Social Security  The co-chairmen of President Bush's Social Security commission said they would probably have to propose politically difficult steps like raising the retirement age and reducing cost of living adjustments to restore the system's long-term financial health.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>No Checks in the Mail  More than one-quarter of American adults will not get an income tax rebate this year. Nearly 40 percent will not get the full $300 for individuals or $600 for couples. The main reason is that after deductions, exemptions and credits, those people paid little or nothing in income taxes.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Ethanol Rule to Be Enforced  The Bush administration decided California must use ethanol as an antipollution fuel additive, a move critics say may push pump prices up 5 cents a gallon this summer in California and in northeastern states, which were ready to seek an exemption if California's had been granted.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>A Kennedy Stays on the Sideline  Maxwell Taylor Kennedy, the 36-year-old son of Robert F. Kennedy, said he would not seek the House seat held by Joe Moakley, who died of leukemia last month and had planned to retire after the current term. Mr. Kennedy, a lawyer who heads a nonprofit environmental group, cited family considerations.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>U.S. Bribery Investigation Of a Lauder Company  A company owned by Ronald S. Lauder, the cosmetics heir and former New York City mayoral candidate, who has worked to build a media empire in Eastern Europe, is under federal investigation because of accusations that it paid at least $1 million in bribes to Ukrainian officials for a television license.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Anger in the Bronx  Some Longwood residents played videotape that they said showed police officers overreacting to disturbances on Sunday night, after the National Puerto Rican Day Parade.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Ruling on Schools and Religion  The Supreme Court, ruling 6 to 3 in a New York case, said public schools must open their doors to after-school religious activities, including those that involve young children, on the same basis as any other after-hours activity that school policy permits.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New High School for Manhattan  The Board of Education will create an old-fashioned neighborhood high school, once thought an endangered species, on the Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Solar Flare Radiation Risk  Scientists say there may be a cause for concern about radiation exposure for people who fly at high altitudes during solar ''storm seasons,'' like the one occurring now, when solar flares intensify the solar winds.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F6</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Fewer Making House Payments  The number of Americans behind on their mortgage payments has risen sharply in the last year, suggesting to some analysts that many new homeowners, who were part of a celebrated surge in house-buying during the last decade, may not be able to afford their mortgages during slow economic times, with energy costs and unemployment rising.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Windows Phone System  Microsoft's new Windows XP operating system for PC's, which is to be made commercially available on Oct. 25, includes software intended to greatly expand the ability to make telephone calls -- and find phone numbers -- over the Internet.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Warnaco Files for Bankruptcy  The apparel company filed for Chapter 11 protection, blaming the economy and its heavy debt load, among other things, for its problems. Warnaco sells brands like Speedo, Calvin Klein and Chaps by Ralph Lauren.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A31</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A32-33</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Bush's European debut; proselytizing in the schools; solutions for gridlock at La Guardia.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
