<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="28DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1288851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DD1139F93BA15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Economic Growth Continues At an Annual Pace of 2%  The economy showed surprising resilience in the first three months of this year, growing at a 2 percent annual rate and extending the longest American expansion on record to a full 10 years, the government reported.</p>
        <p>Despite widespread concerns that a recession could be looming, overall economy activity accelerated in the first quarter. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Economic Growth Continues At an Annual Pace of 2%  The economy showed surprising resilience in the first three months of this year, growing at a 2 percent annual rate and extending the longest American expansion on record to a full 10 years, the government reported.</p>
        <p>Despite widespread concerns that a recession could be looming, overall economy activity accelerated in the first quarter. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Germany Is a Concern for Europe  German economic growth has lagged behind the European average for years now, not as strong in good times and slumping more seriously in bad times. And now, as Europeans nervously ponder their chances of escaping the worst effects of a slowdown in the United States, Germany is once again the Continent's biggest source of anemia. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Dow Breaks Into Positive Territory  The Dow Jones industrial average wiped out its losses for the year, led by advances in Intel, Wal-Mart and Citigroup. The Dow rose 117.70 points, or 1.1 percent, to 10,810.05, giving it a 0.2 percent gain in 2001. The Nasdaq composite index rose 40.82 points, or 2 percent, to 2,075.70. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 18.53 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,253.05. For the year, the Nasdaq has lost 16 percent and the S.&amp; P. 500 5 percent. [C3.]</p>
        <p>More Discussion on Global Warming  In the wake of its rejection of an international treaty to curtail global warming, the Bush administration is seeking advice from a wide array of scientists, economists, business representatives and policy experts as it tries to forge a new approach. [A10.]</p>
        <p>Poor Earnings for Taiwan Chip Maker  Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing said its net income plunged 16.6 percent in the first quarter, below the reduced expectations of analysts. The results capped a week of dismal economic news from Taiwan and showed how hard the slowdown in American technology spending has pinched Asian suppliers. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Strike Leads to Comair Layoffs  Comair, Delta Air Line's commuter airline, said it would lay off about 2,000 employees because of a strike by its pilots that began March 26. The layoffs affect about half of Comair's nonstriking employees, in all departments, the Cincinnati-based carrier said. [C3.]</p>
        <p>$1.4 Million Investment at Airline  In a rare vote of confidence, Sir Christopher Bland, the newly appointed chairman of British Telecommunications, will invest about $1.4 million of his own money in the debt-ridden company. Sir Christopher will replace Sir Iain Vallance on Monday. [C2.]</p>
        <p>An Under-40 Prize in Economics  The American Economics Association named Matthew Rabin of the University of California at Berkeley as the best economist in the United States under age 40. Mr. Rabin, 37, will receive the John Bates Clark medal, which the association awards every other year. He is the first winner to openly embrace behavioral economics, which attempts to incorporate psychology into standard economic theory. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Greenspan Predicts Large Surpluses  Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, predicted that the United States would produce large budget surpluses for some time, permitting it ultimately to pay off the publicly held portion of the national debt. He also offered reassurances on the effect of a dwindling supply of low-risk government debt. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Software Maker to Sell Units  Lernout &amp; Hauspie Speech Products, which makes speech-recognition and translation software, has hired Credit Suisse First Boston to help it find buyers for its units as it tries to avoid insolvency, after having trouble in attracting interest, said Philippe Bodson, the company's new chief executive. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 2001, Monday  A headline in the Business Digest on Saturday about a $1.4 million investment by Sir Christopher Bland, the newly appointed chairman of British Telecommunications, referred to the company incorrectly. The investment was in telecommunications, not in an airline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 2001, Monday</p>
        <p>A headline in the Business Digest on Saturday about a $1.4 million investment by Sir Christopher Bland, the newly appointed chairman of British Telecommunications, referred to the company incorrectly. The investment was in telecommunications, not in an airline.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
