<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Director's Journey Into A Darkness Of the Heart</title>
    <meta content="24LYMA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/24/movies/moviesspecial/24LYMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1304070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spielberg, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kubrick, Stanley (1928-99)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ai (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Osment, Haley Joel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D71131F937A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="3975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Director's Journey Into A Darkness Of the Heart</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Spielberg's Journey Into a Darkness of the Heart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Steven Spielberg on eve of opening of his new movie, AI Artificial Intelligence, project initiated by his hero, Stanley Kubrick, in mid-80's, that two directors briefly worked on together in early 90's and that Spielberg inherited when Kubrick died in 1999; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR more than a quarter-century, Steven Spielberg has been at the pinnacle of American filmmaking, the most famous, influential and consistently successful director in Hollywood. Beginning as a shaggy-haired wunderkind in the early 1970's, with a cadre of similar film school dreamers, he revolutionized movie-making and revitalized the classic Hollywood genres. He grew into a director who alternated between exploiting the visceral pleasures of pure, hyper-charged cinema in films like ''Jurassic Park'' and the ''Indiana Jones'' series and one who exploded the boundaries of the mainstream with bolder fare like ''Schindler's List'' and ''Saving Private Ryan.''</p>
        <p>Now, after a self-imposed three-year hiatus, he is back -- having taken the baton from one of his heroes, Stanley Kubrick, on ''A.I. Artificial Intelligence,'' a project that Kubrick initiated in the mid-80's, that the two directors briefly worked on together in the early 90's and that Mr. Spielberg inherited when Kubrick died in 1999. What is most surprising about the result is that while it plies the same territory as some of Mr. Spielberg's work of two decades ago, a world of benevolent science fiction as seen through the sensibilities of a child, this time he has married it to the darker, emotional currents of his later, adult films. No doubt partly under the influence of his long collaboration with Kubrick on this project, his latest answers are not so simple.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>font size="-1" (June 24, 2001) Filming Stanley Kubrick's "A.I.," Stephen Spielberg welds the benevolent science fiction of his past with darker, emotional currents of his later, adult films.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR more than a quarter-century, Steven Spielberg has been at the pinnacle of American filmmaking, the most famous, influential and consistently successful director in Hollywood. Beginning as a shaggy-haired wunderkind in the early 1970's, with a cadre of similar film school dreamers, he revolutionized movie-making and revitalized the classic Hollywood genres. He grew into a director who alternated between exploiting the visceral pleasures of pure, hyper-charged cinema in films like ''Jurassic Park'' and the ''Indiana Jones'' series and one who exploded the boundaries of the mainstream with bolder fare like ''Schindler's List'' and ''Saving Private Ryan.''</p>
        <p>Now, after a self-imposed three-year hiatus, he is back -- having taken the baton from one of his heroes, Stanley Kubrick, on ''A.I. Artificial Intelligence,'' a project that Kubrick initiated in the mid-80's, that the two directors briefly worked on together in the early 90's and that Mr. Spielberg inherited when Kubrick died in 1999. What is most surprising about the result is that while it plies the same territory as some of Mr. Spielberg's work of two decades ago, a world of benevolent science fiction as seen through the sensibilities of a child, this time he has married it to the darker, emotional currents of his later, adult films. No doubt partly under the influence of his long collaboration with Kubrick on this project, his latest answers are not so simple.</p>
        <p>In ''A.I.,'' death is real, the world is cruel, innocents suffer wounds that can never fully heal, fairy tales come with their edges intact and magical resurrections are possible only at a bitter and tragic cost. And ''Minority Report,'' another science-fiction film he is about to finish shooting, may well carry him further in that darker direction.</p>
        <p>''I have made a lot of the films that I wanted to make over the last 25 years,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''But the thing that I've allowed myself is to let time change my mind about the kind of films I always thought I wanted to make. I've left myself open to how my tastes have changed with my ever-changing life. And with such a large family, my tastes have changed. I am particularly, at this point in my life, somewhat interested in going back a little bit to my past, to tell the kinds of stories I'd like my kids to see. You know, between 'Schindler' and 'Ryan,' I had a lot of complaints from my kids that I'm not making movies for them anymore.''</p>
        <p>''A.I.'' may be an answer to that plea, but if so, it is strong medicine. On a surface level it resembles earlier Spielberg films. It is difficult, for instance, to resist comparisons to another film with initials for a title,  ''E.T.'' (1982), since both films have a child protagonist and take place in a world of science-fiction, fantasy and wonderment. But it is the chasm between the two films that is most striking. Imagine if the scientists in ''E.T.'' had actually captured the alien and dissected him, or that there was no miraculous recovery from his mysterious ailment, and you will not be far off. In ''A.I.,'' Mr. Spielberg is clearly trying to push the audience, even a younger audience, into confronting harder truths and deeper emotions.</p>
        <p>''A.I.'' is set in the distant future, when global warming has flooded coastal cities and the remnants of society are waited upon by convincingly human robots who provide such services as housecleaning, child care and, with astonishing explicitness for a Spielberg movie, sexual satisfaction. (In a supporting role, Jude Law plays a robot called Gigolo Joe, who is seen meeting lonely women in seedy hotel rooms and seducing them with boasts of his sexual prowess.) It is about what happens when scientists build the first child robot capable of love, to ease the loneliness of childless parents. What might happen, Mr. Spielberg asks, if this loving, synthetic creature, played in the film by Haley Joel Osment, is not loved in return?</p>
        <p>''I think 'A.I.' is a film for my own kids, approached entirely differently from my earlier films and requiring a lot more tolerance on their part, to get through some of the stuff that might be a little beyond their reach, to be able to understand some of the things that come later and will be more viscerally interesting to them,'' Mr. Spielberg said.</p>
        <p>It is not, he said, a film that he would have dared to make two decades ago.</p>
        <p>''I would have played it safer than I think I did with 'A.I,' '' he said. ''I don't think 'A.I.' is a safe story, at all. I think it is a solid story, and I think it is an emotional story, but it is also a divergent story that takes you in several directions at the same time and then asks you to bring it all back at the end of a very emotional odyssey to understand what you have seen.''</p>
        <p>MR. SPIELBERG, 53, was working his way through a pair of Subway turkey sandwiches on a round wooden table set up outside his trailer on the 20th Century Fox lot. He had only just completed the final dubbing and color-correcting on ''A.I.,'' which was to have its first pre-release screenings in the next few days, and was within two weeks of finishing a follow-up film called ''Minority Report.'' He said he had read an article about people who lost weight on a diet of Subway sandwiches. ''I thought if I ate them at just one meal a day, I'd lose the last four pounds that I need to get rid of,'' the rail-thin director said with a grin.</p>
        <p>The release of Mr. Spielberg's first film since ''Saving Private Ryan,'' which came out during the summer of 1998, seemed a fitting occasion to talk to him about where he is these days, both as an artist and as a kind of avatar for the state of mainstream filmmaking. It would also provide an opportunity to assess his views on the quarter century of filmmaking that he has dominated -- and on the lasting achievements, if any, of the generation of directors who came of age with him during the fertile 70's.</p>
        <p>''I don't remember any of us, back then, saying to each other, 'O.K., let's swarm the gates and take over Hollywood,' '' Mr. Spielberg said. ''I was much more selfish than that. When I was first starting out, I was more concerned about getting work, about being able to tell my own stories. If I worked in the mainstream, it was because I felt that was the more logical path for me than going in search of independent East Coast financing, or something. Remember, I was reared in the mainstream. I was hanging out at Universal Studios beginning with my last year in high school and through the first three years of college. So I never saw myself as saving Hollywood. I, frankly, didn't know if it needed saving. I was more concentrated on getting somebody to say yes to the movies I wanted to make.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Spielberg said, he has a myopic view of the so-called golden age of 70's filmmaking. ''I kind of leave it to the guys who write the book about our generation to inform me of what the heck we were doing back then,'' he said. ''And at the same time, a lot of the books that have been written about that period, I disagree with, because I don't remember it happening that way. I just remember that there were a handful of watershed films in the late 60's, beginning with Francis Coppola's 'You're a Big Boy Now,' and then Dennis Hopper's 'Easy Rider' and George Lucas's 'THX 1138,' that led me to believe that there was hope I'd get a job. All of a sudden, having long hair wasn't a liability. You got the feeling that the word went down to the guards at the studio gates that if any of those long-haired hippie kids try to get into the studio, they were to start letting them in. I think we can do well with them. I think we can make a lot of money with those guys.''</p>
        <p>While it may seem, in retrospect, that the generation that brought filmmakers like Mr. Spielberg, Mr. Coppola, Mr. Lucas, Brian De Palma, Martin Scorsese, Terrence Malick and others to the forefront was almost a conspiracy to seize the mainstream, that was not the case, Mr. Spielberg said.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Mr. Spielberg said, he and the other young filmmakers of the 70's were quite different from one another. ''When I was making 'Jaws,' Marty knew that that was something he would never want to make. And when he was making 'Taxi Driver,' I knew -- at that time, anyway -- that it was a genre I never wanted to be involved in, because it was too violent and too realistic and too yucky. Yet I thought 'Taxi Driver' was one of the great films when it was all put together.''</p>
        <p>Nor, Mr. Spielberg said, does he ever consider the wider cultural ramifications of the films he chooses to make. While he certainly hoped that ''Schindler's List'' would heighten awareness of the Holocaust, that was not the reason he made the movie. And while it seems clear that ''Saving Private Ryan'' sounded one of the loudest fanfares for the Greatest Generation cycle that the culture is now going through, he was not playing at social reform when he made the film.</p>
        <p>''When I make a picture, I'm not trying to change the culture,'' he said. ''I'm not trying to change the way things are. I'm trying to tell a story. I know it sounds simplistic, but I'm simply trying to get a story down on film that makes sense and is sometimes satisfying and is sometimes controversial. But I am never trying to say that I am doing this because I can't wait to see what the repercussions are going to be socially.''</p>
        <p>He is essentially, he said, too unsure of himself, even after all of his successes, to plot in such grand terms.</p>
        <p>''I'm the fraidy-cat who makes a picture and immediately assumes that nobody is going to show up the first day, and it will be reviled around the world,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''That's the way I've been on every single project. Every one. When it doesn't turn out that way, I'm relieved. Relief is the largest reaction I have to a film that's well received and opens well. I don't celebrate. I don't have victory parties. I simply feel relief.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg leaned back and let the sun play on his face. His little sanctuary was in an alcove formed by a locked entrance to one of the sound stages where he has been shooting ''Minority Report.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg has always been secretive about his projects and the current one,  ''Minority Report,'' is no exception. But as it is based on a science-fiction story by the frequently cynical Philip K. Dick about a future society in which federal agents are allowed to kill potential murderers before they can commit their crime, a kind of preemptive death penalty, the indications are that Mr. Spielberg will once again be exploring a new-found ominousness. The movie is set for release next June.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg's sanctuary was blocked from the view of passersby by a line of trailers where he and the film's stars -- Tom Cruise, Samantha Morton, Colin Farrell -- had their dressing rooms and resting areas. Only through a narrow gap could those walking past peer inside, and at one point another cast member, the Swedish actor Max von Sydow, wandered by, paused, peered in and then moved on.</p>
        <p>''There have always been films of mine that people didn't understand in the way that I intended,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''But I don't ever talk about that or go into detail, because I don't want to sound like I'm bellyaching.''</p>
        <p>He is not referring, Mr. Spielberg hastened to add, to either ''Schindler's List'' or ''Saving Private Ryan.'' What then? Perhaps his sentimental adaptation of ''The Color Purple'' in 1985?</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg sighed. ''Well, 'Color Purple' is a good example,'' he said. ''That was a film where there was more ink shed on the comparison with the Alice Walker novel than there was on the merits or problems with the film. In fact, the film was not analyzed. Instead, a mirror of Alice Walker was held up to it.''</p>
        <p>It taught him a lesson, he said, one that came to mind last year when he was considering which project to choose to end his three-year hiatus, and briefly thought of directing the adaptation of ''Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone'' for Warner Brothers.</p>
        <p>''Every kid in the world will be waiting to see how close 'Harry Potter' will be to the books,'' he said. ''And if they make it religiously and everybody gives it up to the book, there will be tremendous satisfaction.'' But this leaves little for a creative artist to do who wants to tell stories in his own way, free of the tyranny of some sacred text.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Spielberg was reluctant to assess the impact that his generation of filmmakers has had, he has very definite ideas of where movies have come since the 70's -- and what have been the most important technical and creative innovations that have changed them.</p>
        <p>''To me, it's sound,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''To me, the biggest breakthrough in the last 50 years, certainly since Cinerama in the 50's, is the sound. When I think of the sonic experience of the first time I heard Dolby stereo demonstrated at the American Film Institute years and years ago, it was then that I realized that we are making sound pictures. We could do a lot with sound, we could even tell a story with sound. And when we brought the best of sound together with the best of visuals in the 80's and 90's, you were able to show audiences so much more of the movie than they otherwise would have experienced.''</p>
        <p>Even though his ''Close Encounters of the Third Kind'' (1977) was going to be released only on a handful of 70-millimeter prints, Mr. Spielberg said he spent 17 weeks on the sound for it, almost as long as he spent shooting the film. Most of the country, at the time, saw the film with a monaural soundtrack. Only later, with videocassettes and now, with the release of the DVD of the film, can most people hear what he created. And next year, he said, he intends to release a DVD version of ''E.T.'' that will include, for the first time, a Digital Theater Sound, or DTS soundtrack. The emotional experience of seeing it with that enhanced sound, Mr. Spielberg said, will be qualitatively different.</p>
        <p>''You have to be careful, though, that you're not using sound in a way that draws attention away from the screen,'' he said. ''That's one of my pet peeves. Sometimes, a movie's sound design pulls your attention to a part of the theater that is beyond the screen, to the left or right or, worse yet, behind. That's just using the technology to show off.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, another less-welcome trend in recent decades has been what he considers the improper use of technological breakthroughs -- like sound, or like computer effects -- to bludgeon the audience or otherwise distort the stories being told.</p>
        <p>''I remember, back in the 70's, they had something called Sensurround,'' he said. ''Basically, they were speakers about the size of juke boxes. When they were first used, in the movie 'Earthquake,' they shook the theaters so hard you thought the rococo was going to come down around your ears.''</p>
        <p>Too often, he said, the first wave of filmmakers given the use of new high-tech gizmos will overuse them, like children playing with a new toy. ''These are all tools to be folded in,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''They are not the main ingredient. They are accent tools.''</p>
        <p>Another change in the last couple of decades has been the accelerated pace of movie storytelling, especially in adventures aimed at young audiences. It was Mr. Spielberg and his producer, Mr. Lucas, who decided when making ''Raiders of the Lost Ark'' (1981) that they would cut the action sequences into pieces as short as they could while still remaining coherent -- and then chop out one extra frame from each snippet.</p>
        <p>HE believed then, he said, and he believes now that younger audiences can assimilate information much more rapidly than people in their 40's or older. The advent of video games, channel surfing and the Internet have created a generation of people who are able to understand and act upon information more rapidly than previous generations. Action sequences in some films that seem dizzyingly fast to older viewers make perfect sense to younger ones and, in fact, better mirror the way they perceive the world.</p>
        <p>This has led to a kind of film, especially during the summer months, that is designed to be a sensory experience almost physical in its pace and vividness and impact, the so-called ''roller-coaster movie,'' of which even Mr. Spielberg has made a few (the ''Indiana Jones'' and ''Jurassic Park'' series).</p>
        <p>''I happen to like roller-coaster movies,'' he said. ''There's nothing wrong with being a roller-coaster movie, if that's all you're trying to be. Sometimes, though, it almost seems like the movie is on speed, if you will. It takes you through things so quickly that, like a roller-coaster, all you ever see to both sides is blur. You look ahead to the next twist and the next turn and the next tunnel, but when you come out of it, you feel like you've been in a kind of tunnel-vision experience. It's like you didn't have time to savor the experience as it was happening.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg's evolution from his more innocent past to a grimmer future was aided immeasurably by his collaboration, actual and posthumous, with Stanley Kubrick. Although Kubrick came from the previous generation of filmmakers, he and Mr. Spielberg were friends for the last 18 years of Kubrick's life, Mr. Spielberg said. They were simply drawn together by a natural curiosity to get to know each nother, although their relationship deepened into a very close if often long-distance one (Kubrick never strayed far from his London home). They kept up an almost constant correspondence and telephone relationship, peppered with occasional face-to-face visits, right up until Kubrick's death.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg said he considered Kubrick the supreme film artist of the last several decades. Indeed, when he agreed to pay for a new, high-tech sound stage at the University of Southern California film school earlier this year, Mr. Spielberg insisted that it be named for Kubrick (George Lucas endowed an adjacent stage, which he named for one of his heroes, the Japanese director Akira Kurosawa; students at the school refer to the stages as K1 and K2).</p>
        <p>''Kubrick couldn't have made 'A.I.' in the 80's, when he first told me about the story,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''He sent me his first treatment then, and I said, 'How are you going to do some of this stuff?' And he said, 'I don't know if we can yet. But we will be able to, soon.' Now, he's right, anything is possible. With the computer, you can do anything, you can show anything. The only limit is your own imagination.''</p>
        <p>In 1994, Mr. Spielberg said, Kubrick asked him to consider directing ''A.I.,'' based on a 90-page treatment Kubrick had written with Ian Watson, based on a short story by Brian Aldiss.</p>
        <p>''I agreed to do it and knew that the next step was that we would write the screenplay together,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''Stanley wanted a screenplay written in England, which meant Stanley would have about 99 percent control of the screenplay and I would have been happy to shoot whatever Stanley gave me. And I would have, until I realized this was an idea and a subject that really was something Stanley needed to see through to the end. So diplomatically and very carefully, I extracted myself from the project about two months after he got me to say yes to directing it.''</p>
        <p>Not until later, after Kubrick had died in 1999, did Mr. Spielberg entertain the idea of taking that 90-page treatment and writing his own screenplay, one that he would direct, in part, as a tribute to Kubrick and that would be released in 2001, the year Kubrick had made famous.</p>
        <p>''I didn't pass it on to another writer because I thought all the work that Stanley had done to download the story into me in 1994, all the things he wanted to express with this story, would not stand the test of time and would lose generations of emotional power if I tried to pass them on to yet another writer,'' Mr. Spielberg said. ''I felt it was much better, win or lose, to attempt to write the screenplay myself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spielberg was also attracted to the idea of making a more complex and emotionally rich film for children, especially his own. He has seven children. The first, Max, was born in 1985, during his marriage to the actress Amy Irving, which ended in divorce in 1989. The youngest, Destry, 4, was born to his current wife of 10 years, the actress Kate Capshaw.</p>
        <p>''A.I.'' marks the first screenplay to bear Mr. Spielberg's name since ''Poltergeist'' in 1982, and the first he has also directed since ''Close Encounters'' five years earlier.</p>
        <p>An assistant wearing a headset and microphone appeared suddenly and said that Mr. Spielberg was needed. The crew and the actors were ready to begin the afternoon's shooting. ''Is Tom there?'' he asked. The assistant nodded, and Mr. Spielberg rose. After finishing ''Minority Report'' on July 3, he said, he will take a little time off, though perhaps he will begin shooting another film before the year is out. He needs a rest, but he still feels like working.</p>
        <p>What will he make? ''I have three irons in the fire,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The first is his long-delayed adaptation of the Arthur Golden novel, ''Memoirs of a Geisha,'' which Mr. Spielberg said he would still probably direct. He is also considering a screen adaptation of Daniel Wallace's bittersweet novel about a father and son called ''Big Fish.'' And Mr. Spielberg has bought the rights to a forthcoming book by Doris Kearns Goodwin about the last six years in Abraham Lincoln's life.</p>
        <p>First, though, he is sweating out the release of ''A.I.'' on Friday -- convinced, as always, that it will be a disaster. Does he worry, in his secret heart, that if it fails he won't get another turn at bat?</p>
        <p>''Oh,'' Mr. Spielberg said, smiling. ''I know that I've reached a point where I'll get another turn at bat. I know I can strike out a whole bunch of times in a row and I'll always get another turn at bat. That's not really what worries me. It's not communicating the ideas. It bothers me when people don't get it. Even more than people not going, it's not getting it, that's what I'm afraid of.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
