<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Look Sharp; Trying to Run a Country Like a Corporation</title>
    <meta content="08SANG$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/08/weekinreview/08SANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1307825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DA1238F93BA35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Look Sharp; Trying to Run a Country Like a Corporation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Look Sharp: Trying to Run a Country Like a Corporation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on pitfalls of trying to run nation like a corporation; photo of Pres Bush and Vice Pres Cheney checking their watches (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN President Bush was sworn in nearly six months ago, Washington was awash with loose talk of a ''C.E.O. presidency.'' The first president with an M.B.A. to his name, from Harvard Business School no less, would be the chairman of the board of the world's biggest conglomerate, his aides boasted, a leader who delegated to his cabinet of experienced C.E.O.'s.</p>
        <p>They said his administration would apply business discipline to a bloated government.  And cabinet sessions do look a lot like the Business Roundtable, the organization of chief executives that, a few weeks ago, held part of its annual meeting in the East Room. Next to the president sits Dick Cheney, late of Halliburton, and Treasury Secretary Paul H. O'Neill, fresh from Alcoa. Donald H. Rumsfeld is also at the table, in his second run as defense secretary, after running G. D. Searle &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cracks are already beginning to mar the smooth veneer of Bush &amp; Co.'s boardroom table</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN President Bush was sworn in nearly six months ago, Washington was awash with loose talk of a ''C.E.O. presidency.'' The first president with an M.B.A. to his name, from Harvard Business School no less, would be the chairman of the board of the world's biggest conglomerate, his aides boasted, a leader who delegated to his cabinet of experienced C.E.O.'s.</p>
        <p>They said his administration would apply business discipline to a bloated government.  And cabinet sessions do look a lot like the Business Roundtable, the organization of chief executives that, a few weeks ago, held part of its annual meeting in the East Room. Next to the president sits Dick Cheney, late of Halliburton, and Treasury Secretary Paul H. O'Neill, fresh from Alcoa. Donald H. Rumsfeld is also at the table, in his second run as defense secretary, after running G. D. Searle &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Lower level officials, too, look and sound like business folk. ''We effectively are the C.E.O.'s of wholly owned subsidiaries of the Department of Defense,'' said Thomas E. White, who left Enron -- the Texas energy company that wields great influence here -- to become secretary of the army last month.</p>
        <p>But cracks are already beginning to mar the smooth veneer of Bush &amp; Co.'s boardroom table. Part of the problem is Mr. Bush himself: He cast himself first as a Reagan-style figure -- though less detached -- who would define the missions his team would carry out. But on a host of issues, from energy, to stem cell research, to ending bombing exercises on the island of Vieques in Puerto Rico, Mr. Bush has second-guessed his C.E.O.'s and swept decisions back into the White House.</p>
        <p>At Bush &amp; Co., the strategic plans are beginning to collide, and polls suggest that  shareholders are increasingly unconvinced by aspects of the business plan.</p>
        <p>One cause of the president's troubles may be that his C.E.O. approach to running the government conspicuously lacks what Washington demands: the flexibility required to appeal to a variety of constituencies and to horse trade (something Mr. Bush did quite well in Texas).</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush scored a quick, major victory with the tax cut, for example, his  energy initiatives and his ''faith-based'' plan for federal aid to religious groups that perform social services have run into the kind of political cross-currents that are rarely seen in corporate America.</p>
        <p>IN both cases, the White House has shown little willingness to compromise and little ability to persuade voters to share its views.</p>
        <p>''They run the meetings on time but he doesn't have much emotional range in connecting these themes to the public,'' said Rahm Emanuel, a highly partisan aide to President Clinton, who never ran meetings on time but knew how to stir a crowd.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's style has also vexed America's allies. They made it clear during his trip to Europe that they are tired of being treated like foreign subsidiaries of America, Inc. So Mr. Bush listened, and said he was humbled. But as soon as he got home, he boasted to The Wall Street Journal that 15 leaders of the European Union ''told me how wrong I was'' on global warming, but that he stood his ground because his position was ''right for America.''</p>
        <p>Others say the problem is not Mr. Bush, it's the slowness of his C.E.O.'s to readjust to a world where they do not have the last word. It's a huge change, notes Peter G. Peterson, who moved from a chief executive's post to become commerce secretary in the Nixon administration, and who is now chairman of the Blackstone Group, the New York investment bank.</p>
        <p>In the private sector, he notes, Mr. Bush's successful former executives had ''the undiffused power to implement their individual corporate visions.''</p>
        <p>Not in Washington. ''When you are a C.E.O., you observe, listen, and decide,'' Mr. Peterson said. ''When you are a cabinet secretary, you observe, listen, testify, subject everyone to interagency review, get resistance from Congress, and then, more often than not, someone else decides.''</p>
        <p>That should have come as no surprise to Mr. Cheney, Mr. Rumsfeld or Mr. O'Neill, who all had previous experience in government. ''And yet,'' said Thomas Mann of the Brookings Institution, ''they seem like somewhere along the line they forgot what they learned, and they've made some severe errors in judgment.''</p>
        <p>TAKE Mr. Cheney -- former Congressman, former White House chief of staff, former defense secretary. To put together the administration's energy report, he drew on the best minds he knew from his life at Halliburton. Yet his reliance on one slice of his constituency -- his fellow energy executives -- only fed the perception that the Bush team is far too close to energy interests.</p>
        <p>Now, in a classic Washington battle, the General Accounting Office is demanding to know who Mr. Cheney met with as his task force developed its policy in secret sessions, and he  has refused to reveal the list, fueling suspicions about who has his ear.</p>
        <p>''It was less than politically adept,'' one of Mr. Cheney's close friends conceded last week. ''But Dick had strong views, and they were reinforced by others he knew who had similarly strong views.''</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Bush is trying to undo the damage, showing up in places like Sequoia National Forest, restoring $300 million in Federal money for energy conservation that Mr. Cheney cut out of the budget, and calling for Americans to use energy efficient devices that Mr. Cheney ignored.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Rumsfeld is backtracking from his go-it-alone approach. For months he left the Joint Chiefs in the dark about his missile defense plans, and conducted his top-to-bottom review in secret, with a few trusted aides. ''It was very corporate,'' said one senior military official, ''but we had no idea what he was doing, and he had no idea why we do things the way we do.'' He has begun to change, but some of the Joint Chiefs remain wary of him.</p>
        <p>Then there is Mr. O'Neill, a longtime friend of Mr. Cheney and the chairman of the Federal Reserve, Alan Greenspan. But it's unclear who is setting financial strategy -- Mr. O'Neill or the White House chief economic adviser, Larry Lindsey -- and that has many of America's economic partners unsettled. ''Who makes dollar policy?'' a top aide to Japan's new prime minister asked a reporter last week. So far, it's hard to say.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill has also shown a penchant for speaking more frankly than the White House would wish. For example, when asked if it was smart to keep pressing for the elimination of the corporate tax at a time the administration is under fire for being too cozy with corporate America, the former Alcoa chief dismissed the whole issue.</p>
        <p>The corporate tax, he said, ''causes people to say we're getting those rotten bastards who are corporations, and we are taking money away from them.'' But ''at the end of the day individuals pay all the taxes,'' he said, so by cutting taxes for Exxon, I.B.M. and Alcoa, he's really helping consumers.</p>
        <p>It is not an argument the White House wants to hear right now, and it seems to be looking for another way of doing business. The president is in the midst of what business schools might call a ''strategic refocusing.''</p>
        <p>Issues that one might have expected to be decided by the C.E.O.'s have been recalled to the White House. It was Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's political guru, who told the Pentagon that its days of bombing Vieques were coming to an end -- even though the military has no alternative site to train its fliers. The issue was just too important to Latino voters, or so Mr. Rove thought.</p>
        <p>Similarly, the coming decision on federal funding for stem-cell research was sucked back into the White House as soon as it became clear that it involved not only science, but Catholics, anti-abortion groups and other key constituencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is likely to get into the middle of more decisions. With the surplus shrinking and government revenues declining, Mr. Rumsfeld is trying to figure out how to pay for missile defense and new conventional weapons, while Mr. Cheney wants funding for his energy agenda.</p>
        <p>AS Mr. Peterson says, ''when the aggregate of these individual visions don't add up, something, and in particular somebody, has to give.''</p>
        <p>It's possible that these are the usual contortions any new team finds itself in as it struggles to its feet. But it's also possible that Mr. Bush, eager to apply the lessons of private enterprise to Washington, overestimated how transferable those lessons are.</p>
        <p>''The problem isn't the model,'' insists Jeffrey E. Garten, the dean of the Yale School of Management and author of the recent book, ''The Mind of the C.E.O.'' (Perseus, 2001.) ''The problem is the Bush variant of the model.</p>
        <p>''A good C.E.O. has to be able to execute the policy once it's set,'' he said. Mr. Bush, like many politicians, is already ''compromising and backpedaling. The C.E.O.'s aren't accustomed to dealing with that. And so they get antsy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
