<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miners' Union Sees Opportunity in Bush Policy</title>
    <meta content="Y25MIN$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/25/politics/25MINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1304629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Mine Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DE1030F936A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miners' Union Sees Opportunity in Bush Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>FAIRFAX, Va., June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Mine Workers, once nation's most powerful union that has declined more than any other labor group, hopes to end slide because of Pres Bush's coal-friendly energy plan (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Mine Workers, once the nation's most powerful union, has declined more than any other labor group, its working membership having plunged to 30,000, from more than 700,000 six decades ago.</p>
        <p>But now, because of President Bush's coal-friendly energy plan, the union hopes it can end its slide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Mine Workers, once the nation's most powerful union, has declined more than any other labor group, its working membership having plunged to 30,000, from more than 700,000 six decades ago.</p>
        <p>But now, because of President Bush's coal-friendly energy plan, the union hopes it can end its slide.</p>
        <p>After endorsing Vice President Al Gore for president, the union is praising Mr. Bush, hoping his plan, which encourages coal production, will enable it to begin reversing a decline in power and membership that paralleled the long decline in the importance of coal.</p>
        <p>''Now is a very advantageous time for us, not only at the negotiating table but in bringing in new miners,'' Cecil Roberts, the union's president, said in an interview at union headquarters here.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts may be overly optimistic, experts say.</p>
        <p>The industry is scrambling to increase output in response to higher prices and the construction of dozens of coal-fired power plants, but the bad news for the union is that most coal is being mined in the largely nonunionized West and that companies have become experts in defeating unionization drives.</p>
        <p>''If the union doubles from 30,000 to 60,000 members that would be quite an accomplishment,'' Michael LeRoy, a professor of labor relations at the University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana, said.</p>
        <p>This would still be a far cry from 60 years ago, when the union was at its peak, renowned for its militancy and its legendary president, John L. Lewis.</p>
        <p>''John L. Lewis was the second most powerful man in the country,'' Mr. Roberts said. ''Only the president of the United States was more powerful.''</p>
        <p>In Lewis's time the union controlled congressmen and county governments, but with the steep decline in membership has come a steep drop in political influence.</p>
        <p>Many political experts said Mr. Gore lost West Virginia because many miners bucked their union's endorsement of him, out of fear that he would move aggressively against global warming, crippling coal production.</p>
        <p>''The union wasn't that effective, obviously,'' David R. Tyson, chairman of the West Virginia Republican Party, said.</p>
        <p>The union is trying to capitalize on the increase in coal production and prices by asking the Bituminous Coal Operators Association to negotiate a new contract now, though the agreement does not expire for 18 months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts said the resurgence of coal should make it easier to organize miners after the difficulties in doing so in the 1990's, when the union's membership plunged to 30,000 from 50,000, though coal production increased nationally.</p>
        <p>Union officials attribute the membership decline to the Clean Air Act of 1990, which required the use of more low-sulfur coal. Coal producers moved from heavily unionized Appalachia to the West, which is rich in low-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>With coal prices low and many mines closing in the 1990's, companies threatened to close their mines if the workers voted to unionize.  Union officials say that miners no longer need fear such closings and that the time is ripe to expand by organizing more miners.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure the nonunion operators will try real hard to keep out the union,'' John David, an economics professor at the West Virginia University Institute of Technology in Montgomery, said.</p>
        <p>William Raney, president of the West Virginia Coal Association, said coal output was picking up in the East, partly because many new power plants were being built there.</p>
        <p>''People have more confidence; they've got a smile on their face right now,'' Mr. Raney said. He declined to comment on the union's hopes for a rebound.</p>
        <p>Union officials were delighted by Mr. Bush's call to build 1,300 power plants and by his rejection of the Kyoto agreement on global warming, which would limit carbon emissions and which union officials say would be ineffective and costly.</p>
        <p>''I'm not embarrassed to say coal miners should have the right to continued employment,'' Mr. Roberts said. ''I'm not going to run away from defending their jobs.''</p>
        <p>But he insisted that his union was concerned about global warming,  saying it supported research to find ways to burn fossil fuels without releasing carbon dioxide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
