<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D71630F93AA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Israeli Troops Withdraw From Parts of West Bank  Israeli tanks and troops began withdrawing from Bethlehem, despite Palestinian attacks in Israel earlier that killed 5 people and wounded more than 30. Prime Minister Ariel Sharon authorized the pullout, under intense American pressure to end invasions in the West Bank, but indicated through a spokesman that military action would continue in other areas in response to violence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>China Grooms a New Leader  Hu Jintao, vice president of China, is touring Moscow, London, Paris, Berlin and Madrid for smiles and handshakes with presidents, prime ministers and business titans. But what seems like a common diplomatic trip is filled with meaning, because Mr. Hu appears virtually certain to take over as China's supreme leader in the next 18 months.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Israeli Troops Withdraw From Parts of West Bank  Israeli tanks and troops began withdrawing from Bethlehem, despite Palestinian attacks in Israel earlier that killed 5 people and wounded more than 30. Prime Minister Ariel Sharon authorized the pullout, under intense American pressure to end invasions in the West Bank, but indicated through a spokesman that military action would continue in other areas in response to violence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>China Grooms a New Leader  Hu Jintao, vice president of China, is touring Moscow, London, Paris, Berlin and Madrid for smiles and handshakes with presidents, prime ministers and business titans. But what seems like a common diplomatic trip is filled with meaning, because Mr. Hu appears virtually certain to take over as China's supreme leader in the next 18 months.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Singapore's One-Party Vote  With one week left before elections, the hapless opposition party has been able to field candidates for only one-third of the contested seats, another reminder that despite its democratic system, Singapore is in practice virtually a one-party state.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>First Reversal at U.N. Court  Appeals judges at the United Nations war crimes tribunal at The Hague overturned the convictions of three Croats linked to an attack on a Muslim village. Some legal experts believe that the ruling, the first time that convictions have been overturned since the tribunal began hearing cases in 1996, may help strengthen its image as a fair court.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>E.T.A. Says it Wants Peace  The Basque separatist group claimed responsibility for recent car-bombings and said that it wanted peace, but only if the governments in Madrid and Paris allowed a vote on independence for the region. The group's statement suggested it is feeling pressure since the war on terrorism and since the Irish Republican Army began to disarm.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Completing Kyoto's Rules  More than 150 countries began 12 days of talks in Morocco aimed at completing the rulebook for the Kyoto Protocol, a treaty requiring cuts in gases linked to global warming. The United States is attending the summit meeting, but is sitting on the sideline after President Bush rejected the treaty last March.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-9</p>
        <p>Mexican Border Backups Prompt Criticism of I.N.S.  All across the southwest frontier, where tightened security has driven once-brief crossing times to three hours or more, Americans and Mexicans alike are learning to live with perpetual border backups. Some congressmen say the Immigration and Naturalization Service aggravated the delays by failing to complete a program to replace the outdated migration documents held by Mexicans who routinely cross the frontier with a high-tech card that could allow quick border checks.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Hiking Into History  Brian Robinson, 40, completed the longest, fastest walk in American history: A 7,371-mile, 10-month hike fueled by 6,000 calories a day. His finish at the freezing, wind-blown summit in Maine that is the northern end of the Appalachian Trail made him the first person to hike, in less than a year, America's three national scenic trails -- the Appalachian, Pacific Crest and Continental Divide.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Anthrax Is Common on Ranches  More than 1,600 animals have died of anthrax in Texas this summer, the most severe outbreak of the disease since 1987. But no humans have died. Among Texas ranchers, anthrax is just another occupational hazard among many, like drought, low beef prices or coyotes, that can be managed through care and caution. ''There has been anthrax around for as long as there have been people and animals, all the way back to the Bible,'' said Terry Conger, the state's epidemiologist at the Texas Animal Health Commission.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Harvard Provost  Dr. Steven E. Hyman, director of the National Institute of Mental Health, is expected to resign to become the provost at Harvard University, spokesmen for the institute and the university said.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Diamondbacks Take 2-0 Lead  Arizona defeated the Yankees, 4-0, in Game 2 of the World Series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>Alvan Feinstein  An epidemiologist who advanced the science of disease diagnosis and prognosis and made significant strides in preventing rheumatic fever, he was 75.</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>Vasily P. Mishin  A scientist who helped preside over the Soviet Union's failed effort to beat the United States to the Moon, he was 84.</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>New Jersey Candidates Are at Odds Over Schools  Bret D. Schundler is campaigning for governor of New Jersey as the candidate of new, bold ideas, but even by his own standards nothing in his campaign is quite so bold as his proposal to revamp the state's education. Mr. Schundler, a Republican and a supporter of school choice, proposes a program of tax credits to support private school education that he says would save the state almost a half-billion dollars by moving children from high-cost and bureaucrat-heavy public schools to less expensive private ones. His Democratic rival, James E. McGreevey, decries the proposal as ''a scheme that's untested, unproven'' and that could cost public schools $600 million.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>The two candidates clashed over taxes, education, abortion and gun control during an angry fifth debate in which they repeatedly accused each other of lying to the voters. Mr. Schundler, who has been trailing in the polls, also laced two of his remarks with references to the family life of Mr. McGreevey, crossing into territory that is usually considered out of bounds in a political forum.</p>
        <p>F4</p>
        <p>Restoration of Weeksville  Four little clapboard cottages in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn are all that remain of Weeksville, one of the nation's earliest communities of freed slaves. Through nearly $10 million in grants they will soon be fully restored and turned into a museum and education center.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Rabbi Murder Trial  A tantalizing question hovers over the trial of Rabbi Fred J. Neulander of Cherry Hill, N.J., on charges that he arranged the murder of his wife in 1994: Why did an enigmatic member of his temple, Leonard Jenoff, finally confess to the slaying last year and tell prosecutors the rabbi had hired him for $30,000 to rob and kill Ms. Neulander? The jury has heard conflicting explanations for Mr. Jenoff's confession. Which explanation the jury finds more credible will most likely become an important factor in its decision whether to acquit or convict Rabbi Neulander. He could face the death penalty if he is found guilty of murder.</p>
        <p>F4</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Franzen's Criticism Backfires  Jonathan Franzen's book ''The Corrections,'' one of the most critically acclaimed and best-selling novels of the year, earned him a selection by Oprah Winfrey's book club. But after Mr. Franzen disparaged Ms. Winfrey's literary taste -- suggesting that appearing on her show was out of keeping with his place in ''literary tradition'' and might turn off some readers -- he found that he may have inadvertently damaged his own reputation in the literary world. Ms. Winfrey did not revoke her selection but politely withdrew the invitation to appear on her show. And instead of rallying to Mr. Franzen, most of the literary world took her side, deriding him as arrogant and ungrateful.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>G.M. Deals Hughes to EchoStar  General Motors agreed to sell Hughes Electronics, the owner of DirecTV, to EchoStar Communications for about $27 billion in cash and stock. The deal, which would combine the nation's two largest satellite television companies, is certain to draw scrutiny from regulators.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>United Airlines Ousts Chief  James E. Goodwin, the embattled head of embattled United Airlines, was removed as chairman and chief executive of the UAL Corporation, United's parent. He will be succeeded by John W. Creighton Jr., the former chief executive of the Weyerhaeuser Company.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>They Removed His Cheese  Executives at Barnes &amp; Noble have decided that ''Who Moved My Cheese?'' and ''Body For Life'' have been on its best-seller list long enough. In an unusual move for a book seller, Barnes &amp; Noble has begun to remove books from its best-seller list after a year. Those two blockbusters were the first to go.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Aviation Safety System  The wireless technology company Qualcomm intends to announce plans today that it hopes will breathe life into Globalstar Telecommunications, the money-losing satellite company. Qualcomm says it has developed an airborne communications system that can be used to improve existing aviation safety services.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Nestlé à la Mode  The company plans to buy the United States rights to the Häagen-Dazs ice cream brand from General Mills to better compete with Unilever, the world's largest ice cream maker.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Battle Over Browsers  When Microsoft introduced Windows XP, it also upgraded its flagship Web site, MSN.com, and prompted an outcry by preventing users with certain browsers from viewing the site. At first, Microsoft held its ground, but it later backed down.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A10-11</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mark Green for mayor; more environmental rollbacks; Tina Rosenberg on the resurrection of a Nicaraguan revolutionary.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire and Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Crossword</p>
        <p>E2  Weather</p>
        <p>F8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
