<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Quiet One, the D.J., A Man of November, And the Head of the Table</title>
    <meta content="362425SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6D8173BF936A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="6614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Quiet One, the D.J., A Man of November, And the Head of the Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">These sketches were written by Carla Baranauckas, Lisa Belkin, Celestine Bohlen, Adam Clymer, Sherri Day, Jim Dwyer, Jonathan Fuerbringer, Steven Greenhouse, Andrew Jacobs, Kirk Johnson, Felicia R. Lee, Andy Newman, Gustav Niebuhr, Mirta Ojito, Anthony Ramirez, Sara Rimer and Melena Z. Ryzik</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portraits of Grief column on lives of some of victims of Sept 11 terrorist attack on World Trade Center; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here are glimpses of some of the victims of the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>KEVIN PFEIFER  Shouting With His Life</p>
        <p>To the casual acquaintance, Kevin Pfeifer had a manner -- a quiet, thoughtful demeanor -- that seemed of a piece with all the philosophy courses he took at Marist College. His gift for abstractions, though, was far exceeded by his taste for the concrete. And adventure.</p>
        <p>He learned to fly, and logged 400 hours of flying time. He learned to sail, and loved to bring his friends out to race the tankers around Sandy Hook or his nieces and nephews out on Jamaica Bay. He loved to drive, and managed to sneak onto the secure grounds at Kennedy Airport, where he sped along a runway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here are glimpses of some of the victims of the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>KEVIN PFEIFER  Shouting With His Life</p>
        <p>To the casual acquaintance, Kevin Pfeifer had a manner -- a quiet, thoughtful demeanor -- that seemed of a piece with all the philosophy courses he took at Marist College. His gift for abstractions, though, was far exceeded by his taste for the concrete. And adventure.</p>
        <p>He learned to fly, and logged 400 hours of flying time. He learned to sail, and loved to bring his friends out to race the tankers around Sandy Hook or his nieces and nephews out on Jamaica Bay. He loved to drive, and managed to sneak onto the secure grounds at Kennedy Airport, where he sped along a runway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pfeifer, 42, shouted with his life, not with his mouth. Growing up in Middle Village, in Queens, and spending many summer days in Breezy Point, he developed a close circle of friends who ate at Beefsteak Charlie's and joined him for his capers on the ground, at sea, in the air. He knew that fun was where you made it: he organized a legendary bash at an abandoned missile silo near Floyd Bennett Field in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Pfeifer's work as a city paramedic and later as a fire lieutenant, he had a knack for quietly bringing out the best in people, his brother Joseph said. Joseph Pfeifer was among the first battalion chiefs at the trade center on Sept. 11. He spotted his brother coming in with Engine Company 33, and the two Pfeifers exchanged a quick word, and then glances as they parted.</p>
        <p>EDWARD R. PYKON  Fast Eddy From Lehigh</p>
        <p>Life was proceeding more or less on schedule for Edward R. Pykon and his wife, Jackie.</p>
        <p>They met 10 years ago on the Fourth of July, and last August they celebrated their fifth wedding anniversary. In 2000, again on the Fourth of July, they found out that they were going to be parents. By the time their daughter, Jordyn, was born eight months ago, they had already bought a house in Princeton Junction, N.J.</p>
        <p>''We came here to raise a family,'' Jackie Pykon said. ''Our plan was to buy a beautiful home, fix it up and have a baby. Everything was going along just as planned.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pykon, 33, worked at the World Trade Center offices of Fred Alger Management, where he was a senior vice president with a specialty in health care. ''What was great about Ed was that he was brilliant, but not stuffy or boring,'' Mrs. Pykon said. He was very down to earth, modest, and a lot of fun to be around.'' As an undergraduate at Lehigh University, Mr. Pykon was known as Fast Eddy, a nickname he picked up as the D.J. at his fraternity. ''We still have the turntables in the basement,'' Mrs. Pykon said. ''He had a real adventure for life.''</p>
        <p>JASON SEKZER  Campers, United</p>
        <p>Jason Sekzer started going to Camp Sussex as a boy, one of hundreds of city children who grabbed the chance to spend part of each summer in the country in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Then, bit by bit, the camp became an ever larger part of his life. He graduated from camper to waiter, waiter to kitchen helper and finally to chef. ''He used to say that he could cook for 400 but he couldn't cook for 2,'' recalled Robert Silver, executive vice president of Camp Sussex.</p>
        <p>After he got a job at Cantor Fitzgerald, and could no longer spend summers at the camp, Mr. Sekzer joined its board of directors. ''It was something special,'' said his wife, Natalie Makshanov-Sekzer, 31, whom he had met there; the couple married in January. ''The camp and the friends we made there were a major support to me after Sept. 11,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sekzer, 31, the son of a New York City police officer, began at Cantor Fitzgerald as a clerk and worked his way up to vice president. ''Every year he got promoted; he was doing very well,'' his wife said. Once a year, Mr. Sekzer combined his job and his camp: he invited executives from Cantor Fitzgerald to play in a charity golf tournament raising money for Camp Sussex.</p>
        <p>ROBERT T. LANE  A Son's Cake and Candles</p>
        <p>Robert T. Lane was a man whose size might have been intimidating were it not for his magnetic smile. Name a sport, and this towering firefighter played it, but his favorite hobby was cooking.</p>
        <p>''He'd go to restaurants and try to duplicate their food back at the firehouse,'' said his mother, Janet Lane.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lane started work at Engine Company 55 three years ago this month. That was fitting, because November was the month his parents married and the month he and his sister were born.</p>
        <p>This November, on their anniversary, the Lanes dined at Trattoria Romana, a restaurant near their Staten Island home. They ordered shrimp fra diavolo over linguine -- their son's favorite dish. They paid the check with a gift certificate he had given them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lane would have turned 29 on Nov. 29, and until last week his family planned to take a cake, lighted with candles, to the site of the World Trade Center on that day. But they learned last week that their son's body might have been among a group retrieved from the rubble, something that will still take weeks to confirm. So now they will have their cake at home, his mother said, ''and hope he isn't down under there anymore.''</p>
        <p>KEVIN S. COHEN  Friends Everywhere</p>
        <p>When Kevin S. Cohen was 4, his family moved to a new house in Edison, N.J. Rather than being daunted by the move, little Kevin, the youngest of two boys, set out to make new friends. Soon, he was standing at his front door pointing to all the houses where he had made a friend.</p>
        <p>''He would point with his little hands and say, 'That's my friend across the street, and that's my friend from next door, and that's my other friend from that house,' '' said his mother, Marcia Cohen. ''And then, he never changed. He was like a mother that way. You know how children leave home and then it's the mother who brings them together year after year? Well, it was like that with my son. He had friends from all over. He was very compassionate, a lot of fun. He loved people, and people loved him back.''</p>
        <p>On Aug. 17, Mr. Cohen, 28, who worked at Cantor Fitzgerald, took his parents to dinner at a fancy Italian restaurant to celebrate their 36th wedding anniversary. Mrs. Cohen was reluctant at first because she figured he would be tired on a Friday, after working all week. But he insisted.</p>
        <p>''Kevin was so proud that he could take us to a nice place like that and take out his credit card and pay by himself,'' Mrs. Cohen said. ''He thought we had never been there before, but we had. We just didn't tell him.''</p>
        <p>THOMAS M. BRENNAN  Rock Tunes and Giggles</p>
        <p>When Jennifer Brennan was pregnant with her first child, her husband, Thomas M. Brennan, would play Grateful Dead tapes loudly, hoping the music would reach the ears of his unborn daughter. When the baby kicked, as she invariably did, Mr. Brennan was delighted. She, too, he would say, was a fan.</p>
        <p>On the last day he spent with his family, the Sunday before Sept. 11, Mr. Brennan, 32, played Grateful Dead compact discs in the car as the family shopped for furniture for their new house in Scarsdale in Westchester.</p>
        <p>Strapped to her car seat, Mr. Brennan's daughter, Catherine, now 19 months, laughed and moved to the music. And that is how Mrs. Brennan would like to remember her husband: as the only person who could make their daughter giggle uncontrollably.</p>
        <p>With his wife pregnant with the couple's second child, a boy who was born last month, Mr. Brennan took on many of the child care duties. He often got up early with his daughter, fed her breakfast and carried her when she needed a hug.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brennan, an investment banker with Sandler O'Neill, treasured the time with his family, in part because he traveled constantly for work. Tuesday, Sept. 11, was the only day of that week he was scheduled to be in the office.</p>
        <p>FRANK SCHOTT  In the Garden, at the Stove</p>
        <p>Dina Schott could set her watch by her husband's daily routine. Every morning, Frank Schott was up at 5:20 a.m., on the train to his job in Manhattan at 6:09 a.m., and opening the front door again of their home in Massapequa Park, N.Y., at 7:00 p.m.</p>
        <p>Then, after working for 10 hours as the assistant vice president for technology at Marsh &amp; McLennan, Mr. Schott began his first chore of the evening.</p>
        <p>''He would come home, take off his work clothes, put on a pair of shorts -- not even tie his sneakers -- and he was out there picking his vegetables,'' Mrs. Schott said. ''I always knew where to find him. The man never rested.''</p>
        <p>While his wife bathed their three children and put them to bed, Mr. Schott, 39, prepared dinner. Some nights it was Indian food; other nights he made a Spanish entree or a Chinese dish. ''I got used to it very quickly,'' Mrs. Schott said. ''What woman wouldn't?''</p>
        <p>On weekends, Mr. Schott jogged, rode his bicycle and spent time with his children -- sometimes taking them into the office with him if he worked on Saturdays because they loved to ride the trains.</p>
        <p>''If he had survived what happened and knew of the hate that I have for what these people did, he'd say, 'Ah, don't be so hard on them,' '' Mrs. Schott said. ''He would always say, 'You can't judge a whole group of people for the actions of a couple of bad apples.' I know that's what he would say.''</p>
        <p>CARLTON W. BARTELS  Wraparound Buddha</p>
        <p>Her father was aghast: there on the doorstep of her family's West Brighton home in Staten Island stood Carlton W. Bartels, suitor. ''Carl had thick, wavy brown hair, down to his shoulders,'' recalled Jane Bartels, the object of his affection, decades later. ''And a suede fringe jacket.''</p>
        <p>The couple managed to date and grow close, but then careers separated them. While in his 20's, Mr. Bartels took an 18-month trip around the world with his savings. He asked her to join him in Jakarta, where they inched toward Europe. They married in 1988. Mr. Bartels was an electrical engineer by training and had become, at 26, one of the top utility regulators in Vermont. At 44, he was a partner at Cantor Fitzgerald, specializing in using the commodity markets to encourage the reduction of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartels had his antic side, Mrs. Bartels recalled. While on his epic trip, living in a Thai village, Mr. Bartels took to wearing a favorite sarong, a black-and-white skirt with Buddha figures. But one day, the villagers giggled. He was wearing a sarong for a woman. Unfazed, he continued to wear it, even back home, years later, when the couple had settled back in Staten Island. Their daughters -- Melina, who turns 8 today, and Eva, 4 -- loved it.</p>
        <p>JAMES R. PAUL  Finding Their Place</p>
        <p>In 1993, when James R. Paul decided to move to New York after two decades in Chicago, he was walking around Gramercy Park one day with a real estate broker when a building caught his eye. Built in 1883, it appealed to Mr. Paul's taste for the old and beautiful. ''I wish we could find a place there,'' he told the broker, pointing to the red-brownish brick facade. They did.</p>
        <p>Then, two years ago, Mr. Paul and his wife, Pat, decided to begin looking for what one day would be their retirement home. The two got in a car and drove south, hugging the Atlantic coast. They found their place in a condominium in Savannah, Ga., where Mr. Paul could play golf and his wife could enjoy the city's architecture and cultural life.</p>
        <p>That is how Mr. Paul, 58, lived his life: with one foot on the gas pedal and the other on the brakes, making plans, but also letting his impulses guide him. He drove too fast, skied even faster, and loved being on top of the world, on the 92nd floor of 1 World Trade Center, where he was an executive vice president of Carr Futures. He called his wife, an accountant, ''the bean counter.''</p>
        <p>''He was working very hard, six days a week, to make enough money to retire early,'' Mrs. Paul said. ''He wanted to have enough years and energy in him to play golf.''</p>
        <p>PETER SIRACUSE  Game Day, Every Day</p>
        <p>Peter Siracuse lived for competition. As a child he jockeyed for attention with his three older brothers. As a young adult, he took his aggression out on the gridiron and in lacrosse. He also played football in college.</p>
        <p>So when Mr. Siracuse, 29, became a teacher and a coach at Bethpage High School on Long Island right after college, his family thought he was a natural, since he also loved children.</p>
        <p>A little over a year ago, he married his high school sweetheart, Alana, and had a child of his own, Ryan Joseph, now 9 months.</p>
        <p>''He was just so excited that he had a son and a child,'' said Matthew Siracuse, one of Mr. Siracuse's brothers. ''That was probably the biggest thing in his life at this time.''</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Mr. Siracuse left the blackboard for the brokerage house. He quickly developed an affinity for his new job as a bond broker at Cantor Fitzgerald.</p>
        <p>''He loved it; it was like game day every day,'' said George Siracuse, another of his brothers. ''He loved the whole camaraderie of his co-workers. He loved the competition. He thrived on it.''</p>
        <p>GREGORY RICHARDS  The Call of the City</p>
        <p>Gregory Richards just could not stay away from New York. He was born here, grew up in Greenwich Village and went to Stuyvesant High School.</p>
        <p>When he went off to the University of Michigan, he longed to come home. When he went to Florida to work for a hedge fund, he wanted to come back.</p>
        <p>Even after he left Cantor Fitzgerald, moved to Michigan in 1998 to live near his wife's parents and started his own real estate investment business, he dreamed of concrete, skyscrapers, Central Park, the trading floor.</p>
        <p>''He missed the pace of Wall Street; he missed the camaraderie of being around the guys all the time,'' said his wife, Erin. ''He was a true city kid. All the things that made people crazy about New York, he liked.''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Richards, 30, returned to the city in 2000 and rejoined Cantor Fitzgerald, this time working for eSpeed, its electronic subsidiary. He now had a son, Asher, 2, and could run in Central Park on a weekend morning and meet Asher and his wife at the playground.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Richards, who is spending time with her parents in Michigan, said she will also return to New York. But the city, she said, will be empty without her husband. ''He had New York's cocky charisma about him,'' she said. ''He was cool.''</p>
        <p>JAN MACIEJEWSKI  A Guy Just Like Him</p>
        <p>Jan Maciejewski had a knack for being in the right place in the right time.</p>
        <p>In 1990, when Mr. Maciejewski was still living in Poland, a friend got a visa to study in the United States. The friend could not go, but Mr. Maciejewski could, so he postponed his plans to be a soccer coach and immigrated to the land of his dreams.</p>
        <p>In 1995, a young woman named Mary DeFranco was at a restaurant in Midtown where her bartender friend wanted to introduce her to a man named Chuck.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'I don't want to meet a guy named Chuck,' '' she recalled. '' 'I want to meet a guy with an odd name and an accent. Like him.' '' She pointed at a good-looking waiter with brown-green eyes and a distinctly European air. It was Mr. Maciejewski's twin brother. He was already married, so Ms. DeFranco was introduced to Jan Maciejewski instead. They married the next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maciejewski, 37, an avid soccer and tennis player, was always running. He would run from his main job as a waiter at Windows on the World to catch the subway to his other job as a computer consultant. He would run back to the subway to get home to his wife in Astoria, Queens. When she looks through the pockets of his pants, she often finds the Band-Aids he wore on his well-traveled feet.</p>
        <p>A colleague at Windows on the World had asked Mr. Maciejewski to fill in for him on the breakfast shift on Sept. 11. Sure, Mr. Maciejewski had said, and gone off to work.</p>
        <p>NEREIDA DE JESUS  Life With Lauren</p>
        <p>For Nereida De Jesus, life equaled Lauren. Lauren was her daughter, a bubbly 7-year-old whom Ms. De Jesus, 30, was raising alone in Woodlawn in the Bronx. Mother and daughter would do everything together -- get their hair done, go to movies, take bubble baths.</p>
        <p>Ms. De Jesus' new job as a claims adjuster at Aon Insurance, which she started only a few months before Sept. 11, enabled her to send Lauren to a private Catholic school.</p>
        <p>When Ms. De Jesus was not working or taking care of Lauren, she could usually be found at church, either at her sister's missionary church in Dover, N.J., or at a church near her home.</p>
        <p>Ms. De Jesus, said her sister, Elaine De Jesus, wanted to be like her own mother, who had raised three children alone on the Lower East Side -- when that neighborhood was one of the worst in the city -- and somehow had them all turn out fine. ''Her job was helping her accomplish the plans that she had,'' Elaine De Jesus said. ''She was proud.''</p>
        <p>GARNET BAILEY  Ace of 'Bailey-baisse'</p>
        <p>When Garnet Bailey would come to scout a game in Worcester, Mass., he would announce himself by saying, ''table for two, please'' as a tribute to the legendary meals served when the IceCats were at home.</p>
        <p>That is how Bill Ballou, a hockey writer for The Worcester Telegram and Gazette, remembers Mr. Bailey, adding that he was ''a pretty aggressive player on the ice, but a sweetheart off the ice.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bailey, 53, known as Ace, played 11 seasons in the National Hockey League, and was a scout for 20 years, the last seven as director of pro scouting for the Los Angeles Kings. The team's general manager, Dave Taylor, said Mr. Bailey had a gift for measuring the intangibles that a player could ''bring to the table.''</p>
        <p>Food mattered at home in Lynnfield, Mass., too, according to his sister-in-law, Barbara Pothier. For his wife, Kathy, his son, Todd, and friends, he would cook a dish called ''Bailey-baisse, with ''every kind of meat you could think of -- tenderloin tips, chicken, pork chops, sausages,'' Sauted, then baked with onions and tomatoes, Ms. Pothier said, ''it was fall-off-the-bone delicious.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bailey took a Los Angeles flight, United 175, from Boston on Sept. 11. It struck the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>DAVID ALGER  Tales From a Lunch Table</p>
        <p>For a generation of up-and-comers in the money world of Lower Manhattan, the scene was deeply familiar: David Alger's lunch table. Nothing fancy about it -- Mr. Alger seemed to thrive on cheeseburgers and apple pie, and any nondescript Wall Street coffee shop would do. His stories are what live on, and the lessons embedded within them about the stock market, and about life.</p>
        <p>''I can see him chewing apple pie and telling these stories,'' said Rob Lyon, who worked for Mr. Alger at Fred Alger Management in the 1980's and remained close. One of Mr. Alger's lunch lessons was that big companies cannot possibly grow as fast as little ones, and that problems in a company -- or a life -- can never fully be solved in one three-month reporting period. You have to look to the horizon, he would tell the young Turks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alger, who was 57, took over operations at Alger Management from his brother, Frederick, in 1995. But by then his impromptu lunch seminars were Wall Street lore, former pupils like Mr. Lyon said. And strangely, all the stories seemed to have the same opening line: ''That reminds me of something,'' he would say.</p>
        <p>JANICE ASHLEY  A Renaissance Woman</p>
        <p>Janice Ashley was a modern-day Renaissance woman: literary, artistic and skilled in finance, as comfortable on Rollerblades as ordering a meal in a fancy restaurant. She was also outspoken and bubbly, someone who kept her friends from elementary school but relished new experiences, like a trip to Turkey in August.</p>
        <p>''She marched to her own tune,'' said Richard Gallo, a friend she had dated for over five years. ''She wouldn't have chicken or beef when she went out to eat -- she'd order the antelope steak or ostrich burger.''</p>
        <p>In a letter of condolence to the Ashley family, another friend recalled how Ms. Ashley was their only high school classmate to compliment her unconventional Sweet 16 party, at a Manhattan comedy club. ''She just got things,'' Risa Lewak said. ''There was nothing phony about her.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ashley, 25, lived with her mother, father and 18-year-old brother in Rockville Centre, N.Y., and worked as a research associate at Fred Alger Management. She returned home tired from 12-hour days but found time to talk about her dreams, like eventually opening a florist gift shop, said Carol Ashley, her mother. She misses her daughter the most in the evenings. ''She just sparkled,'' Mrs. Ashley said.</p>
        <p>DENIS LAVELLE  A Mother's Devoted Son</p>
        <p>Denis Lavelle idolized Rush Limbaugh and had cleared rooms at many a family gathering arguing his hard-line conservatism, but the last thing his relatives expected him to do was run for public office. But there was Mr. Lavelle over the summer, 42 and an absolute newcomer to retail politics, going door to door around Yonkers, where he was born and raised, collecting signatures for a run for the City Council on the Right to Life line.</p>
        <p>''He had no chance,'' said his brother-in-law, Alex Dziadek. ''But the party picked him because they knew he wouldn't take it lightly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lavelle, an accountant at Marsh &amp; McLennan, had a ready smile, but he took his responsibilities seriously, and his greatest one was caring for his 75-year-old mother, who, widowed when he was 16, had become severely arthritic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lavelle, who never married, lived with his mother all his life, escorted her to Mass every Sunday and to the Italian restaurants on Central Avenue just about every weekend.</p>
        <p>''He was so devoted to her,'' said Mr. Lavelle's sister Marie Paprocki. ''He was a dedicated son.''</p>
        <p>SALVATORE F. PEPE  For Family, a Tomatofest</p>
        <p>Salvatore F. Pepe was an assistant vice president for technology at Marsh &amp; McLennan, but to the Pepe clan he will be remembered as the originator of Tomatofest and the Pepe family calendar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pepe's mother used to can tomatoes every August. So after she died in 1992, he organized a messy, joyous annual get-together where the next two generations of Pepes would gather to cut, skin, cook and can enough tomatoes to last everyone through the winter. ''It was like Little Italy,'' said his sister Leonida Pepe.</p>
        <p>The calendar was another way Mr. Pepe, 45, kept the family connected. He would put together a photo-filled calendar marking the birthdays and anniversaries of the 60-odd members of his, his wife's and his six siblings' families and hand it out to everyone.</p>
        <p>Not everything he did involved huge numbers of people, though.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pepe loved watching the stars, which was hard if you live in Elmhurst, Queens. So on a cold, clear winter day, he would call his wife, Cathy Ng Pepe, and say, ''Let's go.'' They would take the afternoon off work, drive out with the telescope to the Delaware Water Gap and stand beneath the sky, bundled up in hunting suits and warmed by the sparkle of the stars.</p>
        <p>The Pepes had not done much star-gazing since their son, Salvatore Loong Pepe, was born early last year. But Big Sal hoped to take Little Sal to Quebec someday to see the northern lights. ''Maybe when he gets older, we'll take him out there,'' Cathy Ng Pepe said.</p>
        <p>DENEASE CONLEY  Tough, With a Studious Side</p>
        <p>The seeds of Denease Conley's toughness could be seen early on. She once had a fight with an older sister who locked herself in the bathroom, and to get her out, Denny, as she was known, threw a cherry bomb at the bathroom door.</p>
        <p>In high school in Kansas City, she studied karate, loved Bruce Lee and even painted a poster of him on her wall. She served in the Navy for four years, and afterward became a security guard at the World Trade Center. When a supervisor taunted her by saying she was too weak to work as a firefighter, she took up his challenge and passed the qualifying exams to become a New York City firefighter.</p>
        <p>She also had a studious side, receiving a bachelor's degree in English and philosophy from Hunter College. ''Her apartment was filled with books,'' said her sister, Barbara Haynes. ''She had a thirst for knowledge. She read everything. I called her the professional college student. And this was a child that at one time did not want to go to school.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Haynes was surprised at how many people packed the memorial service. ''Several people said my sister helped save their lives,'' she said. ''One friend said the last time he saw Denny she was holding a door open with a fireman. Knowing my sister, she had this take-charge attitude that she had to help other people get out.''</p>
        <p>ARTHUR WARREN SCULLIN  A Schmoozer Extraordinaire</p>
        <p>Arthur Warren Scullin schmoozed with everyone, even telemarketers. ''He never hung up on them,'' said Mr. Scullin's widow, Cathy. ''He'd ask them where they were calling from. He would ask them what the weather was like, what time it was.''</p>
        <p>His gregariousness could get on the nerves of his children, Warren, Jim and Nora, when they were younger. When everyone else was, say, cruising through the tollbooth at the Throgs Neck Bridge, they would be sitting there because their father was chatting up the toll taker.</p>
        <p>As a senior vice president and director of taxes at Marsh Inc., Mr. Scullin, 57, traveled all over the world. Naturally, he talked to everyone he met. ''He would ask people, 'Do you know anybody in New York?' '' Mrs. Scullin recalled. ''If they said no, he would say, 'You do now,' and he'd give them his business card.''</p>
        <p>Born in Woodside, Queens, Mr. Scullin met his wife at the Lowery Street subway station of the Flushing IRT 36 years ago, and together they migrated to Auburndale, Queens. Every week, Mr. Scullin would return to Woodside to visit his mother, Ethel, 90. ''He used to say that when he retired, he was going to move back to an apartment in Woodside so he could return to his roots,'' Mrs. Scullin said. ''I would say, 'I'll send you a postcard from Arizona.' ''</p>
        <p>WILLIAM H. BERNSTEIN  The Late Bloomer</p>
        <p>William H. was the oldest of four sons -- arriving three minutes before his fraternal twin, Robert. The two younger brothers, Steven and David, also twins, were born four years later.</p>
        <p>Among four boys growing up in Brooklyn, life was competitive, which posed a challenge to William Bernstein -- Billy, as he was known -- because he was such a late bloomer physically.</p>
        <p>''At his bar mitzvah, he was a foot shorter than his twin,'' said his brother Steven Bernstein. But he did fill out later, becoming about a 6-foot-2, 220-pound adult, devoted to bodybuilding and karate.</p>
        <p>William Bernstein, 44, a mortgage bond broker at Cantor Fitzgerald, was closest to Robert. ''Same grade schools,'' the latter said in a memorial service, ''same camps, same high school, same college, Syracuse University, living in the same co-op building, working in the same neighborhood, downtown Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>Yet they were not carbon copies. Robert Bernstein is known as meticulous in his habits, while William was more laid back, though he took great care in his appearance. Robert said his brother was more reserved, too, but once people got to know him, ''they could see the genuineness, the kindness.''</p>
        <p>ANDREW M. KING  A Real Golfer</p>
        <p>A lot of the Cantor Fitzgerald crowd played golf. And a lot of them were good at it. But Andrew M. King was REALLY, REALLY good. He had a four handicap and had shot three holes-in-one. ''He had a beautiful swing,'' said his wife, Judy King.</p>
        <p>Mr. King, 42, a bond trader, played the world's great courses, but last summer he led his wife and three children, 14 other family members, and his best friend, Tom Pritchard, to golf nirvana -- the storied St. Andrew's in Scotland. ''We teed off, and Andrew said, 'We're here!' '' said his sister-in-law, Jackie Szafara.</p>
        <p>It was typical of Mr. King that he had been the one to organize the trip. ''He was the head-in-law,'' Ms. Szafara said. ''The family get-together started when Andrew got there.''</p>
        <p>And while he left his home in Princeton at 5:30 a.m. for the World Trade Center, and often entertained clients until midnight, he never missed a family gathering.</p>
        <p>He spotted his future wife at the Denver airport 16 years ago, and talked his way into the limousine she and her friends were taking to Vail for a skiing vacation. ''I thought, 'Oh, God, he's so cute, he's so nice,' '' Mrs. King, 41, recalled. Skiing with him the next day -- watching him ski, he was a superb skier -- she was hooked.</p>
        <p>They would have celebrated their 15th wedding anniversary last week.</p>
        <p>''I never saw him down in his life,'' Ms. Szafara said. ''It was always how great Judy was, how great the kids were, how great the house was.''</p>
        <p>SEAN P. LYNCH  and FARRELL P. LYNCH  Strivers, Like Their Parents</p>
        <p>Whatever their achievements, the Lynch boys were products of their upbringing. The children of Irish immigrants, Sean P. Lynch, top, and his brother Farrell P. Lynch were strivers like their parents.</p>
        <p>''They never forgot where they were from,'' said their sister, Ellen Lynch. Growing up in a family of seven in a two-bedroom house -- ''all the boys slept in the attic,'' she said -- they were a tight-knit group, and as adults with families, they often gathered in that same house, where their parents still live, for traditional Irish breakfasts.</p>
        <p>The brothers both worked at Cantor Fitzgerald; Sean Lynch was an interest rate options broker and Farrell Lynch, who had worked there long enough to be around for the 1993 bombing, was a partner.</p>
        <p>Farrell Lynch lived on Long Island with his wife, Eileen, and daughters Katie, 13, Meghan, 11, and Annie, 7. The couple met as sophomores in high school, and they were looking forward to their 15th anniversary this month. Farrell Lynch also looked forward to a day when he could retire and coach high school basketball, said his wife. ''He wanted to get into coaching one day -- that was his dream. Simple, but that's what he wanted,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Sean Lynch, 36, lived in Morristown, N.J., with his wife, Lori, and daughters Mary, 3, and Grace, 17 months. ''He was a very thoughtful person,'' said his wife. ''He was already saying to Mary, 'Be kind to your sister; always treat people well.' ''</p>
        <p>WILLIAM H. KELLY JR.  Mr. Long Beach Island</p>
        <p>If you lived on Long Beach Island in New Jersey, you knew William H. Kelly Jr. Although Mr. Kelly grew up in Bucks County, Pa., his family spent summers on the island, where he was able to indulge his passion for the water, learning to sail and surf. ''My friends would joke around; they used to call him 'Mr. L.B.I.,' '' said his girlfriend of three years, Sue Magee, an employee of Bloomberg L.P., where Mr. Kelly also worked.</p>
        <p>In fact, even if you did not live on Long Beach Island, you may have known Mr. Kelly, or the type of person he was. ''He wasn't a loud, life-of-the-party kind of guy, but he always sought out the person in any situation who wasn't comfortable, and made them feel welcome,'' said his sister Colleen Kelly. Mr. Kelly, 30, who lived in Stuyvesant Town, was a favorite uncle to his many nieces and nephews. Once, instead of giving them all individual Christmas gifts, he rented an ice rink for an afternoon, and invited his whole family.</p>
        <p>After Sept. 11, his mother, JoAnne Kelly, was surprised to receive an envelope full of a 4-year-old Billy's dark curls, from an early trip to the barber. She had given the envelope to a beloved neighbor, whom Mr. Kelly had nicknamed Pal, as a joke, and Pal had saved it for 26 years. Now Mrs. Kelly has something of her son left to treasure.</p>
        <p>ANTHONY JOVIC  A Special Plaque</p>
        <p>Anthony Jovic videotaped his sons, Matthew, 10, and Peter, 9, at every swimming meet they entered. He went to their practices. And he took them along when he and his wife, Cynthia, went on a cruise in the Caribbean. And whenever he came home from work, the boys would rush up to him and say, ''What did you do? Did you fight any fires?''</p>
        <p>He was a 39-year-old lieutenant, studying for October's captain's exam. Though on the rolls at Ladder Company 34 in Washington Heights, he was assigned on Sept. 11 to Engine Company 279 in Red Hook in Brooklyn, and was among the first men to arrive at the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>At Ladder Company 34, Capt. Arthur DePew recalled, Lieutenant Jovic is also noted for a kind of remembrance that predates videotape -- the brass plaques in firehouses that honor men who died in the line of duty. He did research on some who had never been remembered, like Eugene J. Caffrey, who died in 1921. Next Sept. 11, a plaque will go up with Lieutenant Jovic's name.</p>
        <p>As for the boys, Mrs. Jovic still takes them regularly to swimming and meets, but she says, ''Their hearts aren't in it.''</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHER S. EPPS  Accounting and Poetry</p>
        <p>Geneva Epps has not given up hope that the son she had late in life is alive. ''I'm just being hopeful and prayerful,'' she said of Christopher S. Epps, her seventh child and second son. ''I just can't seem to give up. I know that I'm not considered very wise and not facing reality. But the reality is that no one has showed me any proof that he is not alive.''</p>
        <p>Sister Epps, as she is called at the Greater Zion Baptist Church in the Bronx, knows that the 29-year-old Mr. Epps, an accountant for Marsh &amp; McLennan, was in the World Trade Center on Sept. 11. ''He said, 'Bye, Mom, see ya later,' '' she recalled. ''And I said, 'Have a blessed day.' And that was it.''</p>
        <p>Now she focuses on a September day in 2000 when her church honored her, and Mr. Epps recited from memory a poem he had stayed up all night writing.</p>
        <p>There were times when I was faced with danger</p>
        <p>And fear filled my head.</p>
        <p>Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I fear no evil;</p>
        <p>I remember what Sister Epps said.</p>
        <p>She asked the Lord every morning to watch over my life.</p>
        <p>I live today because God heard her plea.</p>
        <p>Now I go through this life as a grown man fast in your words.</p>
        <p>Please order my steps, for you are the Father.</p>
        <p>Others who love her call her Sister Epps,</p>
        <p>But I am just proud to call her my mother.</p>
        <p>EDNA CINTRON  Her Courage and Strength</p>
        <p>For Edna Cintron and her husband, William, every evening fit into a comforting routine. ''She had everything prompt, clean, neat, organized,'' Mr. Cintron, a 44-year-old doorman, said of his 46-year-old wife, an administrative assistant for Marsh &amp; McLennan. ''She would come out of work, come home, cook, make sure that when I would come out of work there was food on the table and everything. And every night we would have ice cream and we would watch TV.''</p>
        <p>That simple routine in their home in East Elmhurst, Queens, was remarkable, Mr. Cintron said, because they each had been homeless, and in their 12 years of marriage they had struggled with his alcoholism. ''We started from the bottom,'' he said, ''and we worked our way all the way up to the top,'' even opening a florist business, Sweet William's, in East Harlem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cintron said that his wife had given him the courage to go to detox and that last January he celebrated 12 years of sobriety. ''She made sure that she kept me in check,'' he said. ''She made sure that I did the things I was supposed to do. She was a very, very strong woman because she would put her foot down.</p>
        <p>''She was more like a mother to me. She would make sure that I would eat right and she would make sure that no one would manipulate me. So she was also my backbone. She made me strong. She made me who I am today.''</p>
        <p>MARK FRANCIS BRODERICK  A Remarkable Smile</p>
        <p>Mark Francis Broderick had a remarkable smile. It made everyone feel at ease with him, said Chris Dowd, his friend since they were fraternity brothers at St. John's University on Staten Island, N.Y.</p>
        <p>He had a good memory, too. He never forgot to call Mr. Dowd on his birthday. And Mr. Broderick vividly recalled the first time he saw the woman he would marry, in 1991. ''He remembered exactly what I was wearing that day,'' said Carolina Broderick. (It was a black skirt and pink blouse.)</p>
        <p>Organized and thorough -- traits one wants in an accountant -- Mr. Broderick was also known for taking his time -- so much so that he earned an ironic nickname, ''Sparky,'' many years ago. The easy-going Mr. Broderick liked it and it stuck.</p>
        <p>He joined Cantor Fitzgerald in April and when his 40th birthday came around on Sept. 2, he told his wife he wanted a family vacation, not a party. They took their sons, Matthew 7, Andrew 3, and James, 16 months, to Hershey, Pa.</p>
        <p>Eulogizing his friend at a service recently, Mr. Dowd asked, ''How many of us can remember him standing, smiling, with one or more of his kids hanging from his neck?''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
