<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something Missing in Fragile Cloud Forest: The Clouds</title>
    <meta content="20CLOU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/20/science/earth/20CLOU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1344481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Science Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clouds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Costa Rica</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monteverde Cloud Forest (Costa Rica)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Costa Rica</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EED8153BF933A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something Missing in Fragile Cloud Forest: The Clouds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Something Missing in Fragile Cloud Forest: The Clouds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists warn that tropical luxuriance of Costa Rica's Monteverde cloud forest, beloved by biologists and eco-tourists alike, may be at risk: clouds that bathe mountains seem to be disappearing; scientists say problem is deforestation, but not within Monteverde's vast network of reserves; researchers report evidence that deforestation in lowlands is lifting mountains' curtain of life-giving fog and mist out of forests's reach, leaving more and more of what had been cloud forest without clouds; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bathed in a curtain of life-giving fog and mist, the Monteverde cloud forest in the mountains of Costa Rica is a profusion of dripping green that stands as an international model of conservation gone right. But despite Monteverde's tens of thousands of protected acres, scientists say this tropical luxuriance, beloved by biologists and eco-tourists alike, may be at risk: the clouds that bathe the mountains seem to be disappearing.</p>
        <p>The problem, scientists say, is deforestation, but not within Monteverde's vast network of reserves. Instead, in a new study in Science, researchers report evidence that deforestation in the lowlands is lifting the mountains' curtain of life-giving fog and mist out of the forest's reach, leaving more and more of what had been cloud forest without clouds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists believe that deforestation is helping to strip the clouds from a mountain rain forest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bathed in a curtain of life-giving fog and mist, the Monteverde cloud forest in the mountains of Costa Rica is a profusion of dripping green that stands as an international model of conservation gone right. But despite Monteverde's tens of thousands of protected acres, scientists say this tropical luxuriance, beloved by biologists and eco-tourists alike, may be at risk: the clouds that bathe the mountains seem to be disappearing.</p>
        <p>The problem, scientists say, is deforestation, but not within Monteverde's vast network of reserves. Instead, in a new study in Science, researchers report evidence that deforestation in the lowlands is lifting the mountains' curtain of life-giving fog and mist out of the forest's reach, leaving more and more of what had been cloud forest without clouds.</p>
        <p>''We all thought we were doing a great job of protecting the area,'' said Dr. Robert O. Lawton, a tropical forest ecologist at the University of Alabama in Huntsville who was the lead author of the study. ''Now we're seeing that deforestation outside our mountain range, out of our control, can have a big impact.''</p>
        <p>Scientists say tropical mountain cloud forests, among the world's most threatened ecosystems, are likely to be suffering from losses of clouds in other parts of the world as well. Found throughout the tropics, cloud forests are typically rich in biodiversity, with each mountaintop often harboring its own unique suite of species.</p>
        <p>Chilly and difficult to reach, these forests are typically the last areas to be colonized by people, a final refuge of biodiversity in places where lowlands have been cleared and developed.</p>
        <p>''Many cloud forest organisms have literally nowhere to go,'' said Dr. Nalini M. Nadkarni, an ecologist at Evergreen State College in Olympia, Wash. ''They're stuck on an island of cloud forest. If you remove the cloud, it's curtains for them.''</p>
        <p>Of equal concern, some scientists say, are the study's implications for the many watersheds fed by wet highland forests.</p>
        <p>''We always knew that if you have a town and a mountain behind it, you protect the mountain forests to protect the water,'' said Dr. James O. Juvik, a tropical ecologist at the University of Hawaii at Hilo. ''This says, even if you leave the cloud forest intact like good conservationists, if you clear the lowland forests, you can diminish the cloud forest and affect your water flow.''</p>
        <p>Earlier studies provided evidence that global climate change was also lifting the clouds at Monteverde. Scientists said that it was unclear whether deforestation or global warming would be a more potent force, but that the two could easily heighten each other's effects in the mountains.</p>
        <p>While watered by rains during the rainy season, Monteverde gets most of its critical moisture during the dry season from the mist and fog of low-lying clouds. Dr. Lawton said he and colleagues began the study when they realized that deforestation in lowlands could warm and dry the air flowing toward Monteverde. That warmer, drier air, they reasoned, might be forced to rise higher to make clouds, robbing parts of the forest of critical moisture.</p>
        <p>When researchers compared forested and deforested lowland areas, looking at the actual accumulation of clouds and at computer simulations, that was just what they saw. Where there was more forest, there were more and lower-hanging clouds. Air moving over deforested areas, in contrast, formed cloud banks over the mountains that were higher and fewer.</p>
        <p>Shifts in fog and mist up and down a mountain are subtle changes not easily seen and rarely quantified, so it should not be surprising that one of the first places where such changes would be noticed would be Monteverde, a cloud forest heavily peopled by scientists.</p>
        <p>Begun as a colony of expatriate North American Quakers, Monteverde has been a huge attraction for American biologists, many of whom have devoted their careers to the flora and fauna of the region. A quick look at the forest's inhabitants makes clear why -- from the record-breaking diversity of orchids to creatures like the resplendent quetzal, a glittering green, kite-tailed bird truly worthy of its name, and the so-called singing mice that whistle and chirp like birds.</p>
        <p>Longtime researchers say they can see the biological effects of the shifting mists and clouds as well.</p>
        <p>''What really makes it obvious is you can look out the window now and see species you never saw up here before,'' said Dr. J. Alan Pounds, resident biologist at the Monteverde Cloud Forest Preserve. ''We see the black-headed nightingale-thrush and the keel-billed toucan, species you normally only see further downslope. They're now inhabiting what used to be good cloud forest.''</p>
        <p>Researchers say the effects of deforestation and global warming might also explain other mysteries on the mountain, including the puzzling disappearance of Monteverde's golden toad. A flashy orange creature last seen in the late 1980's, the golden toad has become an international symbol of the world's disappearing amphibians. Seeing how even pristine and protected forests like those at Monteverde can lose their crucial mists and clouds, researchers say it becomes less mysterious how a water-loving creature like the golden toad could vanish even from a forest where every tree still stands.</p>
        <p>The disappearance of such charismatic creatures is not only a worry for biologists. Monteverde is an eco-tourism mecca, with nearly 50,000 nature-loving visitors walking its trails each year, stopping for a bite to eat or perhaps picking up a golden toad mug or Monteverde T-shirt along the way. Scientists say that if the cloud forest falters, much business will be lost along with the unique species.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, Monteverde is on the crest of a mountain,'' Dr. Juvik said. ''Maybe if it were on the side, it could migrate upward with the clouds. In this case, it's already at the top. If you move the cloud forest up, then the cloud forest is bye-bye.''</p>
        <p>Researchers said it was difficult to think of a cure for an atmospheric problem like the receding clouds. But Dr. Nadkarni said she hoped the new study would at least rally the scientific troops to begin studying and documenting Monteverde's changes.</p>
        <p>''We need to monitor what's going on,'' she said. ''This is happening now.''</p>
        <p>Science Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
