<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pompeii in Slow Motion</title>
    <meta content="CEIDE.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/08/travel/CEIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1307525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stone Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ceide Fields (Ireland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harlan, Megan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDA1039F93BA35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pompeii in Slow Motion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Pompeii in Slow Motion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEGAN HARLAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harlan, Megan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Megan Harlan article on Ceide Fields in County Mayo, Ireland, one of largest Stone Age sites in world; its farms, houses and tombs have been perfectly preserved by bog that began encroaching on it five millenniums ago; only fraction of site's five square miles has been thoroughly excavated since work began in 1969; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the boggy coastal moors of County Mayo in northwest Ireland lies one of the largest Stone Age sites in the world -- though it might not seem obvious at first glance.</p>
        <p>It isn't that Ceide Fields, a sprawling Neolithic community of farms, houses and tombs, has been destroyed or dismantled in the 5,500 years since it was built. In fact, much of the ancient, enclosed settlement has been perfectly preserved, thanks to the bog that began to encroach some five millenniums ago and slowly enveloped every structure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Neolithic village at Ceide Fields in County Mayo has been well preserved, thanks to a bog that began to overwhelm it 5,000 years ago</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the boggy coastal moors of County Mayo in northwest Ireland lies one of the largest Stone Age sites in the world -- though it might not seem obvious at first glance.</p>
        <p>It isn't that Ceide Fields, a sprawling Neolithic community of farms, houses and tombs, has been destroyed or dismantled in the 5,500 years since it was built. In fact, much of the ancient, enclosed settlement has been perfectly preserved, thanks to the bog that began to encroach some five millenniums ago and slowly enveloped every structure.</p>
        <p>The site's lead archaeologist, Seamus Caulfield, of University College, Dublin, has likened this phenomenon to ''a slow-motion Pompeii.'' While the bog's sudden and inexorable expansion forced Ceide Fields' residents to move away, it also kept a good number of the buildings and objects they used safely submerged beneath what is today a seven-foot layer of marshy earth.</p>
        <p>The Nobel Prize-winning Irish poet Seamus Heaney evoked the discovery of North Mayo's buried archaeological treasures in his 1975 poem ''Belderg'': ''When he stripped off blanket bog/ the soft-piled centuries/ fell open . . .'' Heaney wrote the poem after an inspiring visit with the local schoolteacher Patrick Caulfield, the father of the archaeologist Seamus Caulfield. In the 1930's the elder Caulfield realized that his neighbors, while cutting and drying bog turf into peat (Ireland's traditional fuel), were hitting deep-lying, patterned walls of stones. He rightly surmised that these walls had to be many thousands of years old, since it would have taken that long for such thick bog to accumulate.</p>
        <p>Though only a fraction of the site's five square miles has been thoroughly excavated since work began in 1969, the entire area is open to visitors, and from March through November archaeologists and doctoral students lead tours of numerous fascinating finds. For those of us harboring latent fantasies of a career in archaeology -- and I'll cheerfully admit, I do -- Ceide Fields is a bewitching place, full of tantalizing clues about humanity's prehistoric past.</p>
        <p>On the morning last August when I drove the 20 miles northwest to Ceide Fields from my hotel in Ballina, a bustling city in the heart of County Mayo, I passed through the Moy River Valley, with its quintessentially Irish countryside of peridot green pastures dotted with cottages and churches, and, farther on, the variegated Victorian storefronts of tiny Ballycastle town.</p>
        <p>But as I headed west along Mayo's North Coast Road, the landscape suddenly grew dramatic. The road runs for about five miles alongside the spectacularly serrated Ceide Cliffs, with their countless horizontal strata of limestone and shale rising some 370 feet  -- all in all resembling a huge layer cake cut in jagged slices. Meanwhile, to my left, the lush meadows of Mayo's interior had given way to an empty, khaki-colored expanse of bog.</p>
        <p>Called blanket bog for good reason, these boglands cover hundreds of soggy, unfarmable square miles in northwest Mayo, which helps explain why the region is Ireland's least populous. With its high sloping, treeless hills, this desolate landscape resembled a desert -- one made of sodden soil instead of sand.</p>
        <p>But something glistened in the distance. Ceide means flat-topped hill in Gaelic (and, trickily, is pronounced ''Cajun'' without the ''n''), and as I approached this vast hill, a glint of angled glass reflected in the sun, like a prism catching light. This was the Ceide Fields Interpretive Center, a sparkling glass-and-stone pyramid at the hill's coastal base. As if on cue, the changeable sky, which had undulated between blue and pewter, displayed a rainbow arching over the pyramid to the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>Rising some 60 feet high, the Interpretive Center won Ireland's Building of the Year Award when it opened in 1993. It is a handsome three-leveled edifice, the bottom third  sided with bog turf, so that the building appears to have sprouted naturally from the ground. Gray-green limestone slabs, the same stone found in Ceide Cliffs, front the middle section. And the towering apex is composed of glass walls supported by stainless-steel beams. Designed by Mary McKenna at Ireland's Office of Public Works, these architectural elements are at once harmonious with the environment and in striking contrast to it.</p>
        <p>The pyramid's loftlike, oak-and-sandstone interior is just as stylish. The main floor houses crisp exhibitions on the archaeology and botany of Ceide Fields; a sleek, 75-seat theater screening a short documentary on the region; and a pleasant cafe, serving soups, sandwiches and pastries. The statuesque centerpiece is a 15-foot section of copper-colored 4,500-year-old Scotch pine retrieved from a nearby bog. A second-story gallery contains exhibitions on local geology, while the glassed-in third floor consists entirely of a platform for viewing the fields, cliffs and ocean.</p>
        <p>The center provides a much-needed window onto the landscape's often enigmatic patterns of ruins -- and a much-needed shelter from northwest Mayo's frequent rainstorms. But since an hourlong tour of the excavations was about to begin, I put off exploring it, eager to get outside into the sunlight that now streamed through the glass apex.</p>
        <p>The tour guide, Dredagh O'Connor, a doctoral student at the University of Edinburgh and a native of Ballycastle, ushered our small group out the back entrance and up a wooden staircase ascending Ceide hill. Gravel pathways snaked through the grassy boglands, which, up close, reveal purple heathers and sprays of spotted yellow orchids. The tour follows one such pathway around the boundary of a five-acre field  once inhabited by a Neolithic family. As she led us across olive green moors stretching south to the horizon, Ms. O'Connor explained the extent of what we were looking at.</p>
        <p>Ceide Fields encompasses hundreds of individual, interlinked Stone Age farms once inhabited by as many as 1,000 people. These homesteads were surprisingly well organized. Sets of parallel field walls, over a mile long, run inland from the coast. Perpendicular dividing walls crisscross these longer walls into neat, rectangular plots of anywhere from 5 to 17 acres. Each plot provided just enough room to sustain an extended family of cattle herders and wheat farmers.</p>
        <p>While some sandstone walls have been excavated, most remain buried in a secondary, subterranean landscape. To find these underground walls, archaeologists have borrowed the traditional method of local farmers to dig for trees buried beneath the bog: long iron probes are thrust into the bog; if they strike something hard, a whitewashed bamboo rod is inserted into the probe's hollow center and left as a marker indicating the existence of a wall or a tree.</p>
        <p>Thus much of what visitors see at Ceide Fields are these bamboo poles delineating the ancient field wall system -- which somewhat resemble an enormous game of connect-the-dots. And the center and tour help connect these dots with intriguing evidence about prehistoric life.</p>
        <p>Our first stop was at an ancient animal pen, a small oval enclosure attached to an excavated field wall. The Neolithic settlers of Ceide arrived in longboats -- probably from France or Scotland -- and introduced to Ireland livestock like cattle and sheep. This meant they would have spun wool for fabrics -- so that their fashion sense might have looked revolutionary indeed to Ireland's indigenous Mesolithic people, nomadic fisherman and hunters who probably swathed themselves in animal skins.</p>
        <p>As the sky grew overcast, we hiked another 30 yards to the remains of the 5,500-year-old Behy house, the base of a round hut measuring 20 feet in diameter. Ms. O'Connor told us that the Behy house was abandoned before the Egyptian pyramids were even built. The simple structure yielded key domestic implements like shouldered pottery, leaf-shaped arrowheads, a stone ax and, most important, a stone plow blade, models and drawings of which can be seen in the visitor center. Along with animal husbandry, the Ceide settlers brought with them another giant leap forward for mankind from continental Europe -- cultivation of grains.</p>
        <p>This portrait of an orderly agrarian society undercuts most previous theories about human life during the Neolithic era. Farming was thought to be a much more haphazard affair, because at other Neolithic sites, vestiges of original, systematic plans of settlement have been destroyed or rearranged -- for example, the stone walls dismantled and used for new walls. But Ceide Fields is unique for being so perfectly intact -- and looking about as methodically laid out as any modern suburban subdivision.</p>
        <p>More extraordinary still is that Ceide Fields has no defensive walls. Since the people lived in a dispersed, unfortified community, they apparently did not fear attacks, either by local or foreign invaders. So much for visions of warring Stone Age barbarians: this group, anyway, seems to have lived peaceful, rather idyllic lives.</p>
        <p>As we headed back to the center,  an Atlantic squall swept through, ripping against the sturdy golf umbrellas Ms. O'Connor had quickly run to fetch for the group. She shouted apologies for the storm above the winds, but also pointed out that if it hadn't been for the rain, the bogs would never have grown -- and Ceide's artifacts probably wouldn't have survived.</p>
        <p>A bog is 90 percent water, its soil so saturated that when the grasses and heathers that grow on its surface die, they don't fully decay but accumulate in layers. At least 175 days of rain a year are required for this to happen; North Mayo gets an average of 225 days.</p>
        <p>But Ceide's residents may have played a key role in the bog's devastating growth. To provide fuel, timber and space, they clear-cut the primeval oak and pine forests, thereby directly exposing the soil to persistent rainfall.</p>
        <p>A climate change more than 5,000 years ago -- when the temperature abruptly dropped five degrees, causing more rain -- may have also been to blame, Either way, the people of Ceide probably moved no farther than to neighboring settlements at Ballycastle.</p>
        <p>Soaked through, our tour group retreated to the center to grab warming cups of coffee and explore the exhibitions. The most impressive diorama is a scale model of the Ballyglass house, excavated on private land on the eastern border of Ceide Fields, about three miles from the center. The foundation of the house was discovered beneath a megalithic  tomb typical of the region: a cairn with two galleries contained cremated human remains, and opened onto a circular standing stone courtyard.</p>
        <p>But the Ballyglass house struck me as a more poignant glimpse of prehistory. About 40 feet long and 20 feet wide, it had a large central room, two small chambers, a high-pitched ceiling and an indoor hearth, and was probably roofed with thatch. It is, in other words, strikingly similar to the traditional thatched cottages so common in contemporary rural Ireland.</p>
        <p>I climbed spiral stairs to the viewing platform in the apex, where rain thrashed against the glass walls, and gazed at the windswept fields outside. Seamus Heaney called this ''a landscape fossilized.'' And it was both eerie and comforting to imagine that the familiar Irish countryside of today -- with its neat, rectangular cottages, low stone walls partitioning green pastures, and places of worship -- might not have looked so very different in the Stone Age.</p>
        <p>Windows onto the ruins</p>
        <p>Tour Information</p>
        <p>The Ceide Fields Interpretive Center (353-96) 43325, fax (353-96) 43261, www.heritageireland.ie, is run by Duchas, Ireland's excellent government-run heritage service, and is on R-314, or the North Coast Road, five miles from Ballycastle.</p>
        <p>The center opened in late April this year (rather than the usual mid-March) because of concerns about the spread of foot-and-mouth disease. It is open normal hours now, however, and does not anticipate any more closings.</p>
        <p>From June to September the center's hours are 9:30 a.m. to 6:30 p.m. every day; in October and from mid-March to May, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; in November, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. From December through early March, the center is open to groups with reservations. Rain is the norm in winter, and it is wise to wear or carry waterproofed gear there at all times of the year.</p>
        <p>Entrance tickets cost $2.80 for adults (at $1.13 to the Irish pound), and include a tour of the excavations. These tours usually start every hour on the hour, with the last one beginning an hour before closing.</p>
        <p>Dining and Lodging</p>
        <p>Ballina is the biggest town in Mayo and makes a good jumping-off point for exploring the northwest region. Its restaurants, which specialize in the plentiful salmon from the Moy River Valley, include the cozy Dillon's Bar and Restaurant, (353-96) 72230, on Dillon Terrace (a salmon entree costs about $16 in the restaurant, $10 in the bar, without drinks).</p>
        <p>I stayed at Bartra House, (353-96) 22200, fax (353-96) 22111, a pleasant, rambling old 21-room Victorian hotel with a friendly staff on the bustling main strip, Pearse Street. An exceedingly spacious single room, including Irish breakfast, cost me $40; doubles run $35 a person.</p>
        <p>Closer to Ceide Fields are a number of small B &amp; B's in more dramatic settings. The Yellow Rose, (353-96) 43125) in Belderrig, five miles west of Ceide Fields on R-314, has three rooms with ocean views costing $20 a person for a double. Unlike many other local B &amp; B's, it is open year round.</p>
        <p>MEGAN HARLAN</p>
        <p>MEGAN HARLAN is a journalist and poet who lives in San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MEGAN HARLAN is a journalist and poet who lives in San Francisco.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
