<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AFTER SIX MONTHS, BUSH TEAM PLANS CHANGE OF FOCUS</title>
    <meta content="05BUSH$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/05/politics/05BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1315002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDA103CF936A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AFTER SIX MONTHS, BUSH TEAM PLANS CHANGE OF FOCUS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After First 6 Months, Bush Is to Change Focus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Administration officials say Pres Bush plans significant change of focus, including renewed attention to education and immigration and vigorous discussion of values, interviews; say Bush wants to move beyond conventional Republican agenda that mainly defined beginning of his presidency to tackle issues and themes Americans see in more emotional, personal way; hope shift will improve his and his party's standing with moderates, independents and women; change will also include shift in staging of events to put him in less formal settings; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Midway through his first year, President Bush is planning a significant change in focus that includes renewed attention to issues like education and immigration and a vigorous discussion of values.</p>
        <p>According to interviews with many administration officials, Mr. Bush wants to move beyond the conventional Republican agenda of tax cuts and energy production that mainly defined the beginning of his presidency and tackle issues and themes that strike Americans in a more emotional, personal way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush is planning to move beyond the conventional Republican agenda and devote attention to issues like education and immigration, administration officials say</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Midway through his first year, President Bush is planning a significant change in focus that includes renewed attention to issues like education and immigration and a vigorous discussion of values.</p>
        <p>According to interviews with many administration officials, Mr. Bush wants to move beyond the conventional Republican agenda of tax cuts and energy production that mainly defined the beginning of his presidency and tackle issues and themes that strike Americans in a more emotional, personal way.</p>
        <p>He hopes to put an extra emphasis on what he has called the ''compassionate'' nature of his conservatism with events and remarks this month, during a summer vacation in Texas, and with the initiatives he pursues when he returns to the White House after Labor Day. His aides, and Republican lawmakers who are up for re-election in 2002, hope that in the process Mr. Bush will improve his and his party's standing with moderates, independents and women.</p>
        <p>The president's effort will also include a shift in the staging of his events, as aides look for ways to shove aside lecterns and put Mr. Bush in less formal settings, with small groups of voters. Administration officials and their allies have long bemoaned Mr. Bush's stiffness and, in some cases, clumsiness in front of a microphone, and they have worried that his public appearances do not demonstrate the warmth that they see in him, or his firm grasp of policy.</p>
        <p>''We want to let the country get a glimpse of the real George W. Bush,'' said Nicholas E. Calio, the administration's chief liaison to Congress, adding that the administration also wanted Americans to ''see the ease with which he understands and talks about issues.''</p>
        <p>''We've got to find a way to bring those elements out,'' Mr. Calio said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush pivots from his first six months in office to the rest of a year fraught with political dangers, the important adjustments that he and his aides are deliberating and making partly reflect his movement from old to new items on his legislative and political check list.</p>
        <p>But these changes also underscore a recognition by administration officials that while the president is leaving for his summer break today with a seemingly solid job approval rating and several important legislative victories under his belt, he could be doing much better and has numerous political vulnerabilities.</p>
        <p>In particular, Mr. Bush continues to battle many Americans' perceptions of him as someone who does not necessarily understand their problems or worry as much about them as he does about business. Polls suggest that most voters like and respect him, but that many find him, in a sense, ideologically aloof.</p>
        <p>''That's one of the big frustrations,'' a Republican strategist with close ties to the administration said. The strategist then recalled the way Mr. Bush sought to sell himself during the presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>''Remember the term 'different kind of Republican'?'' the strategist said. ''They want to get back to that. So far, in fact and in perception, be it the tax cut or the pro-business regulatory moves, Bush is a fairly orthodox Republican.''</p>
        <p>So he will do less orthodox things over the coming months, his aides and allies say. He will push for a prescription drug benefit for elderly Americans and for a more accommodating approach to illegal immigrants, something he has already begun advocating.</p>
        <p>He will talk more about values and possibly promote government initiatives to help parents protect their children from certain cultural influences and to reduce teen pregnancy through abstinence-based programs. He will exhort Americans to pitch in and help those who need it, instead of relying on the government to do so.</p>
        <p>And while some of this is traditional music to socially conservative ears, the administration is looking for a broader audience and trying to accomplish more than solidifying its support on the right.</p>
        <p>Celinda Lake, a Democratic pollster, said Mr. Bush had his work cut out for him in convincing Americans that he was a champion of their basic concerns, because many voters see his tax cut as a gift to the rich and believe he is sheltering corporations from environmental responsibility.</p>
        <p>''He is perceived to be too much on the side of wealthy, big-business, monied interests, and it's really starting to permeate broad assumptions about him,'' Ms. Lake said. ''This fall will be very telling.''</p>
        <p>One senior administration official said having Mr. Bush address issues like teen pregnancy and adoption would give voters ''a glimpse of George Bush the man and the things he cares about'' and would focus on ''the commonality that he has with the others in the country.''</p>
        <p>Another official said this values-based discussion, occurring under the rubric ''Communities of Character,'' was a way to ''put some emphasis on his commitment to compassionate, activist government.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will essentially begin doing that this month, with sporadic events during trips from his ranch in Crawford, Tex. His aides have given the month a theme, ''Home to the Heartland,'' and Mr. Bush on Friday offered a preview of how he will seek to position himself.</p>
        <p>''We must help disadvantaged Americans find opportunity,'' he said, foreshadowing what he planned to discuss over coming months. ''We must show that our welcoming society values the ideals and contributions of immigrants. We must challenge Americans to be citizens, not spectators, in the renewal of their neighborhoods and their cities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his aides are also bracing for what they acknowledge will be one of the biggest -- and perhaps most defining -- decisions of his presidency, whether to permit federal financing for research on embryonic stem cells and under what conditions. He said today that he intends to make his decision before Congress returns in September.</p>
        <p>In the process, he could reassure or alienate conservatives, and he could strengthen or surrender a claim to the center. Republicans who think Mr. Bush has tilted too far to the right see the stem cell decision as a critical opportunity for him to find a different political equilibrium.</p>
        <p>Kenneth M. Duberstein, a former chief of staff for President Ronald Reagan, envisioned a way in which the coming weeks and months could, in his view, work powerfully to Mr. Bush's benefit.</p>
        <p>''If you have him in the Rose Garden surrounded by Republican and Democratic legislators signing a patients' bill of rights, and then he makes what I would term the right decision on stem cell -- i.e., federal funding for it -- then he has put real meat on the bones of compassionate conservatism,'' Mr. Duberstein said.</p>
        <p>Administration officials say moral principle, not political calculus, will guide Mr. Bush's stem cell decision. But whatever he decides, these officials concede that his fluency in talking about it, and persuading Americans that he put intense thought into it, is crucial. The administration has been exhaustively deliberating how to handle the announcement.</p>
        <p>Aides have weighed possibilities as disparate as a televised address from the Oval Office and the release of a written document stating Mr. Bush's position. The likeliest scenario, several administration allies say, is some kind of news conference.</p>
        <p>''I believe that the explanation is probably just as important as the decision,'' said Andrew H. Card Jr., Mr. Bush's chief of staff, adding that this was much ''bigger than traditional policy decisions.''</p>
        <p>The administration's determination to present Mr. Bush as thoughtful and ruminative dovetails with its desire to focus on issues that are not simply about dollars and cents.</p>
        <p>In both cases, Mr. Bush and his aides would like voters to see him as more than a tax-cutting conservative. A more rounded portrait could help the administration -- and the party -- during the inevitable battles over appropriations bills this fall, when Democratic leaders will say the tax cut Mr. Bush signed is starving vital spending.</p>
        <p>Their hand could be strengthened considerably by the new surplus estimates the Congressional Budget Office will probably release later this month. Economists and lawmakers expect those estimates to be smaller than previous ones, buttressing many Democrats' claims that the tax cut was not affordable.</p>
        <p>That will also complicate another of Mr. Bush's goals: military reforms, including national missile defense.</p>
        <p>''Because of the budget implications, they have to get that done sooner rather than later,'' said Charlie Black, a Republican strategist who has advised the administration. ''That's going to be a big sales job.''</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Bush's record on foreign policy will come under fresh review when he takes the most ambitious of his overseas trips as president, traveling to China in October.</p>
        <p>Political analysts said that his break with allies on a global warming treaty, other decisions related to the environment and his focus on the tax cut last winter combined to emphasize Mr. Bush's conservatism.</p>
        <p>''He needs to do more for the center,'' said Senator Arlen Specter, a Pennsylvania Republican.</p>
        <p>Mr. Specter said that Mr. Bush was being personally attentive to moderates like him, but that the president ''has to do more on the issues.'' Mr. Specter added that stem cell research, which he favors, would be a perfect place to start.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides feel that inadequate attention has been paid to what they see as his centrist credentials and accomplishments on education. Mr. Bush dropped vouchers from education bills that, in different forms, were passed by the House and Senate, and he and his aides are intent on seeing those bills successfully reconciled and sent to his desk.</p>
        <p>''We've got to get that education package through the conference committee,'' Mr. Card said, later adding, ''He's going to keep talking about education, even after he signs education into law.''</p>
        <p>''He's also going to do an awful lot on the environment,'' Mr. Card said, although he did not specify what that would be.</p>
        <p>What was clear was that, bit by bit, the administration would try to address Mr. Bush's vulnerabilities and cast him as someone who cares deeply and can talk articulately about Americans' noneconomic concerns. The administration is hatching ideas for addressing those issues.</p>
        <p>''They want him to connect more with average citizens,'' said the strategist who worried that Mr. Bush had not established himself as a ''different kind of Republican.''</p>
        <p>''If you're stuck in box of Republican orthodoxy,'' the strategist said, ''and you came on the scene as a different kind of Republican, you better get flat to it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
