<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Easier To Be Green</title>
    <meta content="08ASIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/08/weekinreview/08ASIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1284085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Berkeley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">england</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Berkeley</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Dolgeville</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">McCartney, Paul</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Harvey, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D9123EF93BA35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Easier To Be Green</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Meat eaters, already in panic over foot-and-mouth disease, also face I-told-you-so advice from vegetarians, who usually occupy ground somewhere between temperance ladies, quacks or moralists determined to deprive others of gustatory pleasure; photo of ad on giving peas a chance (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR too long, vegetarians were regarded as kooks, cranks and moralists by a nation that found self-definition in hot dogs and hamburgers rather than carrots and tofu.</p>
        <p>But now the worm -- or rather, the sprout -- has turned. Meat eaters are in a panic over the specter of incurable mad cow disease. They are haunted by images of infected corpses of cows and sheep, burned in Britain to halt the spread of foot-and-mouth disease. And ''Fast Food Nation: The Dark Side of the All-American Meal,'' a muckraking best seller by Eric Schlosser, tells more than many want to know about all those burgers. Surely it is the vegetarians' turn to say, ''I told you so.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR too long, vegetarians were regarded as kooks, cranks and moralists by a nation that found self-definition in hot dogs and hamburgers rather than carrots and tofu.</p>
        <p>But now the worm -- or rather, the sprout -- has turned. Meat eaters are in a panic over the specter of incurable mad cow disease. They are haunted by images of infected corpses of cows and sheep, burned in Britain to halt the spread of foot-and-mouth disease. And ''Fast Food Nation: The Dark Side of the All-American Meal,'' a muckraking best seller by Eric Schlosser, tells more than many want to know about all those burgers. Surely it is the vegetarians' turn to say, ''I told you so.''</p>
        <p>And don't think they won't.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, among my friends there is a lot of gloating,'' said Rynn Berry, a teacher and historian of vegetarianism, whose books include ''Famous Vegetarians and Their Recipes'' (Pythagorean Press, 1990). ''But many are distressed that more people aren't becoming vegetarian. A friend in England told me the vegetarian societies aren't capitalizing on the panic as they should. Vegetarians should be more opportunistic in inducting potential vegetarians into the movement.''</p>
        <p>Of course, organized vegetarianism has achieved little among mainstream carnivores beyond raising their level of resentment. In the popular imagination, vegetarians historically occupied the middle ground between the temperance lady and the quack -- moralists and crackpots determined to deprive people of joy. This stereotype evolved in the last 30 years to include hippies and others whose political, moral or medical consciousness was formed by the ferment of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>The image was abetted by the American impulse to equate vegetables with punishment, or, at least, lack of pleasure -- ''Eat your vegetbles, or no dessert!'' In fact, for generations of children reared on dreary canned peas, or tasteless heads of iceberg lettuce, eating vegetables was punishment. But this changed in recent decades as more Americans experienced the pleasure of eating seasonal, farm-raised vegetables. Landmark restaurants like Chez Panisse in Berkeley, Calif., focused meals around gloriously fresh vegetables, and Americans have become more open to robust cuisines that emphasize vegetables, from Indian to Italian.</p>
        <p>''We still have a lot of myths about vegetarians that have to be overcome,'' said Joanne Stepaniak, a representative of the North American Vegetarian Society in Dolgeville, N.Y. ''They believe that vegetarians subsist on lettuce leaves and carrot sticks. But, with more vegetarian cookbooks, restaurants and TV shows, people are starting to realize that vegetarian meals can not only be beautiful, but tasty and gourmet.''</p>
        <p>Still, even if many Americans are feeling new enthusiasm about vegetables, their attitude toward vegetarians is another matter. For their part, no matter how secure many vegetarians feel on their moral perch, they are often skeptical about a bunch of panicky meat eaters who've only recently pushed away their steaks.</p>
        <p>''A lot of vegetarians look down their noses at people who give up meat out of panic or for what they call the wrong reasons,'' Mr. Berry said. ''But I say any reason for not eating animals is a good one.''</p>
        <p>For most vegetarians, the goal is not simply for others to give up red meat. For some, even giving up all meat isn't enough. They may become vegans, eating no animal products at all, from milk to honey. ''Fruitarians'' and ''rawfooders'' are yet more strict.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berry, 46, has been a rawfooder since 1994, after years of veganism. Eating only raw foods, he says, increased his energy and freed him from cooking.</p>
        <p>''I also felt that I was making a small contribution to the planet's ecological health by not consuming fossil fuels for cooking,'' Mr. Berry explained.</p>
        <p>Such laudable reasons have done little to win over meat-eaters. Nor have the examples of famous vegetarians like Paul McCartney and Isaac Bashevis Singer, to say nothing of Leonardo da Vinci. Even Jesus was a vegetarian, Mr. Berry says, but not Hitler.</p>
        <p>Through their history, Americans embraced vegetarianism periodically, especially in waves of food fears. Many medical professionals in the 19th century believed meat-eating was unhealthy, said Andrew F. Smith, who teaches culinary history at the New School for Social Research in New York City. ''There was a medical view of the world that concluded that eating meats caused disease by transmitting bad humors,'' he said. More analogous to today, he said, was a tuberculosis epidemic in the 1840's in New York that was linked to milk. It turned out dairy cows, moved to the city to supply fresh milk, had been fed brewery refuse and other garbage and were transmitting disease.</p>
        <p>Regardless of your culinary persuasion, vegetarianism has produced some undeniable benefits for humanity. Dr. John Harvey Kellogg, best known as the inventor of breakfast cereals, was a vegetarian who insisted all animal products were bad for the health. But he didn't just scold, he took action. In answer to those who feared a vegetarian diet would not provide sufficient protein, he patented a process for making peanut butter. As generations of parents who pack school lunches for children know, it is the best fast food of all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
