<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Smart Set Wastes Brainpower on Socializing</title>
    <meta content="25LETT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mensa Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burton, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D8163AF936A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Smart Set Wastes Brainpower on Socializing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Burton letter on November 18 article holds Mensa members should divert small portion of brain power to working on solutions to serious problems</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Viewed from my 25 years as a Mensa member, ''Hanging Out With the Smart Set'' (Nov. 18) is an apropos title for the New Jersey chapter, or indeed of the national organization. ''Hanging out'' indicates that our predominant interest is in social gatherings. ''Smart'' applies to our cleverness in games and puzzles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Viewed from my 25 years as a Mensa member, ''Hanging Out With the Smart Set'' (Nov. 18) is an apropos title for the New Jersey chapter, or indeed of the national organization. ''Hanging out'' indicates that our predominant interest is in social gatherings. ''Smart'' applies to our cleverness in games and puzzles.</p>
        <p>What has been disappointing to me and a very small minority of members is what seems to be a lack of  what we had expected to be a forum for intelligent and constructive debates about the tough problems facing the nation and the world.</p>
        <p>The Times article ends with a Mensan saying ''we have our priorities straight. We're searching for happiness.'' Fine, but just as as individuals and as a nation, we feel impelled to divert a small portion of our wealth to the welfare of the less fortunate, should not Mensans divert some small portion of their brainpower to working on solutions to the many serious problems facing the nation and the world in this century?  Is there a way to avert the predictable ill effects of global warming without damaging our economy as our politicians fear? Are there measures in addition to our military actions that we should be taking to address the root causes of the terrorism that is a hazard to our well-being? With a finite planet can we  continue with an never ending growth of population and utilization of natural resources? It is regretful  that Mensan brain power is dormant on such matters.</p>
        <p>JOHN BURTON  Washington</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
