<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="04FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1283094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDC163EF937A35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>China Demands Apology For Planes' Collision  Beijing blamed the United States for the midair collision of a spy plane and a Chinese fighter, and it suggested that the release of the 24-member American crew hinged on Washington's willingness to apologize. President Bush called for the crew's immediate return, though he set no deadline. Secretary of State Colin L. Powell said he saw no reason for an American apology.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>China Demands Apology For Planes' Collision  Beijing blamed the United States for the midair collision of a spy plane and a Chinese fighter, and it suggested that the release of the 24-member American crew hinged on Washington's willingness to apologize. President Bush called for the crew's immediate return, though he set no deadline. Secretary of State Colin L. Powell said he saw no reason for an American apology.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>If the collision occurred where the Pentagon has indicated, the Bush administration has strong legal standing in demanding that both the plane and its crew be released promptly, several legal experts said. But in the more practical realm, they said, the American position could be damaged by some of the Pentagon's own actions in the cold war and after.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Two American officials met with crew members and said their condition appeared to be good.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Palestinian's Bleak Prognosis  Mohammed Dahlan, the Gaza security chief, said Palestinians, with little hope for a full peace settlement, were prepared for a long period of sacrifice. A mortar round wounded an Israeli baby in Gaza, and the Israelis retaliated by shelling.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Milosevic Admission on Bosnia  Bosnia's Foreign Ministry said an admission by the jailed former president of Yugoslavia, Slobodan Milosevic, that he channeled state funds to Serbian forces in Croatia and Bosnia in the 1990's should remove any doubt that Yugoslavia had a role in atrocities committed in those wars.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Putin as Friend to Business  President Vladimir V. Putin promised a governmentwide shake-up intended to make business work in Russia, reverse capital flight and sustain new economic growth.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Battle over Russian TV Station  Foes of the media baron Vladimir A. Gusinsky, who has been a frequent critic of President Vladimir V. Putin, staged a renegade stockholder's meeting at which they appeared to take control of the nationwide NTV television network, the only one not under effective state control.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-18</p>
        <p>Cheney Plays Tiebreaker On a Bush Tax Cut Vote  Vice President Dick Cheney cast his first tie-breaking vote, enabling President Bush's tax plan to pass its first Senate test, 51 to 50. The vote blocked a Democratic effort to pare back the $1.6 trillion tax cut to pay for drug coverage under Medicare.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Shift in Health Priorities  President Bush's budget will propose deep cuts in various health programs for people without health insurance, administration officials said. The programs, championed by President Bill Clinton, would be reduced to $20 million from the current level of $140 million; the programs received $40 million in the previous fiscal year. Over all, officials said, the Health and Human Services budget will rise by 5 percent, to $55.5 billion. But all of the net increase goes to the National Institutes of Health, for biomedical research not patient care.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>No Change on Climate Treaty  The Bush administration rejected a European request to reconsider its decision to abandon the Kyoto Protocol on global warming.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Strategy for Campaign Bill  House supporters of the Senate's newly passed McCain-Feingold campaign finance overhaul began a drive to bring the bill to a House vote before Memorial Day and promised to remind freshman Republicans whose last campaigns were aided by Senator John McCain of their commitment to changing the system.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Recount Review Favors Bush  A newspaperanalysis by The Miami Herald suggested that President Bush would have carried the state of Florida and won the presidency without Supreme Court intervention had a recount ordered by a state court been allowed to proceed.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Diversity, and Segregation  The United States is more racially and ethnically diverse than ever, but an analysis of new census data suggests that people still live in largely segregated neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>A Drug Task Force Under Fire  A state prosecutor has dismissed charges against 17 residents of Hearne, in Central Texas, who were arrested by a drug task force accused of focusing on blacks. The prosecutor said a crucial informer had failed polygraph tests.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Modern Demands Putting Modernist Terminal at Risk  The Port Authority has approval from state officials to demolish a large piece of T.W.A.'s distinctive terminal, which is designated a city landmark, as part of a $10 billion redevelopment of Kennedy Airport.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Airline Passenger Cleared  A jury in Newark acquitted John C. Davis Jr. of assault in connection with his fight with an airline ticket agent, whose neck was broken.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Mets Beat Braves in Opener  The Mets beat Atlanta, 6-4, on a 10th-inning homer by Robin Ventura.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Admission From Strawberry  Darryl Strawberry's probation officer said the ex-slugger had admitted to a weekend cocaine-smoking spree. Strawberry remained hospitalized in Tampa, Fla., as prosecutors sought to have him sent to prison.</p>
        <p>D3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>A Tiff at the Met  Trouble is brewing between members of the grand old Metropolitan Opera Club and the Met over fees and exclusivity of the clubhouse, tucked away on the fourth floor.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>Panel on Decency in Art  Mayor Giuliani appointed 15 men and 5 women to a panel that is to recommend decency standards for art in New York City museums.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>EDCATION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Opening Up M.I.T., Online  The university is to announce today that it will post nearly all course materials on the Web, even video lectures, available free to anyone.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Suspending Unruly Students  Chancellor Harold O. Levy will propose regulations today giving teachers the power to remove disruptive students from their classrooms for up to four days.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Technology Pulls Down Markets  Investors dumped shares of software companies and telecommunications concerns, driving the Nasdaq down 6.17 percent, or 109.97 points, to 1,673.00; the index is now down 32.3 percent in 2001. The Dow fell 292.22 points, or 3 percent, to 9,485.71, and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 3.4 percent.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Discounts Propel Auto Sales  Automakers sold family vehicles at a seasonally adjusted annual pace of 17.1 million vehicles in March; 16 million is regarded as strong. Extensions of rebates and other discounts helped sustain the buying.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Effort to Play Deal Breaker  Maurice R. Greenberg, chief executive of American International Group, offered $23 billion in stock for American General, a move intended to break up a three-week-old deal by Britain's second-largest insurer to take over American General.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Inquiry of Drink Maker Sought  The Council of Better Business Bureaus wants the F.D.A. to investigate whether Hornell Brewing used false advertising for an herbal drink.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. McCain's journey; revisiting execution of the retarded; decency impaneled.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
