<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Youths Held In Eco-Terror Are Reported Nearing Plea</title>
    <meta content="14ELF.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/14/nyregion/14ELF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1270739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Earth Liberation Front</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McIntyre, Jared</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0DC1630F937A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Youths Held In Eco-Terror Are Reported Nearing Plea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyers for two young suspects in underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County, NY, are in negotiations with federal prosecutors that could result in guilty pleas in Federal District Court; third suspect, Jared McIntyre, pleaded guilty last week to arson; McIntyre is believed to be first in nation to cooperate with federal authorities investigating attacks claimed by Earth Liberation Front (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for two young suspects in an underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County are  in negotiations with federal prosecutors that could result in guilty pleas in Federal District Court as soon as Wednesday, a law enforcement official said today.</p>
        <p>The two suspects, whom the authorities would not identify, are not the first to enter into plea negotiations with the federal authorities investigating more than two dozen recent acts of violence for which a radical environmental group, the Earth Liberation Front, has claimed responsibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers for two young suspects in an underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County are  in negotiations with federal prosecutors that could result in guilty pleas in Federal District Court as soon as Wednesday, a law enforcement official said today.</p>
        <p>The two suspects, whom the authorities would not identify, are not the first to enter into plea negotiations with the federal authorities investigating more than two dozen recent acts of violence for which a radical environmental group, the Earth Liberation Front, has claimed responsibility.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Jared McIntyre, the 17-year-old son of a New York City police sergeant, pleaded guilty to arson at a hearing in United States District Court in Central Islip. The hearing was closed to the public and its records were sealed.</p>
        <p>In the proceedings, Mr. McIntyre agreed to be charged as an adult  rather than as a juvenile; under the deal, a federal judge can consider a more lenient sentence than Mr. McIntyre would otherwise have faced.</p>
        <p>The other suspects are expected to do the same.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre is believed to be the first in the nation to cooperate with the federal authorities investigating attacks claimed by the Earth Liberation Front, said Craig S. Rosebraugh of Portland, Ore., who acts as spokesman for the group. It opposes urban sprawl, deforestation and other acts it deems harmful to the environment.</p>
        <p>But it remains unclear whether the suspects are members of some organized national effort or a band of local people sympathetic to the national group but unconnected to any central leadership.</p>
        <p>Thomas F. Liotti, the lawyer for one of the suspects, would not comment on the negotiations today. ''This is very unfortunate,'' he said. ''I think it is being treated much more seriously by the government than it should be. I think these kids had the best of intentions. In no way are they involved in any organized, national ELF effort.''</p>
        <p>On Jan. 15, agents of the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms searched Mr. McIntyre's house on Bristol Downs Street, in Coram. They left with a computer,  cans of red spray paint and other materials similar to those used in Suffolk County attacks. Those attacks were carried out over the last several months against luxury homes and condominiums being built, construction vehicles, a cornfield used in genetic research and a McDonald's corporate office.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 19, federal agents raided the home of a 16-year-old suspect on Helme Avenue, in the hamlet of Miller Place.</p>
        <p>Mr. McIntyre, a senior at Longwood High School in Middle Island, was working at the Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton, just east of Coram, researching the effects of increased carbon dioxide on plants as part of a project dealing with global warming, Mona Rowe, a spokeswoman for the lab, has said.</p>
        <p>The mother of the 16-year-old said today that her son was a smart boy. She said the federal government was being very strict in dealing with him, but she would not elaborate.</p>
        <p>''We really weren't given much of a choice,'' she said when asked why her son was being charged as an adult. ''There was no choice of being charged as a juvenile. That was not an option.''</p>
        <p>Richard J. Kaufman, a lawyer for Mr. McIntyre, declined to comment today.</p>
        <p>When asked about two of the suspects, Elaine D. Close of Portland, a spokeswoman for the Earth Liberation Front, said she knew the F.B.I. had raided both of their houses last month. But she could not say much else about the teenagers.</p>
        <p>''We don't know if they are members of ELF, but anyone could be,'' Ms. Close said. ''But they have not identified themselves as such and we have not had contact with them here in the press office. None of us know any of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh said the group does not disclose information about its members. The group is deliberately decentralized, he said, to prevent the authorities from identifying its leaders. He said the ELF press office, in Portland, acts merely as a conduit between the news media and members, who communicate with it anonymously and in ways Mr. Rosebraugh would not identify.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh said the group had been active around the United States since 1997, and had claimed responsibility for attacks causing more than $37 million in damage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosebraugh said a plea would not dismantle the group, which he supports. ''The group operates under an ideology, not a physical membership,'' he said. ''So it is really impossible to dissolve that ideology.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
