<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Squint No More: A Smart Window Awaits Your Command</title>
    <meta content="06NEXT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/06/technology/circuits/06NEXT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1322737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S NEXT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windows</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisenberg, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/What's Next</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DA1539F935A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Squint No More: A Smart Window Awaits Your Command</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Squint No More: A Smart Window Awaits Your Command</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE EISENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eisenberg, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Switchable windows are being developed that can change from transparent to deeply tinted by degrees and back again when voltage is applied to automatically control amount of light and heat passing through them; include aircraft window that uses thin layer of microscopic particles sandwiched between plastic panes to eliminate glare in response to electric charge; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE many other travelers this month, passengers on flights out of Fort Lauderdale International Airport may continue to fasten their seat belts, look out the window and wait for the air conditioning to kick in. But on one charter jet that flies out of the airport, passengers will no longer have to lower those rickety plastic window shades to block the sun's glare.</p>
        <p>That is because the pull-down shades on the plane have been replaced with high-tech windows that do the shading electronically. Each window has a thin layer of microscopic particles sandwiched between plastic panes to block or admit light in response to an electric charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dialing up darkness with an airplane window that acts as its own shade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE many other travelers this month, passengers on flights out of Fort Lauderdale International Airport may continue to fasten their seat belts, look out the window and wait for the air conditioning to kick in. But on one charter jet that flies out of the airport, passengers will no longer have to lower those rickety plastic window shades to block the sun's glare.</p>
        <p>That is because the pull-down shades on the plane have been replaced with high-tech windows that do the shading electronically. Each window has a thin layer of microscopic particles sandwiched between plastic panes to block or admit light in response to an electric charge.</p>
        <p>These electronic shades are an example of switchable windows: windows equipped to change from transparent to deeply tinted by degrees and back again when a voltage is applied. In the future, such windows may find wide use in homes and offices, for they offer the possibility of big energy savings.  When linked to circuits and light sensors, they could control the amount of light and heat passing into a building automatically, making the buildings more energy-efficient.</p>
        <p>Various technologies to create switchable windows have been developed at research centers in the United States and abroad over the past few decades. Now supporters hope that as the new panes grow less costly to manufacture, more switchable windows will be moving out of the lab and into cars, airplanes, homes and offices.</p>
        <p>The smart windows on the Florida jet were made by InspecTech Aero Service, a manufacturer of aircraft parts and components in Fort Lauderdale, under license from Research Frontiers, a research and development company in Woodbury, N.Y.  These are the first smart windows that the company has installed on a jet, said Joseph M. Harary, executive vice president of Research Frontiers.</p>
        <p>''Our windows act like light valves,'' Mr. Harary said. ''Like a water valve that controls the flow of water, these windows control the flow of light.'' Mr. Harary said that 13 companies had licensed the suspended particle technology for switchable windows.</p>
        <p>The Florida plane using Research Frontiers technology carries seven passengers and is part of a charter fleet operated by National Jets of Fort Lauderdale.</p>
        <p>The windows have thick glass panes on the outside and plastic panes on the inside.  It is the interior, plastic windows that have been retrofitted. The new window is a sandwich of two plastic sheets with an emulsion between them, said Alex Martinez, head of engineering at InspecTech. The plastic sheets are coated with a transparent conductive material, and the emulsion is made up of microscopic polyiodide crystals,  which absorb light strongly.</p>
        <p>Normally the crystals suspended in the emulsion point in random directions, catching the light. But when a voltage is applied to the suspension, the particles line up and let the light pass through.</p>
        <p>The plastic windows draw power from the plane's electrical system. Passengers can adjust the amount of light that flows in by turning a knob. But such windows are capable of being controlled from a central location, so that flight attendants could darken an entire cabin, for example, to show an in-flight movie. They could also be connected to a light sensor to darken automatically, say, when the sun comes up.</p>
        <p>Other technologies for switchable windows are under development, including one known as the electrochromic method. In that design, an electric current causes ions to move between layers of materials deposited on the glass, changing the structure of the molecules in the layers and thus their ability to absorb light.</p>
        <p>Electrochromic technology has been used for years in some rear-view mirrors, primarily for luxury cars and for trucks. Such mirrors darken automatically when bright lights hit a photodetector, which sends a current to the mirror. But extending electrochromic technology to large surfaces has been a challenge, said Dr. Ren Anderson, who tests switchable window coatings at the Energy Department's National Renewable Energy Laboratory in Golden, Colo.</p>
        <p>''It's difficult to produce coatings with a uniform thickness over a wide area so that there is no variation in color across a large window,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Anderson tests switchable windows to see if they can stand up to tough conditions, including extensive exposure to ultraviolet light and long periods without maintenance. ''The main issue is to make sure they are durable, as they change many thousands of time between their clear and darkened states,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many of the switchable window coatings the Energy Department lab has tested are considered promising. ''We've seen the beginnings of a manufacturing process that can produce a window-sized coating and do so in a high-quality way,'' Dr. Anderson said. But much work remains. ''Producing a rear-view mirror is one thing,'' he said. ''Scaling up to produce something as large as a window will take some time.''</p>
        <p>Stephen E. Selkowitz, who directs a windows research program for the Energy Department at the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory in California, is confident that switchable window systems will soon be practical.</p>
        <p>Electrochromic smart windows can change smoothly from transmission of about 2 to 3 percent of the light (a very dark window) to about 70 percent (a window that appears to be highly transparent) and any point in between, Mr. Selkowitz said. ''These smart windows have a huge potential to save energy and control peak electric loads in buildings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added that it would take time to create smart window systems with controls that link them to a building's heating and cooling systems. ''But it will certainly happen.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, back in Fort Lauderdale, the switchable windows are a hit with passengers, said Ricardo Velez, a pilot for National Jets. ''The customers like being able to adjust the intensity of light,'' he said. ''And they can get rid of the glare without obstructing the view.''</p>
        <p>WHAT'S NEXT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
