<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Face Off on 'Noah's Flood'</title>
    <meta content="09FLOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/09/science/09FLOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1261390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Black Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mediterranean Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tigris River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Euphrates River</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Archaeological Institute of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noah (Biblical Figure)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, William B F (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pitman, Walter C 3d (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DE123AF93AA35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Face Off on 'Noah's Flood'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Archaelogists and historians at Archaeological Institute of America meeting, San Diego, question suggestion by marine geologists Drs William B F Ryan and Walter C Pitman 3d that rapid flood of water into Black Sea from Mediterranean 7,600 years ago that inundated surrounding plains could explain rapid spread of early agriculture into eastern and northern Europe and could have inspired biblical story of Noah; most scholars suspect periodic flooding of Tigris and Euphrates Rivers is inspiration for Babylonian flood story that predates biblical story; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two marine geologists from Columbia University in 1996 advanced the idea that a flood of water from the Mediterranean, rushing through the Bosporus with the force of 20 Niagaras, entered the Black Sea 7,600 years ago. In months, at most two years, the Black Sea rose, inundated surrounding plains and attained its present dimensions.</p>
        <p>As a consequence, the geologists suggested, people in the region had to flee, and this could explain the rapid spread of early agriculture into eastern and northern Europe. It was even possible, they said, that the cataclysm became a part of folk memory, inspiring the Babylonian flood myth in the epic of Gilgamesh and, in time, the biblical story of Noah.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two marine geologists from Columbia University in 1996 advanced the idea that a flood of water from the Mediterranean, rushing through the Bosporus with the force of 20 Niagaras, entered the Black Sea 7,600 years ago. In months, at most two years, the Black Sea rose, inundated surrounding plains and attained its present dimensions.</p>
        <p>As a consequence, the geologists suggested, people in the region had to flee, and this could explain the rapid spread of early agriculture into eastern and northern Europe. It was even possible, they said, that the cataclysm became a part of folk memory, inspiring the Babylonian flood myth in the epic of Gilgamesh and, in time, the biblical story of Noah.</p>
        <p>The geologists, Dr. William B. F. Ryan and Dr. Walter C. Pitman 3rd of Columbia's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, elaborated their hypothesis in a book, ''Noah's Flood: The New Scientific Discoveries about the Event That Changed History,'' published in 1999 by Simon &amp; Schuster Inc. They could not have waved a redder flag in the face of some scholars.</p>
        <p>Although many fellow geologists have found the research persuasive and the Black Sea flood plausible, and still do, archaeologists and historians were skeptical from the start. They expressed their doubts and objections, politely but firmly, in an encounter with Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman here on Saturday at the annual meeting of the Archaeological Institute of America.</p>
        <p>The geological evidence for the flood may be sound, the critics said, but they thought it a stretch to ascribe to it such widespread consequences for ancient culture and mythology.</p>
        <p>''The large claim connecting the Black Sea flood and Noah's flood can no longer be sustained,'' Dr. Andrew M. T. Moore, an archaeologist and dean of liberal arts at the Rochester Institute of Technology, said in an interview afterward.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephanie Dalley, a historian at Oxford University in England and a specialist on Babylonian mythology, said that the ''supposed similarities'' between the Black Sea event and the flood story of Gilgamesh ''are random and wrong.''</p>
        <p>For one thing, Dr. Dalley said, it is questionable that a folk memory would have persisted over more than 4,000 years. But suppose it had. If refugees from the Black Sea flood carried the memory with them into the Middle East, where it was eventually written on clay tablets, why is there no flood mythology in the ancient cultures of Eastern Europe, where other refugees may have migrated?</p>
        <p>Most scholars suspect that the periodic flooding of the Tigris and Euphrates Rivers is the inspiration for the Babylonian flood story. In this account, it rained seven days and nights and all dry land vanished; there were no survivors, except those in a boat. On a philosophical level, Dr. Dalley noted, the Gilgamesh epic made the point that ''before the flood, people could live forever or until the next disaster, and after the flood, people died of old age.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, the Black Sea flooded not by rain but from rising sea levels far away. The water encroached steadily, but land never vanished from sight and people had time to flee.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dalley concluded that Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman ''have misunderstood the meaning of the flood myth in Mesopotamia, and its use in the hypothesis should be abandoned.'' Then she added, ''But the rest of the hypothesis is fine, as far as I'm concerned.''</p>
        <p>Over the last 10 years, Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman have surveyed and sampled sediments submerged along the Black Sea shores and in the Bosporus, the strait leading from the Mediterranean and Aegean Seas into the Black Sea at Istanbul. They found compelling evidence, they said, that the Black Sea rose several hundred feet and submerged more than 60,000 square miles of surrounding land, a 30 percent expansion of its size. Marine shells found in the submerged lands were from Mediterranean organisms that had died about 7,600 years ago -- in 5600 B.C.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fredrik T. Hiebert, an archaeologist from the University of Pennsylvania, reported at the meeting that an underwater survey with remote-sensing technology last summer detected the stones of at least one human occupation site off Turkey's northern coast near Sinop. The submerged site appeared to be on what had been a small bluff overlooking an ancient river.</p>
        <p>''This suggests that we will find settlements all along that submerged coast,'' Dr. Hiebert said, indicating that this might support the Ryan-Pitman hypothesis of an enormous flood.</p>
        <p>Dr. Moore, who moderated the debate, said that archaeologists generally accepted the evidence that ''a natural event had significant impact for people living around the Black Sea shores, but a more distant impact is not as certain.''</p>
        <p>Another archaeologist, Dr. Albert Ammerman of Colgate University, specifically raised questions about the supposed link between the deluge and migrations into Europe. He pointed out that there is a 200-year discrepancy between the time of the Black Sea flood and earliest evidence for settlements, in central Hungary, of what is known as the Linear Pottery Culture. These were the people who apparently introduced farming into Europe.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ryan said in an interview that new dating techniques, to be applied to some of the Black Sea sediments, should yield more precise times for the event, possibly erasing the discrepancy.</p>
        <p>Both Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman emphasized that their hypothesis was a work in progress. ''It's a good hypothesis, but it's not proven,'' Dr. Ryan said.</p>
        <p>The marine geologists said their continuing surveys had made another intriguing discovery. Sonar explorations of the Sea of Marmara, which feeds into the Bosporus, revealed an unusual mound more than 1,600 feet long and nearly 50 feet high, with what appears to be a ramp leading up to the summit. What is it? Dr. Ryan said core samples of the mound would be taken in October.</p>
        <p>Even if archaeologists had reservations about elements of the Ryan-Pitman hypothesis, Dr. Ammerman recommended that they begin a ''sustained long-term collaboration'' with the geologists and thus avoid ''a lot of misunderstanding and tension.''</p>
        <p>In summarizing the discussion, Dr. Rita Wright, an archaeologist at New York University, welcomed the Ryan-Pitman hypothesis, whatever its suggested shortcomings. ''Models that fail also instruct,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
