<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Just In: Celebrities Are a Breed Apart</title>
    <meta content="01VIEW$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/01/living/01VIEW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1282350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Talk (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hass, Nancy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hollywood</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Santa Barbara</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Reykjavik</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Disney</org>
        <org class="online_producer">NATO</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richards, Ann</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blumenthal, Sidney</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Buck, Joan Juliet</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cole, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Weinstein, Harvey</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiff, Karenna Gore</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Latham, Aaron</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Sawyer, Diane</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gwathmey, Charles</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hewitt, Don</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DF123FF932A35757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Just In: Celebrities Are a Breed Apart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NANCY HASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hass, Nancy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>View column on Talk magazine's conference of celebrities from diverse fields (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO exactly are you?'' asked Ann Richards (feisty former governor of Texas), her trademark white coif tilted my way as I slid into the chair next to her, a plate of chilled filet mignon in hand.</p>
        <p>Is she asking my name? I wondered. Or does she simply want to know what I'm doing here, at a conference of political insiders, celebrity journalists and Hollywood heavies, where I was one of the only unfamous people. Should I list my credentials? Should I ask who all my tablemates are, even though they were so prominent I already knew?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO exactly are you?'' asked Ann Richards (feisty former governor of Texas), her trademark white coif tilted my way as I slid into the chair next to her, a plate of chilled filet mignon in hand.</p>
        <p>Is she asking my name? I wondered. Or does she simply want to know what I'm doing here, at a conference of political insiders, celebrity journalists and Hollywood heavies, where I was one of the only unfamous people. Should I list my credentials? Should I ask who all my tablemates are, even though they were so prominent I already knew?</p>
        <p>Sidney Blumenthal (Clinton loyalist) threw an exasperated glance at Ann Louise Bardach (former Vanity Fair writer), as Joan Juliet Buck (former French Vogue editor) lost interest in me and mouthed a greeting across the veranda, either at Barry Diller (newlywed media mogul) or James Woods (M.I.T. dropout  actor). Ms. Richards seemed to forget about me. She motioned to a waiter for cappuccino, while Anna  Deavere Smith (performance artist) came over to buss her cheek.</p>
        <p>So I made no response at all. Why bother? The answer was obvious: if I had been someone worth knowing, they would already know me.</p>
        <p>The conference, arranged by Talk magazine in Santa Barbara, Calif., was billed as a way for prominent figures in diverse fields to cross-pollinate ideas, although the publicity it might generate for the magazine was also clearly part of the agenda. As a contributing writer to Talk, I was there to trawl for article ideas. But I spent much of the three days pondering my anonymity, adrift in a sea of 150 of America's most famous people, who constituted an exotic species.</p>
        <p>They strolled the grounds of the luxury resort without publicists or other handlers, feasting at the buffet table and gossiping among themselves in what I came to recognize as the secret murmured language of shared celebrity.</p>
        <p>It isn't as though I had not been exposed to bold-face names before. Most journalists have. One on one, I had never found them intimidating, but en masse they created an electrified fence of eminence. The famous and the infamous were everywhere, including Barbra Streisand (temperamental song stylist), Steve Martin (brainy funnyman novelist), Arianna Huffington (political pundit) and Christiane Amanpour (foreign correspondent). Even a nylon Kenneth Cole bag stuffed with hundreds of dollars worth of designer freebies in my room couldn't make me feel I belonged.</p>
        <p>I realized how wide the divide was the moment I stepped onto the veranda for cocktails the first night. All heads turned. And then turned back. I may as well have been a Salvadoran refugee getting off the plane amid the willowy blondes of Reykjavik.</p>
        <p>Ms. Streisand was schmoozing with Harvey Weinstein (movie mogul) and Donna Karan (designer).  John F. Welch Jr. (corporate titan) was fretting about the plummeting market with Ron Meyer (superagent turned entertainment heavyweight). Glenn D. Lowry (Museum of Modern Art director) was trading inside jokes with Thomas Krens (Guggenheim Museum director), as Karenna Gore Schiff (onetime vice-presidential daughter) stood by laughing. In a room of knowing glances, the only ones I got were from the waiters; they, too, knew what invisibility was.</p>
        <p>I did know a few people. I had interviewed them over the years. But that was not the same as being one of them. I had always been uncomfortable with the phenomenon of the celebrity journalist. I was a product of the old school, believing that cozying up to powerful sources compromised a journalist's integrity. But as I watched Aaron Latham (bearish magazine writer behind ''Urban Cowboy'') whisper into the ear of Michael D. Eisner (Disney chieftain), I wondered if riding on my high horse all these years had been such a bright idea. I may have preserved my objectivity, but how long could I nurse a kir royale while wandering through the crowd and pretending to be on my way to an air-kiss across the room? At one point, Renée Zellweger (Golden Globe winner) caught me making eye contact with a potted palm. Her million-dollar smile made me feel like 15 cents.</p>
        <p>I reminded myself that I wasn't completely anonymous. A couple of weeks before, a man next to me on a plane asked what I do, and when I told him, he excitedly called his wife on the in-flight phone. Then he asked a flight attendant for a copy of a magazine in which I had a story, so I could autograph it.</p>
        <p>At the time, the episode seemed terribly flattering. But now, as I watched Stacey Snider (Universal Pictures chairman) deep in conversation with Maj. Gen. Romeo D'Allaire (NATO commander in Ruanda), and saw David Frum (presidential speechwriter) tease Ms. Streisand about global warming, even the maraschino cherry in my drink seemed to blush.</p>
        <p>What confounded me was how many of these people seemed to be old friends. Sure, they are leaders in their fields, but those fields rarely overlap. So why was Ahmet M. Ertegun (recording industry legend) hugging Diane Sawyer (television personality) like a long-lost daughter? And what explained the look of joy on the face of Charles Gwathmey (celebrity architect) as he spied Don Hewitt (''60 Minutes'' creator)?</p>
        <p>Was there some secret celebrity code in which differences in age, profession and politics are automatically erased by sheer star power? Perhaps it's true that the only people with whom celebrities can be folks are other celebrities.</p>
        <p>After I had spent three days  watching them overeat, sweat on the health club treadmills and tickle one another fondly on the dessert line, they began to seem fairly ordinary. Maybe if everyone is a star, then no one is. And if that's so, then maybe I was the most important person at the conference. I was, after all, the audience.</p>
        <p>But such thoughts did not get me closer to figuring how to answer the question of who I was, exactly. Between panel discussions on the final morning, I made my way toward a silver coffee urn. Mr. Woods was pouring himself a cup and I made a quick joke about how disappointing it was to see an actor known for being wired sipping decaf.</p>
        <p>Days before, I had stopped introducing myself -- it was too awkward when I already knew the names of the other guests from their movies or from the gossip columns, and they would never remember mine. But after a few more quips lobbed back and forth, Mr. Woods politely asked who I was.</p>
        <p>This time I didn't break a sweat. I knew I would never have to answer. Mr. Diller and Mr. Eisner were headed straight for us. Mr. Woods laid a gentle hand on my shoulder. He had to go back to his people. I understood completely.</p>
        <p>VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
