<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Conservation Countdown</title>
    <meta content="Y11SAV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/11/national/11SAVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1292338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn</location>
        <location class="online_producer">East</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cherokee</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Martin</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mountain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Santa Monica</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Orange</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Costco</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Southern California Edison Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Edison International</org>
        <org class="online_producer">PG&amp;E Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Depot Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Diego Gas &amp; Electric Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DB103BF932A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Conservation Countdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California is establishing programs to educate consumers on ways to use electricity more efficiently, provide multitude of rebates on energy-efficient lighting and appliances, and support businesses wanting to cut electricity use; state has also strengthened requirements for new construction and pledges to use 20 percent less electricity in state offices when power supplies fall to level of Stage 2 emergency, which is short of forcing blackouts; states has plan intended to cut peak power use this summer by 5,200 megawatts, or almost 10 percent of projected peak use of about 55,000 megawatts; it hopes consumer outreach and incentives will save 2,000; some California businessmen comment on ways they are trying to save electricity; chart; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To understand what California is up against in its search for enough electricity to get through the summer, look no further than Michael Chroman, owner of Brooklyn Hardware in East Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>In the months since the energy crisis began, he has not changed the way he does business or the way he lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To understand what California is up against in its search for enough electricity to get through the summer, look no further than Michael Chroman, owner of Brooklyn Hardware in East Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>In the months since the energy crisis began, he has not changed the way he does business or the way he lives.</p>
        <p>''I guess I think it's pretty much contrived,'' Mr. Chroman said of the shortage. ''I think it's something they want to do to increase the rates, and they'll do it whether I conserve or not.''</p>
        <p>As for the rising rates, ''I can afford it, I guess,'' he said, as he loaded beverages into his Jeep Grand Cherokee outside a local Costco.</p>
        <p>The state, on the other hand, cannot. Because little new power will be available soon, conservation is crucial.</p>
        <p>Armed with more than $850 million in new money for an array of initiatives, the state is establishing programs to educate consumers on ways to use electricity more efficiently, provide a multitude of rebates on energy-efficient lighting and appliances, and support businesses wanting to cut electricity use. The state has also strengthened requirements for new construction and pledged to use 20 percent less electricity in state offices when power supplies fall to the level of a Stage 2 emergency, which is just short of forcing blackouts.</p>
        <p>''They're putting everything but the kitchen sink into this, and it's probably going to take that kind of effort,'' said Martin G. Kushler, director of the utilities program for the American Council for an Energy Efficient Economy, a nonprofit group based in Washington that promotes energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>The initiatives look promising, experts say -- but not right away. ''Will all these programs be in place by summer?'' said Ed Vine, a staff scientist who evaluates energy-efficiency programs at the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. ''I think that's a big question mark. I think they may get to this goal, but it may be next summer.''</p>
        <p>One hurdle is that there is little fat to cut. As Mr. Kushler and other energy experts have noted, California has been a leader in energy efficiency for more than two decades, and its per capita consumption is among the lowest in the country.</p>
        <p>''California is entering uncharted territory,'' Mr. Kushler said. ''What's different here is the magnitude of what they are trying to accomplish in a very short period of time.''</p>
        <p>This week was not encouraging, with the first rolling blackouts since March -- necessitated by a bout of unusually warm weather just when some power plants were out of service, mainly for maintenance.</p>
        <p>The state projects a shortfall of as much as 5,000 megawatts at periods of peak demand this summer -- out of projected total demand of about 55,000 megawatts. To provide a cushion, it has a plan to cut use by 5,200 megawatts. And it hopes to find 2,000 of those megawatts -- enough to power two million homes -- through consumer outreach and incentive programs. A big question is whether that 2,000 figure is realistic.</p>
        <p>''Quite frankly, the level of savings they're projecting from that have never been accomplished anywhere,'' Mr. Kushler said. ''On the other hand, the situation California finds itself in has never been found before.''</p>
        <p>Much will depend on people like Mr. Chroman. At his home in Los Angeles, he gets his electricity from the city's Department of Water and Power. That public utility did not participate in deregulation and has not suffered the same problems confronting Pacific Gas and Electric, which recently filed for bankruptcy protection, and Southern California Edison, whose rates are about to rise sharply. At his business, Mr. Chroman is served by Southern California Edison, a unit of Edison International. And, like many Californians, he shows no inclination to conserve.</p>
        <p>With little hope of getting significant sources of new generation on line by summer, California -- which confronted rolling blackouts this winter as electricity ran short and prices skyrocketed -- is limited in what it can do.</p>
        <p>The state is seeking a 10 percent across-the-board reduction in energy consumption, and state government is leading by example, making numerous changes in buildings, right down to the way janitors clean, while turning off unnecessary lights and office equipment.</p>
        <p>It also moved quickly to strengthen energy-efficiency regulations for commercial and residential construction, which, when they take effect on June 1, will make the state's guidelines the most stringent in the nation.</p>
        <p>Additional conservation financing approved in April includes $50 million for energy-efficient household appliances; $60 million for high-efficiency lighting in commercial buildings; $35 million for improving the ability to scale back heating, ventilation and air-conditioning when shortages loom; $35 million for real-time or time-of-use meters; and $50 million for peak load reduction programs.</p>
        <p>There is also about $240 million for assistance for low-income customers that will include weatherization programs, cash assistance and discounts.</p>
        <p>But state officials are racing the clock to get the money distributed before hotter temperatures play havoc with demand, and consumer groups have criticized the state for taking too long to act.</p>
        <p>Although much of the new financing will be run through existing channels, questions remain about whether the system can cope.</p>
        <p>''Is the infrastructure ready to handle this?'' Mr. Vine said. ''I don't think anybody knows.''</p>
        <p>He also questioned whether the bankruptcy filing of Pacific Gas and Electric, a unit of the PG&amp;E Corporation, would affect its ability to run rebate programs and whether its financial difficulties, as well as Southern California Edison's, would affect decisions like whether to hire additional people to carry out such programs.</p>
        <p>But whether the state reaches its goal ultimately comes down to whether consumers significantly change their behavior. That is far from clear.</p>
        <p>''Programs that rely only on behavioral changes are fickle,'' said Thomas Feiler, managing director of the Rocky Mountain Institute, which promotes energy efficiency and finding renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Millions of dollars is being spent to get the message out, enlisting a variety of groups. The State Department of Consumer Affairs is orchestrating a $20 million advertising campaign. McDonald's is putting energy-conservation messages on four million tray liners in 1,100 restaurants. The Grocers Association is working with retailers to put messages on receipts and in grocery bags.</p>
        <p>Dana Michels, a 28-year-old Los Angeles resident served by the city's Department of Water and Power, said she did not need to be sold. She said she had always been thrifty about energy and was even more careful now to turn off lights and other household items, like the VCR, when they were not in use. But, she said, many people she works with do nothing.</p>
        <p>In fact, while driving through Santa Monica earlier this spring, she was appalled to see homes that still had Christmas lights lighted.</p>
        <p>By contrast, in areas harder hit, particularly where the investor-owned utilities are predominant, sales of energy-efficient lighting like fluorescent bulbs are soaring.</p>
        <p>Home Depot said sales of such lighting were up more than 300 percent in Northern California, where PG&amp;E is predominant, though the products have not really caught on at stores in Los Angeles and Orange Counties; statewide, they are up 224 percent.</p>
        <p>According to state figures, there is reason to feel encouraged. Power use dropped 6 percent in January, compared with January 2000; 8 percent in February; and 9 percent in March and April.</p>
        <p>Representatives from all three investor-owned utilities -- Pacific Gas and Electric, Southern California Edison and San Diego Gas and Electric -- said they had seen sharp increases in consumers taking advantage of rebate programs in recent months. Though changing a few light bulbs may seem like no big deal, energy officials say no detail is too small to make a difference.</p>
        <p>Steve McCarty, director of customer energy management for Pacific Gas and Electric, said that if every customer turned off three 75-watt bulbs, it would mean a 2 percent energy savings a month. Unplug that second refrigerator and that is an additional 9 percent.</p>
        <p>''There are no silver bullets,'' he said. ''Only silver BB's.''</p>
        <p>State officials said businesses were taking advantage of programs to help them change out inefficient items like lighting and air-conditioning. Businesses are also being asked to turn up the thermostat and turn off some lights, including signs outside stores after closing. Home Depot said that by taking steps like turning off outdoor lighting after closing, its western division saved more than 1.5 million kilowatt hours in February, the equivalent of the total consumption of 1,800 homes or 9 Home Depot stores.</p>
        <p>The Building Owners and Management Association, whose members own about 500 million square feet of office space in California, has pledged to cut consumption by 10 percent. Janitors are supporting their efforts by team cleaning and turning off unnecessary lights. But the organization acknowledged that getting tenants to cut back would be a harder sell.</p>
        <p>In addition, there does not appear to be wide compliance with an executive order by Gov. Gray Davis that businesses -- particularly auto dealers, shopping malls and megastores -- reduce outdoor lighting by 50 percent after hours. Although the order provides for fines of up to $1,000 for violations, no tickets have been issued and law enforcement officials have expressed reluctance about enforcing the order. With downtown office buildings still leaving many lights on well after business hours, state officials are weighing steps to allow landlords to find a way to charge tenants based on electrical use.</p>
        <p>While much of what is being called for is voluntary, the state's plan could get a big lift as many consumers confront higher rates next month. The Public Utility Commission has approved a rate increase of 3 cents a kilowatt hour, on top of a previous temporary 1-cent increase that was made permanent. That will increase bills for PG&amp;E and Southern California Edison customers by as much as 46 percent. However, rates are tiered to reward those who conserve, with customers who stay within 130 percent of a base line level of use facing no increase.</p>
        <p>In addition, the state has a plan that will provide a 20 percent rate reduction for customers of investor-owned utilities who use 20 percent less electricity than they did last year.</p>
        <p>''California has world-class experience in energy-efficiency programs,'' said Mr. Feiler of the Rocky Mountain Institute. ''Where the rubber will meet the road is how those plans are implemented. Are consumers seeing the right incentives, the right type of rebates, the right type of rates to bring about a behavioral change? That will determine whether they win the battle this summer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
