<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undersea, Cannibalism as Population Control</title>
    <meta content="04COPE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/04/science/life/04COPE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1322314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copepods (Shellfish)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DC1639F937A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undersea, Cannibalism as Population Control</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Undersea, Cannibalism as Population Control</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN ABRAHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abraham, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study published in journal Nature indicates female copepods, tiny marine crustaceans that are major source of protein in oceans, prey on copepod eggs to keep population in check; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While moviemakers have been keeping their eyes on dinosaurs, they may be overlooking an oceanic world that could be just as intimidating, although on a much smaller scale. For some creatures in this world, the copepods, cannibalism seems to be the family business.</p>
        <p>Females appear to prey upon copepod eggs to keep the population in check, a study published last month in the journal Nature said.</p>
        <p>The number of copepods, marine crustaceans, matters to many other animals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For some creatures in the oceanic world, the copepods, cannibalism seems to be the family business</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While moviemakers have been keeping their eyes on dinosaurs, they may be overlooking an oceanic world that could be just as intimidating, although on a much smaller scale. For some creatures in this world, the copepods, cannibalism seems to be the family business.</p>
        <p>Females appear to prey upon copepod eggs to keep the population in check, a study published last month in the journal Nature said.</p>
        <p>The number of copepods, marine crustaceans, matters to many other animals.</p>
        <p>Copepods are so small that four of the Calanus finmarchicus species, a common type, would fit end to end on a dime. But they serve as meals for many fish, marine mammals and birds. And they are a major source of protein in the oceans.</p>
        <p>''They are such an important element of the North Atlantic food chain,'' said Dr. Jeffrey Runge of the University of Quebec at Rimousky.  ''They are prey for a wide range of fish, and even for the endangered right whales.''</p>
        <p>While other studies have linked copepod egg mortality to external factors like nutrient availability, the research found that the survival rate for the eggs seemed to depend on the number of female and juvenile copepods.</p>
        <p>The researchers said cannibalism of the eggs by the females appeared to be the reason for this phenomenon.</p>
        <p>The work was done by Dr. Mark Ohman of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography and Dr. Hans-Jürgen Hirche of the Alfred Wegener Institute for Polar and Marine Research.</p>
        <p>Copepods play a critical role in the biological pump that helps regulate the amount of carbon in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The pump is fueled as the small floating plants called phytoplankton convert carbon dioxide, a greenhouse gas, into oxygen and plant matter. Copepods graze on the phytoplankton and release the carbon in fecal pellets that rapidly sink.</p>
        <p>''This accelerates the process of sending carbon atoms to the deep ocean,'' Dr. Ohman said.</p>
        <p>''Copepods are indirectly important,'' he added, ''but significant in the regulation of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>The work was supported by international groups that want to understand the effects of climate change on marine organisms.</p>
        <p>The monitoring of fluctuations in copepod populations is therefore vital. Researchers have attributed changes in copepod populations to factors like external predation and food supplies.</p>
        <p>Cannibalism, an internal process, would help explain why populations of copepods do not always show huge fluctuations when external factors change.</p>
        <p>The study takes a different approach to explaining population changes.</p>
        <p>''Population studies tend to look at births, deaths, immigration and emigration to estimate the rate at which population is changing,'' said Dr. Thomas Powell, a professor at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>''Rarely do studies take into account how various stages in a population prey upon each other,'' Dr. Powell said.</p>
        <p>Using a microscope, Dr. Runge has even caught female copepods in the act. ''We can actually put the females in a beaker and watch them eat their eggs,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Despite their untidy family life, or maybe because of it, copepods have the power to fascinate, Dr. Ohman said.</p>
        <p>''They are very diverse and intricate,'' Dr. Ohman added. ''I think if children took a moment to look at them, they would forget all about dinosaurs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
