<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DC1531F935A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>In Warsaw, Bush Urges Eastward NATO Expansion  President Bush called for an Atlantic Alliance stretching all the way to Russia's borders, one day before his first meeting with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. Mr. Bush urged a broad, steady expansion of NATO into countries of Eastern Europe that are not in the alliance.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A day after Mr. Bush visited Goteborg, Sweden, hundreds of demonstrators continued protesting an array of issues during a meeting of European Union leaders. They clashed with police, forcing the leaders to cancel a dinner in the city center. Police reported dozens of injuries.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>In Warsaw, Bush Urges Eastward NATO Expansion  President Bush called for an Atlantic Alliance stretching all the way to Russia's borders, one day before his first meeting with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. Mr. Bush urged a broad, steady expansion of NATO into countries of Eastern Europe that are not in the alliance.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A day after Mr. Bush visited Goteborg, Sweden, hundreds of demonstrators continued protesting an array of issues during a meeting of European Union leaders. They clashed with police, forcing the leaders to cancel a dinner in the city center. Police reported dozens of injuries.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>U.S. to Stay Out of Macedonia  The Bush administration has told its NATO partners that it does not want to participate in a NATO military mission that the Macedonian government has requested for the disarming of ethnic Albanian insurgents, officials said.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Day Two of Mideast Truce  The second full day of an Israeli-Palestinian cease-fire ended without reports of serious violence, but the two sides accused each other of not doing enough to cement the shaky truce.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Curbs on Global Warming  Japan's foreign minister, Makiko Tanaka, said Tokyo would work ''to the last moment'' to persuade the United States to support the Kyoto Protocol on global warming.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>President Bush's opposition to industrialized countries having to cut heat-trapping gas emissions if developing countries are exempt from similar obligations has intensified a longstanding deadlock over who does what and when.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>America's Catholic bishops voted to issue a statement calling for immediate action to mitigate the effects of global climate change.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-13</p>
        <p>Wife of Spy Suspect Says He Had Confessed to Priest  The wife of Robert P. Hanssen, the former F.B.I. agent charged with espionage, has told the authorities that he confided to her and to a priest in 1980 that he was supplying information to the K.G.B. She said the priest persuaded her husband to donate the $20,000 he had received from the Soviets to charity, according to people involved in the case.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Coal's Comeback  America's energy disruptions combined with an administration that has elevated energy security over environmental protection have given coal a new lease on life.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>California Energy Debate  Aides to Gov. Gray Davis released details of the $43 billion in contracts that California has signed with 18 companies to supply much of its power over the next decade, prompting a debate over whether the contracts have stabilized the state's electricity market or whether Mr. Davis has locked residents into overpaying for power for years to come.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Vieques Referendum Opposed  The secretary of the Navy said he would ask Congress to cancel a referendum among the residents of the Puerto Rican island to determine whether they want American forces to continue to train there.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Officials Accused of Corruption  The top official of a Chicago suburb where Al Capone once reigned was arrested by federal agents along with a former police chief and a former town treasurer, all accused of making Cicero a ''personal piggy bank'' by siphoning $10 million from the town's insurance program.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Fox Intervenes in Execution  President Vicente Fox of Mexico is pleading for the life of a Mexican man scheduled to be executed on Tuesday in Oklahoma, citing a violation of international law that has been at the center of several unsuccessful death penalty appeals. But this time it appears that officials may be receptive to the appeal.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>For Lottery Winner, What A Difference a Year Makes  Two days before the deadline for cashing in a $46 million winning lottery ticket, Melvin B. Milligan, a 40-year-old computer technician, calmly dropped the ticket in a curbside mailbox, bound for lottery headquarters in Trenton. Mr. Milligan told only his mother-in-law and wife, in that order, of his sudden fortune.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Lakers Win Series  Los Angeles beat the Philadelphia 76ers, 108-96, winning the N.B.A. Championship, 4 games to 1.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Sir David Spedding  A British spy who rose to head the Secret Intelligence Service, or M.I.6 -- a position immortalized by the author Ian Fleming as the espionage chief known as ''M'' -- he was 58.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B11-20</p>
        <p>Stranger Than Fiction  Publishers of fiction and literature in the Middle East face not only the loss of serious readers to television, but also regional factors like war, censorship, poverty, religious fervor and illiteracy, all combining to threaten the future of fiction.</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Discriminating Behavior  Kenji Yoshino, a 32-year-old gay Asian-American law professor at Yale, is shaking up the legal establishment's approach to discrimination cases. Instead of sidestepping behavior, Mr. Yoshino says,lawyers should call attention to it, starting with assimilation.</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Huge Loss for Nortel  Nortel Networks of Canada expects to announce one of the biggest losses in corporate history, $19.2 billion this quarter. Nortel, the world's biggest maker of communications equipment, pointed to a steep decline in spending by many customers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Stocks fell after the Nortel announcement. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 66.49 points, or 0.6 percent, to 10,623.64. The Nasdaq composite index fell 15.64 points, and the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index dipped 5.51 points.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Judge Orders Merger  A judge ruled that Tyson Foods Inc., the nation's largest poultry producer, had no legal grounds for withdrawing its $4.7 billion offer to buy IBP Inc. and ordered Tyson to complete the deal.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Honeywell Extension  The European Commission, amid signs of pressure from the United States, said there remained a ''limited opportunity'' for General Electric to offer more to win approval of its planned $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Helping New York grow; fix the flaws in school reform; a win for contraception; too slow an exit from Vieques.</p>
        <p>Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B18  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B20  Crossword</p>
        <p>B18  Weather</p>
        <p>B6  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
