<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recipient of Artificial Heart Has Reversal, Doctor Reports</title>
    <meta content="Y13HEA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/13/health/anatomy/13HEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Artificial Heart</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Hospital (Louisville, Ky)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Laman A (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Bronchitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bronchitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bronchitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DF1E3FF930A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recipient of Artificial Heart Has Reversal, Doctor Reports</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recipient of Artificial Heart Has Reversal, Doctor Reports</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Laman A Gray, one of surgeons at Jewish Hospital in Louisville, Ky, who implanted first completely self-contained artificial heart six weeks ago, reports unidentified recipient has suffered serious setback; says patient developed respiratory infection and continues to experience bouts on intestinal bleeding; says infection is responding to antibiotics and other treatments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the doctors who implanted the first completely self-contained artificial heart six weeks ago said yesterday that the recipient suffered a serious setback last week.</p>
        <p>The patient, whose name has not been made public, developed a respiratory infection and has continued to experience bouts of intestinal bleeding, said the doctor, Dr. Laman A. Gray Jr., who implanted the device with Dr. Robert D. Dowling on July 2 at Jewish Hospital in Louisville, Ky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the doctors who implanted the first completely self-contained artificial heart six weeks ago said that the recipient developed a respiratory infection and has continued to experience bouts of intestinal bleeding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the doctors who implanted the first completely self-contained artificial heart six weeks ago said yesterday that the recipient suffered a serious setback last week.</p>
        <p>The patient, whose name has not been made public, developed a respiratory infection and has continued to experience bouts of intestinal bleeding, said the doctor, Dr. Laman A. Gray Jr., who implanted the device with Dr. Robert D. Dowling on July 2 at Jewish Hospital in Louisville, Ky.</p>
        <p>''He has had a setback, no question about it,'' Dr. Gray said of the recipient, who has been identified only as a diabetic man in his middle to late 50's. ''He is sick.''</p>
        <p>But the respiratory infection, which is severe bronchitis or early pneumonia, is responding to antibiotics and other therapy, Dr. Gray said. He said that there was no evidence of a systemic infection or stroke, and that the bleeding was under control.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray said the patient's appearance was encouraging. ''He looks very good, is up in a chair, exercising lightly with hand weights, and has shown remarkable progress,'' Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Before the implant, the man had chronic malnutrition -- his end-stage heart failure had made it difficult to eat. His nutritional state is better but still needs improvement, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>The man's kidneys, which were failing at the time of the implant, are  functioning normally, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>The patient has a tracheotomy, an opening in his neck through which a tube is connected to a mechanical respirator, which is needed at times to help him breathe.</p>
        <p>About a week ago, the doctors temporarily closed the tracheotomy as part of their effort to wean the man from the ventilator. But when the man became lethargic early last week, the doctors found that his windpipe had become plugged with mucus and that he was retaining too much carbon dioxide. So the doctors reopened the tracheotomy. The doctors plan to try again today to wean the man from the ventilator.</p>
        <p>The precise cause of the man's intestinal bleeding has not been determined, even though doctors on at least eight occasions have inserted tubes so they can check inside his stomach and bowel, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>The man is taking Plavix and persantin to help prevent blood clots, but he is not receiving other anticoagulant drugs because of his intestinal bleeding. Repeated imaging has shown no evidence of clots in the artificial heart, Dr. Gray said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray attributed the setback to the man's chronic debilitated condition before the implant, not to the AbioCor artificial heart. The device has continued to work flawlessly, he said. It pumps about seven liters of blood a minute (within the normal range), compared with the two liters the patient's diseased heart had been able to deliver.</p>
        <p>''Everything is improving,'' Dr. Gray said, ''but we were probably trying to push it too fast because we all want to see him get well so badly. And he wants to be that way, too.''</p>
        <p>Setbacks are common in experiments. But because the man was on the verge of death before the AbioCor was implanted, and testing an artificial heart is extremely risky, a setback can carry greater risks for him than for most patients.</p>
        <p>AbioCor's manufacturer, Abiomed of Danvers, Mass., has insisted on a policy of restricting information about the patient during his recovery. The hospital has held only three news conferences and has rarely issued news releases about the man.</p>
        <p>At the last news conference, on Aug. 1, Dr. Dowling said the man was improving steadily, joking with his doctors and nurses, and taking trips around the hospital. Dr. Dowling said he expected that the man would talk to reporters this month. But Dr. Gray said that date would be postponed to at least mid-September.</p>
        <p>In a letter on Aug. 6 reiterating Abiomed's communications policy to the company's stakeholders, Dr. David M. Lederman, the chief executive officer, rejected ''the notion that any public purpose or right is served by releasing information'' on a regular basis. Dr. Lederman said such releases could compromise the patient's dignity.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray, who has been a pioneer in developing mechanical heart-assist devices, said the nearly six weeks of experience with the AbioCor had convinced him that ''the device will work, and work well'' in the future.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
