<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Twists And Turns Of Pedaling To the Job</title>
    <meta content="21SIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DE1E3DF932A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Twists And Turns Of Pedaling To the Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Melinda Tuhus article describes advantages of commuting in Connecticut by bike between her home and office (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S an old song that goes, ''Dead skunk in the middle of the road and it's stinking to high heaven.'' If you are commuting to work on a bicycle, that sentiment would be putting it mildly.</p>
        <p>I commute to New Haven on my bike and not long ago on my way back to my Hamden home I saw ahead of me -- upwind -- a beautiful skunk lying in the middle of the road. I was riding right past him, a few feet away, when I got my first whiff, which indicated he was very recently departed. The stench made breathing impossible and almost toppled me from my bike. Because I was cycling uphill at that point, it took some time to pass it. There was no escape -- no windows to roll up, no air recirculation button to push.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S an old song that goes, ''Dead skunk in the middle of the road and it's stinking to high heaven.'' If you are commuting to work on a bicycle, that sentiment would be putting it mildly.</p>
        <p>I commute to New Haven on my bike and not long ago on my way back to my Hamden home I saw ahead of me -- upwind -- a beautiful skunk lying in the middle of the road. I was riding right past him, a few feet away, when I got my first whiff, which indicated he was very recently departed. The stench made breathing impossible and almost toppled me from my bike. Because I was cycling uphill at that point, it took some time to pass it. There was no escape -- no windows to roll up, no air recirculation button to push.</p>
        <p>That's the price I pay to smell the roses -- and the lilacs, and the newly mown grass -- as I bike around greater New Haven. I think of my bike as a two-wheeled convertible in low gear with the top permanently down. I hear the birds serenading each other in the spring and hear the squirrels skitter through the leaves in the fall.</p>
        <p>My cycling goal is to ride every day, which includes a 4.5-mile commute from Hamden to work in downtown New Haven, as well as longer recreational rides on weekends.</p>
        <p>Some years -- graced by mild, snowless winters -- I have come pretty close to meeting my goal.</p>
        <p>But the brakes fail in wet weather on my 25-year-old, naturally rusted, three-speed, no-name bicycle -- otherwise perfect for commuting -- on which I've logged more than 25,000 miles in the dozen years I've lived in Connecticut. So if it's raining when I'm starting out, I usually don't bike. If I'm out and it starts raining, I slow down and hope for the best.</p>
        <p>Last fall, I was riding through East Rock Park. I love the sweep of trees, the narrow stretch of sky visible overhead, the families of turkeys I often see walking around. It was drizzling, and, as I took a sharp right turn out of the park, my bike slid out from under me. I used my hand to brace my fall -- 10 feet from a pick-up truck in the intersection. A few minutes later, I was at work with an ice pack on my pulsating palm.</p>
        <p>There have been a few other mishaps and near-mishaps over the years, none requiring serious medical care, but all making my heart beat faster.</p>
        <p>None of these scrapes has reduced my enthusiasm for the freedom, the convenience, the exercise, the economy and the environmental awareness of bicycle commuting.</p>
        <p>I worked in New Haven City Hall for five years, and the amount of work time folks there spent feeding meters or moving their cars around to available parking spaces could have bought me a top-of-the-line bike every month.</p>
        <p>Each day I bike, I save money on gas, parking, and depreciation on our car (yes, my family owns one), or bus fare. I also save a lot of money and time not belonging to a gym. I'm not a slave to bus schedules, car-sharing, or traffic jams. I'm making zero contribution to air pollution or global warming. I ride door to door, locking my bike in a bike rack or to a pole.</p>
        <p>And motorized commuters think I'm the one making the sacrifice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
