<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Ah, Wilderness; The Void Without the 'Great Beyond'</title>
    <meta content="18VERH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/18/weekinreview/18VERH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4DA1030F93BA25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Ah, Wilderness; The Void Without the 'Great Beyond'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's plan to open up Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration renews debate about risks and benefits of drilling, or not drilling, there, and what some Americans value about maintaining ultimate wilderness areas; to some people, it is important simply to know such pristine places exist; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICA has always had something of a Great Beyond in its national psyche, a far end of the wilderness dreamscape.</p>
        <p>This frontier, mythic or otherwise, first pushed to the west, of course. But at some point it took a sharp right and went north -- to Alaska, famously known as the Last Frontier. And at its far end, hundreds of miles north of the Arctic Circle, just over the rugged Brooks Range and rolling down to a frigid sea, is the 19 million acres of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. It is an austere wilderness that lies frozen, white and silent for much of the year, then bursts to life in the late Arctic spring, when migrating caribou herds thunder across the refuge and arrive on the coastal plain to give birth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICA has always had something of a Great Beyond in its national psyche, a far end of the wilderness dreamscape.</p>
        <p>This frontier, mythic or otherwise, first pushed to the west, of course. But at some point it took a sharp right and went north -- to Alaska, famously known as the Last Frontier. And at its far end, hundreds of miles north of the Arctic Circle, just over the rugged Brooks Range and rolling down to a frigid sea, is the 19 million acres of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. It is an austere wilderness that lies frozen, white and silent for much of the year, then bursts to life in the late Arctic spring, when migrating caribou herds thunder across the refuge and arrive on the coastal plain to give birth.</p>
        <p>As Congress takes up President Bush's energy plan, there will be plenty of questions about his case to open up the refuge to exploration by the oil industry and about the benefits and risks of drilling there. But underneath the debate between oilmen who want to tap into billions of barrels of oil and environmentalists protective of wildlife lies another question. What are the benefits of not drilling there?</p>
        <p>Put another way, the question is: what does it mean to Americans to have an ''ultimate wilderness,'' to borrow a phrase from ''Coming Into the Country,'' John McPhee's book about Alaska.</p>
        <p>If the drilling plan goes through,  wildlife -- including polar bears, musk oxen, Dall sheep, tundra swans and millions of migratory birds -- may well adapt, as caribou already have 100 miles or so to the west, at the beginning of the Trans-Alaska Pipeline. (Some caribou even like to ''snuggle up next to the pipeline,'' as President Bush's father memorably put it in his 1988 presidential campaign.) But nobody could really think of the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge as a true wilderness anymore, as some untouched Great Beyond. Therein lies the loss.</p>
        <p>Terry Tempest Williams, the nature essayist, says she heard it best put 24 years ago, at a Congressional hearing on Alaska lands. A man in his 20's, a blind piano tuner from Texas, stood up. ''Gentlemen,'' he said, ''I may never get up to the Arctic and I certainly will never see Wild Alaska, but in those days when my own world seems dark and small, just to know such places exist will fill my soul with hope.''</p>
        <p>How did wilderness come to embody hope? Since the arrival of Europeans on this continent, the concept has existed in the idea of vast tracts of land untouched by ''civilized'' influences. At first, it was an enemy, an impossibly vast, threatening force, hiding hostile ''savages'' and foiling attempts to farm.</p>
        <p>Prof. Noel Perrin of Dartmouth College, who teaches and writes about eco-history, said that an early American farmer and writer, J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, ''took for granted that a field is a wonderful place and a forest is a horrible place where you hear the shriek of the owl and the hiss of the serpent.''</p>
        <p>THAT idea persisted through the founding of the nation.  Thomas Jefferson -- himself a farmer, as was George Washington -- saw farmers as heroic, as they burned, clear-cut and pulled plows with their own bodies through what had been forest. The task seemed limitless.</p>
        <p>Yet it was not long before a more divine image arose. The journals of Lewis and Clark, for example, register exuberance at the majesty of God's creation. And Emerson and Thoreau found spiritualism and the affirmation of free will in the contemplation of nature.</p>
        <p>Still, the first transcontinental railroad inflamed the worship of progress -- and the rationalism and utilitarianism that drove it. The wilderness was less an enemy than a challenge. Infatuated with industrial development, Americans found it possible to celebrate the beauty of the wilderness and the glory of its taming simultaneously.</p>
        <p>Paintings depicted railroads cutting through the wilderness, spectacular mountains in the background, stumps of trees in the foreground. And the stumps ''weren't in any way considered a negative image,'' said Stephen Edidin, a curator at the Dahesh Museum of Art in Manhattan. ''The idea was, it's progress, and progress is a beautiful thing.''</p>
        <p>Both the scenery and the means to alter it were considered inspiring, explained Richard White, a Western and environmental historian at Stanford. ''There was a lot of talk of 'finishing,' he said. ''God created the basic structure, the rivers and the mountains and the soil, but the ultimate finishing was up to man.'' It was all part of Manifest Destiny.</p>
        <p>But the more the landscape got ''finished,'' the more consciousness shifted. John Muir, the naturalist who founded the Sierra Club, began writing of the wilderness as a planetwide cathedral of lofty forests and snow-covered peaks. His purism conflicted with the more pragmatic ideas of another famed American environmentalist: Theodore Roosevelt, who was intent on preserving habitats for animals, though in part because he liked to hunt.</p>
        <p>IT was in that same era, around the turn of the century, when the West was won and the frontier had closed, according to the historian Frederick Jackson Turner, and preservationist notions were gaining ground, that Alaska became the Last Frontier. Jack London's short stories pitted man against heartless nature there -- and nature often won.</p>
        <p>And there may be the core of the desire to save the Alaskan wilderness. Where nature was once perceived as hostile and disastrously potent, it is now fragile. Our fears about nature are far less about what it can do to us than what we have done to it. We are still sometimes at the mercy of nature, but we are perhaps even more at the mercy of our own effects on nature: pollution, sprawl, extinctions, global warming. Wilderness, by contrast, is where the force of nature still rules, where human responsibility lies in staying out, and where, perhaps, we can still see something divine.</p>
        <p>THE area's nearest neighbors -- Alaskans themselves -- often find such abstractions irritating. After all, the state has more untrammeled vistas than any other. ''We have 56 million acres of wilderness,'' said Senator Frank H. Murkowski, an Alaska Republican and strong drilling proponent, who is chairman of the Senate's Energy and Natural Resource Committee. ''There's no mining, no exploration, no vehicles. Alaskans say, that's fine. Wilderness is fine. But how much is enough?''</p>
        <p>Many other arguments will enter into the coming debate. Some will point out that drilling enhances national security: a barrel of Alaskan oil, as long as it's sold on the domestic market (which does not always happen; some has been exported to Asia), is one less barrel of crude to buy from the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Opponents will raise questions about what the oil will be doing for us. It might, Mr. McPhee said in an interview, just help keep ''four S.U.V.'s in somebody's garage somewhere,'' temporarily helping sustain an equation that conservationists say is unsustainable, or at least unforgivable: with 5 percent of the world's population, America still consumes 25 percent of the world's energy.</p>
        <p>But there will remain the unweighed value of simply knowing that the Last Frontier remains.</p>
        <p>''It's a place where there's true silence,'' said Debbie S. Miller, a Fairbanks writer.</p>
        <p>''I stood on a mountain one day and it was so quiet, I could literally hear the blood rushing through my head,'' said Ms. Miller, author of ''Midnight Wilderness: Journeys in Alaska's Arctic National Wildlife Refuge.'' ''I can't hear that in our cities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
