<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Calls Allies in Advance of Missile Speech</title>
    <meta content="01MISS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/01/world/01MISS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1289671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Missiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DE1638F932A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Calls Allies in Advance of Missile Speech</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush begins paving diplomatic path for missile defense system and possibility of renouncing 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty; calls leaders of several major European and Asian allies in preparation for May 1 speech; tells them he wants to begin consultations on new nuclear treaty (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush began paving the diplomatic path today for his missile defense system and the possibility of renouncing the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty. He called leaders of several major European and Asian allies in preparation for a speech about missile defense on Tuesday, telling them he wanted to begin consultations on a new nuclear strategy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is expected to announce a framework for his plans at the National Defense University here. But this afternoon a senior administration official said Mr. Bush would not discuss the budget, schedule or the likely architecture of a new missile defense system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush began paving the diplomatic path today for his missile defense system and the possibility of renouncing the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty. He called leaders of several major European and Asian allies in preparation for a speech about missile defense on Tuesday, telling them he wanted to begin consultations on a new nuclear strategy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is expected to announce a framework for his plans at the National Defense University here. But this afternoon a senior administration official said Mr. Bush would not discuss the budget, schedule or the likely architecture of a new missile defense system.</p>
        <p>''We need to rethink the concept of deterrence that was in the past based on massive nuclear retaliation,'' the official said. While stopping short of saying the president would abandon the missile treaty, which has been a cornerstone of the arms control world for the last three decades, the official left little doubt that the president was headed in that direction.</p>
        <p>''At some point in time we will have to pursue promising technologies, and the ABM treaty would likely be in the way,'' the official said. But the official told reporters that Mr. Bush had ''no preconceived notion'' of what kind of system he would like to build, or what nations, beyond the United States, it might protect.</p>
        <p>Stung by accusations that he abandoned the Kyoto treaty on global warming without warning allies earlier this year, Mr. Bush appeared to go out of his way today to make sure that his fellow leaders were not surprised by what he is to say on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>This morning he called Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany, Prime Minister Jacques Chirac of France, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, Prime Minister Jean Chrétien of Canada, and the NATO secretary general, Lord Robertson. On Saturday he called the new prime minister of Japan, Junichiro Koizumi, to congratulate him and to say he would be sending a team of senior aides to Asia to begin discussing Japan's role in a related theater missile defense system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush apparently has not yet called Vladimir V. Putin, the Russian president, who has vociferously opposed a unilateral American decision on missile defense. But Mr. Putin has more recently hinted that in exchange for some American concessions he might be able to live with some amendments to the ABM treaty. But the Russian position is still unclear, and the White House has gone to some length to play down the diplomatic objections to its plans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has repeatedly said the system is intended to protect against an accidental launch, to repel an attack by states like Iraq or North Korea, or to counter a terrorist threatening nuclear blackmail.</p>
        <p>But China regards the system as an effort to suppress its own minimum deterrent -- Beijing has deployed roughly 20 nuclear missiles able to reach the United States -- and any hint that the system might also protect Taiwan against a medium-range attack is bound to strengthen China's suspicions that the new administration is trying to contain its military reach. Chinese authorities have threatened to respond by greatly increasing the size of their nuclear arsenal. Unlike the Russians, the Chinese have the cash to make good on that threat.</p>
        <p>''This spills over directly into China policy, and the new administration's problems with China,'' Senator John F. Kerry, the Massachusetts Democrat and a strong critic of Mr. Bush's missile defense plan, said in a telephone interview today from Boston. ''What's the rush? This is essentially a satisfy-your-base, political announcement. It serves no other purpose.''</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Bush say the goal of the speech is to make the case -- as he began to do a year ago during a campaign speech at the National Press Club here -- that the ABM treaty is an outdated relic that does not fit America's current defense needs.</p>
        <p>His press secretary, Ari Fleischer, said Mr. Bush's speech would ''reflect on his view of the post-cold-war realities,'' and his belief that the ABM treaty was devised for a world in which two hostile superpowers were in an ever escalating race to build more warheads. Mr. Bush has offered to unilaterally reduce America's nuclear arsenal, but it was not known whether he will offer specific numbers in his speech.</p>
        <p>''Consultation is key,'' Mr. Fleischer said, but he sidestepped questions about whether Mr. Bush was willing to amend his plan if allies objected to central elements of it.</p>
        <p>The delegation that will be sent to describe Mr. Bush's thinking to American allies, and to Russia, will be led by Paul D. Wolfowitz, the deputy secretary of defense, and Richard L. Armitage, the deputy secretary of state, officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
