<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sunday Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="12SUNQ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/12/national/12SUNQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Sunday Q &amp; A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">The New York Times Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">White, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EED9103FF931A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sunday Q &amp; A</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Circulating, and Spending, $1 Coins</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunday Q &amp; A appears in this section weekly. Readers are invited to send in questions about national or international affairs; those selected will be answered by Times correspondents who specialize in those issues. Information about submitting questions appears below.</p>
        <p>Circulating, and Spending, $1 Coins</p>
        <p>Q. How much success is the new $1 coin having?</p>
        <p>A. Richard W. Stevenson, a correspondent in the Washington bureau of The New York Times, responds:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How much success is the new $1 coin having</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sunday Q &amp; A appears in this section weekly. Readers are invited to send in questions about national or international affairs; those selected will be answered by Times correspondents who specialize in those issues. Information about submitting questions appears below.</p>
        <p>Circulating, and Spending, $1 Coins</p>
        <p>Q. How much success is the new $1 coin having?</p>
        <p>A. Richard W. Stevenson, a correspondent in the Washington bureau of The New York Times, responds:</p>
        <p>The dollar coin is not weighing down too many pockets so far.</p>
        <p>More than a year and a half after they were introduced, there are 800 million of the dollar coins  in circulation, said Michael White, a spokesman for the United States Mint. But many of them are going into collections or dresser drawers rather than being spent freely, Mr. White said. A survey by the mint at the end of last year found that 42 percent of adults had received one of the new dollar coins -- but that they expect to collect and save six of them before spending one.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly not a flop,'' Mr. White said. ''People love the design. They may like it too much initially.''</p>
        <p>The coin features the image of Sacagawea, the Shoshone Indian woman who accompanied Lewis and Clark on their transcontinental voyage. It starts out gold in color but darkens, much like a penny, as it ages.</p>
        <p>Whatever its aesthetic merits, it has faced an uphill battle for acceptance as a complement to -- much less a replacement for -- the dollar bill. The mint has tried a variety of marketing ideas, from a deal in which the International House of Pancakes renamed its Silver Dollar Pancake the Golden Dollar Pancake to agreements with supermarket chains to give the coins as change.</p>
        <p>The mint is hoping that the dollar coin will win  further acceptance as cities begin accepting it in parking meters and highway authorities allow its use at toll booths.</p>
        <p>Predictions on Fuel Reserves</p>
        <p>Q. If nothing is done in conservation and in the development of renewable energy sources, how long until we run out of oil and gas?</p>
        <p>A. Neela Banerjee, the energy reporter for the Business section of The New York Times, responds:</p>
        <p>Before we forge ahead, the caveat here is that many previous predictions about when oil and gas  reserves would run out have been proved wrong because new technology has made it possible for energy companies to find and coax from the earth ever-greater volumes of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>We will probably not run out of petroleum in this century, but its diminishing supplies worldwide will eventually make it prohibitively expensive to use, said David Morehouse, the senior petroleum geologist at the Energy Information Administration, the analytical arm of the Energy  Department.</p>
        <p>The United States Geological Survey estimates that there are about three trillion barrels of proven reserves of oil worldwide. The world should reach its peak levels of oil production in 2037, after which output is expected to fall precipitously. Oil will still be eked out of the ground, but, as Mr. Morehouse put it, it will probably be used to make high-priced industrial greases rather than fuel.</p>
        <p>The United States tends to use its own supplies of natural gas and coal. There is the equivalent of a 63-year supply of natural gas here, based on current rates of production, according to the American Gas Association. And a 250-year storehouse of coal is buried in the United States. But all this ignores the possible impact of conservation and new technologies.</p>
        <p>On the supply side, the Holy Grail is powering turbines and engines with hydrogen broken out from water. An equally elusive fuel is methane hydrates, basically natural gas trapped in ice in places like Alaska. Based on research that began in the 1960's, people believe the volume of methane hydrates is far greater than that of oil and other natural gas, but no one has come up with the technology to tap it.</p>
        <p>The Placement of Impulse Items</p>
        <p>Q. Why is it that certain items are always placed near the checkout in stores?</p>
        <p>A. Constance L. Hays, who covers retailing for The New York Times, responds:</p>
        <p>The priciest real estate in supermarkets is those precious few square feet nearest the cash registers, says Burt Flickinger III, a retail consultant with Reach Marketing in Westport, Conn. Magazine publishers, candy and gum companies and battery manufacturers are among the bidders for this space, and they end up paying hefty ''placement fees,'' sometimes $25,000 for a single store, for the right to have their products right under a shopper's nose. Turnover in these areas is  high as well.</p>
        <p>''The sales per square foot always exceed $1,000 per square foot,'' Mr. Flickinger said, ''while shelves in the center of the store tend to generate $200 to $300 per square foot.''</p>
        <p>Some of the companies want to be there because that is the best way to display their products. ''It's critical for gum manufacturers like Wrigley because it's almost never a planned purchase,'' Mr. Flickinger said.</p>
        <p>Others want to be there because they can command a higher price for, say, a cold soda at the checkout than for warm bottles on a shelf. ''For Pepsi and Coke, even after paying for those coolers, that's the highest return on capital for anything they do in the stores,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While fees for this space are already high, some companies have offered to pay even more. Those would be the tobacco companies, which have largely failed to win the battle. ''To the credit of the retailers,'' Mr. Flickinger said, ''they are turning down very significant sums of money from the tobacco companies.''</p>
        <p>Send questions by e-mail to sundayq&amp;a@ nytimes.com, or by mail to Sunday Q &amp; A, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Those of widest interest will be selected, but unpublished questions cannot be answered individually. Previous Sunday Q &amp; A's are available at www.nytimes.com/pages/national/columns/.</p>
        <p>Sunday Q &amp; A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
