<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush and Putin Look Each Other in the Eye</title>
    <meta content="17ASSE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/17/world/17ASSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT IN EUROPE: NEWS ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DB1231F934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush and Putin Look Each Other in the Eye</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>LJUBLJANA, Slovenia, June 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis says that, whatever happens now, new era in America's relations has begun with George W Bush and Vladimir Putin looking each other in the eye; observes that seldom have two leaders so strikingly overcome limited expectations about their first meeting (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever happens now, for good or for ill, a new era in America's relations with Russia began today.</p>
        <p>Seldom have two leaders so strikingly overcome the limited expectations about their first meeting as George W. Bush and Vladimir V. Putin did today, putting their new friendship on a high plane of newfound trust and instructing their defense chiefs, both hard-liners, and their foreign secretaries, to find a common approach for a new framework for international security.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whatever happens now, for good or for ill, a new era in America's relations with Russia began today.</p>
        <p>Seldom have two leaders so strikingly overcome the limited expectations about their first meeting as George W. Bush and Vladimir V. Putin did today, putting their new friendship on a high plane of newfound trust and instructing their defense chiefs, both hard-liners, and their foreign secretaries, to find a common approach for a new framework for international security.</p>
        <p>Whether this constructive new beginning -- made with surprising buoyancy and personal engagement -- will succeed as the genuine partnership that Mr. Bush and Mr. Putin described here this afternoon will depend on how they follow through on the collaborative venture that they outlined only in broad strokes.</p>
        <p>It includes joint work to study security threats, cooperative energy projects and new studies on how American corporations might find investment opportunities in the struggling Russian economy. It also includes American support for Russia's entry into the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>''This was a very good meeting,'' Mr. Bush said standing alongside the Russian president. ''He is an honest, straightforward man who loves his country,'' he added, and he called Mr. Putin a ''remarkable'' leader whom Americans can trust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin confirmed the American president's assessment and said the meeting had proved that ''reality was a lot bigger than expectations.'' He asserted that an important cold war milestone had been passed with Mr. Bush's declaration that Russia is no longer America's enemy.</p>
        <p>The two men had come to look each other in the eye, and Mr. Bush said he did just that to take the measure of Mr. Putin's soul. They  both appeared to like what they saw, even as they laid out the agenda of their extensive disagreements on missile defenses, the expansion of NATO onto the territory of the former Soviet Union and Russia's growing arms trade with Iran.</p>
        <p>And today's reversal of tone in American-Russian relations may reflect how much each leader needed the positive outcome. Mr. Bush needed to prove to Europe and to the Senate that he was not engaged in recklessness as he pursued a new security concept that includes missile defenses. And Mr. Putin needed to know that the new Bush administration was not looking for a confrontation because Mr. Putin has his hands full at home trying to pull Russia beyond the wreckage of the Soviet era.</p>
        <p>For more than two hours, Mr. Bush and Mr. Putin discussed a world rapidly transforming itself from the world of their fathers and despite the surprisingly positive outcome of today's meeting, it cannot be separated from the extraordinary week of diplomatic activity that preceded it.</p>
        <p>In his first major diplomatic foray abroad, Mr. Bush discovered this week that Europe was becoming its own powerhouse of economic and security interests that, while similar to those of the United States, are by no means identical on issues as diverse as climate change and urgent European calls for NATO to step into the fray in Macedonia.</p>
        <p>And though Mr. Bush may have succeeded in fostering what he termed a ''new receptivity'' to his proposal for missile defenses among some European leaders this week, Germany and France stood as formidable skeptics, each concerned that Mr. Bush's plan would trigger a new arms race by not taking into account Russia's and China's concerns.</p>
        <p>As if to sharpen that point, Mr. Putin made his entrance here after flying from China, where he and President Jiang Zemin and the leaders of four Central Asian republics signed the founding charter of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization, not quite an alliance, but a potent new expression of Asian interests.</p>
        <p>Indeed, despite the warming with Mr. Bush, Mr. Putin seems to be fostering a new era of triangular diplomacy, positioning Russia to be an ally of China and of Europe as a hedge against American unilateralism, a concern he mentioned today. His tactic put Mr. Bush on the defensive, and Mr. Bush this week was at pains to assert that America is not about to go it alone in international affairs, but was trying instead to galvanize support for a new international security concept. The concept remains largely undefined except that missile defenses are a prominent centerpiece.</p>
        <p>With all the disagreement, however, what seemed most important was that the two presidents -- neither of whom has been in office very long, one a former Soviet K.G.B. officer, the other a scion of American wealth and political dynasty -- had finally met in the shadow of the Alps, near the fragile epicenter of European instability in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin had been seeking this meeting since almost the day after Mr. Bush's inauguration, but Mr. Bush's advisers delayed it for months, saying they were formulating a new policy toward Russia, one that now seems to be taking shape.</p>
        <p>The two leaders now move on, to see each other again in July and October at the summit meeting of leading industrial nations in Genoa and of Asian and Pacific leaders in Shanghai, and they accepted invitations to visit not just each other's capitals but each other's homes.</p>
        <p>Between now and then, both must return to domestic political challenges. Mr. Bush faces the Senate, now led by Democrats, many of whom are as skeptical as some European leaders about the consequences of abandoning the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty and how to pay for missile defenses even if they turn out to be feasible.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Putin returns to Moscow, where he must prove that he is the democratic leader he advertises himself to be, one who wants to take Russia into Europe, a goal that will be difficult to reach as long as the partisan war in Chechnya continues without negotiation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's yearold government also stands at a critical juncture of reform, with sweeping proposals to build a new judicial system, institute jury trials and privatize land ownership this year, an issue still so contentious in post-Soviet Russia that a fistfight broke out Friday among lawmakers. And though Mr. Putin this week reaffirmed his commitment to a free press and to building civil society, his administration has been dogged by incidents of pressure and intimidation that have called that commitment into question.</p>
        <p>''This is a unique opportunity,'' said Aleksei Arbatov, an influential member of the Russian Parliament watching events from Moscow. ''There are a lot of problems and mutual suspicions between our countries, and the main issue for both leaders is to decide whether they want to resolve these issues cooperatively, or to deal with those problems without dealing with each other.''</p>
        <p>''The fact that the United States is the only remaining superpower in the world,'' he continued, ''means that it has to use this opportunity to demonstrate that it is a well-meaning state trying to establish the rule of the game for international relations on the basis of cooperation and not on force.''</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT IN EUROPE: NEWS ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
