<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Learning What Fuel to Burn</title>
    <meta content="17RICH$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/17/opinion/17RICH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1286211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richter, Burton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DF1F31F934A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Learning What Fuel to Burn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Burton Richter</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richter, Burton (Dr)</byline>
      <dateline>STANFORD, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Burton Richter, Nobel Prize winner in physics in 1976, says Pres Bush is right to go slow on regulating carbon dioxide emissions from power plants, even though global warming is most serious environmental threat on horizon and carbon dioxide from fossil fuel burning is major contributor to it; says Bush is wrong to propose budget cuts for research on alternative energy sources and energy conservation, approaches that would help achieve some reductions in carbon dioxide emissions in near term; says expanded economic incentives, like tax breaks, for deployment of more efficient systems of all types would help move country faster toward curbing its dependence on carbon-based fuels; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like nearly all scientists, I believe that global warming is the most serious environmental threat on the horizon for our grandchildren, and that carbon dioxide from fossil fuel burning is a major contributor to it. Yet I agree with President Bush that we must go slow on regulating carbon dioxide emissions from power plants. That is why we have to fall back on research on alternative energy sources and on energy conservation -- the two approaches that will help us achieve some reductions in carbon dioxide emissions in the near term. But Mr. Bush's proposed budget cuts for research and conservation move in precisely the wrong direction.</p>
        <p>It is clear that the earth's temperatures are rising, and world energy use is projected to double in the next 50 years, making the problem much worse. But something else is also evident: We are simply not ready to regulate carbon dioxide from power plants -- the leading source of industrial carbon dioxide emissions. There is no technology to do it with our present mix of fuels, despite the fervent wish of many environmentalists. What we need instead is a long-term strategy to reduce the use of carbon-based fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like nearly all scientists, I believe that global warming is the most serious environmental threat on the horizon for our grandchildren, and that carbon dioxide from fossil fuel burning is a major contributor to it. Yet I agree with President Bush that we must go slow on regulating carbon dioxide emissions from power plants. That is why we have to fall back on research on alternative energy sources and on energy conservation -- the two approaches that will help us achieve some reductions in carbon dioxide emissions in the near term. But Mr. Bush's proposed budget cuts for research and conservation move in precisely the wrong direction.</p>
        <p>It is clear that the earth's temperatures are rising, and world energy use is projected to double in the next 50 years, making the problem much worse. But something else is also evident: We are simply not ready to regulate carbon dioxide from power plants -- the leading source of industrial carbon dioxide emissions. There is no technology to do it with our present mix of fuels, despite the fervent wish of many environmentalists. What we need instead is a long-term strategy to reduce the use of carbon-based fuels.</p>
        <p>Only nuclear power generation, which does not emit carbon dioxide, is available now as a large-scale alternative. Hydropower and wind and geothermal energy are clean  but naturally limited. Biomass energy from growing and burning plants emits no net carbon dioxide (carbon in the plant comes from carbon dioxide in the atmosphere), but will be limited by the availability of water for growing crops. Solar energy is useful at the moment only for small-scale applications because no practical system yet exists for storing it for use at night or in bad weather. Natural gas, more efficient at producing energy than coal, is currently in short supply.</p>
        <p>Given these existing constraints, government should support research and development of new ways of producing and using energy -- more efficient power sources for transportation, like fuel cells, for example; carbon-free energy sources, like more advanced nuclear power plants and effective solar power systems; underground gasification of coal. We should also be promoting efficiency regulations on things that use energy -- for example, air conditioners. The Bush administration's decision to reduce air conditioner efficiency goals last week was a senseless reversal.</p>
        <p>The president has also promised a long-term energy strategy, and it is in the long term that the government can make a greater difference. The fundamental, harder job is to tilt the economic playing field in our market economy to make carbon-free energy more attractive to both producers and consumers. The genius of the market system lies in its ability to mobilize the best of our industrial capacity to pursue new approaches in the hope of economic gain.</p>
        <p>A sensible way to tilt the field is with a carbon tax that would decrease the profits of users of carbon-based fuels and increase them for users of alternatives. An added excise tax on vehicles based on their fuel efficiency would also help achieve this goal. In fact, expanded economic incentives, like tax breaks, for the deployment of more efficient systems of all types would help us move faster toward curbing our dependence on carbon-based fuels.</p>
        <p>Some say such policies would damage our economy. I doubt it. Some businesses would be hurt, but when the automobile replaced the horse, livery stables, blacksmiths and buggy manufacturers were hurt while the economy boomed. But in a democracy like ours, it is hard to do anything that goes against vested interests until a crisis is upon us.</p>
        <p>The scientific community knows the global warming crisis is here, and the longer we wait the harder it becomes to fix the problem. The effects will be felt more strongly by our grandchildren than by us, and they are too young to do anything about it. It will require effective political leadership to get us moving in the right direction. Mr. Bush's cuts for both conservation and research on carbon-free energy are not a good sign. The government needs to reverse course before more crucial time is lost.</p>
        <p>Burton Richter, director emeritus of the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, won the Nobel Prize in physics in 1976.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Burton Richter, director emeritus of the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, won the Nobel Prize in physics in 1976.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
