<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Walk in the Woods to Discover Trilliums</title>
    <meta content="18WGARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D61630F93BA25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Walk in the Woods to Discover Trilliums</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ginsburg, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elisabeth Ginsburg In the Garden column on woodland plants, particularly trilliums; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I JUST finished reading Ann Mohin's wonderful novel ''The Farm She Was'' (Bridgeworks Publishing Company, 1998). In it, the author uses the literary device of an elderly person reminiscing about an eventful life, and revitalizes it with lyrical prose passages. The book describes the narrator's rural home ground in central New York State, and when the 90-year-old Irene Leahy describes the woods and fields and the plants that grow there, she strikes a responsive chord with me.</p>
        <p>Before very long, the woodland plants in this part of the world will start the yearly cycle of rebirth. I look forward to it, even though the nearest wooded area is a car trip away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I JUST finished reading Ann Mohin's wonderful novel ''The Farm She Was'' (Bridgeworks Publishing Company, 1998). In it, the author uses the literary device of an elderly person reminiscing about an eventful life, and revitalizes it with lyrical prose passages. The book describes the narrator's rural home ground in central New York State, and when the 90-year-old Irene Leahy describes the woods and fields and the plants that grow there, she strikes a responsive chord with me.</p>
        <p>Before very long, the woodland plants in this part of the world will start the yearly cycle of rebirth. I look forward to it, even though the nearest wooded area is a car trip away.</p>
        <p>Woodland plants are in vogue right now. The new catalogs are absolutely full of terrestrial orchids, Dutchman's breeches, trilliums and violets. It seems paradoxical that in this age of global warming, when people no longer plant trees for posterity, shade gardening is the hottest thing since e-mail.</p>
        <p>I try to take a walk in the woods every year in the early spring, as soon as the mud has subsided enough so that I don't feel that it will suck me in.</p>
        <p>I look forward to skunk cabbage (especially if I am upwind of it), and I am always tickled by my first sight of a jack-in-the-pulpit (Arisaema triphyllum). The three large leaves that crown each plant are relatively easy to spot, but the hooded green or purplish-brown jacks are somewhat camouflaged.</p>
        <p>In the wooded areas that I frequent in the Northeast, the plants seem relatively common. However, since undeveloped areas all over are endangered, I regard Arisaema as endangered as well.</p>
        <p>Trilliums seem the most special to me, even though some species, such as the white Snow Trillium (Trillium grandiflorum), show up fairly often in damp shady spots. The three-lobed trillium flowers remind me of the similarly configured leaves of jack-in-the-pulpit. Nature favors such pleasing triads.</p>
        <p>There are, of course, red trilliums (Trillium erectum), as well, but they seem to occur less frequently than their white counterparts. The few reds that I have seen appeared maroon, rather than the brighter red described by some observers.</p>
        <p>I have never seen a trillium in a bouquet, even in the glossy pages of high-end magazines. This could be because they are endangered in some states, or it might be because they don't last well in water. Whatever the reason, it is best to let sleeping trilliums lie in the woodsy areas where they grow. It is always wise to take plant photographs from the woods, rather than the plants themselves.</p>
        <p>Like another of my favorite spring plants, dogtooth violet, some trilliums have mottled foliage. Yellow Trillium (Trillium luteum) and the fancifully named Toad Shade Trillium (Trillium sessile) share that trait. Just as I have never seen a spider on a spiderwort, there are no reported sightings of toads hunkering down under Toad Shade Trillium.  However, both toads and Toad Shade Trillium thrive under similar conditions, so nothing can be ruled out.</p>
        <p>For trillium aficionados with cool summers, Painted Trillium (Trillium undulatum) is an enticing possibility. The white blossoms are splashed with rosy centers. Nodding Trillium (Trillium cernuum) does not hold its flowers proudly above the foliage like some other members of the genus. Instead they pose demurely under the leaves.</p>
        <p>One of the nice things about trilliums is that if they like a particular environment, they will form colonies.  You can start them from seed, but the results happen faster if you install a few established plants. They are sometimes available from local nurseries, but it's important to make sure those nurseries do not purchase plants that were collected from the wild.</p>
        <p>Be a savvy buyer. Even if a plant is labeled ''Nursery Grown'' it may still be a potted-up wild specimen. So-called ''nursery propagated'' plants are born not merely raised, in a nursery, so you can be sure that no wild stores were depleted to obtain them.</p>
        <p>A good source of nursery propagated native plants is eastern Plant Specialties (732-382-2508; online at www.easternplant.com).</p>
        <p>Ann Mohin's narrator said that real estate developers ''turn over a leaf to study its underside and see condominiums.'' It is hard to understand how anyone could study a trillium and see anything other than a miracle.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
