<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D6173CF931A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Mexicans Dispute Claims Their Trucks Are Unsafe  Experts in Mexico and the United States said that American opponents of allowing Mexican trucks to venture much beyond the border had marshaled safety statistics that on close examination were misleading or incomplete. They also said there appeared to be little or no data supporting the contention of the Teamsters and others that Mexican long-haul trucks and truckers were considerably more dangerous.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Senate approved a $60 billion transportation bill that President Bush threatened to veto because it would limit Mexican trucks' access to American roads. The White House says restrictions in the bill violate Nafta provisions and hinder improvements in diplomatic and commercial relations with Mexico.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Mexicans Dispute Claims Their Trucks Are Unsafe  Experts in Mexico and the United States said that American opponents of allowing Mexican trucks to venture much beyond the border had marshaled safety statistics that on close examination were misleading or incomplete. They also said there appeared to be little or no data supporting the contention of the Teamsters and others that Mexican long-haul trucks and truckers were considerably more dangerous.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Senate approved a $60 billion transportation bill that President Bush threatened to veto because it would limit Mexican trucks' access to American roads. The White House says restrictions in the bill violate Nafta provisions and hinder improvements in diplomatic and commercial relations with Mexico.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Senate Action on Warming  The Foreign Relations Committee unanimously urged the Bush administration to develop a plan to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases and to take part in international talks on global warming.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Israel Affirms Target Strategy  Israel, rejecting protests from the United States and elsewhere, defended its missile strike on Tuesday that killed eight West Bank Palestinians and said it would carry out more if it felt Israeli lives were at risk.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Bosnia War Crimes Trial  A former Serb general, Radislav Krstic, the highest-ranking Serb to face judgment in The Hague so far, is expected to hear the verdict today of three judges on the United Nations war crimes tribunal. In 1995, General Krstic commanded troops that overran Srebrenica, where 7,000 Muslims were reported to have been massacred. The verdict will be the tribunal's first on whether genocide was committed in Bosnia from 1992 to 1995.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Progress in Macedonia Talks  Leaders of the Macedonian Slavs and minority Albanians said they had determined that Albanian, spoken by about a third of the population, would become an official language with Macedonian.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Last-Ditch Plan for Ulster  Britain and Ireland proposed measures to start I.R.A. disarmament and avert a breakdown of the power-sharing Northern Ireland Assembly.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-18</p>
        <p>House Backs Arctic Drilling In Victory for Bush's Plan  The House passed a sweeping energy plan, voting to allow drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and rejecting an effort to further raise fuel efficiency standards for vehicles. Republican leaders managed to preserve major portions of President Bush's energy plan while defeating environmentalists on the Alaska and fuel issues.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deal on Patients' Rights  President Bush and Representative Charlie Norwood, a Georgia Republican, a dentist and the leader of a six-year effort for patients' rights, agreed on compromise legislation.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Move to Keep Vieques Open  The House Armed Services Committee approved a measure that would bar the Navy from closing its Vieques firing range until a suitable replacement was found. Democrats said that could keep it open for years.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Arrest in Killing Spree  Gary Sampson, 41, was arraigned in Vermont after confessing to three killings and a series of carjackings in New England, records showed.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Study Faults Death Penalty Use  A study of capital punishment in Nebraska suggests that the death penalty is applied unequally in rural and urban areas and that defendants whose victims are affluent are more likely to receive a death sentence.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Surgery for Epilepsy  Brain surgery is better than prolonged drug therapy for treating the most common form of epilepsy, according to the first study that directly compared the two treatments.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Heart Patient Recovering  The first recipient of a self-contained artificial heart is walking, eating some solid food, exercising lightly and talking a blue streak as he gains strength in a surprising recovery.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Misgivings Over Cloning  The Senate majority leader, Tom Daschle, said he was ''very uncomfortable'' with human cloning even for research purposes as he sought to turn the debate back to embryonic stem cell research, which he and many other Democrats support.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Green Promises No Sequel To Giuliani Administration  Mark Green said in an interview that if he were elected mayor, his administration would be profoundly different from Mayor Giuliani's. For example, Mr. Green, a Democrat, would seek to shift some of the Police Department's overtime budget for fighting crime to social programs for the police and for crime prevention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A.A. Statements Protected  A federal judge in White Plains ruled that conversations between members of Alcoholics Anonymous have the same sort of privilege as contacts between clerics and parishioners, and he overturned the conviction of a man who killed two people 13 years ago in Larchmont, N.Y..</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Bush Presses for Schools Bill  President Bush, addressing the National Urban League, urged the House and Senate to settle their differences and pass final legislation, saying the state of many urban schools was a ''great and continuing scandal'' that needed rapid action.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Pro Football All-Star Dies  Korey Stringer, 27, an offensive tackle for the Minnesota Vikings, died a day after collapsing during preseason practice in 90-degree heat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Heat-related illnesses typically strike young athletes overexerting themselves in hot, humid weather and elderly people living in houses without air-conditioning. An athlete exercising in extreme heat can lose a quart or more of sweat in an hour.</p>
        <p>D4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>New Internet Technology  I.B.M. is announcing a new initiative today to support and exploit grid computing, which the company and many computer researchers say is the next evolutionary step in the development of the Internet. In the grid vision, individual computer users can amass the power of a supercomputer through networks.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Generic Prozac Set for Market  Barr Laboratories, a generic-drug maker in Pomona, N.Y., that battled Eli Lilly over patent rights to Prozac, said it expected to gain final F.D.A. approval to begin shipping a generic version of the antidepressant to pharmacies today. Lilly said it would appeal to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Seeking a Repeat Performance  Theodore J. Forstmann, the financier who revived Gulfstream Aerospace, will try to do the same for the ailing phone company McLeodUSA by investing an additional $275 million and calling in some of the Gulfstream makeover team.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Mixed Day for Stocks  The Nasdaq rose 2.03 percent while the S.&amp; P. 500 edged up 0.12 percent and the Dow slid 0.4 percent.</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mrs. Whitman stays the course; the fate of patients' rights; Bill Berkeley on ''Lumumba.''</p>
        <p>Column: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E9  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
