<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDD1231F930A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Spy Plane Crew Returns; Bush Toughens Criticism  With the crew of an American surveillance plane safely in Hawaii, President Bush and his national security aides criticized China's role in the midair collision with a Chinese jet. The crew faces two days of debriefing in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In his first serious foreign policy challenge, Mr. Bush ultimately took a conciliatory approach that required tamping down the more hawkish instincts of some of his advisers and military commanders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Spy Plane Crew Returns; Bush Toughens Criticism  With the crew of an American surveillance plane safely in Hawaii, President Bush and his national security aides criticized China's role in the midair collision with a Chinese jet. The crew faces two days of debriefing in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In his first serious foreign policy challenge, Mr. Bush ultimately took a conciliatory approach that required tamping down the more hawkish instincts of some of his advisers and military commanders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Extradited Russian Released  A panel of three Swiss judges decided to release Pavel P. Borodin after the case against him all but collapsed. The judges said that without cooperation from Russia, there was little likelihood of proving Mr. Borodin had pocketed millions of dollars in kickbacks from Swiss companies that renovated the Kremlin. Russia promptly paid the $2.9 million bail, clearing the way for his return to homeland.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Russian Relations Discussed  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and the Russian foreign minister, Igor S. Ivanov, outlined several fronts on which they hoped to work together and agreed that their leaders would have their first meeting by the end of July.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>The Day After Israeli Raid  Palestinian residents of the Khan Yunis refugee camp salvaged the remains of the rubble of at least 15 cinder-block houses destroyed by Israeli army bulldozers. The Israelis said these were buildings used by gunmen to shoot at the neighboring Jewish settlement of Neve Dekalim.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Convicted Terrorist Testifies  Pacifico Castrellón, a convicted terrorist who awaits his own retrial, testified against Lori Berenson, 31, of New York in a retrial that could sentence her as a terrorist collaborator to 20 years in a Peruvian jail.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-15</p>
        <p>Florida Plan Would Store Rain Runoff Underground  The state is nearing approval of a plan that would allow billions of gallons of rainwater to be stored underground to head off drinking-water shortages.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Protecting Medical Privacy  President Bush said rules to protect the privacy of medical records would take effect tomorrow. But he said the rules, issued by President Bill Clinton, could be revised to address concerns of the health care industry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Parity for the Disabled  The nation's largest nonprofit H.M.O. agreed to revamp its California health facilities and policies to ensure that people with disabilities have access to all health care.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Clampdown in Cincinnati  A strict curfew was imposed as officials tried to calm racial tensions after the fatal shooting of a black teenager by the police. ''Despite the best efforts of the good citizens of our city, the violence on our streets is uncontrolled and it runs rampant,'' Mayor Charlie Luken declared as he announced a state of emergency.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Viewing McVeigh Execution  Attorney General John Ashcroft said he hoped to help survivors and relatives of victims in the Oklahoma City federal building bombing ''close this chapter in their lives'' by letting them watch the May 16 execution of Timothy McVeigh via the country's first closed-circuit television broadcast of a federal death sentence.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Forest Chief Chosen  Dale N. Bosworth, a career forestry official, was named head of the Forest Service, a move that drew tentative praise from conservationists and timber industry spokesmen.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Greenhouse Gas Studies  Research teams concluded that a buildup of heat in the seas over the last 50 years was almost certainly caused by the greenhouse gases released by human activities.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Former First Lady Is Recast In a More Modest Context  One hundred days after Hillary Rodham Clinton arrived in the United States Senate, she is doing her best to be seen as just another freshman lawmaker. Mrs. Clinton and her advisers have set out to remake her image to suggest that the former first lady is not too big for her new job.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Redress for Man Wrongly Jailed  The State of New York will pay $3.25 million to settle a lawsuit filed on behalf of Kerry Sanders, 34, a mentally ill homeless man whose bungled identification by the authorities led to his mistaken two-year imprisonment, lawyers said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Pataki Picks Secretary of State  Gov. George E. Pataki named Randy A. Daniels secretary of state. If confirmed, Mr. Daniels, 49, would become the highest-ranking African-American in the administration.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Parents Plan Test Revolt  Parents and school officials in Scarsdale, N.Y., where test scores are among the nation's highest, are planning a revolt against state standardized tests, saying they have forced teachers to drop the programs that have made the schools excel.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-28; E29-40</p>
        <p>'Blast!' Prompts Union Talks  When ''Blast!'' opens on Tuesday, it may take its place in history as the first show partly produced by a medical-supply company. It will also be the only show on Broadway in which no one onstage is a member of any performers' union, but talks now under way may change that.</p>
        <p>E2</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Tax Delinquents Spared  The Internal Revenue Service has virtually stopped pursuing more than one million tax delinquents and curtailed other enforcement.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Egyptian Construction Fraud  A group of international construction companies defrauded the American government out of tens of millions of dollars earmarked for Egyptian water projects undertaken as part of the Camp David peace accords, according to United States officials and court documents.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Pessimism Deepens  Americans spent less at retail stores last month then they did in February, and in recent weeks they have turned even more pessimistic about the economy, reports suggested.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart and Sears, Roebuck reported slow sales and warned that quarterly profits would fall below Wall Street's expectations.</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Markets Brighten  With the markets closed for Good Friday, the Nasdaq ended the week up 14 percent and the Dow Jones industrial average was up 3.43 percent for the week.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Witnesses to an execution; a city workers' contract; Steven R. Weisman on the art of apologizing.</p>
        <p>Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E39  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E28  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
