<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DF133FF932A05750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Serbian Police Raid Ex-President's Residence  Serbian special forces stormed the villa of former President Slobodan Milosevic before dawn today, beginning a legal process that could finally imprison the man whose 13-year reign over Yugoslavia brought war, destruction and poverty to his people. The raid followed a night of conflicting reports that he had been arrested on corruption charges. Mr. Milosevic is also wanted on international war crimes charges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>China Seizes Another Scholar  Security agents detained Li Shaomin, a Chinese-born American citizen, as he crossed the border last month from Hong Kong, where he works as a business professor and consultant, the American Embassy said. It was the latest in a series of detentions that are causing friction between Beijing and Washington.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Serbian Police Raid Ex-President's Residence  Serbian special forces stormed the villa of former President Slobodan Milosevic before dawn today, beginning a legal process that could finally imprison the man whose 13-year reign over Yugoslavia brought war, destruction and poverty to his people. The raid followed a night of conflicting reports that he had been arrested on corruption charges. Mr. Milosevic is also wanted on international war crimes charges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>China Seizes Another Scholar  Security agents detained Li Shaomin, a Chinese-born American citizen, as he crossed the border last month from Hong Kong, where he works as a business professor and consultant, the American Embassy said. It was the latest in a series of detentions that are causing friction between Beijing and Washington.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Israeli Arabs Hold Rallies  Israeli officials tensed as the first major pro-Palestinian rallies of Israeli Arabs since October took place throughout Israel. But with the Israeli police under strict orders to remain on the outskirts of the villages, the demonstrations ended peacefully.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Prices of AIDS Drugs Are Cut  The drug giant Merck agreed to cut the price of two AIDS medicines in Brazil, bowing to pressure from the government, which was threatening to develop generic copies of one of them. The government quickly turned up the pressure on another drug company, Hoffman-La Roche.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>European Opening to Korea  The European Commission said steps it was taking toward establishing diplomatic relations with North Korea and a planned visit by a European Union delegation had the blessing of the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Right-Wing Action in Colombia  A right-wing paramilitary group seized 30 villagers accused of collaborating with leftist guerrillas, Gov. Parmenio Cuéllar of Nariño province said. The villagers were thought to have been killed. The incident was cast by Mr. Cuéllar and human rights officials as a byproduct of the American-backed fumigation of coca fields nearby.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-13</p>
        <p>In Divesting, Bush Aides Find Bear Market Costly  A falling stock market is spelling trouble for a number of wealthy Bush administration officials who are selling their multimillion-dollar investment portfolios -- and taking some losses in the process -- to comply with government ethics rules.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Energy-Efficiency Rules Review  The Energy Department is reviewing energy-efficiency standards issued in the last weeks of the Clinton administration that would require new clothes washers, water heaters and whole-house air conditioners to use less electricity and natural gas, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Discord on Climate Policy  An international conference in Montreal ended in disagreement among environment ministers after the United States declined to go along with a Latin American-backed call for industrialized countries to reduce emissions of the heat-trapping gases blamed for global warming.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Virus Not Found in Livestock  Agriculture Department officials said that while tests of four North Carolina pigs suspected of carrying foot-and-mouth disease had proved negative, they would accelerate the training of dogs used to sniff out suspect meat at ports of entry.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Brisket Shortage for Passover  A fire in a kosher processing plant in Kansas last December, along with national shortages caused by overseas cattle disease, has severely reduced the supply of many cuts of kosher beef, just in time for the heaviest kosher-food buying season.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Seeking Answers in Aspen Crash  Federal investigators said they did not know why a chartered twin-engine jet from California on Thursday missed the runway at Aspen, Colo., killing all 18 people aboard.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8-9</p>
        <p>John Lewis  The pianist, the mastermind of one of the most famous ensembles in jazz, the Modern Jazz Quartet, was 80.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Mayor Circulating List Of Decency Panel Choices  Mayor Giuliani has developed a list of about 20 people for his panel to review art in publicly financed museums; the names include members of his administration, friendly clerics and his divorce lawyer, Raoul Felder.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Plan B for Ailing Schools  Chancellor Harold O. Levy said that if, as it appeared, Edison Schools did not gain parental support to take over five poorly performing schools, he would close two and reopen them with different students and teachers and try to turn around the other three.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>New Approach to Heart Disease  Scientists reported progress in using stem cells from bone marrow to repair heart tissue in animals, with human testing a year or more away.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Anesthesia Drug Recalled  Raplon, which aids doctors in inserting breathing tubes, is being taken off the market because five patients, two of them children, died while the drug was being administered.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>New Inquiry at Yale Hospital  Federal investigators in Connecticut, Florida and California are looking into new accusations of fraud against Yale-New Haven Hospital. Three months ago, the hospital was fined $1.4 million for accepting improper Medicaid payments in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Shortcomings at Meat Markets  Federal officials said they had uncovered serious flaws in the way safety checks were made at supermarkets and other meat distributors in the New York region.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B11-20</p>
        <p>Saving Art From Afghanistan  The ruling Taliban's recent destruction of religious images prompted Unesco and others to depart from a long-held policy on keeping artifacts in their historical settings.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Bloodied Markets End Quarter  The Nasdaq gained 19.69 points, or 1.1 percent, to 1,840.26, but ended the quarter down 25.5 percent. The Dow rose 79.72 points, to 9,878.78, but was off 8.4 percent for the quarter. The S.&amp; P. 500 advanced 12.38 points, to 1,160.33, but finished the quarter 12.1 percent below its start.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Beef Packer Sues Tyson  IBP sued Tyson Foods for dropping plans to acquire it for $3.2 billion, and wants Tyson to complete the deal.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Narrow Wireless Spectrum  Three government studies cast doubt on a plan by President Bill Clinton to find more space on already congested airwaves, an effort considered essential to the future of a new generation of hand-held wireless devices.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Gooden Calling It Quits  Dwight Gooden, the Yankee pitcher who won the Cy Young Award as a Met in 1985 at age 20, is retiring.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>N.C.A.A. Tournament  Norte Dame beat Connecticut to set up an all-Indiana women's Championship game with Purdue.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Effective nuclear disarmament; defending abortion rights; violence on South African farms; Mr. Verniero's faulty memory.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B18  Crossword</p>
        <p>B18  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B20  Weather</p>
        <p>B8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
