<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Must Join Fight Against Terror, Bush Tells U.N.</title>
    <meta content="11PREX$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/11/international/11PREX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1342108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DC1238F932A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Must Join Fight Against Terror, Bush Tells U.N.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All Must Join Fight Against Terror, Bush Tells U.N.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Nov. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush, in blunt, direct speech at UN, says every member country is potential target and has binding responsibility to fight terrorism; says time for offering condolences to US for Sept 11 attacks has passed and that each nation must crack down on terrorist financing within its borders, share intelligence information and coordinate law enforcement; annnounces aid to Pakistan worth more than $1 billion, in exchange for support of war in Afghanistan; Gen Pervez Musharraf responds at joint news conference, referring to new era in relationship; photos; Bush speech also cites Osama bin Laden's reference to Sec Gen Kofi Annan as 'criminal,' warning that terrorist leader would use any kind of weapons, cannot be appeased and threatens 'civilization we share' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush tried to cast the war against Osama bin Laden and the Taliban in the broadest global context today as he told the United Nations that every member country was a potential target of terrorism and that responsibility for fighting it was ''binding on every nation with a place in this chamber.''</p>
        <p>In a blunt, direct speech that was his first to the General Assembly, Mr. Bush said that the time for offering only condolences to the United States for the Sept. 11 attacks had passed. He said that each member nation now had a duty to crack down on terrorist financing within its borders and the responsibility to share intelligence information and coordinate law enforcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first speech to the General Assembly, President Bush said that responsibility for fighting terrorism is "binding on every nation with a place in this chamber."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush tried to cast the war against Osama bin Laden and the Taliban in the broadest global context today as he told the United Nations that every member country was a potential target of terrorism and that responsibility for fighting it was ''binding on every nation with a place in this chamber.''</p>
        <p>In a blunt, direct speech that was his first to the General Assembly, Mr. Bush said that the time for offering only condolences to the United States for the Sept. 11 attacks had passed. He said that each member nation now had a duty to crack down on terrorist financing within its borders and the responsibility to share intelligence information and coordinate law enforcement.</p>
        <p>''Every nation has a stake in this cause,'' Mr. Bush said. ''As we meet, the terrorists are planning more murder, perhaps in my country or perhaps in yours.''</p>
        <p>To add critical support to his words, Mr. Bush announced tonight that the United States was providing an aid package worth more than $1 billion to Pakistan in exchange for Pakistan's support of the war in Afghanistan. But it was unclear whether that aid included $500 million already announced by Secretary of State Colin L. Powell in Islamabad in October, and Bush administration officials were unable last night to provide details.</p>
        <p>Gen. Pervez Musharraf, the military president of Pakistan, responded at a joint news conference with Mr. Bush at the Waldorf-Astoria that he saw the ''dawn of a new era of a relationship between Pakistan and the United States.'' Administration officials said that the two leaders did not discuss in meetings today the release of American F-16 fighters sold to Pakistan in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>For the first time, Mr. Bush directly evoked Mr. bin Laden's own words to warn and compel the United Nations to act. Referring to a videotape of Mr. bin Laden broadcast on the Jazeera television network last weekend, Mr. Bush said that ''they called our secretary general a criminal and condemned all Arab nations here as traitors to Islam.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush warned that Mr. bin Laden and his terrorist network would use chemical, biological and nuclear weapons as soon as they were able to do so.</p>
        <p>''No hint of conscience would prevent it,'' Mr. Bush said. ''This threat cannot be ignored. This threat cannot be appeased. Civilization itself, the civilization we share, is threatened.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also said more emphatically than he ever has before that  there should be a Palestinian state, and for the first time referred to that state with the name the Arabs use themselves. ''We are working toward the day when two states --  Israel and Palestine -- live peacefully together within secure and recognized borders,'' Mr. Bush said. The use of ''Palestine'' seemed intended to appeal to an Islamic public that has grown uneasy and impatient with the war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The president's speech opened two days of intense diplomacy to enlist more support for his war against terrorism. Mr. Bush was among more than 40 world leaders planning to address the General Assembly's annual general debate, which was delayed for the first time in the organization's 56-year history because of the September attacks.</p>
        <p>Despite its frankness, much of Mr. Bush's speech was delivered with a plain-spoken eloquence that avoided any references to Mr. bin Laden as ''the evil one,'' a favorite phrase of the president when he speaks to American audiences.</p>
        <p>''A few miles from here, many thousands still lie in a tomb of rubble,'' Mr. Bush said, referring to the site of the World Trade Center's collapse in Lower Manhattan. Mr. Bush said that he and United Nations officials would visit the site on Sunday where the names of every nation and region that lost citizens -- more than 80 at last count -- would be recited.</p>
        <p>''If we were to read the names of every person who died, it would take more than three hours,'' Mr. Bush said. The United States, he added, will never forget Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who as a presidential candidate disdained the ''nation building'' of the Clinton administration, again outlined his administration's plans for reconstructing a post-Taliban Afghanistan. ''The United States will work closely with the United Nations and development banks to reconstruct Afghanistan,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>The address was a dramatic change from the kind that Mr. Bush had been expected to give had the United Nations not postponed its General Assembly meeting in late September because of the terrorist attacks. Before Sept. 11, diplomats said Mr. Bush would have been the unilateralist on the defensive, a president who had walked away from the Kyoto accord on global warming and who had threatened to withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's address seemed to affirm a new faith in multilateralism. Nonetheless, the speech was not interrupted by applause. Neither was the speech of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani at the United Nations in October.</p>
        <p>The reaction to Mr. Bush's speech ranged from positive to restrained. Jack Straw, the British foreign minister, called it a ''very tough, positive speech with a very clear message,'' but a delegate from Zambia, Lazarous Kapambwe, said he would have liked the president to address problems in addition to terrorism. ''The world is moving on,'' Mr. Kapambwe said. ''There are deaths that are occurring from diseases, from H.I.V., from poverty.''</p>
        <p>The Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, who attended a United Nations lunch with Mr. Bush and other world leaders, called the speech ''important, positive and constructive.'' Last week the White House said Mr. Bush had no plans to meet with Mr. Arafat in New York.</p>
        <p>The speech was delivered in an atmosphere of extraordinary security, taken because Mr. bin Laden had singled out the United Nations and various world leaders in a videotaped message broadcast last weekend by the Arab language television network Al Jazeera. In that message, Mr. bin Laden called Secretary General Kofi Annan a ''criminal'' and said that ''the United Nations is nothing but a tool of crime.'' Intelligence analysts said that the United Nations was a target, not only in New York but also throughout the world.</p>
        <p>White House officials promoted the address as a ''fleshing out'' of what they call the Bush doctrine --  the assertion first made in a speech by Mr. Bush on Sept. 21 to a joint session of Congress in which he said that nations that harbored terrorists were just as guilty as the terrorists themselves. As in that speech, Mr. Bush did not name names. But the United States has previously identified a number of nations it says give safe haven to terrorists, including Iraq, Syria and Somalia.</p>
        <p>In his address today to the General Assembly, General Musharraf assured the gathering that his country's nuclear arsenal was in good care.</p>
        <p>''Let me assure you all that our strategic assets are well guarded and in safe hands,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Asked at the news conference with Mr. Bush about Mr. bin Laden's claim that he possesses nuclear and chemical weapons, General Musharraf said he doubted it.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
