<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crew of Listing Bush Ship Draws Republican Scowls</title>
    <meta content="Y02BUS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/02/politics/02BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DE1039F931A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crew of Listing Bush Ship Draws Republican Scowls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE and FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many prominent Republicans who once marveled at the Bush administration's agility say the president's lieutenants are increasingly stumbling in ways that are not merely embarrassing but also perilous to Mr. Bush's political standing.</p>
        <p>Sounding notes of disappointment and concern, these Republicans, who number more than a dozen and include strategists usually sympathetic to the administration as well as several lawmakers, say that the White House political compass has often seemed askew over the last three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many prominent Republicans who once marveled at the Bush administration's agility say the president's lieutenants are increasingly stumbling in ways that are not merely embarrassing but also perilous to Mr. Bush's political standing.</p>
        <p>Sounding notes of disappointment and concern, these Republicans, who number more than a dozen and include strategists usually sympathetic to the administration as well as several lawmakers, say that the White House political compass has often seemed askew over the last three months.</p>
        <p>They point to the arguably clumsy way the administration handled the global warming issue and the initial rollout of its energy plan, the defection of Senator James M. Jeffords of Vermont from the Republican Party and the meeting of a senior administration official with executives from a company in which he owned more than $100,000 worth of stock. And they note that these and other episodes have at times made the administration seem alternately arrogant, sloppy, unethical and out of touch.</p>
        <p>White House officials assert that any mistakes are eclipsed by accomplishments that defied formidable obstacles, the low expectations for Mr. Bush and the tightness of the 2000 election. The president quickly passed his sweeping tax cut and is on the verge of achieving some of his objectives for education.</p>
        <p>But these officials also acknowledge the recently critical reviews of the administration in the press as well as Mr. Bush's slip in popularity in some polls.</p>
        <p>''We're not unconcerned,'' said Mary Matalin, Vice President Dick Cheney's chief political aide. ''We're not so inflexible or blind that we're like Stepford wives and husbands marching like lemmings over a cliff. What we're doing now is recalibrating.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, officials are taking steps to address concerns large and small. At a meeting last week with top aides to Republican House members from Florida, administration officials acknowledged the complaints of some members that they were not properly included on Mr. Bush's recent trip to the Everglades. The House aides were asked to be patient with the relatively new White House staff and told that steps were being taken to better coordinate Mr. Bush's out-of-town trips.</p>
        <p>The White House is also spearheading a program to work closely with the 40 or so most vulnerable House incumbents to help them raise money and hone their messages before the midterm elections. On a policy level, White House officials have in recent days begun convening a daily meeting to plot strategy to sell their energy plan.</p>
        <p>And in the wake of Mr. Jeffords's defection, White House officials have embarked on a drive to work more closely with the centrist Republicans most likely to break party ranks.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, the moderates on the Republican side needed more outreach, and we've tried to engage that,'' said Nicholas E. Calio, the chief White House legislative liaison.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Calio has had breakfast three times with Senator Olympia J. Snowe, Republican of  Maine, who also received phone calls early this week from President Bush and from his chief of staff, Andrew H. Card Jr. In addition, Ms. Snowe had dinner on Monday night with Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief political aide, in a group that also included Senators Arlen Specter, Republican of Pennsylvania, and Susan Collins, Republican of Maine.</p>
        <p>''They have learned that there has to be more contact and more listening,'' Mr. Specter said.</p>
        <p>Republicans' concerns about the administration's nimbleness touch on everything from the handling of crucial policy like stem-cell research and the planned halting of bombing runs on the Puerto Rican island of Vieques to matters of practical politics, like the sometimes awkward staging of Mr. Bush's appearances and the limited degree to which the president is helping Republican Congressional candidates raise money.</p>
        <p>Republicans also complained that on his first presidential trip to California, Mr. Bush stood idly as Gov. Gray Davis, a Democrat, seized the upper hand in talking about the state's energy woes.</p>
        <p>Some Republicans attribute any perceived dimming of the new administration's glow to an inescapable period of adjustment and an inevitable learning curve.</p>
        <p>''I think the transition from campaigning to governing is never easy and sometimes awkward,'' said Kenneth M. Duberstein, who was chief of staff to President Ronald Reagan. ''The initial months of every White House are almost like the early days of a baby, and everyone's saying, 'Isn't he cute? Isn't he wonderful?'</p>
        <p>''And then, before long, the baby grows up to be a gawky adolescent, and they say, 'Boy, he's not well coordinated. God, he's a bit awkward!' And I think that's the stage the Bush administration is going through right now. They will quickly move from adolescent to grown-up and be fully matured and at the top of their game.''</p>
        <p>Many Republicans are less charitable, and they express fear that Mr. Bush's political troubles have already spilled over to the party itself, potentially endangering candidates in next year's midterm elections.</p>
        <p>They are pointing fingers mostly at Mr. Rove, who is generally praised as the mastermind of Mr. Bush's political rise. Republicans close to the administration say that he is such a transparently influential figure -- and thus such a reliable magnet for controversy -- that he needs to monitor his actions more carefully and rein in his broad portfolio.</p>
        <p>These Republicans say that Mr. Rove's most obvious lapse of judgment and vigilance was a decision to meet three months ago with executives of Intel, a company in which he owned stock. Although he said he had not weighed in on the federal approval the executives were seeking for a corporate merger, he drew intense criticism for creating at least an appearance of impropriety.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure if Karl had to do it again he'd do it differently,'' said Representative Thomas M. Davis III of Virginia, who is chairman of the National Republican Congressional Committee. ''It ought to be a wake-up call that the Washington rules are much different than what you have anywhere else. Karl's got to understand that he's a target. If people can't get to Bush they're going to get to Karl. These are lessons you learn the hard way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove acknowledged shortcomings. ''Are there things that I think I could have done a better job on? You betcha,'' he said. ''I'm not going to get into a recitation of my many and manifold sins.''</p>
        <p>Responding to Mr. Davis's comments about him, Mr. Rove said: ''I appreciate his insights. He's a good friend and gives me good advice.''</p>
        <p>A frequent complaint among Republicans is that Mr. Rove has overextended himself, and insufficiently concealed his tracks, so that many decisions coming from the White House have an overly political taint. That taint is especially problematic because of the way Mr. Bush campaigned, with a constant mantra that his White House would be governed by principles in a way that President Bill Clinton's, in his view, was not.</p>
        <p>Although some senior administration officials deny it, Mr. Rove appears to be front and center in the process by which the White House will decide whether to allow federal financing of research on stem cells  from human embryos. A decision to permit the research would outrage many Catholics and religious conservatives, constituencies on which Mr. Rove keeps a watchful eye.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove was also a player at recent meetings about the future of Navy bombing tests in Vieques, and Senator James M. Inhofe, an Oklahoma Republican, accused him of single-handedly making the decision to halt the bombing by 2003 in order to win the favor of Hispanic voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inhofe, who has called the island training vital to the military, said that he had been active on the Vieques matter for years but that Mr. Rove had cut him out of the deliberations. He said he had insisted that Mr. Rove be pulled out of a meeting on the issue and that they had had a telephone conversation that was ''a little contentious.''</p>
        <p>''He wasn't responsive -- he didn't hear what I had to say,'' Mr. Inhofe said. ''It was Karl Rove who made the decision. It was politically motivated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove, told of Mr. Inhofe's comments, denied any political motivations, saying, ''I respectfully disagree with the senator.''</p>
        <p>Despite all the heat Mr. Rove has drawn, Republicans close to the administration say that his standing in the White House is undiminished. ''He has lost no luster with the boss,'' said Representative Rob Portman, an Ohio Republican.</p>
        <p>In any case, many Republicans' frustrations -- and complaints -- extend beyond and above Mr. Rove, to the president himself. Republican lawmakers say that Mr. Bush is at times not as focused on elections as they would like.</p>
        <p>''Bush is not a fund-raiser like Clinton was,'' Mr. Davis said, adding that the president's advisers ''made it very clear his job wasn't the fund-raiser in chief. But they are making it up in other ways.''</p>
        <p>White House officials seem to be mounting an aggressive campaign to mend any tattered relations in the Senate, where Mr. Jeffords's defection threw the balance of power to Democrats, raised questions about Mr. Calio's legislative operation and unearthed complaints from some Senate aides that Mr. Calio simply told lawmakers what the White House wanted rather than creating a dialogue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Calio said: ''Is it our job to present the president's position on Capitol Hill? Yes, and, frankly, we do it unabashedly. What people don't realize is that we come back to the White House and present their position -- unadorned -- too.''</p>
        <p>Even so, many Republicans see in the White House signs of the arrogance of newly acquired power, a state of mind to which these Republicans attribute the lion's share of administration mistakes.</p>
        <p>These Republicans, for example, questioned how Ms. Matalin could not have foreseen the negative way Mr. Cheney's comment about conservation as a ''personal virtue'' might be interpreted and why she allowed him to hold a reception for big Republican donors at the vice president's residence. The press predictably flashed back to the Clinton administration and the Lincoln Bedroom. Ms. Matalin said she did not have complete control over that event but that, in regard to both criticisms, ''It is my responsibility to make better judgments.''</p>
        <p>According to many Republicans, several White House officials could be making better judgments, even on matters as basic and essential as the style of Mr. Bush's public appearances, which do not cast him as suitably presidential in some Republicans' eyes. Too often, a few of them said, he comes across as small, tentative or insufficiently impassioned.</p>
        <p>Sig Rogich, an image consultant who worked in the White House for Mr. Bush's father, said the president and his advisers needed time.</p>
        <p>''He's young and he looks young,'' Mr. Rogich said. ''When he was elected governor of Texas, they talked about the same kinds of things. They talked about stature. He turned out to be one of the most popular governors in Texas history. There will be an evolution. It happens in every White House.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
