<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Closed Mind</title>
    <meta content="16LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/16/opinion/16LEWI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Abroad at Home"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE1D81431F935A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Closed Mind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Closed Mind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column on how European leaders are viewing Pres Bush; says NATO allies see man of strong opinions stubbornly held, in defiance of reason as most Europeans would define it, and they also see man of charm, easy in human relations and adept politically, but with a certitude not earned by experience or accomplishment; says European politicians have long cozied up to American presidents, but European military experts, environmentalists and many ordinary citizens are not so polite; says they are frightened of George Bush (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What President Bush has been telling European leaders this week can be readily summed up: I am not going to do anything about global warming because it needs more scientific study. But I am going to act urgently to develop a missile defense system although none have any proven scientific basis and every test so far has failed.</p>
        <p>In that odd couple of messages the allies got a fair introduction to the veritable George W. Bush: a man of strong opinions stubbornly held, in defiance of reason as most Europeans would define it. They also saw a man of charm, easy in human relations and adept politically, but with a certitude not earned by experience or accomplishment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A striking example President Bush's rigidity, verging on arrogance, is his attitude on the environment he expressed to European leaders this week</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What President Bush has been telling European leaders this week can be readily summed up: I am not going to do anything about global warming because it needs more scientific study. But I am going to act urgently to develop a missile defense system although none have any proven scientific basis and every test so far has failed.</p>
        <p>In that odd couple of messages the allies got a fair introduction to the veritable George W. Bush: a man of strong opinions stubbornly held, in defiance of reason as most Europeans would define it. They also saw a man of charm, easy in human relations and adept politically, but with a certitude not earned by experience or accomplishment.</p>
        <p>''I hope the notion of a unilateral approach died in some people's minds here today,'' Mr. Bush said after talking with NATO leaders about his missile defense project. ''Unilateralists don't come around the table to listen to others and to share opinion.''</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Bush listened -- but only with the ear, not with a mind open to other ideas. No one sitting around that NATO table could have had any illusion of being able to persuade him that it is folly to abandon the most important barrier against a renewed nuclear arms race, the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty, so he can pursue the will-o'-the-wisp of missile defense.</p>
        <p>There is a rigidity in George W. Bush, verging on arrogance, that Americans have seen on a number of issues in his first five months as president. A striking example is his attitude on the environment.</p>
        <p>He began by having his environment administrator, Christie Whitman -- to her evident embarrassment -- withdraw a Clinton administration rule limiting the amount of arsenic in drinking water. Then his secretary of agriculture, Ann M. Veneman, suspended a regulation banning roads in many roadless areas of our national forests.</p>
        <p>Those and other moves brought an outcry from Americans who want to protect our natural surroundings -- and protect themselves from dangerous substances. Many of those who worried were in the suburban districts that voted for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The president reacted to the political problem by putting on a show of concern for the environment. He traveled to the Everglades. He posed amid Sequoia trees in California.</p>
        <p>But his real position on the environment has not changed at all. In the Sequoia appearance he said the federal government must show more deference to states and private groups in conservation efforts -- which is code for scuttling federal enforcement.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks there have been other anti-environment moves. The Army Corps of Engineers proposed relaxing rules against the destruction of wetlands. The Forest Service issued draft regulations that would eliminate the priority for ecological sustainability in forest use plans.</p>
        <p>The administration announced that it would, after all, support the Clinton plan for roadless forest areas. But it quietly made a crucial concession in court to timber and other interests that had sued against the plan: It conceded that they would suffer irreparable injury from it.</p>
        <p>In short, the emollient Bush words about loving the environment did not match the reality of the administration's destructive actions. Mr. Bush's position is still based on a simple proposition: What is good for drillers and developers is good for the country. That same fixed preference for business now over the health of future generations underlay his denunciation of the Kyoto Protocol on global warming.</p>
        <p>A single proposition also underlies Mr. Bush's determination to destroy the ABM treaty. He does not believe in treaties limiting weapons of mass destruction, even though they have manifestly worked well, because they limit our freedom of action -- as if somehow mutual security diminished American manhood. .</p>
        <p>That is the president the European leaders met. Most, though disagreeing, treated him deferentially. For the last 50 years, European politicians have always cozied up to American presidents. They simply feel too dependent for their security on the dominant member of the alliance.</p>
        <p>But European military experts, environmentalists and many ordinary citizens are not so polite. They are frightened of George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>Abroad at Home</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
