<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Going Empty-Handed to Meeting on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="Y29WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/29/science/29WARM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010331T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <location class="online_producer">The United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mexico</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Argentina</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Post Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EEDA173FF93AA15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Going Empty-Handed to Meeting on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Global warming will be main issue at coming meeting of Western Hemisphere's environment ministers; United States, which will be represented by Christie Whitman, adminstrator of Environmental Protection Agency, will be in position of having no policy on issue; Pres Bush has said he opposes Kyoto Protocol and would not submit it for Senate ratification; Whitman, who was overruled by White House in matter of power plant emissions of carbon dioxide, has reportedly tried in vain to obtain clear instructions from White House about how to answer questions from US allies concerned about that policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With an international meeting of environment officials scheduled to begin on Thursday, the United States will be in the position of having no policy on global warming, which will be the main issue at the gathering.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration reconfirmed today that it opposed the Kyoto Protocol, the international treaty to fight global warming, and would not submit it for Senate ratification.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With an international meeting of environment officials scheduled to begin on Thursday, the United States will be in the position of having no policy on global warming, which will be the main issue at the gathering.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration reconfirmed today that it opposed the Kyoto Protocol, the international treaty to fight global warming, and would not submit it for Senate ratification.</p>
        <p>''The president has been unequivocal,'' the White House spokesman, Ari Fleischer, said. ''He does not support the Kyoto treaty. It is not in the United States' economic best interest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleischer, who was asked at a White House briefing to clarify the administration's stance, said the administration was developing other strategies to deal with change in the world's climate.</p>
        <p>The meeting of the Western Hemisphere's environment ministers will be the first such gathering since the Bush administration announced earlier this month that it would not seek to regulate power plants' emissions of carbon dioxide, a decision that amounted to effective abandonment of the Kyoto accord.</p>
        <p>''We're going into the lion's den unarmed,'' said a senior administration official who expressed deep frustration that a new policy had not yet been formulated.</p>
        <p>The American delegate to Thursday's meeting will be Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, who had advised against the decision on power plant emissions but was overruled by the White House. At a news conference on Tuesday, Mrs. Whitman repeated the White House's position that it had ''no interest'' in carrying out the treaty negotiated in 1997 in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
        <p>Administration officials sympathetic to Ms. Whitman's position said she had tried in vain to obtain clear instructions about how to answer questions from United States allies concerned about the carbon dioxide policy. The administration's new stance reverses a campaign pledge made by President Bush and was at odds with the position that Ms. Whitman outlined to other environment ministers just four weeks ago at an international conference on global warming in Italy.</p>
        <p>''She's essentially not been given anything to say,'' one senior official said of the two-day meeting in Montreal, adding that the only thing Ms. Whitman would be able to state authoritatively about the administration's position on global warming was that it was the subject of a cabinet-level review.</p>
        <p>Several foreign leaders, including the German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, have been outspoken in their criticism of the administration for its opposition to the Kyoto accord. Mr. Schröder is to meet with President Bush at the White House on Thursday, and global warming is expected to be high on their agenda.</p>
        <p>A senior official who defended the White House position said foreign governments should not be surprised either by Mr. Bush's opposition to the Kyoto accord, which he has criticized since early in the presidential campaign, or by the lack of a policy so early in a new administration.</p>
        <p>''Diplomatically, we're hearing a lot of criticism from a lot of countries, and I suppose at every meeting we go to we'll hear more,'' said the official, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''At the same time, it's been no secret what the president's position on the treaty has been.''</p>
        <p>The murmurs of dissent within the administration reflected a view attributed to Ms. Whitman that the White House had been unwise to declare its opposition to the Kyoto pact before it could point to an alternative.</p>
        <p>In a memorandum to Mr. Bush earlier this month, before the decision on carbon dioxide emissions, Ms. Whitman warned that most other industrialized nations regarded the Kyoto accord as ''the only game in town.''</p>
        <p>''There's a real fear in the international community that if the U.S. is not willing to discuss the issue within the framework of Kyoto, the whole thing will fall apart,'' Ms. Whitman wrote in the memorandum, whose contents were first reported in The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>''Mr. President, this is a credibility issue (global warming) for the U.S. in the international community,'' she wrote. ''It is also an issue that is resonating here at home. We need to appear engaged and shift the discussion from the focus on the K-word to action, but we have to build some bonafides first.''</p>
        <p>The Kyoto accord would require the United States and other industrialized countries to reduce emissions of heat-trapping gases by an average of 5.2 percent by 2012 compared with  their 1990 levels. The United States and more than 100 other countries signed the treaty, but no industrial country has yet ratified it. An effort by the Clinton administration to win its ratification by the Senate was defeated 95 to 0.</p>
        <p>In the United States, most industry representatives have strongly opposed the accord, warning that it would impose enormous costs on the American economy.</p>
        <p>An official of the Global Climate Coalition, which reflects industry views, said today that the Bush administration had a right to sever any association with the Kyoto treaty's specific guidelines for emissions reductions.</p>
        <p>''There's a fundamentally more effective way of dealing with climate change, which is one based on technological development, and that's the one we support,'' the official, Glenn Kelly, said.</p>
        <p>But a former Clinton administration official, David B. Sandalow, who helped to negotiate the 1997 accord, said the stance would undercut American credibility.</p>
        <p>''It's a textbook case of unilateral diplomacy, which rarely works and always brings resentment,'' Mr. Sandalow said.</p>
        <p>An environmental group, Friends of the Earth, called the American stance ''environmental isolationism.''</p>
        <p>The meeting of environment ministers that begins in Montreal on Thursday will include representatives of Canada, Mexico, Brazil, Argentina and other countries from the Western Hemisphere in advance of a meeting of heads of state in May that will be known as the Summit of the Americas.</p>
        <p>In terms of global warming, a  more important gathering will take place in July, when heads of state have been invited to Bonn under the auspices of the United Nations Framework Convention on Global Warming, which President George Bush signed in 1992. That meeting had initially been scheduled for May, but was postponed at the request of the current administration.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 31, 2001, Saturday  An article on Thursday about the international treaty on global warming referred incorrectly to a 1997 Senate vote of 95 to 0. The vote registered opposition to some provisions. It was not a rejection of the treaty, which has never been submitted for ratification.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 31, 2001, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about the international treaty on global warming referred incorrectly to a 1997 Senate vote of 95 to 0. The vote registered opposition to some provisions. It was not a rejection of the treaty, which has never been submitted for ratification.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
