<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton at Yale: Optimistic on Crisis, But Work Is Ahead</title>
    <meta content="14CLIN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/14/nyregion/14CTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1333631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Connecticut"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D7173FF937A25753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="4350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton at Yale: Optimistic on Crisis, But Work Is Ahead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clinton at Yale: Optimistic on Crisis, But Work Is Ahead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpt from speech by former Pres Clinton, wrapping up Yale University's yearlong 300th birthday celebration, on globalization and terrorism crisis; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FORMER President Bill Clinton wrapped up Yale University's yearlong 300th birthday celebration with a speech on globalization and the current crisis to about 8,000 people on campus on Oct. 6. Following is a portion of that speech as recorded by Yale.</p>
        <p>I was fortunate enough to be here at Yale Law School with a phenomenal number of outstanding men and woman who were my fellow students. One of them did become the United States senator from New York. Senator Clinton went to Harvard. Meeting Hillary was the best thing that happened to me at Yale, and maybe the only thing that really stuck over all of these 30 years. I understand there was some discussion here in the Yale community about whether this tercentennial should go forward in the aftermath of the awful events of the Sept. 11. I thank you for going forward. It is what President Bush asked us to do when he asked us get on with our lives, and it is particularly important at this time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Excerpts from former President Bill Clinton's speech wrapping up Yale University's yearlong 300th birthday celebration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FORMER President Bill Clinton wrapped up Yale University's yearlong 300th birthday celebration with a speech on globalization and the current crisis to about 8,000 people on campus on Oct. 6. Following is a portion of that speech as recorded by Yale.</p>
        <p>I was fortunate enough to be here at Yale Law School with a phenomenal number of outstanding men and woman who were my fellow students. One of them did become the United States senator from New York. Senator Clinton went to Harvard. Meeting Hillary was the best thing that happened to me at Yale, and maybe the only thing that really stuck over all of these 30 years. I understand there was some discussion here in the Yale community about whether this tercentennial should go forward in the aftermath of the awful events of the Sept. 11. I thank you for going forward. It is what President Bush asked us to do when he asked us get on with our lives, and it is particularly important at this time.</p>
        <p>Marking 300 years of learning at any time would be a significant event. But marking it at this time with a commitment to be a truly global university is obviously profoundly important. For 300 years, before the Declaration of Independence, Yale has taught young people the wisdom of the past, the analysis of the present and the importance of looking to the future. Yale has asked hard questions and looked for honest answers. That is what I found here years ago, and that is what I see when I look out on this vast array of faces today.</p>
        <p>America is full of hard questions now. And I have spent a great deal of the last three weeks in Manhattan, visiting the crisis center, visiting ground zero, visiting fire stations and police headquarters, going to three schools, two of them double schools because the children were blown out of their schools by the events of Sept. 11. And I have found so many questions. Hillary and I went to an elementary school in lower Manhattan, where 9- and 10-year-old students asked me these questions: Why do they hate us so much anyway? How did that guy get all those people to commit suicide? I never thought I would hear a 9-year-old ask a question like that.</p>
        <p>I have gotten calls from women friends of Hillary's and mine who are the mothers of young children from all over America with a simple question. 'Bill, is it going to be all right? Tell me it is going to be all right.' Well, first of all, it is going to be all right. I can tell you that.</p>
        <p>Terrorism, the killing of innocent people for political or religious or economic reasons, is as old as organized combat. It has gone on a very long time. If we searchingly look through history honestly, we find it in uncomfortable places. In the crusade in which the European Christians seized Jerusalem, they slaughtered 300 Jews and killed every mother and child on the Temple Mount who was Muslim. But no campaign of terror standing on its own without organized military combat has ever succeeded in all of human history.  Indeed, it is not the purpose of terror to succeed militarily. It is the purpose of terror to terrify, and I would guess a lot of young people in this audience today who have never lived through such a difficult crisis were understandably terrified. And what is sought from the terror is the people who are afraid.</p>
        <p>First of all, in a vast and diverse country like ours, you see we have got people here from just about every country, every racial and ethnic group and every religious heritage. What is sought is, first of all, to make us afraid of each other. And secondly, to make us afraid of the future. We are afraid to plan; afraid to invest; afraid to trust, that is what they seek. Therefore, terrorism cannot prevail unless we cooperate. It is not a military strategy, it is a psychological and human one. We have to give the people that attacked us permission to win. I do not believe we are about to grant them that permission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bin Laden and his allies misjudge America. They think we are fundamentally a weak, greedy, selfish, materialistic people. They think we are weakened by a lack of international religion and imposed social order. But, they are wrong. All Americans have been proud in these last days of the performance of our leaders, to the president, to the governor, to the mayor of New York, yes, to the senators. I am very proud of my wife and her colleagues and the House and the Senate, but especially the people.</p>
        <p>When I went into the family crisis center the first day, a man came up to me and said to me: 'Why Mr. President, I haven't seen you since Oklahoma City.' And I said: 'How did I see you there?' He said: 'You came to console me. My wife was blown up in the bombing of Oklahoma City and I had no one to talk to. So when I saw that this happened, I went in to my job and I told my boss I was taking two weeks off, and I got in my car and I drove here -- and I sit here all day, every day talking to people. I had no one to talk to and I thought I might be of help.'</p>
        <p>I have visited many of the firemen. The fire department is a marvelous organization in the modern world. It is more like a medieval army where instead of sitting and issuing orders, the leaders lead. And so in our fire department, we lost three top aides, the chaplain and some 200 other officers, 340 killed, necessitating over 200 promotions, because no one took a backseat when it came to sacrifice.</p>
        <p>I think those who believed we would be weakened by this have misjudged us. All over America there has been a tremendous outpouring of caring -- over $600 million given from Americans. I thank the workers and the people at Yale for the work you did for those who have lost loved ones or feared they had. We are going to be all right.</p>
        <p>STILL, we must realize that we have a formidable adversary and a difficult challenge. Partly, because in every conflict throughout human history, defense lags offense by a little bit, and we got caught not being caught up. This has always happened. But so far the human race is still around because self preservation and decency catches up and triumphs. Nevertheless, I think we have to take this seriously and see it for exactly what it is. I believe we are engaged for the first great struggle of the soul of the 21st century. We must understand terrorism in the context of the modern world. And we have to ask ourselves what we have to do, not only to prevent terrorism and protect ourselves, but to undermine the conditions and attitudes that bring to terrorists' banners their foot soldiers and sympathizers.</p>
        <p>If I had asked you on Sept. 10 the following question, what would your answer be? What is the dominant trait of the world in the early 21st century? If you are an optimistic person, it seems to me you might have given one of four answers. You might have said, well, it is the globalization of the economy and culture that has lifted more people out of poverty in the last 20 years than any time in all history and brought America unparalleled wealth and opportunity, including the opportunity for, first, immigrants from all over the world.</p>
        <p>Or you might have said if you are a ''techie,'' it is the information technology revolution. When I became president in January 1993, there where 50 sites on the World Wide Web. When I left office, there were 350 million. There was never anything like it in the history of communications.</p>
        <p>Or you might have said if you were a scientist, it's the evolution in the sciences. Last year we found two new species of life, in two previously unexplored rivers. The human genome has been sequenced and soon women will bring home babies from the hospital with little gene cards saying here are the kids' problems and the kids' strengths. And very soon babies born in America and any country with a good health system will have a life expectancy in excess of 90 years. We have scientists working on digital chips to replicate the nerve functions of damage in the spinal cord and raising the prospects that a chip might do for a spine what a pacemaker might do for the heart. And people thought permanently paralyzed might get up and walk. And all of this is truly amazing.</p>
        <p>Or if you are a political scientist you might say the dominant theory of this period is the explosion of democracy around the world and diversity at home. Just for the last three years for the first time in human history, more than half the world lives under governments of their own choosing. This never happened before. And in our country and indeed in most other countries with a strong economy, there is an absolute explosion of diversity. America is a lot more interesting place than it was 30 years ago. If we had this meeting 30 years ago, you wouldn't look like you do. And it's a lot more fun to be here, and a lot more educational and a lot more exciting because of that.</p>
        <p>It seems to me if you are optimistic on Sept. 10 when I said what is the dominant strength of the 21st century world, you could have given one of those four answers. The global economy, the explosion of democracy around the world and diversity, and the scientific evolution.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you are a little more pessimistic, or if you are what Hillary refers to in our family as her being the designated worrier, you might have mentioned four negative things. You might have said all those things are just fine, but the environmental crisis facing us is so great that they all threaten to engulf all the progress and let it go away. Nine of the hottest years ever recorded occurred in the last 12. If the climate warms at the same rate in the next 50 years as it has in the last 10, we will lose 50 feet of the Florida everglades, agriculture will be disrupted all over the world and millions and millions of food refugees will be created and there will be a lot more violence out there.</p>
        <p>There is a terrible water shortage in the world already and one in four people on the globe never get a clean glass of water. There is a serious deterioration in the floor of our oceans, which are responsible for so much of our oxygen. And you could say it doesn't look to me like there is much going on about this and if we don't reverse these we will be having terrible problems.</p>
        <p>OR you could say no, no, before that happens, we will be engulfed by a health crisis, the breakdown of health  all over the world. This year one in four people in the world will die of AIDS, TB, malaria or infections related to diarrhea. Thirty-six million people will have AIDS within five years. The fastest-growing rates are in the former Soviet Union on Europe's back door, and in the Caribbean on our front door, and in any of the world's greatest democracies. And China just admitted they have twice as many AIDS cases as they had previously thought. And only 4 percent of the adults know how the disease is contracted and spread. You could say when we have 100 million AIDS cases it will collapse a lot of these democracies, and it is a recipe for total turmoil and violence.</p>
        <p>Or you could say, no, the real problem is the flip side of globalization.  Half the world's people are really not part of it. It is true that more people have been lifted out of poverty by globalization in the last 20 years than ever before. It is also true that half the people in the world still live on less than $2 a day. That a billion of our people still live on less than $1 a day. And think about it the next time you buy a cup of coffee. A billion go to bed hungry every night, and one woman dies every minute in childbirth. And that is a recipe for revolution, compounded by the fact that 100 million of our children in the globe never go to school at all: half the kids in Africa and a quarter of the kids in East Asia and Indian subcontinent. So you might have said that.</p>
        <p>Or even on Sept. 10, you might have said, no, the biggest problem is going to be terrorism, coupled with weapons of mass destruction and rooted in racial and religious and ethnic hatred.</p>
        <p>And here is what I would like to say. Whether you would have given a positive answer, or a negative answer, there is something that all eight of these elements, positive and negative, have in common. They all reflect the astonishing increase in global interdependence. The extent of which we have seen the collapse of distances and barriers, bringing us closer together for good or ill. Terrorism is simply the dark side of our increasing interdependence. We have not repealed human nature or the fact some people see reality very differently than we do. And it was inevitable, if we take down all the barriers, if we open the society, that people who represent organized forces of destruction would take advantage of the very forces that could make us richer, more diverse, and made our lives better. Therefore, all the great questions of the 21st century boil down to one: Is this new age going to be good or bad on balance for me, my family, my community, my nation and the world?</p>
        <p>What do we have to do to make sure that we encourage the positive forces of independence and that we restrain the negative ones? I'd like to make three points. First, first things first, we have to defend ourselves against terrorism. I want you to know that there are good people, lots of them, who have been working on this for years. And I want you to know that there were many, many more attacks that were planned on the United States which were thwarted by our public servants and our allies. In the last millennium alone there was plan for a bomb in Boston, a bomb in Seattle, a bomb for Los Angeles airport, and half a dozen other plans all thwarted. There are good people who are working hard.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, clearly there is more to do to build our defenses, to build our ability to be offensive, to build our capacity to maximize computer networks to ward off people who mean us harm. I don't want to say more about that right now because the president and national security teams and our allies have some tough technical decisions to make.  And I think we ought to stick with them and give them the room to make decisions. So far they have been making good decisions, and we have no reason to believe they won't do so in the future. I think it is important for America to stay united. We are and we must stay that way. And I will say again, I know it was frightening to have the first massive attack on American soil. And nothing can minimize the humans lost.</p>
        <p>BUT let me remind the young people here, that the century we just left was the bloodiest in all human history. Twelve million died in World War I, 20 million in World War II and another 20 million from government oppression after the war, not counting the million that died in Vietnam. And the world has never been free of violence. And we took down the walls and collapsed the businesses. We were independent and therefore all the things that we have benefited from in this global economy, sharing with it the price tag of being vulnerable to those who would do us harm.  But we will catch up and that will be handled. What we have to do as citizens is to think about what else has to be done and what else we personally can do. We have to lead an assault on the conditions of negative independence and create more opportunities for positive independence.</p>
        <p>Americans should continue to work to reduce poverty, with things like more debt relief, more micro credit, more sensible trade. America should contribute its fair share to the secretary general's health fund to fight the AIDS epidemic and other health problems. America should deal with the challenge of climate change through conservation, through the development of alternative energy, through helping our friends and neighbors throughout the world do the same. America should continue to promote democracy.</p>
        <p>One particular problem we have in the present crisis is that so many people who hear the siren song of radical fundamentalism live in countries growing ever larger, ever younger and ever poorer where there is no democracy or chance to express dissent or even assent in a normal political way. And it keeps the populous in a state of sort of permanent infancy, in which you never have to take responsibility for your own lives and making it better, because you never get to take responsibility.</p>
        <p>And, therefore, it is very easy to listen to someone say your problems were caused by America's success.  It's a hard case to make because people from all of those countries come to America and they share in that success. It is a hard case to make, because America last used military power to protect poor Muslims in Bosnia and Kosovo. But nonetheless, if you never get to vote for office, you never get to stand up in a public forum and say what you think, you are permanently disempowered.  And you could hear the siren song; it is all because of America. So, we have to keep urging our friends to find ways to move to greater democracy and freedom.</p>
        <p>And finally, let me say this. Even more important than what we do, is who we are. We must understand that this present conflict, as agonizing as the loss was, is about far more than the buildings collapsing and the people dying. This is about a global force with a fundamentally different view of the nature of truth, the value of life, the character of human community. Mr. Bin Laden and the Taliban believe they have the truth. And everybody that agrees with them is good, and everybody that doesn't is evil. This great university is dedicated to the proposition that nobody has the absolute truth. We all get to vote. We have the right to freedom of speech. We have the right of freedom of religion. We have the right of freedom of assembly. And we have the responsibilities of a free people because we believe that fundamentally life is a journey because we move closer and closer to the truth. But because we are finite human beings we never will achieve it.</p>
        <p>THEREFORE, we don't have the right to impose our iron will on others. And the more the merrier, with the thought that together we might find more truth. That is a fundamental difference. And it leads people to a different view of the value of human life.</p>
        <p>Because we believe that we are all traveling on this journey together, we have come over time, more and more and more to value all life. To think that everybody counts, that everybody deserves a chance. But for them, they believe there are three kinds of people. There are the people that will embrace their particular views of Islam. And then there are the Muslims who don't agree with their views of the Koran, who keep saying that Allah put different people on the earth not that they might despise one another, but that they might get to know one another and learn from one another. They hate that in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>And the rest of us who are not Muslims are infidels. We are all combatants in the war and we all deserve what happens to us, including death, even if it's a 6-year-old girl who decided on the morning of Sept. 11 to go with her mother to work in the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>Of all the things that I have seen and been moved by in these last few weeks, the thing I will carry with me to the grave is the lines of the victims' families holding their little fliers, because for days and days and days, people didn't know whether their loved ones were in the building when it was hit. But they all made up fliers. And they had pictures of their loved ones. This is my wife, my husband, my brother, my sister, my mother, my father, my child, here is the picture.</p>
        <p>And outside, often in handwriting, this is what floor they were on, this is how tall they were, this is how much they weighed. All these people holding these pictures, there were Indians and Pakistanis, Japanese, Chinese, British, and German, Mexicans, Chileans, there were people from every conceivable religious faith. They were all there. A stunning rebuke, to the people they thought they had the right to kill them because they had the whole truth.</p>
        <p>We believe in a different character of community. We believe we all do better when we work together. And all you have to do in our country is to accept the rules of engagement. Our rules about everybody counting, everybody getting to vote. People who will have to show up every day to do what is right. It gives us the freedom to celebrate our diversity that we could be united by our common humanity. Their community is not united by common humanity, it is united by what it is not.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bin Laden has a political agenda. He wants to take over Saudi Arabia, get rid of Israel and purge the whole Middle East of all the apostates so they all look like the Taliban. What a dreary world. We have seen in the pictures on television from that movie ''Behind the Veil,'' what their ideas are like, forcing women to wear those horrible burqas -- and beating them with sticks in public and worse. But this is a formidable adversary because they do not believe they are evil. They believe they are doing good.</p>
        <p>THE most important thing over and above anything we do, is that we have in our minds clearly the world we are trying to make, that our wealth is not an end in itself, but a tool for the people to live up to their God-given abilities, that we keep struggling to get beyond the categories of difference to our common humanity. And we should never be blind to how difficult it is going to be. Think of the great spirits of the last 50 years, Gandhi killed, not by a Pakistani Muslim, but by one of his own Hindus who hated him because he wanted India for the Muslims, the Sikhs, for everybody. Sadat killed by the organization that Mr. Bin Laden's No. 2 heads now, not by an Israeli, but by an Egyptian who hated him for reaching across the religious and ethnic bloody divide to make peace.</p>
        <p>My friend Yitzhak Rabin -- a lifetime of defending Israel, killed, not by a Palestinian terrorist, but by an Israeli who hated him because he wanted to lay down arms and take up peace. This is hard. I thank God that of all the great spirits of the last 50 years, Mandela survived, probably only because he first had to pay with 27 of the best years of his life being in jail. It is hard. To get people beyond the notion that they are defined by their differences and not by their common humanity.</p>
        <p>But you can do it by living it and you can do it by recognizing that it is time to take America's eternal mission to the world. A mission to widen the circle of opportunity, to deepen the meaning of freedom, to strengthen the bonds of community. We can no longer deny others what we claim for ourselves. That is the ultimate lesson for the independent world.</p>
        <p>We are going to get through this crisis. Our leaders are going to make good decisions. But in the end, we not only have to stop bad things from happening, we have to build for you, the best, the most prosperous, the most peaceful and exciting time the world has ever known. And we can do it, if we remember who we are and what we believe.</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
