<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Shift Could Doom Air Pact, Some Say</title>
    <meta content="Y17WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/17/science/17WARM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1D8153DF934A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Shift Could Doom Air Pact, Some Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts say Pres Bush's decision to withdraw United States from Kyoto Protocol will doom international agreement intended to curtail global warming; critics of Kyoto welcome Bush's unambiguous statement, but others note that process of reducing carbon-dioxide emissions will have to be dealt with by Bush regardless of his opposition to treaty itself (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Efforts to complete the Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement intended to curtail global warming, have been seriously damaged by President Bush this week, negotiators and independent experts on the treaty say.</p>
        <p>The protocol, signed by the United States and more than 100 other countries but not yet ratified, was already in trouble, with the last round of talks concerning details of the agreement collapsing last November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Efforts to complete the Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement intended to curtail global warming, have been seriously damaged by President Bush this week, negotiators and independent experts on the treaty say.</p>
        <p>The protocol, signed by the United States and more than 100 other countries but not yet ratified, was already in trouble, with the last round of talks concerning details of the agreement collapsing last November.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Bush issued a letter on Tuesday that renounced his campaign promise to cut carbon-dioxide emissions from power plants, he delivered what could be the coup de grâce, said many foreign government officials, some White House ones and others involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>Some say this may be just as well, because the pact, negotiated in 1997 in Japan, contains targets for cutting emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases that are nearly unreachable because of rapid recent growth in many economies and energy use in many nations. Others say there are ways to change the agreement without losing years of work by rejecting it outright.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's policy change was welcomed by Saudi Arabia, one of the treaty's staunchest opponents.</p>
        <p>''This announcement by President Bush is the announcement of the death of the Kyoto Protocol,'' said Mohammed Al-Sabban, the energy adviser to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and the leader of that country's negotiating team.</p>
        <p>Dr. Henry D. Jacoby, an expert on the treaty and an economist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said the treaty's outlines probably could not be salvaged. But the negotiating structure that led to it would probably continue, he said.</p>
        <p>''The Kyoto Protocol is really two different things -- it's the current text and numbers, and it's a process,'' he said. ''The numbers are no longer going to work, but the process is going to go on. It has to, because the issue is too important.''</p>
        <p>''It's clear,'' Dr. Jacoby added, ''that this administration won't be able to go four years without dealing with this.''</p>
        <p>The pact, if ratified, would commit the United States and three dozen other industrialized countries to cut their combined emissions of heat-trapping gases by 2012 to 95 percent of the amounts measured in 1990.</p>
        <p>Throughout last year, Mr. Bush had said he opposed the climate treaty because it would harm the economy and exempt developing countries from committing to reductions in emissions.</p>
        <p>But it was the definitive language in the letter, which represented the administration's first elaboration of its emerging climate policy, that startled many people, even some conservative Republicans who had long opposed the treaty.</p>
        <p>Several elements in the letter undermined the treaty. Some were seemingly intentional, like a pointed criticism of China and India. Other language, White House officials and others involved with the treaty said, remained in the letter even after meetings early in the week at which Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and other foreign affairs experts suggested changes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's reversal on power plants took away a valuable bargaining chip: evidence that the United States would commit to reduce emissions within its borders. Treaty experts said the shift would also seem to confirm suspicions of many European nations that the United States would avoid cutting emissions.</p>
        <p>In a separate passage, Mr. Bush alluded to what he called ''the incomplete state of scientific knowledge of the causes of, and solutions to, global climate change.'' Yet environmental groups and even some officials in the chemical industry, where many companies have already started to cut emissions, said the scientific consensus was stronger than ever.</p>
        <p>''We saw sufficient science emerging to warrant what in our judgment was prudent action back in 1991,'' said Thomas R. Jacob, the manager of international and industry affairs for DuPont, one of several dozen corporations that have committed to voluntary reductions in their greenhouse-gas emissions.</p>
        <p>Some longtime opponents of the climate treaty said they were surprised that the letter lacked the usual nuances and qualifications required to sustain diplomatic discussions, regardless of a country's stance on the substance of a treaty.</p>
        <p>Other critics of Kyoto welcomed the unambiguous statement. Dr. S. Fred Singer, a retired physicist and longtime critic of research indicating a warming trend with a human cause, said he hoped Mr. Bush would kill the treaty outright.</p>
        <p>''The Kyoto Protocol is like a vampire,'' Dr. Singer said. ''You need to drive a stake through its heart. Otherwise it'll keep coming back and causing problems.''</p>
        <p>The Bush letter has generated a number of cables from European governments to the State Department expressing concern for the fate of the climate talks.</p>
        <p>More telling, perhaps, was the reaction in China, where an official in the foreign ministry yesterday restated the stance of developing countries, that the United States and other industrialized countries must take the first steps to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>''The developed countries have been discharging greenhouse gases for over a hundred years,'' the official said. ''They bear the historical responsibility on climate changes that cannot be shirked.''</p>
        <p>White House officials said that the letter reflected Mr. Bush's position on Kyoto, but did not preclude further talks. ''The president clearly expects his administration to be active internationally in dealing with the issue,'' said Sean McCormack, a White House spokesman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
