<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Weird Science; A Cool Idea to Save Earth</title>
    <meta content="17RAMI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/17/weekinreview/17RAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laughlin, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adams, Fred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Korycansky, Don</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto Protocol</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D81431F934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Weird Science; A Cool Idea to Save Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Don Korychansky, Greg Laughlin and Fred Adams propose novel solution to global warming: maneuvering asteroid into orbit in which it would tug Earth gently away from Sun; they note that as Sun burns through its hydrogen over next billion years, it will get 10 percent brighter, killing off many forms of life on Earth unless planet can move further away; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the nation once again reaches for an iced tea to rub against its forehead, the chat turns inevitably, if listlessly, to global warming, the artificial raising of the planet's thermostat.</p>
        <p>Ratify the Kyoto Protocol? Harms the American economy, says President Bush. Cut back on greenhouse emissions? Drives up electricity prices, say economists. Require smaller cars? Minivans carry my children to school, say the parents. Swelter, swelter, swelter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the nation once again reaches for an iced tea to rub against its forehead, the chat turns inevitably, if listlessly, to global warming, the artificial raising of the planet's thermostat.</p>
        <p>Ratify the Kyoto Protocol? Harms the American economy, says President Bush. Cut back on greenhouse emissions? Drives up electricity prices, say economists. Require smaller cars? Minivans carry my children to school, say the parents. Swelter, swelter, swelter.</p>
        <p>Enter three scientists pushing a big, if long-term, idea: cool down the Earth by slowly moving it -- the entire planet, that is -- farther away from the Sun.</p>
        <p>In a recent issue of the professional journal Astrophysics and Space Science, Don Korycansky, Greg Laughlin and Fred Adams playfully propose finding an asteroid about 60 miles long -- about half the length of Long Island -- to be used in a ''gravitational sling shot.''</p>
        <p>A rocket could be strapped to the asteroid, they say, and the asteroid maneuvered into an immense orbit more than seven times wider than the radius of the solar system. The asteroid would then pass close enough to Earth to tug it gently away from the Sun. (One hitch, the authors acknowledge, would be a collision, which would ''sterilize the biosphere most effectively, at least to the level of bacteria.'')</p>
        <p>While the solution may seem outsized, the three scientists are actually eyeing a larger-scale version of global warming. As the Sun burns through its hydrogen, it gets bigger and brighter, leading to hotter temperatures on Earth. In a billion years, the Sun will be 10 percent brighter, killing off many forms of life on Earth.</p>
        <p>Moving the planet away from the Sun, in this view, is simply shoving it away from a red-hot stove.</p>
        <p>It would be fitting if the idea occurred to Mr. Korycansky, the paper's principal author and a planetary scientist at the University of California at Santa Cruz, on a blistering summer day. But it was on a sunny and mild September day in 1999 that Mr. Korycansky chatted with Mr. Laughlin, a scientist at NASA's Ames Research Center, about the daunting problem of the Sun's lethal luminosity.</p>
        <p>Earth-moving was Mr. Laughlin's idea, the asteroid was Mr. Korycansky's, while Mr. Adams, a University of Michigan physicist, was brought in later to figure out timing, which, as will be seen, is everything.</p>
        <p>As they write in their paper, ''the general problem of long-term planetary engineering is almost alarmingly feasible'' using current technologies.</p>
        <p>After all, ''gravitational slingshots'' using Jupiter and Saturn have already been used to propel the Galileo and Cassini deep-space missions. The principle is a lot like a planetary square dance in which even the tiniest dancer can slightly deflect and accelerate a gargantuan partner, and vice versa, as they swing each other round and round.</p>
        <p>An asteroid roughly 60 miles long passing within 10,000 miles of Earth would tug the planet into an orbit whose radius gets longer by about 30 miles with each pass, or every 6,000 years. Of course, it would take a long-lived civilization to witness the feat -- the equivalent of the ancient Egyptians firing a deep-space rocket with the expectation that their descendants would greet its return in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Korycansky and his friends foresee at least one million of these orbits, slowly balancing out the Sun's increasing ferocity and thus preserving life on Earth.</p>
        <p>BY the millionth pass, however, the Earth would have a 50 percent larger orbit.</p>
        <p>''Of course, we'd then have to move Mars,'' Mr. Korycansky said. Jupiter would be affected, too, and so would Venus, but probably in ways too small to really matter to Earth. ''The larger question is,'' he said, ''if you move a planet, is it your responsibility to, you know, shepherd the other planets?''</p>
        <p>And the Earth, while rescued, would not escape consequences, either. Every time the asteroid passed, it would exert a tidal force 10 times that of the moon, leading to likely tsunamis, immense storms and other disruptions. ''We would have to batten down the hatches,'' Mr. Korycansky said.</p>
        <p>Don't even mention the seasons, say skeptical climate researchers. A bigger orbit means a longer year, affecting the all-important tilt of Earth toward the Sun.</p>
        <p>''At a zero tilt, straight up and down, there would be no seasons,'' said Dr. Ronald J. Stouffer, who designs computer climate models at the federal Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory. ''At a 90-degree tilt, you have two seasons, one that's all daylight all the time and the other that's all nighttime all the time.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the biggest complication of all is simply this: Instead of missing by a whisker, an ill-timed asteroid larger than Rhode Island could very well crash into the Earth. It would be the gravest miscalculation since, perhaps, a similar one many millions of years ago that wiped out ancient dinosaur astronomers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
