<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burden Seems to Be on Japan to Salvage the Fast-Eroding Climate Treaty</title>
    <meta content="Y02CLI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/02/world/02CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Tokyo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto Protocol</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Tokyo (Japan)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DB1039F931A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burden Seems to Be on Japan to Salvage the Fast-Eroding Climate Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan is in the driver's seat to determine whether a global climate treaty will ever take effect. And supporters of the treaty said yesterday that they were discouraged by the remarks made on Saturday by Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi when he met with President Bush, a fervent opponent of the treaty.</p>
        <p>At Camp David, Mr. Koizumi said that Japan was willing to work until the last minute to rally support for the treaty, but that in the end it would not proceed without the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japan is in the driver's seat to determine whether a global climate treaty will ever take effect. And supporters of the treaty said yesterday that they were discouraged by the remarks made on Saturday by Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi when he met with President Bush, a fervent opponent of the treaty.</p>
        <p>At Camp David, Mr. Koizumi said that Japan was willing to work until the last minute to rally support for the treaty, but that in the end it would not proceed without the United States.</p>
        <p>And responding to a reporter's question, Mr. Koizumi refused to express any disappointment in Mr. Bush. To the contrary, he said, ''The president is enthusiastic about environmental issues and there is still time to discuss this issue.''</p>
        <p>These and other lukewarm expressions of support suggested that the treaty cannot be enacted without fundamental revisions. The treaty, negotiated in Kyoto, Japan, nearly four years ago, would be the first requiring industrial countries to cut emissions of gases linked to global warming.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Koizumi's statements were nuanced and they may be clarified in talks today with Prime Minister Tony Blair in London, and later in the week with President Jacques Chirac of France. Japan has had a strong allegiance to the proposal in part because it was negotiated in Kyoto, but in bargaining over treaty, Japan has tended to side with the United States against European demands for deep cuts in domestic emissions.</p>
        <p>At informal talks in The Hague last week, the European Union held to its position that it would pursue ratification and enactment even without the United States, whose opposition President Bush announced in March. But to reach a threshold for the treaty to take effect, Europe would need Japan's support, and officials gave no indication which way the country would go.</p>
        <p>That appeared to change on Saturday when Mr. Koizumi said during a brief session with reporters, ''Presently, I do not have the intention of proceeding without the cooperation of the United States.''</p>
        <p>And during a news conference on Saturday night, he spoke mainly of ''the spirit of the protocol'' instead of the document itself, and discussed plans by Washington and Tokyo to pursue talks on other options. The leaders said their countries would pursue talks exploring ways to use technology to combat climate change. That is a favorite theme of the Bush administration, which opposes binding limits on emissions.</p>
        <p>All of this implies that a fresh start is needed.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Bush administration officials embraced Mr. Koizumi's comments as an endorsement of their rejection of the treaty.</p>
        <p>''The president's approach of pursuing these issues now on a research and technology basis, instead of the completely unfair approach that Kyoto would have forced the United States to follow, is the sensible way,'' Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham said yesterday.</p>
        <p>And, perceiving a change in Japanese policies, he said, ''I'm glad to see Japan joining us in taking that position.'' He spoke on the television program ''Fox News Sunday.''</p>
        <p>But Japanese officials worked to dismiss any sense that Japan had settled on a clear change in its posture. ''We are not intending to derail the international negotiations,'' said a Japanese environmental official. He added that Japan still felt it was possible to persuade the United States ''to keep alive the spirit of the Kyoto Protocol.''</p>
        <p>The official said his government was divided over how to proceed. ''There are still many arguments from within the ruling party that we should ratify even without the United States,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He and other Japanese officials said they continued to hope that if the treaty's timetable and targets for emissions reductions were adjusted, the United States might consider rejoining the process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has emphatically said he opposes the treaty because the required reductions could harm the economy and because developing nations are excused from similar requirements.</p>
        <p>Japanese officials said yesterday that senior Japanese and American diplomats would meet before the next round of formal talks on the treaty, which is scheduled in Bonn in mid-July.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Japan has been playing its cards carefully, and has gained concessions from the Europe Union. And Japan has also concentrated on its domestic economic ills, which were the primary focus of Mr. Koizumi's talks with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Many other international agreements have entered into force without ratification by the United States, including the Law of the Sea. But barring a sharp turnabout by Japan, a climate treaty with binding emissions reductions is unlikely to be one of them.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto treaty, negotiated by the Clinton administration, is an outgrowth of a convention signed by the first President Bush and unanimously supported by the Senate in 1992. That document called for industrial countries to rein in emissions voluntarily by 2000 to levels measured in 1990.</p>
        <p>The binding cuts required by the Kyoto agreement were negotiated starting in 1995 after the world's governments concluded that the voluntary measures were not working. It would require 38 industrial countries to reduce their combined emissions 5 percent below the 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>But the Kyoto pact has always been extremely fragile. Developing countries only signed on condition that the industrial countries agreed to take the first steps, and the United States all along demanded some form of ''meaningful participation'' by fast-growing countries like China and India. That difference remains unresolved.</p>
        <p>The European Union, the strongest force seeking ratification, has insisted that industrial countries cut greenhouse gases mainly by reducing emissions from smokestacks and tailpipes. That clashed with the position of the Clinton administration, which sought to gain credit toward its targets by growing more forests, which absorb carbon dioxide, the main heat-trapping gas.</p>
        <p>Once Mr. Bush rejected the treaty, the path toward enactment grew far more difficult. The treaty can only go into force if 55 countries ratify it, including a group responsible for at least 55 percent of 1990 emissions from industrial countries.</p>
        <p>David G. Victor, a senior fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations, calculates that without Japan, the European Union could reach that goal only with a disparate group of partners, an alliance that would get it to just 55.07 percent of the 1990 emissions. That course is highly implausible, Mr. Victor said. ''If Slovakia sneezes, the whole thing falls apart,'' he said. ''They need Japan.''</p>
        <p>Timothy E. Wirth, president of the United Nations Foundation, former Democratic senator from Colorado who directed climate negotiations for the Clinton administration from 1993 to 1997, said the nuances of the Japanese statements camouflaged what he described as serious damage and delay by the Bush administration impeding efforts to forge a climate agreement.</p>
        <p>''Now it's up to him,'' Mr. Wirth said, referring to Mr. Bush. ''You can't just move in and kick away the whole structure without offering something in response.''</p>
        <p>But critics of the Kyoto treaty said Mr. Koizumi's statements had done the world a favor by emphasizing the need to explore the mechanisms of the treaty anew.</p>
        <p>''We've been saying for a long time that the treaty was headed down a dead-end street,'' said Frank Maisano, a spokesman for the Global Climate Coalition, a private group financed by industries opposed to binding cuts in greenhouse gases. ''The Canadians were whispering this. The Australians were whispering this. For the Japanese to say it pretty much says we need to look at a new approach.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
