<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dashboard Miser Teaches Drivers How to Save Fuel</title>
    <meta content="07NEXT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/07/technology/07NEXT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1299533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S NEXT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Twente (Enschede, Netherlands)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisenberg, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">van der Voort, Mascha (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/What's Next</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Enschede (Netherlands)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sweden</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DC113FF934A35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dashboard Miser Teaches Drivers How to Save Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE EISENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eisenberg, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Mascha van der Voort, University of Twente, Enschede, Netherlands, develops constant-feedback dashboard device to help maximize drivers' fuel efficiency (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DUTCH and Swedish researchers may have an antidote for rising gasoline  prices. They have developed a computer-driven dashboard display that advises drivers throughout a trip on ways to reduce fuel use.</p>
        <p>City drivers who follow the dashboard advice on acceleration, braking and other maneuvers reduce their gasoline consumption by 20 percent, the researchers reported. The prototype was tested in and around Enschede, the Netherlands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DUTCH and Swedish researchers may have an antidote for rising gasoline  prices. They have developed a computer-driven dashboard display that advises drivers throughout a trip on ways to reduce fuel use.</p>
        <p>City drivers who follow the dashboard advice on acceleration, braking and other maneuvers reduce their gasoline consumption by 20 percent, the researchers reported. The prototype was tested in and around Enschede, the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>The computer program in the device keeps track of essentials like speed, steering wheel angle and distance to the vehicle in front, constantly calculating what the driver should be doing to minimize fuel consumption. The program takes a dim view of idling, a notorious gasoline waster, and of that staple of New York City taxi drivers, rapid acceleration followed immediately by an equally rapid deceleration.</p>
        <p>''If drivers change their habits -- and they can with constant feedback -- they can complete the same journey in similar travel times using far less fuel,'' said Dr. Mascha van der Voort, who just finished her graduate work at the University of Twente in Enschede. Dr. van der Voort devised the computer program and dashboard display with the help of two advisers as part of the work for her doctorate.</p>
        <p>In the long term, Dr. van der Voort acknowledged, the bulk of gasoline savings will probably come from improvements in  engine efficiency, not from changes in driving habits. ''But I wanted to do something right now,'' she said, ''in the short run, to conserve fuel and reduce carbon dioxide emissions.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Therese Langer, transportation program director for the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy, a nonprofit group based in Washington, said that on-board devices that monitored and advised drivers about driving methods that could save gasoline could indeed play a part in energy conservation. But she added, ''Devices like these are not a substitute for the automakers to make a concerted effort to improve their fuel economies.''</p>
        <p>Many dashboards can already tell drivers, for instance, how much fuel they are using for a maneuver. ''This device is different,'' said Dr. Mark S. Dougherty, a computer science professor at Dalarna University in Borlange, Sweden, who supervised Dr. van der Voort's research project. ''It gives you constant feedback during a trip on many ways to improve fuel efficiency.''</p>
        <p>The program was designed for standard-transmission cars, which are far more popular in Europe than cars with automatic transmissions. But the program can be adapted to automatic transmissions, Dr. Dougherty said.</p>
        <p>Dr. van der Voort and her colleagues tested the program first in computer-controlled driving simulations and then on the road. In the simulated runs, drivers read the advice on a display that was next to an indicator light; the light changed from green to orange and finally red when they delayed heeding the admonition. ''The orange warning was when the driver was 10 seconds late, for instance, in shifting from second to third gear,'' she said. Red warnings were given when two minutes had elapsed.</p>
        <p>In the driving simulations, reported this year in the journal Transportation Research, drivers with on-board advice had an average fuel-use reduction of 16 percent.  Drivers in urban areas did even better, reducing fuel use by 23 percent.</p>
        <p>''We decided, based on the simulations,''  Dr. van der Voort said, ''that drivers in city centers could really use detailed advice on how to drive more fuel-efficiently for the complex situations they meet.''</p>
        <p>In the actual road tests that followed the simulated ones, the advice was shown without the colored warning light to make the display less distracting. The system uses a dashboard liquid-crystal display; the idea of audio cues was discarded as too intrusive. The computer program was calibrated to the engine performance of the Volkswagens used in the trials, and 36 people, a mix of men and women, took to the roads, suburbs and highways around Enschede in cars with manual transmissions.</p>
        <p>''People who had the device on the dashboard drove on average 11 percent more efficiently than people without it,'' Dr. van der Voort said. In urban areas the fuel saving was 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Some of the gasoline savings came from changing the patterns of gear shifting. ''People were shifting too late from first to second, and from second to third,'' Dr. van der Voort said. People saved the most gasoline when they pushed down on the accelerator briskly and then shifted quickly, keeping the revolutions per minute low -- not by accelerating very gently.</p>
        <p>''It's not commonly understood by people who drive,'' Dr. Dougherty said. ''They think that the way to get best fuel economy is to accelerate very gently, but that proves not to be the case. The best thing is to accelerate briskly and shift.</p>
        <p>''Don't give it everything the car has, but push down when you're going to shift, using maybe two-thirds of the available power, and change through the gears relatively quickly.''</p>
        <p>Another time when gasoline was saved was during braking. ''The main thing is to anticipate better when you are going to need to stop,'' Dr. Dougherty said. Then you should take your foot off the accelerator and use air resistance and friction to help slow the car.</p>
        <p>In Europe, a number of driving programs, sometimes known as eco-driving or ecological driver training, instruct participants in many of the gasoline-conserving techniques that underlie Dr. van der Voort's computer program. Christina Schaper, a project manager at Deutsche Umwelthilfe (the German Environmental Aid Association) in Radolfzell, Germany, coordinates her work on reducing carbon dioxide emissions from traffic with many of these groups.</p>
        <p>''Most of the groups I work with report about a 20 percent gas savings by teaching people the right way to drive,'' Ms. Schaper said. ''Fuel economy is a big issue here.''</p>
        <p>Driver education programs that stress fuel economy were more popular in the United States after the gasoline shortages of the 1970's, said Philip Patterson, an economist in the Office of Transportation Technologies at the Department of Energy who works with automobile companies to make vehicles more fuel-efficient. ''We had educational programs into the 80's, but most of them gradually dried up,'' he said. ''It's time we started working on this again.''</p>
        <p>Dr. van der Voort acknowledged that some of her dashboard-delivered advice, however sensible, was going to be a tough sell in a world full of people who often either ignore warnings or paste black electrical tape over them. For example, New York City cabbies, if not the ones in Enschede, are sure to reject the advice to turn off their engines after idling in traffic more than 30 seconds. ''Most people don't do that even here,'' Dr. van der Voort said, ''but we are trying to teach them.''</p>
        <p>WHAT'S NEXT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
