<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vanity, Thy New Name Is E-Publishing</title>
    <meta content="01PRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1305911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLISHING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winter, Alan a (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Snowflakes In the Sahara (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0DB1739F932A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vanity, Thy New Name Is E-Publishing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on world of e-publishing, new version of vanity press that new authors who are unable to garner support from traditional publishers and agents use to get their books published; Dr Alan A Winter, periodontist who has written book Snowflakes in the Sahara, complains about his experience with iUniverse Web site and its Writer's Showcase; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Alan A. Winter is a periodontist, he longs to be something else: a novelist. And because he has been unable to secure a publisher, or even a literary agent, he decided to enter the world of Internet vanity publishing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Winter, 53, who has a flair for self-promotion, decided to approach iUniverse, Barnes &amp; Noble's Internet-publishing partner, with ''Snowflakes in the Sahara,'' his novel about global warming, cults and the American annexation of Canada. The heroine is (what else?) a forensic dentist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Alan A. Winter is a periodontist, he longs to be something else: a novelist. And because he has been unable to secure a publisher, or even a literary agent, he decided to enter the world of Internet vanity publishing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Winter, 53, who has a flair for self-promotion, decided to approach iUniverse, Barnes &amp; Noble's Internet-publishing partner, with ''Snowflakes in the Sahara,'' his novel about global warming, cults and the American annexation of Canada. The heroine is (what else?) a forensic dentist.</p>
        <p>''I figured it would have a certain credibility being tied in with Barnes &amp; Noble,'' Dr. Winter said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Winter, a dentist for 28 years, paid an extra fee to be part of iUniverse's Writer's Showcase. The iUniverse Web site says: ''The Writer's Showcase is the choice of new authors who want to ensure their book has the quality to succeed in the marketplace. The iUniverse.com qualification board reviews all submitted manuscripts. The board is composed of former magazine editors, freelance book reviewers, columnists for magazines, newspapers, teachers, screenwriters, producers, publicity consultants, and literary agents. If for some reason, the board feels your manuscript is not ready, you will be given the option to submit to our Writers Club Press program.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Winter hoped the showcase would mitigate the stigma of being a vanity press.</p>
        <p>''I was wrong,'' said Dr. Winter, a Mendham resident and partner in a Manhattan practice on Park Avenue. ''Barnes &amp; Noble had nothing to do with my book -- the stores don't even carry iUniverse books. And the Writer's Showcase, that didn't make any difference.''</p>
        <p>For Internet publishers like iUniverse, Time Warner's iPublish and a half a dozen other e-publishers, the key to success is distribution and marketing. Unlike traditional publishers, Internet publishers don't incur the cost of printing books until a book is ordered.</p>
        <p>A variety of writers use Internet publishers. From authors like Dr. Winter, dreaming of blockbusters and frustrated by the roadblocks of traditional publishing houses, to those writing memoirs to be distributed to family members.</p>
        <p>Andree Abecassis, vice president of the Ann Elmo Literary Agency, said: ''With the influence of the rise of the Internet and the decline of publishers willing to take chances on new authors or nonblockbusters, a new respectability has been given to self-publishing. At least on the Internet, some stigma of old print vanity presses is gone, although the costs of production and lack of marketing support is still there.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Winter said that now he does not see any difference between traditional vanity presses and e-publishers like iUniverse.</p>
        <p>But Lynn Zingraf, iUniverse general manager, insisted otherwise: ''The self-publishing and print-on-demand aspect makes us very different from a vanity press.''</p>
        <p>In 1982, Dr. Winter collaborated with a screenwriter on a science fiction project. He was encouraged, he said, ''by very favorable rejections.''</p>
        <p>A voracious reader, Dr. Winter had a writing background. For 12 years, he was the editor of a journal, Periodontal Case Reports.</p>
        <p>In 1993, MasterMedia, a nonfiction publishing house that wanted to expand, published Dr. Winter's novel ''Someone Else's Son,'' a switched-at-birth thriller. He received no advance. He said about 2,000 copies of the book were sold, generating about $4,000.</p>
        <p>By this time, Dr. Winter said, he had several close calls procuring agents. He was getting rejected, he said, by the best agents and publishers in town: William Morris Agency, Crown and Pocket Books.</p>
        <p>''Snowflakes in the Sahara'' was four years in the making, with Dr. Winter even training as a forensic dentist for accuracy.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of prejudice happening,'' he said. ''I know I'm ahead of myself, but the world isn't ready for a dental thriller. People don't like dentists.''</p>
        <p>It cost Dr. Winter $299 for iUniverse's Showcase evaluation of his book, (the regular package, without evaluation, costs $99), and he received five free copies. Artwork was handled by iUniverse, which publishes softback copies on demand. Dr. Winter was responsible for all marketing, and to his surprise and dismay, proofreading.</p>
        <p>He paid $1,000 for an outside assessment, $300 for editing and $5,000 on books for signings and to send to reviewers (he received no reviews). He pays roughly $15 for each book (which sells for $23.95). He said he had been told by iUniverse that he sold only 125 (he's received $330 in royalties), but he he said he thought he had sold more.</p>
        <p>He donated 100 books to the Manhattan Theater Club, hoping a member would option it for the movies. That didn't happen either.</p>
        <p>''I think this books is as worthy as any out there,'' he said. ''But people can't believe a dentist is capable of writing fiction.</p>
        <p>''Publishing it by a vanity press was my biggest mistake. I'm a serious writer, and people don't look at vanity press authors as serious. I never considered iUniverse as self-publishing, but now I'm disenchanted.''</p>
        <p>Representatives of iUniverse declined to comment on Dr. Winter's specific complaints.</p>
        <p>Still, Dr. Winter likes promoting his work and attending signings. But he will not go to a vanity press with his next book, a novel about German spies living in New Jersey in World War II.</p>
        <p>''I will keep writing and pushing and keep getting rejected until something works out,'' he said. ''I will not go through a vanity press.''</p>
        <p>PUBLISHING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
