<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isolated on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="24TUE1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/24/opinion/24TUE1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D9113AF937A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isolated on Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Isolated on Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A wallflower at what might have been its own victory party, the United States could only watch yesterday as 178 countries agreed on a deal that salvages the 1997 Kyoto Protocol and commits the rest of the industrialized world to orderly, mandatory reductions in the gases that are believed responsible for the warming of the earth's atmosphere. The door was left open for the Bush administration to sign on at any time in the future. But that seems unlikely. President Bush has already called the treaty ''fatally flawed,'' and nothing said yesterday by Paula Dobriansky, the under secretary of state who led an essentially irrelevant American delegation at the talks, suggested any change in Mr. Bush's thinking.</p>
        <p>The agreement must still be ratified by 55 industrialized countries, and even then will not be nearly as effective as it might have been if the United States, which emits one-fourth of the world's greenhouse gases, had signed on. Even so, the agreement will immediately increase the pressure on the administration to develop a plausible alternative strategy. Key Democrats are already calling for big reductions in carbon dioxide, the main global warming gas, through cleaner power plants, industrial processes and vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ratification of the Kyoto Protocol should increase the pressure on the Bush administration to develop a plausible alternative strategy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A wallflower at what might have been its own victory party, the United States could only watch yesterday as 178 countries agreed on a deal that salvages the 1997 Kyoto Protocol and commits the rest of the industrialized world to orderly, mandatory reductions in the gases that are believed responsible for the warming of the earth's atmosphere. The door was left open for the Bush administration to sign on at any time in the future. But that seems unlikely. President Bush has already called the treaty ''fatally flawed,'' and nothing said yesterday by Paula Dobriansky, the under secretary of state who led an essentially irrelevant American delegation at the talks, suggested any change in Mr. Bush's thinking.</p>
        <p>The agreement must still be ratified by 55 industrialized countries, and even then will not be nearly as effective as it might have been if the United States, which emits one-fourth of the world's greenhouse gases, had signed on. Even so, the agreement will immediately increase the pressure on the administration to develop a plausible alternative strategy. Key Democrats are already calling for big reductions in carbon dioxide, the main global warming gas, through cleaner power plants, industrial processes and vehicles.</p>
        <p>There is also pressure from the business community. Many corporate leaders are convinced that the United States will eventually have to join in fighting global warming, and would prefer to begin making capital investments now than waiting until the last minute, when the job will be more expensive. Some corporate leaders are also worried that without binding targets, American companies will have no incentive to develop technologies to reduce global warming gases, thereby ceding a lucrative market to the Europeans and the Japanese.</p>
        <p>The huge irony is that this agreement was tailored in many respects to American specifications -- and with an eye to reducing the putative burdens on America's economy that Mr. Bush used as an excuse to abandon not only the protocol but also his campaign pledge to impose mandatory controls on carbon dioxide. The agreement includes at least two important strategies that President Bill Clinton and Al Gore insisted on in Kyoto four years ago. One is an emissions trading scheme that is designed to use market mechanisms to allow countries to achieve their emissions targets at the lowest possible cost. The other is the so-called ''clean development mechanism'' under which rich countries can earn credits by providing cutting-edge clean-air technologies to poorer countries.</p>
        <p>Cementing the deal required softening some of Kyoto's emissions targets as well as making concessions to Japan, which sought and received extra credits toward its target for protecting its forests, which act as a ''sink'' for carbon dioxide through photosynthesis. And while the revised agreement gives extra credit to Japan for protecting its own forests, it perversely awards no credit at all for projects designed to stop tropical deforestation elsewhere. But even the severest critics conceded that these shortcomings were not disqualifying given the importance of the agreement as a whole.</p>
        <p>The hope now is to have the necessary ratifications in hand by the 10th anniversary of the 1992 Rio Summit on global warming in Johannesburg next year. It was at Rio that Mr. Bush's father first committed the United States to a global effort to reduce greenhouse gases. There is still time for his son to honor that commitment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
