<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D7163DF936A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>AIDS Drug Maker Drops Patent Fight in Africa  Bristol-Myers Squibb said it would no longer try to stop generic-drug makers from selling low-cost versions of the H.I.V. drug Zerit in Africa. The company also said it would cut the price of Zerit and the AIDS drug Videx in Africa, to a combined price of $1 a day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa said his government would not declare AIDS a national emergency as a way to gain access to generic AIDS drugs, indicating he would seek other ways to achieve that goal.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>AIDS Drug Maker Drops Patent Fight in Africa  Bristol-Myers Squibb said it would no longer try to stop generic-drug makers from selling low-cost versions of the H.I.V. drug Zerit in Africa. The company also said it would cut the price of Zerit and the AIDS drug Videx in Africa, to a combined price of $1 a day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa said his government would not declare AIDS a national emergency as a way to gain access to generic AIDS drugs, indicating he would seek other ways to achieve that goal.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Uganda Leader Re-elected  President Yoweri Museveni received 69.3 percent of the vote, a victory he called an affirmation of 15 years of peaceful rule. His main opponent, Kizza Besigye, attributed Mr. Museveni's victory to vote-rigging.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Yugoslav Troops Near Kosovo  NATO let the Yugoslav Army and special police back into a zone bordering Kosovo that has become a haven for Albanian gunmen. The gunmen's attacks are spreading to Macedonia and alarming the West.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>More Livestock Slaughtered  The confirmation of 27 new cases of foot-and-mouth disease brought the total in Britain to 232 and prompted Prime Minister Tony Blair to order an intensified slaughter of animals in areas directly affected.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>China Assails Missile Shield  Beijing's top arms-control negotiator, Sha Zukang, reiterated opposition to American development of a national missile-defense system or a smaller ''theater'' system in Asia, but said China was willing to discuss such shields with the United States to ''narrow our differences.''</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>North Korea Turns Up Heat  North Korea, criticizing American missile-defense plans in a Communist Party newspaper editorial, called the United States ''a cannibals' nation'' and accused the Bush administration of ''escalating its provocative and reckless diatribe.'' The North has intensified its criticism since President Bush, in talks with the South Korean president, expressed ''skepticism'' about the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>In Economy, Bush Finds Both Concern and Optimism  President Bush said he was ''concerned that a lot of Americans' portfolios have been affected'' by the stock market sell-off, but he also expressed ''great faith in our economy.'' Mr. Bush seemed intent on conveying some sense of optimism after months in which Democrats accused him of talking down the economy to build support for his $1.6 trillion tax cut.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said ''an energy crisis'' threatening the economy had led him to decide against regulating power plants' emissions of carbon dioxide, a reversal of a campaign pledge.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Assurances on Medicare Funds  The Bush administration told Congress that all payroll tax revenue flowing into the Medicare trust fund would be used only for Medicare.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>House G.O.P. Tax Plan  Influential House Republicans proposed several tax breaks that would sizably increase the cost and scope of President Bush's tax cut plan.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Clintons Falter in Public Eye  Bill Clinton's public approval rating has plunged to 38 percent, a New York Times/CBS News poll found, though most people appear to believe his pardon explanations. More than 40 percent of Americans view Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton unfavorably.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>'Terrible Metal Hitting Sound'  The captain of the Ehime Maru, the Japanese trawler sunk by the submarine Greeneville, recounted the collision to a naval court of inquiry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Survey of Gay Bias in Military  Reports of harassment of gays in the military declined slightly last year, largely because of improved training programs in the Army, a study by a legal aid group for gay and lesbian service members found.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Job Challenges for Ex-Convicts  Sociologists and economists are warning of a new challenge for the labor force: the steady stream of people coming out of prisons, many of them hard to employ.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Chicago Population Rebounds  Census figures show that Chicago, whose population declined for decades, has risen 4 percent, to nearly 2.9 million people, since 1990.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Study Finds Poor Areas Are Sites for Generators  A study by the Pataki administration acknowledges that the sites the state has chosen for new electric generators in New York City are in poor, heavily minority communities, a finding that supports some arguments of the plan's opponents.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Jury Gets Combs Case  A Manhattan jury began deciding the fate of Sean Combs on charges of gun possession and bribery arising from a 1999 nightclub shooting. The judge took two hours to instruct the jury on deciding the case against Mr. Combs and two associates.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Of Famine, Exodus and New Life  Governor Pataki will unveil the design today for a memorial at Battery Park City commemorating Ireland's famine of the 1840's, which prompted waves of immigrants to New York.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Ali Apologizes to Frazier  Muhammad Ali said in an interview that he was wrong to call Joe Frazier an ''Uncle Tom'' and other names before their first fight 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Leopold Page  No. 173 on ''Schindler's list,'' he was 87 years old. His relentless campaign to honor the German businessman who saved his life and the lives of 1,300 other Jews during World War II led to the book and the film.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Carl A. Capasso  A businessman who played a central role in a bizarre municipal scandal involving a former Miss America, Bess Myerson, he was 55.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Dow Drops Below 10,000  The Dow fell 317.34 points, or 3.1 percent, to 9,973.46; the Nasdaq dropped 42.69 points, or 2.1 percent, to 1,972.09; and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 30.95 points, or 2.6 percent, to 1,166.71. The Dow last closed below 10,000 on Oct. 18.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Some investors are looking for a big interest rate cut next week, but the Fed is typically reluctant to appear as if it is responding to a decline in the market rather than to broader economic conditions.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Coke Bias Settlement at Risk  A groundswell of dissatisfaction has formed among the African-Americans who settled a discrimination lawsuit against Coca-Cola for $192 million, threatening to destabilize or even derail the nation's largest settlement in a racial bias case.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Bush reverses course; the burden of containment; Tina Rosenberg on destroying history's treasures.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>A20  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
