<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Antique Glass Flowers Need to Be Rejuvenated</title>
    <meta content="22ARTS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/22/arts/design/22ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1319079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard Museum of Natural History</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ware Collection of Blaschka Glass Models of Plants (Harvard)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blaschka, Rudolf</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blaschka, Leopold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flaherty, Julie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cambridge</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Museum of Natural History</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E3DE1631F931A1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1216" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Antique Glass Flowers Need to Be Rejuvenated</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even Antique Glass Flowers Need to Be Rejuvenated</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Julie Flaherty</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flaherty, Julie</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvard University is undertaking major effort to preserve Ware Collection of Blaschka Glass Models of Plants at Harvard Museum of Natural History, which was begun in 1800's and has suffered degradation over the years; project is restorative nightmare for curators because models, made primarily of glass but also some wire, paint and animal glue, are as varied in construction as species they represent; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to sex, Lopezia coronata is an aggressor. Its pinkish flower, with its pouting, spoon-shaped lower petal and the offer of sweet nectar, lures an unsuspecting hover fly. But once the insect lands and sticks its head into the blossom's depths, the stamen, hidden inside the lower petal, springs into action, whacking the underside of the fly with a puff of pollen like an excitable makeup artist.</p>
        <p>This intimate transaction is described on the discreet label that accompanies an obsessively detailed model (conduit insect included) of Lopezia coronata, a member of the primrose family. It is one of the almost 840 species represented in the Ware Collection of Blaschka Glass Models of Plants at the Harvard Museum of Natural History here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A collection of almost 840 glass flowers at the Harvard Museum of Natural History is the subject of an extensive and difficult preservation project</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to sex, Lopezia coronata is an aggressor. Its pinkish flower, with its pouting, spoon-shaped lower petal and the offer of sweet nectar, lures an unsuspecting hover fly. But once the insect lands and sticks its head into the blossom's depths, the stamen, hidden inside the lower petal, springs into action, whacking the underside of the fly with a puff of pollen like an excitable makeup artist.</p>
        <p>This intimate transaction is described on the discreet label that accompanies an obsessively detailed model (conduit insect included) of Lopezia coronata, a member of the primrose family. It is one of the almost 840 species represented in the Ware Collection of Blaschka Glass Models of Plants at the Harvard Museum of Natural History here.</p>
        <p>Most visitors know this, the museum's most popular exhibition, as simply the glass flowers. The flowers are not glass in the sparkly, crystal-figurine sense, but shaped and colored to mimic the translucence of petals and the texture of leaves. Some of these works have rested here in their cherrywood display cases for more than a century.</p>
        <p>Starting in the late 1800's, Leopold and Rudolf Blaschka, a father and son team of glass artisans in Germany, spent more than 50 years creating the collection for what was then the Botanical Museum at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>Susan Rossi-Wilcox, who began volunteering at the museum 20 years ago, fell as much for their beauty as for their romantic story. Now she is the exhibition's administrator and curatorial protector. While visitors gape at the realism of the models -- the gently ruffled edge of an orchid petal, the ripe berries on a branch -- Ms. Rossi-Wilcox sees their flaws: faded colors, delamination and fissures of various sizes on this leaf or that blossom.</p>
        <p>''People will come and say, 'Oh, they are magnificent,' '' Ms. Rossi-Wilcox said. ''But in the back of my mind I'm thinking about the extensive repairs that are needed.''</p>
        <p>Last fall, some 114 years after Harvard commissioned the Blaschkas to create the collection, the museum began a major conservation and preservation of the collection. Joshua Basseches, executive director, estimated that even a nonheroic salvage would take five years and cost at least $2 million. More extensive preservation efforts, including hiring extra staff and creating new installations, could raise the cost to $4 to $5 million.</p>
        <p>But first the curators have to figure out exactly how to go about it. The models, a multimedia mix of primarily glass, but also some wire, paint and animal glue, are as varied in construction as the species they represent, creating a restorative nightmare.</p>
        <p>The Blaschkas, who were commissioned by Harvard to make the more than 4,400 models, repeatedly changed techniques over the years. Leopold Blaschka painted his flowers. After his death, Rudolf colored the glass itself by adding elements like tin, cobalt and manganese. He formulated glass with different melting points so he could layer colors, sprinkling powdered glass on top of a flower and fusing it with heat.</p>
        <p>The conservation effort really began in 1989, when the museum did a preliminary study to catalog and prioritize the models. More recently the curators used electron microprobe analysis and X-ray diffraction to see just what substances they were dealing with.</p>
        <p>The analysis is crucial to Carlo Pantano, director of the Materials Research Institute at Pennsylvania State University and one of the glass experts Ms. Rossi-Wilcox has drafted for the project. He has proposed some molecular techniques for treating these aging artworks. One is to bathe the models in a charged oxygen gas that would react with the organic dirt, creating a harmless cloud of carbon dioxide and steam.</p>
        <p>Dirt is just one challenge. Corrosion has left a white precipitate clinging tightly to the surface of some models. (In a painful coincidence, this blight appears primarily in the models depicting fruit tree diseases.) Mr. Pantano is considering using jets of frozen carbon dioxide to blast the alkaline precipitate off the flowers, similar to the way microchips are cleaned.</p>
        <p>Then there are the cracks and breaks, which now show the brown glue smudges of previous repair attempts. Ideally the curators would repair the flowers the way the Blaschkas made them, by fusing leaves to stems with heat. But as Mr. Pantano pointed out, ''If we tried to do that now, the whole thing would probably shatter.'' One solution may be using a gel that hardens with a molecular structure similar to glass.</p>
        <p>''We could glue things back together with just plain old glue, but then they wouldn't be glass flowers anymore,'' he said.</p>
        <p>All these techniques are merely ideas for now, as the curators carefully experiment with what can be done without creating further damage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rossi-Wilcox was clear, however, on what the first step had to be: removing the most endangered plants from the museum floor. For years a number of the models were displayed on the third-floor landing where windows allowed damaging sunlight. Gusts from the stairwell made climate control impossible.</p>
        <p>The curators cringe at the thought of decades of schoolchildren's feet vibrating like jackhammers on the fragile models, truncating an iris leaf and shaking green chips off a shrubby trefoil.</p>
        <p>So far the curators have removed only the most threatened plants from their cases and put them into safer confines. ''Very carefully,'' Ms. Rossi-Wilcox said. ''And without really breathing.''</p>
        <p>A sizable number of models will stay on display during the restoration process. Mr. Basseches, the executive director, said the glass flowers were the biggest draw for the 120,000 visitors to the museum each year.</p>
        <p>''They come from Japan, Germany, Australia, Brazil,'' he said. ''I don't know how that particular exhibit developed such an international audience, but we don't necessarily have people coming from Japan saying we know you have a wonderful kronosaurus, which we do.''</p>
        <p>For some visitors the attraction is as much scientific as aesthetic. When Harvard commissioned the models in 1886, they were intended as teaching instruments, so at least their accuracy has not faded.</p>
        <p>John Thompson, a professor of ecology and evolution biology at the University of California, Santa Cruz, recently came to see the yucca. As a specialist in co-evolution, Mr. Thompson has studied the close symbiotic relationship between the yucca plant and the yucca moth. He was impressed by the accuracy of the model, down to the position of the moth's wings as it alighted on the flower.</p>
        <p>''If you've looked at a lot of moths in the field, you would know that view,'' he said. The Blaschkas, working in their lab in Germany, did not have that opportunity, but they got it just right.</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
