<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Blinkered Energy Strategy</title>
    <meta content="06SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/06/opinion/06SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D71138F935A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Blinkered Energy Strategy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial criticizes Vice Pres Dick Cheney, main architect of Bush administration's forthcoming energy package, for putting too much emphasis on increasing supplies of fossil fuels and dismissing potential of conservation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush has said that his forthcoming energy package will be a balanced mix of recommendations aimed at increasing supply and, through improved energy efficiency, lowering demand. But it will be surprising if things actually turn out that way. The main architect of the energy plan is Vice President Dick Cheney, who made clear in a speech last weekend that the plan would focus heavily on increasing supplies of fossil fuels. With the certitude that he brings to most matters, Mr. Cheney contemptuously dismissed those who would look elsewhere to satisfy the country's energy needs. ''Conservation may be a sign of personal virtue,'' he said, ''but it is not a sufficient basis for a sound, comprehensive energy policy.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Cheney well knows, there are few people who actually believe that conservation alone can satisfy the country's energy needs. The country's electrical transmission lines need upgrading, there are bottlenecks in the system that distributes natural gas, and there are undoubtedly deposits of natural gas that can be extracted with minimal environmental damage from federal lands that are already open for exploration. But conservation -- saving energy by using it more efficiently -- can also make a huge difference, and for Mr. Cheney to imply otherwise simply reinforces the suspicion that his strategy is little more than a clever effort to sell the country on the need for more drilling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush has said that his forthcoming energy package will be a balanced mix of recommendations aimed at increasing supply and, through improved energy efficiency, lowering demand. But it will be surprising if things actually turn out that way. The main architect of the energy plan is Vice President Dick Cheney, who made clear in a speech last weekend that the plan would focus heavily on increasing supplies of fossil fuels. With the certitude that he brings to most matters, Mr. Cheney contemptuously dismissed those who would look elsewhere to satisfy the country's energy needs. ''Conservation may be a sign of personal virtue,'' he said, ''but it is not a sufficient basis for a sound, comprehensive energy policy.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Cheney well knows, there are few people who actually believe that conservation alone can satisfy the country's energy needs. The country's electrical transmission lines need upgrading, there are bottlenecks in the system that distributes natural gas, and there are undoubtedly deposits of natural gas that can be extracted with minimal environmental damage from federal lands that are already open for exploration. But conservation -- saving energy by using it more efficiently -- can also make a huge difference, and for Mr. Cheney to imply otherwise simply reinforces the suspicion that his strategy is little more than a clever effort to sell the country on the need for more drilling.</p>
        <p>Take first the fuel supply. Mr. Cheney is determined to drill for oil on the coastal plain of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, which could yield as much as 600,000 barrels of economically recoverable oil per day by 2010. By contrast, the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy estimates that gradually raising the fuel efficiency of light trucks and cars to 35 miles per gallon would save 1.5 million barrels a day in 2010 and 4.5 million barrels a day by 2020 -- up to seven times what the refuge could produce. Moreover, these would be permanent energy savings that would not require invading an ecological treasure.</p>
        <p>Improved energy efficiency would also diminish the need for new power plants. In the same speech, Mr. Cheney asserted that energy demands are rising so fast that the country will need to build 1,300 new generating plants in the next 20 years. This assertion was based on a report of questionable integrity from the Energy Information Administration, an arm of the Energy Department that  has traditionally promoted conventional energy sources like coal and oil and downplayed the potential of efficiency and renewable energy. It is also the same report that Mr. Bush used to justify his decision to withdraw from the Kyoto accords on global warming.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the administration has conveniently ignored another Energy Department study published late last year -- ''Scenarios for a Clean Energy Future,'' compiled by scientists at some of the Energy Department's national laboratories.  The study argued that efficiency measures alone could obviate the need for building 610 of the 1,300 plants. For example, constructing buildings that were more energy efficient would eliminate the need for 100 plants, while rules approved near the end of the Clinton administration mandating more efficient appliances -- air-conditioners, clothes dryers and water heaters -- would save an additional 180 plants.</p>
        <p>Increased energy efficiency could even rescue the president from the folly of punching holes in the Arctic, drilling off the coast of Florida and invading the national forests along the Rocky Mountain Front. But the key Bush officials do not see the potential in conservation. In its budget, the administration actually proposed a 30 percent cut in funding for a government-auto industry partnership that is seeking to develop a new generation of energy-efficient vehicles. That partnership, an Al Gore favorite that Detroit also loves, is helping to speed development of hybrid cars that get up to 60 miles per gallon. The White House has also threatened to weaken the new standards for central air-conditioners, while the Energy Department proposes to cut in half its spending on alternative fuel sources like wind, solar energy and fuel cells.</p>
        <p>The budget holds out the hope that these research funds will be restored in 2004 -- but only with money earned from oil leases in the Arctic refuge should Congress allow drilling there. There can be no plainer illustration of the bias toward extraction that defines what we know so far about Mr. Cheney's energy strategy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
