<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Trip Aimed at Winning Over Europeans</title>
    <meta content="09PREX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/09/world/09PREX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD143EF93AA35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Trip Aimed at Winning Over Europeans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ and FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank; Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's first major overseas trip, to five counties in Europe, is intended to win over Europeans skeptical of his policies and abilities; Bush and his aides see Europe's disagreements with administration on range of issues as problems that can be overcome by president's charm and personality, as happened with Pres Ronald Reagan two decades ago; many European leaders and opinion makers view Bush as political and intellectual lightweight who has flubbed basic tests on foreign affairs, and whose position on some social issues, like capital punishment, is out of sync with that of rest of world; Bush says he will seek to reassure European allies that United States is not abandoning them by shrinking into isolationist shell; says he will try to allay their doubts about missile defense and impress on them how necessary it is in post-cold-war era; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush will carry few specific proposals when he embarks on his first major overseas trip on Monday, hoping instead that face-to-face encounters will win over Europeans skeptical of his policies and abilities.</p>
        <p>''The common European perception is of a shallow, arrogant, gun-loving, abortion-hating, Christian fundamentalist Texan buffoon,'' said a senior administration official. ''They read all the press about a hard-line unilateralist. They really believe this stuff about cowboys. We need to get it all on a higher plane.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush will carry few specific proposals when he embarks on his first major overseas trip on Monday, hoping instead that face-to-face encounters will win over Europeans skeptical of his policies and abilities.</p>
        <p>''The common European perception is of a shallow, arrogant, gun-loving, abortion-hating, Christian fundamentalist Texan buffoon,'' said a senior administration official. ''They read all the press about a hard-line unilateralist. They really believe this stuff about cowboys. We need to get it all on a higher plane.''</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Bush and his aides say they are aware of Europe's disagreements with the administration on a range of issues -- including the death penalty and the environment -- they have been depicting these as problems that could be overcome by the president's charm and personality -- as happened, experts note, with President Ronald Reagan nearly two decades ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush arrived tonight at his ranch in Crawford, Tex., where he will spend the weekend receiving briefings from his national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice. The briefings are intended to ensure that the president, who has seldom traveled abroad, will be ready to transform himself into a player on the world stage.</p>
        <p>During the five-country trip, which will include a meeting with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, Mr. Bush will confront a Europe increasingly aware of -- and prepared to exercise its economic and diplomatic influence on -- matters including missile defense, climate change, the American peacekeeping role in the Balkans and the creation of a European military force to complement NATO. European leaders have made it clear that they are uncomfortable with the American positions on those issues, and with the unilateralism that seems to underlie them.</p>
        <p>On a personal level, many European leaders and opinion makers view Mr. Bush as a political and intellectual lightweight who has flubbed basic tests on foreign affairs,  and whose position on some social issues like capital punishment is out of sync with that of the rest of the world. The perceptions will only be strengthened by the impending execution of Timothy J. McVeigh -- the first federal execution in the United States in 38 years. It is scheduled for Monday, the day Mr. Bush is to leave for his first stop, Spain.</p>
        <p>In an interview aboard Air Force One this week, Mr. Bush said he would seek to reassure the European allies that the United States was not abandoning them by shrinking into an isolationist shell. He also said he would try to allay their doubts about missile defense and impress upon them the correctness of his view.</p>
        <p>''There are some in Europe who worry about America becoming isolationists,'' Mr. Bush said. ''And I'll ease their concerns. We're an internationalist government.''</p>
        <p>He looks forward to ''making the case,'' he said, that missile defense is necessary in the post-cold-war era because ''we need to use our technologies to be able to develop ways to face down the post-cold-war threats.''</p>
        <p>The possible development of those technologies took a step forward today when the Pentagon's Ballistic Missile Defense Office announced that the next test of an interceptor ''kill vehicle,'' a major component of the missile defense system, would be conducted in mid- to late July, a year after the last test failed.</p>
        <p>Defense Department officials say that more than two dozen options are under consideration for initial deployment of missile defenses, and that no timetable exists for a decision by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Bush's visit to Spain, which was selected as the first stop in large part because the president speaks Spanish and because the administration sees Madrid as a ''center-right government,'' he will go on to Brussels, where he will address NATO. He will then travel to Goteborg, Sweden, for the United States-European Union summit meeting; fly to Poland, where he will deliver a major address on his vision of the American relationship with Europe; and then end up in Slovenia for his meeting with Mr. Putin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he would explain to Mr. Putin that the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty was no longer relevant. He will tell him that ''we don't need to be bound by a treaty that was signed when both of us viewed each other with hostility, and that we need to think differently.''</p>
        <p>Stressing the personal nature of the scheduled two-hour meeting with Mr. Putin in the Slovenian capital, Ljubljana, Mr. Bush said, ''It's very important for him to hear it from me and for me to hear from him.''</p>
        <p>The meeting with Mr. Putin is in fact a late add-on to a long-planned trip that is anchored to the United States-European Union summit meeting, a semiannual event that the White House wants to reduce to once a year because it regards the meetings as unproductive.</p>
        <p>The White House did not want to hold the meeting with Mr. Putin until later, perhaps as part of a summit meeting of seven industrialized nations and Russia in Genoa, Italy, in July.</p>
        <p>But persistent problems with China, including the American spy plane incident, officials said, made the administration reconsider the extent to which it wanted to keep Russia at arm's length.</p>
        <p>Further, in preparatory meetings for the president's trip, European officials made clear that one of the ways of diminishing the doubts in Europe about Mr. Bush was to signal that the administration could manage the relationship with Russia properly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said they had not laid out any major objectives for the meeting with Mr. Putin. ''We're not expecting major agreements here,'' Ms. Rice said in a briefing with reporters. ''What we really are doing here is establishing a foundation with these two presidents in their personal relationship that can help us to promote a constructive and realistic relationship with Russia.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice said that ''the new security framework'' would be the focus of the discussion with Mr. Putin but that other matters would be covered, including Chechnya, press freedom in Russia and Moscow's proliferation of missile technologies.</p>
        <p>Setting a more moderate tone toward Moscow than harsh remarks made by Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld just after he assumed office, Ms. Rice said, ''The president wants to signal his support for having a Russia that is really a part of Europe, that is a respected partner in international politics.''</p>
        <p>As administration officials laid out their game plan for Mr. Bush's journey, they stressed that things were not as bad between Washington and the allies as they might seem.</p>
        <p>''This is a relationship under some stress but by no means in crisis,'' said Richard Haass, the director of policy planning at the State Department. An administration team that went to Europe last month to describe the Bush ideas about missile defense prepared the way for the president's visit and allayed the basic fear that Washington would act unilaterally, Mr. Haass said.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Bush noted in the interview this week that consultations were under way. ''One of the things we did on the missile defense issue is we sent high-ranking officials to consult and spend time with -- in various capitals -- on the issues, explaining our position,'' he said. ''There's a lot of give and take. And that's important.''</p>
        <p>The White House organized the missile defense briefings after failing to take such a course on the international treaty on global warming, known as the Kyoto Protocol.  The sudden announcement that the United States would not abide by the pact contributed to the image in Europe of a high-handed White House.</p>
        <p>At a meeting in Luxembourg on Friday, the European Union's environment ministers set the stage for a standoff on global warming at the summit meeting. The ministers said the European Union would press forward with final negotiations on the Kyoto Protocol so that ratification procedures could get under way.</p>
        <p>But the White House continued to signal this week that Mr. Bush did not plan to change course.</p>
        <p>Despite unanimous support for the pact that is expected to be expressed by the 15 members of the European Union in Sweden, the administration officials said there was no flexibility in their attitude toward the Kyoto proposals.</p>
        <p>They suggested that the administration might work up a set of principles on climate warming but that this would fall far short of any proposal to modify or renegotiate the pact, which requires mandatory emission reductions.</p>
        <p>Concerning the death penalty, which is outlawed in European Union nations, it is not on the formal agenda of the summit meeting. But Mr. Bush is still expected to hear much about it during a free-wheeling dinner discussion with European leaders. Ms. Rice, asked by reporters about the awkwardness of Mr. Bush's arriving in Europe when Mr. McVeigh's execution is expected to occur, said the use of the death penalty in the United States was no one else's business.</p>
        <p>''I believe that our allies probably understand that this is a matter for the American government,'' Ms. Rice said. ''It is a matter for America's democracy, not a matter for international negotiation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
