<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Energy Executives Urge U.S. Shift on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="Y01EMIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/01/business/01EMIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0D71F3DF932A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Energy Executives Urge U.S. Shift on Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Energy Executives Urge Some Gas-Emission Limits on Bush</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN and NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C; Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy companies, which have already spent millions of dollars on voluntary efforts to cut emissions of greenhouse gases, turn their focus to Congress, as Pres Bush continues to oppose international or domestic restrictions on gases linked to global warming; Congress considers several bills that would impose emissions restrictions; some of world's biggest producers and users of energy hope that packaging mandated reductions in carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gas emissions will gain them concessions on other pollution rules; lobbying is intense, industry views are split and some executives feel left out of White House counsels (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With President Bush continuing to oppose international or domestic restrictions on gases linked to global warming, among the losers are energy companies that favor government action and have already spent millions on voluntary efforts to cut emissions.</p>
        <p>Given little credence by the White House despite large expenditures on lobbying and longstanding ties to administration officials, these companies are shifting their focus to Congress, where several bills that would impose emissions restrictions are being debated or prepared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leading energy companies are finding themselves out in the cold as President Bush continues to oppose restrictions on gases linked to global warming</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With President Bush continuing to oppose international or domestic restrictions on gases linked to global warming, among the losers are energy companies that favor government action and have already spent millions on voluntary efforts to cut emissions.</p>
        <p>Given little credence by the White House despite large expenditures on lobbying and longstanding ties to administration officials, these companies are shifting their focus to Congress, where several bills that would impose emissions restrictions are being debated or prepared.</p>
        <p>But in that effort, the companies face formidable opposition from other energy concerns and trade groups that are fighting against any limits.</p>
        <p>''There's an enormous amount of lobbying going on,'' said Rob Long, vice president for government affairs at the National Mining Association. ''It's a three-ring circus.''</p>
        <p>Among the companies that want the United States to embrace some form of greenhouse-gas limits are oil producers including the Royal Dutch/Shell Group and BP, as well as power-generating companies like Cinergy, AEP and Entergy, all of which have moved to reduce their own emissions.</p>
        <p>Another company holding this view is the Enron Corporation of Houston, whose chairman is Mr. Bush's friend Kenneth L. Lay. Enron was the largest contributor among energy companies last year to the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>These companies, which include some of the world's biggest producers and users of fossil fuels, have concluded that limits on carbon dioxide and other greenhouse, or heat-trapping, gases are inevitable. They say that by packaging reductions in greenhouse gas emissions with other environmental measures, like cutting other power plant emissions, they could win concessions on other pollution rules.</p>
        <p>And to plan long-term investments, they want the predictability that comes from quick adoption of clear rules, although more flexible ones than those agreed to in Bonn a week ago by 178 countries that have accepted the Kyoto Protocol, the worldwide climate agreement that President Bush rejects.</p>
        <p>Most of these businesses share Mr. Bush's view that the Kyoto agreement could hurt the United States economy and that it unfairly requires emissions reductions only of big industrial nations. But many officials of these companies said Mr. Bush had blundered by rejecting the agreement outright instead of trying to repair it.</p>
        <p>''What businesses want is policy certainty,'' an environmental expert for a large international energy company said. ''Bush has injected only turbulence.''</p>
        <p>For all their wealth, power and influence, though, these companies say they have been cut out of discussions at the White House. The only ideas that have risen to the highest levels there are those of companies staunchly opposing limits on emissions, according to lobbyists, government officials and executives.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration denied last night that it was excluding any options or ideas in trying to develop an approach to global warming. A White House spokeswoman, Claire E. Buchan, said: ''We are taking this issue very seriously. We're listening to constituencies who represent all perspectives.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to executives of companies seeking limits on the gases, people representing companies opposed to restrictions, including Exxon Mobil and many coal companies, said they thought that their message was resonating.</p>
        <p>Fredrick D. Palmer, executive vice president for legal and external affairs at Peabody Energy of St. Louis, one of the world's largest coal producers, said it was not really necessary to lobby the Bush administration on the issue, because Big Coal's interests and the administration's views were in sync from the start.</p>
        <p>''We don't need to be talking to the White House to know what they want,'' Mr. Palmer said. ''I understand the importance of fossil fuels to the American people. Dick Cheney understands that. The president understands that.''</p>
        <p>For the moment, the two corporate camps -- which have dominated the discussion, with environmental groups largely locked out -- have turned to Congress, where an array of influential members from both parties is hoping to seize the initiative in policy making.</p>
        <p>Senator James M. Jeffords of Vermont, the independent and new chairman of the Environment and Public Works Committee, has said that global warming is his top priority. Senator Ted Stevens, Republican of Alaska, has joined with Senator Robert C. Byrd, the veteran Democrat from West Virginia, a leading coal-producing state, in introducing a bill aimed at controlling emissions. Mr. Stevens has recently expressed deep concern about the apparently growing damage in his state from climate change.</p>
        <p>The energy industry now is focusing its efforts on the energy legislation moving through the House. But company executives and lobbyists are also meeting with members of Congress and administration officials to shape the discussion over a variety of impending emissions measures and proposed changes in regulations.</p>
        <p>In mid-August, the Environmental Protection Agency is expected to make recommendations to the White House on how to reduce releases of nitrogen oxides, sulfur dioxide and mercury from power plants.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Jeffords plans to hold meetings with industry, environmentalists and agency officials in September to seek a consensus on a bill to control the three pollutants, along with ways to limit carbon dioxide, the dominant greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>The one thing so far that unifies the energy industry is its opposition to the Jeffords emissions bill in its current form, mainly because it stipulates that old power plants install the latest technology to clean up emissions within five years. Power producers say that the timetable is too stringent and that such a change would disproportionately hurt the Midwest, where most of the power is generated by older coal-fired plants that are targets of the legislation.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, the industry separates into distinct camps. For energy companies willing to accept some limits on warming gases, one goal is to firm up a market for tradeable credits earned by companies that make sharp cuts in emissions or plant or protect forests, which absorb carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>For such credits to have value, a limit on emissions must exist, the company officials say. Aware of corporate resistance to mandatory limits, some energy industry executives and lobbyists have proposed that the government sponsor a voluntary program to reduce emissions. Once enrolled, companies would have to meet mandatory goals on reductions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>''We haven't said there must be mandatory caps on CO2,'' said Jeffrey Keeler, director of environmental strategies at Enron. ''But it's been proven that voluntary programs don't work well; that's why we are where we are today. We can have limits from the top down and not endanger the economy.''</p>
        <p>Whether the Bush administration will accept even voluntary limits remains to be seen. And later this year, the White House will again be the focus of policy making.</p>
        <p>Businesses that share the view Mr. Bush expressed in March, when he rejected any binding limits on the warming gases, whether in a global accord or federal legislation, say they are confident that there will be no big shifts.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Long, the mining association official, said he was perplexed by those companies that want to reduce carbon dioxide, which his group and its allies do not see as a pollutant or a threat to the environment.</p>
        <p>''I think some of this is the hangover from the Clintonian era, when some of these emissions changes seemed inevitable,'' he said. ''And I think some people got locked into that mind-set. I think the world changed in January. It can't have escaped their notice that the new president won't support constraints on CO2 .''</p>
        <p>One of the staunchest foes of limits on carbon dioxide is the Southern Company of Atlanta, whose nuclear and coal-fired plants span Georgia, Florida, Alabama and Mississippi, and whose donations to the Republican Party last year were second only to Enron's.</p>
        <p>The company recently enlisted Haley Barbour, a former chairman of the Republican National Committee, as a lobbyist. Mr. Barbour mainly works to loosen enforcement of environmental regulations affecting utilities, though other Washington lobbyists said that he had also argued against action on reducing carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barbour did not return phone calls yesterday seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Power companies trying to find a way to reduce carbon dioxide emissions think they have greater sway with Congress than they have with the White House. ''The closer we get to midterm elections,'' a utility executive said, ''both sides of the Hill will feel a high degree of vulnerability on environmental issues, and some will retreat from the White House if they feel they need to.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, opponents of emissions limits are not assuming that the Kyoto accord is dead, despite its having been greatly weakened by the rejection from the United States, the biggest emitter of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Their lobbyists were out in force at last week's negotiations in Bonn, and they said they would keep working to defeat the international agreement, which is still subject to ratification in scores of countries. Among other things, they plan to keep pressure on the Bush administration to propose no alternatives -- particularly anything resembling a limit on greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>''The protocol is like the Titanic,'' said Glenn Kelly, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, which has fought against the Kyoto agreement using contributions from industries that regard gas restrictions as a threat.</p>
        <p>Eventually, he said in an interview in Bonn, the Kyoto Protocol will hit an iceberg, but that will not be the end of the matter. ''After it sinks,'' he said, ''there are still going to be lifeboats that survive to be picked up by the next ship that comes along.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
