<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; Rudeness Awakens America</title>
    <meta content="13CROS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/13/weekinreview/13CROS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations Human Rights Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Narcotics Control Board</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlantic</location>
        <location class="online_producer">European Union</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Austria</location>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sweden</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Richardson</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations Human Rights Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">International Narcotics Control Board</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Human Rights Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Assembly</org>
        <org class="online_producer">House of Representatives</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Freedom House</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Security Council</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Annan, Kofi</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Richardson, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF1F3BF930A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; Rudeness Awakens America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States is jolted at losing American seats in last week and half on United Nations Human Rights Commission and International Narcotics Control Board; event symbolizes evolution of whole new set of relationships between United States and two emerging power blocs--developing world bloc known as G77, and European Union--with strong interests of their own that may come in conflict with American interests; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OVER the last decade, as the United States looked down from the peak of world power, its officials may have overlooked some currents rising below. While the demise of the Soviet system left only one superpower standing, it also freed scores of other nations from the gridlock of East-West confrontation, and they began to build new or stronger alliances outside Washington's reach.</p>
        <p>In the developing world, a bloc known as the G77 that now includes 133 African, Asian and Latin American countries can command a two-thirds majority in the United Nations. Across the Atlantic, the European Union has 15 members and will grow more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OVER the last decade, as the United States looked down from the peak of world power, its officials may have overlooked some currents rising below. While the demise of the Soviet system left only one superpower standing, it also freed scores of other nations from the gridlock of East-West confrontation, and they began to build new or stronger alliances outside Washington's reach.</p>
        <p>In the developing world, a bloc known as the G77 that now includes 133 African, Asian and Latin American countries can command a two-thirds majority in the United Nations. Across the Atlantic, the European Union has 15 members and will grow more.</p>
        <p>Diplomats and American officials say it was these two groups, not normally allies, that came together for one startling moment to jolt the United States in the last week and a half, snatching away American seats on the United Nations Human Rights Commission and the International Narcotics Control Board in a secret vote in the Economic and Social Council.</p>
        <p>The event symbolized a much larger phenomenon: the evolution of a whole new set of relationships between the United States and two emerging power blocs with strong interests of their own that may frequently come in conflict with American interests. Most of the world's nations may now be democratic to one degree or another, but that does not unite them. The challenge is to learn how to manage the differences and to separate the truly crucial ones -- over economic needs, peace, the environment, for example -- from irritants.</p>
        <p>In this light, the sabotaging of American membership on the Human Rights Commission -- apparently an act of cumulative annoyance after years of American rejection of international agreements, the hounding from office of Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali, and Congressional  blocking of dues that beggared the United Nations -- looks like overkill to many Americans. But it has also sounded an alarm.</p>
        <p>''This is one of those seminal events -- like Zionism equals racism -- that is going to haunt us for a long time,'' said Richard N. Gardner, a Columbia University law professor who was in last year's American delegation to the General Assembly. The fear is  that poisoned feelings on all sides could make it more difficult, as Israel-bashing did in the 1970's, for the United States to work  with the United Nations on critical matters, like containing Iraq, for which Americans have needed the United Nations in the past.</p>
        <p>The House of Representatives did strike back last week, voting to withhold $244 million in overdue payments to the United Nations, but paying a $582 million bill.</p>
        <p>Jeane J. Kirkpatrick, President Ronald Reagan's United Nations ambassador and a frequent critic of the organization, nevertheless thinks Congress aimed at the wrong target. ''Kofi Annan didn't cause our problems, and the U.N. secretariat didn't cause our problems,'' she said in an interview. ''Withholding funds from the U.N., we don't really affect the people whom we would like to affect.'' Those responsible, she said, were the Europeans, who didn't relinquish a seat to America when there were four candidates for three slots on the Human Rights Commission, and apparently voted as a bloc for Austria, France and Sweden.</p>
        <p>Since the end of the cold war, Dr. Kirkpatrick said, one of the most important changes in the world has been the consolidation of the European Union, and ''with that has gone an increased influence of France, with its characteristic exclusiveness.''</p>
        <p>Among the developing nations, an Asian ambassador said, votes were cast against the United States for several reasons, including what many see as a paucity of American aid and opposition to American efforts to hold individual countries up to human-rights scrutiny, in particular China. Arthur C. I. Mbanefo, Nigeria's ambassador and last year's chairman of the G77. said poor countries were only flexing muscles in their national interests as Americans do.</p>
        <p>Concerted attacks on the United States are, of course, nothing new in international bodies, but rarely have such strong efforts been made to exclude Americans from what they have come to consider their rightful place at a lot of tables.</p>
        <p>In some ways, the global advance of democracy is part of the problem. In many more nations, public opinion matters, and television audiences can see -- and resent -- how their presidents are treated on visits to Washington or how Americans rank their concerns. So even if many countries now share an interest in advancing democratic  principles, one Asian ambassador said, ''no one has said we must vote for each other'' when interests clash.</p>
        <p>At Freedom House in New York, the president, Adrian Karatnycky, differed, saying it should be possible to build coalitions based on political and civil liberties and adding that there is a danger when ''a bunch of countries are playing with these rather sacrosanct values to make other kinds of extraneous points.'' He dismissed European explanations that the Bush administration's rejection of the Kyoto treaty on global warming was reason enough to punish the United States. ''If you link the Kyoto treaty to human rights, you're doing it to the detriment of both,'' he said.</p>
        <p>MR. GARDNER and some foreign diplomats fault the American  mission here for inept handling of the campaign for the Human Rights Commission seat. But Bill Richardson, chairman of Freedom House's board and a Clinton-era ambassador to the United Nations, pointed in an interview to other issues. He recommended courting the developing bloc, ''perhaps by renewing our efforts to expand the Security Council to include them, and build coalitions'' among its members when their interests clash with Europe's, as on trade and immigration.</p>
        <p>In any event, he and other former American ambassadors to the United Nations seem in agreement that the worst message to send would be a threat of blackmail, as in the congressional demand that the United States be re-elected to the Human Rights Commission before final bills are paid. ''It gives another tool to those who deprived us of the seat,'' Mr. Richardson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
