<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President Promises to Increase Spending on Backlog of Repairs at the National Parks</title>
    <meta content="Y31BUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/31/politics/31BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1297758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sequoia National Park (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <location class="online_producer">White House (Washington, DC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California (USA)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Sequoia National Park (California)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">San Joaquin Valley (California)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Agriculture Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sequoia</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7DB113CF932A05756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President Promises to Increase Spending on Backlog of Repairs at the National Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>SEQUOIA NATIONAL PARK, Calif., May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush announces plans to increase federal spending to help end backlog of billions of dollars in repairs to national parks; makes pledge during visit to Sequoia National Park in California; critics from national environmental groups embrace plan to spend $5 billion over next five years to repair national parks, but say Bush's priorities are misplaced and his spending too stingy; White House earlier backed away from its contention that Bush would set aside $1 billion for making park repairs in next year's budget; it is unclear how much of Bush's proposed $5 billion figure is actual increase; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first major speech about the environment since he took office, President Bush stood beneath the ancient sequoias here today and announced plans to increase federal spending to help end a backlog of billions of dollars in repairs to national parks.</p>
        <p>''Our duty is to use the land well, and sometimes, not to use it at all,'' Mr. Bush said, clearly seeking to answer critics who had protested his hopes of drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, to build hundreds of new power plants and to start from scratch on any accord with  developed and developing nations  over global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first major speech about the environment since he took office, President Bush stood beneath the ancient sequoias here today and announced plans to increase federal spending to help end a backlog of billions of dollars in repairs to national parks.</p>
        <p>''Our duty is to use the land well, and sometimes, not to use it at all,'' Mr. Bush said, clearly seeking to answer critics who had protested his hopes of drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, to build hundreds of new power plants and to start from scratch on any accord with  developed and developing nations  over global warming.</p>
        <p>Many of those critics from national environmental groups said today that while they embraced Mr. Bush's plan to spend $5 billion over the next five years to repair the national parks -- repaving roads, cutting new trails and fixing decrepit sewage and water systems -- his priorities were misplaced and his spending too stingy.</p>
        <p>The White House had to back away from its contention early in the day that Mr. Bush would set aside $1 billion for making park repairs in next year's budget, now before Congress. The Interior Department's  budget request said $439.6 million would be spent for that purpose next year, with $61 million of that involving new appropriations from Congress. The rest would build on money the Clinton administration had planned to spend or redirect fees collected from park concessions. Previously, the parks could use the concessions money as they chose.</p>
        <p>While the $5 billion figure is impressive, it is unclear how much of it is an actual increase, as the department spends limited amount each year on repairs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's speech today ended a  two-day trip to California, including a tense meeting with Gov. Gray Davis, a Democrat, on Tuesday over how to deal with the state's energy crisis.</p>
        <p>Today, White House officials sought a backdrop that would help emphasize their insistence that Mr. Bush understood the need for both environmental protection and careful development. They selected the park that the naturalist John Muir helped create in 1890.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he was asking Interior Secretary Gale A. Norton to create annual ''stewardship plans'' to operate parks more efficiently and take better care of their resources. He said he would also create an annual ''State of the Parks Report.''</p>
        <p>In a brief interview, Ms. Norton confirmed reports that she was effectively putting a moratorium on the acquisition of land for the national parks. ''We are really trying to focus on taking care of what we have,'' she said after joining Mr. Bush on a short, steep hike to Moro Rock, where they had a spectacular view of the Sierras. ''There is so much more political attention to creating new parks, but it's a lot harder to get support for fixing a lot of the problems that we have found.''</p>
        <p>All national parks, which are run by the Interior Department, are off limits to mining, oil and gas exploration and drilling, which are policies Mr. Bush says he will continue.</p>
        <p>Most of the criticism from Democrats and conservation groups involves the administration's plans for national forests, which are run by the Agriculture Department, and other federal lands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's energy plan, released two weeks ago, directs the secretary of the interior ''to examine land status and lease stipulation impediments to federal oil and gas leasing'' and to speed environmental studies that have held up more leasing of those lands for exploration and development of energy resources. The plan stipulates that any such action must be ''consistent with the law, good environmental practice and balanced use of other resources.''</p>
        <p>But he made no mention of those directives today, or of the Sequoia National Forest and similar lands that could be affected by that initiative. Nor did he discuss the problem that park rangers here say is one of the most disturbing as they try to preserve Sequoia National Park: the effects of ozone that settles over the Sierras from the nearby San Joaquin Valley.</p>
        <p>William Tweed, a park official, said today that ozone had ''shortened the life of yellow pines'' in the park, but did not appear to have affected the giant sequoia. ''The tiny seedling sequoia seem to suffer,'' Mr. Tweed  said, making it difficult for new groves of the rare trees to prosper.</p>
        <p>He noted that Moro Rock, which Mr. Bush visited today, ''is one of the best places to see air pollution'' as it settles in the valley.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday the administration said it would not challenge rules put out in the last days of the Clinton administration to impose pollution controls on aging power plants near the national parks, which would reduce haze that has severely cut views from places like Moro Rock.</p>
        <p>The Sequoia National Park has been a symbol for the kind of changes that environmental groups have been calling for throughout the park system. It has spent tens of millions of dollars tearing down cabins that were built on top of the roots of the grand trees and evicting food sellers and trinket shops from park buildings near the most spectacular Sequoia. Mr. Bush spent Tuesday night at a new lodge on the perimeter of the park that was intended to make up for the lost rooms for visitors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
