<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bush's Words: ABM 'Prevents a Full Exploration of Possibility'</title>
    <meta content="Y13PTEX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/13/world/13PTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aznar, Jose Maria (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3DB113EF930A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bush's Words: ABM 'Prevents a Full Exploration of Possibility'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from news conference by Pres Bush and Prime Min Jose Maria Aznar in Madrid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference by President Bush and Prime Minister José María Aznar after their talks yesterday in Madrid, as recorded by Federal News Service Inc. Prime Minister Aznar's remarks were provided by a interpreter.</p>
        <p>Q. (TO MR. BUSH) -- The E.U. today rejected your global warming initiative, Mr. President, and weeks of consultations have not eased objections to your missile defense plans in most European capitals. I have two questions on that. Are these issues so important that you're willing to go it alone if the European allies won't come on board? And what is your response to the E.U. today calling your climate change plan short on results?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from a news conference by President Bush and Prime Minister José María Aznar after their talks yesterday in Madrid, as recorded by Federal News Service Inc. Prime Minister Aznar's remarks were provided by a interpreter.</p>
        <p>Q. (TO MR. BUSH) -- The E.U. today rejected your global warming initiative, Mr. President, and weeks of consultations have not eased objections to your missile defense plans in most European capitals. I have two questions on that. Are these issues so important that you're willing to go it alone if the European allies won't come on board? And what is your response to the E.U. today calling your climate change plan short on results?</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH -- Well, first, there's a lot that unites us -- trade, common values, great opportunities. I look forward to making my case, as I did today over lunch, about missile defense.</p>
        <p>It starts with explaining to Russia and our European friends and allies that Russia is not the enemy of the United States, that the attitude of mutually assured destruction is a relic of the cold war and that we must address the new threats of the 21st century if we're to have a peaceful continent and a peaceful world. Those new threats are terrorism, based upon the capacity of some countries to develop weapons of mass destruction and therefore hold the United States and our friends hostage. . . .</p>
        <p>As far as global warming, I made a strong statement yesterday that said our nation is concerned about CO2 emissions and that we've begun the process to address that problem. I started with an energy plan that on the one hand talks about conservation measures. Our country can and will do a better job of conserving energy.</p>
        <p>But I also talked about new supplies that will not harm the environment -- renewables, natural gas and clean nuclear energy. And I hope the United States Congress responds positively to these measures, which will help in the global warming issue.</p>
        <p>I also said our nation is willing to continue to spend money on science, to make sure that any collective approach is one based upon sound science.</p>
        <p>I did speak out against the Kyoto Treaty itself because I felt the Kyoto Treaty was unrealistic, was not based upon science. The stated mandates in the Kyoto Treaty would affect our economy in a negative way. On the other hand, I did say loud and clear that we must continue the process of dialogue. . . .</p>
        <p>PRIME MINISTER AZNAR -- It's absolutely understandable for any president to be concerned about the security of his citizens, and in this particular case, obviously, there is a concern that's shared as a result of the collective security that we share. I sincerely believe that no one should be surprised that when we pose issues based on overcoming the past of the cold war, policies going beyond the cold war, presentations that go beyond the historical conflict of the cold war, and we talk about new threats, new challenges, new problems, new challenges in general, again, in security we come to new initiatives. . . .</p>
        <p>With regard to the second issue, on the environment, as you know, Spain continues to support the position of E.U., and it has ratified the Kyoto Protocol. I understand that we have positions that may have some differences, but . . . President Bush has adopted some initiatives, and those initiatives need to be studied by the E.U. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. (TO MR. BUSH) -- About your decision to withdraw from the Kyoto Protocol. . . . Do you agree that the European view on this is colored more by emotion than by science, and do you think that there is some hint of posturing in some of their criticism? . . .</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH -- I believe the Kyoto Treaty is a flawed treaty. I think that it set unscientific goals. It didn't include developing countries. On the other hand, I want to reiterate today, and I will do so throughout the week, that we're committed to reducing greenhouse gases in the United States. I had the opportunity to explain to the president that our nation faces an energy crisis, and it's a serious issue.</p>
        <p>We've got incredible trading opportunities between our nations and between the United States and the E.U. In order for us to be active traders, our nation's economy must recover. We've taken some steps toward that. We've got a sound monetary policy by the Federal Reserve. We've got a new fiscal stimulus package that is going to take effect soon. But we also must address energy, and we can do so in a way that not only enhances our economy, a way that makes us less dependent on foreign sources of crude oil and a way, as well, that helps clean the environment. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. -- I would like to ask President Bush how will this commitment that you have taken on to help Spain in the fight against terrorism be translated? What can the United States do? How can the United States provide any assistance, bearing in mind that in Spain our ethical principles do not allow us to apply the solution that you apply, the death penalty, for terrorists. . . .</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH -- Freedom-loving people are going to be faced with terrorism, and countries such as ours must not yield, must not waiver in the face of terrorist activity. And to the extent that we can help the government of Spain to fight terrorism within its borders, we will do so. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. (TO MR. BUSH) -- You say the scientific evidence isn't strong enough to go forward with Kyoto. So how then do you justify your missile defense plan when there is even less scientific evidence that that will work?</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH -- Part of the problem with the ABM Treaty is that it prevents a full exploration of possibility. We're bound by a treaty signed in 1972 that prohibits the United States from investigating all possibilities as to how to intercept missiles. For example, the technology of intercept-on-launch is a technology that we must more fully explore in order to make sure that we have the defensive capabilities necessary to prevent what I call blackmail. So part of the reason we're having the dialogue in the first place is to enable us to explore all our options. . . .</p>
        <p>The ABM Treaty is a relic of the past. It prevents freedom-loving people from exploring the future, and that's why we've got to lay it aside, and that's why we've got to have the framework, the discussions necessary to explain to our friends and allies, as well as Russia, that our intent is to make the world more peaceful, not more dangerous.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
