<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Polar Puzzle Inspires Extreme Acts of Science</title>
    <meta content="17POLE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/17/science/17POLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1286190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Pole</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Soviet Union</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlantic</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Oregon</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Science Foundation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">John, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEED81E31F934A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Polar Puzzle Inspires Extreme Acts of Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists step up their efforts to monitor changes in environment around North Pole, including chilling of high stratosphere, shifts in movement and temperature of surface air and sea water and apparent thinning and shrinking of milling cap of ice floating on Arctic Ocean; changes match computer predictions of how frozen north could respond to buildup in atmosphere of heat-trapping greenhouse gases, mainly carbon dioxide released by burning fossil fuels; team encamped at very top of world has embarked on ambitious five-year effort to take pulse of polar air, ice and ocean depths; drawings; charts; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For two decades and counting, with a growing mix of fascination and concern, scientists have been measuring big changes in the environment around the North Pole.</p>
        <p>These include a chilling of the high stratosphere, shifts in the movement and temperature of surface air and sea water and, most visibly, an apparent thinning and shrinking of the milling cap of ice floating on the Arctic Ocean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For two decades and counting, with a growing mix of fascination and concern, scientists have been measuring big changes in the environment around the North Pole.</p>
        <p>These include a chilling of the high stratosphere, shifts in the movement and temperature of surface air and sea water and, most visibly, an apparent thinning and shrinking of the milling cap of ice floating on the Arctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>The changes match computer predictions of how the frozen north could respond to the buildup in the atmosphere of heat-trapping greenhouse gases, mainly carbon dioxide released by burning fossil fuels. But the situation in the Arctic remains far from clear, and the changes could also be part of some undetected long-term cycle, many polar experts say.</p>
        <p>Now scientists are intensifying their efforts to determine the causes of the changes -- natural or human -- and the potential consequences.</p>
        <p>Over the last two weeks, at a tenuous encampment at the very top of the world, a team of researchers, coping with frigid winds and solar storms that cut radio links with the outside world, went into high gear on an ambitious five-year effort to take the pulse of the polar air, ice and ocean depths.</p>
        <p>Instruments that send climate data via satellite were placed on the ice, and others were strung along two miles of cable lowered last week through a hole in the ice and anchored to the floor of the Arctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>The encampment, the North Pole Environmental Observatory, run by scientists from the University of Washington, was, of necessity, temporary, because the ice cap is always moving.</p>
        <p>An initial foray took place last year, and the camp -- evacuated Sunday -- will be rebuilt from scratch at the North Pole each April through 2004, under a $3.9 million grant from the National Science Foundation.</p>
        <p>The project is being watched by many oceanographers and climate scientists hungry for fresh data from that end of the earth.</p>
        <p>''We know very little about the rhythms up there,'' said Dr. Richard B. Alley, an expert on the age-old cycles of glaciers and sea ice and a professor of earth sciences at Penn State.</p>
        <p>Collecting basic data on salinity, ice thickness, temperature and the like is crucial, he said, because only with such sustained monitoring can trends and their causes be spotted.</p>
        <p>The work is also expected to help computer scientists fine-tune models that simulate global climate. Despite substantial progress, the models  only roughly approximate the matrix of interactions by the ocean, atmosphere and ice that shapes conditions in northern latitudes.</p>
        <p>''Of all the places in the world where we're seeing big changes in climate over the past couple of decades, these are the most dramatic,'' said Dr. John Michael Wallace, a professor of atmospheric science at the University of Washington, who is not directly involved in the project.</p>
        <p>Much of the research involves ice. Because it reflects sunlight and thus helps make a cold place even colder, widespread melting of arctic ice could accelerate a warming trend.</p>
        <p>''Permanent summertime melting of the whole Arctic could happen in a few decades if trends of the last 20 years continue,'' Dr. Wallace said. On the other hand, the recent ice retreat ''could be a short-term flip.'' After years of unusual conditions,  ''typical'' wind and barometric pressure patterns returned last year, and some scientists predicted a much icier summer in the Arctic.</p>
        <p>Other scientists have challenged the data pointing to a sharp thinning of the ice cap recently, and some  contend that the shrinking of the ice-covered area at the pole has been a trend for a century or more, not a new anomaly.</p>
        <p>It is all the more important, then, many scientists say, to solve this polar puzzle. But seeking the necessary clues is about the closest science gets to an extreme sport.</p>
        <p>The quest to reach and comprehend the nature of the North Pole has claimed dozens of lives, from causes including starvation, freezing, carbon monoxide asphyxiation of crews shivering over coal ovens in icebound ships and even poisoning of a captain by a mutinous crew.</p>
        <p>In much of the 20th century, the Soviet Union took the lead, maintaining a series of research stations on the polar ice from the 1940's until 1991. The research ended with the economic collapse after the fall of communism. Soviet data, released over the last few years, have provided a valuable, although limited, window on earlier decades, said Dr. James H. Morison, the University of Washington oceanographer directing the new polar project.</p>
        <p>But, he added, the Russian effort ended ''just as all this change started up there.''</p>
        <p>More recent research efforts have probed the region, some by icebreaker or Navy submarine. But good data are scattered and hard to come by.</p>
        <p>Unlike other regions, which offer scientists evidence in tree rings, ancient glacial ice or layers of sediment from seasonal plankton, the pole is largely bereft of clues to its climates past. The nearest glaciers, in Greenland, reflect mainly conditions in the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>The clues that do exist are tantalizingly vague. A recent study reported  scratches made by icebergs on an underwater ridge near the pole, suggesting the sea was once shallow and the ice sheet vast. But there is no way to tell the age of the marks.</p>
        <p>The new polar team of scientists from several American universities and a Japanese marine research center established a base camp on April 2 less than 30 miles from the geographic pole. Equipment and fuel were delivered in a series of air drops from fat-bellied cargo planes; scientists shuttled to the site in the small Twin Otter craft from a Canadian military base on Ellesmere Island, 500 miles south.</p>
        <p>The operation faced various challenges. Several flights to the ice were delayed by gales and snow. Researchers described polar weather  more than 20 degrees colder than normal for early April, with temperatures often falling to 40 degrees below zero as they huddled in three fabric huts. Intense solar storms interrupted radio communications, meaning that planes taking off for the three-hour flight to the pole had no word on the conditions awaiting them.</p>
        <p>One scientist heading to the project from Oregon via an Air National Guard base in upstate New York found herself temporarily stranded last week when a C-130 craft was diverted from its regular Greenland run to Antarctica, as part of an effort to reach a doctor at the research base there, who was stricken with pancreatitis.</p>
        <p>Unlike similar research stations at the South Pole, where an underlying continent has allowed countries to build sophisticated science villages, the Arctic encampment had to be built on a river of ice that rises off the Siberian coast, then grinds its way through the Fram Strait east of Greenland.</p>
        <p>As a result, the station itself was on the move, shifting up to several miles a day as the polar ice, pushed by winds and currents, slowly drifted over the point at which the world turns.</p>
        <p>Even in early spring, the ice, which is usually 10 feet thick or thicker, provides an uncertain foundation. One morning, an inspection of the camp's ice runway disclosed a two-foot-wide crack that had opened since the night before.</p>
        <p>If all goes as planned, the technology left behind on and beneath the ice -- including compact, rugged, computer-controlled instruments similar to space probes -- will create the first continuous profile of changes in the air, ice and ocean depths at the pole itself.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the project is the four-ton chain of instruments anchored to the sea floor. Held aloft by glass fishing-net floats, the chain reaches up like a giant synthetic kelp frond. At the top, just 150 feet or so below the ice, is an upward-focused sonar device designed to keep a yearlong record of the thickness of the ice drifting overhead.</p>
        <p>From there down to the sea floor, more than a dozen instruments will track currents, salinity, temperature, and other conditions at various depths. Next year, an acoustical signal from above will release the cable from its base and send it floating up under the ice, said Dr. Richard E. Moritz, the University of Washington oceanographer whose prime focus is the ice-measuring sonar.</p>
        <p>The cable also has a beacon like those some skiers wear in case they are buried in an avalanche. From the ice or an icebreaker, the scientists will home in on the signal. The recovery team will include at least two divers, in case the cable is snarled on one of the jumbled submerged ice ridges that crisscross the ice cap.</p>
        <p>Then the plan is to repeat the drill, resetting the underwater instrument chain for two more years.</p>
        <p>''It's a gamble,'' said Dr. Moritz, adding that there are a dozen ways the project could fail. But answers to many key questions lie beneath the ice, and so the risky effort proceeds.</p>
        <p>A central challenge is to track changes in the sharply defined layers of ocean water under the ice.</p>
        <p>Water in the top 100 yards or so, fed by four rivers that flow into the Arctic Ocean and by melting ice, tends to be relatively fresh and frigid. Under it is much warmer, saltier water that flows into the Arctic Ocean from the Atlantic, in one of the ocean's endless conveyer belts that move heat from the Equator.</p>
        <p>This influx of Atlantic water appears to have grown and warmed sharply in recent years, the scientists say.</p>
        <p>And a thin layer of water of intermediate temperature and salinity that normally lies between the cold, fresh surface and the warm, salty depths vanished in the 1990's, said Dr. Douglas G. Martinson, an oceanographer at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University. In theory, this has allowed more heat from the deep Atlantic water to reach the ice, accelerating its melting.</p>
        <p>Dr. Martinson said expectations for the new research should be tempered because even a five-year study is only nibbling at the edges of environmental phenomena that could have cycles of decades or centuries.</p>
        <p>''This work is unlikely to give you the answer you want,'' said Dr. Alley, at Penn State. ''But it's work that has to happen to get to the answer you want.''</p>
        <p>Now that the researchers have flown home, only the automated probes remain, steadily recording</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
