<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Problem, Local Alarm</title>
    <meta content="04WARM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1275194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DE1138F937A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Problem, Local Alarm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on warnings from planners and scientists that Long Island should begin preparing for effects of global warming in response to United Nations-sponsored report and regional analysis projecting that wetlands, beaches and coasts will be submerged within several decades if current trends continue; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG ISLAND should prepare now for the incremental effects of global warming, planners and scientists said last week in response to an international report that offered some dire predictions.</p>
        <p>The United Nations-sponsored report and a regional analysis of it project that warming may submerge wetlands, batter beaches and coasts, flood low-lying areas, increase rainfall and bring more storms and hurricanes within the next several decades if current trends continue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG ISLAND should prepare now for the incremental effects of global warming, planners and scientists said last week in response to an international report that offered some dire predictions.</p>
        <p>The United Nations-sponsored report and a regional analysis of it project that warming may submerge wetlands, batter beaches and coasts, flood low-lying areas, increase rainfall and bring more storms and hurricanes within the next several decades if current trends continue.</p>
        <p>The first observable sign of global warming on Long Island, officials said, would be the gradual disappearance of coastal wetlands and South Shore salt marsh islands caused by rising sea levels, a process some research suggests may have already begun.</p>
        <p>''The wetlands would be the first thing to go,'' said Lee E. Koppelman, executive director of the Long Island Regional Planning Board. ''And then, of course, all the low-lying areas.''</p>
        <p>''The lead time we have to prepare for sea-level rise may be shortened,'' said Jay Tanski, a geologist for New York Sea Grant, a network of universities conducting coastal research. ''We are going to have to start thinking about our policies and management strategies.''</p>
        <p>Local effects of global warming, Mr. Tanski and others said, could include loss of wetlands like those in the Mastic-Shirley area and a gradual submersion of the salt marsh islands in Nassau County. Sea Grant maps showed significant shoreline inundation would be apparent by 2050 in South Shore areas be apparent by 2050 in South Shore areas like Freeport and Merrick, where wetlands were filled for housing and boating canals.</p>
        <p>like Freeport and Merrick, where wetlands were filled for housing and boating canals.</p>
        <p>The global report, released last month by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, was based on research by scientists from 99 nations. It said global temperatures could increase by up to 10.5 percent by 2100 because of greenhouse gases from industry, power generators and motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>Entitled ''Climate Change 2001: Impacts, Adaptation and Vulnerability,'' the report said that climate change would come sooner and be more severe than previously predicted, underscoring the need for global agreements to reduce air pollution.</p>
        <p>Researchers said the predicted temperature increase over the next century would exceed the cumulative global warming of the past 10,000 years, or nearly the length of time Long Island has existed. The worldwide result, they said, would be drought, famine, floods and altered weather patterns.</p>
        <p>In a regional analysis based on the projections of the United Nations panel, the United States Environmental Protection Agency said the effects in New York could include more days of extreme summer heat, higher concentrations of ground-level ozone associated with heat spells, 20 percent more rain, warmer and wetter conditions that would foster more mosquitoes and ticks, and more intense and frequent algal blooms in warmer water.</p>
        <p>The agency said that the state's coastal waters had been rising at 10 inches a century, but were likely to rise an additional 22 inches by 2100. With greater vulnerability to storms, South Shore barrier islands face severe damage, the agency said.</p>
        <p>It said loss of wetlands and flooding of low-lying areas would be accompanied by beach erosion, saltwater intrusion into drinking water, and shorter life spans for coastal roads and bridges.</p>
        <p>Researchers for the Metro East Coast Regional Assessment, a group that analyzes the effects of global warming, said that gradual changes in a 31-county metropolitan area including Nassau and Suffolk ''may be punctuated by surprises such as severe precipitation events.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cynthia Rosenzweig, an environmental research scientist at Columbia University and co-leader of the regional assessment, said that 100-year storms, defined as severe storms that happen on average once a century, could occur once every 40 years or as frequently as once every 4 years.</p>
        <p>The regional group also concluded that most salt island marshes in Jamaica Bay, an area it studied, would be lost within 30 years if trends continued. It said the islands appeared to be drowning for reasons yet to be determined but that could include a rise in sea level.</p>
        <p>''We need to start getting ready,'' Dr. Rosenzweig said. ''We need to begin to take these projections of climate change on board now so we can prepare to adapt at minimum cost.''</p>
        <p>Adapting could involve building up beaches with dredged sand; shore-hardening with sea walls and bulkheads to hold back high water; and revisions of regulations to allow maintenance of wetlands.</p>
        <p>The response could also involve a measured retreat from the shorelines. Robert DeLuca, president of the Group for the South Fork in Bridgehampton, said storm recovery plans were needed that stopped redevelopment of areas at risk.</p>
        <p>''For many years the guiding policy for shoreline development has been that any potential impacts from global warming were so far off in the future we didn't have to plan for them,'' Mr. DeLuca said. ''This new research suggests we have to prepare for serious shoreline changes in very realistic time frames.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Koppelman said that while hurricanes ''produce at once what global warming will take a century to produce'' more gradual changes caused by higher water were difficult to observe and less likely to prompt government response. He said the changes occurred outside the normal 10-to-20-year scope of planning.</p>
        <p>But he said temporary flooding during storms previewed what would become permanent as sea level rose.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tanski of Sea Grant said the predicted rate of sea-level rise might be too great for wetlands to adjust naturally or retreat inland. He said a revamping of regulations to allow intervention might be necessary. Some regulations that sought to protect wetlands in the short term might harm them in the long term in the face of rising sea levels, he said.</p>
        <p>The recent research may spur the use of beach nourishment as an early response to global warming, particularly on the South Shore barrier islands. ''The report is very clear that beaches and dunes should be raised,'' said Gerard Stoddard, the president of the Fire Island Association and chairman of the Long Island Coastal Alliance.</p>
        <p>Some communities already make allowances for the rising sea level. Bruce Nyman, the city manager of Long Beach, said the recent predictions hit hard in a city where ''some places are almost below sea level now.''</p>
        <p>''Most of the homes on the coast were built before global warming was even in the dictionary,'' Mr. Nyman said. ''Now, when we bulkhead, we bulkhead higher.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Koppelman said international action to reduce pollution was all that would spare the region and the world. ''The real planning has to be to control pollution in the first instance,'' he said. ''Otherwise we'll be riding gondolas to the World Trade Center.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
