<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe's Chance in the Mideast</title>
    <meta content="16WHEA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/16/opinion/16WHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1309798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wheatcroft, Geoffrey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium/Brussels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Tel Aviv</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany/Berlin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway/Oslo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">England,Europe,America,Middle East,Israel,Washington,European Union,Brussels (Belgium),Paris,Tel Aviv (Israel),London,Berlin (Germany),United States,Oslo (Norway)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Le Monde</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.,Jospin, Lionel,Arafat, Yasir,Wagner, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DB123BF935A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe's Chance in the Mideast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe's Chance in the Mideast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geoffrey Wheatcroft</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wheatcroft, Geoffrey</byline>
      <dateline>BATH, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoffrey Wheatcroft Op-Ed article on role Europe may be able to play as broker in Middle East conflict (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a range of issues from global warming to the small arms trade, the policy gulf between Europe and America is noticeably widening. But one potentially important area of divergence is among the least noticed: the Middle East conflict, where Europe and America have sharp differences and where, at the same time, Europe may be set to play an increasingly prominent part.</p>
        <p>Many Israelis would be alarmed by this suggestion: Israeli governments have always been very wary about encouraging any European role. But the changing political landscape -- not least the Bush administration's uneasy attempt to stand back from the conflict -- could make one necessary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are sharp differences between Europe and America's policies toward the Middle East, and Europe may be set to play an increasingly prominent role</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a range of issues from global warming to the small arms trade, the policy gulf between Europe and America is noticeably widening. But one potentially important area of divergence is among the least noticed: the Middle East conflict, where Europe and America have sharp differences and where, at the same time, Europe may be set to play an increasingly prominent part.</p>
        <p>Many Israelis would be alarmed by this suggestion: Israeli governments have always been very wary about encouraging any European role. But the changing political landscape -- not least the Bush administration's uneasy attempt to stand back from the conflict -- could make one necessary.</p>
        <p>At present, relations between Israel and European governments are not at all good. President Bush and Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel may have agreed to differ, but Mr. Sharon's welcome in Washington was positively effusive compared with the reception he received in Europe. He was unable even to visit the European Union headquarters in Brussels because of a Belgian judge's threat to arrest him on human rights charges. Then came a glacial meeting with Prime Minister Lionel Jospin in Paris. Afterward, Mr. Sharon said grimly that the discussion was held ''in a very clear manner'' and ''it is evident we do not agree at all points.''</p>
        <p>Not that the Israelis have ever agreed on all points with the Europeans. Quite apart from the terrible shadow of history, there is a rooted Israeli belief that most European governments lean toward the Palestinians. And many Israelis are convinced of a European media bias in coverage of the conflict.</p>
        <p>There is some evidence for that view. On the day after the horrific Tel Aviv disco bombing, a cartoon appeared on the front page of Le Monde. Captioned ''Kamikazes,'' it showed two figures side by side, both with bundles tied in belts round their waists. One was a Palestinian suicide bomber with sticks of explosive, the other an Orthodox Jewish settler, whose bundles were buildings labeled ''Colonies.'' This cartoon could scarcely have appeared in any mainstream American paper.</p>
        <p>No doubt its implication of moral equivalence was unusually sharp. But there is a prevalent view in Europe, expressed much more often than in America, that Israeli settlements are one root of the problem and need to be addressed. Likewise, Paris, London and Berlin have been more blunt than Washington in condemning assassination of Palestinian militants and other repressions of the uprising. And virtually all Europeans, unlike many Israelis, think that Israel should stick with Yasir Arafat as a negotiating partner, if only for lack of a better alternative.</p>
        <p>Given all of this, prospects for a European role in the Middle East may not look promising. And yet there is another side to the story. Israel is in many ways a European country, and relations with Europe are both intimate and fruitful. Israel is certainly closer to Europe than America, not just on a map but culturally and commercially. Israel bears many political marks of its origins under the British Mandate, and of the various European theorists who helped build the country.</p>
        <p>Most Israeli universities, newspapers and orchestras were created by European emigrants. The latest fierce row in the country concerned Daniel Barenboim, an Israeli who has spent much of his career in Europe, conducting a European orchestra in a performance of the music of Richard Wagner, most definitely a European composer -- one whose music was adored not only by Hitler but by Theodor Herzl, founder of political Zionism. On a more popular level, Israeli teams compete in European soccer tournaments, if not with much recent success, alas.</p>
        <p>What is at least as important (and may be unrecognized in America) is that Israel imports about twice as much from the E.U. as from the United States, and American tourists to Israel are outnumbered almost three to one by Europeans. Israel may resent European criticisms, but it can't live without European ties.</p>
        <p>If Europe is drawn more and more into the Middle East, it won't be for only economic reasons. Political nature abhors a vacuum, and one is being created by President Bush's dislike of intimate involvement in the conflict. There is also the undoubted fact that the whole process known as ''Oslo'' -- it could be called ''Clinton'' -- has faltered, and may be near death.</p>
        <p>Indeed, throughout the Middle East American influence is palpably weakening. Maybe that was only a matter of time. Washington has long tried to perform an awkward juggling act, closely supporting Israel while doing its best to befriend Arab countries and to play the honest broker. It isn't very surprising if the Arabs at last reject the idea that America is an even-handed intermediary.</p>
        <p>It could be that the relationship between Israel and America has had counterproductive consequences for Israel. And it might even be advantageous for Israel to negotiate with the Palestinians through an alternative intermediary that is considered genuinely neutral.</p>
        <p>There could be benefits for Europe also. The European Union may be an effective free trade area, but it does not, as yet, have an effective common foreign or defense policy. Henry Kissinger used to say that he would take ''Europe'' seriously when it had a telephone number he could call in a crisis. Might the bitter and intractable battle in the Holy Land provide the occasion for making Europe a real, working toll-free number?</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Wheatcroft's books include ''The Controversy of Zion: Jewish Nationalism, the Jewish State, and the Unresolved Jewish Dilemma.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoffrey Wheatcroft's books include ''The Controversy of Zion: Jewish Nationalism, the Jewish State, and the Unresolved Jewish Dilemma.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
