<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Peter Shapiro; Death of a Deadhead Dive</title>
    <meta content="05NITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/05/fashion/05NITE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A Night Out With"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wetlands (Nyc Nightclub)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shapiro, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/A Night Out With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Preserve</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Preserve</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wetlands</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Wetlands</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Dylan, Bob</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dylan, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DB123CF936A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A NIGHT OUT WITH: Peter Shapiro; Death of a Deadhead Dive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Peter Shapiro: Death of a Deadhead Dive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Night Out With column follows Wetlands nightclub owner Peter Shapiro on tour of his favorite night spots; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THURSDAY, 11:45 p.m. at Wetlands, a k a Wetlands Preserve, a k a the TriBeCa club that is closing Sept. 15 to make way for yet another set of condominiums.</p>
        <p>Blueground Undergrass, a six-man band from Atlanta, was about to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wetlands owner Peter Shapiro is enjoying the last days of his club, saddened by its closing, but optimistic that he and it will be back</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THURSDAY, 11:45 p.m. at Wetlands, a k a Wetlands Preserve, a k a the TriBeCa club that is closing Sept. 15 to make way for yet another set of condominiums.</p>
        <p>Blueground Undergrass, a six-man band from Atlanta, was about to play.</p>
        <p>''Let's check out some tunes,'' Peter Shapiro said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro, who bought Wetlands five years ago from the club's founder, Larry Bloch, waded into the small but enthusiastic crowd in front of the stage. As the lights darkened, he stepped forward in anticipation, beer in hand. The band began to jam, and the crowd swayed in mellow synch to a sound that was eerily like the Grateful Dead.</p>
        <p>For 13 years, seven days a week, Wetlands has been a place for New York music fans, kids from New Jersey and Long Island and overage hippies from all over to listen to live bands of the kind that prefer extended jam sessions to tight set lists or screaming guitars. With its battered bar and random Christmas lights, Wetlands has been a refuge from the moneyed attitude of trendier boîtes like NV and Jet Lounge a few blocks north. At this club for the neo-hippie set, patrons do not wear $700 distressed jeans or designer tie-dye. Just old jeans and T-shirts.</p>
        <p>Perhaps 10,000 bands have played here, including Pearl Jam and Rage Against the Machine. It may be the only club in the world with an ''activism center,'' where between sets, the young and idealistic can sign petitions to stop global warming.</p>
        <p>''It's been my life,'' said Mr. Shapiro, a scruffy blond who is a big hugger.</p>
        <p>Around 12:30, with Blueground Undergrass in full swing, Mr. Shapiro made his way to the band room.</p>
        <p>''This is where I like to hang out,'' he said, plopping down on a worn, aggressively ugly orange and gray couch. This colorfully dingy room directly behind the stage is covered with thousands of band stickers and obscure graffiti that's piled up over the years. ''Every night, it's like throwing a party,'' Mr. Shapiro said.  He made his way back to the stage. About 100 fans stood out front, swaying, as the band launched into an extended jam with Mike Gordon, the bass player from Phish. A couple of marijuana pipes worked their way through the crowd. One was offered to Mr. Shapiro. He declined.</p>
        <p>The nights blur together, Mr. Shapiro said, good and bad, though a few stand out. On the club's 10th anniversary, Bob Weir, of the Grateful Dead, played with the Hanson brothers. At 1:30 a.m., Mr. Shapiro was keeping the party alive. ''More shots,'' he yelled, corralling employees, who gathered for a toast to the club.</p>
        <p>Then Blueground Undergrass took a break, and some of the audience filed into the night. Mr. Shapiro left with them. He still had one more club to visit. This club is very new. It does not yet exist. A developer planning to put up a commercial building on a parking lot a few blocks from Wetlands has asked Mr. Shapiro to help create a 1,500-person venue for live shows.</p>
        <p>Of course, community boards must be appeased and financing arranged at a time when finance is increasingly scarce. The odds are long. But Mr. Shapiro has faith.</p>
        <p>''I could see in my head the stage right here,'' he said, leaning against the chain-link fence protecting the lot. The new club will be big and modern, but suffused with the same gentle energy that filled Wetlands. Bob Dylan for four nights, intimate shows with artists like Sheryl Crow.</p>
        <p>''This is my dream,'' he said, looking at the delivery trucks parked silently on the asphalt. ''To take the spirit of what that place is and take it to the next level.''</p>
        <p>A Night Out With</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
