<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gephardt Launches an Attack on Bush's Foreign Policy</title>
    <meta content="Y03GLO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/03/international/03GLOB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1314274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanker, Thom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gephardt, Richard A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Richard A Gephardt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0DB153CF930A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gephardt Launches an Attack on Bush's Foreign Policy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gephardt Launches an Attack on Bush's Foreign Policy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOM SHANKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shanker, Thom</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Richard A Gephardt accuses Bush administration of obsession with missile defense and of pursuing unilateralist approach to world affairs that risks antagonizing Russia and undermining relations with Europe; vows to unite Democrats and persuade Republicans to forge bipartisan majority in Congress to block any missile defense system that would violate 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty; defends formal arms control negotiations as essential to maintaining nuclear peace; says NATO allies are worried that Bush administration has embraced go-it-alone policy that undermines international security, hurts economic and environmental interests and prevents US from seizing opportunity for engagement with Russia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Drawing clear battle lines with the White House on foreign policy, Representative Richard A. Gephardt accused the Bush administration today of an obsession with missile defense and of pursuing a unilateralist approach to world affairs that risks antagonizing Russia and undermining relations with Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt, the House minority leader, vowed to unite Democrats and persuade Republicans to forge a bipartisan majority in Congress to block any missile defense system that would violate the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty. He also defended formal arms control negotiations as essential to maintaining the nuclear peace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt accused the Bush administration Thursday of pursuing a unilateralist approach to world affairs that risks undermining relations with Europe</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Drawing clear battle lines with the White House on foreign policy, Representative Richard A. Gephardt accused the Bush administration today of an obsession with missile defense and of pursuing a unilateralist approach to world affairs that risks antagonizing Russia and undermining relations with Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt, the House minority leader, vowed to unite Democrats and persuade Republicans to forge a bipartisan majority in Congress to block any missile defense system that would violate the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty. He also defended formal arms control negotiations as essential to maintaining the nuclear peace.</p>
        <p>On Russia, Mr. Gephardt sketched his version of a framework for new relations, one that would reject ultimatums on missile defenses and warhead reductions but never shy from complaining about Russian failures to protect press freedoms, ethnic relations and religious tolerance. Eventually, he said, the goal would be to ''extend to Russia the prospect of NATO membership.''</p>
        <p>The Missouri Democrat, widely seen as an undeclared candidate for his party's presidential nomination in 2004, recently returned from a visit to Europe and Russia, and said NATO allies ''are worried that America is on the sidelines.''</p>
        <p>''They think the Bush administration has embraced a go-it-alone policy that undermines international security, hurts our economic and environmental interests and prevents us from seizing a historic opportunity for engagement with Russia,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gephardt's speech, given to the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace today, is added to recent statements from three Senate Democrats -- Carl Levin of Michigan, chairman of the Armed Services Committee; Joseph R. Biden of Delaware, chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee; and Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the majority leader -- a consensus party agenda on international security comes sharply into focus.</p>
        <p>While differences are inevitable, the Democrats generally unite in arguing that nuclear deterrence still works, even against Iraq and North Korea. They broadly agree that there is no need to rush deployment of missile defenses, although continued research and development, within treaty constraints, in pursuit of a limited system is a national interest.</p>
        <p>The Democrats also hold that President Bush, by rejecting important treaties, is leading Americans into a new isolationism that will weaken their ability to pursue a broad range of global interests, and that the United States should return to negotiations on global warming and stick to peacekeeping commitments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt focused his harshest criticism on the Bush administration's dealings with Moscow on arms control and missile defense.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Russia, he said: ''This is a country that is strapped financially in the most severe way. And they've got multiple thousands of warheads. How can they keep them in repair? How can they avoid accidents? Are we worried about their command and control, about something getting out of hand? So that to me is the major threat that we still face. And treating that in a sensible way is severely complicated by our obsession with going ahead with this missile defense plan, which we haven't proven can work, and we haven't developed, and that we certainly haven't worked out with the Europeans and the Russians.''</p>
        <p>The president's senior advisers say that the Bush administration will apply the standard of American national interest in determining whether to support or reject international accords. For example, in the case of the Kyoto Protocol on global warming, administration officials say, the pact would damage the American economy and harm global financial health.</p>
        <p>And on relations with Russia, the administration has stated that the ABM treaty is outdated and stands in the way of moving rapidly toward both historic reductions in arsenals and building a defense against ballistic missiles launched by an enemy -- or accidentally by Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt said the administration ''has ratcheted up its unilateral rhetoric,'' which he said had led to ''the largely symbolic, yet potentially destabilizing treaty between Russia and China, designed in part to counter U.S. global dominance.'' He was referring to a treaty of ''friendship and cooperation'' signed by the two countries last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt said the president's policies had already resulted in Russian threats to place more nuclear warheads on its missiles and a Russian decision to block American efforts to strengthen international sanctions on Iraq.</p>
        <p>''These examples, I think, demonstrate a simple yet profound fact of international relations,'' he said. ''One nation, acting alone, cannot possibly build a lasting strategic framework to which all other nations submit.''</p>
        <p>After the speech, Ari Fleischer, the White House press secretary, tossed the unilateralist charge back at Mr. Gephardt, accusing him of working to shackle the president's authority to negotiate trade deals and saying that he and other Democrats were thwarting the tenets of the North American Free Trade Agreement by trying to keep Mexican truckers off American highways.</p>
        <p>''Given his isolationist record on Mexico, on Nafta, on free trade, the president hopes that Mr. Gephardt will pursue a more internationalist course this fall on trade promotion authority,'' Mr. Fleischer said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt had anticipated that charge in his speech, saying that in order to get a trade agreement through Congress, ''it's got to have enforceable provisions on labor and environmental matters'' and on human rights.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
