<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Cast of Creatures At Steinbeck's Monterey Bay</title>
    <meta content="06MONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/06/science/06MONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010207T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1268667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Monterey Bay (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hopkins Marine Station (Monterey Bay, Calif)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4DA113EF935A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Cast of Creatures At Steinbeck's Monterey Bay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Biologists at Hopkins Marine Station on California's Monterey Bay report on disappearance of a number of species that were abundant in 1930's and arrival in large numbers of species rarely seen in bay back then; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his novel ''Cannery Row,'' John Steinbeck describes ''the parklike property'' of the Hopkins Marine Station, the research center Stanford University has operated for more than 100 years at the edge of Monterey Bay.</p>
        <p>It is said that Edward F. Ricketts, the proprietor of a nearby biological supply house who befriended many a student at the marine station, was the model for the novel's Doc, who sold research specimens to schools and researchers. ''The sea rocks and the beaches were his stockpile,'' Steinbeck wrote of Doc. ''He knew where everything was when he wanted it. All the articles of his trade were filed away on the coast, sea cradles here, octopi here, tube works in another place, sea pansies in another. He knew where to get them. . .''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his novel ''Cannery Row,'' John Steinbeck describes ''the parklike property'' of the Hopkins Marine Station, the research center Stanford University has operated for more than 100 years at the edge of Monterey Bay.</p>
        <p>It is said that Edward F. Ricketts, the proprietor of a nearby biological supply house who befriended many a student at the marine station, was the model for the novel's Doc, who sold research specimens to schools and researchers. ''The sea rocks and the beaches were his stockpile,'' Steinbeck wrote of Doc. ''He knew where everything was when he wanted it. All the articles of his trade were filed away on the coast, sea cradles here, octopi here, tube works in another place, sea pansies in another. He knew where to get them. . .''</p>
        <p>In 1939, Ricketts, Jack Calvin, an illustrator and photographer, and Joel W. Redpath, a marine biologist, described this abundance in ''Between Pacific Tides,'' a prodigiously detailed inventory of all the living creatures, plant and animal, that were to be found in the bay.</p>
        <p>Since then, the book, published by Stanford University Press, has periodically undergone revisions. The latest edition shows, though, how much life has changed in Monterey Bay. A number of species abundant in the 1930's are disappearing from the bay today. And other species, rarely seen in the bay then, have settled in, in large numbers.</p>
        <p>Why? No one can say for sure. Overharvesting, human interference with habitat through jetty construction or other activities are possible culprits. But in a study reported recently in Ecological Monographs,  Raphael D. Sagarin, a graduate student at the University of California at Santa Barbara who has worked at the marine station, and other researchers, noted that the diminished species were predominantly cold-water creatures and that the newcomers seemed to have moved in from the south. This suggests that warmer water, possibly the result of human-induced climate change, is responsible, at least in part.</p>
        <p>''There is no doubt that Homo sapiens is one of the most powerful organisms ever to reside on this planet,'' David W. Phillips wrote in the epilogue to the latest edition of ''Between Pacific Tides.'' ''What remains to be discovered is what we will do with our power -- create a park or produce a cesspool -- for it is clear that not all our hopes for the shore are compatible.''</p>
        <p>'The tide goes out imperceptibly. The boulders show and seem to rise up and the ocean recedes leaving little pools, leaving wet weed and moss and sponge, iridescence and brown and blue and China red. On the bottoms lie the incredible refuse of the sea, shells broken and chipped and bits of skeleton, claws, the whole sea bottom a fantastic cemetery on which the living scamper and scramble.'</p>
        <p>JOHN STEINBECK  ''Cannery Row''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 7, 2001, Wednesday  An article in Science Times yesterday about changes in the ecology of Monterey Bay in California misspelled the name of the author of ''Between Pacific Tides.'' He was Joel W. Hedgpeth, not Redpath.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 7, 2001, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about changes in the ecology of Monterey Bay in California misspelled the name of the author of ''Between Pacific Tides.'' He was Joel W. Hedgpeth, not Redpath.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
