<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Find Way to Gauge Earth's Glow</title>
    <meta content="Y21EART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/science/21EART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Big Bear</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Acton</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Union's committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DB1030F932A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Find Way to Gauge Earth's Glow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The eerie glow of earthshine -- sunlight bouncing off Earth and striking the Moon -- makes the dark part of the Moon's disk just barely visible to the naked eye. Now a team of astronomers and physicists has done what the eye cannot. They have detected slight variations in the glow, in effect, variations in how much sunlight Earth reflects hour by hour, season to season and year to year.</p>
        <p>They say the results lend tenuous support to a highly controversial theory that Earth is cloudier, and therefore reflects more sunlight, when the Sun is near the minimum of its 11-year activity cycle and has the fewest sunspots and solar storms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The eerie glow of earthshine -- sunlight bouncing off Earth and striking the Moon -- makes the dark part of the Moon's disk just barely visible to the naked eye. Now a team of astronomers and physicists has done what the eye cannot. They have detected slight variations in the glow, in effect, variations in how much sunlight Earth reflects hour by hour, season to season and year to year.</p>
        <p>They say the results lend tenuous support to a highly controversial theory that Earth is cloudier, and therefore reflects more sunlight, when the Sun is near the minimum of its 11-year activity cycle and has the fewest sunspots and solar storms.</p>
        <p>Other scientists are praising the researchers' technique, which they say may one day be useful in studies of climate. But they dismiss the  early conclusions as little more than moonshine. These critics say they fear the findings will give support to critics of the idea that greenhouse gases cause global warming.</p>
        <p>But the team of researchers, who made their observations at Big Bear Observatory in California and who will report their findings in the May 1 issue of Geophysical Research Letters, say they are simply turning to earthshine as a way of sharpening scientists' knowledge of how much solar radiation Earth reflects.</p>
        <p>''If you think about what drives our climate, it's the net sunshine that reaches us,'' said Dr. Philip R. Goode, the leader of the research and the director of Big Bear, which is owned by the New Jersey Institute of Technology. ''That depends on the sun's output and how much the mirror of the Earth reflects.''</p>
        <p>Earth's overall reflectivity, or albedo, depends almost entirely on cloud cover and is difficult to measure with any certainty using satellites, said Dr. Loren Acton, a solar physicist at Montana State University who was not involved in the research. He said satellites were often too close to see the big picture.</p>
        <p>Using earthshine is ''pretty straightforward and pretty clever,'' Dr. Acton said.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Stephen H. Schneider, a Stanford climatologist, said it was ''very unlikely'' that solar activity could replace greenhouse gases as the likely cause of global warming.</p>
        <p>The new measurements, which used a small telescope outfitted with an electronic camera, were made over about seven years.The observations resurrected an idea tried by a French astronomer in the 1930's, said Dr. Steven E. Koonin, a professor of theoretical physics at the California Institute of Technology who collaborated on the work.</p>
        <p>Dr. Koonin said that in the early 1990's, he realized new techniques for translating the earthshine into an albedo could turn earthshine into an important tool.</p>
        <p>Observers grew accustomed to seeing fluctuations of up to 10 percent in the earthshine over a single night. They also saw unexpectedly large seasonal variations.</p>
        <p>The scientists also found sketchy indications that the average albedo was a few percentage points greater around 1995, a minimum of solar activity, compared to the present, a period of maximum activity.</p>
        <p>That sort of difference might be expected according to the controversial notion that cosmic rays, or high-energy particles from space, seed clouds. The more powerful magnetic fields generated by the Sun during maximum activity are known to block many of the particles, which would theoretically lead to less cloud cover and less reflection, or a lower albedo.</p>
        <p>But many scientists challenge that theory. Aside from the issue of whether cosmic rays really do seed clouds, Dr. Schneider said, some clouds primarily trap heat, warming Earth, and others mainly reflect sunlight, cooling it. Cosmic rays would presumably make both kinds.</p>
        <p>Other climate experts echoed that caution but said it did not doom earthshine as a novel way of peering back at Earth.</p>
        <p>''It's a valuable new tool for looking at a fundamental aspect of Earth's climate,'' said Dr. Eric Sundquist, a geochemist at the United States Geological Survey and chairman of the American Geophysical Union's committee on global environmental change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
