<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: Man in the News; Edmund Spencer Abraham</title>
    <meta content="Y03ABR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/03/politics/03ABRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DC103BF930A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: Man in the News; Edmund Spencer Abraham</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Man-in-the-News biographical profile of Spencer Abraham, former US senator nominated as energy secretary by Pres-elect George W Bush; he was born Edmund Spencer Abraham on June 12, 1952 in East Lansing, Mich (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spencer Abraham, a conservative Michigan senator who has fought to abolish the Department of Energy during his Congressional career, is now poised to take it over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham would assume control of a federal agency he has decried as wasteful and ungainly, with ''no core mission.'' In 1999 he made his third effort in five years to abolish the department, joining forces with three other senators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spencer Abraham, a conservative Michigan senator who has fought to abolish the Department of Energy during his Congressional career, is now poised to take it over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham would assume control of a federal agency he has decried as wasteful and ungainly, with ''no core mission.'' In 1999 he made his third effort in five years to abolish the department, joining forces with three other senators.</p>
        <p>''Energy oversees everything from nuclear waste disposal to energy conservation to corporate welfare,'' Mr. Abraham wrote in a 1997 opinion article in The Washington Times, in which he also called for abolishing the Commerce Department. ''What is not unneeded or harmful in this list would be better secured without Energy's wasteful umbrella organization.''</p>
        <p>Such candor in the name of cutting taxes and reducing the federal bureaucracy is a trademark of Mr. Abraham, a one-term senator who lost his re-election bid in November. His voting record is solidly conservative; he opposes abortion, favors free trade and dislikes environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>But he has occasionally challenged the Republican orthodoxy, particularly in successfully fighting Republican colleagues' efforts to restrict legal immigration.</p>
        <p>Edmund Spencer Abraham was born in East Lansing, Mich., on June 12, 1952, the son of an autoworker and the grandson of Lebanese Christian immigrants. During the last session  of Congress he was the only Arab-American senator.</p>
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush said Mr. Abraham would be deeply involved in establishing an energy policy that will include finding ways to meet rising demand through greater domestic production.</p>
        <p>''He's ready to join me in seeking energy security for the United States,'' Mr. Bush said. ''We understand our national security depends on energy security.''</p>
        <p>A Bush transition spokeswoman said today that Mr. Abraham was traveling and not available to comment on his efforts to abolish the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>In accepting the nomination, he described himself as proud and eager to take up the task of addressing the nation's consumption needs while remaining sensitive to the environment. In praising the incoming administration's expertise, he appeared to be acknowledging the oil backgrounds of both Mr. Bush and Vice President-elect Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>''As we know,'' Mr. Abraham said, ''many significant Energy Department-related issues face us at this time, ranging from the adequacy of supply, to affordability, to the development of new technologies, to the issues of security at our facilities, and more. Fortunately, this administration is comprised of many individuals with incredible expertise in these areas, and I look forward to helping the president-elect to effectively address these challenges in the days ahead.''</p>
        <p>But his selection worried conservationists, who see the emerging Bush cabinet as increasingly hostile to their interests.</p>
        <p>Daniel F. Becker, director of the Sierra Club's global warming and energy program, said Mr. Abraham's ties to automotive interests had led him to oppose efforts to require greater fuel efficiency in sport utility vehicles. Overseeing fuel mileage falls under the purview of Transportation, not Energy, but some environmental activists feared that even so, Mr. Abraham would work against tighter regulations.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line here,'' Mr. Becker said, ''is that President-elect Bush is choosing a senator who led the fight for more gas-guzzling S.U.V.'s -- to go find the oil to keep them running.'' He added that the Sierra Club, assessing the last Congress on environmental issues, had given Mr. Abraham its lowest rating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham stands to inherit control of a troubled department with sweeping jurisdictions -- over the nation's weapons laboratories, the cleanup of nuclear waste sites and the management of the Strategic Petroleum Reserve.</p>
        <p>The agency has been shaken by recent security breaches at its research laboratories, as well as lawmakers' efforts to reduce its budget and manage its contractors. The new energy secretary is likely to face a series of challenges from the start, including electricity shortages on both coasts next summer and efforts among some OPEC nations to keep oil prices high.</p>
        <p>The agency will also have primary responsibility for cleaning up nuclear weapons construction sites. It will also probably face new controversy over Mr. Bush's plan to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration, a move fiercely opposed by conservationists.</p>
        <p>Robert Alvarez, a former senior Energy Department official, said the agency's responsibilities were so far-flung and disparate that they required ''a tough-minded manager who can define a vision and unify this department at a time when it is essentially falling apart.''</p>
        <p>Allies of Mr. Abraham say that with his intelligence and political contacts, he is up to the task. At Harvard Law School he founded the Federalist Society, a conservative legal activist group, and began a conservative version of the law review. His closest political allies include Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader, and Gov. John Engler of Michigan.</p>
        <p>After serving as Michigan State  Republican Party chairman at the age of 30, he became deputy chief of staff to Vice President Dan Quayle in 1990. He was elected to the Senate in 1994, the first Republican in more than two decades to take a seat from that centrist state.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
