<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Federal Case in Suffolk: Eco-Terrorism or Adolescence in Bloom?</title>
    <meta content="18ELF.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/18/nyregion/18ELF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Earth Liberation Front</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rammelkamp, Matthew T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcintyre, Jared</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mashkow, George III</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cash, Connor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">fires_and_firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">robberies_and_thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Groups and Movements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Suffolk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Central Islip</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Oregon</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Wisconsin</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle Island</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Center Moriches</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brookhaven</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Longwood</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cold Spring</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Montauk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Portland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">elaine</location>
        <org class="online_producer">York office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">core group</org>
        <org class="online_producer">core</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3D71130F93BA25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Federal Case in Suffolk: Eco-Terrorism or Adolescence in Bloom?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article examines contrasting views about Suffolk County teenagers who pleaded guilty in federal district court in Central Islip, NY, to setting fires to protest anti-sprawl mission of Earth Liberation Front; US government portrays them as terrorists, while their lawyers maintain they are impressionable teenagers in over their heads; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last two months, a rash of destruction in Suffolk County -- fires set in newly built subdivisions, anti-meat graffiti, torched construction equipment -- posed a puzzle: Was it the work of a smart, devoted band of eco-terrorists or young vandals merely blowing off adolescent steam?</p>
        <p>Last week, after three high school students pleaded guilty in the incidents, and a 19-year-old was charged as the mastermind, it appeared that both possibilities might have shreds of truth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last two months, a rash of destruction in Suffolk County -- fires set in newly built subdivisions, anti-meat graffiti, torched construction equipment -- posed a puzzle: Was it the work of a smart, devoted band of eco-terrorists or young vandals merely blowing off adolescent steam?</p>
        <p>Last week, after three high school students pleaded guilty in the incidents, and a 19-year-old was charged as the mastermind, it appeared that both possibilities might have shreds of truth.</p>
        <p>To hear the United States government tell it, the local youths are terrorists. They constitute a Suffolk cell of the Earth Liberation Front, a militant environmental terrorist group whose ''campaign of violent crime has stretched from the Pacific Coast to the Rocky Mountains to the Midwest,'' said Barry W. Mawn, the head of the New York office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for two of the youths, however, paint their clients as impressionable teenagers who got in over their heads. They described them as bright young people who learned about the Earth Liberation Front through the Internet and who made the mistake of acting to carry out its anti-sprawl mission here on Long Island.</p>
        <p>The contrast in views about the suspects was underscored on Wednesday in United States District Court in Central Islip. As one of the teenagers, Matthew Rammelkamp, prepared to plead guilty to arson conspiracy, the judge, William D. Wall, looked down from the bench and asked sternly if he had used any drugs.</p>
        <p>''I've taken medicine for acne,'' Mr. Rammelkamp, 16, said. ''Acutane.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, the handful of crimes in Suffolk County in December and January appear less dramatic when compared with some of the other violence the Earth Liberation Front has claimed responsibility for since 1997: a $12 million arson at a mountaintop ski resort in Vail, Colo.; a $1 million arson at a lumber company's office in Oregon; and the freeing of 310 minks, ferrets and polecats from a research farm in Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>When the Long Island group sought to burn an upscale subdivision in Middle Island on Dec. 9, three of four gasoline-and-punk incendiary devices failed to ignite. Their plot to free some ducks from a Center Moriches farm failed miserably. And a later plan to burn the farm was never carried out.</p>
        <p>The four charged in the attacks do not seem to fit the profile of the stereotypical terrorist. Mr. Rammelkamp is a first-rate student, takes advanced placement biology, plays electric guitar and wants to go to college, his mother, Debra, said. Jared McIntyre, 17, who is the son of a New York Police Department sergeant, is studying global warming at the Brookhaven National Laboratory and writes for the Longwood High School newspaper, The Lion's Roar. George Mashkow III, 17, is bright but troubled, a poor student who is easily led, his lawyer said. All three pleaded guilty to arson conspiracy.</p>
        <p>The fourth youth, Connor Cash, 19, is more of a mystery, but officials said he had been arrested before. Mr. Cash has maintained his innocence.</p>
        <p>What little information has emerged about the four teenagers has been spun in contrasting webs. Either they plotted a wave of federal crimes together or they landed in hot water for amateurish pranks.</p>
        <p>''I am banking all my years of working with juveniles that this kid is no terrorist,'' said Charles C. Russo, the lawyer for Mr. Mashkow.</p>
        <p>''He is a kid in crisis. He is not an impassioned environmentalist that is working for a cause,'' he said. ''He succumbed to the peer pressure here and he joined in this vandalism. Yeah, it is high-end vandalism, but it is vandalism. There are environmental terrorists out there, but they are infecting these kids through the Internet. These kids are not the leaders of these environmental attacks.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the motivations of the four, one thing is clear: ELF has claimed credit for more destruction in Suffolk than the arrested teenagers have been blamed for, including the trampling, last July, of a Cold Spring Harbor cornfield used in genetic research, the first ELF act covered in local news reports.</p>
        <p>Loretta E. Lynch, the United States attorney for the Eastern District, was asked a series of questions at a news conference on Thursday about the case. Was another ELF cell active on Long Island? Did these teenagers take directions from the group? In most cases, Ms. Lynch declined comment, and the questions seemed to hang in the air like a Montauk fog.</p>
        <p>Other investigators admitted to being mystified.</p>
        <p>''Is this all of it or is there more out there?'' a law enforcement official asked in an interview, noting that the police had not proclaimed victory in the case or said that the movement was dead.</p>
        <p>George A. Stamboulidis, the assistant United States attorney prosecuting the case, declined comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rammelkamp's lawyer, Thomas F. Liotti, said the three youths who pleaded guilty had no connection to any centralized ELF leadership, and he criticized the federal government for bringing the case against them.</p>
        <p>Richard J. Kaufman, the lawyer for Mr. McIntyre, has declined comment on the case, as has Frederick K. Brewington, the lawyer for Mr. Cash.</p>
        <p>Craig S. Rosebraugh, a spokesman for ELF in Portland, Ore., said the youths were strangers to him. But Elaine D. Close, who works with him, said their actions fit the group's model of acting in autonomous groups with no chain of command.</p>
        <p>''People take actions under the guidelines of the ELF. The guidelines are very widely circulated, and have been for quite a while,'' Ms. Close said. ''But beyond that, I don't know if there is anything we can add.''</p>
        <p>One theory to consider, said Bill Wasley, the director of law enforcement for the United States Forest Service, is that the teenagers were recruited by a core group of nomadic ELF members who came to Long Island, planted the seeds of their movement, and disappeared. Alternatively, he said, the core members may limit their supervision of the movement to anonymous instructions via the Internet.</p>
        <p>Despite the unanswered questions about the case, the indictments were  significant because they represented the first major infiltration by law enforcement into more than $30 million worth of damage for which ELF has claimed responsibility.</p>
        <p>But here in New York, the activity appears to have been halted -- at least for now. No more communiqués announcing mayhem in Suffolk have come from Mr. Rosebraugh's Portland office. No more Suffolk subdivisions have gone up in flames.</p>
        <p>Lest anyone consider further violence, however, Mr. Mawn of the F.B.I. offered one parting shot.</p>
        <p>''The ELF has a motto, which it often leaves in spray paint at the scene of the crime. It reads, 'If you build it, we will burn it,' '' he said. ''In response, let me say, 'If you burn it, we will find you.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
