<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDE1E3AF937A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>178 Nations, but Not U.S., Agree on Emissions Curbs  One hundred seventy-eight countries agreed in Bonn to require industrial countries to cut emissions of gases linked to global warming, a deal that rescued the preliminary accord, the Kyoto Protocol, by softening it. The United States stayed on the sideline. President Bush has repudiated Kyoto as ''fatally flawed'' for placing too much of the clean-up burden on industrial countries and for being too costly to the American economy.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>178 Nations, but Not U.S., Agree on Emissions Curbs  One hundred seventy-eight countries agreed in Bonn to require industrial countries to cut emissions of gases linked to global warming, a deal that rescued the preliminary accord, the Kyoto Protocol, by softening it. The United States stayed on the sideline. President Bush has repudiated Kyoto as ''fatally flawed'' for placing too much of the clean-up burden on industrial countries and for being too costly to the American economy.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pope's Plea on Embryos  John Paul II, speaking with President Bush at his side, condemned creation of human embryos for research as an evil akin to euthanasia and infanticide. Mr. Bush is weighing whether to allow federal financing for embryonic stem cell research.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Firm on Missile Shield  President Bush said that ''time is of the essence'' in new arms talks with Moscow and warned that he would move ahead with testing antimissile technology even if he did not reach an agreement on scrapping the Antiballistic Missile Treaty of 1972. His comments came a day after he and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia agreed to ''consultations'' on nuclear weapons cuts and discussions on defensive technologies.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>National security experts in the Democratic Party are pushing Congressional Democrats to unite behind an alternative to missile defense.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Push to Ban Biological Arms  European nations and other major powers urged completion of a draft agreement to enforce the 1972 ban on biological weapons, a move at odds with the Bush administration, which concluded that the draft was flawed beyond repair.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Transfer of Power in Jakarta  Megawati Sukarnoputri was sworn in as president in the most peaceful transfer of power in Indonesia's history, moments after the nation's top legislative body voted to cut short the fractious tenure of her predecessor, Abdurrahman Wahid, who refused to recognize the action.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17</p>
        <p>Bush Advisers Recommend Amnesty for Mexican Aliens  A cabinet-level panel has recommended that President Bush endorse a limited plan giving permanent legal status to some of the three million Mexicans thought to be living illegally in the United States. The plan, which would require Congressional approval, grew out of discussions between Mr. Bush and President Vicente Fox of Mexico.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Lets Thai Boy Stay  Attorney General John Ashcroft gave ''humanitarian parole'' to a 4-year-old Thai boy with AIDS, Phanupong Khaisri, who was used as a decoy in a human-trafficking scheme, saying the United States should not deport him. The boy has been with a Los Angeles couple who want to adopt him. His grandparents are seeking custody and his return to Thailand.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Exile Dissension in Miami  Ninoska Pérez Castellon has become the latest prominent member of the Cuban American National Foundation to leave the exile group in a generational clash over ideology and leadership since the death of its founder, Jorge Mas Canosa, in 1997.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Maneuvering on Patients' Bill  Senior House Republican aides said Republicans were seeking votes to defeat a bipartisan patients' bill of rights favored by Democrats, opposed by President Bush and tentatively set for a vote this week.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>A Second Baptism  The Vatican has decided that Mormons must be rebaptized before converting to Catholicism, effectively treating Mormon converts as Mormons deal with Catholics who embrace Mormonism. The decision, following a similar move by the United Methodist Church a year ago, rubs against Mormon efforts to be clearly understood as a Christian church.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Talking While Driving  About 3 percent of daytime drivers in the United States -- or about 500,000 -- are using hand-held cell phones at any given moment, the government said in its first on-the-street survey of phone use in vehicles.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Deadly Currents Claim Three Young Lives  Four cousins wading in knee-deep water at a beach in Far Rockaway, Queens, were swept away by fierce currents while their uncle and scores of other people watched helplessly from shore. The three girls, ages 12, 13 and 16, drowned, but the boy, age 11, made it back to shore.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Tack on Drug Laws  Governor Pataki, seeking to revive moribund efforts with Democrats to soften Rockefeller-era drug laws, would give many more defendants the chance to undergo drug treatment rather than long prison terms.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>New Bishop for Newark  Bishop John J. Myers, the head of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Peoria, Ill., is to be introduced today as the new archbishop of Newark.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Ranking Regional Tax Loads  Connecticut, New York and New Jersey rank first, second and third among the 50 states in state and local taxes, with New York the leader in local taxes, a census study found.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>U.S. Eases Research Ban  A federal agency investigating the death of a volunteer in a study at Johns Hopkins University said it would partly lift its four-day-old suspension of human research there.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Storied Bookshop Moving On  The Gotham Book Mart, the most tradition-bound of all New York bookstores, has put its cluttered West 47th Street town house up for sale for $7.9 million and is planning to move to a new modern home.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8-9</p>
        <p>Eudora Welty  The writer whose evocative short stories made her a revered figure in contemporary American letters was 92 years old.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>AOL Investment in Amazon  Amazon.com got a $100 million investment from AOL Time Warner, part of a broader deal in which AOL will buy technology from Amazon to operate its online shopping channels. Amazon reported quarterly results showing sales short of expectations but losses lower than analysts projected.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Internet Venture Hurt AT&amp;T  AT&amp;T lost $149 million loss in the second quarter, hurt by a swift erosion of revenue from long-distance operations and a $1.1 billion plunge in the value of its Net2Phone investment.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Lucent Moves to Sell a Unit  Lucent Technologies was said to be near a deal to sell its fiber optic business to Furukawa Electric and Corning for $2.75 billion to raise cash.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Ewing Tells of Sex Favors  Patrick Ewing testified that he twice received sexual favors from dancers at an Atlanta stip club at the heart of a federal racketeering trial.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Isolated on global warming; a new Indonesian leader; taking care of Gracie Mansion; Mississippi's teacher salaries.  Column: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
