<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 5-13-01: On Language; Semantitheft</title>
    <meta content="WLN103151" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/13/magazine/13ONLANGUAGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010603T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1292764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On Language (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EEDA173BF930A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 5-13-01: On Language; Semantitheft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column on adoption of specialized terms for general use that distorts their meaning; cites 'beg the question,' 'myopic,' 'ecology' and others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the issue I raise today cries out for an answer, if the point of this article invites close cross-examination, am I begging the question?</p>
        <p>No. Though my trickle-down convictions may beggar my neighbor, I will not beg the question, because I am not in the fallacy dodge. Of the many fulminations from specialists about the distortions of their vocabularies by the lay public, this mendicant phrase leads all the rest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the issue I raise today cries out for an answer, if the point of this article invites close cross-examination, am I begging the question?</p>
        <p>No. Though my trickle-down convictions may beggar my neighbor, I will not beg the question, because I am not in the fallacy dodge. Of the many fulminations from specialists about the distortions of their vocabularies by the lay public, this mendicant phrase leads all the rest.</p>
        <p>Here's how it is mistakenly used: Tom Daschle, the Senate Democratic leader, noted that a downturn in the economy would reduce tax revenues and said: ''So it begs the question, how large the tax cut? And it begs the question, how long the tax cut?''</p>
        <p>''As a retired teacher of logic,'' writes Daniel Merrill, who taught philosophy at Oberlin College, ''I implore you: give the technical use of beg the question back to the logicians!''</p>
        <p>A Rutgers University philosophy professor, Tim Mauldin, agrees: ''Let's stomp out this abuse!'' He explains: ''If the defender of the thesis asks (begs') that his interlocutor accept as a premise of the argument the very issue in dispute (the question'), then he or she has begged the question. This error is sometimes called 'circular reasoning.'''</p>
        <p>Example of circular question-begging: ''Parallel lines never meet because they are parallel.'' That takes you right around the barn and back where you started.</p>
        <p>Example of linear question-begging: ''Anything Safire says about anything is suspect because you can't believe what you read in the newspapers.'' All the people who fervently believe that to be true make no legitimate argument because they take for granted a premise that is unproven. Their solution to that would be to offer proof: ''Safire is suspect because he misspelled the name of James Madison's wife (Hello, Dolley!).'' That causes me to beg pardon, not question.</p>
        <p>Schoolteachers should petition their principals to stop taking for granted this abuse of fair argument. Let us now turn to the second most constant gripe of ophthalmologists (the first is the tendency of linguistic Magoos to pronounce the first syllable of their profession with a p rather than the correct f).</p>
        <p>''Myopic, in ophthalmological practice,'' writes Heskel Haddad, M.D., ''is a person with sharp vision at near. However, it is often used to connote someone as 'narrow minded.'''</p>
        <p>That's the meaning Ralph Nader had in mind at the Detroit Economic Club last year, when he called the assembled auto executives who opposed tighter fuel economy standards ''craven and myopic.''</p>
        <p>The Greek myops means ''shortsighted.'' Distant objects cannot be seen sharply because light entering the eye is focused in front of the retina.</p>
        <p>Shortsighted and nearsighted are interchangeable, according to the ophthalmologist Malvin Krinn, M.D., of Washington. ''But nearsighted may sound a little more sophisticated.''</p>
        <p>The word myopia was coined in 1693, and the meaning was soon extended. In 1801, the poet and novelist Charlotte Smith wrote of ''the myopia of the mind,'' and in 1891 Oliver Wendell Holmes, the poet of the breakfast table, referred to ''the kind of partial blindness which belongs to intellectual myopia.''</p>
        <p>Because their word's meaning was stolen so long ago, eye doctors should blink away their tears at the loss. Besides, the general sense has a nice metaphoric connection to the eye: ''lack of foresight.''</p>
        <p>Ecologists, however, have a more legitimate beef. ''One of my many pet peeves,'' notes Terence Ball of Phoenix, ''concerns people who speak of President Bush and others 'hurting the ecology.' What they mean is 'hurting the natural environment.''' Nancy Eldblom, a field botanist in Potsdam, N.Y., says, ''Here's an example of 'stealing' an entire branch of science: using ecology, the life science 'concerned with the interrelationship of organisms and their environments,' to mean the environment generally.''</p>
        <p>My call: if you're discussing that branch of biology dealing with the way living organisms relate to their surroundings, use ecology, rooted in the Greek for ''dwelling.'' If you're talking about air or water pollution or global warming (now renamed ''global climate change''), use environment, from the Latin viron, ''circle.'' (Lincoln: ''I am environed with difficulties.'') If you just want to apply a political label, green will do fine.</p>
        <p>''Equating theory with hypothesis is the booboo that boils the blood,'' fulminates Joe Rosen of Bethesda, Md. Judith Weiss, president of the American Institute of Biological Sciences, agrees: ''In science, the word theory refers to an underlying principle of observed phenomena that has been tested and verified. However, in common usage, it has come to mean 'hunch' or 'speculation' (what the word hypothesis means in science).''</p>
        <p>While scientists who admire precision often treat the word theory as ''a confirmed hypothesis,'' lexicographers since 1706 have defined it as ''a supposition'' far from proven. I recall sitting in a box with Henry Kissinger at a Washington football game; when the referee outrageously penalized the Redskins for pass interference, Henry rose to his feet, shook his fists and shouted, ''On vot theory?'' Strictly speaking, he meant hypothesis, but ''only a theory'' -- as against demonstrated fact -- is a longtime sense of the term.</p>
        <p>Sports enthusiasts as well as scientists defend their linguistic turf. ''Railbirds bristle at the misuse of track record,'' vents Dan Hely of Carlisle, Pa., who reminds us that the track record for the mile and a half at Belmont is 2 minutes 24 seconds, held by Secretariat since 1973. Yeah, adds David Hawkins of Brooklyn: ''As a former horseplayer, I get exercised at the use of track record as in 'the track record shows that he'll make a good president.' A track record is the fastest time ever recorded for a specific distance at a given track. The racing term that should be used is past performance.''</p>
        <p>All this raises, not begs, the question: Are specialists understandably miffed at the expropriation of their precise vocabulary by the generalist ''meaning thieves''? Sure; but they don't own the words and should stop being so myopic.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 3, 2001, Sunday  The On Language column on May 13 misspelled the surname of the president of the American Institute of Biological Sciences, who commented on the usage of the word ''theory.'' She is Judith Weis, not Weiss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 3, 2001, Sunday</p>
        <p>The On Language column on May 13 misspelled the surname of the president of the American Institute of Biological Sciences, who commented on the usage of the word ''theory.'' She is Judith Weis, not Weiss.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
