<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police Sergeant's Teenage Son Is Suspect in Environmental Group's Campaign of Destruction</title>
    <meta content="18ELF.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/18/nyregion/18ELF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1263758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Earth Liberation Front</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vandalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5DA1F3DF93BA25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police Sergeant's Teenage Son Is Suspect in Environmental Group's Campaign of Destruction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Jan. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seventeen-year-old son of New York police sergeant is suspect in radical environmental group's underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County; Earth Liberation Front has claimed responsibility for more than 2 dozen acts of arson and vandalism in Suffolk County (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 17-year-old son of a New York police sergeant is a suspect in a radical environmental group's underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County, several law enforcement officials said today.</p>
        <p>The loose-knit group, the Earth Liberation Front, had been active mostly in the Pacific Northwest. But in recent years it has claimed responsibility for crimes farther east, in Colorado, Indiana and Boston. The group surfaced on Long Island last summer, when it announced through a spokesman that it had uprooted a Cold Spring Harbor cornfield used in genetic research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 17-year-old son of a New York police sergeant is a suspect in a radical environmental group's underground campaign of arson and destruction in Suffolk County, several law enforcement officials said today.</p>
        <p>The loose-knit group, the Earth Liberation Front, had been active mostly in the Pacific Northwest. But in recent years it has claimed responsibility for crimes farther east, in Colorado, Indiana and Boston. The group surfaced on Long Island last summer, when it announced through a spokesman that it had uprooted a Cold Spring Harbor cornfield used in genetic research.</p>
        <p>Since then, the group has claimed responsibility for more than two dozen acts of arson and vandalism in Suffolk County, against luxury homes and condominiums being built, construction vehicles and a McDonald's corporate office.</p>
        <p>A law enforcement official familiar with the investigation said, ''We are trying to find out what happened and who did it and how many people are involved.'' The official said a tip received in New York City led investigators to the 17-year-old. The police would not disclose his identity, although law enforcement officials said his father was a sergeant with the New York City police.</p>
        <p>On Monday, agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, armed with a search warrant, went through the house on Bristol Downs Street in Coram where the teenager lives with his family, looking for evidence.  The agents left with computer files, cans of red spray paint and other material.</p>
        <p>The agents also interviewed residents of the quiet cul-de-sac, which is less than a mile from a site where a house under construction had been vandalized and marked in red paint reading ''E.L.F.'' and ''Stop Urban Sprawl.''</p>
        <p>Neighbors of the teenager described him as a normal student who never got in trouble and received good marks. One neighbor said he believed that the youth was working  at Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton, just east of Coram.</p>
        <p>Mona Rowe, a spokeswoman for the lab, confirmed that he had been working there after school since November on a research project dealing with global warming and the effects of increased carbon dioxide on plants. ''In our experience with him, the work is going well,'' she said. ''He is bright, motivated and a good student.''</p>
        <p>A senior law enforcement official, speaking on the condition of anonymity, said today that an arrest had been expected on Monday. But for reasons that remained unclear tonight, no arrest was made.</p>
        <p>The authorities are investigating a second person in connection with the case, another law enforcement official said.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, two F.B.I. agents visited Longwood High School in Middle Island, where the youth is a senior, an athlete and a reporter for the student newspaper, The Lion's Roar. The agents went there in search of a ''certain student'' whom they found  and interviewed in the presence of the high school principal and an assistant principal, said B. Allen Mannella, an assistant superintendent of the Longwood Central School District. Mr. Mannella would not identify the student.</p>
        <p>He said some F.B.I. agents returned today, seeking information about school computers. The agents also interviewed other students, he said, adding that he believed that  their questions had to do with e-mail.</p>
        <p>''They may come back with subpoenas,'' Mr. Mannella said of the federal agents. ''Of course we will cooperate. We are distressed by this also.''</p>
        <p>Today, the teenager's mother referred questions about the matter to Richard J. Kaufman, a Port Jefferson lawyer who was representing the  youth. But Mr. Kaufman refused to say whether federal officials had told his client whether he was a suspect.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, there is not much I can comment on at this time,'' Mr. Kaufman said. ''There are no charges or anything of that nature that I am aware of.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Suffolk County district attorney, James M. Catterson Jr., is conducting an independent investigation.</p>
        <p>A rift between Mr. Catterson and federal prosecutors has widened in recent weeks. As a result, the federal authorities had to subpoena all of the records the Suffolk County police had compiled in connection with its months-long investigation into the destruction that the group has claimed, said Lt. William Rohrer, a Police Department spokesman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
