<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Negotiators Push to Settle World Treaty On Warming</title>
    <meta content="10CLIM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/10/international/10CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Morocco</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D61438F933A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Negotiators Push to Settle World Treaty On Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Delegates Work Late to Complete Treaty to Fight Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Delegates from 164 countries negotiate in Morocco on remaining issues in Kyoto Protocol, which is to set first firm restrictions on amount of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases released in industrial nations; treaty is key step even without US participation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With momentum building for a treaty curbing global warming, delegates from 164 countries, cloistered in a convention center in Morocco, negotiated late into the night yesterday to resolve several lingering disputes.</p>
        <p>If completed and enacted, the treaty, the Kyoto Protocol, would set the first firm restrictions on the amount of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases released by industrialized countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With momentum building for a treaty curbing global warming, delegates from 164 countries negotiated late into the night in Morocco on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With momentum building for a treaty curbing global warming, delegates from 164 countries, cloistered in a convention center in Morocco, negotiated late into the night yesterday to resolve several lingering disputes.</p>
        <p>If completed and enacted, the treaty, the Kyoto Protocol, would set the first firm restrictions on the amount of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases released by industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>''We're in a state of hard negotiations, with everyone delivering a huge effort to find an agreement,'' said Vincent Georis, a spokesman for Olivier DeLeuze, the head of the European Union delegation, in a telephone interview from Marrakech.</p>
        <p>The outlook for the treaty was substantially dimmed in March when President Bush rejected it, reversing the position taken by President Bill Clinton, whose administration negotiated the outlines of the accord in Japan in 1997. The United States, with 5 percent of the world's population, accounts for a fourth of all emissions of the so-called greenhouse gases, mainly carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Still, climate experts and government officials said that even without participation from the United States, adoption of the treaty would be a small but significant first step toward limiting the human impact on the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''If this holds together, it is a piece of architecture in place and it is quite an achievement to get this far,'' said Dr. Henry D. Jacoby, co-director of the Joint Program on the Science and Policy of Global Change at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>Most climate scientists say that a buildup of greenhouse gases in recent decades has contributed to a worldwide warming trend that could lead to droughts, floods and agricultural disruption, particularly in developing countries.</p>
        <p>The treaty aims to introduce the first global trading system for greenhouse gas credits. The system would allow countries that surpassed targets for reducing emissions to sell extra credits to countries that lagged, creating an incentive to make the deepest cuts wherever they could be done at the lowest cost.</p>
        <p>But big issues remain, Dr. Jacoby said, especially the challenge of fostering international environmental and economic cooperation without the United States -- the biggest economy and polluter.</p>
        <p>''How will we proceed when we have a fragmented system with us and perhaps others on the outside?'' he said. ''How does that evolve?''</p>
        <p>A series of compromises, particularly between the European Union on the one hand and Russia, Japan, Canada and Australia on the other, cleared the way for a final push last night, according to some environmental experts.</p>
        <p>Remaining issues included how much credit Russia should get toward its emissions goals for the role its vast forests play in absorbing carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Europe, the bloc most firmly fighting for the treaty, still differed with Japan over whether countries should first be required to accept the treaty as legally binding before they could buy and sell emissions credits.</p>
        <p>Another issue involves Saudi Arabia and other oil exporting countries that want compensation for any lost revenue should countries reduce their use of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Even with this workload, many delegates and observers said last night that they felt confident they would find agreement by today.</p>
        <p>The goal of many negotiators was to settle on language that satisfied enough countries to enact the treaty next year, the 10th anniversary of the Rio Earth Summit, where the first climate treaty was forged. To gain legal force, it must be ratified by at least 55 countries, including a group responsible for at least 55 percent of the heat-trapping emissions from industrialized countries in 1990.</p>
        <p>If that happens, the treaty will require by 2012 that participating industrialized countries cut emissions of carbon dioxide and similar warming gases about 5 percent below their levels in 1990.</p>
        <p>With the United States on the sidelines, the support of Japan and Russia is crucial for ratification.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto Protocol was framed as a successor to a 1992 climate treaty -- signed by Mr. Bush's father and approved unanimously by the Senate -- that set voluntary goals for greenhouse-gas reductions by industrial powers, but failed to come close to its target.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration sought to complete the treaty last year, but talks at the Hague last November fell apart. The issue then fell to Mr. Bush, who had long questioned the science pointing to human-caused global warming and was heavily lobbied by energy companies to reject it outright.</p>
        <p>When he did reject it, he said the pact could harm the economy and was unfair because the required emissions cuts applied only to industrial powers and not to fast-growing developing countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
