<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1304770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD1130F935A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>U.S. Escort for Rebels Sets Off Riot in Macedonia  American troops waded into the deepening crisis in Macedonia in an unplanned operation to escort several hundred armed Albanian rebels from a town near the capital as part of the cease-fire agreement. The operation set off a riot in the capital, Skopje, where citizens are angry about outside intervention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>U.S. Escort for Rebels Sets Off Riot in Macedonia  American troops waded into the deepening crisis in Macedonia in an unplanned operation to escort several hundred armed Albanian rebels from a town near the capital as part of the cease-fire agreement. The operation set off a riot in the capital, Skopje, where citizens are angry about outside intervention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>At U.N., a Call for War on AIDS  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, addressing the General Assembly in a special session on AIDS, said the world's response to the disease ''must be no less comprehensive, no less relentless and no less swift than the pandemic itself.'' He held out the possibility of further American contributions, in addition to $200 million offered last month, to a global fund to fight the disease.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The United States unexpectedly dropped a patent complaint against Brazil in the World Trade Organization and agreed to settle a dispute widely seen as symbolic of the debate over who may manufacture and sell drugs to treat AIDS in poor countries.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Pope Visits Jewish Memorial  Pope John Paul II visited Babi Yar in Ukraine, where the Nazis killed 100,000 Jews. He quietly recited ''De Profundis,'' a Latin prayer for the dead. By paying his respects, the pope was working on the continuing and sometimes edgy reconciliation process between Catholics and Jews.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Ex-Spy Chief Returned to Peru  Vladimiro Montesinos, the former Peruvian spy chief who evaded an international manhunt for eight months before his arrest this past weekend, was flown to Lima in handcuffs and a bullet-proof vest and began what promises to be months of questioning and legal processing.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Sharon Puts Pressure on Arafat  Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel, speaking in New York, demanded an end to violence by Palestinians as a condition of carrying forward peace efforts and called on Yasir Arafat to bring a halt to attacks on Israelis.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17</p>
        <p>Justices Grant a Reprieve To Some Convicted Aliens  The Supreme Court ruled 5 to 4 that immigrants who pleaded guilty to crimes in the years before strict new provisions of immigration law took effect in 1996 do not face automatic deportation, as the Clinton and Bush administrations maintained, but can still seek exemptions under old rules that gave relief to more than half the people who applied.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled 7 to 2 that a group of newspaper and magazine publishers infringed the copyrights of freelance contributors by making their articles accessible in the companies' databases after publication, without permission. The publishers, including The New York Times, may have to pay substantial damages to the six freelancers who brought the lawsuit in 1993 and perhaps to thousands of others.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court, in a 5-to-4 vote, upheld limits on how much political parties can spend in coordination with candidates.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Census Critics Want Data Now  Three months after the Census Bureau decided against adjusting the 2000 tally to make up for millions of uncounted people, civil rights groups, big-city mayors and Congressional Democrats are accusing the agency of suppressing data.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Revival of the B-2  The B-2, the world's most expensive aircraft, is trying to make a comeback. Four years after Northrop Grumman stopped producing the planes because Congress had balked at their $2.2-billion-apiece price, Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld is considering buying 40 more, for $735 million per plane.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Bush Defends Charity Plan  President Bush sought to reassure critics of his plan to expand government financing of religious groups' charitable work that the money ''will be spent on social services, not worship services.''</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Patients' Rights Deal Sought  The Senate began a second week of debate on a far-reaching bill to define patients' rights, with Democrats looking for a compromise to limit the liability of employers who might be sued by employees in disputes over health care benefits.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>New York Will Ban Use Of Phones Held by Drivers  New York will become the first state to ban talking on a hand-held cellular telephone while driving, under a bill that the Assembly passed and that Governor Pataki promised to sign later this week.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Invasion of the Gypsy Moths  Patches of Long Island and New Jersey are facing the worst gypsy moth infestation in perhaps three decades. There have also been infestations in pockets of Connecticut, Maine, New Hampshire and Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>G.O.P.'s Fight for Supremacy  A day before New Jersey voters pick a Republican for the governor's race, Bob Franks, the favorite just 10 days ago, was campaigning hard, while Bret D. Schundler, the supposed dark horse, struck a front-runner's pose by resting much of the day.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Penguins in Trouble Worldwide  Many penguin populations are declining, and evidence is mounting that global warming and overfishing are prime causes. Ten of the world's 17 penguin species are already listed as threatened or endangered.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Hingis Loses at Wimbledon  Wimbledon begins with an upset as No. 1-seeded Martina Hingis loses in straight sets to Virginia Ruano Pascual, who is ranked 83rd.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Garcia Wins Again  Sergio Garcia won the rain-delayed Buick Classic, his second victory in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Divorced Women Work Longer  Hundreds of thousands of women in their 60's, part of the surge of divorces that started a generation ago, are finding themselves forced to stay in the work force because they lack sufficient money to retire. Wages are becoming their pensions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Switch for Compaq  Compaq Computer said it planned to phase out the Alpha microprocessors at the heart of most of its high-performance computers. By 2004, all of its business computers will be designed around Intel's new processor family.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Opposition to Honeywell Deal  A draft decision to block the proposed $45 billion acquisition of Honeywell International by General Electric was endorsed by a panel of European regulators. The final deadline for a ruling is July 12.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Self-Cleaning Glass  Pilkington, a British glass maker, is set to outline its American sales plans for a new technology: window glass that cleans itself.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Blue Chips Languish  Blue-chip stocks sagged but technology shares made modest gains in listless trading as investors awaited this week's Federal Reserve meeting on interest rates.</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Rulings on funding and fairness; dictators in the dock; the return of Sammy the bull.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
