<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warming Up To the Notion Of Warming</title>
    <meta content="07BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/07/nyregion/07BIG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1349096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="The Big City"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Newsweek</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED6123CF934A35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warming Up To the Notion Of Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Warming Up to the Notion of Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column concludes that global warming will be economic boon to country, especially benefiting Northeast with longer growing season; says biggest losers will be tropical countries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you've been enjoying 72-degree weather in December, you may appreciate Robert O. Mendelsohn's new analysis of global warming. He, too, concludes that it's not such a bad deal for New York.</p>
        <p>Global warming has been the most notorious environmental menace since the summer of 1988, which was so miserably hot in New York and Washington that the resident journalists looked for a villain. The greenhouse effect made front-page news and the cover of Newsweek. ''Danger: More Hot Summers Ahead,'' warned the cover, which showed a family sweating profusely inside a glass dome amid a cracked, parched plain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Global warming might be an environmental menace that is not so menacing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you've been enjoying 72-degree weather in December, you may appreciate Robert O. Mendelsohn's new analysis of global warming. He, too, concludes that it's not such a bad deal for New York.</p>
        <p>Global warming has been the most notorious environmental menace since the summer of 1988, which was so miserably hot in New York and Washington that the resident journalists looked for a villain. The greenhouse effect made front-page news and the cover of Newsweek. ''Danger: More Hot Summers Ahead,'' warned the cover, which showed a family sweating profusely inside a glass dome amid a cracked, parched plain.</p>
        <p>But there's another side to global warming, even if the recent weather hasn't inspired a cover story headlined, ''Good News: More Pleasant Autumns Ahead.'' Warmer weather is not something that Americans dread -- to the contrary, people and businesses have been migrating south. They apparently see benefits to climate change, and so does Dr. Mendelsohn, an economist at the Yale University School of Forestry and Environmental Studies.</p>
        <p>He is the editor of a new book, ''Global Warming and the American Economy'' (Edward Elgar Publishing), featuring detailed projections by economists and climate scientists. The bottom line is that the economic benefits of global warming seem likely to slightly outweigh the overall costs in America, and that Northerners will especially benefit. The best guess, which assumes a four-degrees-Fahrenheit rise in temperature and a one-foot rise in sea level over the next century, is that the net annual benefit will be $20 billion.</p>
        <p>''Scientists originally thought there were going to be horrific results from climate change, but we're not seeing that,'' Dr. Mendelsohn said.</p>
        <p>The biggest beneficiaries will be farmers, who will have longer growing seasons and crops that grow faster, thanks to the extra carbon in the air. ''Crops will move north,'' Dr. Mendelsohn said. ''It will be easier to grow food in Connecticut, and New Jersey will have fresh vegetables longer. You could have tree plantations of Southern pine in the mid-Atlantic region.''</p>
        <p>Some maple trees might leave southern New England, which would be a noticeable loss in foliage season. ''There will be changes that offend people,'' Dr. Mendelsohn said. ''But it appears that they will be more gentle than we thought. Scientists had feared that we'd go from some intact forests to moonscapes, but that's not likely to happen. We'll go from one type of ecosystem to another, which for most people will not be that dramatic.''</p>
        <p>For Northerners, the savings in heating bills will offset the higher air-conditioning bills in the summer, Dr. Mendelsohn said, but Southerners will see their energy costs increase. Southern coastal dwellers will be more affected by the sea-level rise because there's more low-lying land in the South. Northern skiers will have their own problems.</p>
        <p>''SKIING in New York State will undoubtedly be worse,'' Dr. Mendelsohn said. ''But in fact, most outdoor recreation happens in the summer, so there would be a large increase in outdoor recreation from global warming. More people would be hiking and playing golf all fall, as they did this year.''</p>
        <p>There's no way, of course, to put a dollar figure on some effects of global warming, like the loss of species or the pain people feel on being dislocated. Most Americans would probably prefer not to see any change in the climate, and Dr. Mendelsohn is sympathetic to their view.</p>
        <p>''If it were cheap to do, I'd keep the climate constant,'' he said. ''But it's not cheap. For every dollar we spend on mitigation, at most we would get 10 cents back, and it could only be 1 cent. To me, it looks like a very bad investment. I'd rather spend the money on programs today to cut  pollution, improve public health and establish zones for protecting biodiversity. We'd get larger benefits, and we wouldn't have to wait 100 years for them.''</p>
        <p>In other work, Dr. Mendelsohn has found that the worldwide economic costs and benefits of climate change would roughly balance out. Again, most of the benefits would be in the North, while farmers in the tropics would suffer.</p>
        <p>''There's a definite inequity,'' Dr. Mendelsohn said. ''The losers are the poor tropical countries, not the rich industrialized countries that have done the most polluting. Even if it's not worth trying to stop this climate change, I think we have a responsibility to make things right for the tropical countries. We should be helping them right now to develop economically. The more developed they are, the better they can adapt.''</p>
        <p>The Big City</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
