<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Easygoing Words and a Hard Line</title>
    <meta content="Y18BUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/18/world/18BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DC1331F93BA25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Easygoing Words and a Hard Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>BLED, Slovenia, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis; Pres Bush, during five-day visit to Europe, established approach to foreign policy much like his approach to domestic affairs: occasionally humble remarks matched by largely unswerving positions, sweet words coupled with hard-line actions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last week, as President Bush pinged from country to country and prime minister to president, he was in some senses the epitome of diplomatic etiquette.</p>
        <p>Always, he told the European leaders he met on his first overseas trip as president that he was eager and delighted to hear from them. Always, he stressed his desire to cooperate with them, to learn more about them, to come to a point where they could work blissfully together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last week, as President Bush pinged from country to country and prime minister to president, he was in some senses the epitome of diplomatic etiquette.</p>
        <p>Always, he told the European leaders he met on his first overseas trip as president that he was eager and delighted to hear from them. Always, he stressed his desire to cooperate with them, to learn more about them, to come to a point where they could work blissfully together.</p>
        <p>It was, in Mr. Bush's stated view, a transcontinental listening tour, the beginning of ''consultations'' -- a word he used time and again -- that would embrace all the important issues and carry through the duration of his presidency.</p>
        <p>And yet he had abandoned the Kyoto accord on global warming -- and offered no apologies for it. He was launching into more intensive research for, and development of, a missile defense shield -- and demonstrated no equivocation or willingness to turn back in the face of profound reservations from important allies.</p>
        <p>Over the course of five European countries and five frenetic days, Mr. Bush established an approach to foreign policy much like his approach to domestic affairs: occasionally humble remarks matched by largely unswerving positions, sweet words coupled with hard-line actions.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to consulting,'' he said at the first news conference of his trip in Madrid on Tuesday, adding that he was eager to ''continue the consultations that have already begun.''</p>
        <p>''I realize it's going to require a lot of consultation, but I'm willing to listen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But by Saturday evening, when he left this country in the northwest corner of what used to be Yugoslavia in its previous form, it was not all that much clearer than it had been at the start what he meant by consulting, or what the fruits of that consultation would be.</p>
        <p>Compromise certainly did not appear to be one of them. Mr. Bush had come to Europe with several hot-button issues -- global warming and missile defense being the two most prominent ones -- dividing him and his European counterparts, or at least rendering their relations somewhat tense.</p>
        <p>He left with many of them agreeing to disagree with him, and with Mr. Bush in particular expressing a strong resolve to continue on the path he had already chosen.</p>
        <p>''It was striking,'' said Ivo Daalder, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution in Washington, who worked as a European specialist on the National Security Council during the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>''Consultation really implies, to many other people, a give-and-take, putting one view on the table, hearing the other view and seeing if what emerges from the disagreement a way forward that satisfies both sides,'' Mr. Daalder said. ''That's not what Bush is about. There's no sense from this trip that he has changed one iota on his views.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials see it differently. They say that Mr. Bush's concern for conciliation was apparent in his repeatedly stated desire to spend money and lead research on technologies to cut emissions of greenhouse gases and his expressed interest in having European allies, and even Russia, help determine the specific architecture of a missile shield.</p>
        <p>In regard to the missile shield, Condeleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's national security adviser, said, ''The idea here is that we should have a new security framework. Now, we are open as to what form that takes.''</p>
        <p>She and other administration officials added that a reason Mr. Bush was trying to bring other countries on board early was so that they could have a say in that form.</p>
        <p>But these officials never publicly entertained the notion during Mr. Bush's European trip that missile defense itself was up for negotiation, just as they never invited a fresh discussion on the administration's abandoning of the Kyoto accord.</p>
        <p>Foreign policy experts suggested that part of that seeming intransigence may be attributable to the kinds of bluffs involved in international poker -- to the idea that if you proclaim a willingness to budge before you have to, you may end up budging more than you want. That was Mr. Bush's method as he sought to drive his tax cut through Congress, and he ended up signing a bill very much like the one he proposed.</p>
        <p>Besides, Mr. Bush was speaking during his travels not just to a European audience but also to Americans, and many of them support American unilateralism and believe the United States should have its way and exert its will abroad.</p>
        <p>But the line between insistence and arrogance can be a fine one, and the principal evidence of the humility that Mr. Bush has long said should be a part of American foreign policy existed mostly in the politeness of his speech and the frequency of his smiles, not in concessions.</p>
        <p>He talked one way and walked another, using symbols (in this case, meeting dissenting leaders on their turf or in neutral places) and language to send a message at odds with the substance of his plans.</p>
        <p>This, too, was reminiscent of his political style at home, of the way in which the decorations adorning his policies sometimes obscure their actual effect.</p>
        <p>When he was selling his tax cut to Americans, he stood beside middle-class families and talked about waitresses raising children on their own, but the wealthy were by far the biggest beneficiaries in dollars and cents. And he was making superficially nice and jocular with Democrats, just as he did with European leaders last week, without bending all that much to their wishes.</p>
        <p>It was unclear, after it was all said and done, what exactly Europeans could expect to negotiate with Mr. Bush. When one of the president's foreign policy advisers was asked during the trip about the impact Europeans had made thus far on Mr. Bush's plans for missile defense, his answer concerned the nomenclature of the project.</p>
        <p>For a long while, Mr. Bush's advisers referred to the project as national missile defense, which implied that it was designed to protect only  the United States, rather than Europe as well.</p>
        <p>''Europeans came to us,'' the adviser said, referring to the first months of the administration, ''and the first thing they argued was, 'How can you tell us this isn't de-coupling when you use 'national?''</p>
        <p>''And it sort of stopped the conversation,'' he continued, ''and, frankly, none of us had a really good answer. So we dropped 'national,' because they had a point.''</p>
        <p>Whether that simple editing will be enough remains to be seen, and some foreign policy experts contend that if Mr. Bush does not do more, he may wind up estranging Europe at a time when its growing unity makes the United States less important to it.</p>
        <p>''The notion that you can just act in the way you did 25 years ago -- which is that we'll assert our leadership and expect others to follow -- doesn't play anymore,'' Mr. Daalder said. ''Unilateralism has nothing to do with whether you're willing to talk to people. It's whether you're willing to take their views into account.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
