<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Shift, White House Cites Global Warming as a Problem</title>
    <meta content="Y08WAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/08/politics/08WARM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1299883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Sciences</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DD163EF93BA35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Shift, White House Cites Global Warming as a Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush White House, with new scientific report in hand that reaffirms reality of global warming, readily acknowledges that climate change is a problem but gives little clue as to what it intends to do about it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a new scientific report in hand that reaffirms the reality of global warming, the Bush White House readily acknowledged today that climate change was a problem but gave little clue as to what it intended to do about it.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, the president's spokesman, told reporters that when President Bush heads for Europe next week: ''He's going to tell the Europeans that he takes this issue very seriously, that global climate change is an issue that nations do need to deal with -- all nations, industrialized nations, the United States, developing nations, as well. And that through technologies and through growth and through other measures, that the world has a responsibility to face up to this.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a new scientific report in hand that reaffirms the reality of global warming, the Bush White House readily acknowledged today that climate change was a problem but gave little clue as to what it intended to do about it.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, the president's spokesman, told reporters that when President Bush heads for Europe next week: ''He's going to tell the Europeans that he takes this issue very seriously, that global climate change is an issue that nations do need to deal with -- all nations, industrialized nations, the United States, developing nations, as well. And that through technologies and through growth and through other measures, that the world has a responsibility to face up to this.''</p>
        <p>This is the strongest language the White House has used on the issue and a far cry from its earlier position that the science was too uncertain to proclaim global warming a problem.</p>
        <p>But a report from the National Academy of Sciences, requested by the White House and released on Wednesday, reaffirmed the mainstream scientific view that the earth's temperature is rising, largely because of human activities, and that this could cause drastic climate changes throughout the century.</p>
        <p>Even before the report, the president was meeting with cabinet officials to work out a position and figure out how to present it at home and abroad.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is expected to address the subject of global warming on Monday before leaving for Europe that night. Administration officials said that a draft of his remarks was being reworked to reflect a more accommodating tone because of the new report.</p>
        <p>Still, it is not clear whether the president will speak in generalities or put forth a specific proposal that he will take to appease European leaders, who have been furious with him for walking away in March from the international treaty on global warming, known as the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say that the central argument in the White House is whether to require countries to live under mandatory emission limits or to allow them to comply voluntarily.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleischer declined today to specify what approaches the White House was considering but said that it was looking at a wide variety of proposals, ''many with great specificity about what to do.''</p>
        <p>Another debate is over how much to rely on the framework of the Kyoto accord, with its market-based incentives, to draft a new proposal. Some administration officials contend that Kyoto, which required mandatory emission reductions, is something the president would never accept and that it would be bad for the American economy.</p>
        <p>Eileen Claussen, president of the Pew Center on Global Climate Change, which represents several multinational corporations that favor the Kyoto accord as a basis for some kind of agreement, said: ''Our companies are convinced this is a serious problem, convinced there will be an international agreement, and want the rules flexible and market based. And Kyoto has that framework.'' The companies represented by Pew include DuPont, the Enron Corporation and Alcoa.</p>
        <p>Ms. Claussen said the Bush administration was trying to figure out what approach to take on emissions in the United States before agreeing with other countries on limiting emissions. ''They are weighing very heavily what they are prepared to do at home before deciding what to do abroad,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But that inevitably leads to a conflict with the administration's energy proposal, which relies heavily on increasing production of coal and oil refineries, a difficult position for the administration to advocate at the same time it advocated reduced emissions. The problem of global warming was given only glancing attention in the energy report released last month.</p>
        <p>Ian Bowles, President Bill Clinton's senior director of global environmental affairs at the National Security Council, said that he understood the Bush White House to be focusing on domestic emissions as well, and that this could be useful.</p>
        <p>''The big-picture dynamic that the Clinton administration faced on Kyoto was that Europe never thought the U.S. was serious about reducing its own emissions,'' Mr. Bowles said. ''Bush is correct that this boils down to whether the U.S. does anything domestically. But if Bush says our plan is to acknowledge that global warming is real and create incentives and voluntary commitments, that will be wholly unpersuasive to Europe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bowles is a co-author of an article in the journal Science in which he discusses the challenges of creating an international treaty on climate change. One of the big problems, he noted, is that climate change is occurring on a vast geologic time scale that is not usually evident to politicians running for office on a four-year cycle.</p>
        <p>''Temperature changes during any single election cycle are likely to be quite small,'' the article says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
