<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restoring The Luster To Sacred Sites</title>
    <meta content="15COV.$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDE1531F936A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restoring The Luster To Sacred Sites</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NUMBER of things convinced the Abyssinian Baptist Church that the time had come for a boiler-to-finial renovation of its landmark home. One was the Sunday the lights went out. As the Rev. Dr. Calvin O. Butts III was preaching.</p>
        <p>''Well, if Jesus is the light, we don't have to worry,'' Dr. Butts assured his congregation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NUMBER of things convinced the Abyssinian Baptist Church that the time had come for a boiler-to-finial renovation of its landmark home. One was the Sunday the lights went out. As the Rev. Dr. Calvin O. Butts III was preaching.</p>
        <p>''Well, if Jesus is the light, we don't have to worry,'' Dr. Butts assured his congregation.</p>
        <p>But along with clanging radiators, faltering air-conditioning and a baptismal pool cold enough to induce shock, it was a sign that the 78-year-old structure needed more than a cosmetic fix.</p>
        <p>Today, the $8.5 million renovation is roughly at the midway point. Outside, the twin-towered neo-Gothic structure at 132 West 138th Street is shrouded in scaffolding while the exterior is repointed and repaired. Inside, the amphitheater-style sanctuary positively gleams under its newly restored alabaster chandeliers. And it echoes with the sound of workers from the Superior Pools company rebuilding the enormous walk-in font, adding new lighting and heating. ''The River Jordan is chilly and cold, but not our baptismal font,'' Dr. Butts said.</p>
        <p>All around New York, houses of worship are renovating. The number of applications for loans and grants from the Sacred Sites Program of the New York Landmarks Conservancy is at an all-time high, said the director, Ken Lustbader, as are requests for technical assistance and referrals. He credited a ''deeper appreciation for historic architecture'' as well as the widespread feeling -- at least until recently -- that times were flush. And he noted that small houses of worship, as well as the more renowned landmarks, were participating. The program has made $5.23 million worth of grants and loans statewide, with $3.65 million going to 140 projects in New York City.</p>
        <p>Some congregations are forced to rebuild. Central Synagogue, at Lexington Avenue and 55th Street, burned in 1998 as an earlier renovation neared an end. Though the exterior walls and minaretlike towers were spared, as was the Ark, the roof and most of the interior was gutted. The $45 million stabilization, reconstruction and restoration project includes reclaiming fantastically stenciled walls and intricately contrasting woodwork.</p>
        <p>Today, painting crews from Creative Finishes Ltd. are slathering the walls of Central with a bouquet of 69 colors in extravagant floral forms and latticework. Golden stars pierce fields of electric blue above expanses of cornflower blue, jade green, terra cotta, slate, sand, peach, ruby and chocolate.</p>
        <p>On a scaffold about 55 feet above the sanctuary floor, Hugh Hardy of Hardy Holzman Pfeiffer Associates, architects of the restoration, pointed out how the painters were deliberately skewing some of the patterns, ever so slightly, to maintain the feeling of having been applied by hand and not mechanically.</p>
        <p>''There's an uneven quality which we've tried very hard to achieve so it wouldn't look like silk-screening,'' Mr. Hardy said. ''Too many straight edges are sterile.''</p>
        <p>No worry at Central, where there are virtually no straight edges. Completed in 1872, the synagogue was designed by Henry Fernbach as an exuberant Moorish Revival composition. As materials aged and tastes changed, however, its vibrancy diminished.</p>
        <p>That is being recovered not only in the stenciling but in the restoration of the walnut, ash and rosewood millwork and in the recreation of elaborate plaster moldings.</p>
        <p>''It's not true that craftsmanship is dead,'' Mr. Hardy said. The ornamental plasterwork is by Shroid Construction, the wood restoration by Hird/Blaker and the stained glass by Rambusch. Fisher Marantz Stone is the lighting consultant. The restoration consultants are DPK&amp;A of Philadelphia. The construction manager is the F. J. Sciame Construction Company.</p>
        <p>They all faced a critical challenge.</p>
        <p>''How do you keep a balance between old and new?'' Mr. Hardy asked. ''Seamless was our goal.'' For instance, to be sure that the 38-foot Ark is not upstaged by the interior, its decorative marquetry will be regilded. But the gilding will be lightly abraded with steel wool to tone down its gleam.</p>
        <p>If it works as intended, the restoration will leave congregants feeling that they are returning to the space they left -- spruced up, certainly, but not fundamentally altered. ''This was our home,'' said Livia Thompson, the executive director of the synagogue. ''It's going to be our home again.''</p>
        <p>She said that the project is being financed by insurance proceeds and other sources but that details were ''not fully resolved.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, she said, the congregation expects to be back in its home by the High Holy Days this year, in September. Services have been held across 55th Street in the 440-seat Carrie M. K. Beir Chapel in the basement of Central's community house. Stenciled panels and a cusped arch were among the decorative features added to the modern space to evoke the 19th-century sanctuary.</p>
        <p>Not everything about the old synagogue was cherished. ''We thought about ways in which the building was starting to be an impediment,'' Ms. Thompson said.</p>
        <p>To reduce the steep proportions of the front stairs, the entry vestibule was lowered 14 inches, an operation that had ripple effects throughout the front of the structure.</p>
        <p>Air-conditioning is being added, as planned in the earlier renovation. Otherwise, Ms. Thompson said, the sanctuary is unusable from June to September.</p>
        <p>FOR the Rev. Brenda G. Husson, rector of St. James' Episcopal Church, at Madison Avenue and 71st Street, the lack of air-conditioning can amount to a pastoral issue in summer. ''The heat in the church is so oppressive that it makes it difficult for some of the older parishioners in particular,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Built in 1884 and reconstructed in 1924, St. James' must now accommodate the growing number of families in the parish, with about 700 children, and the increasing number of activities and programs for church members and the wider community.</p>
        <p>''The building isn't working very well,'' the rector said. ''It's one thing to say we're open to all people and then quite another to put 14 steep steps in your way.''</p>
        <p>The renovation, designed by Lee Harris Pomeroy Architects, ''essentially keeps the building as it is on the outside but radically changes it inside,'' Mr. Pomeroy said.</p>
        <p>And yes, that means the ungainly steeple from 1950 will remain. ''We all know it doesn't fit architecturally,'' the rector said. ''But it's our steeple. And it's been our steeple for a very long time.''</p>
        <p>That and the sanctuary will be among the few things unchanged by the $25 million project, to be finished in 2002 and financed by a $9.5 million capital campaign and the parish endowment. The construction manager is Barr &amp; Barr and the owner's representative is Levien &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>A reconfigured entrance to the parish house, at sidewalk level, will make it far easier to enter both buildings.</p>
        <p>New space will be claimed throughout the complex, most ingeniously over the low roof of the north aisle in the church, between the nave and the parish house. Here, a small multipurpose atrium is to be constructed that will continue to admit light to the clerestory windows through its glass roof.</p>
        <p>In the corner tower, a three-story columbarium -- in essence, an above-ground burial chamber -- is to be built. Niches in its wall are designed to receive the ashes of those who have been cremated.</p>
        <p>The east hall in the basement will be rebuilt. The congregation will move there in June so that the sanctuary floor can be replaced. Running under the floor will be a space known as a plenum that will permit air-conditioning. The rector hopes to be back in the sanctuary by Christmas Eve.</p>
        <p>Ralph Adams Cram, the architect of the 1924 reconstruction, was no fan of Tiffany windows, which he broke up and moved around the church. Several dispersed panels will be reunited in the east hall.</p>
        <p>Tiffany windows are the heart of a project at St. Michael's Episcopal Church, Amsterdam Avenue and 99th Street, which has one of the more magnificent suites of stained glass in New York: Louis Comfort Tiffany's ''St. Michael's Victory in Heaven.'' Installed in 1895, the seven windows, each 22 by 5 feet, form a single composition, like celestial Cinerama. They were restored in the late 1980's as the rector, the Rev. Frederick Hill, worked on many fronts to revive parish life.</p>
        <p>After only a decade, however, the Tiffany windows were in trouble again.</p>
        <p>''We realized when we started seeing daylight on top of one of the arches that we had a problem,'' said the Rev. Canon George W. Brandt Jr., the current rector.</p>
        <p>The problem could be traced in part to the original engineering of the windows, in which some pieces are thickly molded and others have up to four layers of glass. ''Tiffany didn't anticipate the weight or longevity of his windows,'' said Ron Melichar, a member of St. Michael's restoration and renewal committee. And part of the problem could be ascribed to the fact that the wooden frames had not been restored.</p>
        <p>BUT church leaders acknowledged that the protective glazing system that was installed during the earlier restoration inadvertently contributed to the rapid deterioration of the windows.</p>
        <p>The culprit, they said, was insufficient ventilation between the leaded glass and the protective panels of polycarbonate plastic. This created a greenhouse effect, trapping heat and moisture. As the windows self-ventilated, they bowed and sagged.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Walter M. Cain, co-chairman of the restoration committee, said the cleaning and releading by the Jack Cushen Studio in 1988 and 1989 provided an invaluable head start. ''None of that work was wasted,'' he said. ''This project would be hugely more expensive if the glass had not been cleaned already.''</p>
        <p>One window already has a restored frame, new horizontal support beams and a new protective glazing, this time in glass and adequately ventilated. Two windows are now at Rohlf's Stained and Leaded Glass Studio in Mount Vernon, N.Y. The conservator is William Stivale.</p>
        <p>The $650,000 project, to be finished in 2003, includes repainting the church, which suffered damage when moisture was trapped inside the walls by a repointing project.</p>
        <p>Not every renovation has such unintended results but neither do incremental projects always cure what ails a structure.</p>
        <p>A somewhat cosmetic renovation in the early 70's left Abyssinian with continuing maintenance problems. Church leaders came up with a list of $250,000 in needed repairs. ''It went from $250,000 to $2 million,'' Dr. Butts recalled. ''Then it went from $2 million to $4 million. Then we started to look at the outside of the church. Then we said, 'We've always had problems with the sound system.' Then we had to get the lights right. Then the stained glass.''</p>
        <p>A sense of stewardship prevailed. ''We think it is important to preserve architecture,'' Dr. Butts said, ''particularly because we are involved in so many other ways in the rebirth of Harlem.''</p>
        <p>Donors are more easily persuaded to finance tangible, visible features like pews, particularly if their names can be attached. It is harder to get them to underwrite invisible, prosaic infrastructure.</p>
        <p>''They never see this,'' Dr. Butts said, as he inspected the rooftop air-conditioning. ''You have to tell them, 'This is what costs money.' You never see air-conditioning but, oh, do you feel it.'' Or hear it, in the case of radiators that had to be replaced. ''Each Sunday morning you say, 'Let us meditate' -- then Clang! Bang!'' the pastor said.</p>
        <p>The architect is Claude Hurt Jr. and the interiors are by Alma Nugent of Nugent Designs. The construction manager is the G. P. J. O'Donoghue Contracting Corporation, which has been involved in the renovation of the Calvary Baptist Church and Rutgers Presbyterian Church in Manhattan and St. Sebastian's Church in Woodside, Queens, among others. The project manager, Greg Graves, belongs to Abyssinian.</p>
        <p>To undertake this work, Abyssinian has borrowed $6 million from the Carver Federal Savings Bank. ''We'll be 200 years old in seven years,'' Dr. Butts said, ''by which time we hope all of this is paid for.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
