<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; Fuel Cell Companies Offer Choice and Risk</title>
    <meta content="23CELL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/23/business/yourmoney/23CELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1353760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ludlum, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">FuelCell Energy Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D61E3EF930A15751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; Fuel Cell Companies Offer Choice and Risk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fuel Cell Companies Offer Choice and Risk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LUDLUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ludlum, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysts comment on outlook for fuel cell industry and particular companies in it; shares of fuel cell companies soared to triple-digit gains in 2000 and plunged as much as 95 percent in 2001; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHARES of fuel cell companies soared last year, posting triple-digit gains during the California energy crisis. This year,  as energy supplies have rebounded, their prices have sunk as much as 95 percent from the highs.</p>
        <p>''The valuations had gotten way ahead of themselves,'' said Richard A. Giesen, manager of Munder Power Plus fund, which invests in energy companies. Now, he says, prices are low for some stocks, and he is buying selectively. Some analysts agree with that outlook, at least for investors willing to take some risks with companies that may not be profitable for several years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As energy supplies have rebounded, share prices of fuel cell companies have sunk as much as 95 percent from the highs. Is the price now right to buy?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHARES of fuel cell companies soared last year, posting triple-digit gains during the California energy crisis. This year,  as energy supplies have rebounded, their prices have sunk as much as 95 percent from the highs.</p>
        <p>''The valuations had gotten way ahead of themselves,'' said Richard A. Giesen, manager of Munder Power Plus fund, which invests in energy companies. Now, he says, prices are low for some stocks, and he is buying selectively. Some analysts agree with that outlook, at least for investors willing to take some risks with companies that may not be profitable for several years.</p>
        <p>According to ratings compiled by Thomson Financial Services, the analysts' current favorites are FuelCell Energy of Danbury, Conn; Hydrogenics of Mississauga, Ontario; and Proton Energy Systems of Rocky Hill, Conn.</p>
        <p>Fuel cell companies are developing products to power homes, offices and factories as well as vehicles and electronic devices. Most fuel cells are still prototypes that can be expensive to buy and to operate. To realize the promise of fuel cells, the companies need to push down costs.</p>
        <p>Like batteries, fuel cells use a chemical reaction that can be twice as efficient as burning a fuel. The fuel cells cut carbon dioxide emissions and produce essentially no noise or noxious fumes. They make electricity by combining oxygen from the air with hydrogen, which they can extract from a fuel like natural gas or propane. ''You don't have to go to the Middle East or drill in Alaska to get it,'' said David Redstone, editor of The Hydrogen and Fuel Cell Investor, a newsletter.</p>
        <p>Analysts tend to see the most immediate market, and investment opportunity, in fuel cells for stationary applications: powering remote equipment, homes, offices and factories. The big fuel cells that a few companies are developing tend to be more efficient than smaller ones so they generate electricity at a lower cost, said Tom O'Neill, a power technology analyst at Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>That helps explain FuelCell Energy's popularity among analysts. The company is developing particularly efficient fuel cells for large commercial and industrial users. ''If you're looking for pure plays in the big fuel cells,'' said Christine Farkas, an energy technology analyst at Merrill Lynch, ''FuelCell Energy is the one you play.''</p>
        <p>But ''hold'' is the consensus among analysts for Ballard Power Systems of Burnaby, British Columbia, which is associated primarily with the vehicle market, and for Plug Power of Latham, N.Y., which focuses on residential and light commercial uses. ''Autos and residential are further out than commercial and industrial,'' Mr. Giesen said.</p>
        <p>The shares of FuelCell Energy jumped 23 percent when the company announced a distribution and development deal last month with Caterpillar of Peoria, Ill., which makes generators. Using what she calls conservative assumptions, Ms. Farkas assigns the shares a target price of $25 to $30 in 12 to 18 months. They closed at $13.99 on Friday.</p>
        <p>The stock of Hydrogenics has performed the best among the group this year, more than tripling since September. In October, the company announced an alliance with General Motors that includes plans to demonstrate the use of fuel cells to power cellphone towers. The alliance gives Hydrogenics access to G.M.'s research and marketing might, said David B. Smith, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. The stock is the only one he recommends among fuel cell companies; his target price is $12 in 12 months. It closed at $6.34 on Friday.</p>
        <p>PROTON ENERGY SYSTEMS plans to sell fuel cells with devices that produce hydrogen from electricity and water. Marko Pencak, an analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston, has a buy recommendation on the company, with a target price of $13 in 12 months; it closed at $7 on Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pencak said any climb in the price might be limited, however, until Proton announced a significant partnership. ''That could happen next week or a year from now,'' he said. ''The more progress they make, the more confidence we have.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts and investors say that the stocks will trade less on industry trends than on company fundamentals -- and that the companies are risky investments because  they are not yet profitable.</p>
        <p>''They can be incredibly volatile,'' said David Schoenwald, co-manager of the New Alternatives fund. ''It's very hard to value these things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
