<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Ever More Powerful As Crucial Link to Congress</title>
    <meta content="13CHEN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/13/politics/13CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1293116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EED71F3BF930A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Ever More Powerful As Crucial Link to Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ and ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dozen House Republicans from California were seething when they met with Vice President Dick Cheney last week to discuss the state's power crisis.</p>
        <p>Angry that Gray Davis, the state's Democratic governor, was trying to pin the blame for the problem on Republicans, the lawmakers urged the White House to fire back. Mr. Cheney, a former House leader, listened patiently as the lawmakers encouraged him and the White House to attack Mr. Davis, before tersely cutting off the clamor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dozen House Republicans from California were seething when they met with Vice President Dick Cheney last week to discuss the state's power crisis.</p>
        <p>Angry that Gray Davis, the state's Democratic governor, was trying to pin the blame for the problem on Republicans, the lawmakers urged the White House to fire back. Mr. Cheney, a former House leader, listened patiently as the lawmakers encouraged him and the White House to attack Mr. Davis, before tersely cutting off the clamor.</p>
        <p>''It's not part of the White House strategy and it won't be,'' Representative George P. Radanovich recalled Mr. Cheney saying.</p>
        <p>As quickly as he silenced talk of one option, he rekindled discussion of others. Legislators asked Mr. Cheney if the government could tell its offices in California to conserve energy. A few days later, it was done: Mr. Bush ordered federal offices in the state to lower their thermostats.</p>
        <p>''You talk to Dick Cheney and things happen, and he doesn't necessarily take credit,'' said Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader. ''There is a connection between going to Dick Cheney and getting action.''</p>
        <p>More than any vice president before him, Mr. Cheney has emerged as a supreme power broker within the Bush administration and between the White House and Capitol Hill. It is a role Mr. Bush planned for Mr. Cheney, the 60-year-old former secretary of defense and White House chief of staff with impeccable conservative credentials, when he picked him as his political partner. But Mr. Cheney has proved to be even more influential than was imagined during the campaign.</p>
        <p>As President Bush's consigliere, Mr. Cheney helps connect the dots for the administration as he zigzags all day long from hot-button issue to high-level meeting, discreetly imparting advice whenever his boss asks or needs to know.</p>
        <p>Behind the scenes, Mr. Cheney urged Mr. Bush to follow up quickly and unequivocally on his campaign pledge to build an expansive missile defense system. Last week, Mr. Bush gave that commitment in a major speech.</p>
        <p>Last month, when the White House sought to avert a divisive Republican Senate primary in Minnesota that could upset plans to challenge Senator Paul Wellstone, a Democrat, Mr. Cheney was asked to intervene. Shortly after the vice president called, one of the contenders, Tim Pawlenty, the majority leader of the Minnesota House, abandoned the race.</p>
        <p>''Because of the way the vice president operates, in a rather low-profile way, I think his influence oftentimes is substantially underestimated,'' said Senator Larry E. Craig, Republican of Idaho. ''His fingerprints are everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig credited Mr. Cheney with helping win Senate approval on Thursday for a budget plan close to what President Bush had proposed, clearing the way for the first big tax cut in two decades.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the vote, Mr. Cheney called a handful of senators, including Max Baucus of Montana, one of five Democrats who eventually backed the plan.</p>
        <p>In interviews and in recent television talk show appearances, Mr. Cheney has sought to paint a more prosaic picture of his work.</p>
        <p>''When you're in one of these jobs, there's the perception from the outside that you're powerful,'' he told CNN's Larry King. ''On the inside, you're not sure of the leverage you're connected to anything. I mean, you deal with difficult problems, try to move the Congress, shape public opinion, deal with a difficult situation -- and it's usually three yards in a cloud of dust. There aren't very many home runs in this business.''</p>
        <p>It is a business that begins every morning at 8 in the Oval Office, where Mr. Cheney sits down for coffee with the president to review world affairs and the day's agenda. Most days, the two men seem tethered at the hip.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush meets separately each week with Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, Mr. Cheney is there. When Mr. Bush has his weekly economic and domestic policy briefings, Mr. Cheney sits in. When Mr. Bush meets foreign leaders and dignitaries, Mr. Cheney is usually by his side.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney also meets weekly for lunch with Mr. Powell, Mr. Rumsfeld and Condoleezza Rice, the national security adviser. ''He has excellent judgment,'' Ms. Rice said. She said she especially valued Mr. Cheney's advice on the Middle East, a region he has known well since the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>This operating style, critics say, makes Mr. Bush a figurehead and Mr. Cheney the real man in charge. That is a perception the vice president rejects.</p>
        <p>''I see him several times a day, but that's what the president wanted when he asked me to be his running mate,'' Mr. Cheney said in a television interview last month. ''We work very closely together. But he's very much the C.E.O. of the operation. He runs the show, and I do whatever he wants me to do.''</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Cheney is getting ready to release a far-reaching energy report that was drafted by an interagency task force he led. Even though the report is expected to call for more oil and gas drilling, Mr. Cheney insists it will be balanced.</p>
        <p>''The idea that somehow only the energy industry has access just simply isn't true,'' Mr. Cheney said in an interview. ''We'll make decisions on what we think makes sound public policy.''</p>
        <p>In the coming weeks, Mr. Cheney will turn to overseeing an anti terrorism commission that will try to make one cohesive unit of the sprawl of agencies responsible for responding to acts of terrorism. And he will probably help reconcile the Pentagon's request for billions of extra dollars with fiscal restraints imposed by the White House budget office.</p>
        <p>White House aides say Mr. Bush entrusts the vice president with so much not only because of Mr. Cheney's experience and judgment, but also because he has no presidential ambitions of his own.</p>
        <p>''The vice president is ready to be president but he is not looking to be president,'' said Andrew H. Card Jr., the White House chief of staff. ''The vice president is on the president's team, and everyone who works for the vice president is on the president's team. That's a big change. With Reagan-Bush and Clinton-Gore, the reality is they had political interests that were sometimes not converging.''</p>
        <p>When he is not tackling issues at the White House, Mr. Cheney dashes quietly around Capitol Hill, where he responds to the questions, travails and ideas of countless Republican lawmakers in the House and Senate as he tries to push Mr. Bush's agenda. Senate Republicans call him the 51st senator, and Mr. Cheney responds in kind by attending their weekly policy lunches.</p>
        <p>But Democrats have complained that Mr. Cheney has ignored their views and has conducted his energy review largely in secret. Mr. Cheney has accepted an invitation to join Senate Democrats for lunch this Tuesday, and some of his aides are bracing for a contentious meeting.</p>
        <p>In the House -- where Mr. Cheney is most comfortable -- he attends Republican leadership meetings and holds court in an office just steps from the House floor, which Speaker J. Dennis Hastert cleared especially for him.</p>
        <p>But his involvement on the Hill goes far beyond meetings with leaders. In his quest to create a broad coalition for Mr. Bush's agenda, Mr. Cheney carves out time for just about any lawmaker who requests a meeting. And he is direct in a way many politicians are not.</p>
        <p>''There is no deviousness or hidden agenda,'' said Senator Pat Roberts, a Kansas Republican and a friend of Mr. Cheney's. ''What it is, is what it is. There is no wiggle-waggling around.''</p>
        <p>It is a care-and-feeding strategy with Congress that has gone a long way to win over lawmakers, who are often looking as much for an influential ear to bend as for results. ''When I convey my views to the vice president, it's equivalent virtually to the president,'' said Senator Susan Collins, Republican of Maine.</p>
        <p>The scene at the Senate Republicans' weekly luncheon last Tuesday illustrated how Mr. Cheney operates. The vice president sat at a table with seven senators, and throughout the meal lawmakers drifted over, dropped off notes or papers, and whispered requests about personnel, policy or legislation. He jotted it all down on a notepad.</p>
        <p>After the Senate lunch, Mr. Cheney spent a half hour with a half-dozen House Republican moderates, who have been critical of the administration's environmental policies and have expressed alarm at reports that Mr. Cheney's energy review will give short shrift to conservation.</p>
        <p>The legislators seemed as impressed by the vice president's accessibility as they were by his promises to promote conservation and renewable energy sources. ''This is the third or fourth time we've sat down with Dick Cheney since January,'' said Representative Wayne T. Gilchrest, a Maryland Republican whose district includes Chesapeake Bay. ''I didn't talk to Al Gore more than once in eight years, and that was for barely 45 seconds.''</p>
        <p>During the debate over the budget resolution in the Senate, Mr. Cheney practically camped out near the Senate floor, where he tried to persuade reluctant Republicans to vote for Mr. Bush's tax cut and helped soothe jittery nerves. When he was hungry, he ate in the Senate dining room. In the end, he cast two tie-breaking votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney is not one for grand entrances -- unlike former Vice President Al Gore, who often descended on Capitol Hill in a flurry of blaring sirens. His small motorcade stops at traffic lights on his orders.</p>
        <p>He has reduced his security detail to attract less attention. The sergeant-at-arms of the Senate, who is typically charged with walking vice presidents around the Capitol, has been relieved of that duty.</p>
        <p>''He seems to be everywhere, but in an understated way,'' said Senator Jon Kyl, Republican of Arizona.</p>
        <p>But is Mr. Cheney -- a man who has had four heart attacks over the last two and a half decades -- cramming too much into each workday?</p>
        <p>In March, he complained of mild chest pains, and doctors found that one of the arteries in his heart had become partly clogged again. They reopened the stent in the artery. Two days later, he was hustling from meeting to meeting. This week he acknowledged that he might have to return for another minor procedure someday.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cheney has tried to blunt people's fears by following doctors' orders. He works out for 30 minutes nearly every morning on an exercise machine, eats healthier foods and has lost 20 pounds since last fall.</p>
        <p>''There is a danger that he could be spread too thin,'' said Senator Roberts, comparing Mr. Cheney to Marshal Matt Dillon, the television western hero everyone always turned to to head up a posse. ''I don't know how many posses he can lead. I suppose that's a worry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
