<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Inside Al Gore's Head</title>
    <meta content="13DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/13/opinion/13DOWD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto Protocol</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7D6113EF930A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Inside Al Gore's Head</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column satirizes Pres Bush's visit to Europe, his first prtesidential trip, from perspective of former Vice Pres Al Gore (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Talk about Goofy meets Goya.</p>
        <p>W.'s in Spain consulting with the prime minister about the Kyoto Protocol on global warming, and I'm here giving the commencement address to the high school seniors at Sidwell Friends, telling them how I used to be the next president.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Talk about Goofy meets Goya.</p>
        <p>W.'s in Spain consulting with the prime minister about the Kyoto Protocol on global warming, and I'm here giving the commencement address to the high school seniors at Sidwell Friends, telling them how I used to be the next president.</p>
        <p>Ho-la! What is WRONG with this picture?</p>
        <p>All that guy knows about my issue is that the acid rain in Spain falls mainly on the plain.</p>
        <p>Does he know that Kyoto was founded as Heiankyo in A.D. 794? (Sigh) Does he know that Kyoto is the home of 20 percent of Japan's national treasures and 15 percent of its important cultural properties, as well as 17 temples and shrines designated as World Heritage Sites by Unesco in 1994? (Big sigh)</p>
        <p>I can't believe he's treating his first presidential trip like ''National Lampoon's European Vacation.'' He finally gets to go to Europe and he's not even hitting Europe. Europe is France, England and Germany, n'est-ce pas? W.'s going to Spain, Poland, Sweden and that other hotbed of intrigue and international tension, Brussels, to sign the all-important Godiva Accord of 2001.</p>
        <p>Not exactly the big powers, Boy George!</p>
        <p>I'd be off to Germany to wrest control of the future of Europe from the Bundesbank. I'd be off to France to tell Chirac just who's in charge of this alliance. I'd be off to England to help Tony Blair cure foot-and-mouth disease, fix the National Health Service and put an end to fox hunting, once and for all.</p>
        <p>It's pathetic the way they arrange his whole illegitimate presidency to cater to his teensy interests. He starts with glad-handing in Spain so he can show off his mangled Spanish.</p>
        <p>I spoke Spanish during the campaign, too. I told folks that oportunidad is not just a palabra.</p>
        <p>W. thinks Madrid is El Paso East. He thought there'd be a mariachi band at the airport. He's over there asking Queen Sofia for her chalupa recipe. He went to the Prado to pick up a nice handbag for Laura.</p>
        <p>W.'s own top guy told The Times that they have to convince the Europeans that the president is not ''a shallow, arrogant, gun-loving, abortion-hating, Christian fundamentalist Texan buffoon.'' And his daddy's still sending him memos on how to handle North Korea. Caramba!</p>
        <p>Saturday is going to be the scariest day, when he meets with the president of Russia about the ABM treaty in Slovenia, which he probably still thinks is Slovakia. I bet he's not even bringing any charts or diagrams with him. He'll be blubbering ''Get me Condi!'' in no time.</p>
        <p>You think Kennedy looked rattled when he came out of the Khrushchev meeting? Wait until little Georgie gets a load of that K.G.B. stare. He probably thinks Putin is a rude French word a Deke once tried to teach him at Yale.</p>
        <p>I got criticized for losing Russia and cozying up to corrupt oligarchs. Critics thought I turned a blind eye while Chernomyrdin and his cronies got rich by sucking billions of dollars from the collapsing Soviet Union into their Swiss bank accounts. Just because a vice president hangs around with penniless Communist bureaucrats who turn into Donald Trumps overnight, people doubt your sincerity. I prefer to think of it as launching Russian capitalism in Zurich.</p>
        <p>Anyhow, I can tell you from experience, W., trust but verify.</p>
        <p>I know everyone's been wondering why I haven't spoken out against W. and Cheney's environmental pillaging if I feel so passionately about emissions and chlorofluorocarbons and fungicides and stuff.</p>
        <p>I do care about the Earth. But I care more about getting to be president. So I need to focus on my fund-raising and strategizing.</p>
        <p>As I told the kids at Sidwell, I have been studying Kahlil Gibran and Deepak Chopra. That's because I'm getting ready to take on W. after I sweep aside those other uppity Ken dolls -- Evan Bayh, John Edwards and John Kerry, and that ungrateful upstart Joe Lieberman already heading to New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''The Prophet'' advises silence:  ''For thought is a bird of space, that in a cage of words may indeed unfold its wings but cannot fly.''</p>
        <p>I have put on a little weight, and I still have The Spot. But that's O.K. As Deepak says, ''Your body is just the place your memories call home.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
