<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conservation-Mindful Bush Turns to Energy Research</title>
    <meta content="Y29ENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/29/politics/29ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1305525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DC1439F93AA15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conservation-Mindful Bush Turns to Energy Research</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conservation-Mindful Bush Turns to Energy Research</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush tours Energy Department and sends Congress an outline of his program to meet America's hunger for gasoline and electricity; Bush unexpectedly proposes nearly $300 million to finance Clinton-era research programs on energy conservation, money that administration struck from budget earlier this year; photo of Bush and Energy Sec Spencer Abraham (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As President Bush toured the Energy Department today and sent Congress an outline of his program to meet America's hunger for gasoline and electricity, something unexpected cropped up: a presidential proposal for nearly $300 million to finance Clinton-era research programs on energy conservation, money that the administration struck from the budget earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The proposal to restore the research money followed a series of polls showing that Americans believed that Mr. Bush's energy plans were primarily about helping oil companies and drilling in the Arctic  rather than energy savings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush sent Congress an outline of his energy program, with an unexpected proposal for nearly $300 million to finance research on conservation</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As President Bush toured the Energy Department today and sent Congress an outline of his program to meet America's hunger for gasoline and electricity, something unexpected cropped up: a presidential proposal for nearly $300 million to finance Clinton-era research programs on energy conservation, money that the administration struck from the budget earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The proposal to restore the research money followed a series of polls showing that Americans believed that Mr. Bush's energy plans were primarily about helping oil companies and drilling in the Arctic  rather than energy savings.</p>
        <p>The White House maintained that polls had nothing to do with Mr. Bush's decision and that instead a ''preliminary review'' by Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham showed that the research programs, on energy efficiency and the development of renewable energy, ''may be supportive of the president's objectives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush used his visit to the Energy Department today to talk extensively about conservation, a topic to which he has turned with increasing frequency. That focus runs contrary to earlier dismissive references by Vice President Dick Cheney, who previously suggested that while conservation was a sign of ''personal virtue,'' it did not constitute an energy strategy.</p>
        <p>In addition to the research funds, Mr. Bush today called for federal and corporate work on small devices called ''vampire slayers'' that could cut the power consumption of appliances that constantly draw electricity as they await use -- copiers, fax machines, cell-phone chargers and the like.</p>
        <p>''Vampire devices use about 4 percent of the electricity in the average home,'' Mr. Bush said. ''And to put this on a national scale, if we multiplied the vampire devices' energy consumption across the country, we're talking about 52 billion kilowatt-hours of power a year, or the equivalent of 26 average-size power plants.''</p>
        <p>Environmental groups said Mr. Bush was neglecting conservation measures that could prove far more effective, like raising fuel-efficiency standards for cars. ''Everything he did on the standby-power problem is good, but it is comparatively small potatoes,'' said David Nemtzow, president of the Alliance to Save Energy, which has been lobbying for more conservation measures.</p>
        <p>Both mileage standards and a restoring of the Clinton administration's proposals on air-conditioner efficiency, Mr. Nemtzow said, would save far more power than anything the president discussed today.</p>
        <p>Senate and House Republicans, meanwhile, stepped up the pressure on Democrats to push Mr. Bush's long-term energy plan. They accused Democrats of delaying action on an energy bill for the sake of political gain and vowed to explain to voters in their districts during the Congressional recess next week the urgency of passing comprehensive legislation. The Republican effort over the recess -- complete with handouts, videos and talking points -- is being coordinated with the White House.</p>
        <p>Hoping to prod the process on Capitol Hill, Mr. Bush sent Congress today his energy plan's broadly written legislative initiatives, dealing mostly with conservation (including the restored research money), modernizing and expanding pipelines and tramission lines, drilling for oil and  promoting nuclear energy. Many of the ideas are already addressed in Senate Republican energy legislation. The House is beginning work on a separate bill.</p>
        <p>Republicans called on the Senate majority leader, Tom Daschle of  South Dakota, to schedule floor debate on the legislation. For his part,  Mr. Daschle said the Democrats planned to begin committee hearings in July. ''It's a schedule that I think illustrates the degree to which we are taking the matter seriously,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Senator Frank H. Murkowski, the Alaska Republican who formerly headed the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said of the Democrats: ''By refusing to take this matter up in a timely manner, they are setting a very dangerous precedent. Now I know they are playing politics. The longer they refuse, the more they can point out, 'Well, this is a Republican problem, it's the Republicans that aren't solving it.' ''</p>
        <p>In pressing their message on energy, Republicans have tried to blunt the Democrats' political advantage on the issue. Taking Mr. Bush's lead, they are now quick to talk about conservation and protecting the environment before moving on to speak of a need for increased oil and gas production. Recent public opinion surveys find that voters prefer investing time and money in conservation and the search for cleaner-burning fuels than in drilling for more oil.</p>
        <p>Like the Republicans, Democrats  expect to talk about energy during the recess; their emphasis will be on  the large campaign contributions that Republican leaders have received from the energy industry.</p>
        <p>The president's energy plan ''is heavy on rhetoric and short on action,'' said Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader. ''He brings out a glossy paper book four weeks ago, and they seem to be doing the opposite of what's in the plan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
