<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Appraisal; Bill Clinton's Mixed Legacy</title>
    <meta content="14SUN1$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/14/opinion/14SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1262794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DC143DF937A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Appraisal; Bill Clinton's Mixed Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial appraising Bill Clinton's mixed legacy, and near-miss quality of presidency that never quite lived up to potential within him; observes that Clinton's White House years have been marked y prosperity, rancor, achivements, disappointments and something approaching national psychodrama involving man himself</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent editorial cartoon by Matt Davies of The Journal News showed Bill Clinton trying to make a diving catch of a huge ball. The ball, labeled ''Greatness,'' lands just out of his reach. The drawing provided a haunting visual metaphor for the near-miss quality of a presidency that never quite measured up to the potential that every supporter and most critics knew resided within Mr. Clinton. Yet simply stating the fact that Mr. Clinton is not destined to enter the pantheon of great, universally respected presidents does not capture the richness, complexity and drama of these eight years. No citizen is likely to forget them or, for that matter, to quit debating the man's remarkable gifts and the narcissistic indiscipline that diminished them.</p>
        <p>His White House years have been been marked by prosperity, rancor, achievements, disappointments and something approaching a national psychodrama involving Mr. Clinton himself. Trying to separate Mr. Clinton from the times he presided over is like trying, in Yeats's phrase, to tell the dancer from the dance. Mr. Clinton presented himself as an agent for change. But with or without him, the 90's were bound to be a decade when change rolled across the economy, international relations and the political culture with a grinding inexorability. Historians will surely record Mr. Clinton as the first president to be impeached since 1868 and as having presided over America's longest economic expansion. That's the easy sentence to write. But they may also come to see him as the shaper of some main themes of governance for the 21st century. President-elect George W. Bush, who gained a lot of votes from Clinton fatigue, will not be able to ignore the policies Mr. Clinton installed or the expectations he created.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A recent editorial cartoon by Matt Davies of The Journal News showed Bill Clinton trying to make a diving catch of a huge ball. The ball, labeled ''Greatness,'' lands just out of his reach. The drawing provided a haunting visual metaphor for the near-miss quality of a presidency that never quite measured up to the potential that every supporter and most critics knew resided within Mr. Clinton. Yet simply stating the fact that Mr. Clinton is not destined to enter the pantheon of great, universally respected presidents does not capture the richness, complexity and drama of these eight years. No citizen is likely to forget them or, for that matter, to quit debating the man's remarkable gifts and the narcissistic indiscipline that diminished them.</p>
        <p>His White House years have been been marked by prosperity, rancor, achievements, disappointments and something approaching a national psychodrama involving Mr. Clinton himself. Trying to separate Mr. Clinton from the times he presided over is like trying, in Yeats's phrase, to tell the dancer from the dance. Mr. Clinton presented himself as an agent for change. But with or without him, the 90's were bound to be a decade when change rolled across the economy, international relations and the political culture with a grinding inexorability. Historians will surely record Mr. Clinton as the first president to be impeached since 1868 and as having presided over America's longest economic expansion. That's the easy sentence to write. But they may also come to see him as the shaper of some main themes of governance for the 21st century. President-elect George W. Bush, who gained a lot of votes from Clinton fatigue, will not be able to ignore the policies Mr. Clinton installed or the expectations he created.</p>
        <p>Clinton fatigue is a catch phrase for the public disenchantment engendered by Mr. Clinton's lapses. When he failed, he failed big. First came health care and its secretive process run by the first lady, Hillary Rodham Clinton. The refusal to be open about Whitewater was a joint responsibility, but Mr. Clinton's later fateful decision to deceive Mrs. Clinton, a grand jury and all Americans about sexual adventurism in the Oval Office was a mistake for which he alone was responsible.</p>
        <p>By contrast, when Mr. Clinton achieved, it was in increments. Historians may never discern a grand architectural edifice of achievements on the scale of the New Deal or Great Society. Yet those increments add up to an impressive benchmark.</p>
        <p>Setting a Course</p>
        <p>In his book on President John F. Kennedy, Richard Reeves argues that a presidency can be measured by a handful of fateful decisions. For Mr. Clinton, a string of decisions on the economy belies his reputation as a poll-driven politician. In many cases, Mr. Clinton relied instead on gut instincts and was proved right. In 1993, for instance, he rejected the advice of many Democrats to stick with a liberal agenda of spending programs. Instead, he listened to his chief economic adviser, Robert Rubin, and went with fiscal restraint. His tax increase on the top brackets angered conservatives and led to the loss of Congress to the Republicans in 1994. But without a stringent fiscal policy, the United States would not today be trying to decide what to do with surpluses instead of deficits.</p>
        <p>Another bold move came when he stood up to his party's orthodoxy and embraced opening trade barriers with the North American Free Trade Agreement with Mexico and Canada, the accord to create a new World Trade Organization and the upgrading of trade relations with China. It is too soon to be positive that these will bring the benefits Mr. Clinton promised, but there is no doubting that he planted himself on the right side of history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has been at his best and most memorable in advocating engagement in the world in order to lift everyone's hopes for freedom and economic growth. If Ronald Reagan reasserted America's military power, Mr. Clinton reasserted its economic power in the information age. His growing confidence enabled him to act audaciously, first intervening to save the Mexican economy and later to prevent a collapse in Asia. These steps were among the president's finest moments.</p>
        <p>Days of Battle</p>
        <p>As a new president, Mr. Clinton did not truly find his identity until adversity struck. It came like a thunderclap in November of 1994 when the voters handed the Congress over to Newt Gingrich and the Republicans. Mr. Clinton seemed wobbly at first, and perhaps overly obsessed with polls. But Mr. Clinton's pride in his ability to bounce back after a heavy punch was justified. Early in 1995, he stood up to the Republican leadership and later allowed the government to close rather than accept the Gingrich revolution's punitive budget cuts.</p>
        <p>Two of Mr. Clinton's biggest achievements flowed from that standoff. First, on the environment, the president was persuaded by Vice President Al Gore and others to fight Republican efforts to eviscerate the Clean Water Act. Thereafter he vetoed repeated Congressional attempts to weaken environmental standards and compiled the best conservation record of any president since Theodore Roosevelt. Among his achievements were tighter air pollution controls, new protections for wilderness areas, national forests and national parks, and the negotiation of a still-unratified global warming treaty.</p>
        <p>The second outgrowth of the confrontation with Congress was Mr. Clinton's determination to build a progressive record step by step. Among the accomplishments are an expanded earned-income tax credit for millions of poor families; a health initiative covering 3.3 million poor children; welfare-to-work aid enacted in the years subsequent to his signing of welfare reform; a doubling of Head Start and school aid for the disadvantaged; and an expansion in college tuition aid for low- and moderate-income students. The administration estimates that in all an extraordinary $64 billion is now newly channeled annually to working-class and poor families, far more than might have been enacted in one big program. None of this can outweigh the failure to install the universal health care he promised in 1992. But for the first time in at least two decades, the lowest-income families have gained from good times, and indeed have gained the most.</p>
        <p>A Dangerous World</p>
        <p>As the first post-cold-war president, Mr. Clinton has had difficulty finding a theme to sum up his approach to the world. He was slow to engage, in part because his first two years were spent on the economy and health care. His inattention led to missteps in the Balkans and Africa. But nowhere, this page not excepted, could one find flawless guidance and predictions on Serbia and Rwanda. Yet the president got his footing and developed a distinctive style, and he leaves office as the most authoritative figure in international diplomacy. He often succeeded by becoming involved personally  with other leaders. The most dramatic instance was his effort to advance democracy and free markets in Russia by allying the United States with Boris Yeltsin, despite the Russian president's erratic leadership. That was a tough call that came with a cost as international indifference to corruption encouraged criminalization of the Russian economy and soured many Russians on American leadership. But the decision helped thwart a resurgence of Communism and secure crucial Russian support for a negotiated end to the bombing campaign that forced the Serbs out of Kosovo and hastened the departure of Slobodan Milosevic in Serbia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's personal involvement with Prime Ministers Yitzhak Rabin and Ehud Barak of Israel, and with Yasir Arafat and King Hussein of Jordan, surely speeded the possibility of a settlement in the Middle East, even though a final deal has eluded him. Less noticed was his willingness to make some tough decisions to try to bring trust to combatants in Northern Ireland and between India and Pakistan and to ease tensions with North Korea. Mr. Clinton's early emphasis on human rights in China did not achieve results and led to a confrontation over Taiwan. He salvaged relations with the Chinese by emphasizing economics. But the overarching theme of his presidency has been the twin impulses to embrace economic globalization and to get warring countries in various regions talking.</p>
        <p>Finally, there was the bold decision to wage a bombing campaign in Kosovo. It was this campaign that expanded the role of NATO for the first time to include combatting ethnic and genocidal conflict at its European back door, which united European powers around American leadership. In general, Mr. Clinton has rightly broadened the definition of national security to encompass the spread of disease, poverty and ethnic strife, ending his term with honorable involvement in the world and revitalization of the United Nations and regional peacekeeping alliances.</p>
        <p>Moments of Truth and Untruth</p>
        <p>Of course if these decisions were moments of truth in which Mr. Clinton faced a tough set of choices and made the right call, his biographers can never ignore the catastrophic ethical lapses that punctuated his tenure. The conduct ranged from overt lying about Monica Lewinsky to inhibiting the Whitewater real estate investigations to flooding his 1996 campaign with foreign money. By allowing his attorney general, Janet Reno, to block a full investigation of the 1996 fund-raising abuses, he blotted both their records. The impeachment will always stand as the emblem of Mr. Clinton's character flaws and failure to achieve the greatness inherent in his better self.</p>
        <p>Yet his self-indulgence and self-pity and recklessness have come, like it or not, intertwined with great empathy, especially for those who have been victims because of their race, gender or sexual orientation. As he leaves the presidency, we hope Mr. Clinton will find a way to use those gifts on the national and world stage. He will likely have a different role than Jimmy Carter's strictly humanitarian one of opposing poverty and disease. But Mr. Clinton, at 54, will be a very young ex-president. If he disciplines himself to be as intent on enriching the world as on enriching himself, he could write a constructive and surprising last chapter to this most novelistic of modern presidencies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
