<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuel With a Dark Past Has a Bright Future</title>
    <meta content="16COAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/16/science/16COAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gillette (Wyo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wyoming</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E7DC1531F935A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuel With a Dark Past Has a Bright Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Energy Disruptions Brighten Future of Coal, a Fossil of a Fuel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>GILLETTE, Wyo., June 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Power disruptions and new administration that puts greater focus on energy security than environmental protection has given coal new lease on life; in places like Gillette, Wyo, which might be called new capital of coal, utilities are beginning to reconsider plans, switching to coal from gas, helping coal industry and its miners; about 52 percent of nation's electricity is generated by coal; this year, nation's coal production is expected to reach record of more than 1.1 billion tons; one-quarter of that comes from Wyoming, where coal is low in sulfur and near surface; two factors have influenced coal's re-emergence, after years of vilification by environmentalists: soaring natural gas prices and Bush administration's decision to back away from imposing restrictions on carbon dioxide; Congressional Democrats and Republicans from coal states have joned forces to fend off industry's foes; photos; graph (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Switch on a light somewhere in the country and the odds are one in two that it will be powered not by oil, natural gas, uranium, water, wind or anything else but by coal, that Industrial Revolution-era fuel that seems, at least for now, to have reclaimed a 21st-century future.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, coal was widely considered a fuel of the past, vilified by environmentalists for its links to acid rain and global warming. But power disruptions and an administration that has put a greater focus on energy security than environmental protection have given coal a new lease on life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>America's energy disruptions combined with an administration that has elevated energy security over environmental protection have given coal a new lease on life</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Switch on a light somewhere in the country and the odds are one in two that it will be powered not by oil, natural gas, uranium, water, wind or anything else but by coal, that Industrial Revolution-era fuel that seems, at least for now, to have reclaimed a 21st-century future.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, coal was widely considered a fuel of the past, vilified by environmentalists for its links to acid rain and global warming. But power disruptions and an administration that has put a greater focus on energy security than environmental protection have given coal a new lease on life.</p>
        <p>And now, to great joy in places like Gillette, in Campbell County, which might be called the new capital of coal, utilities have begun to reconsider plans, switching to coal from gas, helping not only the industry but also miners like Colt Johnson, 36.</p>
        <p>''What I try to explain to my kids is that without coal, we wouldn't have lights,'' Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>About 52 percent of the nation's electricity is generated by coal, a figure that has been fairly consistent over the last 5 years, but is a big increase over 10 years ago. And this year, the nation's coal production is expected to reach a record of more than 1.1 billion tons. About one-quarter of that will come from Wyoming, where coal is low in sulfur and near the surface, giving the state two big advantages as the industry tries to retain its share in energy supply.</p>
        <p>This is what has happened in the last year: Natural gas prices have soared, frightening those who saw that fuel as a kind of panacea for electricity. The Bush administration has backed away from imposing restriction on carbon dioxide, a move would have dealt new setbacks to the industry. And the support for coal has proved politically formidable, with Congressional Democrats from coal states in Appalachia and Republicans from the Rockies joining forces to fend off the industry's foes.</p>
        <p>The political support has been strengthened by the fact that the concerns of environmentalists have been focused less on coal mines than on oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge.</p>
        <p>Coal's brighter future is a product in large part of a task force headed by Vice President Dick Cheney, a Wyoming native, which ruled out proposals that might have relegated coal to secondary status and issued a report with no plans to wean the country from the fossil fuel.</p>
        <p>''If rising U.S. electricity demand is to be met, then coal must play a significant role,'' the task force said in its report last month, projecting that coal would continue to account for about 50 percent of electricity generation for at least the next 20 years.</p>
        <p>Of the new electric generation planned for the United States from  now to 2005, as much as 16 percent is  to come from coal, according to the Edison Electric Institute, the industry's main trade group. That is a major increase from a year ago when no coal-fired plants were on the drawing board, and it is a sign that  coal, whose reserves are estimated to be enough to power the country for the next 275 years, is anything but dead.</p>
        <p>Because the burning of coal is a major contributor to global warming, scientists say, responsible for about one-third of American emissions of heat-trapping gases, the industry's future may still be fragile.</p>
        <p>For now, the Bush administration has rejected imposing strict controls on the emissions of carbon dioxide, a major byproduct of burning coal and  major contributor to global warming. But some top officials in the industry say the question concerning such controls is not if, but when.</p>
        <p>''We have our work cut out for us in terms of addressing environmental issues,'' said Gary J. Goldberg, president and chief executive officer of the Kennecott Energy Company, one of the country's largest coal producers. ''Ultimately, there's going to have to be some kind of a target in terms of Co2 reduction, and if we can't get there voluntarily, we'll have to get there somewhere else.''</p>
        <p>But even as the Bush administration and the industry pump money into projects designed to promote so-called clean-coal technology, the basic work of stripping back the earth, gouging out the coal, and loading it on rail cars bound for power plants is thriving as never before in places like Wyoming's Powder River Basin, of which this town is the center.</p>
        <p>''The ugly head of environmentalism has been pushed down,'' said David Haddix, 40, a major-equipment operator at Kennecott's Cordero Rojo mine, about 30 miles southeast of Gillette, and where antelope and deer vie for space with huge  trucks at one of the largest coal mines in the country.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, since the 1990 amendments to the Clean Air Act, the coal industry has already weathered major changes. With power plants required by the amendments to reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide, which contributes to acid rain, and nitrous oxide, a heat-trapping gas and an ingredient of smog, some installed equipment known as scrubbers. Others switched their supply from sources like West Virginia and Kentucky, where coal is high in these chemicals, particularly sulfur, to new sources like Wyoming, where the low-sulfur content of the coal reduces polluting emissions.</p>
        <p>Over all, those changes have brought about a major geographic shift in the mining of coal, so that the Western United States, not the East, is the country's biggest supplier. The emissions of pollutants from burning coal have plunged, government statistics show, with emissions of sulfur dioxide per kilowatt hour down as much as 35 percent since 1989.</p>
        <p>But there has been no reduction in emissions of carbon dioxide, the so-called greenhouse gas. In the presidential campaign, President Bush promised to regulate carbon dioxide emissions but reversed that plan in March, citing energy concerns.</p>
        <p>But because the coal-fired power plants account for about 30 percent of emissions of carbon dioxide in the United States, environmentalists like David Hawkins of the Natural Resources Defense Council say they believe that further restrictions are inevitable.</p>
        <p>''What is happening in terms of coal's resurgence may be a very short-term phenomenon,'' Mr. Hawkins said. ''If the coal industry wants to establish a viable strategy for maintaining its existing role in the energy structure, it's going to have to address these questions about global warming.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration and the  industry are spending hundreds of millions of dollars on the development of technologies designed to make the burning of coal environmentally cleaner. The most promising is to turn the coal into gas before it is burned, so that the carbon is separated, minimizing the contribution to global warming. The carbon would be stored deep underground.</p>
        <p>A handful of coal companies, including Kennecott, have joined in this effort, enlisting in projects like one founded by the Pew Center for Global Climate Change, in Washington, to address the problem. But most others have not, and that has frustrated those who think that coal's lease on life will be no more than temporary unless the industry agrees to some plan for reducing the emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>Still, people like Mr. Haddix, a miner for 18 years, said they see environmentalists as their biggest foe. ''I do enjoy our environment,'' Mr. Haddix said. ''I like to hunt, fish, hike and camp. But on the other hand, I like having lights and watching the Colorado Avalanche.''</p>
        <p>Cost has also contributed to the shift of mining to Wyoming, where it is considerably less expensive to mine coal from huge seams near the surface than in Appalachia, where coal lies deep underground. Just as important is the fact that Western coal is much lower in sulfur.</p>
        <p>Since 1999, the overall production of coal from states west of Missouri has eclipsed that from the East.</p>
        <p>The energy crisis facing California, with a quadrupling in the cost of natural gas, has been a major factor in the utilities' decisions to shift their plans from gas to coal.</p>
        <p>Still, people like Mr. Ginsberg, the coal company executive, say they are uneasy. ''The coal industry has no free pass,'' Mr. Ginsberg said, ''and we must continue to demonstrate the sustainable role coal can play in our country's affordable energy future as we work to continue to reduce emissions from coal-fired generation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
