<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France and Germany Jointly Seek a Ban on Cloning Humans</title>
    <meta content="Y22GER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/22/international/europe/22GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1319133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischer, Joschka (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vedrine, Hubert (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D71631F931A1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France and Germany Jointly Seek a Ban on Cloning Humans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">France and Germany Jointly Seek a Ban on Cloning Humans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>French and German governments ask UN to approve call for worldwide ban on human cloning for reproductive purposes; will also seek US support; Foreign Ministers Joschka Fischer and Hubert Vedrine met in June to plan renewed cooperation on range of issues; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French and German governments have come together in a request to the United Nations to approve a measure seeking a worldwide ban on human cloning for reproductive purposes.</p>
        <p>In a joint statement, the two nations have called on Secretary General Kofi Annan to present their proposal to the General Assembly, which meets in September. They urge the creation of a working group to draft a convention that would ban reproductive cloning as an offense ''to human dignity.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French and German governments have come together in a request to the United Nations to approve a measure seeking a worldwide ban on human cloning for reproductive purposes</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The French and German governments have come together in a request to the United Nations to approve a measure seeking a worldwide ban on human cloning for reproductive purposes.</p>
        <p>In a joint statement, the two nations have called on Secretary General Kofi Annan to present their proposal to the General Assembly, which meets in September. They urge the creation of a working group to draft a convention that would ban reproductive cloning as an offense ''to human dignity.''</p>
        <p>The two countries say they hope and expect that their proposal, made early this month, will get backing from the Bush administration. While Mr. Bush has said his administration would allow limited stem cell research, he has expressed strong opposition to human cloning.</p>
        <p>The French and Germans hope that an anticloning convention would  be one international treaty that President Bush would choose to support, after he infuriated much of the Continent by pulling back from treaties about global warming, missile defense and biological warfare.</p>
        <p>A recent opinion poll of Europeans by the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press and The International Herald Tribune found unhappiness with Mr. Bush strongest in France and Germany. Solid majorities of those polled in both countries -- 65 percent in Germany and 59 percent in France -- said they disapproved of his handling of foreign policy.</p>
        <p>While the two countries agree on cloning, they differ in their laws about cloning stem cells for research.</p>
        <p>The French have been most outspoken in condemning human cloning, with Health Minister Bernard Kouchner telling Le Monde that ''we have to ban the photocopying of human beings right now'' and that it is ''simply morally unacceptable to create life while hijacking its very meaning.''</p>
        <p>But the French have only now drafted legislation that will specifically ban human cloning for reproduction, while the Germans banned cloning -- and anything that smelled of Nazi-era euthanasia and eugenics -- more than 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>The joint French-German proposal is as important for its diplomatic impact as its scientific one, officials from both countries said in interviews. After conflicts that arose over voting rights for nations of various sizes in an expanded European Union at a summit meeting in Nice last December, France and Germany moved quickly to increase and emphasize their cooperation.</p>
        <p>The French in particular have wanted to keep the Germans from playing too independent a role in Europe, or from drawing closer to Britain or the new candidate countries in Central Europe at the expense of France.</p>
        <p>Foreign Ministers Joschka Fischer of Germany and Hubert Védrine of France met in Paris on June 21 and laid the ground for renewed comity and cooperation.</p>
        <p>''A French-German initiative like this is a first,'' said Bernard Valero, the deputy spokesman for the French Foreign Ministry, describing the joint proposal on cloning. ''After Nice, we decided at the highest level to increase and develop Franco-German cooperation on many issues, from the Middle East and mad cow disease to Macedonia, immigration and cloning.''</p>
        <p>A German Foreign Ministry official agreed, saying: ''From the European perspective, cloning is a worthwhile issue on which it's safe to find common ground, both with the French and the Americans. It's a Franco-German initiative and a worthwhile goal.''</p>
        <p>With an informal European Union mandate, Mr. Fischer is currently in the Middle East, where he has been working to bring together Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, and Shimon Peres, the Israeli foreign minister. Today there were announcements that they were prepared to meet soon on how to put a cease-fire into effect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valero pointed out that Mr. Fischer will be in Paris again next week to have further meetings with Mr. Védrine about the Mideast, Macedonia and other issues.</p>
        <p>On the cloning issue, the German legislation, passed in 1990, bans all genetic research on embryos. There has been a debate about a potential loophole that might allow scientists to import stem cells grown elsewhere, but experimentation on such cells is forbidden in any case. In vitro fertilization is allowed, but only to aid conception; embryos not used are frozen for later use or discarded, and even testing of embryos before they are used to check for genetic flaws is forbidden.</p>
        <p>In France, the draft legislation, expected to be voted on next year, will revise 1994 laws on bioethics. If passed as written, the law would explicitly ban human cloning for reproduction for the first time, but it would permit therapeutic cloning and also allow -- and control -- scientific research on in vitro embryos and stem cells. Any embryos used in research must be formally deemed to be no longer intended to produce a child.</p>
        <p>The law would require the couple who originated the embryo to consent explicitly to its use for scientific research and would also create a new commission to provide advice, guidance and control.</p>
        <p>In Germany, there was a small furor at the end of May when Chancellor Gerhard Schröder, a pragmatic Social Democrat, spoke of the need for the nation to remain modern and to create jobs. Gene technology, he argued, produces new drugs, more jobs and new opportunities, and he argued for the possibility of scientific research on in vitro embryos. He also suggested that testing the embryos before they are used could prevent the birth of sick or deformed children.</p>
        <p>President Johannes Rau, however, although also a Social Democrat, argued vehemently against such research. ''Eugenics, euthanasia and selection are labels that are linked to bad memories in Germany,'' he said. ''Where human dignity is affected, economic arguments do not count.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schröder has set up -- and handpicked -- a commission of 24 scientists, philosophers, clergymen and other experts to guide the debate over bioethics.</p>
        <p>What is driving the ethical and political debate in Europe is simply the advance of science, the German ministry official said. ''In the last half year, suddenly cloning and sophisticated biomedical research on embryos has become scientifically possible and affordable,'' he said. Everyone is struggling with the ethics of this new world, he suggested, but especially the Germans, with their particular burden of the Nazi past.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
