<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Few Answers and Few Waves At Energy Designee's Hearing</title>
    <meta content="Y19ENE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/19/politics/19ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="TRANSITION IN WASHINGTON: THE ENERGY DEPARTMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EEDF173CF93AA25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Few Answers and Few Waves At Energy Designee's Hearing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres-elect Bush's choice for energy secretary, Spencer Abraham, disavows position he took as senator to dismantle Energy Dept, only question put to him about his energy record at congenial Senate confirmation hearing; Abraham refers to need for 'balanced' energy solution, including increased domestic production of oil and gas, conservation and more use of renewable energy sources, and decreased reliance on imported oil; offers no specifics about how to achieve these goals; committee approves Abraham's selection by unanimous voice vote; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush's choice for energy secretary, Spencer Abraham, today disavowed the position he had taken as a senator to dismantle the Energy Department, answering the only question put to him about his energy record at a congenial confirmation hearing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham was pressed a little harder on what the federal government should do about the California electricity crisis, but he refused to comment, saying he did not want to upset negotiations there among utilities, generators and state legislators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush's choice for energy secretary, Spencer Abraham, today disavowed the position he had taken as a senator to dismantle the Energy Department, answering the only question put to him about his energy record at a congenial confirmation hearing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham was pressed a little harder on what the federal government should do about the California electricity crisis, but he refused to comment, saying he did not want to upset negotiations there among utilities, generators and state legislators.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Abraham has been selected to head a department facing many contentious issues, members of the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources failed to extract specifics from him on most of the questions they asked.</p>
        <p>Most senators referred to the nominee, who is a former colleague, as Spence, but informality did not squeeze out the bizarre. Following Senate tradition, the nominee was introduced by the senators from his own state, Michigan, one of whom is Debbie Stabenow, a Democrat who defeated Mr. Abraham in November in his bid for a second term. The state's other senator, Carl Levin, also a Democrat, referred to the presentation as ''American democracy at its ironic best.''</p>
        <p>In about three hours, most of it taken up by panel members voicing their own opinions on subjects ranging from electricity shortages and gasoline mileage to nuclear waste, Mr. Abraham made these points:</p>
        <p>*The electric generation industry's shift to building plants that run almost exclusively on natural gas is creating an unbalanced system.</p>
        <p>*The National Nuclear Security Agency may be conducting too many lie-detector tests, subjecting even Mr. Abraham himself to the procedure.</p>
        <p>*Nuclear waste cleanup may need to be altered so the nation can ''begin to gain some ground on the cleanup of these sites.''</p>
        <p>''Overhead and security issues have consumed so much of the budget,'' Mr. Abraham complained. Environmental management will cost about $6.75 billion this year, he said, about a third of the department's spending. Hardly any land has been completely cleaned, but the work has cut the risk of spread of contamination in some cases, department officials say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham referred to the need for a ''balanced'' energy solution, including increased domestic production of oil and gas, conservation and more use of renewable energy sources, and decreased reliance on imported oil. But he offered no specifics about how to achieve these goals.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups complained today that as a senator from Michigan, Mr. Abraham opposed increases in fuel economy standards; today he said he thought the market was moving faster than was possible for the government to turn out fuel-efficient hybrid vehicles.</p>
        <p>After a break for lunch, the committee approved Mr. Abraham's selection by unanimous voice vote. But while members were supportive, several offered words of caution. Senator Frank H. Murkowski of Alaska, a Republican who will become chairman of the committee after the presidential inauguration, told Mr. Abraham, ''This is not necessarily a glamorous position.''</p>
        <p>While committee members seemed eager to pass legislation intended to cut reliance on oil imports, one, Senator Don Nickles, Republican of Oklahoma, said Congress would have to do better than in 1979, after the last oil crisis.</p>
        <p>The major bills then, he said, were the Synfuels Act, a billion-dollar effort to make liquid vehicle fuel from solid fuels; the Natural Gas Policy Act, which controlled the price of that fuel; the Fuel Use Act, which forbade the use of natural gas in power plants; the Windfall Profits Tax, which put price limits on oil, and the Energy Allocation Act, which gave government the power to distribute scarce supplies.</p>
        <p>All were later repealed, he said.</p>
        <p>TRANSITION IN WASHINGTON: THE ENERGY DEPARTMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
