<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back Issues</title>
    <meta content="11GRAHAMT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/11/books/review/11GRAHAMT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1342166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Loren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piel, Gerard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Age of Science, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Scientific American</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Piel, Gerard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEED71030F932A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back Issues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Age of Science': Back Issues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Loren Graham</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graham, Loren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Loren Graham reviews book The Age of Science: What Scientists Learned in the 20th Century by Gerard Piel (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AGE OF SCIENCE</p>
        <p>What Scientists Learned in the 20th Century.</p>
        <p>By Gerard Piel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Peter Bradford.</p>
        <p>460 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A Cornelia and Michael Bessie Book/</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $40.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gerard Piel, the founder of Scientific American, presents us with a synthesis of scientific knowledge drawing on issues of the magazine during the last 53 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AGE OF SCIENCE</p>
        <p>What Scientists Learned in the 20th Century.</p>
        <p>By Gerard Piel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Peter Bradford.</p>
        <p>460 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A Cornelia and Michael Bessie Book/</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $40.</p>
        <p>In May 1948 Gerard Piel, a former science editor for Life, started a new science magazine bearing the purchased title of a moribund periodical, Scientific American. Within a few years he and several associates created a model for science journalism that has had worldwide influence. By 1986 Scientific American had a circulation of over a million and was printed in English and nine other languages.</p>
        <p>The distinguishing characteristics of Piel's science journalism were a conviction that science is both objective and a social good, a refusal to talk down to his audience and careful, even lavish illustrations and photographs. His ideal reader was a scientist seeking knowledge outside his or her own field. He often enlisted scientists as authors, coaxing them with meticulous editing to find ways of explaining their recent work to intelligent people with other backgrounds. A nonscientist (he was an undergraduate in history at Harvard), Piel educated himself in science at the same time he promoted and edited informative overviews of recent scientific developments, which the editors of journals serving the individual scientific disciplines did not do.</p>
        <p>Piel, who retired as the publisher of Scientific American 15 years ago, now presents us with a synthesis of scientific knowledge drawing on issues of the magazine during the last 53 years. He describes his new book as ''what I have learned about what scientists learned in the 20th century.'' The main sections are ''Light and Matter,'' ''Space and Time,'' ''The Living Cell,'' ''Earth History and the Evolution of Life'' and ''Tools and Human Evolution.'' The resulting book is somewhat similar to a text for general science at the advanced high school or elementary college level, but infinitely more interesting. As Piel observes, such texts usually have an author named ''Dull.'' Piel is anything but dull.</p>
        <p>Impressive as this work is, however, it bears the stamp of the times in which Scientific American was born. Immediately after World War II, most educated American readers agreed wholeheartedly with Piel that science was truth and ''offers the example of reason, tolerance and individual autonomy.'' He still subscribes to this view, and gives us an optimistic vision of the fate of the world if we can all only learn to think and act like natural scientists.</p>
        <p>In his discussion of the future, Piel strongly emphasizes ''the demographic transition,'' the coming stabilization of the world's population as a result of increasing education and development. He correctly notes that in most industrialized and highly educated societies, fertility has fallen to, or below, the replacement rate of two children per childbearing female lifetime, and he cheerfully predicts that all countries will be in the same situation before the end of this century.</p>
        <p>He endorses Jacob Bronowski's rebuke of foreign-policy makers for not letting ''the tolerance or the empiricism of science enter the parochial rules by which we still try to prescribe the behavior of nations.'' Does he actually believe that natural scientists have better insights into the religious, ethnic and economic passions of the world than people who have spent their lives studying them?</p>
        <p>In the years since Piel began writing about science in 1938, his readers have become much more sophisticated. At that time many Americans thought that science was an unproblematic positive force; the most difficult questions connected with it were the technical issues themselves. If we could just get the technical details straight, other problems would solve themselves.</p>
        <p>Recent public opinion polls show that Americans are still usually enthusiasts for science, but they no longer believe that the most difficult problems concerning science are in the body of science itself; those problems are in the ways in which science interacts with society. In a time</p>
        <p>of discussions of cloning, bioterrorism, global warming, stem cell research, nuclear energy, genetically modified crops and euthanasia, educated citizens have learned that knowledge of the basic science involved is only a necessary, not a sufficient, condition for intelligent decisions. Furthermore, Americans have learned that in such controversies scientists often disagree with one another. While they have not turned against science or scientists, they now recognize that scientists, like all other people, are involved in rivalries and disputes in which reason and tolerance are not as obvious as they were to Piel when he began his magazine. Citizens in the new millennium feel a need for a new kind of science journalism that will neither praise nor condemn science, but instead help them sort their way through these extremely difficult issues. Asking scientists to explain recent developments in their fields, as Piel did so well, is no longer adequate.</p>
        <p>AT the moment this new need is not being well served. One logical source of help would be historians and philosophers of science, as well as the specialists in our universities in programs called ''Science, Technology and Society.'' With few exceptions, however, these scholars are interested only in talking to one another, not in communicating with the larger public. The sociologists of science, in particular, have developed an arcane jargon about the ''sociology of scientific knowledge'' (S.S.K.) that only the most avid veteran of academic disputes is willing to follow. (I should admit that I am a member of the editorial board of one of the main journals in the field, and therefore shoulder some of the blame.) And science journalists, by and large, have not adequately appreciated the new need and do not usually have appropriate backgrounds in science, ethics and politics to pursue these issues in a way that helps citizens develop more informed opinions.</p>
        <p>When Piel and his colleagues created Scientific American over a half-century ago, he correctly saw the need for a magazine that would transcend the specialist science journals and offer overviews for educated lay people of developments in the individual scientific disciplines. He succeeded brilliantly. Let us hope that another such talented journalist of the sciences will emerge in the near future who will respond to the need of the new century and give us similarly informed descriptions and analyses of how science and technology are interacting with the society around us.</p>
        <p>Loren Graham's most recent book is ''What Have We Learned About Science and Technology From the Russian Experience?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Loren Graham's most recent book is ''What Have We Learned About Science and Technology From the Russian Experience?''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
