<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DB1731F936A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>China Is Said to Reduce Carbon Dioxide Emissions  China has greatly slowed emissions of carbon dioxide in the last decade, Chinese and Western energy experts say, pushing back the day that China will presumably pass the United States as the biggest source of the air pollution that scientists believe is warming the planet. The specter of runaway Chinese emissions has been cited by President Bush as a major reason for why the Kyoto climate accord is ''fatally flawed.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>At a European Union meeting, President Bush and European leaders expressed differences and conflicting intentions on global warming.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>China Is Said to Reduce Carbon Dioxide Emissions  China has greatly slowed emissions of carbon dioxide in the last decade, Chinese and Western energy experts say, pushing back the day that China will presumably pass the United States as the biggest source of the air pollution that scientists believe is warming the planet. The specter of runaway Chinese emissions has been cited by President Bush as a major reason for why the Kyoto climate accord is ''fatally flawed.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>At a European Union meeting, President Bush and European leaders expressed differences and conflicting intentions on global warming.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Caution Urged on Missile Plan  Gen. Ronald T. Kadish, the head of the Pentagon's missile defense program, warned Congress that accelerating development of a missile shield would be a mistake without meticulous planning and more money.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Macedonia Seeks NATO Aid  Macedonia formally asked NATO to send troops to help it disarm ethnic Albanian rebels if terms are reached to end the insurgency.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Lawyer Fees in Holocaust Case  Fifty-one lawyers representing Nazi-era slave laborers split more than $52 million in legal fees; the laborers will get $5,000 to $7,500 each.</p>
        <p>A10  Killings Mar Mideast Truce  An Israeli intelligence officer and a Palestinian man were killed in a shootout on a West Bank road. Both sides still seemed prepared to pursue efforts to end months of violence.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Report on Nepal Massacre  An official panel of inquiry into the killings of most of the royal family on June 1 put the blame solely on Crown Prince Dipendra, who also died.</p>
        <p>A3  Rights Advocate Attacked  Barb Bocek, a researcher for Amnesty International, was attacked at a Guatemala hotel during a failed kidnapping attempt, colleagues said.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Deadly Protests in Algiers  The police fired tear gas as hundreds of thousands of protesters marched on the presidential palace demanding greater democracy. Two people died and more than 400 were hurt.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-36</p>
        <p>Both Sides Assail Plan To Phase Out Vieques Use  President Bush's compromise plan to halt the Navy's bombing exercises in Puerto Rico came under intense attack from critics who said it did not go far enough and from Congressional allies of the Pentagon who said it undermined military readiness.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A New Military Strategy  Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld plans to scrap the Clinton administration's guiding strategy for the military and replace it with four principles that include a de-emphasis on humanitarian missions, a senior defense official said.</p>
        <p>A34</p>
        <p>Partisan Fight Over Nominees  Senior Senate Republicans said talks with the new Democratic majority leader on organizing the Senate had stalled over disputes on the handling of judicial nominees. They called for the issues in contention to be put to a full Senate vote.</p>
        <p>A31</p>
        <p>New Interest in Patient Rights  House Republican leaders rushed to write a bill defining patients' rights and said they hoped to push it through the House before the Senate completed work on a rival bill favored by Democrats, who want to impose much more stringent standards for health insurance plans.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Accused Spy Could Get Life  Prosecutors and lawyers for accused spy Robert P. Hanssen are said to be close to a deal that would spare Mr. Hanssen from the death penalty in exchange for a sentence of life in prison and his full cooperation.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Agent Avoids Charges  An Idaho prosecutor said that although a federal appeals court had allowed it, he would not press manslaughter charges brought by his predecessor against an F.B.I. sharpshooter who killed a woman during the Ruby Ridge standoff in 1992.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Arrest in Chicago-Area Killings  The police said a 31-year-old rapist free on parole, Paul Frederick Runge, had murdered and sexually assaulted six women and a girl, including two Bosnian immigrants lured to their deaths by the promise of jobs. With others, he pretended to be interested in property they were selling or renting, officials said.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>$46 Million Lottery Winner Beats the Clock by Mail  Three days after officials declared that no one had claimed a $46 million multistate lottery prize, the winning ticket arrived by mail in Trenton, postmarked two days before the one-year deadline. Officials will disclose the winner's identity today.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Jersey Debate  Bob Franks and Bret D. Schundler, Republican gubernatorial candidates, held their second televised debate.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Sharpton Settles Up  The $65,000 damage award against the Rev. Al Sharpton for defaming a former Dutchess County prosecutor, Steven A. Pagones, in the Tawana Brawley case has been paid in full by supporters of Mr. Sharpton.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>A federal appeals court in Boston upheld the convictions of Mr. Sharpton and three other New York City politicians serving sentences for trespassing during protests on Vieques.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; B31-40</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Senate Approves Overhaul  The Senate passed, 91 to 8, a bill that requires annual testing and penalizes schools that do not improve.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A37</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Research Volunteer Dies  A healthy volunteer recently died after inhaling a drug in a federally financed asthma study by Johns Hopkins University, officials said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Vitamin C Pills May Do Harm  The pills that millions of health-conscious Americans take may actually help produce poisons that can damage DNA, a step toward forming cancer cells, a study suggested.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>$45 Billion G.E. Deal Ailing  General Electric's acquisition of Honeywell International appeared near collapse after G.E. said its final concessions would probably not satisfy European regulators.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Airline and Pilots Have Deal  Striking pilots and Comair, a commuter carrier of Delta Air Lines, reached a tentative agreement on the 81st day of a strike.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Market Research Inquiry  A House subcommittee began hearings on brokerage firm research analysts, with some witnesses saying analysts had simply been caught off guard by the sudden downturn in stocks but with others saying Wall Street research was biased.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Ford Faults Replacement Tires  Ford said some of the Firestone tires it began replacing last month failed even more often than those recalled last fall and that a crucial component of many of the tires was too thin.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Crackdown on Net Fraud  The Federal Trade Commission and the Food and Drug Administration are stepping up enforcement actions against companies marketing fraudulent health products online.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A38-39</p>
        <p>Editorials: Misrepresenting the ABM treaty; Wall Street's conflicted research; aid for dissidents in Cuba.</p>
        <p>Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E28  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>C16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
