<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Powell Seeks to Put Japan First, but U.S. May Find Itself Left Out</title>
    <meta content="24DIPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/24/international/24DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Tokyo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tokyo (Japan)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4DC1E3AF937A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Powell Seeks to Put Japan First, but U.S. May Find Itself Left Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Powell Seeks to Put Japan First, but U.S. May Find Itself Left Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Tuesday, July 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On his trip to Asia, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell insisted that Japan, with which Washington wants to strengthen its ties, would be the first port of call. By going out of his way to put Tokyo at the top of his five-nation list -- if only for seven waking hours -- the secretary wanted to demonstrate Japan's importance to the United States.</p>
        <p>But soon after arriving here Monday night, he discovered that the new government of Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi, by agreeing to a compromise with the Europeans, had played the pivotal role in isolating the United States at a conference of the world's industrialized countries on climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soon after arriving in Japan, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell discovered that Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi had played the pivotal role in isolating the United States at a conference of the world's industrialized countries on climate change</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On his trip to Asia, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell insisted that Japan, with which Washington wants to strengthen its ties, would be the first port of call. By going out of his way to put Tokyo at the top of his five-nation list -- if only for seven waking hours -- the secretary wanted to demonstrate Japan's importance to the United States.</p>
        <p>But soon after arriving here Monday night, he discovered that the new government of Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi, by agreeing to a compromise with the Europeans, had played the pivotal role in isolating the United States at a conference of the world's industrialized countries on climate change.</p>
        <p>In so doing, Japan rescued the Kyoto protocol on climate change from extinction and increased the possibility of eventual ratification of the treaty that President Bush has said his administration will have no part of. Secretary Powell put the best face on the Japanese move, saying that Mr. Koizumi had expressed a preference for finding a way ''to move forward with the United States.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has welcomed the popular Mr. Koizumi as a breath of fresh air in a stagnant political and economic scene here and is placing considerable faith in his ability to pull off an ambitious economic reform program.</p>
        <p>In the longer term, Secretary Powell and Deputy Secretary of State Richard L. Armitage have said that they want to strengthen the military relationship with Japan and, in particular, hope that the Japanese will take on more responsibilities in the region. Mr. Armitage, who is the secretary's closest adviser, argued last year in a widely read paper, which was also co-authored by other senior Bush administration officials, that the special relationship between the United States and Britain should be the model for the Japanese-American alliance.</p>
        <p>But before tackling that, Secretary Powell and Mr. Armitage argue that Japan must improve its economy.</p>
        <p>The omens for the economy were quite mixed as Secretary Powell arrived. The Tokyo stock exchange tumbled to a 16-year low Monday, apparently in alarm over aspects of Mr. Koizumi's proposed economic austerity program. The Prime Minister has said he will force Japanese banks to write off bad loans, estimated at between $300 billion and $1.2 trillion.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell met today with Japanese economic specialists assembled at the American embassy for a roundtable discussion. The idea was for him to learn more about the economic reform agenda. He then met with Mr. Koizumi, who had just returned from the Genoa summit of industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>The State Department worked overtime to try to ensure that Secretary Powell's brief interlude here was not dominated by recent incidents of American soldiers who have been arrested at the Okinawa base.  But in the Japanese press, the arrest of an American soldier on charges of rape and his eventual release to the custody of Japanese authorities has dominated. The Japanese were critical that it took four days for the Pentagon to hand over the soldier for what the Japanese called a heinous crime. The secretary said the United States does ''everything we can to instruct our youngsters as to how to behave as guests in Japan, especially in Okinawa, but there will be these occasional incidents.''</p>
        <p>Overall, the secretary stressed,  the 50,000 American troops in Japan ''are playing an important and valuable role.''</p>
        <p>''I don't think it is possible,'' he said ''for us to remove our presence from Okinawa and I don't think that is the position of the Japanese government.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
