<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6D9153EF933A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-19</p>
        <p>Bush Gets Fatherly Advice On North Korea Policy  Former President George Bush sent the president a memo forcefully arguing the need to re-open negotiations with North Korea, according to people who have seen the document, which appears to have been incorporated into the president's announcement last week that his administration would seek to talk to North Korea.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Iran Re-elects Reform Leader  Preliminary results gave President Mohammed Khatami more than 76 percent of the vote, a majority deemed crucial to reviving his attempts to establish a more representative government and greater social freedom in the Islamic Republic. A huge voter turnout belied predictions that disillusioned Iranians would stay home.</p>
        <p>4</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-19</p>
        <p>Bush Gets Fatherly Advice On North Korea Policy  Former President George Bush sent the president a memo forcefully arguing the need to re-open negotiations with North Korea, according to people who have seen the document, which appears to have been incorporated into the president's announcement last week that his administration would seek to talk to North Korea.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Iran Re-elects Reform Leader  Preliminary results gave President Mohammed Khatami more than 76 percent of the vote, a majority deemed crucial to reviving his attempts to establish a more representative government and greater social freedom in the Islamic Republic. A huge voter turnout belied predictions that disillusioned Iranians would stay home.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Diplomats Urge Execution Limit  Nine highly regarded veterans of the Foreign Service are calling for an end to the death penalty for the mentally retarded, saying that the practice puts the United States at odds with the rest of the world and harms foreign policy interests.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Ulster Vote Puts Pact in Doubt  Britain announced that talks to put the Northern Ireland peace agreement in place would resume this week, but shifts in Parliament after Thursday's elections may make the accord even more fragile.</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>Japan Mourns Slain Students  Families prepared to bury the eight children murdered at their elementary school in Ikeda on Friday, as Japan struggled to come to terms with the killings, which shattered its image as a haven of safety and order.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>20-42</p>
        <p>Group Provides Oasis For Illegal Immigrants  A wary collaboration has begun between Border Patrol officers and a religious group, Humane Borders. The two sides disagree on immigration policy but are working together to help save the lives of people crossing rugged deserts and mountains into the United States.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Higher Profile for Arctic  The debate over oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge has had an unexpected side-effect: a boom in the tourist industry there.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Men Reporting Harassment  More and more men are coming forward to file sexual harassment charges about behavior that employers once dismissed as simply horseplay, according to employment lawyers and government regulators.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Altered Crops More Common  Genetically modified crops are spreading so rapidly that it has become almost impossible for consumers to avoid them, experts say.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Divisions in Los Angeles  The election of James K. Hahn as mayor of Los Angeles has highlighted the divisions among the city's whites, blacks and Hispanics.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Flooding Hits Texas  Thousands of people were forced out of their homes as torrential rains from a tropical storm hit Houston and southeast Texas.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>New Stance on Energy  Some officials in the Bush administration are backing away from its projections of how much coal, oil and gas the United States will burn in coming years and preparing to announce new steps to address global warming.</p>
        <p>32</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>45-53</p>
        <p>Retired Homicide Detective Helps Reverse Convictions  A detective-sergeant sent hundreds of suspects into the criminal courts during one of Brooklyn's bloodiest eras. Today, as a private investigator, he helps reverse the convictions of those imprisoned for murder.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Season for Apologies  Several colleges have declared this spring the season for righting past wrongs. New York University honored former students it suspended 60 years ago as they protested the university's policy of not allowing black athletes to compete in certain sporting events. Brooklyn College bestowed an honorary degree on a civil rights lawyer whom college officials had once called unfit for public office. And the graduating class at Princeton University embraced a judge who said he was admitted to the school in 1936 and then turned away when officials discovered that he was black.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>52</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>54</p>
        <p>Edward Wright  An amateur archaeologist whose youthful curiosity about three oak planks poking out of the English beach where he and his brother searched for dinosaur bones led to the discovery of the oldest seaworthy boats found in northern Europe, he was 82.</p>
        <p>54</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>53  Weather</p>
        <p>55  Sunday Q&amp;A</p>
        <p>42</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
