<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: No-Show Politics; Suppose They Convened, but No One Came</title>
    <meta content="02MARQ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/02/weekinreview/02MARQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1321979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United Nations World Conference Against Racism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marquis, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DF1130F931A3575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: No-Show Politics; Suppose They Convened, but No One Came</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No-Show Politics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER MARQUIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marquis, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration decision to snub racism conference in Durban, South Africa, by sending only midlevel delegation is latest of many instances in which US has shown itself willing to hold itself apart from world gatherings it distrusts; mere threat of US boycott has at times prompted other nations to address Washington's objections, but not always; American unilateralism can sometimes have a price; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO go or not to go?</p>
        <p>The United States decided last week to snub a racism conference in Durban, South Africa, by sending only a midlevel delegation to protest efforts to equate Zionism with racism and promote reparations for slavery. In a world where international meetings often provide a forum for nations to challenge or second-guess America's dominance and interests, it isn't always easy to decide when to stay home and when to plunge in and fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States decision to stay away from a racism conference in South Africa has critics second-guessing the move</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO go or not to go?</p>
        <p>The United States decided last week to snub a racism conference in Durban, South Africa, by sending only a midlevel delegation to protest efforts to equate Zionism with racism and promote reparations for slavery. In a world where international meetings often provide a forum for nations to challenge or second-guess America's dominance and interests, it isn't always easy to decide when to stay home and when to plunge in and fight.</p>
        <p>''They create terrific problems for American policymakers,'' Lee H. Hamilton, director of the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, said of such gatherings. ''The agenda is often taken over by voices we don't agree with.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamilton, the former Democratic chairman of the House International Relations Committee, said he was ambivalent about boycotting the Durban meeting, which began this weekend, though ''in general, my instinct is that the U.S. should go to these conferences and make its case.''</p>
        <p>Gaddis Smith, an emeritus professor of history at Yale, said it was a ''serious mistake'' for the United States to absent itself from conferences where conflict awaits, or to scale back its presence. The Bush administration is demonstrating ''a head-in-the-sand attitude,'' Mr. Smith said. ''We're more likely to be a target of anti-American rhetoric if we're not there. It says the United States has something to hide.''</p>
        <p>Ever since the Senate dashed the hopes of President Woodrow Wilson and voted to reject American membership in the League of Nations, the United States has shown itself willing to shun world gatherings it distrusts.</p>
        <p>At times, the mere threat of an American boycott has prompted other nations to address Washington's objections. In 1980, with tensions boiling over in the Middle East, the Carter administration derailed an Arab effort to expel Israel from the United Nations General Assembly by making clear that it would withdraw and effectively paralyze the organization.</p>
        <p>But sometimes threats are insufficient. In 1984, the Reagan administration withdrew from the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, complaining that it was wasteful, poorly managed and a stage for anti-Western propaganda. The American departure put the agency under economic pressure, and Unesco's board voted the following year to tone down its activism. But the gambit failed to produce rapid reforms. After a 17-year boycott, House lawmakers this spring finally urged the administration to rejoin a much less politicized organization.</p>
        <p>In 1992, American officials stewed for months over whether President George Bush would attend the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. The administration opposed the two main agreements at the environmental conference -- accords to protect biodiversity and curb emissions that contribute to global warming -- but with the United States a major force in both conservation and pollution, Mr. Bush risked being blamed for singlehandedly wrecking the meeting by staying home. He decided to attend and ultimately persuaded the world leaders to water down their treaty on emissions.</p>
        <p>In 1995, First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton led an American delegation to the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women. Many Republican lawmakers had opposed the American participation, and Mrs. Clinton's attendance in particular, because of China's poor human rights record and their belief that the conference would endorse abortion. When Chinese security agents clamped down on demonstrators at the conference, Mrs. Clinton excoriated her Chinese hosts for their failure to tolerate dissenting views.</p>
        <p>Running through the American ambivalence toward such meetings are competing imperatives. With a commercial, political or military presence in virtually every corner of the globe, the United States has a unique stake in international affairs. To protect its interests, it secured a dominant role in the main institutions of the post-World War II era: the United Nations, the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank.</p>
        <p>YET the American impulse has been to dismiss the international order when it is seen as running counter to the national interest or as meddling in domestic affairs. ''We Americans always talk about multilateralism,'' said Kenneth N. Waltz, a political scientist who teaches at Columbia University. ''In fact, we're unilateralists.''</p>
        <p>That perception, which is widespread among American allies as well as critics, has grown in recent months as the Bush administration has rejected the Anti-Ballistic Missile treaty with Russia and the Kyoto accord on global warming. Resentment has also built over the United States' failure to pay arrears to the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration learned this spring what happens when it ignores such rumblings: the United States itself gets boycotted.</p>
        <p>For the first time in its 54-year history, the United Nations Human Rights Commission failed to approve a seat for the United States. The vote, which was seen as a rebuke to the Bush administration's foreign policy, left astonished American officials vowing to press for human rights from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>But that's not the same as being in the game.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
