<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Bad Luck Tipped the Scales to Disaster</title>
    <meta content="28POLA$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/28/science/28POLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1320630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Robert Falcon (1868-1912)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amundsen, Roald (1872-1928)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Susan (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Coldest March, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Scott and Amundsen (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Pole</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Antarctica</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scott, Robert F.</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Amundsen, Roald</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DA1F31F93BA1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="2291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Bad Luck Tipped the Scales to Disaster</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Bad Luck Tipped the Scales to Disaster</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Susan Solomon writes book on Capt Robert F Scott's ill-fated expedition to South Pole in 1912 that challenges prevailing view that he was a bungler and that attributes its failure chiefly to unusually frigid Antarctic weather that year; Roland Huntford, whose 1979 book on Scott and Roald Amundsen largely shaped current disparaging view of Scott, is unmoved by Solomon's findings; her book is The Coldest March; photos; chart; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In March 1912, two months after reaching the South Pole, Capt. Robert F. Scott froze to death in a tent just 11 miles from a depot of food and heating oil.</p>
        <p>His arrival at the pole, with four of his men, had been a bitter disappointment, for they were not the first to make it there. A Norwegian team led by Roald Amundsen had beaten them by a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bitter turn in weather deserves much of the blame in the deaths of the 1912 Antarctic team, an analysis suggests</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In March 1912, two months after reaching the South Pole, Capt. Robert F. Scott froze to death in a tent just 11 miles from a depot of food and heating oil.</p>
        <p>His arrival at the pole, with four of his men, had been a bitter disappointment, for they were not the first to make it there. A Norwegian team led by Roald Amundsen had beaten them by a month.</p>
        <p>Scott set out to return to base camp on Antarctica's coast, but the 900-mile journey proved too harsh for him and the other men, Lt. Henry Bowers, Seaman Edgar Evans, Capt. Lawrence Oates and Dr. Edward Wilson.</p>
        <p>When word of their deaths reached England, Scott was hailed as a hero, an exemplar of English gentlemanly pluck in the face of dire adversity. In recent decades, however, history's view has turned to less flattering second-guessing.</p>
        <p>In a new book, Dr. Susan Solomon, a senior scientist at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Boulder, Colo., revisits Scott's unfortunate expedition, looking for insights that modern climate data can offer on what went wrong and why.</p>
        <p>She concludes that the crucial factor was not bungling by Scott, but an unusually frigid Antarctic autumn.</p>
        <p>From late February through March 19, temperatures for every day except one dipped below minus 30 Fahrenheit -- 10 to 20 degrees colder than Scott had anticipated.</p>
        <p>In 15 years of modern data, from 1985 to 1999, only one year, 1988, exhibited such a persistent March chill. Global warming would not account for the difference. In the past century, since Scott's time in the Antarctic, temperatures have risen by only a degree or two.</p>
        <p>The cold slowed Scott's progress north, to about 6 to 8 miles from 15 miles a day. Then a blizzard trapped the men in a tent.</p>
        <p>''They planned meticulously, and they were undone by an act of nature,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''It would have been a perfectly workable plan in a normal year.''</p>
        <p>Not all agree. The notion that Scott was waylaid by bad luck is ''a lot of codswallop,'' said Roland Huntford, a British historian. ''If one goes into extreme conditions, you have to be prepared for the worst, and therefore if he was taken by surprise, this was really bad planning.'' Mr. Huntford's 1979 book, ''Scott and Amundsen,'' largely shaped the current disparaging views of Scott. (Modern Library reissued Mr. Huntford's book in 1999 under the title ''The Last Place on Earth.'')</p>
        <p>Dr. Solomon published the temperature findings two years ago in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. Her book, ''The Coldest March,'' to be published in October by Yale University Press, provides a wider scrutiny of Scott's decision-making.</p>
        <p>''She was able to use modern science to help understand a historical event that had received much speculative writing over the years,'' said Guy G. Guthridge, manager of Antarctic information for the National Science Foundation. ''Scott did have many high qualities, and I hope this new evaluation will help people reevaluate their thoughts about Scott.''</p>
        <p>Historians have criticized many of Scott's decisions. Did his last-minute decision to take along four men instead of the planned three for the final trek to the pole leave them starved and short of food at the end? Why did Scott and his men act as their own pack animals, pulling a sled loaded with more than 200 pounds of equipment and supplies? Why did they continue to lug 35 pounds of rocks they had collected, even as their strength waned? How could they not have been expecting extreme cold in Antarctica?</p>
        <p>The account of the Scott expedition drew Dr. Solomon's attention when she went to Antarctica in 1986 to lead a team investigating why a hole had opened in the ozone layer above. Her research pinpointed the culprit: chemical reactions triggered by chlorofluorocarbons that had been emitted into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In the middle of the McMurdo research station on the coast is a hut that was erected during Scott's first Antarctic expedition in 1902 and frequently used during the second. ''Anyone who goes to McMurdo sees this remarkably preserved wooden building, and it's right in the middle of all this modern activity,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''I just began to wonder what the story was with the people who built it.''</p>
        <p>At first, she subscribed to the prevalent notion of Scott as a bumbling whiner -- ''Keystone Kops on ice,'' she said. Then she started reading the journals of the men as well as books written by the surviving members. (The other 20 or so men on the expedition who were not part of the South Pole party returned safely.)</p>
        <p>''As I read them,'' she said, ''I began to see many interesting differences between what the men themselves said and what was later said about them.''</p>
        <p>Although Scott, a Royal Navy officer, was not a scientist, he had a problem-solving mind-set like a scientist's, Dr. Solomon said.</p>
        <p>''He was certainly no fool,'' she said. ''He made decisions that at the time seemed very logical and which I don't think we can fault today. And I think what he deserves is a little more understanding of his character, his motives and his actions.''</p>
        <p>In the book, Dr. Solomon argues that Scott made the last-minute addition of Henry Bowers to the polar party not because of whim or sentimental reasons, but as insurance and because he wanted to take advantage of Bowers's strength and skills. Scott admitted in his journal that it had probably been a mistake because it took a half-hour longer to cook for five men instead of four.</p>
        <p>Dr. Solomon said the hunger that Scott and the others experienced was not the result of having an additional member of the party -- they almost reshuffled the rations, she said -- but because the rations themselves were insufficient. The explorers had conducted test treks to determine how much food they would need, but those tests had been at sea level. At the 10,000-foot altitude of the South Pole plateau, the body burns 300 to 500 more calories a day.</p>
        <p>The decision to haul the sled themselves was the result of bad experiences with sled dogs during the earlier 1902 expedition.</p>
        <p>The weight of the rocks probably did not slow them much -- the increased friction because of the ultracold temperatures would have been a much bigger drag. Scott would also have been reluctant to discard the rocks because they contained fossil imprints of plant leaves, one of the first pieces of evidence that Antarctica once lay in much warmer climes.</p>
        <p>Other miscalculations could not have been foreseen. On the voyage to Antarctica in December 1910, Scott's ship took three weeks to push through the ice pack to reach its destination. Amundsen, taking roughly the same route a few weeks later, passed through in five days, leading some to question Scott's sailing acumen.</p>
        <p>Today, satellite images reveal how each year the sea ice around Antarctica, frozen solid in December, breaks apart quickly at the end of the month. ''They had no way of knowing that,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''He tried to be early. As a result, they got stuck.''</p>
        <p>And, Dr. Solomon said, Scott had  ''very good scientific reasons'' for expecting the weather to be warmer during that fateful March of 1912.</p>
        <p>An analysis of temperature measured at the base camp and during earlier forays on the Ross Ice Shelf led George Simpson, the meteorologist on the Scott expedition, to conclude that during winter, temperatures on the ice shelf were 20 to 30 degrees colder than at the base camp. In March, that would have meant temperatures on the ice shelf of roughly minus 10 to minus 20 degrees.</p>
        <p>Dr. Solomon compared Simpson's predictions with data that is now collected by automatic weather stations dotted across Antarctica. ''It was unbelievable how accurate he was,'' she said. ''He nailed what the temperatures should have been like.''</p>
        <p>The forecasts, while they gave Scott a good indication of what to expect, perhaps left him vulnerable to the unexpected. ''In a way, that was his undoing,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''He was a guy who tried to do things efficiently. Usually he was right, but not always.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Solomon and Mr. Huntford agree that Amundsen, with a less complete understanding of Antarctic meteorology, prepared for harsher conditions than Scott.</p>
        <p>But while Dr. Solomon admires Scott for his scientific approach, Mr. Huntford said that even if Simpson had largely been accurate, Scott was foolhardy to rely on forecasts based on limited data rather than a healthy fear of the unknown.</p>
        <p>''It is not a question of understanding meteorology, but having a feeling for weather and being attuned to nature,'' Mr. Huntford said. ''The British were divorced from her.''</p>
        <p>Scott's party arrived at the South Pole on Jan. 17 and headed out two days later. Evans's condition started deteriorating in early February, possibly from malnutrition, effects of the high altitude and injuries from a fall in a crevasse. As the men descended the polar plateau, temperatures rose, and they enjoyed warmer-than-normal, above-zero weather for more than a week. Then Evans's health worsened again, and he died on Feb. 18. At about the same time, the temperatures started falling.</p>
        <p>That the cold dipped below minus 35 is not unusual for March, but a couple of cold days are typically followed by a warmer one, with a low temperature around minus 20. During their last three weeks, Scott and his men had only one such respite.</p>
        <p>Oates's feet became badly frostbitten, and Oates realized that he was slowing the party's progress. On the morning of March 17, he said to the others, ''I am just going outside and may be some time,'' and walked out to his death.</p>
        <p>Besides the debilitating effects of the cold itself, the low temperatures meant that the winds would have been calm. Wind mixes cold, dense air at the surface with warmer air higher up, raising temperatures. The explorers had counted on wind blowing from behind so that they could literally set a sail on the sled carrying their supplies and equipment.</p>
        <p>Also, at temperatures that cold, the texture of snow often turns into gritty sand, and friction no longer melts the snow into a slippery liquid layer beneath skis and sled runners.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of a triple whammy,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''The way home was supposed to be the easy part.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Solomon's analysis of the diaries and meteorological data also offer some new insight on the final days of the remaining three men: Scott, Bowers and Wilson.</p>
        <p>They set up the tent at their final campsite on March 20, stopped by a fierce blizzard. In Scott's last diary entry, dated March 29, he wrote, ''Since the 21st we have had a continuous gale from the W.S.W. and S.W.''</p>
        <p>A 10-day storm would have been extraordinary. Antarctic blizzards are triggered when pockets of cold air roll off the polar plateau and rush across the ice shelf. Because the pockets of cold air can be only so large, ''there's a fundamental limitation to how long a blizzard can last in the Antarctic,'' Dr. Solomon said.</p>
        <p>The weather-monitoring station near Scott's last camp, in operation since 1985, has never observed a blizzard longer than four days. ''That doesn't prove there couldn't be one of 10 days,'' Dr. Solomon said.</p>
        <p>However, another set of observations shows the March 1912 one did not last that long.</p>
        <p>In late March, two other members of the expedition, Dr. Edward Atkinson and Seaman Patrick Keohane, made a trip in the hope of meeting Scott's party. Between March 27 and March 29, directly downwind of where Scott, Bowers and Wilson remained in the tent, Atkinson and Keohane recorded relatively warm temperatures and light winds.</p>
        <p>Good weather there meant the weather must have been good at Scott's tent, too. ''You can think of it as a river,'' Dr. Solomon said. ''That air had to have passed through.''</p>
        <p>If a blizzard did not stop Scott from making a final push to the depot, what did? ''The full answer is a human question beyond the powers of science to answer,'' Dr. Solomon writes in her book.</p>
        <p>She speculates that Scott, who was now suffering from frostbite, could not go farther and that Wilson and Bowers decided not to leave him. Since they were still able to leave the tent, she surmises, they may have told Scott that there was a blizzard so he would not know they had chosen to follow their leader into death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
