<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diesel Engines Get Spotlight in Fuel-Efficiency Contest</title>
    <meta content="Y12DIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/12/business/12DIES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DA133EF931A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diesel Engines Get Spotlight in Fuel-Efficiency Contest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>MILFORD, Mich., June 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diesel engines for sport utility vehicles are getting spotlight in fuel-efficiency Future Truck contest in Milford, Mich; competition is to see which vehicles emit least amount of global-warming gases; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each of the 16 Chevrolet Suburban sport utility vehicles in a barnlike garage at the General Motors vehicle testing center here is painted a different bright color and festooned with the logos of sponsoring corporations. But the Suburbans are here not for a road race but for a different kind of competition: to see which can emit the least amount of global-warming gases.</p>
        <p>Designed by students at the nation's top mechanical engineering schools with cutting-edge equipment supplied by the world's largest auto parts makers, the Suburbans are part of a contest, Future Truck, that has become an annual showcase for what might be done by automakers to address global warming. Because automobiles emit 19.5 pounds of carbon dioxide, a global-warming gas, for each gallon of fuel they burn, the contest has taken on new prominence as Washington has become increasingly interested in global warming and in whether fuel-efficiency rules should be raised.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each of the 16 Chevrolet Suburban sport utility vehicles in a barnlike garage at the General Motors vehicle testing center here is painted a different bright color and festooned with the logos of sponsoring corporations. But the Suburbans are here not for a road race but for a different kind of competition: to see which can emit the least amount of global-warming gases.</p>
        <p>Designed by students at the nation's top mechanical engineering schools with cutting-edge equipment supplied by the world's largest auto parts makers, the Suburbans are part of a contest, Future Truck, that has become an annual showcase for what might be done by automakers to address global warming. Because automobiles emit 19.5 pounds of carbon dioxide, a global-warming gas, for each gallon of fuel they burn, the contest has taken on new prominence as Washington has become increasingly interested in global warming and in whether fuel-efficiency rules should be raised.</p>
        <p>The entries here showed a striking split that is also apparent within the auto industry: whether to switch to diesel engines. Eight of the Suburbans burned diesel, which gives excellent mileage and produces minimal emissions of greenhouse gases but tends to produce more soot and smog-causing gases. The other eight used a variety of fuel sources, including two demonstration models of fuel-cell vehicles that did not work well enough to participate in various tests, like towing a 7,000-pound trailer.</p>
        <p>Two gasoline-electric vehicles already on the market are the Toyota Prius and Honda Insight. G.M., Ford Motor and DaimlerChrysler plan to introduce gasoline-electric hybrid sport utility vehicles within the next three years.</p>
        <p>Diesel engines lack the sex appeal of fuel cells, which combine hydrogen and oxygen in a chemical reaction to produce energy to drive a vehicle's wheels. But diesels are technically feasible now, especially if their pollution problems can be fixed, and provide remarkable fuel economy.</p>
        <p>A diesel vehicle has nearly the same emissions of greenhouse gases as a gasoline-electric hybrid, said Robert Larsen, the director of transportation research at the Energy Department's Argonne National Laboratory. A diesel-electric does even better, with emissions of global warming gases almost as low as those of a fuel-cell vehicle, he added. Making hydrogen for a fuel cell requires some emissions of global-warming gases.</p>
        <p>Preliminary figures showed that the Suburban that emitted the least carbon dioxide and other global-warming gases today was designed at the University of Wisconsin at Madison, Mr. Larsen said. The diesel-powered, four-wheel-drive Suburban got 28 miles to the gallon on the fairly easy course here, which involved driving at speeds no faster than 60 miles an hour and minimal stop-and-start driving. An unmodified Suburban got 17.3 miles a gallon on the same course, several miles a gallon better than most drivers achieve.</p>
        <p>The Suburban from the University of Wisconsin did well partly because it was a hybrid and partly because it used a lot of lightweight aluminum, including an aluminum underbody frame. Mass-producing aluminum frames is extremely difficult, but Audi is already doing it for some cars, and American automakers plan to start trying it in the next few years.</p>
        <p>Julie Marshaus, a graduate student in mechanical engineering who led the University of Wisconsin team, said that choosing diesel had been easy. ''We used a diesel engine because they're more efficient than any other internal combustion engine,'' Ms. Marshaus said.</p>
        <p>But while her team's Suburban emitted less smog-causing nitrogen oxides than any of the other diesel vehicles here, the big vehicle's emissions were still not low enough to meet tough new government regulations that will take effect in the 2004 model year. And her team's Suburban failed miserably on the soot test today, producing emissions of tiny particles that were off the top of the chart for the contest.</p>
        <p>The poor pollution performance of the diesels left it unclear today which engineering school had won the competition. The results of the tests here, which have been taking place for a week, will be announced on Wednesday evening in Washington. G.M. plans to announce separately its own progress on fuel cell vehicles in separate news conferences on Tuesday in Warren, Mich., and on Wednesday morning in Washington.</p>
        <p>G.M. gives a Suburban and $10,000 to each of the nation's top mechanical engineering schools for the contest. The students then raise up to $250,000 more each from other corporate sponsors to design a Suburban that gets the best possible mileage with the least pollution and no reduction in driving performance. The Energy Department is co-sponsor of the competition.</p>
        <p>Automakers are lobbying for less strict pollution standards for diesels, contending that the rules in 2004 will effectively ban diesels. But Mark Mayer, G.M.'s director of North American engine development, acknowledged that recent innovations in pollution-control devices ''will probably get us there, at enormous expense.''</p>
        <p>Europe applies less strict pollution rules to diesels, and sales of diesel cars are soaring there, claiming a third of the market compared with almost none here.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists dislike diesels. Jason Mark, the director of the clean- vehicle program at the Union of Concerned Scientists, said that the real problem was that too many Americans prefer 5,800-pound Suburbans to cars, which get much better mileage with less pollution. Diesel engines are not the answer, he said, adding that ''until they solve their public health liabilities, they shouldn't be in Suburbans and other vehicles.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
