<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clashing Opinions at Meeting on Alaska Drilling</title>
    <meta content="Y10OIL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/10/science/10OIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1261695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Slope (Alaska)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D9103AF933A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clashing Opinions at Meeting on Alaska Drilling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>ANCHORAGE, Jan. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oil companies, conservation groups and Alaska Native communities square off before panel of scientists in Anchorage, presenting clashing visions of impact of expanding oil and gas drilling on North Slope; oil industry claims new techniques will minimize pollution and harm to wildlife; conservationists fear irrevocable damage to one of nation's wildest and most fragile landscapes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oil companies, conservation groups and Alaska Native communities squared off before a panel of scientists here over two days this week, presenting clashing visions of the impact of expanding oil and gas drilling on the country's Arctic frontier, Alaska's North Slope.</p>
        <p>Industry experts said that new technologies for efficiently finding and drilling for oil had sharply reduced pollution and other environmental problems and that their studies showed wildlife was generally not harmed by the work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oil companies, conservation groups and Alaska Native communities squared off before a panel of scientists here over two days this week, presenting clashing visions of the impact of expanding oil and gas drilling on the country's Arctic frontier, Alaska's North Slope.</p>
        <p>Industry experts said that new technologies for efficiently finding and drilling for oil had sharply reduced pollution and other environmental problems and that their studies showed wildlife was generally not harmed by the work.</p>
        <p>But scientists from conservation groups said the expansion of the oil fields would irrevocably mar one of the country's wildest and most fragile landscapes. And leaders for Eskimo communities said that although they benefited from the oil industry, development was leaving deep scars on their culture.</p>
        <p>Both sides agreed, however, that momentum had never been more strongly on the side of the oil companies.</p>
        <p>With the meeting, the panel, convened by the National Research Council at the behest of Congress, began an 18-month study of the effects of the maze of oil fields, pipelines, roads and causeways that has unfurled from Prudhoe Bay, the site of a large oil find 32 years ago, on the environment, landscape and residents.</p>
        <p>The study is likely to influence debate over the proposed expansion of oil drilling into the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, which is east of Prudhoe Bay and is thought to sit atop significant oil reserves.</p>
        <p>The contrasting views presented before the panel frame what is likely to be President-elect George W. Bush's first environmental battle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said in his campaign that a cornerstone of his energy policy would be to open the coastal plain of the refuge to drilling, which was also a goal of his father's administration. The Prudhoe oil fields are dwindling,  and oil companies have been eager to move east into the refuge and west into other federal lands.</p>
        <p>But environmental groups say  they will fight hard to keep oil rigs out of the refuge, which has often been described as an American Serengeti because of its grand vistas and masses of migrating wildlife.</p>
        <p>Oil industry representatives said they were convinced that Republicans in Congress, riding a wave of worries about energy shortages and spurred by an oil-friendly president, would be able to garner sufficient votes to authorize drilling in the reserve.</p>
        <p>''We will prevail,'' said Roger C. Herrera, a consultant on energy and environmental policy for Arctic Power, a lobbying group representing oil companies working in Alaska. ''It's just a matter of time now.''</p>
        <p>The refuge occupies the eastern end of the 500-mile-long North Slope, a rumpled treeless plain that drapes between the jagged Brooks Range and the nation's only Arctic shore.</p>
        <p>The state-owned area west of the refuge is already peppered with oil wells and laced with pipelines, including the Trans-Alaska Pipeline.</p>
        <p>One sign of industry confidence that it will succeed this time is that it was not environmental groups but oil companies -- in particular BP Amoco -- that suggested the impartial study to Alaska's Congressional delegation of three Republicans, who inserted $1.5 million for the project into a bill last year.</p>
        <p>''Republicans asked for this review because we're confident it'll say there's been no environmental damage to the Arctic,'' said Chuck Kleeschulte, a spokesman for Senator Frank H. Murkowski, Republican of Alaska, who is chairman of the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
        <p>Environmental campaigners in Anchorage said they were just as confident that the panel would draw very different conclusions, but added that the panel's nonbinding report, expected in July 2002, might end up being irrelevant if Republicans moved ahead with legislation unlocking the refuge.</p>
        <p>People on both sides of the issue agreed that such a legislative move could come as early as spring, most likely as ''a stealth rider hidden deep in the bowels of a budget bill,'' in the words of Deborah Williams, the executive director of the Alaska Conservation Foundation and a former top aide to the interior secretary,  Bruce Babbitt.</p>
        <p>''The conservation community is going to have to work extra hard to identify when and if that rider is attached and bring it to the attention of the American people,'' Ms. Williams said.</p>
        <p>The issue lay dormant for eight years, but now the conservation groups have lost any security they felt they had.</p>
        <p>''There is no longer the veto firewall you had with the Clinton administration,'' Ms. Williams said.</p>
        <p>Oil industry officials say that conditions, both political and environmental, are very different now than they were in 1991, when President George Bush failed to get his way despite the high oil prices from the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>The image of the 1989 Exxon Valdez spill of Alaskan crude has faded, and in recent years the Alaskan oil industry has largely eliminated road building, waste dumping and other practices that previously damaged the fragile tundra, said Steven D. Taylor, the director of environmental policy for BP Exploration Inc., a division of BP Amoco.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor was one of many experts who gave presentations before the panel, which consists of 16 geologists, ecologists and other experts, most from academia and some with ties to industry and conservation groups.</p>
        <p>He flashed a slide presentation showing how old, polluting ways were ancient history -- with new well fields occupying tiny patches of land instead of sprawling over the spongy peat, and calving caribou munching lichens a few feet from pipelines.</p>
        <p>But other presenters told different stories. Some pointed out that the existing oil operations annually released more than 56,000 tons of nitrogen oxides, a source of acid rain. That is double the nitrogen oxides wafting into the air from traffic and smokestacks in Washington.</p>
        <p>Peter H. Van Tuyn, a lawyer for Trustees for Alaska, a private group that has frequently sued Alaskan polluters, warned the committee to approach the studies it would soon contemplate with ''a large grain of salt.''</p>
        <p>''There are huge data gaps,'' Mr. Van Tuyn said, pointing not only to industry studies but also to those of federal and state agencies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said BP was confident it would be able to make its case that the oil fields of the new century would bear little resemblance to those of the last.</p>
        <p>Displaying a level of candor rarely seen in such meetings, he said: ''This is not good works. It's trying to improve our image so that we can get into other areas.''</p>
        <p>George M. Ahmaogak Sr., the mayor of the North Slope Borough and an Inupiat Eskimo, reminded the committee that some impacts of oil drilling were far more difficult to measure than shifts in the numbers of caribou or pollution cleanups.</p>
        <p>He described how Nuiqsut, a village near the newly built Alpine oil field west of Prudhoe Bay, is essentially surrounded by pipelines.</p>
        <p>''The pipelines can be punctured by a bullet,'' Mr. Ahmaogak said, so shooting is forbidden in the area. ''Now our children can't practice their hunting skills.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
