<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Shifts, So Lobbyists Who Seek to Influence Its Legislation Scramble to Shift, Too</title>
    <meta content="09LOBB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/09/politics/09LOBB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayne, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Senate (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jeffords, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Daschle, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDB143EF93AA35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Shifts, So Lobbyists Who Seek to Influence Its Legislation Scramble to Shift, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wayne, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lobbyists are scrambling to adjust to power shift in Senate from Republicans to Democrats, replacing finely calibrated lobbying strategies geared to Republican sensibilities with tactics intended to win over Democrats; close political ties with Republicans are now less valuable than ties to Democratic senators and their staffs; issues lobbyists promote are also changing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>James Albertine thought he had a winning strategy for selling Republicans on an issue he was lobbying,  getting dry cleaners to use new carbon dioxide solvents to clean clothes. To encourage their use, he advocated tax credits for dry cleaners, a provision that could be tucked into a tax bill to help small businesses, a core Republican constituency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Albertine had to go back to the drawing board when control of the Senate shifted from the Republicans to the Democrats this week. The prospects for a small-business tax bill plummeted to zero, so he has come up with an argument intended to win Democratic votes for these tax credits: emphasizing the environmentally friendly nature of the dry-cleaning solvents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>James Albertine thought he had a winning strategy for selling Republicans on an issue he was lobbying,  getting dry cleaners to use new carbon dioxide solvents to clean clothes. To encourage their use, he advocated tax credits for dry cleaners, a provision that could be tucked into a tax bill to help small businesses, a core Republican constituency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Albertine had to go back to the drawing board when control of the Senate shifted from the Republicans to the Democrats this week. The prospects for a small-business tax bill plummeted to zero, so he has come up with an argument intended to win Democratic votes for these tax credits: emphasizing the environmentally friendly nature of the dry-cleaning solvents.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Albertine had to rethink his political game plan, so have hundreds of other lobbyists like him. The decision by Senator James Jeffords of Vermont to leave the Republican Party not only upended Capitol politics, it also ricocheted through the corridors of influence in the lobbying firms along K Street in Washington.</p>
        <p>Finely calibrated lobbying strategies geared to Republican sensibilities are being replaced with tactics intended to win over Democrats in power. And close political relationships with Republicans are now less valuable than ties to Democratic senators and their staff members.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, this has shot up the value of Democratic lobbyists who now, some say, can command starting salaries $20,000 to $25,000 higher than a few weeks ago or lay claim to larger bonuses from the business they generate.</p>
        <p>In addition, the issues lobbyists promote will change. All committee chairmanships in the Senate will switch to Democrats -- and these chairmen wield enormous power over what legislation reaches the Senate floor and what bills do not.</p>
        <p>Once-dormant measures, like environmental regulations and a patients' bill of rights, have been resuscitated, while those that had a chance under Republicans, like tort reform, are being written off as dead.</p>
        <p>''Democratic lobbyists' stock has gone up 100 percent,'' said Mr. Albertine, who is president of the American League of Lobbyists, a trade group. ''It would be naïve to say that Democratic lobbyists haven't overnight increased their influence. Everyone is trying to put the best face on it. But one party has control where they didn't before, and truth and justice in the Senate is 50 votes plus one.''</p>
        <p>Of course, with Republicans controlling 49 votes in the Senate, many large lobbying firms have both Democrats and Republican on staff, to be well-positioned to argue their case on both sides of the aisle.</p>
        <p>Moreover, many lobbyists are part of Washington's permanent class: they stay while the politicians come and go. These lobbyists have close relationships with many senators -- regardless of the political affiliation of either the lobbyist or the senator -- that can weather the inevitable shifts in the political landscape.</p>
        <p>Still, the suddenness with which the Democrats gained control for the first time in six years caught Washington lobbyists off guard. They say they are having to turn on a dime, dropping some issues, taking on new ones, learning to deal with a different set of power brokers, all while fielding questions from nervous corporate clients.</p>
        <p>''It feels like you are living on the West Coast, except that here the earthquakes are political,'' said Missi Tessier, a Republican lobbyist with Podesta/Mattoon, a bipartisan firm that changed its name earlier this year from Podesta.com when Dan Mattoon, a Republican lobbyist, joined the firm. Now, the firm is promoting Democratic partner Anthony Podesta.</p>
        <p>Lobbying firms of every partisan stripe are scrambling to make sure they have the right line-up of employees with ties to the new Democratic inner circle.</p>
        <p>The lobbyist closest to the source of power is Linda Hall Daschle of the firm of Baker, Donelson, Bearman &amp; Caldwell. Her husband is Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the new majority leader.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Daschle says that her close ties do her no good in business, because she has made it clear that she does not lobby her husband or his Senate colleagues.</p>
        <p>Some exclusively Republican firms may play down the shift's impact, but they are clearly in a less enviable position than earlier this year.</p>
        <p>''This change puts bipartisan firms back in vogue,'' said one prominent Republican lobbyist, who asked not to be named. ''It gives Democratic firms a new lease on life and there are a lot of Republican firms probably scrambling to find some Democrats to hire.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence F. O'Brien III, a principal in the bipartisan lobbying firm of O'Brien Calio, added: ''In firms like ours, which have both Democrats and Republicans, the lobbying dynamic will change. The Democrats might start to step forward a bit more aggressively to defend the point of view of our clients, and Republicans will have to recalibrate their approach. They will be dealing with their brethren in the Senate from a position of being a minority. And it remains to be seen what attitude the Republican leadership will send out.''</p>
        <p>The shift is more than a numbers game. As the Senate legislative agenda changes, it means that some lobbying options have been closed, while new opportunities are being created.</p>
        <p>For instance, Kenneth E. Feltman, a Republican lobbyist, will use Senator Daschle's pledge to bring up a patients' bill of rights -- a measure that had been considered dead under Republican control -- to promote another project: letting users of flexible health spending accounts roll over unused money in their accounts from one year to the next.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying that the Republicans wouldn't have given us favorable consideration on this measure,'' said Mr. Feltman, who is executive director of the Employers Council on Flexible Compensation, a trade group. ''I just don't know if they would have gotten to the bill.''</p>
        <p>For the business lobby, which had been anticipating another round of tax cuts next year from the Bush administration, tax relief may be harder to achieve than before.</p>
        <p>And in financial services, lobbyists are bracing for big changes as the banking committee chairmanship switches from Senator Phil Gramm of Texas, who had a laissez-faire attitude toward banking regulation, to Senator Paul Sarbanes of Maryland, who has an activist approach.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest impact is on lobbyists for the telecommunications industry, who had been planning to do battle over a bill to make it easier for regional Bells to enter the long-distance market. Now, at a commerce committee headed by Senator Ernest F. Hollings, Democrat of South Carolina, who opposes the bill, it is considered a non-starter.</p>
        <p>The need for lobbyists with close ties to Democrats is good news for Clinton administration officials who have not yet landed new jobs and Democratic congressional aides who lobbying firms are now courting.</p>
        <p>''People are very interested in what the Democrats are thinking, what will be first on the agenda and what the committee structures will look like,'' Rita Lewis, a partner in The Washington Group and a former aide to Senator Daschle, said.</p>
        <p>Democrats leaving the Hill for K Street can now name their price. ''It's like in baseball,'' said Mr. Feltman, ''when one gets a big contract, another one does, too. Suddenly they are perceived to be closer to the sources of power.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
