<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 New Studies Tie Rise in Ocean Heat to Greenhouse Gases</title>
    <meta content="Y13CLI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/13/science/13CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Diego</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Silver Spring</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Columbia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Scripps Institution</org>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Levitus's group</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6D61531F930A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 New Studies Tie Rise in Ocean Heat to Greenhouse Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Separate research teams, using two different computer simulations, conclude that buildup of heat in seas over last five decades is almost certainly caused by heat-trapping effect of greenhouse gases released into air by human activity; work is described in two papers in journal Science; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using two different computer simulations of climate and the oceans, separate research teams have concluded that a buildup of heat in the seas over the last five decades was almost certainly caused by the heat-trapping effect of greenhouse gases released into the air by human activities.</p>
        <p>The findings provide new evidence that people, mainly through the burning of fossil fuels, have caused at least a substantial portion of a global warming measured since the 1950's,  several independent experts on climate models said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using two different computer simulations of climate and the oceans, separate research teams have concluded that a buildup of heat in the seas over the last five decades was almost certainly caused by the heat-trapping effect of greenhouse gases released into the air by human activities.</p>
        <p>The findings provide new evidence that people, mainly through the burning of fossil fuels, have caused at least a substantial portion of a global warming measured since the 1950's,  several independent experts on climate models said.</p>
        <p>The work is described in two papers in today's issue of the journal Science. The raw data on the oceans' rising heat were published last year, but the two new studies were the first to offer an explanation for what influence, natural or otherwise, accounted for them.</p>
        <p>The computer models used in the research were among the world's most advanced efforts to recreate the behavior of earth's climate system and so study how changes in the atmosphere might change weather patterns. Even so, they are relatively rough sketches of the real world.</p>
        <p>In fact, some climate experts said the papers' conclusions were overstated, a result, they said, of the computer models' lacking sufficient detail to deal with small but potentially important changes in ocean conditions.</p>
        <p>But an author of one study, Dr. Tim P. Barnett, said the findings  were strong enough to overcome his long skepticism about the models' ability to pinpoint a human influence amid all the naturally chaotic ups and downs of climate.</p>
        <p>Dr. Barnett, a marine physicist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography, in San Diego, said in an interview that he was now convinced that people were contributing to global warming.</p>
        <p>''I was maybe 60-40 before, but I'm at least 90-10 now,'' he said. ''The chances that our model could have done this by itself are virtually nil.''</p>
        <p>He added that the ability of the two computer simulations to reproduce the warming actually measured in the oceans in recent decades indicated that these models were valid tools for projecting how the continuing emission of greenhouse gases might spur further climate changes in coming decades.</p>
        <p>This is important because the models, and others like them, are the basis for many of the forecasts being used by experts to recommend how forcefully societies must move to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>At least one aspect of the new studies bears directly on that question. Dr. Barnett and other scientists said the analyses supported the idea that by absorbing most of the heat trapped by greenhouse gases in the air above, the oceans could act as a strong buffer against abrupt climate warming.</p>
        <p>''The immediate impact may not be as great, because the oceans may slow things down a little,'' he said. But eventually that heat will be released from the ocean's surface back into the air, he and others said.</p>
        <p>The other modeling study was led by Dr. Sydney Levitus, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's ocean climate laboratory, in Silver Spring, Md. It was Dr. Levitus who collated the millions of accumulated temperature measurements, taken around the world's oceans, that detected the heat rise.</p>
        <p>Other scientists said the new analyses showed the importance of Dr. Levitus's decade-long effort.</p>
        <p>''In putting together this global data set, he's like a national treasure,'' said one expert on computer climate models, Dr. Andrew Weaver, a professor of atmospheric science at the University of Victoria, in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>Dr. Weaver said previous efforts to identify human interference with the climate system had focused on changes in air temperature, which varies enormously day to day, year to year, in ways that hide clues.</p>
        <p>The oceans, in sharp contrast, are a vast long-term repository for heat absorbed from the air, and so exhibit little confounding variability, he said.</p>
        <p>''This is a much more convincing approach,'' he said. ''It's not only consistent with the land-based detection schemes, but it doesn't suffer from the problems of being clouded by the noise that critics always focus on.''</p>
        <p>Even so, some scientists said they were concerned that such similar results could emerge from models that deal very differently with forces affecting climate. For example, the model used by Dr. Levitus's group included the sun-blocking effect of volcanic emissions that have punctuated recent decades, while the model used by Dr. Barnett did not.</p>
        <p>Others had different criticisms. Chris N. Hill, a designer of ocean computer models at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said, ''The models being used, although state of the art, still represent the ocean as a viscous oil-like fluid, rather than the turbulent and highly variable real ocean.''</p>
        <p>But members of both modeling teams said their results were so robust, and the match to the rise in greenhouse gases was so clear, that more detail was unlikely to make a difference.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
