<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1311659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFD6103AF930A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-9</p>
        <p>Bush and Putin Discuss New Defense Talks Stance  On the last day of a meeting of the leaders of the world's richest nations, President Bush and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia agreed to link discussions of American plans to deploy a missile defense system with the prospect of large cuts in both nuclear arsenals, hinting that if an accord was reached quickly it might take the place of the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The national leaders and the leaders of groups that sought to protest peacefully at the summit meeting began reflecting on how to carry out their goals without repeating the violence that marked the meeting in Genoa. The national leaders sought a remote location for their next meeting, while the groups that came to march pondered how to deal with violent protesters.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-9</p>
        <p>Bush and Putin Discuss New Defense Talks Stance  On the last day of a meeting of the leaders of the world's richest nations, President Bush and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia agreed to link discussions of American plans to deploy a missile defense system with the prospect of large cuts in both nuclear arsenals, hinting that if an accord was reached quickly it might take the place of the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The national leaders and the leaders of groups that sought to protest peacefully at the summit meeting began reflecting on how to carry out their goals without repeating the violence that marked the meeting in Genoa. The national leaders sought a remote location for their next meeting, while the groups that came to march pondered how to deal with violent protesters.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Indonesia Moves to Oust Leader  Indonesia's legislature began proceedings aimed at removing President Abdurrahman Wahid from office and ending the short, tempestuous rule of the country's first democratically elected leader in a generation. It planned to install Vice President Megawati Sukarnoputri as his successor.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rebels Enter Macedonia Town  Ethnic Albanian rebels have taken advantage of a NATO-brokered cease-fire in Macedonia to move into Tetovo and a few surrounding villages in an area of western Macedonia that is mainly populated by Albanians, right under the noses of government forces.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Norway to Export Blubber  Norwegian whalers are preparing to export hundreds of tons of edible minke whale blubber to Japan in the face of widespread condemnation by nations that oppose whaling. Such exports would represent the first international trade in whale products in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Climate Treaty Marathon  For the second time in eight months, the fate of the Kyoto Protocol, the first treaty to require cuts in gases linked to global warming, came down to a marathon all-night session as countries sought to ensure that the agreement to protect the atmosphere did not harm their economies or other interests. The United States remained immersed in the talks, but was on orders from the White House not to interfere with other countries' efforts to reach a consensus, even though President Bush rejected the treaty as ''fatally flawed.''</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Stem Cell Research Debate  As President Bush and Congress struggle with the question of regulating embryonic stem cell research, one fact is being overlooked: nearly two dozen states have laws that govern research on embryos and fetuses, and at least nine ban any experimenting with human embryos.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Crossing  Plans to turn clay pits in Golden, Colo., into a golf course have prompted a dispute about measures to preserve dinosaur footprints.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-15</p>
        <p>Choice to Head Joint Chiefs Seen As Signal on Military  Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld has the opportunity in coming days to put an indelible personal stamp on the American military when he gives President Bush his recommendation for the next chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. The selection of the nation's chief military adviser to the president is anticipated as a statement of how Mr. Rumsfeld expects to carry out Mr. Bush's defense priorities.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Ethanol Gains Ground  Supporters of the fuel made from corn are gaining in their push to make it a major part of the nation's energy policy despite persistent doubts about its economic and environmental benefits. The Senate's new Democratic leaders and the Bush administration are promoting a growing number of measures to bolster ethanol demand.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cleanup in Baltimore  Crews worked to pull the last smoldering boxcars from a downtown tunnel, days after a train derailment and fire shut down parts of the city and disrupted Internet service nationwide.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Shuttle on Its Way Home  Atlantis and its crew left the International Space Station and headed for home, their mission accomplished despite what one astronaut called ''bumps in the road.'' The shuttle is due back at Kennedy Space Center early tomorrow.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Bar Report on Campaign Funds  States should provide public financing for campaigns for judgeships to limit the growing role of money in judicial politics, a study by the American Bar Association is to recommend this morning.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Raising Capital, and Criticism  Haley Barbour, the Washington lobbyist and former chairman of the Republican National Committee, contends that the campaign finance system does not need to be overhauled -- and it is not hard to see why. Already, with the White House in Republican hands, he has become the capital's most successful lobbyist and party fund-raiser. Some advocates of revamping political donations are critical of his influence and his dual roles.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Pitfalls for Performing Arts  The foremost presenters of the performing arts in Middle America, medium-size arts institutions, are likely to face financial strains and even sudden death, a study of 30-year trends in the performing arts has found. The RAND Corporation study concludes that in order to survive many of these groups will have to become more community oriented and adjust their budgets, programs and styles to build audiences.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Modern Concerns Threaten Those Old Swimming Holes  Coalitions of swimmers, land conservation groups and local officials are trying to save an endangered joy of summer, community swimming holes. In High Falls, 90 miles north of New York, and elsewhere around the nation, these popular spots are quietly fading away as an influx of affluent newcomers assert themselves as country landowners. They are fencing off the swimming holes, literally or figuratively, because they expect privacy at their bucolic hideaways and, in these increasingly litigious times, they fear being sued.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Town Returns From the Dead  The rebirth of the stately American Hotel is the most visible symbol of the comeback of Sharon Springs, N.Y., a legendary but depopulated Brigadoon of gingerbready, abandoned Victorian resort hotels. Rooms are being rented at the American for the first time in five decades. Sharon Springs ''has literally come back from the dead,'' said State Senator James L. Seward, who represents the historic mineral-spring village and remembers when not a living soul stirred on Main Street.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Candidate Criticizes Giuliani  The Republican mayoral candidate Michael R. Bloomberg, after weeks of offering little but praise for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, criticized Mr. Giuliani as being wrong in 1995 when he ousted Yasir Arafat from a concert for world leaders.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>City School Plan  Chancellor Harold O. Levy has ordered the New York City public school system's 32 district superintendents to meet with his deputies at least four times a year to analyze reams of data about their students, schools and teachers, and to outline strategies for improvement. The data, and the superintendents' responses to it, will factor heavily into their annual evaluations, which Mr. Levy began conducting last year.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Joan Bove  A New Yorker who helped make hair-coloring respectable by introducing stylists to a product called Clairol that she and her husband discovered in Paris, she was 99.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Aveline Kushi  An advocate of a macrobiotic diet who taught cooking and helped found one of the first natural food stores in America, she was 78.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-9</p>
        <p>Duval Wins British Open  David Duval captured his first major with a final round that started with four players tied for the lead, and ended as a defining performance for his career.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Cable Deal Is Seen  Walt Disney is close to buying Fox Family Worldwide from the News Corporation and its partner for $3.2 billion, people close to the deal said. The agreement, which is expected to be announced as early as today, would add to Disney's cable operations a network with 81 million subscribers in the United States, 24 million in Europe and 10 million in Latin America.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Opposition to Hacker's Arrest  The arrest of a Russian programmer accused of violating an American digital copyright law has stirred opposition, both against the law itself and Adobe Systems, the software company that initiated the case.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Stock Scandal in India  India's anticorruption police arrested the former head of the country's largest mutual fund and three of its officials on charges of defrauding the fund of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Cell-Phone Chips For Sale  Motorola plans to announce today that it will sell its most advanced cell-phone microchip sets, software and production tools to anyone who wants to buy them, including major rivals of its own handset unit.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Architect Hired as Adviser  Condé Nast has hired the Dutch architect Rem Koolhaas as an adviser to its magazines.</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Bush's Genoa diplomacy; rethinking Mexican immigration; unhealthy cuts for Head Start.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E5  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D10</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
