<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Sees Bush's Trip Exceeding Expectations</title>
    <meta content="Y18EUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/18/world/18EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">European Union</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E4DE1331F93BA25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Sees Bush's Trip Exceeding Expectations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many experts and newspapers across Europe call Pres Bush's five-country excursion success, at least compared with what they had expected; his brand of good cheer, first names and small jokes charmed hosts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the dust settled on President Bush's first official visit to Europe, many experts and newspapers on the Continent called his five-country excursion a success, at least compared with what they had expected.</p>
        <p>''He proved he was not quite the Texas dolt that everyone thought he was,'' said Josef Joffe, a German foreign policy analyst. ''And he used moderate language. In international relations, that is very important.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the dust settled on President Bush's first official visit to Europe, many experts and newspapers on the Continent called his five-country excursion a success, at least compared with what they had expected.</p>
        <p>''He proved he was not quite the Texas dolt that everyone thought he was,'' said Josef Joffe, a German foreign policy analyst. ''And he used moderate language. In international relations, that is very important.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, expectations were so low that some believed that Mr. Bush could not fail to impress. And the trip had no particular goals beyond getting acquainted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush had been derided on this side of the Atlantic with nicknames like the Toxic Texan and Bully Bush for the go-it-alone ''cowboy'' manner in which he decided that the United States would not ratify the Kyoto agreement on global warming and for his willingness to toss out arms control agreements in pursuit of building a missile shield. Those are things that European leaders, including President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, have opposed.</p>
        <p>By the end of his visit, neither Mr. Bush nor the Europeans moved an inch from their starting points, but the American president gave his Europeans allies at least some of what they wanted: he came offering handshakes, back-slapping, some gentler wording and the promise of future discussion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's brand of good cheer, first names and small jokes -- for instance, he called Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain ''Mr. Landslide'' -- charmed his hosts from Spain to Slovenia. During a long dinner with European Union leaders in Sweden, he apparently deftly handled a barrage of questions on global warming and defense issues.</p>
        <p>''Really,'' a Scandinavian official said, ''he left a very positive impression of knowing some facts.''</p>
        <p>Still, the European press did not miss any of the president's gaffes. Mr. Bush mangled the last name of Prime Minister José María Aznar of Spain. He made mistakes when he tried to speak Spanish. He kissed Queen Sofia of Spain on the cheek when protocol called for a handshake. In Sweden, he called Africa a nation.</p>
        <p>But headlines across Europe suggested a softening of tone. ''No More Mr. Unilateralist,'' said The Financial Times of Britain. The left-wing French daily Libération wrote, ''George W. Bush is manifestly not the 'superficial buffoon and arrogant Texan' portrayed in the media.''</p>
        <p>Editorial writers who 10 days ago were condemning him for a failure to consult suggested that he was proving more flexible than advertised.</p>
        <p>The leftist La Repubblica of Rome noted that Bush had responded to a question by saying, ''Unilateralists don't sit around tables listening to the views of others.''</p>
        <p>The editorial went on: ''He did sit at the table. With passion he asked for the Europeans' help in convincing Putin. With humility he asked for their trust, guaranteeing that he would consult at every step.''</p>
        <p>Charles Grant of the London-based Center for European Reform said: ''The personal stuff is quite important. Europe's big worry was that he was not interested and ignorant. Just the fact that he spent a week here goes a long way.''</p>
        <p>Experts point out that most new American presidents have been regarded at first with skepticism and derision in Europe.</p>
        <p>''It's a process,'' Mr. Joffe said. ''They called Carter a peanut farmer, when in fact he was an engineer. They called Reagan an actor in B-movies, when in fact he had run the state of California with a huge economy quite successfully. Europeans have to work out their clichés about Bush, and that has started to happen now.''</p>
        <p>For many here, it was actually Mr. Bush's last stop -- his meeting with Mr. Putin -- that was deemed the most important, and there again many were relieved to see a friendly encounter between the two men, even if their views seemed intractably apart.</p>
        <p>Europeans have been much more reluctant than the United States to contemplate moves that might rattle Mr. Putin, like the proposed defense missile shield and the enlargement of NATO to include the Baltic States.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Bush and Mr. Putin made clear that they did not agree on those two issues, the tone of the meeting was cordial enough to allay European fears, at least for now. That was something Mr. Bush needed.</p>
        <p>''Bush and Putin; first good friends'' said the headline in the French weekly ''Le Journal du Dimanche.'' In Russia, too, television reporters cast the meeting as a success, emphasizing how the two men had agreed to visit each other soon.</p>
        <p>None of this is to say that Mr. Bush's intractability on the issues went unnoticed.</p>
        <p>His refusal to budge on the Kyoto Protocol on global warming prompted headlines in Germany like, ''Bush disappoints Europeans' hopes: underlines his ''no'' to Kyoto agreement.''</p>
        <p>One cartoon in the liberal Süddeutsche Zeitung showed Mr. Bush with a big grin and a smoking six-shooter. The headline over the nearby article was ''The Boss -- charming but tough.''</p>
        <p>Some newspapers said Mr. Bush's reiteration of his stand on the Kyoto Protocol was a contributing factor in prompting the riots that plagued the European Union summit meeting in Goteborg, Sweden.</p>
        <p>And some experts considered his speech in Poland on the future of Europe to contain some of the ''usual'' American misconceptions. In the speech, Mr. Bush called for the enlargement of NATO and the European Union almost as if they were the same entity. Moreover, some said, urging quick European Union enlargement failed to understand the complexity of the issues involved.</p>
        <p>''A lot of times, Americans talk about it like you just sign a bit of paper and you're in,'' Mr. Grant said. ''It is a little bit more complicated than that. There are 80,000 pages of documents to go over. You are half way to joining a state. That's why it takes years to negotiate these things.''</p>
        <p>But European leaders seemed eager to like Mr. Bush, and one measure of their newfound comfort may be that as soon as he left, he was hardly mentioned again for the remainder of the summit meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
