<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Family Takes the Helm; Effort to Overcome Rift At Troubled Company</title>
    <meta content="31FORD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/31/business/31FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nasser, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Henry (1863-1947)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DD1230F932A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="2458" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Family Takes the Helm; Effort to Overcome Rift At Troubled Company</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ford Family Takes the Helm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr, great-grandson of Henry Ford, assumes control of Ford Motor Co as sole chief executive, ending awkward power sharing arrangement with ousted Jacques Nasser; says there is need for change in company's top ranks, which has been struggling to devise turnaround plan, especially since September 11 terrorist attacks has worsened already bleak outlook for automobile industry; has solid support of extended Ford family, which holds 6 percent of stock and just 3 of 14 seats on board of directors, but voting rights that gives it effective control of company; company's problems include loss of market share, two consecutive quarterly losses, frayed relations with dealers, lowered credit rating and dwindling of cash reserves; graphs; charts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Fords, one of the most prominent and enduring families in American business, reasserted control today of the Ford Motor Company for the first time in more than two decades.</p>
        <p>But William Clay Ford Jr. -- the family member who took over as the company's sole chief executive, ending an awkward power sharing arrangement with the ousted Jacques A. Nasser -- assumes leadership of a company mired in deep trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Fords, one of the most prominent and enduring families in American business, reasserted control of the Ford Motor Company for the first time in more than two decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Fords, one of the most prominent and enduring families in American business, reasserted control today of the Ford Motor Company for the first time in more than two decades.</p>
        <p>But William Clay Ford Jr. -- the family member who took over as the company's sole chief executive, ending an awkward power sharing arrangement with the ousted Jacques A. Nasser -- assumes leadership of a company mired in deep trouble.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said yesterday that the events of Sept. 11 had worsened an already bleak outlook for the auto industry and accelerated the need for change at the top of Ford, which has been struggling to devise a turnaround plan.</p>
        <p>''This isn't a time for grand visions and for a lot of barnstorming tours of the world talking about how we're going to revolutionize the world,'' he said at Ford's headquarters here. ''What we need to do now is fix our core business, put a plan together that is credible and, underlying all of that, fix the quality and introduce cars that are exciting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford, 44, has a lot going for him. He is regarded as affable and open -- qualities rarely associated with Mr. Nasser, who resigned after meeting with Mr. Ford on Monday afternoon. He has a winning sense of humor, too. As hundreds of workers cheered him today, Mr. Ford began a speech by cracking, ''You'd think the Detroit Lions had won a game or something'' -- a reference to the family's football team, the only squad without a victory in the National Football League.</p>
        <p>He has friends in odd places for an auto executive. A Sierra Club official today called Mr. Ford -- who has pledged the company to improve the fuel economy of its sport utility vehicles by 25 percent, prompting General Motors and Chrysler to make similar commitments -- ''an enlightened executive.''</p>
        <p>And he has the solid support of his family, which holds only 6 percent of Ford's stock and just 3 of 14 seats on the board but has voting rights that give it effective control of the company. Family members, who regularly meet three times a year, gathered for a particularly gloomy discussion of the company's prospects three weeks ago. The company had just cut its dividend, at great cost to the Fords, and the yearlong tug-of-war for power between Mr. Ford and Mr. Nasser was on everyone's mind, Mr. Ford said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''We talked about all of the issues facing the company,'' he said. ''They wanted my input into how I saw things. It was probably clear then that if things didn't get better, this was going to happen.''</p>
        <p>What is less clear is if Mr. Ford has the skills to succeed as a chief executive at an increasingly difficult time. Ford is locked in a price war with G.M. and Chrysler and is losing market share. Its two consecutive quarterly losses are the first such six-month period in a decade. Its relationships with dealers, suppliers and employees are frayed. Its credit rating has been lowered, its cash reserves are dwindling and the industry expects overall sales to fall sharply in 2002. It stock closed yesterday at $16.05, down 16 cents.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Ford -- who first came to work at Ford when he was 22 years old -- said he would surround himself with seasoned executives and make it his business to smooth ruffled feathers. Among other squabbles, he said he would consider ending the company's bitter feud with Bridgestone, the tire manufacturer whose American Firestone unit was founded by his maternal great-grandfather.</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts said today that Mr. Ford was unproved, but generally agreed that having a Ford at the company's helm would improve morale.</p>
        <p>More important, they said, was that Mr. Ford has chosen credible top executives to serve under him. Nicholas V. Scheele, brought back from Ford of Europe this summer to run the company's automotive operations in North America, was named president and chief operating officer. Carl E. Reichardt, a longtime board member, was named vice chairman. Mr. Reichardt, who served for more than a decade as the chief executive of Wells Fargo &amp; Company, will oversee Ford's financial operations at a time when they are struggling.</p>
        <p>''I'm not dictatorial at all,'' Mr. Ford said. ''I look to Nick and Carl both as sort of an easygoing partnership where we just sit around and figure things out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford never was able to achieve that kind of partnership with Mr. Nasser. They vowed to work as a team in 1999, when Mr. Ford was named nonexecutive chairman and Mr. Nasser was named chief executive. But Mr. Ford complained increasingly that he was outside the flow of important information, and he was clearly uncomfortable with Mr. Nasser's more autocratic management style.</p>
        <p>As the company's financial problems mounted -- along with the cost in dollars and reputation from the deaths and injuries in Ford Explorers equipped with Firestone tires -- the two men renegotiated their relationship. In July, Mr. Ford created an office of chairman and chief executive in a move to share power, and there was speculation that Mr. Nasser's days were numbered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser's demise is the latest in a long history of Ford family dust-ups with management. The original Henry Ford, the company's brilliant but spiteful founder, clashed frequently with his managers, though perhaps none so bitterly as his own son, Edsel B. Ford, who served for years as the company's president but died before, and never escaped the shadow of, his father.</p>
        <p>Edsel's son, Henry Ford II, became the second Ford to dominate the company, presiding over it for three decades. He was known for his refusal to delegate much authority and for shuffling top executives. When he brought a top G.M. executive, Semon Knudsen, to the company as president in 1968, Mr. Knudsen lasted 19 months. When he fired another president, Lee A. Iacocca, Mr. Ford said simply: ''Well, sometimes you just don't like somebody.''</p>
        <p>The new chief executive, who prefers to be called Bill, came to the company in 1979, at 22, the same year that his, uncle Henry Ford II, stepped down, and now becomes the third Ford to preside over the company that bears his name. He is considered the only family member of his generation to possess the qualifications of a top executive. He has worked in manufacturing, sales, product development and finance. He left in 1983 to study finance at M.I.T., and has run the company's finance committee for five years.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ford has not been a chief executive, and in an interview today said he had mixed feelings about running the company.</p>
        <p>''I came close to leaving several times, as I got frustrated with the company and the pace of change and some of the positions we'd taken,'' he said. ''In the end, I really love this company, and it's my children's future and my grandchildren's future. So here I am.''</p>
        <p>Most analysts said it was time that the company moved past Mr. Nasser's stormy tenure and faced up to the problems at hand.</p>
        <p>''Whether rightly or wrongly, Jacques Nasser had become a lighting rod for many of Ford's problems, and moving past his tenure will help this new team attack the new problems,'' said Jim Benson, an auto analyst and fund manager for the Oakmark Funds, which invest in Ford.</p>
        <p>Stephen J. Girsky, an analyst at Morgan Stanley, said, ''I think Nasser wanted to do too much too quickly, and the organization wasn't ready too accept it.''</p>
        <p>He added that Ford's organization -- Mr. Nasser never named a chief operating officer -- itself was not up to the task. ''The job is bigger than one person,'' Mr. Girsky said. He noted that the structure Ford announced today was similar to that recently put in place at G.M.</p>
        <p>Until now, arguably, Mr. Ford's biggest impact on the car business has been a push for the industry to accept responsibility for its impact on the environment.</p>
        <p>''He recognizes that we have to solve the problem of global warming,'' said Daniel Becker, director of global warming issues for the Sierra Club, who praised Mr. Ford's elevation to chief executive.</p>
        <p>''People always like to put you down as something, either a numbers guy, a car guy or a tree hugger,'' Mr. Ford said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''If you look at where society is going, those distinctions are becoming blurred between being a businessman, an environmentalist and an industrialist,'' he added.</p>
        <p>He said his primary focus as chief executive would be turning the company around and using his name to create opportunities, rather than bearing it as a burden.</p>
        <p>''For years, probably all the way back to Henry Ford the first, there has always been kind of a cult of personality that has swirled around the Ford Motor Company,'' he said. ''This company is bigger than any individual, and it has proven that time and time again. We're a strong family with a strong ethic and a strong culture. It transcends any individual, including me.''</p>
        <p>Still, some things are personal. Mr. Ford said it might be time to end hostilities with Firestone. Ford Motor and Bridgestone/Firestone have feuded bitterly over responsibility for hundreds of deaths in Explorers equipped with Firestone tires. The fight has pitted the companies against each other in Congressional hearings and courtrooms, has led Ford to spend $3 billion replacing Firestone tires and resulted, earlier this year, in the severing of a business relationship that last nearly a century.</p>
        <p>''My mother is a Firestone,'' Mr. Ford said, adding that when the controversy over the tires first became public in August 2000, he was scheduled to be the keynote speaker at a Firestone family reunion.</p>
        <p>''I called my mother up and said, 'Mom, I can't go.' '' he said ''And she said, 'Do you think I shouldn't go?,' And I said 'No, no, you should go. People aren't going to expect you to know about Explorer details.' So she went, and my wife and children went.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said that Mr. Nasser's handling of the Firestone dispute did not play a role in his departure. But he indicated he might take a different approach.</p>
        <p>''We're caught up in so many legal issues and everything else that I don't know where we go from here,'' he said. ''But I would like to have a constructive relationship with Firestone, with Bridgestone, the parent company. Whether that's possible, I'd certainly be open to it.</p>
        <p>''In the broader sense, leaving Firestone aside, we need to reach out to all of our constituents -- suppliers, dealers, government and obviously the biggest of all, our employees, and really start to rebuild relationships that may have been frayed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
