<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making the Most of Free Compost</title>
    <meta content="17WCUTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1302234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFD71E3EF934A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making the Most of Free Compost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT looked like a gathering of the nations two Sundays ago, on the parking lot of Medgar Evers College in Crown Heights, Brooklyn. Only these delegates weren't talking global warming, but shoveling deep, dark compost as fast as they could.</p>
        <p>Every New York City resident who got there in time (this black gold went fast) was allowed 30 gallons -- enough to fill a large trash can -- from the Department of Sanitation, which had delivered 90 cubic yards that morning for the Brooklyn Botanic Garden's Urban Composting Project.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT looked like a gathering of the nations two Sundays ago, on the parking lot of Medgar Evers College in Crown Heights, Brooklyn. Only these delegates weren't talking global warming, but shoveling deep, dark compost as fast as they could.</p>
        <p>Every New York City resident who got there in time (this black gold went fast) was allowed 30 gallons -- enough to fill a large trash can -- from the Department of Sanitation, which had delivered 90 cubic yards that morning for the Brooklyn Botanic Garden's Urban Composting Project.</p>
        <p>''My friend told me my rhododendrons are dying because my soil is so compacted,'' said a woman in an orange linen suit, having rushed over from services at the Bethany Baptist Church. ''They can't live because I don't put anything in the soil.'' She seemed on a mission, as she gingerly shoveled away, trying not to mess up her pretty dress and pumps.</p>
        <p>A Bangladeshi boy who now lives in Woodside, Queens, Novel Ahmed, 12, was working alongside his mother, Zulhas Bagum, and his older sister Rumena Kabir. ''We have a backyard of vegetables, fruit, flowers, tomatoes, cucumbers, beans, green chilies and jute leaves,'' Ms. Kabir said. ''We were going to buy compost from Home Depot when we saw a notice about this on TV.''</p>
        <p>While Novel scraped the blacktop for the last crumbs of compost, Ms. Kabir bought a rigid black plastic  composter for $20 -- a big discount from the $70 store price -- and the family headed home to treat their garden to this feast of nutrients teeming with micro-organisms ready to work on tired soil.</p>
        <p>Eilaine Li from Coney Island and Brent Li from Bay Ridge were helping their clan fill 15 rice bags with the crumbly compost that was headed for their mother's house. ''She needs it for her flowers and vegetables,'' said Mr. Li, as his relatives hefted the heavy bags into their van.</p>
        <p>Some arrived too late, so fast had the garden locusts descended on the pile, and Bernadette Dorvil was literally in tears. 'I came so far to get here,'' said Ms. Dorvil, who lives in Canarsie. ''I'm shocked. I never saw the compost. Just the bare floor!'' She looked so sad that Suzanne Curley, a gardener from Park Slope, handed her one of her own bags. And Daxius Gregory, a composting instructor from the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, offered another.</p>
        <p>''You think if I shed a tear, this gentleman would help me?'' asked Rose Butler, who grows blueberries and figs on her fire escape in Bedford-Stuyvesant. She had hoped to load her blue Ford pickup with her allotment of 30 gallons and head down to Williamston, N.C., where she grows a field of corn, collards, tomatoes and squash.</p>
        <p>Such is the passion compost inspires, and for good reason. If you don't have a compost pile on the edge of your garden, or an indoor worm box tucked in a corner of the kitchen or basement, you are missing out on nature's own fertilizer.</p>
        <p>Entire books have been written on the art of composting and its benefits, from the complex ''Rodale Book of Composting,'' edited by Deborah Martin and Grace Gershuny (St. Martin's Press, 1992) to a paperback called ''Worms Eat My Garbage,'' by Mary Appelhof, who explains how redworms do the job (Flower Press, 1997). A good one to start with is ''Easy Compost: The Secret to Great Soil and Spectacular Plants,'' edited by Beth Hanson, one of the many excellent handbooks from the Brooklyn Botanic Garden's 21st Century Gardening Series.</p>
        <p>Composting can create the kind of topsoil it takes nature about a century to create without human help, and depending on how compulsive you are, you can turn your leaves, clippings and vegetable matter from the kitchen (no meat or grease, though, as these attract rodents) into sweet-smelling nutrients in six weeks to a year. A fast ''hot'' pile has equal amounts of carbon-rich material (brown leaves, pine needles, twigs, eggshells, shredded newspaper) and nitrogen-rich material (green leaves, vegetable and fruit peelings, coffee grounds or spent flowers).</p>
        <p>If you turn these elements regularly, to aerate the pile, and keep it moist but not wet, an army of earthworms, sowbugs, centipedes, mites, beetles, molds, fungus and bacteria will transform this ''waste'' -- which otherwise gets trucked at great cost to a landfill -- into humus, a complex stew of biochemical compounds that can bring moisture, air and nutrients to worn-out soil. It can also protect roots and plants from pathogens. (An excellent Web site, www.soilfoodweb.com by Dr. Elaine Ingham, a soil scientist based at Oregon State University, as well as the resource lists in back of books like those mentioned above can get interested gardeners started down the fascinating road of composting. Gardens can really thrive with the stuff, and why pay for it when it's sitting right there in your kitchen and backyard?</p>
        <p>Most botanical gardens and county agricultural extension services provide information and maybe even workshops on composting, and some municipalities offer free compost.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
