<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surveys Find European Public Critical of Bush Policies</title>
    <meta content="Y16POL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/16/international/europe/16POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1317608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DB143EF935A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surveys Find European Public Critical of Bush Policies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Surveys Find European Public Critical of Bush Policies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New survey of four European countries finds many Europeans disapprove of Pres Bush's foreign policy and see his decision-making process as unilateralist; surveys of public in Britain, France, Germany and Italy find at last 73 percent of those polled say Bush makes decisions 'entirely on US interests' without considering European interests; surveys find vastly more Europeans liked former Pres Clinton's foreign policy than like Bush's; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ordinary Europeans strongly back their political leaders' unhappiness with American foreign policy on specific issues like the Kyoto environmental treaty and the Bush administration's threat to withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty, polls in France, Germany, Great Britain and Italy show.</p>
        <p>Indeed, on those two issues, European leaders command more public support for their criticism than Mr. Bush does in the United States for the policies themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ordinary Europeans strongly back their political leaders' unhappiness with American foreign policy on specific issues like global warming and missile defence, polls show</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ordinary Europeans strongly back their political leaders' unhappiness with American foreign policy on specific issues like the Kyoto environmental treaty and the Bush administration's threat to withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty, polls in France, Germany, Great Britain and Italy show.</p>
        <p>Indeed, on those two issues, European leaders command more public support for their criticism than Mr. Bush does in the United States for the policies themselves.</p>
        <p>The surveys, conducted early this month for The International Herald Tribune, the Pew Research Center and the Council on Foreign Relations, found that at least 73 percent of the public in the four European countries said that President Bush makes decisions ''entirely on U.S. interests'' without considering European interests. That 73 percent response came from Germany. Among Italians 74 percent felt that way, as did 79 percent of Britons and 85 percent of the French.</p>
        <p>The telephone surveys of about 1,000 people in each country found that vastly more Europeans liked former President Bill Clinton's foreign policy than liked Mr. Bush's. In Italy, for example, 29 percent endorsed current policies, while 71 percent remembered Mr. Clinton's approach approvingly.</p>
        <p>Only in Germany did a slight majority express confidence that Mr. Bush would do the right thing in world affairs -- 51 percent compared with 46 percent who disagreed. Fifty-nine percent of Italians, 64 percent of Britons and 75 percent of French respondents said they did not have confidence in him.</p>
        <p>For each country the margin of sampling error was plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>Samuel P. Wells, head of West European studies for the Woodrow Wilson Center, said he was surprised by the depth of the Europeans' feelings. ''The strength of opinion holds up across borders and across age groups,'' he said. If the president ''wants Allied support for anything,'' he added, ''he's got his work cut out for him.'' Mr. Wells blamed the administration's approach for the strength of European antipathy, saying it amounted to: ''We will listen to you, but we may not hear you.''</p>
        <p>In Hamburg, Josef Joffe, chief editor of the German newspaper Die Zeit, said that while these opinions were ''not cast in concrete or in granite,'' they reflected ''an underlying reality which is hard to deny'' -- that President Bush is a unilateralist. He added that the president was very different from his father, who ''was very careful in keeping his international ducks lined up. There was a guy who knew that he represented Mr. Big, but who also understood that Mr. Big needed allies for legitimacy.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Joffe said the data also reflected a ''kind of trans-Atlantic Kulturkampf,'' or cultural struggle. He said Europe sees itself as kind of morally and socially superior: ''Socially, because we care about social justice and an egalitarian distribution of income. Morally, because we don't have the death penalty.''</p>
        <p>''This may well be psychological compensation for this sense of growing weaker strategically and economically,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The poll found overwhelming opposition to American policy on two crucial issues.</p>
        <p>On American rejection of the Kyoto treaty on curbing greenhouse gases, only 12 percent of Italians approved, as did 10 percent in the other three countries. Americans themselves oppose Mr. Bush's rejection of the treaty, a separate poll showed, by 44 percent, with 29 percent supporting his decision.</p>
        <p>On the question of the United States developing a missile defense system ''even if it means withdrawing from the A.B.M. Treaty,'' 24 percent of Italians approved, while 65 percent did not. Among Britons, 20 percent approved and 66 did not, while 14 percent of the French approved and 75 percent disapproved. In Germany, 10 percent approved and 83 percent did not.</p>
        <p>In a Pew poll taken in June, Americans were about evenly split, with 39 percent for and 43 percent against.</p>
        <p>The polls did find widespread European approval for the administration's decision last month to keep troops in Bosnia and Kosovo. And solid majorities in each country backed Mr. Bush over his support for free trade.</p>
        <p>But except for Britain, where the public was about evenly split, at least two-thirds of the public disapproved of Mr. Bush's support for the death penalty in the United States. Those percentages were 67 percent in France, 68 percent in Germany and 73 percent in Italy.</p>
        <p>In Britain, which has banned capital punishment, there is considerable support for reinstating it, a move backed by two-thirds of the public in a 1995 poll. In the United States, according to a poll taken in May by CBS News, 66 percent of the public supports the death penalty, while 24 percent opposes it.</p>
        <p>While there was great variation from country to country in confidence that Mr. Bush would ''do the right thing regarding world affairs,'' in every country he enjoyed more public confidence than Russian President Vladimir V. Putin did, the margin was never large. In Germany, 41 percent had confidence in Mr. Putin, compared to 51 percent for Mr. Bush. In Britain, 26 percent had confidence in Mr. Putin, compared to 30 percent for Mr. Bush. In Italy, 23 percent had confidence for the Russian president, and 33 percent in the American. In France, 14 percent had confidence in Mr. Putin and 20 percent in Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The polls suggested that the European unhappiness was more with Mr. Bush than with the United States. Asked whether American and European interests had grown closer or farther apart in recent years, only in Britain did a plurality say they had grown apart, a view held by 24 percent compared with 13 percent who said they had grown closer. The French were about evenly divided, while Germans and Italians were considerably more likely to think European and American interests were converging.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
