<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hard Questions on Nuclear Power</title>
    <meta content="29TUE1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/29/opinion/29TUE1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1297278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">White House (Washington, DC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iran</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Yucca Mountain (Nevada)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Nevada (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Island</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Impact</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D7153CF93AA15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hard Questions on Nuclear Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says there are good reasons to take fresh look at nuclear power, which has been 'much maligned' source of energy, but says Bush administration has seemingly endorsed its resurgence with little sustained analysis of pluses and minuses; says administration must adddress some critical questions pertaining to impact nuclear power on global warming, weapons risks, waste disposal, reactor safety and economics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After decades in the doghouse because of environmental, safety and cost concerns, nuclear power is enjoying a renaissance of expectations. The Bush administration's new energy plan gives a place of prominence to nuclear power as a clean and efficient energy source, and the industry itself is bubbling with new hopes and plans. In truth, there are good reasons to take a fresh look at this much-maligned source of energy that has been stalled in this country for the past three decades. But it is worrisome that the administration seems to have endorsed a nuclear resurgence with little sustained analysis of its pluses and minuses.</p>
        <p>As an article by Katharine Seelye in The Times revealed last week, nuclear energy was barely in the consciousness of the drill-centric energy team at the White House until a delegation of nuclear industry executives sought a chance to make their pitch and succeeded so well that Vice President Dick Cheney almost immediately started touting the virtues of nuclear energy. A case can be made for greater exploitation of nuclear power in this country, but before the nation plunges too far down this path the administration will need to address some critical questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After decades in the doghouse because of environmental, safety and cost concerns, nuclear power is enjoying a renaissance of expectations. The Bush administration's new energy plan gives a place of prominence to nuclear power as a clean and efficient energy source, and the industry itself is bubbling with new hopes and plans. In truth, there are good reasons to take a fresh look at this much-maligned source of energy that has been stalled in this country for the past three decades. But it is worrisome that the administration seems to have endorsed a nuclear resurgence with little sustained analysis of its pluses and minuses.</p>
        <p>As an article by Katharine Seelye in The Times revealed last week, nuclear energy was barely in the consciousness of the drill-centric energy team at the White House until a delegation of nuclear industry executives sought a chance to make their pitch and succeeded so well that Vice President Dick Cheney almost immediately started touting the virtues of nuclear energy. A case can be made for greater exploitation of nuclear power in this country, but before the nation plunges too far down this path the administration will need to address some critical questions.</p>
        <p>The rationale for a reassessment comes partly from the performance of the industry itself, and partly from changed circumstances in the environment in which it must operate. By most accounts, the industry has learned to operate its plants more safely and efficiently than in the years leading up to the traumatic near-tragedy at Three Mile Island. American nuclear plants are operating with much greater reliability and many fewer minor incidents. Moreover, the industry is consolidating, with plants being purchased and operated by companies that have more expertise than some of the previous operators. So there is reason to trust the industry a bit more than in past decades.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, external events are increasing the appeal of nuclear power. One is the rising concern over global warming, which is caused primarily by the emission of carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. Nuclear power plants emit no carbon dioxide, thus to the extent they can replace plants burning coal, oil or natural gas they can be considered a plus. Nuclear power can also contribute to the diversity of the nation's energy supplies. Nuclear plants already supply some 20 percent of the electricity generated in this country, compared with fossil fuel contributions of 52 percent for coal, 16 percent for natural gas and 3 percent for oil. But the great majority of all new power plants are being built to burn natural gas, the cleanest of the fossil fuels, making utilities and consumers vulnerable to price spikes when supplies become tight as they have this year.</p>
        <p>President Bush's energy plan offers a wide range of steps to accelerate the use of nuclear power. But before Congress and the regulatory agencies proceed too far, some crucial questions require answers.</p>
        <p>Impact on global warming: If this is the main reason for turning to nuclear power, the proponents will need to do a much better job of spelling out just how far nuclear power would have to spread to make a real dent in the problem. Nuclear power is used almost exclusively to generate electricity, thus it cannot reduce the nation's reliance on imported oil to power transportation systems. Nuclear fuel will primarily be substituting for natural gas -- the least of the carbon dioxide emitters -- as the clean fuel to which electric utilities turn. Moreover, fossil fuels are burned in mining and preparing nuclear fuels and in building reactors, so even nuclear energy is not entirely free of greenhouse gases. Some analyses suggest that to make a real impact in slowing global warming, nuclear power plants would need to spread widely around the world, a prospect that brings new challenges of its own.</p>
        <p>Weapons risks: Expansion of nuclear power in this country poses no weapons danger, but the spread of nuclear plants into other countries could pose a risk. The uranium fuel for nuclear power plants is not generally considered of high enough grade to be used in weapons. But as more and more technicians around the world learn the skills of working with nuclear materials, and as governments become engaged in procuring nuclear technologies, there is a danger that civilian nuclear programs could serve as a cover for clandestine weapons activities. That is why, for example, the United States is angry that  Russia is helping Iran build a nuclear power plant. Even though Iran has pledged to abide by nonproliferation treaties and allow international inspections of the plant, there is grave concern that it will find a way to build weapons. Increasing the use of nuclear power in countries that already have either the bomb or nuclear power plants is not much of a danger. Spreading nuclear power to additional countries might be.</p>
        <p>Waste disposal: In the political world, the lack of a proven method to store spent fuel from nuclear reactors for the tens of thousands of years the material remains radioactive has long been considered the Achilles' heel of the nuclear industry. In truth, spent fuel has been stored safely for decades in pools at the sites of nuclear power plants with no adverse effect. The problem is, the storage pools are filling up and critics are loath to expand nuclear power with no clear idea where to store the waste. The Bush administration is considering a site at Yucca Mountain in Nevada that has been studied for years, and it has proposed a new look at reprocessing the fuel to remove the long-lived plutonium for reuse as reactor fuel. That could greatly ease the storage problem here but might encourage wider use of reprocessed materials abroad, increasing the risk of weapons-grade plutonium's falling into the wrong hands.</p>
        <p>Reactor safety: The safety problem in conventional nuclear plants is that, if things start to go wrong, emergency cooling systems and human operators have to act correctly to prevent a catastrophic meltdown. That makes nuclear power a cruel and unforgiving technology that cannot tolerate equipment failures or human mistakes. But the industry is exploring new technologies that would not lead to meltdown even in a worst-case malfunction, making them inherently safer and cheaper to build and operate. This is where the administration and the industry should be focusing their efforts -- to develop demonstrably safer power plants. That would ease many of the concerns provoked by the current generation of nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>Economics: No matter what else is done to make nuclear power more attractive, the industry will make little headway unless it can overcome the high capital costs that brought it to a halt in recent decades. Some relief should come from the advance approval of standardized designs, allowing plants to be built more quickly and cheaply than in past years when each plant had a customized design. But Congress will need to take a close look at whether it should renew one of the industry's economic underpinnings -- the so-called Price-Anderson Act that limits the liability of nuclear companies in the event of an accident. If the industry is as safe as it says, it may not need such subsidized protection. On the other hand, eliminating the liability protection might scare off investors for good.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power has been stalled for so long in the United States that it is surprising to see it back in the spotlight. There may be a case for extending the licenses of existing plants, as has already happened in several cases, or for building new plants on existing nuclear sites where the risks are already understood. But the case has not yet been made for truly large-scale expansion of nuclear power, in this country or around the globe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
