<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Changeable as the Weather</title>
    <meta content="Y04JAP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/04/world/04JAPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koizumi, Junichiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Tokyo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kyoto Protocol</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Tokyo (Japan)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DD1F39F937A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Changeable as the Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of Japanese Prime Min Junichiro Koizumi's shifting and contradictory positions on global warming as he travels from country to country on his first official overseas trip; says his decision-making process seems to be subordinating strictly environmental considerations to single issue on which he has staked his political fortunes: economic reform (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anyone interested in clearly understanding Japan's position on the Kyoto Protocol on global warming would search in vain through Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi's statements over the last several days, during his first official overseas trip.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koizumi's extraordinary popularity at home was built in part from his straight-shooter style -- which differs significantly from that of recent predecessors, who were more often given to endless hedging. But from Washington to London to Paris, sometimes on the same day and within the same city, his position on what is probably the most ambitious international environmental agreement seemed to shift by the hour or the audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anyone interested in clearly understanding Japan's position on the Kyoto Protocol on global warming would search in vain through Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi's statements over the last several days, during his first official overseas trip.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koizumi's extraordinary popularity at home was built in part from his straight-shooter style -- which differs significantly from that of recent predecessors, who were more often given to endless hedging. But from Washington to London to Paris, sometimes on the same day and within the same city, his position on what is probably the most ambitious international environmental agreement seemed to shift by the hour or the audience.</p>
        <p>Whether deliberate or accidental, Mr. Koizumi's ambiguity appears to stem from a variety of causes.</p>
        <p>To begin with, this is his first experience on the world stage.</p>
        <p>Moreover the protocol -- whose name comes from Japan's ancient capital, where its terms were hammered out nearly four years ago after a decade of arduous talks -- represents a rare opportunity for Japan to take the pivotal position on an issue of major international importance. But because Japan has had little experience wielding such influence, it finds itself stuck between firmly formed and opposing schools of thought: those of the European Union and the United States.</p>
        <p>Japan's self-image as a world power has become increasingly tied to environmental issues, which are loosely linked in the minds of the public with the country's postwar vocation as a kinder, gentler power, constitutionally at peace and devoted to assisting the development of poorer nations.</p>
        <p>With important parliamentary elections scheduled for July 29, many opposition candidates, and even some members of the governing Liberal Democratic Party, have turned support for the Kyoto Protocol and other environmental issues into campaign themes. Many newspaper editorials have also supported ratification of the protocol.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Japan is as firmly attached to the United States -- economically, diplomatically and in security terms -- as perhaps any country. Going against its ally on a major issue like carbon emissions does not come naturally for Tokyo.</p>
        <p>As a new, stirringly reformist prime minister, Mr. Koizumi has yet another important consideration: the need for support from Washington for his sweeping but risky economic restructuring. Mr. Bush gave Mr. Koizumi's plans a strong endorsement, which could prove useful for warding off critics at home.</p>
        <p>Those strong crosswinds have brought an extraordinary sequence of shifts and nuance and near contradictions from the Japanese leader about the agreement, which establishes a timetable for strictly limiting the carbon emissions of industrial nations.</p>
        <p>After the talks last weekend between Mr. Koizumi and President Bush at Camp David, Md., the Bush administration, which has rejected the protocol as ''fatally flawed,'' all but claimed that it was indeed dead.</p>
        <p>In support of that view, administration officials cited Mr. Koizumi's supposed pledge not to ratify the protocol without Washington -- a decision that would leave the accord short of the minimum number of countries needed for it to take effect.</p>
        <p>''When Japanese politicians go to the United States, they are just engulfed by the American atmosphere, and when they go to places like Camp David they forget their original positions and are often overwhelmed by the agenda of the American side'' said Kaoru Okano, a political scientist and former leader of Meiji University. ''When we saw Koizumi playing baseball with Mr. Bush, we knew he was totally immersed in the American environment.''</p>
        <p>But while still in Washington, Mr. Koizumi spoke of respecting the ''spirit'' of the protocol. And by the time he reached London, where support for the protocol is strong (as it is throughout Europe), Mr. Koizumi's language had become more affirmative still. Speaking to reporters there on Monday, he said he would ''continue to talk to the Americans so that the Kyoto Protocol becomes an effective document.''</p>
        <p>Even that, however, was not the final word. Mr. Koizumi appeared to take another step backward on Monday, contradicting his own government's chief spokesman, when he denied that he had discussed possible revisions to the protocol with Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain that might make it acceptable to the United States.</p>
        <p>The distance Mr. Koizumi has traveled in his various statements is all the greater when one considers that just last month, speaking before Parliament, he described Mr. Bush's opposition to the protocol as deplorable. During a photo session in Washington on Saturday, though, Mr. Koizumi praised Mr. Bush as someone who is ''enthusiastic about environmental issues.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps reflecting that confusion, officials at Japan's environmental agency did not return telephone calls today seeking an explanation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koizumi may be trying to avoid making a firm decision now, which will disappoint many at home and abroad. But for now his decision-making process seems to be subordinating strictly environmental considerations to the one issue upon which the prime minister has staked his political fortunes: economic reform.</p>
        <p>''Koizumi's priority has been economic and structural reform,'' said Yuuri Onodera, an official with Friends of the Earth Japan. ''The environment remains a relatively low priority in his blueprint. This is the first global environmental issue he has tackled, and he has not decided what approach to take.</p>
        <p>''But the most important reason for his present position is that he needs the Bush administration's wholehearted support for his economic reforms.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
