<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Dept. to Raise Efficiency of Air-Conditioners and Heat Pumps</title>
    <meta content="Y19CONS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/19/politics/19CONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Heaters</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Heaters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFD8163CF93AA25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Dept. to Raise Efficiency of Air-Conditioners and Heat Pumps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Dept issues rule that will increase efficiency of new residential central air-conditioners and heat pumps by 30 percent, with eye to potential electric crises after rule takes effect in 2006, and beyond; rule was required by 1987 law but then blocked by Congress in mid-90's and delayed further by dispute in air-conditioner industry; it is being issued at almost last possible moment of Clinton administration (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department issued a rule today that will increase the efficiency of new residential central air-conditioners and heat pumps by 30 percent, with an eye to potential electric crises after the rule takes effect in 2006, and beyond.</p>
        <p>The rule has a tortured history, having been required by a 1987 law but then blocked by Congress in the mid-90's, and delayed further by a dispute in the air-conditioner industry. It has been bottled up in the White House for weeks, and was issued at almost the last possible moment of the Clinton administration. Bill Richardson, the energy secretary, said that the reduction in energy bills and in pollution from power plants expected as a result would be ''one of the biggest environmental achievements of the Clinton administration.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department issued a rule today that will increase the efficiency of new residential central air-conditioners and heat pumps by 30 percent, with an eye to potential electric crises after the rule takes effect in 2006, and beyond.</p>
        <p>The rule has a tortured history, having been required by a 1987 law but then blocked by Congress in the mid-90's, and delayed further by a dispute in the air-conditioner industry. It has been bottled up in the White House for weeks, and was issued at almost the last possible moment of the Clinton administration. Bill Richardson, the energy secretary, said that the reduction in energy bills and in pollution from power plants expected as a result would be ''one of the biggest environmental achievements of the Clinton administration.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the cliffhanger nature of the rule, Dan W. Reicher, the departing assistant secretary of energy for efficiency and renewable energy, said, ''We pressed very hard to conclude this standard at the end of the administration, because of the enormous energy savings it promises, and because of the risk that it might linger in the next administration.''</p>
        <p>President Clinton said in a statement that the new standards would ''serve as a foundation upon which our nation can continue to meet the profound challenge of climate change.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the rules were finally issued in part because of pleas from California, New York and Texas. It is part of a late flurry of rules, joining new standards on the efficiency of water heaters, published in the Federal Register on Wednesday, and clothes washers and commercial heating and cooling equipment, published on Jan. 12. The rules on water heaters, clothes washers and commercial equipment were issued by the Energy Department after manufacturers and consumer groups reached agreement on what they should say; the air-conditioner rule was published over the objections of some manufacturers, who said they would try to get Congress to overturn it.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department has ''burdened the American consumer with a multibillion-dollar regulatory rip-off,'' said Clifford H. Rees Jr., the president of the Air-Conditioning and Refrigeration Institute, a trade group, in a statement. His group favored an efficiency increase of 20 percent rather than 30 percent.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department and the manufacturers disagree over how many extra dollars the more-efficient machines will cost to produce. While experts differ on that estimate, a more crucial and difficult question is the future cost of electricity. Much of that is made from natural gas, which has quadrupled in price in the last year, but its price in 2010 or 2020 is uncertain now.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department says the four new rules together will make building 91 400-megawatt plants by 2030 unnecessary. Under the same 1987 law, the Energy Department has issued three other rules since 1997, on home refrigerators, room air-conditioners and fluorescent lamp ballasts, which together will eliminate the need for 124 such power plants, the Energy Department predicted.</p>
        <p>None of this offers immediate help for California, or the Northeast, where consumption approached the limits of generation last summer and will probably do so again in 2001. But all of it will have a gradual salutary effect in coming years, experts say.</p>
        <p>''Not just in California, but in all regions of country, if you work to meet growing demand, you have a choice between building power plants and controlling demand through better energy efficiency,'' said Andrew DeLaski, executive director of the Appliance Standards Awareness Project, a Boston-based nonprofit group. ''What this means is that for each year for California, beginning in 2006, there's 200 megawatts of supply they won't have to come up with.''</p>
        <p>About 5 percent of central air-conditioners sold now for home use already meet the new standard, which is a Seasonal Energy Efficiency Rating of 13, usually referred to in sales literature as SEER.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
