<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Members of Congress Begin Effort to Get U.S. to Join in Fighting Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="Y27ENV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/27/politics/27ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1312572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeffords, James M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DB153DF934A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Members of Congress Begin Effort to Get U.S. to Join in Fighting Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lawmakers Begin Effort to Get U.S. to Fight Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several lawmakers press Congress to take lead toward reducing emissions of greenhouses gases, now that Bush administration has refused to join in global agreements; EPA Admr Christie Whitman defends go-slow approach at hearing, saying it is premature to present plans for cutting carbon dioxide absent further study; Sen James Jeffords makes debut as chairman of Committee on Environment and Public Works; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the United States now alone in the world in opposing the treaty to combat global warming, some lawmakers are pressing for Congress to take the lead toward reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases, the issue on which the Bush administration has so far kept to the sidelines.</p>
        <p>Both Democratic and Republican Congressional aides say it is now likely that Congress will pass one or more measures this year calling for cuts in emissions of carbon dioxide, a main provision of the Kyoto global-warming treaty. But it is less clear whether majorities would back the mandatory restrictions spelled out in the treaty and rejected by the administration, or whether they would favor a voluntary approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some lawmakers are pressing for Congress to take the lead toward reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the United States now alone in the world in opposing the treaty to combat global warming, some lawmakers are pressing for Congress to take the lead toward reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases, the issue on which the Bush administration has so far kept to the sidelines.</p>
        <p>Both Democratic and Republican Congressional aides say it is now likely that Congress will pass one or more measures this year calling for cuts in emissions of carbon dioxide, a main provision of the Kyoto global-warming treaty. But it is less clear whether majorities would back the mandatory restrictions spelled out in the treaty and rejected by the administration, or whether they would favor a voluntary approach.</p>
        <p>Still, when Christie Whitman, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, arrived on Capitol Hill this morning, she heard calls for Congress to make up for the administration's inaction this week in Bonn, where the United States opted out of an agreement on the Kyoto treaty that was backed by more than 180 countries.</p>
        <p>''The administration can refuse to commit the United States to the Kyoto accord; that is their choice,'' Senator James M. Jeffords of Vermont told Mrs. Whitman at a hearing on power plant emissions that was his debut as chairman of the Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works, a job he won in May by shifting his party affiliation to independent from Republican.</p>
        <p>''But this Congress, this Senate, and especially this committee will not let our international partners down,'' Mr. Jeffords said. ''We plan to take steps to reduce our nation's contribution to this growing problem by working with industry to reduce carbon emissions.''</p>
        <p>The White House has criticized the Kyoto treaty as ''fatally flawed,'' saying its provisions are unfair to the United States. This morning, Mrs. Whitman defended the administration's go-slow approach in offering any alternative to the treaty, saying it would be premature to present any plan for carbon dioxide reductions until further studies are completed.</p>
        <p>''We're still a long way from knowing how to solve the problem,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Emissions of carbon dioxide are widely regarded as the main contributor to global warming, and the United States is the world's largest source of that gas, about one-third of which comes from old coal-burning power plants.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration's refusal to adopt mandatory limits on carbon dioxide has put it at odds not only with Europe and Japan, but also with senators like Mr. Jeffords, who has introduced a bill requiring power plants to reduce carbon dioxide emissions. The bill is also sponsored by 2 Republican senators from Maine, Susan Collins and Olympia J. Snowe, and 12 Democrats.</p>
        <p>Other measures to reduce carbon dioxide emissions are also floating around Congress, including some, like one that Senator Chuck Hagel, Republican of Nebraska, is expected to introduce next week, that would stop short of mandatory restrictions in favor of voluntary measures.</p>
        <p>Even as the administration scrambles to come up with its own stand on the issue, the Congressional aides and several senators said, the pressures of public opinion and concern over international fallout appear to have added to a view that Congress would be irresponsible to do nothing.</p>
        <p>''Very few of us up here want to have America seen as not participating in something that's important,'' Mr. Hagel said in a telephone interview. He said that what happened in Bonn had redoubled a sense of broad support for doing something.</p>
        <p>Senator Jeff Bingaman, the New Mexico Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said, ''I certainly feel that leadership's got to come from somewhere. It's not coming from the administration.''</p>
        <p>''And I think it would be a failure for us,'' Mr. Bingaman said, ''to just sit by idly and let the rest of the world work on this problem while our scientists tell us that the problem is very real.''</p>
        <p>Today's hearings on the subject were the first since the breakup of the Bonn meetings, and a sense of frustration over the administration not offering an alternative was evident even among Republicans who have been supportive of the White House position. Their comments may have reflected recent opinion polls showing that increasing numbers of Americans see the problem as serious.</p>
        <p>In the months before the Kyoto treaty was framed in 1997, the Senate voted 95 to 0 for a resolution opposing any treaty that would reduce carbon dioxide emissions unless developing  countries were also made subject to the rules that would bind industrialized countries like the United States.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has often pointed to that vote as an indication that a treaty requiring mandatory cuts in carbon dioxide emissions could never win Senate ratification. But supporters of mandatory measures point out that the mounting evidence of the scope and potential severity of climate change problems that has emerged in the last four years has significantly altered both the political and the scientific debates.</p>
        <p>Senator George V. Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, told Mrs. Whitman, ''The fact of the matter is that we need to deal with the carbon issue, substantively and politically.''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Senator John Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts and a leading critic of the administration's policy, was more explicit, saying: ''What happened in Bonn has reinvigorated the notion that the United States is in a very unfortunate position, which encourages many here to think that we've got to take some steps to respond domestically, to put the United States in better graces.''</p>
        <p>President Bush has said that his administration takes the problem of climate change seriously and is determined to address it. But he has criticized the Kyoto treaty because it does not require immediate action from developing countries and because, he has argued, the steep cuts it would require in carbon dioxide emissions would exact a heavy cost to the American economy.</p>
        <p>The administration has said little about its plans since last month when Mr. Bush promised more money for research into causes and possible solutions to global warming.</p>
        <p>Administration officials now say that the White House hopes to come up with an alternative to the Kyoto plan in time for the next meeting of the Kyoto group, in October.</p>
        <p>Today's hearing focused on emissions from power plants. Mr. Jeffords, whose bill would rein in power-plant emissions of four problem-causing gases said it was wisest to address all four of the gases at once.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Whitman, advocating the administration's three-pollutant approach, said it would be more prudent to move now to tighten restrictions on three undisputed public health problems -- nitrogen oxide, sulfur dioxide and mercury -- while deferring action on carbon dioxide until its role in global warming was better understood.</p>
        <p>''It would be a shame to deny people an important public health goal while we await consensus on carbon dioxide emissions,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
