<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proposal Is Latest U.S. Reaction To Concerns That Wax and Wane</title>
    <meta content="17ENER$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/17/politics/17ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DC103AF934A25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proposal Is Latest U.S. Reaction To Concerns That Wax and Wane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many veterans of past energy shortages suggest United States has failed to stick with policies to fight them as energy crises wax and wane; say debate in Bush administration seems very familiar; debate raises some of most complicated and politically charged trade-offs involving conservation, environment and government regulation vs production and market forces; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Bob Wise of West Virginia was in a bullish mood when he met with his state's leading coal-industry officials last week. Once again, he said, an administration has declared an energy crisis and concluded that coal, the domestic workhorse of fossil fuels, is a major part of the solution. ''We're back,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there was a wariness between the lines of Mr. Wise's message, and more than than a little sense of déjà vu.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Bob Wise of West Virginia was in a bullish mood when he met with his state's leading coal-industry officials last week. Once again, he said, an administration has declared an energy crisis and concluded that coal, the domestic workhorse of fossil fuels, is a major part of the solution. ''We're back,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But there was a wariness between the lines of Mr. Wise's message, and more than than a little sense of déjà vu.</p>
        <p>''It seems to be running in a 20-year cycle: The country vows, by golly, we're going to do something about energy,'' Mr. Wise, a Democrat, told the group. ''But then memories get short,'' he added. ''The question is whether we will truly be back in a sustained way.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration produced its energy plan tonight, declaring that ''America in the year 2001 faces the most serious energy shortage since the oil embargoes of the 1970's.'' But many veterans of the past energy wars share a guarded view of such plans. The nation, they suggest, may be better at declaring energy crises than sticking with policies to fight them.</p>
        <p>James R. Schlesinger, secretary of energy from 1977 to 1979, when the issue dominated and arguably consumed the Carter administration, said somewhat ruefully, ''It's easier to make plans than to get them accepted.''</p>
        <p>In fact, there has been no shortage of energy proposals over the years: for a big investment in synthetic fuels, for vast new efforts in energy efficiency, for major expansions of coal use, for the creation of new agencies and the regulation -- and deregulation -- of oil and natural gas. Some endured, some lost support when the price of oil dropped, some did not survive the changes of administrations and philosophies.</p>
        <p>As expected, the Bush administration's energy plan calls for added supply from domestic oil, gas and coal but also calls for government to ''streamline the licensing of nuclear power plants.'' It also declares that ''our energy crisis has been years in the making, and will take years to put fully behind us.''</p>
        <p>In recent days, many energy veterans have said the debate seems very familiar.</p>
        <p>Jody Powell, press secretary for President Jimmy Carter, said: ''One would think now, after all these many years, starting in '72, '73, that we might have learned this is a recurring problem that we probably ought to think about dealing with on a longer-term, more thoughtful basis.  We've had two oil shocks, a third one of unknown dimensions on the horizon. And we also went to war about this.''</p>
        <p>But Walter Rosenbaum, an expert on energy at the University of Florida, suggested that the policy zigzags of the last 30 years should not be surprising.</p>
        <p>''Short of a war, this has probably been the most difficult kind of planning,'' said Mr. Rosenbaum, a professor of political science, ''because it requires us to make sacrifices that hit the pocketbook directly. And it's hard for politicians because those are the things that people remember.''</p>
        <p>Both in the 1970's and today, the energy debate raises some of the most complicated and politically charged trade-offs: conservation vs. production; environment vs. energy;  government intervention vs. market forces.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, beginning with the Arab oil embargo of 1973, the energy crisis seemed an enduring feature of American life. It led to elaborate regulatory structures, an array of new government agencies, (first the Federal Energy Administration and the Energy Research and Development Agency, then the cabinet-level Department of Energy) and the first of many vows to end the nation's dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>When President Richard M. Nixon announced Project Independence in 1973, he compared it to the Manhattan Project and the Apollo program, and promised, ''By the end of this decade, we will have developed the potential to meet our own energy needs without depending upon any foreign energy sources.'' (The nation's dependence on foreign oil was greater by 1980 and greater still by 2000.)</p>
        <p>But it was Mr. Carter who essentially staked his presidency on what he called, just a few months after taking office in a cold winter during a natural gas crisis, ''the moral equivalent of war.''</p>
        <p>It was a war fraught with symbolism: solar panels on the White House roof (eventually removed during the Reagan administration), sweaters on the president, urgent pleas to the nation to set winter thermostats at no more than 65.</p>
        <p>The war was also waged with huge new investments. Mr. Rosenbaum said that between 1974 and 1981, federal support for all forms of energy research and development increased 475 percent.</p>
        <p>Daniel Yergin, chairman of Cambridge Energy Research Associates, noted that the Carter years saw a move toward rolling back a ''Rube Goldberg system of price controls'' for oil and natural gas, overcoming intense political opposition and ''the great skepticism about the ability of markets to actually work.''</p>
        <p>In those years there was also a  heavy emphasis on conservation and energy efficiency, with measures like tax credits for home insulation and energy efficiency standards for home appliances.</p>
        <p>David Nemtzow, president of the Alliance to Save Energy, an advocacy group, said that one of the most enduring elements of the Carter era was the push toward conservation and efficiency. The fuel economy standards were passed just before Mr. Carter took office but were put into effect in his tenure and save more than three million barrels of oil a day, Mr. Nemtzow said. The appliance standards were haggled over for years but eventually took hold.</p>
        <p>''If you buy a full-size refrigerator today,'' Mr. Nemtzow said, ''it will use no more than 40 percent of the electricity that a full-size refrigerator did in the 70's.''</p>
        <p>As time passed, and the price of oil dropped, the public's zeal for conservation eased; witness the popularity of less efficient sports utility vehicles and small trucks. But the overall trend toward energy efficiency remained, Mr. Yergin said.</p>
        <p>Other energy initiatives from the Carter years, though, proved to be dead ends. One was the Synthetic Fuels Corporation, intended to pump billions into developing new ways of producing fuels, like coal liquefaction and gasification. An area outside Morgantown, W.Va., was slated to get a $1.4 billion plant designed to produce a clean-burning liquid from high-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>But after President Ronald Reagan came in, and the price of oil began to drop, the Synthetic Fuels Corporation proved a tempting target. It was abolished in 1985; the site where the synfuel plant was supposed to be built is now being developed as an industrial park.</p>
        <p>It was emblematic of the sharp shift between the Carter and Reagan philosophies. Mr. Reagan preached the virtues of a free market and campaigned for the abolition of the Energy Department. Financing for energy research and development was cut substantially, and fuel economy standards were relaxed. Meanwhile, world oil prices were falling. The energy crisis receded for a while, although it was rediscovered in the first Bush administration around the time of the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Federal policy on coal has been  particularly inconsistent over the years; power plants were discouraged from burning coal for environmental reasons and encouraged to burn it for energy reasons. The Bush plan released tonight may be starting another cycle.</p>
        <p>This policy roller coaster is hard for a state like West Virginia, which has far too much experience with the boom-bust cycle of coal. Governor Wise says he is setting up his own task force to see how his state can create a sustainable boom.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the governor said, ''I want this country to recognize that you can't turn energy off and on like a spigot.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>James Watt Sees Vindication</p>
        <p>DENVER, May 16 (AP) -- James G. Watt, interior secretary under President Reagan, said in an interview published today that the Bush administration's focus on drilling to solve energy problems was just what he suggested 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watt called for tapping energy on public land, and in recent weeks Vice President Dick Cheney has said production should take precedence over conservation.</p>
        <p>''Twenty years later, it sounds like they've just dusted off the old work,'' Mr. Watt said in an interview with The Denver Post.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
