<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Muscadet Stars in a Loire Revival</title>
    <meta content="28WINE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/28/dining/28WINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1281259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDF1F3CF93BA15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Muscadet Stars in a Loire Revival</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wine Talk: Muscadet Stars in a Loire Revival</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial Wine Talk column on muscadet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOUIS MÉTAIREAU is a tall, dashing fellow with an elegant mustache, the wardrobe of a boulevardier and an unerring sense of theater. But he is a not a matinee idol from the Comédie Française; he makes muscadet wine in the west of France.</p>
        <p>Or rather he directs a group of muscadet producers. They are called, theatrically, Louis Métaireau et Ses Vignerons d'Art -- Louis Métaireau and His Artistic Winemakers. And all this in the often grim, rain-swept reaches of the Loire River known as the Pays Nantais.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Louis Métaireau is a not a matinee idol from the Comédie Française; he makes muscadet wine in the west of France</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOUIS MÉTAIREAU is a tall, dashing fellow with an elegant mustache, the wardrobe of a boulevardier and an unerring sense of theater. But he is a not a matinee idol from the Comédie Française; he makes muscadet wine in the west of France.</p>
        <p>Or rather he directs a group of muscadet producers. They are called, theatrically, Louis Métaireau et Ses Vignerons d'Art -- Louis Métaireau and His Artistic Winemakers. And all this in the often grim, rain-swept reaches of the Loire River known as the Pays Nantais.</p>
        <p>Once, some years back, Mr. Métaireau invited me to meet a dozen or so of his ''vignerons'' at his offices near Nantes. I arrived on a cold, rainy morning to find a room full of intense-looking men and about 20 of their wines lined up on a table. I was expected to comment on them. It was one of the worst moments in my life. I knew almost nothing about muscadet, and they had spent their lives making them.</p>
        <p>I got out alive by turning the tables on them. I asked questions. So eager were they to talk about their wines that they soon forgot I was supposed to be some kind of expert. And I came away knowing a lot more than when I went in.</p>
        <p>Most of the grape-growing and winemaking regions of France can be traced to the Romans. They must have been shrewd viticulturists because, for the most part, the grapes grown today are not all that different from those they planted.</p>
        <p>There is one place, however, where they got it all wrong: Brittany. In the country around what is now Nantes, they planted red varieties. The Pays Nantais -- the Nantes country -- is a relatively flat region frequently beset by fierce Atlantic storms, like the one blowing the day I walked into Mr. Métaireau's office. Red wine grapes need the sun. What the Romans could have been thinking of is still a mystery.</p>
        <p>Seventeen centuries later, the Dutch fixed things up. Brandy drinkers, they had been buying the base wine for distillation in the Charente region, south of Nantes. Squeezed by Charente taxes, Dutch traders talked to the growers around Nantes, which had much the same climate as Charente, but no taxes. They persuaded the growers to switch to white grapes.</p>
        <p>Their timing was good. After a disastrous frost in 1709 wiped out most of the mediocre red grapes, Louis XIV ordered the growers to come up with a white replacement. They chose a Burgundian grape called the melon, actually an offshoot of gamay, the grape of Beaujolais.</p>
        <p>Because it had a musky flavor, the locals came up with the name muscadet. It is a tough grape, relatively unaffected by frost, and it thrives in a region where the sun is often in short supply. In all of France, only the Champagne region has less summer sun.</p>
        <p>Muscadet's modern history is much like that of Beaujolais. Until the 1950's, it was a local wine, rarely seen elsewhere. Then as living conditions improved in France, and good fish became available all over the country, muscadet was ''discovered.'' It was light, fresh, moderately acidic, inexpensive and plentiful. The appellation covers 30,000 acres, most of it in the department of the Sèvre-et-Maine.</p>
        <p>There is actually a muscadet nouveau, just like Beaujolais nouveau. But, unlike Beaujolais's popularity, muscadet's was short-lived. A great deal of one-dimensional, boring muscadet was produced, and by the 1960's supply far exceeded demand. That's when Mr. Métaireau and a handful of other growers, including the Sauvions and the Chéreaus, decided to go for quality and then to promote their wines vigorously.</p>
        <p>Today's muscadet is better than it was 40 years ago and is known and enjoyed all over the world. Much of its charm can be traced to the ''sur lie'' process by which the best muscadets are made.</p>
        <p>The lees are mostly broken-down dead yeast cells that remain after the wine has fermented. They sink to the bottom of the fermenting barrel or tank. Most white wines are decanted off the lees as soon as fermentation is over in the fall.</p>
        <p>Sur-lie wines spend the winter before they are bottled literally on the lees, or sur lie, without first being separated from them. Those dead yeast cells give off acids, which combine with other elements in the wine to give it extra depth and flavor.</p>
        <p>The lees also retain some of the carbon dioxide produced by the original fermentation so that the wine has a slight but appealing spritz when the bottle is opened.</p>
        <p>Muscadet is at its best with oysters at a small cafe on the Breton coast. But it is almost as good at home with steamed mussels or any other seafood.</p>
        <p>At a time of outrageous wine prices, muscadet is one wine that continues to be reasonably priced. So much so, that many potential customers stay away because they can't believe that a bottle of white wine under $10 can be good.</p>
        <p>Mr. Métaireau's Grand Mouton, at around $10, is at the high end for a muscadet but worth the price. The Sauvions's Château du Cleray sells for around $9 and their Nobleraie for less than $7. One of my favorites, from the Marquis de Goulaine, is around $9. Château de Chasseloir, from the Chéreau family is about $7.</p>
        <p>Muscadet is vivid proof that good white wine need not be expensive. Now if only they could do something about the price of the fish to go with it.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
