<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Terrific News in Mexico City: Air Is Sometimes Breathable</title>
    <meta content="05MEXI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/05/world/05MEXI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1260391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico City (Mexico)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molina, Mario J (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Mexico City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DF163AF936A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Terrific News in Mexico City: Air Is Sometimes Breathable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Jan. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexico City's air, called worst in world by United Nations in 1992, is getting fresher--or at least less foul; Dr Mario J Molina, Nobel Prize winner in chemistry who has lead most intensive study of problem yet undertaken, says there are data suggesting that air may be improving; notes there has been no smog alert for 15 months, and that amount of lead, carbon dioxide and sulfur dioxide in air is down; other pollution levels are still often unacceptably high, but on many days, especially weekends, air is sometimes clear enough to breathe with pleasure, in city where foul air contributed to deaths of hundreds of people in one week four years ago; improving air is result of increasingly stringent environmental rules, which call for cleaner fuels, catalytic converters on cars, emissions tests and rules on industry; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The atmosphere is infamous here. For decades it has been a danger to the millions inhaling it. But now something new is in the air.</p>
        <p>It seems to be getting fresher -- or at least less foul. This would be quite a change: in 1992, the United Nations called Mexico City's air the world's worst.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The atmosphere is infamous here. For decades it has been a danger to the millions inhaling it. But now something new is in the air.</p>
        <p>It seems to be getting fresher -- or at least less foul. This would be quite a change: in 1992, the United Nations called Mexico City's air the world's worst.</p>
        <p>''That's no longer true,'' said Dr. Mario J. Molina, a Mexico City native leading the most intensive study of the problem yet undertaken. Dr. Molina, a chemistry professor at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, shared the Nobel Prize in Chemistry in 1995 for showing 20 years earlier that chlorofluorocarbons, then widely used in aerosols, refrigerators and air conditioners, were depleting the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>''There are data that suggest that the air may be improving,'' said Dr. Molina. Indeed, there has been no smog alert for 15 months. Lead, carbon dioxide and sulfur dioxide in the air are down.</p>
        <p>Other pollution levels are still often unacceptably high, but on many days, especially weekends, the air is sometimes clear enough to breathe with pleasure -- this in a place where it contributed to the deaths of hundreds of people in one terrible week four years ago.</p>
        <p>''You would have expected pollution levels to increase if you look at the increased number of cars, people and economic activity in the past three years,'' Dr. Molina said.</p>
        <p>They have not. While fair winds and cleansing rains may take some credit, so do increasingly stringent environmental rules, which call for cleaner fuels, catalytic converters on cars, emissions tests and rules on industry.</p>
        <p>The air has tested the limits of human endurance. The air quality index runs from zero to 500, zero representing the Garden of Eden, and 300 or more representing hell on earth. Below 100 is officially satisfactory, 101 to 200 is unsatisfactory, and anything higher is dangerous -- and a potential threat to life. In the mid-1990's, it exceeded 100 about 9 days out of 10; simply breathing was like smoking two packs of cigarettes a day. Sometimes it went off the charts: once, in 1996, it spiked at 394. There are good days and bad days, and the pollution level still often exceeds 100. But on Wednesday, in the heart of Mexico City, it peaked at 69, with a low of 9. Levels of sulfur dioxode, nitrogen dioxide, carbon monoxide and particulates were all 40 or less. And winter is normally the worst time of year for air pollution.</p>
        <p>Mexico City still rates as one of the planet's more toxic places, along with Beijing, New Delhi, Jakarta, Bangkok, Tehran and other mega cities with too many people, too many cars, too many polluting industries and too few coordinated efforts to clear the air.</p>
        <p>This is where Dr. Molina and his wife, Dr. Luisa T. Molina, a research scientist at M.I.T., come in. They are leading the Mexico City Case Study, part of a program at M.I.T. for exploring the problems of megacities in the developing world. With close to $2 million from M.I.T., the National Science Foundation and the Mexican government, they have brought together scores of government officials, scientists, engineers, economists and other experts to figure out how to cut the smog.</p>
        <p>No mad scientist could think up a better machine for creating air pollution than this capital of nearly 20 million people. It sits in a bowl 7,400 feet above sea level, ringed by mountains, under a tropical sun -- a petri dish for brewing and trapping bad air. The miasma spews from three million cars, buses and trucks, and from thousands of dirty companies and dump sites. They fill the air with toxic chemicals and tiny particles of everything from heavy metals to human waste.</p>
        <p>Mexico's leaders spent most of the 1970's and 1980's ignoring the pollution. The Institutional Revolutionary Party, which until last year had enjoyed a monopoly on power for decades, had little incentive to be accountable to the public, to listen to scientists or to press for changes, especially ones that could thwart economic development.</p>
        <p>This attitude filtered down to the public in the form of fatalism, a disbelief that anything but a strong wind could clear the air. Pemex, the national oil company, which produces much of Mexico's gasoline, also spent years ''sort of denying the problem,'' Mario Molina said. ''There were statements that there was no pollution problem.''</p>
        <p>Not until 1995 did federal health authorities state clearly that the air was unhealthy. That year, the World Bank financed a study suggesting that high ozone levels alone were responsible for as many as 1,000 premature deaths and 35,000 hospitalizations for respiratory diseases each year in Mexico City. Those numbers appeared conservative when, in November 1996, a five-day smog emergency sent 400,000 people to hospitals and contributed to the deaths of 300 or more, according to city officials.</p>
        <p>So what has gone right?</p>
        <p>The gasoline is cleaner than it was a few years ago. Pemex took the lead out, upgraded its refineries, and since 1996 has quadrupled its gas imports from the United States. That cleaner fuel from the United States accounts for as much as a quarter of the gasoline burned in Mexico today.</p>
        <p>New cars have catalytic converters, which reduce carbon monoxide and nitrogen oxide. Some large industries have become cleaner or moved away from Mexico City. A hulking oil refinery within the city limits was closed in the face of political pressure from labor unions.</p>
        <p>F. Sherwood Rowland, one of two other scientists who shared the 1995 Nobel Prize in Chemistry with Dr. Molina, demonstrated that same year that leaks of liquefied petroleum gas, or L.P.G., used for cooking and heating in almost every home in Mexico City, were a major factor in the poisoning of the air.</p>
        <p>People burn more than two million tons of L.P.G. a year in Mexico City -- 70,000 barrels a day. Pemex reformulated the bottled fuel, removing butylene, a volatile and environmentally harmful ingredient, but the gas still leaks from millions of poorly maintained pipes and tubes, and it represents perhaps 15 percent of the air pollution in Mexico City, the Molinas say.</p>
        <p>Then in 1997 the first popularly elected municipal government took power in Mexico City. Its left-of-center leaders were more amenable to stiffer environmental regulations, the Molinas say.</p>
        <p>The Mexico City study, which will continue for another two years, suggests that ''new technology exists that is clean enough to solve the problem to a significant extent,'' Mario Molina said. ''But it's expensive. The main one would be clean cars, buses, trucks -- I'm just talking about plain standard internal combustion engines. Then, the next set of changes are harder: repairing leaks of L.P.G. in peoples' homes, replacing pilot lights, the use of solvents in small industries and homes. For industries, you need clean furnaces, to remove nitrogen oxide and other pollutants.''</p>
        <p>Things had gotten so bad in Mexico City that some scientists seriously proposed blowing a hole in the mountains on one side of the capital and setting up giant fans on the other to push away the smog. Dr. Molina suggests that with clear-air regulations -- and cleaner government to enforce them -- such desperate measures may not be necessary.</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago, the air in Los Angeles was worse than it is in Mexico City today, Dr. Molina says. ''Mexico City's air can improve as much as Los Angeles's did, and in a shorter time,'' he said. ''That's a goal that can be achieved.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
