<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIVE QUESTIONS/for NANCY F. KOEHN; An Information Age Led by Business, So Far</title>
    <meta content="25FIVE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/25/business/25FIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1280563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flaherty, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koehn, Nancy F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Harvard</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Act</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DE153CF936A15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIVE QUESTIONS/for NANCY F. KOEHN; An Information Age Led by Business, So Far</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE FLAHERTY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flaherty, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nancy F Koehn, Harvard business historian, answers questions on prospects for business-friendly policies of Bush administration; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUSINESS has scored a number of regulatory victories in recent weeks. Early this month, Congress voted to repeal ergonomics standards meant to protect workers from repetitive strain injuries. In an abrupt turnabout, President George W. Bush last week reversed a campaign pledge to limit power plants' emissions of carbon dioxide. And this week, the Environmental Protection Agency canceled a plan that would have reduced the allowable amount of arsenic in drinking water by 80 percent.</p>
        <p>Those moves, which coincide with other signs that the change in the White House  will mean more business-friendly policies -- like the opening of the Alaskan wilderness to oil drilling -- appear to point to a new political climate for corporate America. Nancy F. Koehn, a business historian at Harvard University and the author of ''Brand New: How Entrepreneurs Earned Consumers' Trust from Wedgwood to Dell'' (Harvard Business School Press), takes a broader view. Last week, she talked about what comes next.</p>
        <p>JULIE FLAHERTY</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUSINESS has scored a number of regulatory victories in recent weeks. Early this month, Congress voted to repeal ergonomics standards meant to protect workers from repetitive strain injuries. In an abrupt turnabout, President George W. Bush last week reversed a campaign pledge to limit power plants' emissions of carbon dioxide. And this week, the Environmental Protection Agency canceled a plan that would have reduced the allowable amount of arsenic in drinking water by 80 percent.</p>
        <p>Those moves, which coincide with other signs that the change in the White House  will mean more business-friendly policies -- like the opening of the Alaskan wilderness to oil drilling -- appear to point to a new political climate for corporate America. Nancy F. Koehn, a business historian at Harvard University and the author of ''Brand New: How Entrepreneurs Earned Consumers' Trust from Wedgwood to Dell'' (Harvard Business School Press), takes a broader view. Last week, she talked about what comes next.</p>
        <p>JULIE FLAHERTY</p>
        <p>Q.  Why are we seeing an expansion of the rights of businesses now? Is it more than just a friendlier government?</p>
        <p>A.  We've seen business become more prominent in the life of the country for some time. It is not brand-new to the Bush administration. An administration can accelerate that perception, but the fundamental drivers of what is going on transcend the White House.</p>
        <p>What we're seeing is an inflection point in the history of capitalism as the information age takes hold. Business is leading that transformation. We're seeing businesses experiment with trying to exploit, trying to take advantage of and, over the next few years, make profits from the possibilities of the information age.</p>
        <p>Those are Chapters 1 and 2. Coming chapters will be about other actors responding to business initiatives. It will be about workers, politicians and voters making the information age their own, regulating and trying to exert more control.</p>
        <p>Q.  Are there historical parallels that we should be examining for insight into what happens next?</p>
        <p>A.  The late 19th century is a perfect analogue. People perceived the country to be ruled by business and what business wanted. If we look back to the second industrial revolution, you think about someone like John Rockefeller and the birth of oil refining. That industry was not initially very regulated.</p>
        <p>But as industrialization took hold, a whole lot of other people got in the game. The formation of what would become the A.F.L.-C.I.O. meant the acceleration of the unionization movement. The Sherman Antitrust Act, and others before it, initiated large-scale government regulation. A whole range of social and political movements was formed against what people saw as too much business power.</p>
        <p>I believe we will see extraordinarily vibrant responses on the part of workers and government to the new imperative of the information age over the coming three to six years. It could be a new form of collective action on the part of workers or new policies on intellectual property rights on the Web. It could be anything from sales taxes on electronic commerce to new standards in the workplace, because the workplace itself is changing so rapidly.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is there some opportunism at work here, with businesses seizing on signs of economic weakness to claim they need more flexibility, less regulation and so on?</p>
        <p>A.  Businesses, like workers, like politicians, will take advantage of any window of opportunity. That's the nature of the system we live in, economically and politically. Some business people perceive that window now.</p>
        <p>But business is hardly monolithic. Almost all the executives I talk to say they have not lived in a more confusing moment. Some signals seem very robust and others seem to point toward a real economic downturn. They wonder: What does that mean for pursuing competitive advantage? For motivating and retaining your most valuable workers? Or, if you're a young enterprise, staying afloat? I do not think this is a moment when most business people are sitting back, rubbing their hands and saying, ''Great, let's go for the gusto.''</p>
        <p>Q.  How much of a backlash will there be from voters, employees and consumer groups?</p>
        <p>A.  The importance of the stakes involved and people's perception of those stakes are critical determinants. How intensely do people care about the issues? When the economy is very good and people perceive that a rising tide is lifting their boat, a whole bunch of issues can be diluted in their importance. When the tide is no longer rising so fast, people take a different look.</p>
        <p>Q.  If the stock market continues its downturn, will people view business more critically? Will it affect whether business can keep winning in Washington?</p>
        <p>A.  The jury is out on that one. We've not been through a moment in history in which the economy was potentially turning downward and so many people were so involved in the stock market. The huge boom market of the 1990's drew in a lot of people. They are not only buying and selling stock, but thinking and talking about the market as part of their daily calculus. How will that affect people's actions in the workplace, in the polling booth? We don't really know that yet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
