<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DB1230F935A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Barak May Join Sharon In Israeli Unity Government  Ehud Barak, Israel's caretaker prime minister, conditionally agreed to serve as defense minister under Prime Minister-elect Ariel Sharon, Israeli news reports said. Mr. Barak tentatively agreed to bring his Labor Party into a unity government with Mr. Sharon's Likud Party, according to a statement from his office.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Plans to Relax Mexico Border  President Bush and President Vicente Fox of Mexico are expected to announce high-level talks on proposals that would include opening the border to a freer flow of Mexican guest workers and granting residency to undocumented Mexicans working in the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Barak May Join Sharon In Israeli Unity Government  Ehud Barak, Israel's caretaker prime minister, conditionally agreed to serve as defense minister under Prime Minister-elect Ariel Sharon, Israeli news reports said. Mr. Barak tentatively agreed to bring his Labor Party into a unity government with Mr. Sharon's Likud Party, according to a statement from his office.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Plans to Relax Mexico Border  President Bush and President Vicente Fox of Mexico are expected to announce high-level talks on proposals that would include opening the border to a freer flow of Mexican guest workers and granting residency to undocumented Mexicans working in the United States.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Assigns Security Duties  Mr. Bush has given his national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, the traditional powers of the post and rejected suggestions that Vice President Cheney head important meetings of the security council.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Congo Peace Steps  Congo's new president, Joseph Kabila, left, agreed to open political talks with the rebels challenging his government. And Congo's warring parties moved closer to peace with unexpected agreements on crucial issues.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>France Culls Its Cattle  The French government announced plans to kill up to 10,000 head of cattle a week to support beef prices, down by as much as 80 percent because of the mad cow crisis.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Climate Issues on Back Burner  The Bush administration is only slowly turning to climate issues and so is being left on the sidelines in international talks that could shape a treaty curtailing global warming, say government officials and executives involved in the discussions.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-16</p>
        <p>Focus on Rich's Pardon Puts Governors in Spotlight  As many as 2,000 clemency orders are issued each year by state governors, but they have seldom received the degree of attention being paid to former President Bill Clinton's last-minute pardons. But with Mr. Clinton still defending his pardon of Marc Rich, the fugitive commodities trader, state pardons are coming under increased scrutiny.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats are furious at Mr. Clinton for how he left the White House. His pardon of Mr. Rich and his departure with tens of thousands of dollars worth of household gifts from wealthy donors have even inflamed stalwart allies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have prepared subpoenas demanding the bank records of Mr. Rich's ex-wife in an effort to determine the source of her large contributions to Democratic causes in recent years, including $450,000 to Mr. Clinton's presidential library, government officials said.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Opposition to Tax Cuts  Two Republican senators have come out against President Bush's proposal for a $1.6 trillion tax cut across 10 years, and Democratic Congressional leaders began a drive for a tax cut less than half that size.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Subs to Shun Civilians  The Navy has tightened its rules on civilians participating in exercises aboard submarines, at least until the investigation into the sinking of a Japanese fishing trawler off Hawaii is completed, the Pentagon said.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Major League Headache  Roger Clemens, left, is not named in a memorandum to umpires that reinforces their discretion to eject a pitcher when a ball is thrown near a batter's head. But Joe Torre, the Yankees manager, sees Clemens between the lines, and frets about his pitcher with the reputation as an intimidator.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Another Brooklyn Exhibit Draws Fire From Giuliani  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said an exhibit at the Brooklyn Museum of Art that included a photograph of a nude woman as Christ at the Last Supper was ''disgusting,'' and said he would appoint a commission to set ''decency standards'' to keep such work out of museums that receive public money. Mr. Giuliani, who tried to shut down the museum over an exhibit in 1999, said that despite losing that case in court, he was considering filing suit again.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Driver Testifies in Combs Case  A former driver for Sean Combs, the hip-hop mogul known as Puffy, testified that Mr. Combs offered him $50,000 to claim ownership of a gun that the police found in the men's vehicle when they were arrested after a nightclub shooting.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-32; E33-48</p>
        <p>Watergate Revisited  The director Steven Soderbergh, left, says the 1976 movie ''All the President's Men'' is one of his ''favorite American films,'' and he drew on it when making ''Erin Brockovich'' and ''Traffic,'' which received Oscar nominations for best film while bringing him nominations for best director. He said he turned to the Watergate film because ''we were trying to make films about serious issues that were also very entertaining.''</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Sir Richard William Southern  An Oxford University historian whose insights on the early Middle Ages won praise not only for their erudition but also for their literary style, he was 88.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Less Scrutiny From I.R.S.  Audits of tax returns, which reached a record low in 1999, fell sharply last year as new taxpayer rights and procedural changes ordered by Congress reduced the agency's efficiency and its audit staff dwindled.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Skepticism About Xerox  The company's stock has been popular with investors, but traders of its bank debt are more skeptical about its prospects.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Victory for Law Firm  A judge has rejected accusations that Milberg Weiss Bershad Hynes &amp; Lerach, a law firm that represents plaintiffs in securities class action cases, made misrepresentations to lay claim to control of litigation against Oxford Health Plans Inc.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Optimism Returns to Markets  Stocks jumped, with the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index hitting its highest close in a week. Blue chips also rose, with the broader market buoyed by optimism that the economy may recover this year.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Defending the estate tax; the mayor and the arts, round 2; a new front in the pardon investigation.</p>
        <p>Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E48  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E32  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>C10</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
