<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Truckers Get Cool Air Without Fouling the Air Around Them</title>
    <meta content="07WHIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/07/nyregion/07WHIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1315412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hunts Point Terminal Market (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hunts Point (New York)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E5DF1F3CF934A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Truckers Get Cool Air Without Fouling the Air Around Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Truckers Get Cool Air Without Fouling the Air Around Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hunts Point market becomes among first places in country to use external sources to supply heat, air conditioning and electricity to trucks laying over, rather than using their diesel engines to idle; technology is set to be installed at 28 truck parking areas and is expected to reduce by 2,300 tons annually pollution caused by diesel emissions and to save thousands of dollars in fuel costs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like fashion models showing off a new look, three trucks sat quietly humming at the Hunts Point Cooperative Market in the South Bronx yesterday. With 90-degree heat outside, the trucks' drivers were coolly air-conditioned in their cabins. Yet none of their engines were running. Not an ounce of diesel fuel was being expended, not a single noxious fume emitted. Instead, the air was being funneled into the trucks through bright yellow tubing.</p>
        <p>Under a pilot program introduced yesterday, with Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, in attendance, the Hunts Point market will become among the first places in the country to use external sources to supply heat, air-conditioning and electricity to trucks laying over, rather than allowing their diesel engines to idle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>the Hunts Point market in the South Bronx will become among the first places in the country to use external sources to supply heat, air-conditioning and electricity to trucks laying over, rather than allowing their diesel engines to idle</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like fashion models showing off a new look, three trucks sat quietly humming at the Hunts Point Cooperative Market in the South Bronx yesterday. With 90-degree heat outside, the trucks' drivers were coolly air-conditioned in their cabins. Yet none of their engines were running. Not an ounce of diesel fuel was being expended, not a single noxious fume emitted. Instead, the air was being funneled into the trucks through bright yellow tubing.</p>
        <p>Under a pilot program introduced yesterday, with Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, in attendance, the Hunts Point market will become among the first places in the country to use external sources to supply heat, air-conditioning and electricity to trucks laying over, rather than allowing their diesel engines to idle.</p>
        <p>The technology, to be installed over the next few months at 28 truck parking areas in addition to the four that began operating yesterday, is expected to reduce by 2,300 tons annually the pollution caused by diesel emissions and to save thousands of dollars in fuel costs.</p>
        <p>A Giuliani administration official also announced yesterday that when the Fulton Fish Market is moved to a new site within the Hunts Point market, all of its truck bays will have electrification capacity.</p>
        <p>There may be no better place than the market to try out the new technology, which was developed by the IdleAire Technologies Corporation of Knoxville, Tenn. The Hunts Point market is the world's largest wholesale food distribution center. Since it opened in the mid-1970's, hundreds of thousands of tractor-trailers spewing diesel fumes have traveled through the neighborhood, which is home to 9,000 people. The trucks sometimes sit for more than 10 hours waiting to unload, or for their drivers to rest. And often, the drivers let their engines idle to provide air-conditioning or heat or to operate appliances.</p>
        <p>The Hunts Point neighborhood is also home to dozens of waste transfer stations, and the combination has meant that its air has become harder to breathe. One in three children there suffers from asthma, and the childhood asthma hospitalization rate is 12 times the national average. Although research has yet to prove a direct link between diesel emissions and asthma, studies suggest that diesel exhaust can help cause attacks.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman went to the market, along with Erin Crotty, the state commissioner of environmental conservation, to show support for the electrification project, and Mrs. Whitman said that her agency would provide resources to analyze its effectiveness. ''Every community has a right to have clean air,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Hunts Point pilot program is being financed by part of a $5 million grant from Consolidated Edison to a nonprofit organization, Clean Air Communities. A thermostatically controlled heating, ventilation and air-conditioning unit will be installed at each truck space. A console unit tethered to it will provide local telephone, television and Internet service -- even a cable TV hookup -- as well as an outlet for appliances. Drivers can pay the fees for the services with a credit card.</p>
        <p>Before the ceremony, Mrs. Whitman met privately for 45 minutes with local environmental advocates. They pressed her to take a leadership role in enforcing the federal Clean Air Act neighborhood by neighborhood, rather than citywide or regionwide, to address the acute pollution in the South Bronx.</p>
        <p>''We hope there will be a much more hands-on approach by the E.P.A. to low-income communities of color,'' said Majora Carter, the executive director of the new nonprofit organization Sustainable South Bronx, who led the fight for the electrification pilot project.</p>
        <p>Of Mrs. Whitman, Ms. Carter said: ''Frankly, her coming here was a positive step and I want to acknowledge that. None of us are interested in providing good public relations for Bush's energy policies, not to mention his environmental policies, but we are open to working with the administration.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has been seeking a better image in the wake of criticism over its environmental policies, like refusing to sign an international protocol to reduce greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman defended those policies yesterday, and she touched briefly on a decision many New York environmentalists have praised: to order General Electric to dredge 100,000 pounds of PCB's from the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Asked whether she expected a strong fight from General Electric, Mrs. Whitman said, ''I have no idea.''</p>
        <p>But when asked whether she preferred that the government or General Electric do the dredging, Mrs. Whitman said, ''We certainly want G.E. to pay.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
