<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Noblesse Oblige</title>
    <meta content="31FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/31/opinion/31FRIE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Foreign Affairs"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D7113DF932A05754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Noblesse Oblige</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Noblesse Oblige</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column criticizes Bush administration's approach to foreign policy, which he says seems based less on rules than on power and on belief that being world's only superpower means 'never having to say you're sorry;' says key to global stability is that world's only superpower be ready to pay disproportionate share to maintain global institutions and norms, because ultimately it will be biggest beneficiary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beyond the normal sniping that always goes on between Europe and America, there is today a real disagreement about what it means for America to be the world's leader. The Bush team thinks being the world's only superpower means never having to say you're sorry, and the Europeans think being the world's most powerful democracy means always having to ask permission.</p>
        <p>For the Bush team, being the world's leader means we should be able to do whatever we want when we want, unconstrained by treaties or multilateral agreements that might limit our consumption of resources (Kyoto) or our military power (the ABM and nuclear testing treaties and the biological weapons convention) or our insane gun laws (the U.N. pact on small arms). For Europe, the more economically and militarily dominant America becomes, the more people here feel that it should be answerable not only to the American people but to the rest of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Bush team offered no alternatives to Kyoto, there is a real disagreement about what it means for America to be the world's leader</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beyond the normal sniping that always goes on between Europe and America, there is today a real disagreement about what it means for America to be the world's leader. The Bush team thinks being the world's only superpower means never having to say you're sorry, and the Europeans think being the world's most powerful democracy means always having to ask permission.</p>
        <p>For the Bush team, being the world's leader means we should be able to do whatever we want when we want, unconstrained by treaties or multilateral agreements that might limit our consumption of resources (Kyoto) or our military power (the ABM and nuclear testing treaties and the biological weapons convention) or our insane gun laws (the U.N. pact on small arms). For Europe, the more economically and militarily dominant America becomes, the more people here feel that it should be answerable not only to the American people but to the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>''The whole point of having the kind of power America has today is that you're accountable to people outside your country, because what you do affects people outside your country,'' remarked Heather Grabbe, director of research for the Institute for European Reform in London. ''Bush can't just get away with saying, 'Well, the American people elected me and they don't like Kyoto, so tough,' and that settles the matter. Because you're so dominant, you have to be the example-setter.''</p>
        <p>Last week saw Europe and Japan reach agreement, without the U.S., on a new basis for implementing the Kyoto treaty on climate change, which the Bush team has trashed, arguing that it requires too deep a cut in U.S. energy usage. Then a few days later the Bush team rejected a stronger interpretation of the accord banning biological weapons, because the new inspection-verification provisions -- which we had advocated -- might expose the industrial secrets of U.S. companies. ''For six years everybody talks of the importance of verification,'' wrote London's normally pro-U.S. paper The Independent. ''And then, America discovers that its facilities, too, would have to be verified. The brazen nerve! America might be treated as though it were just another country! Mr. Bush's America seems in danger of convincing itself that it can force everybody to make concessions, while itself remaining impervious to change.''</p>
        <p>America is referred to as a ''rogue state'' in Europe now as often as Iraq. Some of this is silly. But some is not. U.S. foreign policy has always been about creating a world that operates by rules, not by force, because ideally we would like to see the world operate as much as possible like our own country. Many people around the world look to America as the ultimate upholder of rules and norms. But the message we have been sending to the world lately is that we do not believe in rules, we believe in power -- and we've got it and you don't.</p>
        <p>For now, we can always get our way, but when we elevate power in that way we invite others to challenge us on the same basis. That is the meaning of the recent China-Russia cooperation treaty. After last week's deal between Europe and Japan on Kyoto, the E.U.'s environment commissioner, Margot Wallstrom, declared: ''We've managed to rescue the Kyoto Protocol. I think something has changed today in the balance of power between the U.S. and the E.U.''</p>
        <p>It would be one thing if the Bush team said, ''We don't like Kyoto, or the bio-weapons treaty, but we have alternative approaches that can accomplish nearly the same ends with slightly different means.'' But they have offered nothing of the kind, because they spent all their time out of power trashing these agreements, not thinking of creative alternatives.</p>
        <p>Frankly, I don't care if we're unpopular. Sometimes countries have to assert their will to protect their interests. The same Europeans who now complain about our flouting of rules are the ones who love to sell arms to Iraq or Iran. But having said that, America is different -- or at least it should be -- because we have a special role in the world. The key to global stability today is that the world's only superpower be ready to pay a disproportionate share to maintain global institutions and norms -- because, ultimately, we will be the biggest beneficiary of such a world and because, if we aren't interested in rules, who will be?</p>
        <p>Foreign Affairs</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
