<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="04PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1268238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DF123EF937A35751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA DELBANCO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FLATBUSH  Puppeteers Bring Potter to Life</p>
        <p>Beatrix Potter's classic story ''The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck''  tells of a duck's flight in search of a special place to lay her eggs, and ''The Story of a Fierce Bad Rabbit'' tells of a fight between said rabbit and the Nice Gentle Rabbit over ownership of a carrot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FLATBUSH  Puppeteers Bring Potter to Life</p>
        <p>Beatrix Potter's classic story ''The Tale of Jemima Puddle-Duck''  tells of a duck's flight in search of a special place to lay her eggs, and ''The Story of a Fierce Bad Rabbit'' tells of a fight between said rabbit and the Nice Gentle Rabbit over ownership of a carrot.</p>
        <p>These stories are being brought to life in a full-scale production at the Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts put on by Hudson Vagabond Puppets.</p>
        <p>The puppeters have been working together since 1980 to make their programming fit into school curriculums while also entertaining children and their families.</p>
        <p>The puppeteers wear black clothing and use masks, costumes and rod puppets that stand up to eight feet tall, borrowing from traditional Japanese bunraku puppetry (one of the characters is pictured below).</p>
        <p>The action, part of the Family Fun series, is accompanied by music by William Walton.</p>
        <p>''Stories of Beatrix Potter,'' next Sunday, 2 p.m.; Walt Whitman Theater at Brooklyn Center for Performing Arts, on the campus of Brooklyn College, one block southwest of the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues; all tickets $10; (718) 951-4500.</p>
        <p>ASTORIA  When Terra Cotta Was King</p>
        <p>The New York Architectural Terra-Cotta Company was based in Long Island City on Vernon Boulevard, near the Queensboro Bridge, and produced ornamental terra cotta for thousands of structures that are sometimes called ''the last of the handmade buildings.''</p>
        <p>Some of these structures still exist in the five boroughs. These structures, with an emphasis on those in Queens and information about use, history and manufacture of architectural terra cotta, will be the subject of ''The Reign of Terra Cotta,'' a lecture by Susan Tunick, the president of Friends of Terra Cotta, a preservationist group.</p>
        <p>The lecture, with slides, will be presented in the context of the growth and development of technology and architecture at the beginning of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>''The Reign of Terra Cotta''; tomorrow 7:30 p.m.; Quinn's Gallery, 35th Street and Broadway, Astoria, Queens; free; (718) 278-0700.</p>
        <p>LOWER EAST SIDE  Global Warming, One Heart at a Time</p>
        <p>Anna West puts warmth into a freeze by painting hearts on snow in neighborhoods all around the city, hundreds of hearts at a time. She has been doing so since the heavy snowfalls of the winter of 1995-96.</p>
        <p>New York is not the only city she has given a little heart to: she has also applied her art to St. Petersburg, Russia, and Akron, Ohio.</p>
        <p>An exhibit of her photographs titled ''Snow Hearts'' is on view at the Charles E. Culpeper Gallery of the Henry Street Settlement. The exhibit also includes photographs of dolls and is the fourth solo show of the artist, who lives in Williamsburg, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''Snow Hearts'' tomorrow through March 1, open Monday through Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; opening reception Wednesday from 6 to 8 p.m.; Charles E. Culpeper Gallery at the Henry Street Settlement Abrons Art Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street; free; (212) 598-0400.</p>
        <p>ALSO AROUND TOWN</p>
        <p>MIZRAHI SPEAKS -- Isaac Mizrahi, who has designed costumes for movies, theater, dance and opera, as well as his own ready-to-wear line, will speak in the ''Evening With . . .'' series at St. Luke's School, to which all proceeds are given; Tuesday 7:30 p.m.; 487 Hudson Street, between Christopher and Barrow Streets; $20; (212) 924-5960.</p>
        <p>BELLOW BIOGRAPHER -- James Atlas, author of ''Bellow, a Biography,'' will speak tomorrow evening on ''Saul Bellow's Adventures in America'' at the Center for Jewish History, which officially opened last October; 6:30 p.m.; 15 West 16th Street; free; for reservations, (917) 606-8200.</p>
        <p>IMPROV SHOWDOWN -- Two teams of actors will challenge each other to create stories, scenes and poems spontaneously, based on audience suggestions, in ''TheatreSports,'' an improvisational event by Freestyle Repertory Theater; the audience will vote on the best performances at the end of the show; today 3 p.m.; Queens Theater in the Park in Flushing Meadows Corona Park; $18; members of Queens Theater in the Park, $12; (718) 760-0064.</p>
        <p>ANDREA DELBANCO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
