<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Mates Clown a Bit for the Aussies</title>
    <meta content="31DIPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/31/international/31DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Reporter's Notebook"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Australia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Howard, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DB1E3DF932A05754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Mates Clown a Bit for the Aussies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Two Mates Clown a Bit for the Aussies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>CANBERRA, Australia, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook column offering vignettes of Sec of State Colin Powell's visit to Beijing and his visit to Australia with Defense Sec Donald Rumsfeld; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Australia's friendship with the United States is long and deep. Indeed, perhaps only such a strong ally would have the pull to persuade two of the most powerful people in the Bush administration, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, to fly to the bottom of the world and then sit next to each other on the same stage to face reporters.</p>
        <p>The occasion was an annual joint meeting on defense and diplomacy. Secretary Powell had just come from China, where he noticeably avoided calling Beijing a ''strategic competitor,'' a phrase concocted during the Bush election campaign to signify toughness. (He stopped using it months ago.) But Mr. Rumsfeld, considered more of a hawk on China, was asked at the news conference whether he still called China a ''strategic competitor.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps only such a strong ally like Australia would have the pull to persuade two of the most powerful people in the Bush administration to sit next to each other on the same stage</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Australia's friendship with the United States is long and deep. Indeed, perhaps only such a strong ally would have the pull to persuade two of the most powerful people in the Bush administration, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, to fly to the bottom of the world and then sit next to each other on the same stage to face reporters.</p>
        <p>The occasion was an annual joint meeting on defense and diplomacy. Secretary Powell had just come from China, where he noticeably avoided calling Beijing a ''strategic competitor,'' a phrase concocted during the Bush election campaign to signify toughness. (He stopped using it months ago.) But Mr. Rumsfeld, considered more of a hawk on China, was asked at the news conference whether he still called China a ''strategic competitor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld, not known for his love of the press, bristled a bit, then replied: ''I don't recall using that phrase. I've heard the last administration talk about strategic partners, and then I've heard others say strategic competitors. I've always, I think, characterized it as a relationship that is multifaceted and is evolving. And I haven't put any Rumsfeldian code words on it.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting further, he parried, ''Are you trying to find some daylight between Colin and me?''</p>
        <p>That was too much to resist for an American reporter, who asked, ''Do you always agree on everything?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld shot back, ''Except for those few cases where Colin is still learning.''</p>
        <p>Upstaged!</p>
        <p>When such senior American officials land in Australia they generally receive top news billing, a reflection of the significance this thinly populated nation places on its military alliance with the faraway United States.</p>
        <p>But Secretary Powell and Mr. Rumsfeld were upstaged by something even more important to this sports-obsessed country. The Australian team at the world swimming championships in Japan won 13 gold medals and smashed world records. Huge front-page photographs of the swimmers relegated the American visitors to the inside pages.</p>
        <p>A Land of Yeasayers</p>
        <p>Why all the attention to Australia? Especially by Mr. Rumsfeld, who does not care to travel much and who dashed out here on a small jet and stayed for little more than 24 hours before returning to Washington. While the Bush administration is criticized in Europe and Asia for its missile defense policy and its rejection of the Kyoto protocol on global warming, the conservative Australian government of Prime Minister John Howard agrees wholeheartedly with the White House on both.</p>
        <p>The two sides found another mutual interest: renewing ties with the Indonesian military. Legislation tying American military assistance to Indonesia to the its army's human rights record limits what the United States can do. But American officials encouraged Australia, which has similar concerns, to take the lead in upgrading contacts. ''I find the position of the United States, with respect to Indonesia, is, as far as I can tell, identical to that of Australia,'' Mr. Rumsfeld said.</p>
        <p>American aides who accompanied Mr. Rumsfeld and Secretary Powell, find themselves hectored in other parts of the world. They seemed to appreciate being appreciated.</p>
        <p>The Australians do disagree over proposals for enforcing the 1972 biological weapons convention, which the Bush administration rejects as flawed. Foreign Minister Alexander Downer said that having an enforcement mechanism, though imperfect, was preferable to none at all. But the Australians, not wanting to sour the atmosphere, refrained from making a big deal of the issue.</p>
        <p>Dinner With Real People</p>
        <p>The day in Canberra was the last leg of an odyssey that took Secretary Powell to four Asian countries in six days. In Beijing, his hosts let him off the hook on a formal dinner, which the secretary always tries to avoid. Instead, he went out to one of the large eating halls where ordinary Chinese take their families, accompanied the new American ambassador, Clark T. Randt. Asked what the reaction was when he entered, Secretary Powell said people glanced up and then went back to their noodles.</p>
        <p>The last meal of the trip was tonight at the prime minister's lodge.  Mr. Downer arranged a special chariot. A crimson 1980 Volvo 262 awaited the secretary as he walked out his hotel door. He is passionate about Volvos -- his hobby is fixing up old models -- and he immediately lifted the hood to inspect the engine. He then got in the driver's seat -- on the right hand side -- and chugged off, proclaiming the car the ''most magnificent Volvo ever made.''</p>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
