<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Before &amp; After; Awakening to Terror, and Asking the World for Help</title>
    <meta content="16KAHN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/16/weekinreview/16KAHN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1325519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D81F38F935A2575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Before &amp; After; Awakening to Terror, and Asking the World for Help</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Awakening to Terror, and Asking the World for Help</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fight against terrorism will likely require global cooperation of sort that Bush administration has previously dismissed, and administration may have to temper its unilateral instincts on many issues as a result; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OF all the offers of support that Americans received last week from friends and acquaintances abroad, one of the most remarkable came from the editors of Le Monde, the French daily newspaper often noted for wariness of the United States. ''We are all Americans,'' the paper declared in a banner headline.</p>
        <p>That sentiment may last only as long as the mourning for the victims of the terrorist attacks, or until the United States strikes back at those responsible. But just as World War II and the cold war drew the United States out of isolationism, and Iraq's invasion of Kuwait prompted the Americans to assemble an international alliance to repel it, the fight against terrorism seems likely to require global cooperation of a sort that the Bush administration previously dismissed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fight against terrorism seems likely to require global cooperation of a sort that the Bush administration previously dismissed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OF all the offers of support that Americans received last week from friends and acquaintances abroad, one of the most remarkable came from the editors of Le Monde, the French daily newspaper often noted for wariness of the United States. ''We are all Americans,'' the paper declared in a banner headline.</p>
        <p>That sentiment may last only as long as the mourning for the victims of the terrorist attacks, or until the United States strikes back at those responsible. But just as World War II and the cold war drew the United States out of isolationism, and Iraq's invasion of Kuwait prompted the Americans to assemble an international alliance to repel it, the fight against terrorism seems likely to require global cooperation of a sort that the Bush administration previously dismissed.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to imagine President Bush being in a position to plausibly declare victory against terrorism if a crisis of confidence in the United States and Europe forces already tottering economies into a deep recession, for example. Similarly, the administration may find it hard to deny aid to the wobbly economies of potentially important allies in the battle against terrorism, like Indonesia, the largest Muslim nation.</p>
        <p>''The terrorists obviously understood the American influence in the world is multidimensional,'' said Robert B. Zoellick, the United States trade representative. ''They targeted the Pentagon, symbolic of our military might. But they also targeted our economic power when they hit the World Trade Center. We have to respond in a multidimensional way.</p>
        <p>''This is a new enemy, characterized by intolerance and closed societies,'' Mr. Zoellick said. ''We are marked by openness, and our response to this should be a fresh breath of tolerance around the world.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration was developing a reputation for being less international than parochial. President Bush dropped out of at least six international agreements, including accords intended to ban germ warfare and control global warming. Treasury Secretary Paul H. O'Neill emphasized that the United States had a skeptical attitude about coordinating currency policy with allies or arranging financial bailouts for developing countries that mismanaged their economies or squandered previous aid packages from the West.</p>
        <p>That approach could change in coming weeks. Wealthy countries will meet in Washington later this month to consider ways of bolstering the global economy, and coordinated interest rate cuts are already under discussion, administration officials said. Mr. O'Neill, who reluctantly backed an International Monetary Fund rescue package for Argentina last month, will face fresh pressure to help that country, as well as Brazil and Turkey, a strategic ally that straddles Europe and the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The administration last week encouraged Megawati Sukarnoputri, Indonesia's new president, to proceed with a planned eight-day visit to the United States even though her visit will come before travel or security arrangements have returned to normal. Administration officials said they were also preparing to offer her some economic concessions.</p>
        <p>THE fact that Indonesia has a shaky democracy, a fragile, quasi-capitalist economy and regional rebellions led by Islamic militants has suddenly made it a top foreign-policy priority.</p>
        <p>''Now that the Bush administration sees that it needs the rest of the world, it will have to temper its unilateral instincts on many issues,'' said C. Fred Bergsten, head of the Institute for International Economics in Washington.</p>
        <p>Military threats tend to compel economic cooperation. The advent of the cold war prompted Western nations to liberalize trade rules and to found the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund, lending agencies that sought to rebuild Europe. The Persian Gulf war prompted another flurry of international diplomacy that quickly spilled over into the economic realm. Shortly after the victory against Iraq, the United States, Japan and European nations completed the negotiations that led to the creation of the World Trade Organization. At the same time, the United States sealed a free-trade agreement with Canada and Mexico.</p>
        <p>The war against terrorism could require even more intermingling of political, military and economic interests. Terrorism is borderless and the enemy is both omnipresent and evanescent. To fight it, the United States will need the goodwill of its allies to arrange overflight and basing rights for the military, and it will rely heavily on other nations' intelligence services. Which means that the United States may have to reciprocate.</p>
        <p>France, Germany and even Switzerland have been more eager than the United States to force banks to monitor international money transfers by criminals, for example. But Washington's attitude seems likely to change as it tries to stop terrorists from financing their international network.</p>
        <p>THEN, too, only economic engagement will transform the environment in which terrorists thrive, analysts say. Osama bin Laden and others prefer to live where people are poor and governments have failed, Afghanistan most notably. Military action may take out individual terrorists, but won't alter the conditions that help to produce them.</p>
        <p>''I don't see how you can really tackle the problem without considering the reaction in the Arab street,'' said Robert Hormats, a managing director of the investment firm Goldman Sachs. ''This is a war you've got to fight on the economic front.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
