<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DB1630F932A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>NATO Would Send Troops To Aid a Macedonia Accord  NATO is planning to send a force of up to 3,000 mainly European troops to Macedonia to disarm ethnic Albanian rebels if a political settlement is reached to end the insurgency. The United States is likely to provide transport, intelligence and other forms of support, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deadlocked talks on ending the conflict were suspended, and President Boris Trajkovski sought international help in breaking the impasse.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>NATO Would Send Troops To Aid a Macedonia Accord  NATO is planning to send a force of up to 3,000 mainly European troops to Macedonia to disarm ethnic Albanian rebels if a political settlement is reached to end the insurgency. The United States is likely to provide transport, intelligence and other forms of support, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deadlocked talks on ending the conflict were suspended, and President Boris Trajkovski sought international help in breaking the impasse.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>American Found Guilty in Peru  Lori Berenson, a 31-year-old New Yorker held more than five years in Peruvian prisons on terror charges, was convicted by a civilian court in Lima and sentenced to 20 years in prison for collaborating in a foiled plot to take lawmakers hostage.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Powell Mideast Trip Planned  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell will travel to the Mideast next week to help shore up the cease-fire and try to push the Israelis and Palestinians on a path toward political talks.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Israel authorized plans for military operations against the Palestinian Authority, but officials said they would be held in abeyance to give the cease-fire plan more time.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Coke Joins Africa AIDS Fight  Coca-Cola, the largest employer in Africa, said it would use its advertising and distribution resources to combat AIDS on the continent.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Refugee Chief Scolds Nations  On the first World Refugees' Day, the United Nations high commissioner for refugees criticized wealthy West European countries and Australia for increasingly closing their borders to the world's 21 million refugees.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Self-Promotion in Pakistan  General Pervez Musharraf named himself president and head of state, 20 months after toppling the civilian government and taking the misleadingly modest title chief executive.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-22</p>
        <p>Bush's Standing Declines In Public's Eye, Poll Finds  President Bush's approval rating has dropped 7 percentage points since March, to 53 percent, despite his first overseas trip as president and his successful push for a big tax cut. The poll found uneasiness in the public's perception of Mr. Bush's trustworthiness, domestic policies and ability to handle foreign affairs and crises.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>White House Business  The White House defended several recent private meetings with corporate executives who have important issues before the government, as scores of other executives from the Business Roundtable came to see President Bush, Vice President Dick Cheney and other top officials.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>House G.O.P. Patients' Bill  House Republican leaders, fearing defections on the issue of patients' rights, have drafted a bill that goes further than President Bush would like in allowing consumers to sue H.M.O.'s and other insurers.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>The Bush administration is pressing House Republicans to reinstate hundreds of millions of dollars they cut from politically sensitive disaster relief projects.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Subjected to Review  Attorney General John Ashcroft announced a wide-ranging review of the F.B.I. as the Senate Judiciary Committee held the first in a series of hearings into managerial and investigative lapses at the agency.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>U.S. Dropping Bear Program  The Interior Department said it was abandoning a Clinton administration plan to reintroduce grizzly bears, a threatened species, into the isolated wilds of Idaho and Montana.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Governor Assails Regulators  Gov. Gray Davis of California, testifying in Congress, accused federal regulators of allowing power companies to ''bilk our state'' of billions.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Missing Intern Case  The District of Columbia police have asked Representative Gary Condit for a second interview about his relationship with a missing 24-year-old woman, Chandra Levy.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>City Board Gives Landlords Bigger Rent Increases  The New York City Rent Guidelines Board reversed itself by imposing increases one percentage point higher than it proposed a month ago: 4 percent for one-year lease renewals and 6 percent for two-year leases.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Insurers Threaten to Leave  American International said it had filed documents requesting approval to close shop in New Jersey, where the company insures about 4 percent of the 4.8 million vehicles in the state. Liberty Mutual, with 11 percent of the state's business, said it too was looking to pull out. State Farm, which has 17 percent of the state market, announced a similar intention last week. The companies cite regulatory issues, inadequate rates and slow progress on cost-saving measures enacted in 1998.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Republican Primary Battle  Bob Franks called Bret D. Schundler, his rival for the Republican gubernatorial nomination in New Jersey, an ''extremist'' whose ''radical'' stands against abortion rights and gun control would make him unelectable in November. A poll gave Mr. Schundler a wide lead over Mr. Franks.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Manhattan Alligator Hunt  Officials are trying to track down an alligator sighted in Central Park by several people, and figure out what to do with it once they catch it.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>A Poet Laureate From CUNY  Billy Collins, distinguished professor of English at Lehman College in the Bronx, was chosen to be the next poet laureate of the United States.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Bolstering Ethanol Program  A report prepared for Congress by the Bush administration recommends continuing federal incentives for ethanol-fueled vehicles, despite finding that the program has failed to reduce gasoline consumption or substantially increase the use of alternative fuels and has contributed to global warming.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Software Maker Is Target  A billionaire Texan, Sam Wyly, plans to begin a proxy fight today to take control of Computer Associates.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Greenspan's Plea to Lenders  Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, said more businesses have had trouble repaying loans as the economy has slowed, but he urged lenders not to cut credit to healthy borrowers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Merger-busting in Europe; disturbing numbers for Mr. Bush; South Africa's failure on AIDS.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
