<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tree Project Helps the Genes of Champions Live On</title>
    <meta content="10TREE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/10/science/10TREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1308145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Champion Tree Project</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Tree Trust</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4D71038F933A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tree Project Helps the Genes of Champions Live On</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Tree Project Helps the Genes of Champions Live On</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>BIG TIMBER, Mont.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Handful of enthusiasts are searching out largest tree of each species and taking cutting of new growth to make copies for study; have replicated 52 of 827 living giants and are planting offspring in what they call 'archival living libraries'; have planted over 20,000 offspring; work is part of Champion Tree Project, begun in 1996 with aid from National Tree Trust; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a bald eagle wheels overhead against a crystalline blue sky, Martin Flanagan walks toward a grove of towering cottonwood trees beside the Yellowstone River, which is the color of chocolate milk as the spring runoff rushes past.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Flanagan leaves the glaring sun of the prairie and enters the shady grove, his eyes search for a specific tree. As he reaches a narrow-leaf cottonwood, a towering giant, he cranes his neck to look at the top. ''This is the one I plan to nominate for state champ,'' he says, spanking the bark with his hand. ''It's a beauty, isn't it?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new environmental program is trying to ensure the survival of some of the nation's finest trees in the old-growth forests</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a bald eagle wheels overhead against a crystalline blue sky, Martin Flanagan walks toward a grove of towering cottonwood trees beside the Yellowstone River, which is the color of chocolate milk as the spring runoff rushes past.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Flanagan leaves the glaring sun of the prairie and enters the shady grove, his eyes search for a specific tree. As he reaches a narrow-leaf cottonwood, a towering giant, he cranes his neck to look at the top. ''This is the one I plan to nominate for state champ,'' he says, spanking the bark with his hand. ''It's a beauty, isn't it?''</p>
        <p>When Europeans first came to North America, one of the largest primeval forests in the world covered much of the continent. Experts say a squirrel could have traveled  from the Atlantic coast to the Mississippi River without touching the ground. But only about 3 percent of America's native old-growth forest remains, and many of the trees they hold are those that were not big enough to attract a logger's eye. The result is a generation of trees that barely resemble the native forests that once blanketed the country.</p>
        <p>That makes some scientists suspect that the surviving forests have lost much of their genetic quality, the molecular muscle that made them dominate the landscape. When the loggers swept through, these scientists say, only poor specimens were left to reproduce. Other researchers wonder what -- whether environmental factors or just plain luck -- may explain a good part of the supertrees' success.</p>
        <p>To answer those questions, the mightiest trees of their types, or genetically identical offspring, must be preserved for study, and that is what is being done by a handful of enthusiasts, including Mr. Flanagan and David Milarch, a nurseryman from Copemish, Mich. They are searching out the largest tree of each species and taking cuttings of new growth to make copies -- genetic clones -- of the giants. With tissue culture and grafting, they have replicated 52 of the 827 living giants and are planting the offspring in what they call ''archival living libraries.'' More than 20,000 offspring have been planted.</p>
        <p>The work is part of the Champion Tree Project, which began in 1996 with financial help from the National Tree Trust, a nonprofit group in Washington.</p>
        <p>''These big trees are the last links to the boreal forests,'' Mr. Milarch, president of the Champion Tree Project, said.</p>
        <p>State and federal agencies and private organizations have been keeping track of the largest trees in each state for some time. The largest effort is the National Register of Big Trees, run by American Forests, a 125-year-old nonprofit group based in Washington. But the Champion Tree Project takes things a step further by perpetuating the largest trees.</p>
        <p>The supertrees' genetic legacy is being preserved in five main tree libraries in different climates. The repositories are at Arlington National Cemetery; the gardens of George Washington's Virginia home, Mount Vernon; the Florida Botanical Gardens, near Tampa; the Oregon Botanical Gardens, in Salem; and the Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village, in Michigan.</p>
        <p>Eventually the Champion Tree  Project hopes to replicate enough exemplary trees for a nationwide reforestation project. The offspring of the native trees, should they prove  genetically superior, could be especially valuable in urban settings, where the average tree lives just 7 to 10 years. But things like soil conditions, moisture and other environmental factors can also affect the success of the trees.</p>
        <p>But it remains to be seen whether  superior genetics -- characteristics like insect or drought resistance or fast growth -- is behind the longevity of the giant trees or whether something else is responsible.</p>
        <p>''Nobody has done any research to investigate the genetics of these trees,'' said Dr. John C. Alleyne, a plant geneticist at the Florida Botanical Gardens, who has begun that work. But the results of that research are 5 to 10 years away, Dr. Alleyne said.</p>
        <p>''The genetics might be responsible,'' he said, ''and there's every reason to believe it is, but chance could be the reason they survived. That's why we need to get them into a library and studied.''</p>
        <p>Three measurements determine a champion. Each tree measured gets a point for each foot of height, a point for each four feet of crown spread and a point for each inch of circumference, measured at chest height.  Champions are often dethroned and  new ones proclaimed, as larger trees are found and old ones die.</p>
        <p>A related program is run by American Forests, which replicates and sells historic trees from famous properties like President Dwight D. Eisenhower's home in Abilene, Kan., and Elvis Presley's home, Graceland, in Memphis. Officials of American Forests say they are peeved that the Champion Tree Project is using its list to raise money. ''They basically reinvented our program,'' said Dr. Deborah Gangloff, the American Forests executive director.</p>
        <p>The Champion Tree Project bases its search on the National Register of Big Trees, which American Forests has kept since 1940, when foresters grew alarmed at the number of trees being rapidly cut because of demand for wood in the war years. The list was established and updated by a cadre of dedicated tree hunters, who fan out across the landscape competing to find the largest trees so they can be preserved.</p>
        <p>Some experts, including those at American Forests, say claims that champion trees possess a genetic superiority are misleading.</p>
        <p>''From an emotional standpoint,'' said Dr. Roger Funk, a plant physiologist who is head of research at the Davey Tree Expert Company in Kent, Ohio, which works with American Forests, ''there is interest in perpetuating an organism with superior qualities.'' But from a scientific standpoint, Dr. Funk said, ''it's very speculative.''</p>
        <p>''You can move an individual as little as 20 feet,'' he said, ''and have different characteristics.''</p>
        <p>But to Dr. Frank Gouin, a plant physiologist who cloned the Wye Oak, a national champion in Wye Mills, Md., for the Champion Tree Project, it makes sense.</p>
        <p>''A lot of white oaks get blight, but I have never seen a blight on this tree,'' Dr. Gouin said. ''These trees are like people who have smoked all their lives and drank all their lives and are still kicking. Let's study them.'' Dr. Gouin is the retired chairman of the horticulture department  at the University of Maryland.</p>
        <p>Compared with the genetics of  crops, the genetics of trees has not been well researched. ''In plants it's known which genes confer which traits,'' said Dr. Denny Townsend, a research geneticist at the National Arboretum. So few genes have been cataloged in trees, he said, that the only way to tell whether one tree is better than another is ''to propagate them and compare traits, and that can take years.''</p>
        <p>Trees taken from national champion cuttings have been grown for about four years. So far, there is little to distinguish them from other trees, nursery experts say.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing that jumps out that's different about them,'' said Keith Warren, director of product development at J. Frank Schmidt &amp; Son nursery in Boring, Ore., which is  growing green ash and Norway maple commercially from champion stock. ''But you are not going to be a national champion if you are below average. I suspect it's above-average genetics with quite a bit of luck.''</p>
        <p>Preservation efforts, supporters say, are a race against time, for national champions are dying. There were 67 national champions in Michigan when the Champion Tree Project was conceived; there are now 51. Such trees are lost to wind,  age, ice storms and, especially, development. Climate change and pollution may also be taking a toll.</p>
        <p>In at least one case, a champion has filled a need. Terry Mock, executive director of the Champion Tree Project, took cuttings from a national champion silver buttonwood a year before it was destroyed in a hurricane on a golf course in Key West, Fla. Two years later the project presented Key West with clones of the champion to replant.</p>
        <p>Because America's forests have been cut so many times, most of the national champions are found in urban areas.</p>
        <p>''There are 13 national champions in inner-city Detroit,'' Mr. Milarch said. ''The national champion white ash is in Palisades, N.Y., in front of Tony's Steak and Lobster House.''</p>
        <p>All states have at least one champion tree, though Florida has the most, 170. The champions range in age from 300 to 3,500 years old.</p>
        <p>Expanding America's urban forests, Mr. Mock said, is critical to improving urban environments.  Trees filter rain, for example, slowing its fall. In doing so, the ground better absorbs the water. Without trees, much of the rain runs off into storm sewers and does not recharge aquifers.</p>
        <p>The United States Forest Service supports the Champion Tree Project for such reasons. It points to a 1999 Forest Service study showing that in California's San Joaquin Valley, for example, a single large London plane tree in a front yard saved $29 in summer air-conditioning costs, absorbed 10 pounds of air pollutants annually, intercepted 750 gallons of rainfall in the crown, cleaned 330 pounds of carbon dioxide from the air and added 1 percent to the sale price of the house.</p>
        <p>But the emotional reasons for the Champion Tree Project may be as valid as the scientific aims. People are fascinated by big trees.</p>
        <p>''The champions are what the old-growth forest used to look like,'' Mr. Mock said. ''What people alive on the planet see today are bushes compared to what trees used to look like.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
