<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="30OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/30/science/30OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20011031T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaelogy and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Egyptian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mummies and Mummification</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fugu (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dna (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">nenana (alaska)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">university of bristol</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Egyptian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Egyptian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Stanford University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDB1730F933A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gamblers Aid Science</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stanford University scientists looking for historical data on climate change find Nenana, Alaska, has measured for lottery held since 1917 precise minute ice in local river breaks up each spring; University of Bristol study of organic compounds present in Egyptian mummies finds embalmers often used complex mixture of different plant oils, resins and fats, with recipe changing over time; consortium reports sequencing of genome of fugu, also known as Japanese pufferfish; fugu and humans have similar complement of genes, but fugu DNA is much more concise; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gamblers Aid Science</p>
        <p>They say a good man is hard to find; good data fall into the same category. Since good science needs good data, scientists will take it wherever they can find it. It can be found in some odd places.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week's column includes items on gambling on global warming, the well-dressed mummy and mapping a delicacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gamblers Aid Science</p>
        <p>They say a good man is hard to find; good data fall into the same category. Since good science needs good data, scientists will take it wherever they can find it. It can be found in some odd places.</p>
        <p>Two scientists at Stanford University, for example, looking for historical data on climate change, found it in a very odd place: a small town in Alaska, in the form of a gambling contest.</p>
        <p>Each spring since 1917, the village of Nenana, 50 miles west of Fairbanks, has been home to the Nenana Ice Classic. It is a lottery of sorts, with residents and thousands of others betting on the precise minute the ice in the local river, the Tanana, will break up.</p>
        <p>A tall wooden tripod is set up on the frozen river and attached by wire to a switch on a clock on the river bank. When the tripod moves far enough to turn the clock off, the contest is over and cash prizes are handed out. This year's jackpot of more than $300,000 was divided among eight winners, who guessed the clock would stop at precisely 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>The Stanford researchers realized that the annual records of the time of breakup might reflect atmospheric temperature trends. They had no doubts about the accuracy of the data, they wrote in describing their research in the journal Science, ''as the high stakes lead to constant vigilance at the time of breakup.''</p>
        <p>The researchers compared the time of ice breakup with weather records from Nenana and Fairbanks and found that the time correlated well with temperature change over the decades. On average, the river breaks up five and a half days later nowadays than it did back in 1917.</p>
        <p>The Mummy's Recipe</p>
        <p>Fashion note for trick or treaters: Those planning on dressing up as mummies tomorrow night might care to add a touch of pine resin for that authentic, just-from-the-sarcophagus look.</p>
        <p>In perhaps the most comprehensive, and certainly the least destructive, study of ancient embalming methods ever conducted, two scientists from the University of Bristol in England have analyzed the organic compounds present in 13 Egyptian mummies of known provenance, dating from about 1900 B.C. to A.D. 400.</p>
        <p>The study used gas chromatography and mass spectrometry for analysis, requiring extremely small tissue samples (on the order of a tenth of a milligram), essentially sparing the mummies any damage. In the past, many tests on mummies had involved unwrapping them.</p>
        <p>The results confirmed some of what scientists had already known about mummification -- that many embalmers used beeswax, for example. But it also showed that the process was often more complex, with a mixture of different plant oils, resins and fats used. The recipe also changed over time, perhaps as some of the materials became more or less available. The researchers also found no evidence that petroleum-derived bituminous compounds were used, as has often been speculated.</p>
        <p>New Role for Fugu</p>
        <p>Fugu, also known as Japanese pufferfish, is an expensive and occasionally deadly delicacy. Diners in Japan pay hundreds of dollars for a fugu meal, but unless the fish is expertly prepared and a certain neurotoxin-containing portion removed, it may be a last meal as well.</p>
        <p>But now fugu has a new reputation: as an important cog in the effort to understand the human genome. A consortium including institutions in the United States, Singapore and Britain announced the sequencing of the fugu genome last week.</p>
        <p>Fugu and humans have similar complements of genes, but fugu DNA is much more concise, composed of about 365 million nucleotide pairs, or one-eighth of the 3 billion pairs in the human genome. With less DNA to sift through, scientists hope to be able to find genes and other important DNA sequences in fugu fairly easily, and then apply what they've learned to hunt down genes in human DNA.</p>
        <p>Observatory  Correction:  October 31, 2001, Wednesday  A brief report in the Observatory column of Science Times yesterday  about a climate-change study that used data from an annual contest to predict the time a frozen river in Alaska will break up misstated the finding. On average, the researchers found, the river breaks up five and a half days earlier than it did 80 years ago, not five and a half days later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 31, 2001, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A brief report in the Observatory column of Science Times yesterday  about a climate-change study that used data from an annual contest to predict the time a frozen river in Alaska will break up misstated the finding. On average, the researchers found, the river breaks up five and a half days earlier than it did 80 years ago, not five and a half days later.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
