<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Booming Car Sales, but at a Price</title>
    <meta content="24PLAC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/24/business/24PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1336600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Market Place"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">White, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3D91431F937A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Booming Car Sales, but at a Price</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Booming Car Sales, but at a Price</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Oct. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big Three automakers' interest-free financing plans have evolved into price war that is great news for car buyers and car deals but increasingly costly for automakers; some critics and environmental groups have also criticized domestic automakers for wrapping up their new discounts in patriotic ad campaigns at time when nation's dependence on Middle East oil is subject of new debate; Big Three's total vehicles sales in October are expected to top annual pace of 19 million, second only to record 21.2 million sales pace set in August 1986; graph; photos (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Corporate earnings are plummeting, unemployment is rising, consumer confidence is shaky, the country is at a war footing at home and abroad. Yet auto sales have rarely been better.</p>
        <p>Come again?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A forecast from General Motors predicts October will be the second-biggest month ever for overall auto sales in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Corporate earnings are plummeting, unemployment is rising, consumer confidence is shaky, the country is at a war footing at home and abroad. Yet auto sales have rarely been better.</p>
        <p>Come again?</p>
        <p>A forecast from General Motors predicts October will be the second-biggest month ever for overall auto sales in the United States, and many analysts have offered similar outlooks. But if the industry is on pace for one of its best sales months, the question is how it happened and how much it will all cost, not only in financial losses now but also in lost sales down the road.</p>
        <p>In reality, the Big Three's interest-free financing plans, offered to revive sales after the Sept. 11 attacks, have evolved into a price war that is great news for car buyers and car dealers but increasingly costly for the automakers footing the bill. Some critics and environmental groups have also criticized domestic automakers for wrapping up their new discounts in patriotic ad campaigns at a time when the nation's dependence on the Middle East's oil is the subject of renewed debate.</p>
        <p>But for car sellers -- like those sales reps and dealers who make their living  along a long stretch of showrooms and lots on Central Avenue in Toledo, Ohio -- there have been few better months than October.</p>
        <p>''Zero percent is just bringing lots of people in, creating lots of interest,'' George Ballas, founder of George Ballas Buick GMC, said in an interview this week at his dealership. There is a yard-high ''0% A.P.R.'' banner in the showroom's window and American flags fluttering from car hoods on the lot. On a typical month, Mr. Ballas, who has been a G.M. dealer for more than three decades, said he might sell 125 new G.M. cars and trucks. Last month, sales were just short of 100. This month, he thinks he can sell 150 new vehicles.</p>
        <p>Down the road, Ross Yuse, who has been a salesman for 15 years at Jim White Toyota, extended his arm outward and tallied the white, red and green cars before him. Toyota Motor has also offered zero-interest financing on some of its vehicles.</p>
        <p>''We're out of cars,'' he said. ''We have four Corolla's and four Camry's. We usually like to carry 60 Camry's and 20 Corolla's.''</p>
        <p>But Mike Knierim, a previous Corolla owner, did not let that stand in the way. He was set on buying another Toyota. ''You can't go wrong with zero percent interest,'' he said. ''Chevy, Ford or Toyota -- it's a deal.''</p>
        <p>G.M. led the wave of zero percent offers, which were ignited in part by the visit of Commerce Secretary Donald L. Evans and Labor Secretary Elaine L. Chao to Detroit shortly after the attacks. The Bush administration's focus was on restarting economic activity and it urged the industry to do what it could.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the meeting, G.M. introduced its Keep America Rolling interest-free financing with a splashy ad campaign. The subtext was clear: Do your part to fight terrorism by buying American vehicles.</p>
        <p>But when G.M. moved recently to extend its program past the end of the month and through at least Nov. 18, it was a bid to sustain its recent glimmer of momentum in recapturing market share. The news, however, was not well received by Ford Motor or Chrysler, whose financial positions appear to many analysts to be worse than that of General Motors. Chrysler is a unit of DaimlerChrysler.</p>
        <p>G.M. sees the discounts, coupled with a fresh lineup of sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks, as a chance to stem years of market share declines. The company needs to maintain its scale, if for no other reason than to keep up with its enormous legacy costs -- G.M. has about 2.5 retirees per worker whose benefits and pensions it must continue to support. On the other hand, such incentives only increase its red ink. Last week, the company reported a net loss of $368 million for the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Still, G.M. is gaining a small amount of market share while Ford and Chrysler, which matched G.M.'s zero percent financing offers, continue to lose ground and money. Top executives of both companies have expressed concern recently that the offers are pulling sales from the future and hurting profits now.</p>
        <p>''While programs like this make the equation work for our customers, it is unsustainable for us in the longer term,'' Jacques Nasser, chief executive of Ford, wrote in a memo to employees last Friday. ''Even without zero percent financing, our marketing costs are still far too high.''</p>
        <p>Martin Inglis, Ford's chief financial officer, said last week that incentives had risen from 11 percent of the company's revenue last year to 16 percent this year. Each percentage point increase, he said, deducts about $1 billion from the company's pretax profits.</p>
        <p>In recent forecasts, G.M. predicted October's seasonally adjusted annual sales rate would come in above 19 million. That would rank it right behind the record 21.2 million sales pace the industry achieved in September 1986, according to Ward's AutoInfoBank, a data service in Southfield, Mich. John Casesa, an analyst at Merrill Lynch, projects a rate of 20.2 million vehicles.</p>
        <p>But then what? Ending a sale is harder than starting one. When G.M. gave its October forecast, it also lowered its forecast for total 2002 sales of 15 million to 15.5 million units, which would be considered a mediocre year. Mr. Casesa sees 2002 sales dropping to an even worse rate of 14.6 million vehicles.</p>
        <p>The falloff, Mr. Casesa said, is ''going to lead to very cautious production schedules in the first quarter.''</p>
        <p>''These companies,'' he added, ''are going to go from working on overtime to working half-shifts.''</p>
        <p>''That will cause a retrenching in their businesses,'' he said, ''and that will ripple through the supply chain.''</p>
        <p>From some perspectives, increasing sales to near record levels at a time of turmoil is distasteful, especially when the Big Three are increasingly dependent on sport utility vehicles and trucks. Take a recent cartoon in the New Republic magazine, which depicted a man putting an ''End our dependence on Arab oil!'' bumper sticker on a smoke-belching vehicle so enormous his head reached only the top of the wheel.</p>
        <p>''Detroit is treating this tragedy as a chance to pad their profits by pushing gas guzzlers,'' said Daniel F. Becker, director of the global warming and energy program for the Sierra Club. ''Real patriotism means showing responsibility by decreasing our oil dependency by producing more fuel-efficient cars.''</p>
        <p>For the Big Three, padding profits is not the issue. Stemming losses is.</p>
        <p>And holding off the resurgent foreign automakers. ''All three of the Big Three are between a rock and a hard place,'' said Stephen J. Girsky, an auto analyst at Morgan Stanley. ''The competition is not each other, but the competition is the outside parties.''</p>
        <p>A recent Morgan Stanley report pointed to Ford and G.M.'s huge financing operations as areas of concern, for several reasons. First, the residual value of leased vehicles continues to decline as sales of new cars, and leases, increase. That influx of sales reduces the value of vehicles coming off leases that are reclaimed by Ford and G.M.</p>
        <p>Second, recent downgrades of the credit of Ford and G.M. make their loans to customers more expensive. Ford and G.M. raise money to make those loans with big bond offerings and their borrowing rates, while still quite low, will become less attractive for the companies at a time when they are charging customers less, and in many cases, nothing, for loans. Third, the worsening economy has caused the rate of customers' defaulting on auto loans to increase.</p>
        <p>For dealers and buyers, this is not their problem. At least not yet.</p>
        <p>''It's absolutely spectacular,'' said Michael Maroone, president of AutoNation, which operates dealerships in 17 states, referring to the zero percent deals.</p>
        <p>''It's an absolute windfall for the dealers,'' he said. ''The business climate right now is fantastic.''</p>
        <p>For some Americans shopping for a new car, there is little doubt that heart-felt patriotism is one of the main reasons they are buying now.</p>
        <p>''I had one little old gal tell me that was the only reason she was buying a car,'' said Jim Nimphie, a vice president of George Ballas Buick GMC.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ballas believes the improving sales have less to do with patriotism and more to do with low prices and free money. With the new offers, he said, ''you could save roughly $4,500 on a $20,000 car.''</p>
        <p>Market Place</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
