<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1312561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DB153DF934A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Forced Out, Indonesia Chief Heads to U.S. for Checkup  Abdurrahman Wahid, 61, exhausted and bitter, ended his occupation of the presidential palace in Jakarta and left Indonesia for a medical checkup in the United States. Hamza Haz, leader of a Muslim party, was elected vice president by lawmakers. In 1999, he opposed the candidacy of Megawati Sukarnoputri, the new president, partly on the ground that a woman should not be president.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Jailed Scholar Returns to U.S.  Gao Zhan, a Chinese citizen with permanent residency in the United States, returned to the United States after five months in a Beijing jail. Two days earlier, she was convicted of spying for Taiwan and sentenced to 10 years in prison. Her release, which was sought by the United States, came two days before Secretary of State Colin L. Powell was to arrive in Beijing.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Forced Out, Indonesia Chief Heads to U.S. for Checkup  Abdurrahman Wahid, 61, exhausted and bitter, ended his occupation of the presidential palace in Jakarta and left Indonesia for a medical checkup in the United States. Hamza Haz, leader of a Muslim party, was elected vice president by lawmakers. In 1999, he opposed the candidacy of Megawati Sukarnoputri, the new president, partly on the ground that a woman should not be president.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Jailed Scholar Returns to U.S.  Gao Zhan, a Chinese citizen with permanent residency in the United States, returned to the United States after five months in a Beijing jail. Two days earlier, she was convicted of spying for Taiwan and sentenced to 10 years in prison. Her release, which was sought by the United States, came two days before Secretary of State Colin L. Powell was to arrive in Beijing.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>A third person in the case, Qu Wei, remained in a Beijing jail, sharing a fate with more than a dozen people in similar trouble in China whose cases usually fall by the wayside even with high-profile diplomatic lobbying.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Plan Offered for Weapons Talks  The national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, offered President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia a blueprint for talks on building a new nuclear-weapons framework, a process that she cast as part of a broader plan for transforming the relationship between Washington and Moscow.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Macedonia Negotiations  Western diplomats who flew to Macedonia pressed all sides in the increasingly divided nation to stop fighting and start talking again.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Israeli Killed in West Bank  A 17-year-old Israeli was killed, presumably by Palestinian gunmen, as he drove with his father along a road just north of Jerusalem. The shooting came on a night studded with attacks on Israelis and followed Palestinian calls for revenge for an Islamic militant killed by the Israeli army on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>U.S. Warning to Iraq  President Bush declared that Saddam Hussein ''is still a menace'' and a Pentagon official warned that the United States reserved the right to respond at any time to Iraq's attempt this week to shoot down a U-2 surveillance plane with a surface-to-air missile.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17</p>
        <p>Senate Favors Safety Rules For Trucks From Mexico  The Senate, rejecting pressure by the White House and Mexico's government, voted overwhelmingly to support efforts to impose safety standards on Mexican trucks seeking access to United States roads.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Flexibility on Immigrant Status  President Bush raised the possibility that millions of illegal immigrants from countries besides Mexico might be able to earn permanent legal status over time.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Edging Toward Compromise  President Bush offered new concessions on Congressional legislation to define patients' rights, but Democrats said they were not enough.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>President Bush indicated to two senators a willingness to rethink legislation exempting religious groups from state and city anti-bias laws.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Bill to Curb Attacks on Gays  The Senate Judiciary Committee voted, 12 to 7, to make hate attacks on gays a federal crime and to help finance local law enforcement agencies' prosecution of such offenses.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Defending Climate Stance  The head of the E.P.A., Christie Whitman, testifying in the Senate, defended the administration's go-slow approach in offering an alternative to the Kyoto climate treaty, saying it would be premature to present a plan for carbon dioxide reductions until studies were completed.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Rethinking Mileage Prediction  A National Academy of Sciences panel was said to have toned down a report on automobile fuel economy, suggesting that big increases in gas mileage might be harder to achieve than a draft report had stated.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Pentagon Critic's Complaint  A leading critic of the missile shield testing program, Theodore A. Postol, has accused the Pentagon of trying to silence him and intimidate his employer, M.I.T, by investigating him for disseminating classified data.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Young Killer to Learn Sentence  A Florida judge said he would impose sentence today on Nathaniel Brazill, 14, who faces 25 years to life for murdering his teacher. The judge heard testimony yesterday.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>New No. 2 Editor at The Times  Gerald M. Boyd, a deputy managing editor of The New York Times for the last four years, will become managing editor in September.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Ferrer Would Seek Return Of Activist Government  Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx borough president, who is seeking the Democratic nomination for mayor, said in an interview that he would revive a tradition of activist government abandoned by Mayor Giuliani and lift up ''the other New York'' left out of the city's economic boom. He said he hoped to pay for most of his new programs with existing taxes, more state aid and the weeding out of fraud and abuse, but he did not rule out the possibility of a tax increase.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Questionable Endorsement  Many of the Hasidim photographed outside City Hall in a campaign appearance with Mark Green last week were from a smaller group at odds with the Satmar establishment, which is based in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. And some of those pictured live in Orange County, precluding their voting for Mr. Green for mayor.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Beach Restrictions Voided  The Connecticut Supreme Court said the residents-only policy for Greenwich's town beach violated the federal and state Constitutions on free speech and association grounds.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Stem Cells and Brain Disease  Biologists said they had found that human neural stem cells could become incorporated in a fetal monkey's brain and share in its development, suggesting a novel way of correcting inborn brain diseases.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-24; E25-34</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Board's Management Assailed  A state commission investigating possible mismanagement of New York City schools said school construction should be taken out of the hands of the Board of Education and assigned to ''professionals'' who answer directly to the mayor.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Robert O. Lowery  A career firefighter who became New York City's first black fire commissioner, in 1965, he was 85.</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12, 14</p>
        <p>No Resurgence in Ads Seen  New estimates indicate that advertising spending, which set a record last year at $243.7 billion and has not declined from one year to the next since 1991, will fall 2 percent to 3 percent from 2000.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Record Write-Off  JDS Uniphase, a leading maker of components for telecommunications networks, said it was writing down the value of companies it had acquired in two years of rapid growth by $44.8 billion. It was believed to be the largest loss in business history.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Computer Maker's Cutbacks  Hewlett-Packard, a bellwether of consumer spending, said that it would cut 6,000 jobs and that revenue for the quarter would be lower than expected, all because further deterioration of economic conditions.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>A New Chief for Xerox  Xerox said its president, Anne M. Mulcahy, 48, a 25-year employee, would become chief executive, effective Aug. 1, succeeding Paul A. Allaire, who will remain chairman until the end of the year.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>A Delicate Relationship  Ford created an office of the chairman and chief executive to be shared by its chief executive and president, Jacques A. Nasser, and its chairman, William Clay Ford Jr. The move is to increase Mr. Ford's formal role in decision making.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Stock Prices Rise  The Dow gained 49.96 points, to 10,455.63; the S.&amp; P. 500 rose 12.44 points, or 1.04 percent, to 1,202.93; and the Nasdaq jumped 38.64 points, or nearly 2 percent, to 2,022.96.</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: A biased Social Security report; budgeting that harms education; sharks in shallow water.</p>
        <p>Column: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E33  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E34  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
