<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0D71638F93AA35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bush Will Not Meet With Arafat at the U.N.  The national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, said President Bush would not meet with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, at the United Nations this weekend because Mr. Arafat did not appear serious about the war against terrorism.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Mexico Frees Prisoners  President Vicente Fox ordered the release of two rural ecologists who had been tortured by soldiers and jailed after leading a campaign to stop the destruction of forests in the Pacific coast state of Guerrero. Amnesty International has considered the men prisoners of conscience.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Bush Will Not Meet With Arafat at the U.N.  The national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, said President Bush would not meet with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, at the United Nations this weekend because Mr. Arafat did not appear serious about the war against terrorism.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Mexico Frees Prisoners  President Vicente Fox ordered the release of two rural ecologists who had been tortured by soldiers and jailed after leading a campaign to stop the destruction of forests in the Pacific coast state of Guerrero. Amnesty International has considered the men prisoners of conscience.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Argentina Fiscal Talks Falter  President Fernando de la Rúa and opposition governors failed to agree on curtailing spending, dealing him a setback just before he left for New York to seek emergency international help to avert a financial collapse.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Editor Arrested in Zimbabwe  Geoff Nyarota, the editor of the country's only privately owned daily newspaper, was arrested for the second time in less than three months, raising fear of a widening government crackdown on the opposition ahead of next year's elections.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>International Climate Talks  Negotiators from more than 160 countries haggled in Morocco over a few important details in an effort to complete a pioneering climate treaty, the Kyoto Protocol, intended to reduce heat-trapping greenhouse gases linked to global warming. The United States is on the sidelines, a result of President Bush's decision in March that the treaty would harm the economy and unfairly apply only to industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Deadly Storm in the Philippines  Officials said that a devastating storm ripping through the Philippines' central and southern regions might have killed as many as 350 people, most of them in an area known as Paradise Island.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-24</p>
        <p>Democratic Stimulus Plan Is Passed by Senate Panel  Democrats pushed their $66.4 billion economic recovery plan through the Senate Finance Committee, 11 to 10. The plan, which sets out their negotiating position on an issue dividing the two parties, expands programs to help the unemployed and offers a tax rebate for low-income people and tax breaks for some businesses.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Deal on Ballot Overhaul  House Republicans and Democrats reached agreement on a bill to overhaul the nation's election system.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Suicide Law Back in Force  A federal judge temporarily blocked Attorney General John Ashcroft's move this week to overturn Oregon's law allowing assisted suicide.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Oil Refinery Plan Blocked  The religious broadcaster Pat Robertson had his plan to turn crude oil into gasoline for charitable purposes stymied by a federal judge's order. The judge has sided with residents in Santa Fe Springs, Calif., who oppose restarting a refinery bought by Mr. Robertson in 1998 with $20 million from a charitable trust.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Drugs and After-School Activity  The Supreme Court agreed to decide whether public schools may require students to pass drug tests as a condition of participating in extracurricular activities.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>D1-13</p>
        <p>Bloomberg Reaches Out To Powerful Union Leaders  Mayor-elect Bloomberg met with leaders of two of the city's most powerful municipal unions, seeking to build ties with officials who will be important players in dealing with the city's mounting budget problems. The move also offered a sharp stylistic difference with the man he is succeeding, Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Questions on a SUNY Contract  State Comptroller H. Carl McCall released an audit citing improprieties in a SUNY contract with James M. Copeland, an architect who owns Hudson Design and who has close personal ties to Governor Pataki.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Baby's Death  The commissioner of the Administration for Children's Services, Nicholas Scoppetta, detailed the extensive case history of Sylena Herrnkind, 3, whose parents are accused of killing her. Mr. Scoppetta promised a top-to-bottom inquiry into how his agency had dealt with the family.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Kerik's Jarring Discovery  Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik, 46, said that in researching a memoir he learned that his mother, who abandoned him as a child, was a convicted prostitute who died in 1964 from a massive blow to the head. He suspects a pimp killed her.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>D12</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C12-13</p>
        <p>Rose Shapiro  President of the New York City Board of Education during the stormy times of the late 1960's, she was 97.</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-28; E29-42</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Fewer Choices for Workers  Thousands of employees are having to drop their health plans and choose new ones as companies cut back their rosters of H.M.O.'s and other managed care insurers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Slow Going in Early Trade Talks  International trade officials are still deadlocked on several core issues -- farm trade, antidumping rules and textiles -- on the agenda of global talks that begin today in Qatar.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Enron's Suitor Undeterred  Enron sliced more than half a billion dollars from its reported profits over the last five years, but its crosstown rival, Dynegy, still appeared willing to acquire Enron, executives said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bid to Avert Europe Recession  The European Central Bank and the Bank of England cut interest rates by half a percentage point.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Stocks End Nearly Unchanged  The Nasdaq lost 9.76 points, to 1,827.77; the Dow rose 33.15 points, to 9,587.52; and the S.&amp; P. 500 edged up 2.74 points, to 1,118.54.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>S1-7</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: A homeland pep talk; up from Seattle; Brent Staples on flags.</p>
        <p>Column: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E42  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E27  Public Lives</p>
        <p>D2  Weather</p>
        <p>S2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
