<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="17FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1278477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFDF123DF934A25750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-5</p>
        <p>Growing Ethnic Skirmishes Threaten War in Macedonia  Police troops in Tetovo, Macedonia's second-largest city, fired for hours at ethnic Albanians who belong to a group of insurgents trying to claim parts of Macedonia that are overwhelmingly Albanian. Fierce fighting is breaking out and the population is quickly dividing between Slavs and Albanians in Macedonia, which until now had escaped the ethnic carnage of Kosovo, to the north.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deadly Blasts in China  Explosions that appeared to be coordinated killed at least 18 people in Shijiazhuang, an industrial city 120 miles south of Beijing, sending riot police officers into the streets and setting off rumors that laid-off factory workers were seeking revenge.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-5</p>
        <p>Growing Ethnic Skirmishes Threaten War in Macedonia  Police troops in Tetovo, Macedonia's second-largest city, fired for hours at ethnic Albanians who belong to a group of insurgents trying to claim parts of Macedonia that are overwhelmingly Albanian. Fierce fighting is breaking out and the population is quickly dividing between Slavs and Albanians in Macedonia, which until now had escaped the ethnic carnage of Kosovo, to the north.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deadly Blasts in China  Explosions that appeared to be coordinated killed at least 18 people in Shijiazhuang, an industrial city 120 miles south of Beijing, sending riot police officers into the streets and setting off rumors that laid-off factory workers were seeking revenge.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Plans for Taiwan Arms Sale  The Bush administration officially gave Congress details of a request by Taiwan for advanced weapons, a deal that China vigorously opposes.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Bush Weighs Stance on Yen  The White House is said to be debating whether to allow a rapid and steep devaluation of the yen to ease the growing financial crisis in Tokyo. Such a move is strongly opposed by American automakers and other businesses that compete with Japan.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Saudis Storm Hijacked Jet  The police in Medina forced their way into a Russian jet that officials said had been hijacked by two Chechen men. One hijacker was shot dead after he fatally stabbed a flight attendant, and another passenger was killed, officials said.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>More N.C.A.A. Upsets  No. 10-seeded Butler beat No. 7-seeded Wake Forest, 79-63, in the Midwest Region. No. 12-seeded Gonzaga beat No. 5-seeded Virginia, 86-85.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Chinese Player to N.B.A.  Beijing has reportedly agreed to let Wang Zhizhi, a 7-foot-1 center drafted by the Dallas Mavericks in 1999, leave China to become the first Asian player in the N.B.A..</p>
        <p>D4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A6-9</p>
        <p>Bush May No Longer Seek Bar's Advice on Nominees  President Bush's legal advisers have told the American Bar Association that they want to end the group's nearly half-century role as a semiofficial screening panel for judicial nominees, lawyers involved in the discussions said. Many conservative Republicans have long complained that the bar association has displayed a liberal bias in evaluating prospective federal judges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Accelerated Tax Cut Urged  The Bush administration, faced with growing signs of a troubled economy, encouraged Congress to rework the president's tax cut proposal and put more money than previously contemplated back into the hands of individuals this year. But administration officials said they would continue to insist that the total cut not exceed $1.6 trillion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Delay on New Forest Rules  The Bush administration essentially put off a decision on whether to defend a court challenge to Clinton administration rules putting a third of the national forests off limits to development. It also offered to postpone when the new rules would take effect, probably until at least early summer. The moves signaled that the administration might consider a settlement that could significantly scale back the effect of the rules.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Warming Pact in Trouble  Efforts to complete the Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement intended to curtail global warming, have been seriously hurt by President Bush's reversal of a campaign promise to cut carbon dioxide emissions at power plants, negotiators and independent experts said.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. administrator, Christie Whitman, said Mr. Bush's decision was driven by concern that capping emissions could cause the energy problems in California to spread.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>California Refunds Ordered  Federal regulators told electric-power suppliers to refund $55 million to state utilities unless they could justify prices that the regulators called excessive.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Jury Clears Combs Of Gun and Bribery Charges  A Manhattan jury acquitted the hip-hop mogul Sean Combs of all charges arising from a 1999 nightclub shooting that left three people injured. A second defendant, Anthony Jones, was also cleared, but a third, Jamal Barrow, 21, a young rap artist, was convicted of five of eight charges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>If he could do it all over again, Mr. Combs would shed the bad-boy stuff, he said in an interview that was conducted before the verdict.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Pay Figures in Torricelli Inquiry  Two former aides to Senator Robert J. Torricelli, Democrat of New Jersey, have told a federal grand jury that his office paid government salaries for months to four aides who mainly worked on his 1996 campaign, lawyers and others said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Prosecutor Is Dismissed  The Brooklyn district attorney, Charles J. Hynes, fired Francis A. Mainiero, a senior prosecutor who is the subject of a federal investigation into accusations of bribe-taking. Officials said Mr. Mainiero had failed to report his being offered a bribe.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>End of Ill-Fated Center Effort  Queens College returned $3 million of the $4.5 million donated by Dr. Bernard Salick, an alumnus who had given the money to seed what he and the college hoped would become a renowned AIDS research center.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>Drawings Detoured by Lawsuit  Vatican concerns about a California lawsuit against its library led to the Metropolitan Museum of Art's losing an exhibition of Botticelli drawings to the Royal Academy in London.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Ann Sothern  The snappy actress and singer, whose career included Broadway, Hollywood and television, was 92.</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-15</p>
        <p>Stocks Hold Downward Course  The Dow fell 207.87 points, or 2.1 percent, to 9,823.41; the Nasdaq dropped 49.80 points, or 2.6 percent, to 1,890.91; and the S.&amp; P. 500 lost 23.03 points, or 2 percent, to 1,150.53, capping one of the worst weeks ever for stocks. Investors are looking for relief from the Fed, which is expected to cut interest rates on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Wall Street consensus is that the Fed will cut rates at least half a percentage point, though some experts wonder if that will lift the markets.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Decision to Cut Oil Production  Analysts and cartel officials at the OPEC meeting in Vienna said production would be cut back by about one million barrels a day, or 4 percent, to buoy falling prices.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Airline Deal Clears Hurdle  The Justice Department said it would not challenge American Airlines' bid to take over T.W.A., eliminating the last major hurdle to the proposed $742 million deal. T.W.A. filed for bankruptcy protection in January.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Joins Suits Against HCA  The government joined eight whistle-blower lawsuits against the nation's largest hospital company that contend that the company schemed to defraud federal health programs.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A10-11</p>
        <p>Editorials: New York City's population peak; dealing with Mr. Putin; new weapons against tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B13  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
