<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moving Beyond the Kyoto Impasse</title>
    <meta content="31PARS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/31/opinion/31PARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parson, Edward A (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DE1E3DF932A05754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moving Beyond the Kyoto Impasse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Moving Beyond the Kyoto Impasse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward A. Parson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Parson, Edward A (Prof)</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prof Edward A Parson Op-Ed article examines criticisms of Bush administration's exclusion of US from agreement reached by 178 countries to move forward on combating global warming; says both those who deplore administration's snub and those who agree that America can ill afford to join in are losing sight of long view; says to really head off climate change, world must eventually make even larger cuts in emissions of greenhouse gases than those envisioned in Kyoto protocol, and that to make them in time private businesses and private inventiveness must be engaged immediately in attacking problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much is being made of the Bush administration's exclusion of the United States from an agreement reached by 178 countries last week to move forward on combating global warming. But both those who deplore the Bush administration's snub and those who agree with the president that America couldn't afford to join in are losing sight of the long view. To really head off climate change, the world must eventually make even larger (much larger) cuts in its emissions of greenhouses gases than those envisioned in the Kyoto agreement and its refinements in Bonn. But we have some time. The Kyoto protocol calls for reductions from 2008 to 2012. In fact, the large reductions can wait for another decade or two after that. But to make these cuts in time, we must begin now to engage private business and private inventiveness in attacking the problem.</p>
        <p>The world's success in preventing damaging climate change will depend on how it gets its energy over coming decades, as conventional oil and gas grow scarcer. If most new energy comes from burning coal or new fossil fuels, like oil sands, by 2100 the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will be higher than it has been for 50 million years. If most of the energy comes from nonfossil sources, or if new technologies allow us to burn fossil fuels without emitting carbon dioxide, then climate change can at least be greatly slowed and perhaps eventually stabilized. Relative to this vast choice looming a few decades ahead, squabbles over the stringency of the Kyoto emission targets are foolish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To really head off climate change, the world must make even larger cuts in its emissions of greenhouses gases than those envisioned in the Kyoto agreement</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Much is being made of the Bush administration's exclusion of the United States from an agreement reached by 178 countries last week to move forward on combating global warming. But both those who deplore the Bush administration's snub and those who agree with the president that America couldn't afford to join in are losing sight of the long view. To really head off climate change, the world must eventually make even larger (much larger) cuts in its emissions of greenhouses gases than those envisioned in the Kyoto agreement and its refinements in Bonn. But we have some time. The Kyoto protocol calls for reductions from 2008 to 2012. In fact, the large reductions can wait for another decade or two after that. But to make these cuts in time, we must begin now to engage private business and private inventiveness in attacking the problem.</p>
        <p>The world's success in preventing damaging climate change will depend on how it gets its energy over coming decades, as conventional oil and gas grow scarcer. If most new energy comes from burning coal or new fossil fuels, like oil sands, by 2100 the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will be higher than it has been for 50 million years. If most of the energy comes from nonfossil sources, or if new technologies allow us to burn fossil fuels without emitting carbon dioxide, then climate change can at least be greatly slowed and perhaps eventually stabilized. Relative to this vast choice looming a few decades ahead, squabbles over the stringency of the Kyoto emission targets are foolish.</p>
        <p>We have a model that can help. The 1987 Montreal protocol on the ozone layer, now endorsed by 177 countries, is an example that is being overlooked. Its success did not come from its initial 1987 controls on the use of chemicals that deplete ozone, but from its adaptability in achieving its goals. The flexibility of the Montreal protocol made it easier for industry and governments to accept firm goals in the first place, making it possible for the world to move in a common direction.</p>
        <p>The international controls under the protocol have been revised five times, each time with the advice of independent experts from many nations, on the applicability of new developments in science and technology. Letting regulations adapt to changing technical possibilities promoted an intense effort by private industry to reduce the use of ozone-depleting chemicals and develop substitutes for use in products like air conditioners and refrigerators. By participating, industries were better able to solve the technical problems they faced in meeting existing and anticipated regulations, and they could spot commercial opportunities in the phasing out of the old chemicals. Since 1987 the use of ozone-depleting chemicals has declined 90 percent worldwide at modest cost, an achievement that once seemed unthinkable.</p>
        <p>The Montreal lesson has not been learned well; political forces remain polarized on climate policy. The paralyzing deadlock grows ever more perilous as new scientific reports continue to strengthen the case that we are changing the global climate, that changes are likely to accelerate and that the effects, in all countries, will be serious. We must break the impasse.</p>
        <p>First, the nations of the world must make some -- any -- move to curb emissions, some law or rule that will exact a cost on power generators and other industries when they emit greenhouse gases, even if only a modest cost at first. Strategically, this would show the world is moving in a new direction, and the additional cost would be an incentive to develop new, cleaner technology. Implementing the Kyoto protocol without American participation can help if it means adoption of real controls by other nations. But international leaders must also keep trying to bring the United States on board. Soon, because of the dominance of the American economy, American participation will be necessary to make global financial penalties and incentives work.</p>
        <p>Second, the world must establish a process to identify and evaluate new technologies to reduce emissions (like ways of separating the carbon from fossil fuels and putting it underground) and linking periodic review and adaptation of rules to these advances. It is vital that the energy industry and other businesses be serious participants in this process. This will require some combination of providing incentives to needed changes and removing barriers to innovation.</p>
        <p>The failure of the Bush administration to participate in Kyoto does not  mean that significant progress cannot be made by other nations. Eventually, domestic politics here may well force the administration to become engaged on this issue. In the meantime, providing incentives for innovations from private industry will help make a response to global warming economically more palatable in the future.</p>
        <p>Edward A. Parson, associate professor of public policy in the John F. Kennedy School at Harvard, was a consultant in the White House Science Office under Bill Clinton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Edward A. Parson, associate professor of public policy in the John F. Kennedy School at Harvard, was a consultant in the White House Science Office under Bill Clinton.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
