<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1415642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2DB113AF930A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-9</p>
        <p>Hamas Stalls in Signing Pact on Attack Policy  Pressed by Yasir Arafat, 13 Palestinian factions, including Hamas, drafted a unity platform that could be interpreted to signal an end to attacks on civilians within Israel. But Hamas has not signed the result, saying it needs more time to consult with its leadership. Sheik Ahmed Yassin, the Hamas spiritual leader, warned that no one should expect him to declare a cease fire soon.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-9</p>
        <p>Hamas Stalls in Signing Pact on Attack Policy  Pressed by Yasir Arafat, 13 Palestinian factions, including Hamas, drafted a unity platform that could be interpreted to signal an end to attacks on civilians within Israel. But Hamas has not signed the result, saying it needs more time to consult with its leadership. Sheik Ahmed Yassin, the Hamas spiritual leader, warned that no one should expect him to declare a cease fire soon.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>European Flooding Worsens  The prime minister of the Czech Republic, Vladimir Spidla, declared a state of emergency in nearly half the country and 50,000 residents were ordered evacuated when rivers swelled after more than a week of rain. Floods have killed more than 70 people across central Europe and southern Russia in the last week.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Soldier Hurt in Afghanistan Dies  A Green Beret assigned to Special Operations has died of wounds suffered two weeks ago in a firefight with suspected Qaeda terrorists in Afghanistan, the Pentagon said.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Taking Tokyo's Temperature  During the past century, Tokyo's temperatures have increased five times as fast as global warming. There are other such ''heat islands,'' researchers say, which have temperatures far warmer than the surrounding landscape. That can change the weather itself, the scientists found.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Young Indians Take to Tobacco  Gutka, an indigenous form of smokeless tobacco, is as portable as chewing gum and sometimes as sweet as candy, luring many Indians, including children, into addiction. And young people have become an alarming avant-garde in what doctors say is an oral cancer epidemic.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Russian Tycoons Move In  A pulp and paper mill 575 miles northeast of Moscow is the latest in a series of small businesses under attack by large business groups that use their financial might and political connections to consolidate wealth in Russia. One result: just eight business groups control 85 percent of revenue from Russia's 64 biggest private companies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-16</p>
        <p>Economic Forum's Guests: Executives and Democrats  The White House released a list of participants that included a sprinkling of prominent Democrats and some influential corporate leaders not associated with partisan politics to counter critics of the forum.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Child-Smuggling Ring Broken  The Immigration and Naturalization Service said it had broken up a huge ring that has smuggled in hundreds of children from Guatemala, El Salvador and Honduras at a cost of $5,000 to $7,000 each since 1994.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Crackdown on Legal Filings  A rapidly expanding cottage industry that helps people file papers in bankruptcy and divorce cases and other legal proceedings has drawn increasing attention from judges and lawyers who objected to the scope of the preparers' work and fees.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Report Cites Health Violations  A Sierra Club report says the rapid growth of corporate feedlots and slaughterhouses in the 1990's has overwhelmed state and federal regulators.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Bridge Warning From Abroad  The Bush administration received vague reports from a foreign government in recent weeks about threats to several bridges and a major landmark in Chicago.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Linguist Shortage Revealed  The campaign against terror has exposed a shortage of linguists who speak languages like Dari, Urdu and Hindi, and instructors at the Pentagon's Defense Language Institute are rushing to fill the void.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Port Workers Threaten Strike  In a move that would paralyze ports along the West Coast, thousands of longshoremen are threatening to strike, citing a proposal that would eliminate 400 jobs.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Archdiocese Proposes Cuts  Stock market losses and the prospect of settling sexual abuse claims have prompted the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles to cut its budgets for ministry and education by some 30 percent and leave a few jobs unfilled.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>New Scrutiny on Donations To Political Campaigns  In the current wave of corporate scandal and collapse, the old question of which campaign contributions a politician should or should not keep has taken on a new urgency. Democrats have made it a central part of their national strategy in this year's Congressional races to tie Republicans to the most notorious corporate failures.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Icons Return to Winter Garden  With a forklift hoist, palm trees once again stood tall in the Winter Garden of the World Financial Center, which was heavily damaged on Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Israeli Deportee Returns Home  Adam Shapiro, the aid worker from Brooklyn who was trapped in Yasir Arafat's compound when Israeli soldiers besieged his West Bank headquarters in April, returned home after nearly a week in an Israeli prison. Mr. Shapiro, who faces deportation charges in Israel, said he left of his own accord.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>The Voyagers After 25 Years  Twenty-five years after two identical spacecraft took off with little fanfare on missions to explore deep into the outer solar system, the Voyagers are still going strong.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>No Strike Date, Yet  The Major League Baseball players union put off setting a strike date, saying there was hope that recent progress in bargaining talks could lead to an agreement.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Restructuring at US Airways  US Airways has received approval for $75 million in financing after filing for bankruptcy protection on Sunday. But the airline industry had a turbulent day, with stocks falling and passengers wondering how travel would be affected by the carrier's reorganization.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Because of its size and continuing operations, US Airways could benefit from a bankruptcy reorganization by streamlining its operations.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>F.D.A. Approves Cancer Drug  After the shortest review ever for a cancer drug, federal regulators approved Eloxitan, a drug for last-ditch use by patients with colorectal cancer.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Schwab to Eliminate Jobs  Charles Schwab plans to close one of its five customer call centers, eliminate 375 jobs, and look for ways to save another $200 million a year as it braces for an extended slump in trading.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Women In the Boardroom  The success of a recent management seminar suggests that women may step in to fill the void on corporate boards left in the wake of the Enron scandal.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Cheney factor; connecting the dots downtown; overwrought on the criminal court; US Airways' flight to bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
