<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bigger They Are, The More They're Falling</title>
    <meta content="Y31STE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/31/sports/baseball/31STER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McGwire, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF173AF932A05750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bigger They Are, The More They're Falling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Use of Supplements Suspected as Injuries Rise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Use of steroids and performance-enhancing supplements among baseball players is suspected as being factor in increase in injuries, not just in strength and size of performers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A slightly built major league infielder arrived in spring training last month with his physique transformed. Rounded muscles on his shoulders, arms, neck and chest filled his jersey. The player ''has been through the change,'' mused the general manager of the team.</p>
        <p>The baseball executive believed the player was taking a performance-enhancing drug. Steroids, perhaps, or maybe human growth hormone, or androstenedione, the supplement the retired slugger Mark McGwire acknowledged using in the year he broke the single-season record for home runs. It could be that the player began ingesting packs of creatine, the powdered-protein supplement commonly seen in all major league clubhouses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is apparent that more baseball players are taking supplements, but its exact scope and its precise impact is not yet known.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A slightly built major league infielder arrived in spring training last month with his physique transformed. Rounded muscles on his shoulders, arms, neck and chest filled his jersey. The player ''has been through the change,'' mused the general manager of the team.</p>
        <p>The baseball executive believed the player was taking a performance-enhancing drug. Steroids, perhaps, or maybe human growth hormone, or androstenedione, the supplement the retired slugger Mark McGwire acknowledged using in the year he broke the single-season record for home runs. It could be that the player began ingesting packs of creatine, the powdered-protein supplement commonly seen in all major league clubhouses.</p>
        <p>There is no drug testing in Major League Baseball, and general managers are left to speculate why a player has suddenly gained size and strength. The executives say it is apparent to them that more and more players are taking supplements, including pitchers, who may benefit in more subtle ways than hitters.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Andrews, the surgeon most noted for his work on pitchers, embraces the notion that the use of supplements is baseball's version of global warming. No one knows the exact scope of what is occurring, no one knows the precise impact, but there is lingering fear of a terrible unknown.</p>
        <p>Calculating a New Risk</p>
        <p>In the short term, general managers acknowledge that speculation regarding supplement use is increasingly a factor in decisions on whether to sign players to multiyear contracts. The conventional wisdom is that players using a substance like andro may be at a much higher risk for injury because they have more body mass.</p>
        <p>''It's a fairly routine topic when discussing a player who suddenly is a lot bigger,'' said Randy Smith, general manager of the Detroit Tigers. ''To me, you've got guys who look to enhance their performance and get a contract, and become much different than they were in the past. It's very hard to evaluate. You see guys with slider bat speed all of a sudden become good hitters with tremendous power potential.</p>
        <p>''I think it's all over the industry, and I think with all the money that's out there it becomes more relevant.''</p>
        <p>When a player is acquired, San Diego General Manager Kevin Towers said, ''you have to be very cautious if you feel the player is a user.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''You are cautious about doing a long-term deal if he's had one or maybe two big years.''</p>
        <p>Towers said he was not sure of the percentage of players using supplements, ''but I would say there's probably more users this year than last year, and last year more than the year before.''</p>
        <p>''I think it's growing and I think the sad thing is there has been a trickle-down effect to college and even high school players,'' he said.</p>
        <p>McGwire is seen by executives as Exhibit A of someone who was helped and hurt by supplements. He drew a national following in 1998 as he set the single-season home run record, and fans were fascinated by his tape-measure shots and his Paul Bunyan size and strength. But McGwire began breaking down two years later with patellar tendinitis, and he retired last fall at age 38, trailed by speculation that his frame could not sustain his mass.</p>
        <p>General managers say the increase in bulk and weight is the reason for many injuries these days.</p>
        <p>''Your body is built to carry a certain amount of mass,'' said Pat Gillick, general manager for the Seattle Mariners. ''Your muscle size might increase, but your frame stays the same, and I think sometimes, with some of these players, they get too big for their bodies.''</p>
        <p>Weight training without supplements will increase muscle size, said Toronto General Manager J. P. Ricciardi, ''but only to a certain degree.''</p>
        <p>''You can only get so big if you're just working out,'' he said. ''You see how big some of the players are getting and you know it's more than just working out.''</p>
        <p>The general managers look for statistical evidence to see if a player may be using supplements -- a hitter averaging 10 or 15 home runs a year suddenly hits 30 or 35. A longtime reserve becomes a star. ''You look for players who have a spike year, and that's pretty good evidence of someone who's using,'' said Towers.</p>
        <p>The executives see typical physical traits in players who use supplements: rounded and puffy muscles, as if their biceps were injected with helium; unusually large thighs and neck muscles; squared and bloated facial features. And then there are the injuries. ''Usually it's different types of injuries,'' Towers said. ''Injuries that don't normally happen to players. Muscle pulls that end up keeping them out for a year, chronic hamstring problems.''</p>
        <p>Cleveland General Manager Mark Shapiro and others believe there has been a marked increase in the number of pitchers using supplements. For a long time, it was thought that most of the players using supplements were hitters because of the direct benefit: as hitters became stronger, they hit the ball farther.</p>
        <p>But some of the supplements are thought to help in a pitcher's recovery after an outing. So while the use of creatine or andro may not necessarily translate into more velocity on a fastball, it may enable a pitcher to resume strength training quickly.</p>
        <p>An Elbow's Enemy</p>
        <p>Mets pitcher Al Leiter recalled a conversation with a former teammate. ''I think I was doing my usual complaining about why the hitters are so much stronger and hit all these home runs and are on steroids,'' he said. ''And Todd Zeile proceeds to defend the hitters and say, 'What are you trying to tell me, the pitchers aren't on it?' ''</p>
        <p>Shapiro says he believes supplement use is related to an increasing number of elbow injuries in pitchers because there is extra torque on the joint created by additional body mass. Shapiro's theory is supported by Andrews, who is alarmed by the types of injuries he is seeing in baseball players -- beginning with teenagers and into the majors -- as well as the number of injuries.</p>
        <p>Andrews cannot say for sure if the rise in injuries is related to supplement use, but he has strong suspicions. Creatine can be bought over the counter and is viewed as more benign than steroids or human growth hormone -- performance-enhancing drugs he is certain some players are taking. But Andrews calls the use of creatine worrisome because it increases muscle size by retaining fluid and causing dehydration. Andrews says he has seen more incidents of explosive injuries like tendon ruptures, in which the muscle literally strips away from the bone, and a rise in cases of patellar tendinitis in the knee.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing an awful increase in elbow injuries,'' Andrews said. ''We don't know if we're diagnosing it better or there's an actual increase. In the past, I might have done an elbow operation on one 15-year-old in a year, and now it's not uncommon for me to see two in the same day.''</p>
        <p>Andrews reviews medical records for major league teams before the June amateur draft. ''We're seeing fewer and fewer kids come into the draft that haven't been operated on,'' Andrews said. ''So they don't have any healthy kids left. You're saying to yourself, 'What's the deal?'</p>
        <p>''You see the body type all the time: muscled-up kids who go from 180 pounds last year to 210 pounds this year, and scientifically, it's all worrisome.''</p>
        <p>Andrews said there should be an emphasis on flexibility in baseball weight training instead of muscle building.</p>
        <p>A National League manager said he had to approach a player last year who was losing flexibility and gaining weight. The manager said the player was using too much creatine, had to be hydrated constantly and was losing his skills.</p>
        <p>''Just look for the players who are constantly carrying water bottles, and they are the ones using this stuff,'' the manager said.</p>
        <p>For general managers deciding whether to give a player a one-year deal or a three-year contract, it is problematic. They are making huge financial investments based on educated guesses on whether players are at an increased risk of injury because of supplements. ''It's obviously well known and taken as a fact that if a player is on that, there are effects down the road,'' said Allard Baird, general manager for the Kansas City Royals.</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball tests players in the minor leagues for steroids, and each of the 10 general managers interviewed -- except for Gillick -- acknowledged that players in his farm system had tested positive. There are education programs in the minor leagues, and counselors meet with players who test positive for steroid use.</p>
        <p>There is no testing for steroids in the major leagues. The Players Association has condoned random testing with probable cause for drugs like cocaine, but it has fought steroid testing on the principle of privacy. Major League Baseball has asked for steroid testing, but has never regarded it as a make-or-break issue in collective bargaining.</p>
        <p>The feeling among many players is that Major League Baseball will never aggressively fight the use of supplements and performance-enhancing drugs because it will cast a shadow over the accomplishments of its biggest stars, like McGwire. ''If it were to come out and Major League Baseball were to go back and implement drug testing for steroids and find out that some of the guys were on steroids, it could open up a whole can of worms,'' said Leiter, and place ''asterisks next to numbers.''</p>
        <p>Covering Up</p>
        <p>Some stories about the use of performance-enhancing drugs are commonly repeated as gossip. There was the slugger who walked around shirtless in the clubhouse at an All-Star Game with acne -- one possible side effect of steroids -- covering his back. Another player threw a T-shirt at the player and said, ''Will you please put this on?''</p>
        <p>There is the tale of a National League player injecting himself with a steroid in the shower after a game, in full view of teammates.</p>
        <p>The general managers see players getting larger and larger and worry that the risk is becoming greater and greater. ''I think the only way the trend is going to stop is if it becomes illegal and you're able to test roster players for it,'' Towers said. ''The only way that's going to happen is if a life is lost, or two, and it wakes people up. A star player is going to lose his life and everybody is going to wake up and say, 'This is not good.' ''</p>
        <p>Gillick said, ''It's going to take a tragedy to make people change.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
