<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apology Aside, Germany Vote Has U.S. Hinge</title>
    <meta content="21GERM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/21/international/europe/21GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1425420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stoiber, Edmund</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daubler-Gmelin, Herta (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schroder, Gerhard</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D61F30F932A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apology Aside, Germany Vote Has U.S. Hinge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Apology Aside, Germany Vote Has U.S. Hinge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chancellor Gerhard Schroder writes Pres Bush personal letter apologizing for 'supposed remarks' by German Justice Min Herta Daubler-Gmelin, who reportedly compared Bush's political tactics over Iraq to those of Hitler; bitter German election campaign draws to close with Schroder inching ahead of Edmund Stoiber, largely by attacking US threats to invade Iraq; poll graph; letter reflects unease and friction in US-German relations; minister denies comparing Bush to Hitler, but her apparent indiscretions are only most vocal expressions of conflict M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chancellor Gerhard Schröder wrote a personal letter to President Bush today apologizing for ''the supposed remarks'' by his justice minister, who is said to have compared Mr. Bush's political tactics over Iraq to those of Hitler.</p>
        <p>His letter was sent two days before a German election that has turned into the closest and most bitter political battle here for many years. Polls suggest that Mr. Schröder, a Social Democrat, has inched ahead of his conservative rival, Edmund Stoiber, largely by attacking American threats to invade Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Germany's chancellor apologized to President Bush for remarks by his justice minister, who is said to have compared Mr. Bush's tactics over Iraq to those of Hitler.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chancellor Gerhard Schröder wrote a personal letter to President Bush today apologizing for ''the supposed remarks'' by his justice minister, who is said to have compared Mr. Bush's political tactics over Iraq to those of Hitler.</p>
        <p>His letter was sent two days before a German election that has turned into the closest and most bitter political battle here for many years. Polls suggest that Mr. Schröder, a Social Democrat, has inched ahead of his conservative rival, Edmund Stoiber, largely by attacking American threats to invade Iraq.</p>
        <p>''The minister has assured me that she did not make the remarks attributed to her,'' Mr. Schröder wrote to Mr. Bush. ''I would like to make it clear to you how much I regret that through the supposed remarks of the German justice minister an impression was left that could deeply injure your feelings.''</p>
        <p>The letter, from the leader of what is traditionally one of America's staunchest European allies, illustrated the accumulation of unease and friction that have afflicted German-American relations over Iraq. The personal relationship between Mr. Bush and Mr. Schröder has never been an easy one, but it has clearly deteriorated in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Evidently furious, Mr. Bush said today that he was ''deeply troubled'' by the remarks attributed to Justice Minister Herta Däubler-Gmelin, a 59-year-old Social Democrat.</p>
        <p>Ms. Däubler-Gmelin held a combative news conference today in which she denied comparing Mr. Bush to Hitler. She insisted that the report quoting her as doing so had been ''an evil election maneuver.''</p>
        <p>But she again appeared to confuse her denial by saying she had indeed talked about the way Mr. Bush's foreign policy could divert attention from domestic problems, and had added that debate on such political methods had been well known since the time of ''Adolf Nazi.'' Her original remarks were reportedly made on Sunday at a meeting with labor union leaders.</p>
        <p>Today, she added: ''It is absurd and slanderous to connect me to a comparison between a democratically elected politician and Nazi leaders. I deeply regret that this has thrown shadows on German-American relations, and I am here to clear that up.''</p>
        <p>But little is clear in this turbulent election. Mr. Schröder's resurgence, based on his refusal to support any form of war in Iraq, has thrown him into a conflict with the Bush administration that is both substantive and personal. Ms. Däubler-Gmelin's apparent indiscretions are only the most vocal and wounding expressions of this conflict.</p>
        <p>In the vote on Sunday, Germans will elect the 669-member Parliament. The next governing coalition, and the future chancellor, will be chosen on the basis of showings of the parties.</p>
        <p>The German system is so carefully weighted -- with voters casting ballots both for parties and for individuals in their district, and a barrier of 5 percent of the overall vote required to get into Parliament at all -- that one party almost never emerges the clear victor, and coalition government is required.</p>
        <p>Polls released today suggested that the election was too close to call, with the Social Democrats and the conservatives, represented by the Christian Democrats and the Bavarian Christian Social Union, each getting about 37 to 38 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>The Free Democrats, a party committed to reducing the role of the state in the economy, are between 7 and 10 percent; the environmentalist Greens between 6 and 8 percent; and the former East German Communists just below the 5 percent minimum that would win them seats.</p>
        <p>As a result, the makeup of the future government is unpredictable, although Mr. Schröder appears to have a very slight edge. Whether he will continue to rule with the Greens, or in some other coalition, is unclear. The Greens had long appeared vulnerable, but have also rallied in recent weeks as a result of anti-American sentiment over Iraq.</p>
        <p>As for the Free Democrats, they are in a state of some confusion. Under their new leader, Guido Westerwelle, 40, they entered the campaign confident that they would re-enter government in coalition with Mr. Stoiber and the conservatives, ousting Mr. Schröder and his Green coalition partner, Foreign Minister Joschka Fischer.</p>
        <p>While the Free Democrats largely campaigned as the natural partners of Mr. Stoiber, the party now offers its help to either major party. But there is a strong chance that no one will need them at all.</p>
        <p>At their final rally here Thursday night, Mr. Westerwelle appeared with some of the grand old men of German politics, like Hans-Dietrich Genscher, a former foreign minister, and Count Otto von Lambsdorff, a former finance minister.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Westerwelle ran into trouble with his deputy, Jürgen Möllemann, a former paratrooper with a penchant for harsh criticism of Israel and of a prominent Jewish talk show host, Michel Friedman. Mr. Möllemann's comments, seen as an effort to win right-wing votes, were judged by many to be anti-Semitic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Westerwelle had ordered Mr. Möllemann to behave himself, but the day of the final rally, there was news that Mr. Möllemann had circulated an election flyer repeating his criticisms. An embarrassed Mr. Westerwelle ordered his deputy to stay away from the rally.</p>
        <p>But he showed up anyway, attracting most of the attention. He told journalists that he did not want to create a bad image for the party, then, having done so, drove away.</p>
        <p>At the rally, Mr. Westerwelle tried to ignore the entire affair and spoke of the Free Democrats' commitment to structural economic change, lower taxes and less government.</p>
        <p>Wolfgang Gerhard, a former Free Democratic Party leader and likely foreign minister in any coalition with the conservatives, which he clearly prefers, said, ''I would expect us to win 10 to 11 percent.''</p>
        <p>''That would be better for a strong and clear government,'' he said. ''We are open to either party, but we want to bring about serious labor-market and tax reform.''</p>
        <p>If the Free Democrats are anxious, the mood of the rival Greens and of their popular leader, Foreign Minister Fischer, is ebullient. A rally in Cologne was full of young people and good humor, with a hoarse Mr. Fischer creating rock star-like excitement, especially as he jabbed away at Mr. Stoiber.</p>
        <p>The rally showed once again how far the Greens have traveled from their founding radicalism. They once held that no one should remain in office longer than one term.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fischer spoke of climate change, of environmental responsibility, of basic fairness to the poor and of war and peace. ''To have more means to have more responsibility for the rest of the world,'' he said, to great applause, ''you must not cut the branch on which you sit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
