<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.E. Research Returns to Roots; Management Again Gambles On Costly Long-Term Ideas</title>
    <meta content="Y26LAB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/26/business/26LAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Technologies Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Siemens Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Philips Electronics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Immelt, Jeffrey R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John F Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD103CF935A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="2040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.E. Research Returns to Roots; Management Again Gambles On Costly Long-Term Ideas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.E. Research Returns to Roots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <dateline>NISKAYUNA, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Electric's chief executive, Jeffrey R Immelt, is letting central reseach unit in Niskayuna, NY, refocus its attention on long-term projects and the next big idea; under his predecessor, John F Welch Jr, researchers at central lab lost freedom to follow their instincts and had to seek funds from GE's business units, which were not inclined to finance projects that did not have short-term payoff; GE must take gamble, since its competitors, including Siemens, Royal Philips Electrics and United Technologies, are all stepping up long-term research; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anil Duggal is 37 years old, but he looks like a mischievous boy as he turns his office lights low. He hits a button and grins gleefully as the flat panel he holds generates a white glow bright enough to light the room.</p>
        <p>The panel is made from thin sheets of specially treated plastic on glass that seems to generate almost as much light from a small jolt of electricity as an incandescent light bulb running on standard current.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of researchers for G.E. is hoping to usher in an era of cheap, clean-burning lights, batteries, solar cells  and the beginning of plastic-based electronics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anil Duggal is 37 years old, but he looks like a mischievous boy as he turns his office lights low. He hits a button and grins gleefully as the flat panel he holds generates a white glow bright enough to light the room.</p>
        <p>The panel is made from thin sheets of specially treated plastic on glass that seems to generate almost as much light from a small jolt of electricity as an incandescent light bulb running on standard current.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Duggal and his team of researchers at the General Electric Global Research Center in this small town not far from Schenectady can figure out how to dispense with the glass, they could be a short hop away from developing super-thin lighting and energy sources that could be rolled off printing presses like newspapers. And that could usher in an era of cheap, clean-burning lights, batteries, solar cells -- and the beginning of plastic-based electronics.</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Duggal's laboratory, where he specializes in light and energy, is a regular stop for Jeffrey R. Immelt, G.E.'s chief executive, as well as the heads of G.E.'s businesses. Mr. Duggal reassures them that his project is a question of when, not if, and that he is meeting research milestones. But he does not promise a new product any time soon, and no one pressures him to do so.</p>
        <p>''People used to ask for quarterly progress reports, and I had to struggle to get funding renewed,'' said Mr. Duggal, who joined G.E. in 1992. ''Now I feel I have at least two years before I have to show progress.''</p>
        <p>For G.E., that change is nearly as radical as the science being pursued. John F. Welch Jr., Mr. Immelt's predecessor, spent two decades pushing the Niskayuna lab to churn out profitable products. Now Mr. Immelt is letting it return to the mission that Charles P. Steinmetz, a G.E. engineer who set up the lab, laid forth more than 100 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Steinmetz did not want this lab to worry about next quarter's product,'' said Scott C. Donnelly, senior vice president for research. ''He wanted it to work on the next big idea, even as G.E.'s businesses were refining the last one.''</p>
        <p>The numbers reflect the shift back to those roots. Two years ago the central lab spent $28 million, or only about 10 percent of its $286 million budget, on long-term projects. This year, $91 million of the center's $344 million budget has gone to such research; next year, the center's team expects to direct $104 million -- almost 30 percent of its $349 million budget -- to long-range projects.</p>
        <p>Some of the money comes from G.E.'s business units. But it is not used to improve whistles or polish bells.</p>
        <p>''When Aircraft Engines wants a turbine blade, or Medical Systems wants a CT scanner that does thinner slices, we say 'Hey guys, you are capable of doing that yourself,' '' Mr. Donnelly said. ''We use the central lab to study things that require major technological breakthroughs.''</p>
        <p>The business leaders have bought into that idea. ''I come up regularly to make sure that the stuff they are looking at will make a difference in the marketplace,'' said John G. Rice, president of GE Power Systems. ''It just doesn't have to make a difference in three or even five years.''</p>
        <p>Some projects will be dead ends. On others, G.E. may be beaten to market by one of the start-ups carving niches in biotechnology, nanotechnology and other modern-day sciences.</p>
        <p>But G.E. must take the gamble. Its industrial businesses are suffering in the sluggish economy and its insurance units are still reeling from losses associated with last year's terrorist attacks. Competitors like Siemens, Royal Philips Electronics and United Technologies are all stepping up long-term research. And G.E.'s executives know that if they are first to introduce innovative products, they will grab customers not just for equipment, but for the lucrative contracts to service that equipment.</p>
        <p>''Jack Welch won the socket wars, the battle to stay ahead with tangible products,'' said Nicholas P. Heymann, who follows G.E. for Prudential Securities. ''Jeff must now use R.&amp; D. to win the value-added wars.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Immelt, G.E. is ''incubating'' service-heavy businesses in security, water treatment, oil and gas and other areas that cannot be bolted onto existing G.E. units. It is even doing research into hydrogen energy, which some see as a way, first, to turn fossil fuels into clean energy and ultimately as a means to replace petroleum.</p>
        <p>''I'd be surprised if, a bunch of years down the road,'' Mr. Immelt said, ''we aren't into businesses that require new names.''</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Immelt is trying to recreate Niskayuna's glory days. It was here, in 1913, that William Coolidge invented the X-ray tube, eventually giving birth to the diagnostic imaging industry -- and to GE Medical Systems. Now, his intellectual descendents are using information from the human genome project and similar efforts to develop molecular imaging techniques that could probe each bodily cell -- and spot diseases before any symptoms occur.</p>
        <p>Lexan polycarbonate, the first super-strong heat resistant plastic and the precursor to the whole family of so-called engineered thermoplastics, was born here in 1953; it became the underpinning of GE Plastics.</p>
        <p>Today, G.E.'s nanotechnology researchers are studying why nature can turn calcium carbonate into lustrous, strong seashells, while human beings can only wrest chalk from the same substance. If they crack that mystery, the result might be heat-resistant ceramic materials that are as light as dinner plates yet as strong as steel. GE Power Systems and GE Aircraft Engines could use the materials to make more durable and efficient generators and turbines, and GE Plastics could probably find a host of outside customers.</p>
        <p>In one sense, G.E. is catching up with its competition. Gerard J. Kleisterlee, chief executive of Royal Philips Electronics -- a rival to G.E. in medical equipment -- insists that each of his company's five divisions sponsor research with a three-to-five year time span. ''We were giving our business units too much autonomy on how their research money should be spent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But G.E. has a problem that Philips does not face. When G.E. failed to acquire Honeywell International last year, its portfolio of businesses was left top-heavy with financial services. Even during the best of times the shares of financial services firms trade at lower multiples of earnings than those of advanced industrial companies. G.E. stock, once a Wall Street favorite, is trading at $25.33, about $16 below its level a year ago.</p>
        <p>Clearly, Mr. Immelt faces different challenges than Mr. Welch ever did. Mr. Welch, who rose up through G.E. Plastics, concentrated on paring a bloated management and whipping operations into shape. Research did not escape his baleful glare.</p>
        <p>Until Mr. Welch became G.E.'s chief executive in 1981, the central lab had run primarily on corporate dollars and had let researchers follow their instincts. Mr. Welch insisted that the researchers petition G.E.'s business units for funds. He figured -- correctly -- that the units would not pay for projects that just satisfied intellectual curiosity.</p>
        <p>''Jack thought the lab operated too much like the old Bell Labs, and they never did much for AT&amp;T,'' said Noel M. Tichy, a professor at the University of Michigan Business School. ''Jeff is nudging the pendulum back toward the center.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Immelt, who rose through GE Medical Systems, one of G.E.'s most technology-dependent units, established himself as a salesman-cum-technophile early on. He was the first G.E. business leader to apply Six Sigma, a quality control method, to product design. He often asked customers for wish lists, and turned them into work orders for researchers. Now he wants all of G.E. to think -- and act -- along those lines.</p>
        <p>''Superior technology is the only route to consistent growth without declining margins,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The researchers say a heavy weight has been lifted. Tony Dean, a mechanical engineer who specializes in propulsion, spends most of his time leading experiments in pulsed detonation, a process in which fuel is ignited in hundreds of thousands of tiny explosions every second, instead of in a continuous burn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dean, who has worked for G.E. for 10 years, is certain the nascent technology is more efficient, and he and his people are tinkering with it on engines. If they get the kinks out, they expect to derive jet engines that use less fuel at all speeds, and ''afterburners'' that enable older engines to fly at supersonic speeds.</p>
        <p>But the first pulsed detonation engine is unlikely to show up for at least five years. In pre-Immelt days, Mr. Dean said, he could have wrested just enough money from headquarters and from the government to justify spending a day a week on the project. ''I'd have had to juggle five projects at once,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Immelt is also giving researchers better operations. He is spending $81 million to build technology centers in Munich and Shanghai, and is pumping $100 million into updating the 525-acre Niskayuna complex. Generic laboratories are being torn down, replaced with ''wet'' labs tailored for biotechnology and chemistry.</p>
        <p>The 1960's-era auditorium that sat upward of 300 people is being replaced with a wired room that seats about 165 -- but in which attendees can plug in laptops and interact with one another. A lodge that can sleep 35 people is also going up.</p>
        <p>The need for a lodge is itself a sign of changing times. Mr. Welch rarely dropped by the lab; Mr. Immelt holds meetings here twice a year. Those who run G.E.'s business units used to visit Niskayuna only when the mood struck; Mr. Immelt insists they come four times a year.</p>
        <p>Even more startling for the once insular G.E., outsiders are welcome. For example, scientists from GlaxoSmithKline, the pharmaceutical company, often visit, interested in the work on molecular imaging. That research could lead to non-invasive diagnostic tests, which are G.E.'s forte, but also to new drugs, which G.E. does not make but Glaxo does.</p>
        <p>''We write secrecy agreements, but it makes sense to have technology-sharing arrangements,'' said Joseph M. Hogan, chief executive of GE Medical Systems.</p>
        <p>Word of G.E.'s new openness is spreading. Rick Snyder, chief executive of Ardesta, a new company specializing in technologies that operate at the size of the human hair and smaller, said he plans to call the G.E. lab soon. ''I could see us joint venturing on research now, and development later,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The G.E. businesses are chipping in for research outside their primary areas, too. GE Capital is paying for research into artificial intelligence, which could help it with such tasks as setting prices for service contracts. GE Aircraft Engines is paying for most of the pulsed detonation research, but GE Power Systems is kicking in, too. And nearly every business is supporting nanotechnology -- the study of tiny molecular structures that could lead to such things as ceramics that withstand high heat, magnets that yield sharp X-ray images, and security systems that play color against particle size.</p>
        <p>''Shared R.&amp; D. makes total sense,'' said James N. Kelleher, who follows G.E. for Argus Research. ''Companies want to eliminate duplicate efforts in all kinds of back-office operations, so why not in research?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
