<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Hole Is Now Seen as a Cause for Antarctic Cooling</title>
    <meta content="Y03OZON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/03/science/03OZON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1389123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chlorofluorocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ultraviolet Light</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Antarctica</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6D61331F930A35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Hole Is Now Seen as a Cause for Antarctic Cooling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ozone Hole Is Now Seen as a Cause for Antarctic Cooling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several scientists attribute cooling of Antarctica to ozone hole that opens up in atmosphere each spring as result of artificial chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons; say ozone hole may account for fact that winds blowing around Antarctica and trapping cold air at South Pole have accelerated in recent decades, keeping cold air even more confined; suggest that peninsula stretching north toward South America has defied cooling trend because it lies outside wind vortex (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most scientists blame people, at least in part, for global warming. Now, some researchers say people may be partly to blame for the cooling of Antarctica as well.</p>
        <p>While average global temperatures have risen about one degree Fahrenheit over the past century, Antarctica over all appears to have cooled slightly in the past few decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some researchers say people may be partly to blame for the cooling of Antarctica.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most scientists blame people, at least in part, for global warming. Now, some researchers say people may be partly to blame for the cooling of Antarctica as well.</p>
        <p>While average global temperatures have risen about one degree Fahrenheit over the past century, Antarctica over all appears to have cooled slightly in the past few decades.</p>
        <p>That has been puzzling, because the polar regions are thought to be more sensitive to warming trends than the rest of the globe. Even more puzzling, a small portion of Antarctica -- the peninsula that stretches north toward South America -- defies the cooling trend. It has been warming very rapidly, about five degrees over the past 50 years, 10 times the global average.</p>
        <p>Writing in today's issue of the journal Science, Dr. David W. J. Thompson, a professor of atmospheric science at Colorado State University, and Dr. Susan Solomon, a senior scientist at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Boulder, Colo., argue that the ozone hole, which has opened up each spring over Antarctica in recent years, may help explain both contradictory trends.</p>
        <p>''Ozone seems to be capable of tickling the Southern Hemisphere patterns,'' Dr. Thompson said in an interview.</p>
        <p>A vortex of winds continually blows around Antarctica, tending to trap cold air at the South Pole. In the new paper, Dr. Thompson and Dr. Solomon show that the winds have strengthened in the past few decades, keeping the cold air even more confined.</p>
        <p>The peninsula, which lies outside the wind vortex, escapes the cooling effect, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>They say the ozone hole may be the cause of the stronger winds.</p>
        <p>''That's where we speculate,'' Dr. Thompson said, ''and the emphasis is on the word 'may.' ''</p>
        <p>Close to the ground, ozone, a molecule consisting of three oxygen atoms, forms a large and unhealthy component of smog. High in the atmosphere, however, naturally occurring ozone is essential for life, blocking ultraviolet rays that would fatally mangle DNA.</p>
        <p>Artificial chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, once ubiquitous in aerosol spray cans and air-conditioner coolant, cause a chain of reactions that destroy ozone. In September 2000, the ozone hole opened up to a record 17.1 million square miles. With the most damaging CFC's now phased out, the ozone hole is expected to heal over the coming decades.</p>
        <p>Until it does, however, fewer ozone molecules mean the atmosphere absorbs less ultraviolet radiation. Instead of warming the air, the rays bounce off the snow and ice of Antarctica and reflect back into space.</p>
        <p>Scientists already knew that the ozone hole had cooled the upper atmosphere. Dr. Thompson and Dr. Solomon show that the troposphere, the lowest six miles of the atmosphere, has also cooled.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of food for thought in there,'' said Dr. John E. Walsh, a professor of atmospheric science at the University of Illinois and an author of a paper in Science in January that indicated Antarctica was cooling.</p>
        <p>Dr. Walsh said the data tying the cooling to stronger winds was convincing. ''My one reservation,'' he said, ''is the link to the ozone.''</p>
        <p>He noted that the ozone hole was usually largest in November or December, but that the greatest cooling had been about six months later.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thompson agreed that the ozone hole could not explain the whole climactic picture, and said other influences like ocean currents probably played important roles, too.</p>
        <p>''I seriously doubt it's the only player,'' he said. ''I think it's one of many.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
