<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small World After All</title>
    <meta content="05SUST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/05/international/africa/05SUST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1421104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Summit on Sustainable Development</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD143EF936A3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small World After All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of new view of environmental problem-solving that has emerged at United Nations World Summit on Sustainable Development, Johannesburg; strategy, which has evolved as way around governmental resistance to change, involves pragmatic partnerships, sometimes between traditional adversaries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1997 environmental activists from Greenpeace occupied one of BP's North Atlantic oil-drilling platforms as part of a campaign to get the world to abandon fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Last Friday in Johannesburg, at the World Summit on Sustainable Development, the activists joined representatives of the corporation on a different platform, at a news conference where they all endorsed binding government commitments to stem global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1997 environmental activists from Greenpeace occupied one of BP's North Atlantic oil-drilling platforms as part of a campaign to get the world to abandon fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Last Friday in Johannesburg, at the World Summit on Sustainable Development, the activists joined representatives of the corporation on a different platform, at a news conference where they all endorsed binding government commitments to stem global warming.</p>
        <p>Their partnership, though limited, was emblematic of a new view of environmental problem-solving that emerged at the United Nations conference, which concluded yesterday.</p>
        <p>The strategy, which has evolved as a way around governmental resistance to change, involves pragmatic partnerships, sometimes between traditional adversaries.</p>
        <p>Experts and many of those taking part said this new approach might offer the best chance of seeing progress after years of stagnation on important environmental issues. Big pledges by major industrial powers may sound good, they say, but what is needed is progress on the ground.</p>
        <p>As the 10 days of formal talks and plenary sessions proceeded, projects were announced, some small and others ambitious, involving novel partnerships of governments, private groups, foundations and businesses.</p>
        <p>Their goals include improving health and sanitation, protecting forests, preserving fisheries and providing energy to the world's poorest communities.</p>
        <p>''It's time to end the lofty aspirations and move to action -- to real commitments,'' said one senior American official at the Johannesburg meeting.</p>
        <p>For nine months leading up to the summit meeting, that official said, government negotiators, private environmental groups, businesses and international agencies sifted for ideas they could put on the table in South Africa as evidence of their resolve. Dozens of proposals have been announced and will be under way soon.</p>
        <p>One, unveiled on Tuesday at the meeting, would protect 120 million acres of the Amazon River basin over the next 10 years, with money coming from Brazil, Germany, the World Bank, United Nations environmental funds and the World Wildlife Fund, a private group.</p>
        <p>Others involve commitments by industrial powers to export clean-burning energy technologies to developing countries that might otherwise burn coal, oil or other fuels without regard to pollution.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the Johannesburg meeting also produced the usual volume of delicately negotiated texts in which rich countries pledged to help poor countries.</p>
        <p>The declarations are important, providing governments with goals to which the public can hold them accountable. But they are are not binding.</p>
        <p>Generally, campaigners promoting an end to poverty and environmental damage said the negotiations had resulted in far too many compromises that in most cases did not advance countries' commitments beyond those they already made years earlier in other forums.</p>
        <p>Some weary environmental campaigners expressed equal grumpiness about what they saw as a lack of leadership on the part of the United States and a tendency of other countries to abandon hard targets for environmental cleanups or new energy technologies and blame the impasse on the United States.</p>
        <p>Still, there were enough of the new-style agreements to generate at least a modicum of optimism among experts ranging from environmental activists to corporate chiefs.</p>
        <p>Many of those participants say they are not disappointed that the Johannesburg meeting had no specific treaty or other agreement as a goal. The 1992 Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro produced two major treaties, they note, one on preserving biological diversity and another on preventing harmful climate change. Few experts regard either as effective.</p>
        <p>The lack of treaties as focal points may be exactly why this meeting could produce some breakthroughs, said several of those taking part. There was less of an impetus for the usual suspects to play their usual prominent adversarial roles.</p>
        <p>Both Greenpeace and the corporate executives emphasized that they still harbored major differences on many issues. ''This is not a merger,'' Bjorn Stigson, the president of the business council, said at the event.</p>
        <p>But they said they had decided to come together to show that they agreed on the importance of pushing ahead with the Kyoto Protocol, an addendum to the 1992 Rio climate treaty that would require industrial powers to reduce emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration rejected that treaty last year, while most other industrial countries have chosen to ratify it and abide by its terms. On Tuesday, Russian officials said their government planned to ratify it. If Russia does so, possibly before the end of the year, the Kyoto treaty will go into force, though only for the countries that ratified it.</p>
        <p>Over all, many delegates and lobbyists said, the new partnerships -- between old adversaries, between governments and private concerns -- were the heart of a promising new model for development.</p>
        <p>Antonio La Vina, a senior fellow at the World Resources Institute, a private Washington research group, said it was vital that the pace of change not rely on the once-a-decade pace of summitry.</p>
        <p>''It's a real challenge to find new ways of making these decisions and moving forward,'' he said. ''The old way has been glacial, which has not really served the planet or the people of this planet. If it's going to be a hundred years' war, there will be no victors.''</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
