<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA to View Interaction of Earth's Water and Climate</title>
    <meta content="30AQUA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/30/science/space/30AQUA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1388295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D71F3EF933A05757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA to View Interaction of Earth's Water and Climate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NASA to View Interaction of Earth's Water and Climate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA prepares to launch six-year, $952 million Aqua satellite project, which will study myriad ways in which water affects Earth's climate and how relationship may be changing; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Viewed from space, some of the earth's most pronounced features are the blue of the vast oceans, the white swirls of moisture-laden clouds and bright swaths of ice covering the poles. Much of what the planet is stems from its water, and NASA is about to launch a satellite to study the many ways that water affects the climate and how that relationship may be changing.</p>
        <p>The Aqua satellite is a large spacecraft with sensors designed to follow the cycle of the earth's water in its many forms to determine whether it is being affected by climate change. Six types of instruments aboard Aqua are to scan through the atmosphere down to the surface, gathering the most detailed data ever on water vapor in clouds, ice crystals in the air, evaporation, water in the oceans, icebergs and other sea ice, as well as glaciers and snow pack on land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much of the earth stems from its water, and NASA is about to launch a satellite to study the many ways that water affects the climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Viewed from space, some of the earth's most pronounced features are the blue of the vast oceans, the white swirls of moisture-laden clouds and bright swaths of ice covering the poles. Much of what the planet is stems from its water, and NASA is about to launch a satellite to study the many ways that water affects the climate and how that relationship may be changing.</p>
        <p>The Aqua satellite is a large spacecraft with sensors designed to follow the cycle of the earth's water in its many forms to determine whether it is being affected by climate change. Six types of instruments aboard Aqua are to scan through the atmosphere down to the surface, gathering the most detailed data ever on water vapor in clouds, ice crystals in the air, evaporation, water in the oceans, icebergs and other sea ice, as well as glaciers and snow pack on land.</p>
        <p>Scientists said the $952 million program, planned to last six years, should also help in understanding biological systems dependent upon water, like plankton in oceans and vegetation on land. In addition, they said, the data should help improve long-term weather and climate forecasting, and should help in understanding the workings of severe storms. For example, temperature changes on sea surfaces can signal widespread weather shifts like El Niño.</p>
        <p>''The Aqua satellite will tell us about water in all of its forms,'' said Dr. Claire Parkinson, a sea ice expert and Aqua project scientist at the Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., which is in charge of the program. ''This comprehensive approach enables scientists to study the interactions among key elements of the earth system so as to better understand our planet.''</p>
        <p>Seventy percent of the earth is covered with water, but only a tiny amount occurs in the atmosphere as vapor or ice crystals. Yet atmospheric water is one of the most important greenhouse gases controlling the radiation and heat balance of the earth, Dr. Parkinson said. Because it is so little understood, its impact on global warming is hard to gauge.</p>
        <p>Another unknown is how global warming may be affecting the cycle of water from sea to sky to earth, with some scientists suspecting that this hydrologic cycle may be speeding up.</p>
        <p>Different forms of water greatly influence the amount of heat absorbed, retained and reflected away from the earth, scientists say. Clouds containing tiny particles of water and solids like ash and sea salt influence weather patterns by absorbing or scattering solar energy, or reflecting some of it back into space. Sea ice can reflect solar energy to reduce surface warming or insulate water against heat loss.</p>
        <p>Snow cover can keep heat from escaping from the land, allowing the formation of cold air masses and limiting frost's penetration into the ground. Variations in sea temperatures can reflect shifts in heat exchanges between the ocean and the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Aqua carries some instruments identical to those on a sister satellite, Terra, and is to provide data that will be cross-referenced with information it is gathering. Launched in 1999, Terra carries instruments that concentrate on landmass studies, monitoring vegetation and the spread of deserts, among other things. The third major satellite in this system, a craft called Aura that will focus on atmospheric studies, is to be launched in 2004. (The three satellites carry Latin names that correspond to their missions: Aqua for water, Terra for land and Aura for heaven.)</p>
        <p>Dr. Ghassem R. Asrar, NASA's associate administrator for earth science, said Aqua's data, combined with information gathered by the other satellites that are part of the agency's Earth Observing System, would help resolve scientific conflicts about global warming and how much of it could be attributed to human activity. The comprehensive, uniform information provided by this system will give policy makers more confidence in making decisions about influencing global warming that can have worldwide economic impact, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Parkinson, the Aqua project scientist, says some of the uncertainties about global warming and climate change arise from conflicting data gathered by different instruments at different times in different parts of the world. ''Satellites are the best way to get a good global view,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Aqua is to be launched on Saturday from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California aboard a Boeing Delta II rocket. The spacecraft, weighing 6,468 pounds at launching, is to be placed in a low polar orbit 428 miles high that has it circling the earth top to bottom every 99 minutes. Flying in this orbit, Aqua will take readings of every part of the globe every 16 days, building a comprehensive database that allows scientists to assess changes and drastically improving computer models for long-term forecasting.</p>
        <p>In space, the big satellite, built by TRW Inc., will deploy antennas and booms to measure 16 feet by 26 feet, with solar power panels unfurling to stretch 55 feet across.</p>
        <p>Aqua's suite of instruments include devices that will measure cloud properties, the wetness of land surfaces, land and sea temperatures, humidity and temperature at different levels of the atmosphere, the properties of particles in the air, fluctuations in solar energy absorption and many other parameters.</p>
        <p>Two instruments are provided by other countries. The National Space Development Agency of Japan contributed a microwave scanning radiometer to measure water vapor content and precipitation rates, and Brazil's space agency provided a device to measure atmospheric humidity.</p>
        <p>While Aqua's measurements are geared toward understanding long-term problems like global climate change, the satellite is also likely to have an immediate effect on everyone.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft's Atmospheric Infrared Sounder, an instrument that measures infrared heat radiation as it leaves the atmosphere, is expected to provide vastly more and better temperature and humidity readings worldwide than are available now from weather satellites and other sources. These readings in 2,378 infrared wavelengths, compared with 24 from most other satellites, will give forecasters greater quantities of more accurate data to put into their computer models.</p>
        <p>Dr. Asrar said five major forecasting groups around the world, including the United States' National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and its National Weather Service, have arranged to get the Aqua data to see if it improves weather forecasts. To meet this need, he said, NASA has arranged to process this data and make it available to forecasters within two hours after it is received.</p>
        <p>Scientists said the data could greatly improve the accuracy of three-day to five-day forecasts of temperature, precipitation and humidity, perhaps making the three-day forecast as accurate as today's 24-hour one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
