<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="05FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1398002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDD1E3AF936A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Arafat Offers Proposal To Reshape Security Force  Yasir Arafat laid out plans to reorganize the Palestinian security apparatus, proposing to consolidate the array of police and intelligence forces into a few streamlined agencies under his direct control. Senior aides to Mr. Arafat said that in a meeting with C.I.A. Director George J. Tenet, the Palestinian leader urged Mr. Tenet to press Israel to stop military incursions into Palestinian-controlled areas. Near Hebron, Israeli soldiers shot and killed a Palestinian teenager in a clash.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>India Rejects Moscow Offer  India rejected a Russian effort to ease tensions with Pakistan. At a summit meeting of 16 Asian and Middle Eastern nations in Kazakhstan, India said it would neither negotiate nor rein in a powerful military buildup until Pakistan halted a flow of armed guerrillas into Kashmir.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>Arafat Offers Proposal To Reshape Security Force  Yasir Arafat laid out plans to reorganize the Palestinian security apparatus, proposing to consolidate the array of police and intelligence forces into a few streamlined agencies under his direct control. Senior aides to Mr. Arafat said that in a meeting with C.I.A. Director George J. Tenet, the Palestinian leader urged Mr. Tenet to press Israel to stop military incursions into Palestinian-controlled areas. Near Hebron, Israeli soldiers shot and killed a Palestinian teenager in a clash.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>India Rejects Moscow Offer  India rejected a Russian effort to ease tensions with Pakistan. At a summit meeting of 16 Asian and Middle Eastern nations in Kazakhstan, India said it would neither negotiate nor rein in a powerful military buildup until Pakistan halted a flow of armed guerrillas into Kashmir.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Rumsfeld Wary on Philippines  Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld said he would not want to expand an American military training mission in the Philippines unless top aides justified a step that would put Army Special Forces at greater risk and probably commit the Pentagon to a longer-term military role there.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Japan Ratifies Warming Accord  Japan ended more than six months of internal debate and ratified the Kyoto Protocol, an international accord on limiting emissions of heat-trapping gasses. Officials said they would lobby the United States and other large polluters to do the same.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>French Rightists Expect Gains  Polls indicate that the extreme-right National Front party is headed for its best showing to date in the northern France, as the country gears up for a two-stage parliamentary election starting on Sunday. Although the party may not ultimately win many seats, it may gain leverage for political horse-trading.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Britain's Jubilee Party Ends  Queen Elizabeth II closed out a four-day national holiday celebrating her 50 years on the throne.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-24</p>
        <p>U.S. Sees Connection In Trade Center Attacks  American intelligence officials said a possible relative of Ramzi Ahmed Yousef, who coordinated the 1993 World Trade Center bombing and a failed plot to bomb American airliners over the Pacific, helped plan the Sept. 11 attacks. Officials said the relative, Khalid Shaikh Mohammed, appeared to be a leading figure in Osama bin Laden's Qaeda network.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The House and Senate intelligence committees said their investigation would examine the government's response to international terrorism dating as far back as 1986.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Fingerprinting and Registration  The Justice Department plans new regulations requiring tens of thousands of Muslim and Middle Eastern visa holders to register with the government and be fingerprinted.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bishops' Proposal on Abuse  A Roman Catholic bishops committee proposed mandatory procedures that would obligate American bishops to remove from the priesthood anyone who abuses a minor in the future, but would allow leeway in old cases involving a single incident.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Left Behind in the 90's  The poor remained entrenched despite the surging economy of the 1990's that brought affluence to many Americans, census data show.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Shifting Medicare Priorities  House Republicans say they will increase Medicare payments to doctors, hospitals and H.M.O.'s, reducing the money available to provide prescription benefits to the elderly.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>New Air Radar System Faulted  A new air traffic-control radar system has serious flaws and is not ready for use, according to the inspector general of the Transportation Department and the union that would maintain it.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Air Pollution Risks Revised  Scientists who made influential studies that linked sooty air pollution with higher death rates lowered their estimate of the risk on bad-air days.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Red Cross to Open Its Books on Donations  American Red Cross officials plan to announce ''major changes'' in fund-raising practices, a response to political pressure arising from anger and concern over the charity's performance in the aftermath of Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Indicts 3 Gottis  Federal prosecutors in Brooklyn announced the indictment of two of John J. Gotti's brothers, his nephew and six other people accused of plundering docks and the dockworkers' union.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Senate Primary  Douglas R. Forrester, a wealthy New Jersey businessman, defeated two rivals in the Republican primary for the United States Senate seat held by Robert G. Torricelli, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Friend vs. Friend  Woody Allen testified that his longtime friend and producer, Jean Doumanian, had betrayed his trust and essentially forced him to sue her for $12 million in movie profits.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Altering of Test Texts Halted  The New York State education commissioner said literary passages in state tests would no longer be altered to delete references to race, religion, sex and other sensitive subjects.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>1 Tony, and Closing  ''Sweet Smell of Success,'' whose star, John Lithgow, won a Tony on Sunday, will close on June 15, after losing about $10 million.</p>
        <p>E3</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-11</p>
        <p>Women's Semifinals Set  Jennifer Capriati, Venus Williams, Serena Williams and Clarisa Fernandez of Argentina advanced to the semifinals of the French Open.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Edison Finds $40 Million  Edison Schools, the largest commercial manager of public schools, said it had arranged to borrow $40 million to finance its takeover of 20 struggling Philadelphia public schools.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Tyco's Ex-Chief Indicted  L. Dennis Kozlowski was accused of evading more than $1 million in sales taxes on six paintings he bought last fall. He pleaded not guilty and was freed on $3 million bail.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. Presses Energy Traders  Federal regulators threatened to strip El Paso, Avista, Portland General Electric and the Williams Companies of the ability to charge unregulated rates for electricity.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>States Sue Drug Maker  Attorneys general from 29 states accused Bristol-Myers Squibb of illegally profiting with schemes to keep lower-priced generic versions of Taxol, a cancer drug, off the market.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: President Mubarak's peace ideas; warily circling the Sept. 11 fund; a new welfare policy for New York.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D12</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
