<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Rocky Start, Whitman Attains Measure of Influence</title>
    <meta content="Y11ENV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/11/politics/11ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1374939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Christine Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD81639F932A25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Rocky Start, Whitman Attains Measure of Influence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Rocky Start, Whitman Attains Measure of Influence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Christie Whitman, administrator of Environmental Protection Agency, who says she has become more comfortable in job after rocky start; she is now being credited with savvier moves within Bush administration and even with prevailing in some high-profile disputes; some critics still maintain she is ineffective, has no feel for finer pressure points of regulatory process, and has undermined her own agency's enforcement efforts against industrial polluters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For some, Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, is becoming the Joan of Arc of the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, last week portrayed her as riding a ''white horse'' and referred repeatedly to the ''battle'' for the environment she is waging within the Bush administration. At a hearing that seemed designed to embarrass the president, Mr. Lieberman heaped praise on Mrs. Whitman and asked for a status report on the battle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For some, Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, is becoming the Joan of Arc of the Bush administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For some, Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, is becoming the Joan of Arc of the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, last week portrayed her as riding a ''white horse'' and referred repeatedly to the ''battle'' for the environment she is waging within the Bush administration. At a hearing that seemed designed to embarrass the president, Mr. Lieberman heaped praise on Mrs. Whitman and asked for a status report on the battle.</p>
        <p>She demurred, saying it was not a battle but a ''vibrant discussion.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, as the hearing ended, Senator Lieberman encouraged her to ''keep up the battle!''</p>
        <p>The exchange revealed how times have changed for her. A year ago, she seemed to have little control over her own agency and little influence in the boys' club of former oil executives in the administration. The president had undercut her often enough that the question in Washington was how much longer she could be humiliated before she resigned.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman even revealed to an interviewer last August that Colin L. Powell, the secretary of state, called her the administration's wind dummy. ''It's a military term for when you are over the landing zone and you don't know what the winds are,'' she said then. ''You push the dummy out the door and see what happens to it.''</p>
        <p>For now, she seems to have parachuted to safety. She is being credited with savvier moves within the administration and even with prevailing on some high-profile disputes. For example, she sided with environmental groups against General Electric, ordering the company to pay $480 million to clean up toxic wastes it had dumped in the Hudson River. She also set acceptable levels of arsenic in drinking water at the same level proposed by the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>In addition, the administration is beginning to play to her personal strengths. The former governor of New Jersey, Mrs. Whitman is to represent the president on Monday in New York City at the six-month commemoration of the attacks on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>''Back in the spring she was still feeling her way,'' said Representative Sherwood L. Boehlert, a New York Republican and leader of pro-environmental Republicans in Congress. ''People see that she is very influential in terms of having her position be considered. She doesn't always win the day, but she has earned the respect of her colleagues.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman still has critics. They say she is ineffective, has no feel for the finer pressure points of the regulatory process and has undermined her own agency's enforcement efforts against industrial polluters. Moreover, they say, her biggest test -- on how far to go in forcing new pollution controls on aging power plants -- is still ahead.</p>
        <p>But even some of those who are hostile to what they see as the administration's pro-industry tilt say Mrs. Whitman has been doing a better job of working the system to her advantage than she did last year.</p>
        <p>''She has been much more careful not to position herself publicly on issues until they have been thoroughly thrashed out in the White House,'' said Phil Clapp, president of the National Environmental Trust.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mrs. Whitman said she had become more comfortable in the job. She said the immediate task of reviewing a host of Clinton regulations when she took office had not allowed her to set priorities. It took time, she said, to assemble her own staff. But now, she said, ''we can set more of a coherent agenda.'' She said her focus was on cleaning up brownfields, old urban industrial sites, and on clean air.</p>
        <p>She also said she had forged a close working relationship with Condoleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's national security adviser, a move that has made her seem less isolated within the administration, Mr. Lieberman's characterization aside. Ms. Rice, along with Secretary Powell, shares Mrs. Whitman's view that the United States cannot ignore the need for global action on greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Despite this, Vice President Dick Cheney may have the strongest hand in the administration, and he and Mrs. Whitman are often at odds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clapp said: ''I think it's pretty clear that she has allies in the cabinet and other parts of the administration who believe in a more moderate approach on most environmental issues. The problem is that the vice president continually marginalizes the entire cabinet.''</p>
        <p>Still, administration officials said that as the president's political advisers look toward Mr. Bush's re-election campaign in 2004, some are becoming more aware of the importance of his environmental record, especially with women and independent voters in the suburbs, for whom the environment is a voting issue. But there is another view in the White House that the hostility from environmental groups and the media is so intense that officials have little incentive to put on an environmentally friendly face.</p>
        <p>''There's a feeling we're going to get killed anyway,'' one official said, ''so why worry about how we'll look?''</p>
        <p>Officials also said Mrs. Whitman had taken a strong stand in demanding that the administration issue a policy, called Clear Skies, on new guidelines for clean air before it issued new rules for pollution controls on power plants. Utility lobbyists wanted the pollution rules issued first because they expect the president to relax the rules, which could save the industry billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>''I was pretty outspoken about that,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''I felt we should get Clear Skies out first before we got the push-back'' on the power plant regulations from environmentalists.</p>
        <p>She rejected the portrait that Senator Lieberman painted of her.</p>
        <p>''This is not an administration that is hellbent on rolling back anything important in environmental protection in order to satisfy industry,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''What the president asks and demands of his cabinet is each of their best arguments for their particular areas of concern. I represent the environment. I will give him my best feelings on things. But he has to make the final decision as to where the balance lies.''</p>
        <p>Still, she hesitated to suggest that her future was settled. Asked if she could survive through the president's first term, she said: ''It's such a long way away, 2004, I just don't know. At this agency, there is always something going on, and when you're on a smooth plane, you hit a great wind bump. The key to me is that I'll stay as long as I think I'm making a positive difference.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
