<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Energy Paper Followed Industry Push</title>
    <meta content="27ENER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/27/business/27ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1379156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Natta, Don Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Abraham, Spencer</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DC103BF934A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Energy Paper Followed Industry Push</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Documents Show Energy Official Met Only With Industry Leaders</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON VAN NATTA Jr. and NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela; Van Natta, Don Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of newly released Energy Department documents show Sec Spencer Abraham met with 109 energy industry and trade association representatives as he helped Bush administration write national energy report in 2001, not 36 reported in department summary; documents show he met with no environmental or consumer group representatives in period; many of executives he met with led corporations that were generous Republican campaign donors; graph of top energy industry political contributors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As he helped the Bush administration write its national energy report last year, Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham heard from more than 100 energy industry executives, trade association leaders and lobbyists, according to documents released by the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham did not meet with any representatives of environmental organizations or consumer groups, the documents show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The energy secretary did not meet with environmental organizations or consumer groups as he helped the Bush administration write its national energy report last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As he helped the Bush administration write its national energy report last year, Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham heard from more than 100 energy industry executives, trade association leaders and lobbyists, according to documents released by the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham did not meet with any representatives of environmental organizations or consumer groups, the documents show.</p>
        <p>In a press release on Monday night, the Energy Department summarized the secretary's calendar by saying that Mr. Abraham met with 36 industry representatives on task force matters. Most news organizations reported that figure today.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Abraham actually met with 109 representatives of energy industry companies and trade associations, according to a comprehensive review of his daily calendar from late January 2001 to May 17, 2001, the day the White House released its national energy report. Many of the executives were leaders of corporations that were among the most generous financial supporters of President Bush's presidential campaign and the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Among the individuals and groups that met with Mr. Abraham, 18 contributed a total of $16.6 million to the Republican Party since 1999, nearly three times what they gave to the Democratic Party, according to an analysis of data compiled by the Center for Responsive Politics.</p>
        <p>Jill Schroeder, spokeswoman for the Energy Department, said the department came up with its figure of 36 industry representatives meeting with Mr. Abraham based on executives who had asked to discuss the work of the task force with Mr. Abraham, who was an influential task force member. But many of the other meetings not counted by the Energy Department also dealt with the executives' interest in topics covered by the national energy policy.</p>
        <p>''He's the energy secretary, he meets with these folks about energy issues,'' Ms. Schroeder said. ''It's his job.''</p>
        <p>Energy Department officials also pointed out that Mr. Abraham occasionally rebuffed energy industry executives. Officials said 23 requests for meetings from industry leaders were denied. Kenneth L. Lay and Jeffrey K. Skilling, the former top executives of the Enron Corporation, were among the executives who were turned away, officials said. But on March 29, 2001, Mr. Abraham met with two other Enron executives, Joe Hartsoe and Linda Robertson.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Lay met with Vice President Dick Cheney, who headed the task force, on April 17, 2001, to discuss energy policy and the California energy crisis. David Addington, counsel to Mr. Cheney, has said that altogether, Enron executives had six meetings with task force staff members in 2001.</p>
        <p>A coalition of nearly 30 environmental groups asked to meet with Mr. Abraham to discuss the energy policy on Feb. 20, 2001. Energy Department officials declined the request, citing Mr. Abraham's ''busy schedule,'' department officials said.</p>
        <p>But in the days following, Mr. Abraham met with numerous industry representatives, including a top executive of the American Coal Company; the chairman of UtiliCorp United, a power company now known as Aquila Inc.; executives from a half-dozen utility companies; executives from a half-dozen nuclear power corporations and the corporate leaders of ExxonMobil, BP/Amoco, Shell, ChevronTexaco, Anadarko Petroleum and Ashland Inc.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, the White House press secretary, said today: ''News flash -- no surprise to anybody, the secretary of energy meets with energy-related groups.''</p>
        <p>Over three days in late February 2001, Mr. Abraham met with six petroleum executives, a railroad executive and the leader of a coal producing company. On Feb. 21, he met with executives of five oil companies, including David O'Reilly, the president of ChevronTexaco, and Steven Miller, the president and chief executive of Shell Oil Company.</p>
        <p>The next day, Feb. 22, Mr. Abraham met with John W. Snow, the chief executive of the CSX Corporation, one of the nation's largest railroad companies. According to Mr. Abraham's calendar, the meeting's topics included ''the role coal plays in electric utility generation, mountaintop mining and the National Energy and Environmental Technology Act.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham also met with a number of energy industry lobbyists, including Haley Barbour, who represents utility companies, and Tom Kuhn, the executive director of the utility industry trade group, the Edison Electric Institute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham's calendar was among the 11,000 pages of documents that Democratic lawmakers and environmental groups said today demonstrated that the administration sought the advice of utility companies, oil companies and the producers of natural gas, coal and nuclear energy in developing its energy policy.</p>
        <p>Congressional Democrats and environmental groups have long argued that the administration relied on advice from industry leaders while spurning environmentalists who were arguing for conservation, renewable energy sources and energy efficiency measures. Today, the groups said that Mr. Abraham's calendar has proved that suspicion.</p>
        <p>''The documents indicate that great deference was given to energy industry executives and lobbyists and almost none was given to the environmental industry and the concerns of consumer groups,'' said Larry Klayman, chairman and general counsel of Judicial Watch, the legal watchdog group and one of several groups that sued executive branch agencies for the documents' release.</p>
        <p>The boxes of documents released by the Energy Department include hundreds of internal e-mail messages that are heavily edited. Other apparently benign e-mail messages are entirely blank; some blank pages have tantalizing titles like, ''Importance: High.'' The Energy Department also failed to print out e-mail attachments; one was titled ''proposed energy policy language.''</p>
        <p>Energy officials cited an array of exemptions to the Freedom of Information Act, including internal deliberations about policy and personnel matters.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the two groups that sued to get the documents said today that they would ask federal judges to review the full texts of the edited documents and press for their complete release. They also complained that the Energy Department refused to release an additional 15,000 pages of documents.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot missing,'' said Sharon Buccino, a senior lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council, another organization that sued to get the records. ''We have 11,000 pages of scrubbed, purged and sanitized documents. Even despite those efforts to hide the documents, they are littered with evidence of industry access.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Schroeder said that all outside documents submitted to the Energy Department were made public. ''What we have withheld is not any kind of communication between D.O.E. and anyone on the outside but discussions inside the administration about what the report should say,'' she said. ''It is standard practice not to produce information about such discussions.''</p>
        <p>The documents include papers from industry representatives about the relationship between gasoline consumption and air pollution. The Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers noted in a report to the Energy Department on March 22, 2001, that ''fuel economy standards are an ineffective energy policy.''</p>
        <p>The federal task force essentially accepted that argument. Instead of calling for new fuel efficiency standards, it recommended only that new standards receive further study.</p>
        <p>And the energy policy report warned that increases in fuel efficiency had to be done ''without negatively impacting the U.S. automotive industry.''</p>
        <p>The Energy Department noted that the National Mining Association asked for an overhaul of the New Source Review program, an Environmental Protection Agency regulation that requires power plants, oil refineries and other industrial plants to meet new emissions standards when they undertake a major upgrade of operations. The energy industry has fought the regulation for years, claiming it lacks clarity.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration is now trying to overhaul the rule, a move that has touched off debate between the Energy Department and the Environmental Protection Agency, and within the agency itself.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schroeder said that other Energy Department officials met five environmental and consumer groups -- the American Council for an Energy Efficient Economy, the Sierra Club, Environmental Defense, Resources for the Future and the American Wind Energy Association. And she said five other groups did not respond to a request for comments, including the World Wildlife Fund and Greenpeace.</p>
        <p>Gary Skulnik, a Greenpeace spokesman, said yesterday that ''a low-level staffer called us on March 22, 2001, and gave us 24 hours to provide any input we had on energy policy.'' The organization decided not to scramble to meet the tight deadline.</p>
        <p>''If they were serious about getting input,'' Mr. Skulnik said, ''that was certainly not the way to go about it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
