<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pushed to the Margins, She Stood Her Ground</title>
    <meta content="06COV.$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1357142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roukema, Marge (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD91030F935A35752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pushed to the Margins, She Stood Her Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on US Repr Marge Roukema, New Jersey's most senior member of Congress, who was passed over by Republican Party for job as head of House Financial Services Committee; Roukema, who has served for two decades, is outspoken moderate in party that has become more conservative; repeatedly has found herself at odds with Republican leaders on host of issues; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN now, a year later, Marge Roukema still bristles at the way Congress snubbed her.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema, New Jersey's most senior member of Congress, had been in line to head the House's powerful Financial Services Committee, a job she very much wanted. But when the position finally opened up in January, leaders of her own party passed her over despite her seniority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN now, a year later, Marge Roukema still bristles at the way Congress snubbed her.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema, New Jersey's most senior member of Congress, had been in line to head the House's powerful Financial Services Committee, a job she very much wanted. But when the position finally opened up in January, leaders of her own party passed her over despite her seniority.</p>
        <p>''The fact that I was a woman had something to do with it,'' Mrs. Roukema protested as recently as last month.</p>
        <p>That episode, in many ways, captures how marginalized Mrs. Roukema has become, even after two decades of service in Congress. Mrs. Roukema, an outspoken moderate, represents a wing of the Republican Party that is less and less welcome here in the nation's capital as conservatives assert greater control over the party agenda, particularly in the House.</p>
        <p>''I think Marge Roukema's ability to bargain was probably greater under the Democratic majority, whose leaders were willing to offer her something'' in return for her vote, said Stephen Salmore, a Republican political consultant who is also professor of political science at Fairleigh Dickinson University. ''Republican leaders resented her independence.''</p>
        <p>Again and again, Mrs. Roukema found herself at odds with Republican leaders on a host of issues, from abortion rights and gun control to campaign finance reform. Her difficulties only mounted after George W. Bush moved into the White House with an agenda that frequently placed moderates like Mrs. Roukema in the unenviable position of having to choose between their principles and their president.</p>
        <p>The political climate has been just as trying back home in New Jersey. In her last two campaigns, the congresswoman has had to fend off tough primary challenges from the party's conservative wing. Mrs. Roukema won both times, but the victories were remarkably narrow for a sitting member of Congress with her seniority.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has had enough.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, the 11-term lawmaker from Ridgewood announced that she intended to retire at the end of the year. Mrs. Roukema insisted that her decision had nothing to do with the direction her party had taken in recent years or the assaults she had come under. Still, she clearly sounded exasperated.</p>
        <p>In one of her first interviews since announcing her retirement, Mrs. Roukema, 72, warned that unless the Republican Party made room for centrists like herself, voters would turn away from it.</p>
        <p>''There has to be a recognition that without the moderates,'' she said, ''we cannot be a majority party.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema also looked back on the successes and disappointments of her two decades in office. She spoke of the political price she had to pay for her outspokenness. But far from voicing regret, Mrs. Roukema took pride in her accomplishments along with her willingness to stand by her principles, even when that made her a political outcast.</p>
        <p>''I make up my own mind and go my own way,'' Mrs. Roukema said one recent afternoon as she sat behind her desk in the Rayburn House Office Building.</p>
        <p>It would be a mistake to conclude that Mrs. Roukema is ending her career on a bad note, however. Maurice Carroll, the director of the Quinnipiac University Polling Institute, said that Mrs. Roukema continued to be an enormously popular figure within her district despite the trouble she has run into with Republican leaders.</p>
        <p>He noted that Mrs. Roukema had consistently won decisive victories in the general elections after squeaking by in Republican primaries. Mr. Carroll also contended that Mrs. Roukema's brand of Republicanism was very well received not only in her district but also among New Jersey's relatively moderate voters.</p>
        <p>''The kind of Republicans who get elected in New Jersey are moderates,'' Mr. Carroll explained. ''Marge Roukema typifies that. She is a solid suburban Republican. She is a perfect representative of where she comes from.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema's involvement in politics began in the early 1970's, when she returned to the Republican Party after a short time as a Democrat. It was a statement for this New Jersey mother, doctor's wife and school board member. But Mrs. Roukema did not feel completely at home with the Republican Party. The party was showing conservative impulses, and Mrs. Roukema felt obliged to play a larger role in shaping the Republican agenda.</p>
        <p>The first opportunity presented itself in 1977 when a moderate named Tom Kean decided to run for governor. Mrs. Roukema volunteered to work in his campaign and quickly became Mr. Kean's campaign coordinator in 30 towns. Mr. Kean lost that year, but Mrs. Roukema found a new calling.</p>
        <p>A year later, Mrs. Roukema decided to launch her own campaign, making an unsuccessful bid for Congress. In 1980, she ran again -- and won in the Reagan landslide. The victory came after a tough campaign in which Mrs. Roukema attacked the Democratic incumbent, Andrew Maguire, as a liberal who was out of touch with the district.</p>
        <p>Once in office, Mrs. Roukema placed health care near the top of her agenda, partly as a result of a personal ordeal she went through years earlier: the death of her son Todd in 1976 as a result of leukemia. To this day, Mrs. Roukema has sought to push the federal government into playing a greater role in managing the nation's health care system, even when that goal has put her at odds with Republicans who see it as big-government meddling.</p>
        <p>In that sense, it is not surprising that her proudest accomplishment in Congress is a controversial law requiring employers to give up to 12 weeks of unpaid leave to workers with family health care emergencies. It had been vetoed twice by a Republican President, George H. W. Bush, before being signed into law by a Democrat, Bill Clinton, in 1992.</p>
        <p>''This was my major accomplishment,'' Mrs. Roukema recalled. ''And Bill Clinton made it a signature item during the campaign he ran against George Bush? That was my bill! That was my legislation!''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has also been one of her party's most prominent supporters of women's issues typically taken up by Democrats, including abortion rights and the Equal Rights Amendment. But curiously enough, she bristles at being called a feminist, perhaps because that label is frequently associated with liberal Democrats.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has also stood out because of her willingness to challenge the Republican Party's ideological excesses, particularly in recent years as the conservative wing has become more and more prominent.</p>
        <p>On welfare, for example, there were plenty of Republicans who sought to demonize women collecting public assistance. But in 1984, it was Mrs. Roukema who proposed legislation that eventually became a major tool in helping reduce the welfare rolls in the 1990's: making it easier for single mothers to collect unpaid child support from so-called deadbeat dads.</p>
        <p>''We often talk about the Republican Party as being the party of family values,'' she said in explaining the reason she sponsored the measure. ''What's more family-value oriented than child support?''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema also protested loudly when her Republican colleagues in the House tried to kill the National Endowment for the Arts, warning that their ideological zealotry would badly damage the party.</p>
        <p>In the end, however, the stature of moderate Republicans like Mrs. Roukema began to diminish substantially in the aftermath of 1994 House elections when Newt Gingrich, the fiery House speaker at the time, charged his party with the Contract on America. Those elections gave Republicans control of the lower chamber for the first time in four decades.</p>
        <p>That, in turn, ushered in a period of conservative Republican dominance, beginning with Mr. Gingrich and continuing to this day under the stewardship of such hard-liners as Dick Armey of Texas, the majority leader, and Tom Delay, also of Texas, the majority whip.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was Mr. DeLay who rejected Mrs. Roukema's attempt to lead the Financial Services Committee last January, apparently because he was annoyed with her willingness to cross party lines. Mrs. Roukema acknowledged that her independence cost her that job. But she added that there were two other reasons she didn't get the job: the fact that she was a woman, and the fact that she did not raise enough money to steer to the campaigns of her fellow House Republicans.</p>
        <p>This year, Mrs. Roukema's troubles within the party were compounded by the arrival of a new Republican president, George W. Bush. Many moderates in the party had hoped Mr. Bush would temper the ideological fervor of the party's conservative wing, given that he christened himself a ''compassionate conservative'' during the campaign. But those hopes were quickly dashed once he took office.</p>
        <p>On issue after issue, Mrs. Roukema and her fellow moderates found themselves at odds with the President.</p>
        <p>In April, Mrs. Roukema felt compelled to fire off a letter to the president after his administration reversed itself on limiting carbon dioxide emissions from power plants.</p>
        <p>''Mr. President, health and safety first!'' she wrote. ''We urge you in the strongest possible terms to reconsider your decision.''</p>
        <p>In July, Mrs. Roukema defied President Bush once again, openly supporting a patients' rights bill that Democrats and Mr. Bush's chief rival in the Republican Party, Senator John McCain of Arizona, pushed through the Senate. In the end, President Bush got House Republican leaders to counter that proposal with one that was more to his liking.</p>
        <p>That same month, Mrs. Roukema defied the president in the contentious debate over revamping the nation's campaign finance laws -- another measure with the ardent backing of Senator McCain. Mrs. Roukema was among a handful of moderates who endorsed a bill that the president opposed. More than that, she agreed to join an effort to bring the bill to the floor of the House in defiance of House leaders.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has even found herself clashing with the White House since the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, even though the president has been enjoying a remarkable degree of popularity in public opinion polls from Democrats as well as Republicans.</p>
        <p>In November, Mrs. Roukema criticized the Bush administration for supporting a bill pushed by his party's conservative wing that rejected the complete federalization of airport security that many Americans seemed to want.</p>
        <p>Like other moderates, Mrs. Roukema complained that the president and his conservative allies had given a powerful campaign issue to Democrats, who supported a bill that would make all 28,000 airport baggage and passenger screeners federal employees.</p>
        <p>''I simply do not understand it,'' Mrs. Roukema said at the time after voting against the president's bill in the House. ''I just have to shake my head. The Democrats will beat us up and down on it, no question about that. But besides the politics, we'll be inviting more airline disasters and putting more lives at risk.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Bush relented on the matter, signing into law a compromise bill that strongly resembled the Democratic measure.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has shown some flexibility herself with the administration. Like many moderates, for example, she initially opposed the Bush administration's proposal to allow oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. But in the end, Mrs. Roukema joined House Republicans this summer in approving an energy bill proposed by the president even though it allowed for oil drilling in the Alaskan wildlife refuge.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mrs. Roukema said that she decided to back the bill because she felt it would help the nation reduce its reliance on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>''Do we want to be more dependent on Middle East oil?'' she said. ''We have to do what we reasonably can to increase energy resources here in our hemisphere.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema has also had her share of political difficulties back home in New Jersey. She Roukema was never able to establish herself as the leader of the state's Congressional delegation despite the fact that she was known as the dean of the delegation because of her seniority. Nor was she ever considered a major force within New Jersey Republican circles, according political analysts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salmore, the Republican political consultant, said that the popularity she enjoyed in her own districted never translated into a larger, statewide political base.</p>
        <p>''She was personally very popular,'' he said. ''But I don't think she was a very heavy hitter within Jersey Republican politics.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema wasn't immune to trouble even in her own backyard of the Fifth Congressional District. She came under increasing attack from conservatives in the district, where she was almost unseated in two recent primary challenges. The closeness of those two races, in 1998 and then in 2000, suggested that her hold on the Fifth District was slipping.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Roukema scoffs at that suggestion, saying that she is as popular as ever in her district, and pointed to the differences between results in the primary and general elections in 2000, the last time she had to defend her seat.</p>
        <p>In the Republican primary fight, Mrs. Roukema defeated a more conservative opponent, Assemblyman E. Scott Garrett, by a mere 1,992 votes. But in the general election, she trounced the Democrat, Linda A. Mercurio, 65 percent to 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema also said that her primary opponent got as far as he did because he received huge infusions of campaign money from national conservative groups seeking to oust her, including the National Rifle Association and the Right to Life organization.</p>
        <p>''I still get strong support within the district,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Roukema also sought to dispel any notion that she was retiring because of the recent challenges waged against her. She said she wanted to spend time more time with her family, as well as on other pursuits, like undertaking projects to help children and being a guest lecturer at colleges.</p>
        <p>''I don't want anyone to infer that I am retiring because I am intimidated by primaries,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Never a woman to back down, she said: ''I believe in sticking to my principles. It's one of the reasons I started running for public office.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
