<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sense of Wonder Under the Sea</title>
    <meta content="27SALA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/27/arts/television/27SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1362596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fothergill, Alastair</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Blue Planet, The: Sea of Life (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Discovery Channel</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fothergill, Alastair</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DC133BF934A15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sense of Wonder Under the Sea</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Blue Planet': A Sense of Wonder Under the Sea</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews BBC-Discovery Channel documentary series Blue Planet: Sea of Life, produced by Alastair Fothergill; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PREPARING a promotional interview for ''The Blue Planet: Seas of Life,'' his breathtaking nature epic, Alastair Fothergill, the series' producer, was asked what surprised him most during five years of filming this vast exploration of the world's oceans. ''I was surprised by the amount of failure,'' Mr. Fothergill said. ''I knew there would be failure but not on that scale.''</p>
        <p>Only a world-class perfectionist -- and Mr. Fothergill clearly is that -- would lament the ones that got away, when his cameras captured one extraordinary image after another of creatures both familiar and bizarre. What appear to be black oil slicks off the coast of South Africa turn out to be millions of swarming sardines. In the deepest part of the ocean we see a netherworld populated by transparent and neon marine life -- living special effects, including an octopus the filmmakers call Dumbo because it looks like a morphed version of the Disney elephant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An epic nature series on the Discovery Channel recalls the days when Jacques Cousteau made the oceans miraculous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PREPARING a promotional interview for ''The Blue Planet: Seas of Life,'' his breathtaking nature epic, Alastair Fothergill, the series' producer, was asked what surprised him most during five years of filming this vast exploration of the world's oceans. ''I was surprised by the amount of failure,'' Mr. Fothergill said. ''I knew there would be failure but not on that scale.''</p>
        <p>Only a world-class perfectionist -- and Mr. Fothergill clearly is that -- would lament the ones that got away, when his cameras captured one extraordinary image after another of creatures both familiar and bizarre. What appear to be black oil slicks off the coast of South Africa turn out to be millions of swarming sardines. In the deepest part of the ocean we see a netherworld populated by transparent and neon marine life -- living special effects, including an octopus the filmmakers call Dumbo because it looks like a morphed version of the Disney elephant.</p>
        <p>A product of the BBC's natural history division, co-produced by the Discovery Channel, the eight-hour ''Blue Planet'' is unabashedly, poetically awestruck, yet unsentimental. There's lots of sex and violence (none of it gratuitous), but, thankfully, no cute anthropomorphizing. The first four hourlong installments will be shown on Discovery tonight and tomorrow; the series will continue in May.</p>
        <p>Since the advent of Discovery and its spin-offs, including Animal Planet, television has become rife with nature. It's much harder to recreate the sense of wonder viewers must have felt when Jacques Cousteau began filming his underwater investigations in the 1950's. Cousteau subsequently became a television star and pop culture figure with his documentary specials, called ''The Undersea World of Jacques Cousteau,'' which were shown on ABC for a decade, then moved to PBS in the 1970's and finally to cable, reflecting the evolution of television itself. As nature documentaries became a television staple, Cousteau, who died in 1997, found it difficult to contend with all the competition, even if no one matched his idiosyncratic charm and intensity.</p>
        <p>Ambitious and beautiful, ''Blue Planet'' contains echoes of those days when the chance to witness natural exotica at home seemed miraculous. Though not a swashbuckler like Cousteau, Sir David Attenborough, who began doing nature broadcasts 48 years ago, narrates with brisk authority and vivid, unadorned prose (and never appears on-screen). Introducing the frozen nothingness of the Arctic, he simply says, ''For much of the year it is dark and cripplingly cold.''</p>
        <p>The images are startling, right from the start. The series opens with a rare overhead shot of a blue whale, 100 feet long, and never loses its visual momentum. The prevailing sense of grandeur is reinforced by George Fenton's emphatic music; no surprise to learn that his credits include the scores for the films ''Gandhi'' and ''Cry Freedom,'' both directed by Sir David's brother Sir Richard.</p>
        <p>''Blue Planet'' isn't an ecological piece about impending global warming or endangered species. It is strictly observational, bent on exploring places where humans have hardly been before -- which turns out to be a surprisingly big chunk of the earth. More people have traveled into outer space than to the bottom of the ocean, Sir David says in the introduction to ''The Deep,'' the fourth and most visually astonishing segment. Filmed from inside a specially outfitted submersible, a mini-submarine designed to go to the ocean floor, this segment brings viewers face to face with some truly strange creatures.</p>
        <p>They include the fangtooth fish, with teeth so big it can't close its mouth, and the hairy angler, as grotesque as its name implies, with frantic-looking eyes and antennas sprouting everywhere. The submersible's headlights reveal spectacular iridescent markings and animals that have adapted to this dark, cold environment by becoming completely transparent.</p>
        <p>The underwater cameras scan landscapes of cliffs and mountains, though the most surprising find is an underwater lake, complete with tide line and sandy shore (the ''sand'' is actually piles of mussels crammed together). The filmmakers also discovered tubeworms and other organisms that live in complete darkness, without energy from the sun. Watching this film, the realization thoroughly sinks in: when you've been to the bottom of the ocean, you've definitely been somewhere you've never been before.</p>
        <p>Dolphins may be familiar, but they are crowd pleasers, so they, too, are given their due. So are sharks, of course, superstar predators of nature programming (''Shark Week'' has been a persistent ratings draw on Discovery for 14 years.)</p>
        <p>While it's possible to enjoy ''Blue Planet'' as a purely hypnotic experience, the filmmakers have made it educational as well as visceral. (The four episodes will repeat twice Friday, beginning at 7 p.m., and then from 9 a.m. to 11 a.m. Saturday and next Sunday, perhaps giving younger viewers a better chance to see them.) Facts abound about the hottest, the fastest, the coldest, the deepest. But more memorable than the data are images demonstrating the interconnectedness of life in the starkest terms. We can watch what happens when ocean currents stir up nutrients that attract fish, which become magnets for sharks. And when El Niño causes temperatures to rise, the fungus that grows on sharks becomes a snack for little fish.</p>
        <p>''Frozen Seas,'' the second segment, about life at the poles, may be the most compelling -- especially for those of us with a weakness for polar bears and penguins. The filmmakers capture the stunning majesty of that frigid terrain and the terrible beauty of blood spilled in the name of survival.</p>
        <p>One sequence focuses on a cluster of beluga whales turning frantic somersaults, their thin bodies scarred by assaults from bears. A giant polar bear parks itself by the ice hole where the belugas are swimming, waiting for them to pop up for air. It's a long wait, but the bear is patient, even after diving into the hole and hauling itself out with a magnificent shudder, but no whale. The bear waits for days until he lands his prey. The kill produces a striking image, as the bright red blood stains the pristine white-on-white of ice, snow, bear. The bear feeds until it's stuffed, but there are lots of leftovers; even a starving whale literally weighs a ton. Gulls and wolves converge on the carcass.</p>
        <p>The filmmakers specialize in crowd scenes (of turtles, sharks, fish, birds), but the best ones appear in ''Frozen Seas.'' Hordes of shrieking chinstrap penguins gather on a volcano to breed, pulsing with the urgency of teenagers at a rock concert. In the Antarctic, emperor penguins huddle en masse on the frozen sea, trying to protect themselves from the fierce winds. Other penguins shoot out of the water like rockets to escape from hungry seals, but once they land on shore trudge through the snow like tired old men.</p>
        <p>Thirty-five photographers are credited, and they were apparently working nonstop. Filming at night, they spotted Olive Ridley turtles crawling onto the Pacific shoreline of Costa Rica to lay eggs. Sir David reports that 400,000 turtles lay 40 million eggs a season, and then shows us why: when the eggs are washed out of the sand by strong tides, vultures eat them. Therefore the turtles lay their eggs in the first and fourth quarters of the moon's cycle, when its pull is weakest, one of many poignant demonstrations of both the fragility and durability of life.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
