<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans Give Bush Plan on Climate Change a Tepid Reception</title>
    <meta content="Y15REAX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/15/international/europe/15REAX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1368016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFD6153FF936A25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans Give Bush Plan on Climate Change a Tepid Reception</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europeans Give Bush Plan on Climate Change a Tepid Reception</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Daley, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Union gives tepid welcome to Pres Bush's new proposals, strictly voluntary, to address climate change (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saying that any action taken to reduce emissions of heat-trapping gases was at least a step in the right direction, the European Union gave a tepid welcome today to President Bush's new proposals to tackle climate change.</p>
        <p>The Bush proposals, which are strictly voluntary, would rely on tax credits to coax big business to pollute less. As word of the proposals began to filter out, many environmentalists and political commentators in Europe said that Mr. Bush's plan was far too little, too late, and would not improve his image abroad as a servant of the oil industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Union gave a tepid welcome on Thursday to President Bush's new proposals to tackle climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saying that any action taken to reduce emissions of heat-trapping gases was at least a step in the right direction, the European Union gave a tepid welcome today to President Bush's new proposals to tackle climate change.</p>
        <p>The Bush proposals, which are strictly voluntary, would rely on tax credits to coax big business to pollute less. As word of the proposals began to filter out, many environmentalists and political commentators in Europe said that Mr. Bush's plan was far too little, too late, and would not improve his image abroad as a servant of the oil industry.</p>
        <p>The most outspoken reaction came from France, where the head of an intergovernmental task force on global warming calling the proposals ''window dressing.''</p>
        <p>The expert, Philippe Meunier, said that although it was hard to judge the new plan before knowing its details, ''the total volunteerism approach makes us worry.''</p>
        <p>''It lacks credibility,'' Mr. Meunier added. ''We worry that without sanctions it just won't work.''</p>
        <p>He asserted that while the plan was a step in the right direction, it showed that the United States sought change ''at no cost and in a way that would not in any way challenge the American lifestyle and especially its consumption.''</p>
        <p>Echoing the concerns of most other specialists reacting today, Mr. Meunier evoked the Kyoto Protocol, the widely accepted treaty that would require emissions cuts by 2010 to well below their 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>The Bush plan might ''destabilize'' support for the Kyoto pact, which is awaiting ratification.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Meunier put it, ''You may have countries that say, why should we who are poorer do anything?''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration's rejection of the protocol last March caused an outcry in Europe and came to be seen here as another example of America's refusal to limit its options in almost any sphere.</p>
        <p>When he rejected the treaty, Mr. Bush called its targets arbitrary, its schedule too costly to meet and its terms unfair.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, no other country has chosen to abandon it.</p>
        <p>The voluntary measures in the plan Mr. Bush unveiled today would, if followed, slow but not halt the growth in emissions of heat-trapping gases linked to global warming. It would use $4.6 billion in tax credits over the next five years to encourage companies and individuals to limit those emissions.</p>
        <p>In Brussels, a European Commission spokeswoman, Pia Ahrenkilde-Hansen, said, ''We feel that the multilateral approach is the best way to face up to this tremendous challenge.'' She said that the European Union still hoped the United States would return to the Kyoto pact.</p>
        <p>In Britain, Chris Hewett of the Institute for Public Policy Research, added his voice to criticism of the plan as not enough. He said Britain had proved ''that you can cut emissions and still have a healthy economy,'' adding that there was no ''inextricable link'' between carbon dioxide emissions and economic growth.</p>
        <p>Some green groups said they were suspicious of the timing of the White House announcement, just days before Mr. Bush is scheduled to meet with Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi in Japan.</p>
        <p>Japan has so far remained committed to the Kyoto pact, but it has made no secret of the fact that it will have difficulty meeting its targets.</p>
        <p>Hiroshi Oki, the new Japanese environment minister, said it would be best for the United States to return to the the protocol.</p>
        <p>But, he said that ''our joint efforts'' must not be halted by disagreement on that point.</p>
        <p>The only real praise for the Bush administration had nothing to do with the environmental proposal.</p>
        <p>In Germany, Hans-Joachim Schellnhuber, director of the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research and a member of the government's advisory council, made a point of citing a second American plan announced today, one that affects emissions but not global warming. He hailed Mr. Bush's call for mandatory restrictions on three power plant pollutants -- mercury, sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides -- as ''a great air pollution policy.''</p>
        <p>''A wonderful policy,'' Mr. Schellnhuber added. ''But the wrong target.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
