<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Camellia Grows In Boston</title>
    <meta content="26DELT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/26/opinion/26DELT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1443798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Del Tredici, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D71E39F935A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Camellia Grows In Boston</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Camellia Grows in Boston</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Del Tredici</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Del Tredici, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Del Tredici Op-Ed article on shift in growing patterns brought about by climate change in world that is getting warmer; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there's one trait that gardeners have in common, it's a desire to grow plants that experts tell them they shouldn't be able to grow. Be it bamboo in Boston, evergreen magnolias in New York or tree ferns in Atlanta, the urge to cultivate something that nobody else in the neighborhood has runs deep. Whether this passion comes from a need to compete, to experiment or just to be different is irrelevant. What counts is pushing the limits of possibility and proving the experts wrong.</p>
        <p>But what happens when the limits of possibility are pushed not by gardeners but by climate change? Some of the joy leaves the enterprise; ambivalence seeps in. At least it has for me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gardeners share a desire to grow plants that experts tell them they shouldn't be able to grow. But what happens when the limits of possibility are pushed by climate change?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there's one trait that gardeners have in common, it's a desire to grow plants that experts tell them they shouldn't be able to grow. Be it bamboo in Boston, evergreen magnolias in New York or tree ferns in Atlanta, the urge to cultivate something that nobody else in the neighborhood has runs deep. Whether this passion comes from a need to compete, to experiment or just to be different is irrelevant. What counts is pushing the limits of possibility and proving the experts wrong.</p>
        <p>But what happens when the limits of possibility are pushed not by gardeners but by climate change? Some of the joy leaves the enterprise; ambivalence seeps in. At least it has for me.</p>
        <p>The arboretum where I work has given me a special vantage point from which to witness -- and react to -- the shift in growing patterns brought on by a world that's getting warmer. The Arnold Arboretum was founded in 1872 for the purpose of scientific research. Its charter specifies that it cultivate ''as far as practicable, all the trees, shrubs, and herbaceous plants, either indigenous or exotic, which can be raised in the open air.''</p>
        <p>It's a concept that has its origins in the passion for collecting that characterized the Victorian era in America, and it's one to which the arboretum has remained true throughout its history. We gather plants from all over the world, grow them outdoors in Boston and see how they fare. For the first 114 years, observations were recorded on index cards; since 1986 they've been fed into a computer.</p>
        <p>The process of testing a plant's adaptability to any given climate is essentially one of trial and error, with the results defying predictability. It is possible, though, to draw a couple of conclusions from the arboretum's experiments. First, plants from parts of the world that have a climate similar to Boston's (in terms of rainfall and temperature) have a greater chance of surviving than plants that come from areas with very different climates.</p>
        <p>Second, there are always exceptions to this rule, most of them attributable to the effects of glaciation, which long ago transported cold-tolerant plants into some very warm climates. Identifying these vestigially hardy plants is one of the most rewarding aspects of my job. It's also one of the most challenging, because a wide variety of environmental factors can influence the survival of a given plant. A series of warmer or wetter years, for example, may allow us to grow something for a time. It's not until a fatal act of nature comes along -- a summer drought or a winter ice storm -- that the true extent of a plant's hardiness is revealed.</p>
        <p>Climate change has complicated this enterprise. To see how, one need only review the arboretum's ''dead files,'' the records of plants that were planted on our grounds but that are no longer living. Take, for example, the Chinese tulip tree, Liriodendron chinense. We first imported this tree from China in 1908. It lived for 11 years. We imported the species at least seven more times over the next 70 years, and the tree never survived more than 15 years and never flowered.</p>
        <p>Last year, two trees we raised from seed imported from China in 1980 flowered for the first time in the history of the arboretum at the age of 22. What does this mean? Simply that this species, which has always been considered marginally hardy in Boston, has finally survived long enough to bloom.</p>
        <p>Another example is Magnolia grandiflora, the famous evergreen magnolia so characteristic of the Deep South. We've been growing this species at the arboretum since 1932, but it has always suffered winter injury and seldom flowered. Since 1984, however, our efforts have been much more successful. Now, our plants bloom almost every year, produce viable seed and make it through the winter with very little damage, except for the breakage of limbs caused by the buildup of ice on their evergreen leaves.</p>
        <p>And finally there's Camellia ''Winter's Star,'' which has survived the past four winters in our outdoor nursery. It's the first camellia ever to make it out onto the grounds, and it's in full bloom right now.</p>
        <p>What's curious about all these observations is my personal reaction to them. At first there is a flush of pride, and even triumph, at being able to accomplish something that hasn't been done before. This is the gardener in me. But then comes the letdown when I realize that I am staring at hard evidence that our climate today is not the same as it was when the arboretum was founded. What should be a horticultural triumph turns out to be a hollow victory -- one that has less to do with skill than it does with a changing climate (and, I imagine, America's love of fossil fuel).</p>
        <p>But this is not the end of the story, for something else is happening to our plants. As the winters have been warming in Boston, the summers have been getting drier, especially over the last decade. This has led to problems with viburnums, umbrella-leaf magnolias and many other plants that have never struggled here before. While a serious drought can kill some plants outright (particularly the very young and the very old), it can also weaken healthy plants, making them more susceptible to insects and disease. Based on my observations, our longstanding concern about the cold hardiness of plants is being trumped by concerns about their tolerance of summer drought. What nature gives with one hand, it takes away with the other.</p>
        <p>Certainly the effects of global climate change are unpredictable. All we really know is that the weather is going to be different than it has been in the past. Unheralded species of plants, waiting in the wings like Broadway understudies, may become dominant over time, while old favorites decline. From the garden where I work, the plants seem to be telling us something we may not want to hear: the world is changing.</p>
        <p>Peter Del Tredici is director of living collections at Harvard University's Arnold Arboretum.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Peter Del Tredici is director of living collections at Harvard University's Arnold Arboretum.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
