<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="03FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1389185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DA1031F930A35756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Announces Gathering To Seek Middle East Peace  The Bush administration will join Europe, Russia and the United Nations in convening an international conference on Middle East peace and economic reconstruction this summer. Details have not been worked out, but foreign ministers and Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, not heads of state, will participate. President Bush repeated his commitment to creation of a Palestinian state but warned that it could not be built ''on a foundation of terror and corruption.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The House and Senate expressed strongly worded support for Israel in its recent military operations.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>U.S. Announces Gathering To Seek Middle East Peace  The Bush administration will join Europe, Russia and the United Nations in convening an international conference on Middle East peace and economic reconstruction this summer. Details have not been worked out, but foreign ministers and Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, not heads of state, will participate. President Bush repeated his commitment to creation of a Palestinian state but warned that it could not be built ''on a foundation of terror and corruption.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The House and Senate expressed strongly worded support for Israel in its recent military operations.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>The Israeli government said Palestinian leaders under Israeli interrogation had implicated Yasir Arafat in the financing of terror attacks. But the statement from Prime Minister Ariel Sharon's office neither provided a link between Mr. Arafat and any particular attack nor produced new documents to back its assertions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>An American-based human rights group said Palestinian claims of hundreds of civilian deaths in Jenin were exaggerated, but its inquiry did find evidence of Israeli abuses and it urged further investigation.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Palestinian negotiators offered a compromise to end the monthlong Church of the Nativity standoff.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>French Rightist on the Stump  Jean-Marie Le Pen continued efforts to refashion his image from an immigrant basher to a people's champion in his last public meeting before the presidential runoff on Sunday.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>New U.S. Embassy in Berlin  Germany and the United States signed an agreement to build an American Embassy on the site of the one that stood until World War II.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Serb Ex-Official Surrenders  Nikola Sainovic, once a top aide to former President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia, surrendered to the war crimes tribunal in The Hague.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Chávez Rebounds After Ouster  President Hugo Chávez of Venezuela said in an interview that his self-proclaimed peaceful revolution would continue, with the goal of reforming an oil-dependent economy and funneling money into social programs.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-20</p>
        <p>Poll Finds U.S. Catholics Support Zero Tolerance  American Roman Catholics say priests who sexually abuse children and teenagers should be barred from participating in parish life, and any accusations of abuse should be investigated by local law enforcement rather than the church, a New York Times/CBS News Poll found. Seventy percent said Catholic lay people should be involved in decisions about cases of abuse by priests.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Rev. Paul R. Shanley, accused of molesting 26 boys while serving in the Boston area, was arrested in San Diego and charged with three counts of child rape in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The Vatican is cracking down on priests it regards as too free in granting group absolution to sinners.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Child Care in Florida  The disappearance of a 5-year-old girl in state custody is an extreme example of an overburdened agency struggling to keep up with an increasing number of vulnerable children, officials and child advocates said.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Democrats and Welfare  A dozen Democratic senators, including Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York, proposed toughening work requirements for people who receive welfare benefits.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Pushing to Arm Pilots  Four senators said airlines and the government should let pilots carry guns, and a Boeing safety expert told a House panel that his company's planes could sustain bullet holes.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Identity Theft Arrests  Federal officials charged several people with using false credentials to cover up a murder, to sell homes belonging to the elderly and to exercise 176,000 stock options belonging to an unknowing company executive.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Bosses Were Last to Know  Interior Secretary Gale A. Norton and the E.P.A. chief, Christie Whitman, said they were caught by surprise when Ms. Whitman's agency issued a letter supporting a snowmobile ban in Yellowstone National Park.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Farm Bill Advancing  The House approved the compromise farm bill, 280 to 141, and President Bush said he would sign it into law once it cleared the Senate.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Lawyer Argues Ex-Officer Was Drunk but Not Culpable  Joseph Gray's lawyer, delivering his closing statement, said his client, who was off duty at the time his van ran down three people in Brooklyn last year, was guilty of drunken driving but not manslaughter because the victims had darted into his path. Jurors began their deliberations.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Ruling on Upstate Casino  A Mohawk casino near Hogansburg is operating under an invalid agreement with New York, a state appeals court panel ruled in a decision that could call into question the legality of any casinos in the state, though it did not address the broader issue of whether casino gambling is allowable.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-34; E35-48</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Tensions Build Over Contract  The New York City teachers' union president accused Mayor Bloomberg of delaying a contract deal despite the apparent infusion of state funds, and she warned that teachers could strike next month.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>College Loan Change Dropped  The White House, facing Congressional opposition, dropped a proposal that would have raised the cost of federally backed college loans.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Nets Advance in Playoffs  The Nets beat Indiana, 120-109, to move into the second round of the N.B.A. playoffs against Charlotte.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>One Answer for Two Questions  Scientists say the hole in the southern polar ozone layer may help explain both global warming and Antarctic cooling.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12, 14</p>
        <p>Scrutiny for Kmart Ex-Officials  Kmart is investigating a group of former executives who presided over the ailing retailer in the months before it filed for bankruptcy protection, and severance payments promised to those executives are being postponed until the inquiry is complete, a lawyer for the company said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Dell's Costly Options Bet  Dell Computer spent $3 billion in its last fiscal year buying back 69 million shares at an average price of about $43 a share, though the average market price was about $25 a share. Dell had to do so because of complicated options deals.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cable Company Revising Books  Adelphia Communications said it was restating its financial statements for the last three years to include more than $1 billion in loans that the embattled cable company had guaranteed to entities controlled by the family of its chairman, John Rigas.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Now that Yasir Arafat is free; children who live in dread; a worthy hate-crimes bill; the Hubble achievement.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E44  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E33  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
