<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Sopranos' Encroaches on the Series</title>
    <meta content="22SAND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/22/sports/baseball/22SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1434053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sopranos, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fox Sports</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fox Sports</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bonds, Barry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED6163CF931A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Sopranos' Encroaches on the Series</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">`Sopranos' Encroaches on Series</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir TV Sports column discusses airing of HBO's popular television series The Sopranos during postseason and World Series games and effect on ratings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is it more important to watch Barry Bonds or Bobby Bacala?</p>
        <p>Liván Hernández or Livia Soprano?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is it more important to watch Barry Bonds or Bobby Bacala? Liván Hernández or Livia Soprano? The Big A or the Bada Bing?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is it more important to watch Barry Bonds or Bobby Bacala?</p>
        <p>Liván Hernández or Livia Soprano?</p>
        <p>The Big A or the Bada Bing?</p>
        <p>The 16-month layoff before the start of the current season of ''The Sopranos'' led that HBO show into October for the first time, creating a poser: what does a baseball fan watch on Sundays in October from 9 to 10 p.m. Eastern?</p>
        <p>There is evidence that Team Soprano is muscling in on baseball's postseason. Consider Oct. 13, when ''The Sopranos'' was shown against Game 4 of the National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>From 8:30 to 9 p.m., the game on Fox generated a 7.5 Nielsen rating (or 5.5 million households) in 55 major markets across the country. But from 9 to 9:30, the rating dipped to a 7.2, then rose to a 7.4 from 9:30 to 10 o'clock (forming the lowest-rated hour of the game). But in the half-hour after ''The Sopranos,'' the rating spiked to an 8.6.</p>
        <p>The rating for ''The Sopranos'' rose for the first 45 minutes to an 18.2 peak in HBO's universe of 28 million subscribers, ending with an 18.0 for the last 15 minutes (just over five million households).</p>
        <p>Although HBO lacked ratings information for this week's episode, Game 2 of the World Series on Fox showed a ratings sag from 9 to 10, only to recover when ''The Sopranos'' concluded. That period included some of the early offense in Anaheim's 11-10 victory Sunday over San Francisco.</p>
        <p>For this game, the overnight rating began with a 14.1 rating from 8:30 to 9, dipped to a 13.6 from 9 to 10, then leaped to a 15.2 from 10 to 10:30.</p>
        <p>''The Sopranos'' (and maybe another factor or two) thus made 533,500 households -- or more than a million viewers -- disappear from baseball's universe for an hour. HBO's ''Curb Your Enthusiasm'' (not about Lou Piniella's real interest in managing Tampa Bay) evidently could not stop baseball fans from returning to the game.</p>
        <p>So far, this exciting World Series has more than the simmering subplots of ''The Sopranos'' (or the rising rating of NBC's ''Law and Order: Criminal Intent'') to worry about. The overnight rating for Game 1 fell 5.1 percent from last year's Yankees-Arizona World Series to an 11.2, and Game 2 fell 13 percent to a 14.0.</p>
        <p>Already, ratings for the first two games are badly behind those of the Subway Series in 2000, when the Yankees and the Mets played the lowest-rated World Series.</p>
        <p>World Series ratings might benefit if they did not start every year on a Saturday, the least-viewed night of the week. In nearly every World Series, the worst-rated game is the one on Saturday night. And, in a seven-game format that starts on Saturday, two games would be played on Saturday nights, and quite often the lowest-rated games are Games 1 and 6.</p>
        <p>The World Series used to start on Tuesdays, which gave it a chance to post a higher leadoff rating.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that you go into Games 1 and 2, on a Saturday and Sunday, sharing the focus of the day with college football or the National Football League,'' Ed Goren, president of Fox Sports, said from Los Angeles yesterday. ''If you start on Tuesday, you've cleared out college football and there's only a rehash of the N.F.L., and the sole focus is baseball.''</p>
        <p>Goren said there had been talks with Major League Baseball about a switch to a Tuesday start, but it would require starting the playoffs earlier or extending the World Series into November. But he suggested that those who fear chilly baseball Novembers should remember that global warming is not going away. Bowie Kuhn, put your woolies away.</p>
        <p>Football's Conflicts</p>
        <p>When the Jets' 20-7 victory over Minnesota ended Sunday on Channel 5, Fox offered viewers bonus coverage of the San Francisco-New Orleans game. It was a beauty of a game, with the Saints scoring 22 points in the fourth quarter. But just as the 49ers' final series took them downfield, Fox switched away, citing an N.F.L. doubleheader rule that precluded it from staying until the end of the game, lest it bleed into the game about to start at 4:15. Fox then showed commercials before the Tampa Bay-Philadelphia game.</p>
        <p>Before the N.F.L. shifted the kickoff for late games to 4:15 p.m. Eastern from 4 p.m., networks were allowed to show only two one-minute ''cut-ins'' from a game in progress after the main 1 p.m. game in a market ended. ''Then, with the 4:15 games, we said show as much as you want, as long as you get out by 4:15,'' Dennis Lewin, the N.F.L.'s senior vice president for broadcasting, said.</p>
        <p>But bonus coverage can act as an absurd tease if the network has to slip away at the potential conclusion of a game to insert a mandated, unmovable block of commercials sold by local stations, not the network.</p>
        <p>''People in bonus coverage want to see that,'' Lewin said, ''but a lot more people want to see the start of the 4:15 game.''</p>
        <p>Fox's Goren said, ''More often than not, most viewers see bonus coverage and the conclusion to the game, but you can be in an awkward position when you set the table, capture viewer attention and you can't pay it off.''</p>
        <p>Goren said the only solution was one that the N.F.L. would never offer: delay the kickoff of the later game until the earlier one was over.</p>
        <p>Fox almost found itself with a football-caused delay when the Dallas-Arizona game went into overtime, cutting into the World Series pregame show on Sunday night. Had Arizona not won, 9-6, with a field goal with 3 minutes 10 seconds left in overtime, the game might have continued for several more minutes.</p>
        <p>At that point, the Dallas and Phoenix markets would have continued getting the game, damaging World Series viewership.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
