<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Realism in Cutting Emissions</title>
    <meta content="15HUBB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/15/opinion/15HUBB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1367929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council of Economic Advisers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubbard, R Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE153FF936A25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Realism in Cutting Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Realism in Cutting Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. Glenn Hubbard</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hubbard, R Glenn</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by R Glenn Hubbard, chairman of President's Council of Economic Advisers, says climate policy announced by Pres Bush sets out better and more workable approach for measuring progress against global warming than one in Kyoto framework he rejected; notes that president set specific goals for reducing greenhouse gas intensity rather than arbitrary goal for curbs on total emissions; says fixed emission limit harms economy, while tying goals to economic activity, as president's policy does, encourages flexible response without economic risk; calls Bush's plan reasonable approach to slow, stop and then reverse growth in greenhouse gas emissions without wrecking economy in the process (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The climate policy President Bush announced yesterday sets out a better and far more workable approach for measuring progress against global warming than the one in the Kyoto framework he rejected last spring. The president set the goal of an 18 percent reduction over the next 10 years in greenhouse gas intensity -- the ratio of emissions to economic activity -- rather than an arbitrary goal for curbs on total emissions. And he announced steps to get there.</p>
        <p>This emphasis not only removes a large part of the economic risk associated with goals based on a fixed emission limit, but gives American industries a target, similar to a goal for productivity or efficiency, that they can shoot for in practical ways. Because it is realistic and workable, it is likely to move us, at last, beyond arguments at the extremes and toward real action against climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The climate policy President Bush announced on Thursday sets out a better and far more workable approach for measuring progress against global warming than the one in the Kyoto framework he rejected last spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The climate policy President Bush announced yesterday sets out a better and far more workable approach for measuring progress against global warming than the one in the Kyoto framework he rejected last spring. The president set the goal of an 18 percent reduction over the next 10 years in greenhouse gas intensity -- the ratio of emissions to economic activity -- rather than an arbitrary goal for curbs on total emissions. And he announced steps to get there.</p>
        <p>This emphasis not only removes a large part of the economic risk associated with goals based on a fixed emission limit, but gives American industries a target, similar to a goal for productivity or efficiency, that they can shoot for in practical ways. Because it is realistic and workable, it is likely to move us, at last, beyond arguments at the extremes and toward real action against climate change.</p>
        <p>For most of the past century, economic growth, energy use and emissions of carbon dioxide -- the dominant greenhouse gas -- have been linked. In this setting, a fixed emission limit harms the economy. Until we invent and commercialize new technologies to generate electricity and provide transportation -- as the president's science and technology initiatives encourage -- a fixed emission limit eventually means lowering economic growth. In fact, as Russia demonstrated in the past decade, the surest way to experience emissions declines is to go through an economic collapse.</p>
        <p>By tying goals to economic activity, the president's policy encourages a flexible response but does not take economic risks.</p>
        <p>The goal of his plan is both serious and meaningful: an 18 percent decline in greenhouse gas intensity over 10 years implies a 4.5 percent reduction by 2012 in annual greenhouse gas emissions, relative to what they would be if we moved ahead according to current forecasts. Meeting this goal will require real reductions: faster adoption of energy-saving technologies; improved recovery of methane that currently escapes from coal mines, gas pipelines and landfills; and programs to improve forestry and agriculture so they absorb more carbon dioxide. These are reasonable steps that require a level of effort the administration believes is warranted, given the current state of climate science.</p>
        <p>Yet many of these reductions are not easily encouraged in traditional ways. An economist's first choice for lowering industrial pollution is usually a cap-and-trade program. Companies are required to measure their emissions in tons and obtain an equal number of emission allowances, which can then be traded with other companies. This encourages the least expensive reductions. President Bush has proposed such a system to control sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and mercury emissions from power plants. But applying this concept to greenhouse gases would be premature and would risk unnecessarily high costs. The methane and carbon storage options that are among the most practical means now to reduce greenhouse gases cannot easily be measured for trading.</p>
        <p>Instead, the president has challenged businesses to figure out innovative ways to measure and record their reductions. And he has promised them that not only would their investments in emissions reductions today be protected from future policy decisions, but the credits generated by these investments could be traded.</p>
        <p>For too long, the loudest voices in the climate change debate have either called for large emission reductions in the next 10 years or ignored the fact that climate change is a real risk. President Bush's plan makes sense: focus on a reasonable approach to slow, stop and then reverse growth in greenhouse gas emissions; don't wreck the economy in the process; and adjust future policy in response to scientific and technical progress. He has added a fresh, reasoned voice to the debate.</p>
        <p>R. Glenn Hubbard is chairman of the President's Council of Economic Advisers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">R. Glenn Hubbard is chairman of the President's Council of Economic Advisers.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
