<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking Green vs. Making Green</title>
    <meta content="Y28FORD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/28/business/28FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1379373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Becker, Daniel F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3D9113BF93BA15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking Green vs. Making Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talking Green vs. Making Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr has muted his pronouncements on environmental issues since becoming chief executive of Ford Motor Co and gaining operational control of struggling company last October; many environmental activists are angry that Ford backed intense lobbying and advertising effort against Senate proposal to raise fuel economy standards for first time since 1980's; some also say they sensed shift in Ford's priorities when, in recent television campaign, he spoke of his love of outdoors in ad promoting SUV, vehicle environmentalists love to hate most; Sierra Club spokesman Daniel F Becker says Bill Ford is showing his true stripes as just another short-sighted auto executive with no interest in environment; William Ford declines comment; company officials say Ford Motor Co has stood by its main commitments, including pledge in 2000 to improve fuel economy of its SUV's by 25 percent within five years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before he became chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, William Clay Ford Jr. made a point of joining the environmental camp.</p>
        <p>Global warming, he wrote in a citizenship report in 2001, ''stands out from other environmental issues because of its potentially serious consequences and its direct relationship to our industry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once one of Detroit's most outspoken executives on environmental issues, William Clay Ford Jr. has recently muted his pronouncements, disappointing environmentalists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before he became chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, William Clay Ford Jr. made a point of joining the environmental camp.</p>
        <p>Global warming, he wrote in a citizenship report in 2001, ''stands out from other environmental issues because of its potentially serious consequences and its direct relationship to our industry.''</p>
        <p>Global warming? Auto executives talk about cars, golf and every tenth of a percentage point of market share. But they do not speak of global warming, unless prompted, and then often dismiss it as scientifically unproved.</p>
        <p>Such statements made Mr. Ford -- a vegetarian, guitar-strumming black belt in tae kwon do -- the Motor City's most outspoken executive on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>But since becoming chief executive and gaining operational control of the struggling company last October, Mr. Ford, 44, has muted his pronouncements on such issues and has made decisions that have bitterly disappointed environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Many activists are most angry that Mr. Ford, the great-grandson of Henry Ford, backed an intense lobbying and advertising effort against a Senate proposal to raise fuel economy standards for the first time since the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Some also say they sensed a shift in Mr. Ford's priorities when, in a recent television campaign, he spoke of his love of the outdoors in an ad promoting the vehicle environmentalists love to hate most: the S.U.V.</p>
        <p>''My fear is that Bill Ford is showing his true stripes as just another short-sighted auto executive with no interest in the environment, our oil dependence, or the truth,'' said Daniel F. Becker, who monitors global warming and energy issues for the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>Fairly recently, Mr. Becker said of Mr. Ford: ''His tenure offers real hope for progress.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford declined requests for comment. But company officials say that Ford Motor has stood by its main commitments, including a pledge in 2000 to improve the fuel economy of its S.U.V.'s by 25 percent within five years. The company has said it aims to sell the first hybrid gasoline-electric S.U.V. -- a step toward fulfilling that promise -- in 2003. It is also undertaking an ambitious project to rebuild its huge River Rouge plant as an eco-friendly operation.</p>
        <p>''What is the commitment we've made that we've backed away from?'' asked James G. Vella, Ford's vice president for corporate public affairs.</p>
        <p>But even a few of the company's white-collar workers, in an internal message board, recently expressed discomfort with Ford Motor's role in the defeat of a proposal backed by Senators John Kerry and John McCain to raise fuel economy standards 50 percent by the 2015 model year.</p>
        <p>''This is a victory for American big business, including Ford lobbying,'' read one message given to The New York Times by an employee who did not support the company's position. ''Fuel economy has improved hardly at all in 20 years.''</p>
        <p>Now, environmentalists, embittered after the Senate defeat, are lining up against the man they once viewed as a potent ally. They say it will be difficult for Mr. Ford to lay claim to a green mantle if his company continues to adhere to the industry line on fighting fuel economy regulation. Ford's tangible record is undistinguished, they argue, because the fuel economy of its automotive fleet is roughly equivalent to vehicles built by General Motors, its main rival, and because Toyota Motor and Honda Motor are already selling environmentally friendly vehicles that use hybrid engines.</p>
        <p>The heart of the anger is directed at the company's support for an advertising blitz in newspapers and radio stations across the country to sway lawmakers during the recent fuel economy debate. The ads claimed, among other things, that S.U.V.'s and pickups would be driven to extinction and farmers would have to use subcompact cars to tend their crops. Ford also drafted letters for its workers to send to Congress.</p>
        <p>''Everybody had a lot of high hopes and optimism for what Bill Ford was doing at Ford,'' said Scott Stoermer, spokesman for the League of Conservation Voters. ''It's one thing to be opposed to it,'' he said of the Senate proposal, ''but it's quite another to personally ask your employees to lobby senators and to use arguments that you know are wrong.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that the notion that the S.U.V. or pickup would be legislated out of existence is belied by the fact that Ford's planned hybrid Escape S.U.V., due in 2003, will get 40 miles a gallon, well above the standards in the Kerry-McCain proposal.</p>
        <p>Industry lobbyists counter that vehicles like the Escape will be made in limited numbers and that the legislation would have made it far more expensive to build -- and for consumers to buy -- pickups and S.U.V's.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anybody would argue that the Kerry bill wouldn't have the impact of reducing choice,'' said Martin B. Zimmerman, Ford's group vice president for corporate affairs.</p>
        <p>One alliance of environmental groups and corporations, the Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies, is now reviewing Ford's membership, as well as G.M.'s.</p>
        <p>''The recent actions by Ford and General Motors on fuel economy standards have raised some serious questions about their sincerity,'' said Robert K. Massie, the group's executive director.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Ford became chairman in 1999, he had an easier platform to make grand pronouncements. The company was prosperous, and, as chairman, he was not responsible for day-to-day operations.</p>
        <p>Much has changed since then. Ford lost $5.5 billion in 2001 and is in turmoil. The company faces its usual unyielding competition from abroad, but has also been caught off guard by a resurgent G.M. that is stealing market share and eroding profits by leading a price war. In January, Mr. Ford announced a restructuring plan that included 35,000 job cuts and five plant closings.</p>
        <p>The crisis presents Mr. Ford with a quandary that puts his stated environmental beliefs up against preserving the corporate inheritance of his children and extended family.</p>
        <p>''I used to wonder,'' he said in late 2000, ''if running a large industrial company would really square with my values.''</p>
        <p>More recently, he has been less Hamlet and more Prince Hal, worrying less out loud about saving the earth and talking instead about the hard realities of how the company became distracted during the bull market and how it must now refocus on building profitable cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>''We strayed from what got us to the top of the mountain and it cost us greatly,'' he said recently.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say the gospel of green should not be one of convenience. But Wall Street, the United Automobile Workers union and stockholders have their own concerns, starting with the bottom line and preserving jobs.</p>
        <p>''You might irritate the environmentalists, but you have three other key constituencies,'' said Saul Rubin, an analyst with UBS Warburg. ''The consumers, who are not particularly interested in fuel economy; the U.A.W., who are not particularly interested in fuel economy; and the shareholders, who are not particularly interested in fuel economy.''</p>
        <p>''Bill Ford,'' he continued, ''is going to have to give up on his ambitions to create an environmentally friendly company. They need to focus all of their resources on becoming competitive again.''</p>
        <p>The disenchantment among environmentalists is in stark contrast to their attitude as the new decade began. Then, Mr. Ford led the company to abandon the Global Climate Coalition, a group of corporations that lobbied against restricting emissions of gases linked to global warming. And in a landmark corporate citizenship report released in 2000, the company acknowledged that the rise of S.U.V.'s had increased fuel consumption and added to greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>''S.U.V. owners who use their vehicles for off-road recreation can damage the nature they and others seek to enjoy,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford pressed for the report in an attempt to address questions about the impact of the rise of S.U.V.'s, not a popular area of inquiry in Detroit. ''The court of public opinion sometimes decides before you're ready for them to decide, and I want to make sure we're ready and ahead of the curve,'' he said at a news conference when the report was released.</p>
        <p>Michelle Robinson, who works for the Union of Concerned Scientists, said liberal activist groups like hers saw Mr. Ford ''as a breath of fresh air.''</p>
        <p>More recently, she said, she has felt discouraged by his company's actions. G.M., if viewed by groups like hers as a nemesis, has at least been more consistent, she said.</p>
        <p>''I think there's a little more duplicity, or schizophrenia, with Ford right now,'' she said. ''You're not quite sure what they really are advocating when they're saying one thing publicly and another behind closed doors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zimmerman, the Ford official, said the company was only agreeing with the rest of the industry that the Kerry-McCain proposal was too ambitious. Even Honda, increasingly seen by environmental groups as their last hope for an ally, opposed the proposal. Honda, however, is the only major automaker that is not a member of the trade group that sponsored many of the ads. It has also said that significant increases are achievable.</p>
        <p>Inside Ford, noted one white-collar worker who said he feared losing his job if identified, ''the camps are fairly well split between people who think not much or nothing needs to be done versus the group of people that think a lot needs to be done.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zimmerman argued that the vast majority of employees support Ford's position. He added that the company still had backing from some environmental groups, citing Conservation International, a group that promotes biodiversity that has accepted a $25 million grant from Ford.</p>
        <p>Peter A. Seligmann, the chief executive of that group, said of Bill Ford, ''In his heart of hearts, he is truly concerned about environmental issues and truly recognizes the impact his industry has on the environment.</p>
        <p>''He would like to be engaged in finding solutions on these issues,'' he added, ''and is trying to figure out how to get the industry there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
