<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boys Face Questions Of Life And Death</title>
    <meta content="25MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/25/arts/theater/25MATT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1386965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaudreault, Jean-Rock</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Potvin, Jacinthe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brochu, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Eric</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Matthew and Stephen (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gaudreault, Jean-Rock</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Davis, Eric</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brochu, Daniel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD8173EF936A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boys Face Questions Of Life And Death</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boys Face Questions of Life and Death</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews Jean-Rock Gaudreault's play Matthew and Stephen, directed by Jacinthe Potvin; Daniel Brochu and Eric Davis star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Life's melancholy pervades ''Matthew and Stephen,'' the new attraction at the New Victory Theater.</p>
        <p>An awareness of death colors this drama about two 8-year-olds. Matthew knows he is dying. Stephen is afraid of living.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Death may be the ineluctable end of all stories, but in its sweetly perceptive way, "Matthew and Stephen" validates the case for life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Life's melancholy pervades ''Matthew and Stephen,'' the new attraction at the New Victory Theater.</p>
        <p>An awareness of death colors this drama about two 8-year-olds. Matthew knows he is dying. Stephen is afraid of living.</p>
        <p>They are destined for friendship.</p>
        <p>Straightforward and unsentimental, this hourlong intermissionless play by Jean-Rock Gaudreault shuns all easy ways out as it confronts both the inevitability of death and the rich promise of life. In so doing, ''Matthew and Stephen'' conveys sadness and joy.</p>
        <p>Playing through Sunday and intended for audiences 8 and older, this play, translated by Linda Gaboriau from the French original, ''Mathieu Trop Court, François Trop Long,'' and directed by Jacinthe Potvin, is a production of the Montreal-based company Mathieu, François et les Autres.</p>
        <p>What precisely is the illness at the somber heart of ''Matthew and Stephen''? It is, explains Matthew, saying he got the name from television, ''The sickness of our time.''</p>
        <p>For Matthew, the illness is of the flesh. For Stephen, who once lived near an air base where jets roared overhead, consciousness brings an illness of the spirit: an inhibiting awareness of the possibility of nuclear annihilation, the threat of meteorites and the consequences of global warming and overpopulation.</p>
        <p>Yet the message of ''Matthew and Stephen'' is that each of its characters, given the chance, would opt for life.</p>
        <p>To enter the serious and occasionally buoyant spirit of ''Matthew and Stephen,'' it is necessary, though not always easy, to accept two adult actors, who appear to be in their 20's, as the children who are the play's only characters: Daniel Brochu as the doomed Matthew and Eric Davis as Stephen.</p>
        <p>At the outset of the play, Matthew in a jester's cap and colorful cloak, is huddled at the bottom of an empty swimming pool, where he overhears enough of a conversation to realize that Stephen is an unhappy newcomer to town who is not looking forward to the new school year. What they have in common is that each has no friends, Matthew because nobody is allowed to get near him because of his illness, even though it is not contagious; Stephen because he has just arrived.</p>
        <p>Matthew maintains that he wants no friends, that he likes being alone. But Stephen persists, and the two embark on a friendship that includes not only their revelations about themselves but also incantations composed of food ingredients, slingshot attacks on sparrows and exercises in imagination.</p>
        <p>More important, Matthew instructs Stephen in risk taking, including the art of the lie. And Stephen learns that adults are not always right.</p>
        <p>Death may be the ineluctable end of all stories, but in its sweetly perceptive way, ''Matthew and Stephen'' validates the case for life.</p>
        <p>MATTHEW AND STEPHEN</p>
        <p>A creation of Mathieu, François et les Autres. By Jean-Rock Gaudreault; directed by Jacinthe Potvin; translator, Linda Gaboriau; costumes by Ginette Grenier; sets by Stéphane Roy; assistant director, Isabelle LaPointe; composer, Catherine Gadouas; lighting engineer and technical director, Martin St.-Gelais; lighting by Éric Champoux; sound engineer, Emmanuel Cognée; stage manager, Mary-Susan Gregson; creative partners, Le Théâtre Français du Centre National des Arts (Ottawa) and Les Coups de Théâtre (Montreal). Presented by the New 42nd Street. At the New Victory, 209 West 42nd Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Daniel Brochu and Eric Davis.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
