<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Love You, You're Perfect, Goodbye</title>
    <meta content="10KELL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/10/opinion/10KELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1414767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Correction Stories</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keller, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">butz, earl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bill Keller</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gore, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6153AF933A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Love You, You're Perfect, Goodbye</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">We Love You, You're Perfect, Goodbye</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Keller, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Keller Op-Ed column urges key Democrats to dissuade Al Gore from running for president in 2004; cites his failures in 2000 campaign; notes many people voted for George W Bush because they did not like Gore; corrects previous column, in which he attributed wrong misdeed to Earl Butz, who lost post for telling offensive, racist joke; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before it's too late, somebody Democrats listen to (which probably means somebody who can produce an obscene amount of money, if not the editorial writers of this paper) should take Al Gore aside and tell him: Stop. Don't run. You had your chance, you blew it, now get out of the way. An awful lot of influential Democrats are already saying this, but they seem to be saying it mostly to each other. Meanwhile Mr. Gore is half-heartedly engaged in the campaign foreplay of op-ed-writing, fence-mending, fund-hunting and weight loss. Will nobody step in front of this misbegotten bandwagon?</p>
        <p>Hold on a second. That's awfully presumptuous. Mr. Gore was vice president during eight years of national prosperity. He was partner in an administration that moved the Democrats to the tenable center, advanced free trade, defanged the socially divisive issue of welfare, left us budget surpluses without the need for a lot of funny bookkeeping, and -- after some early dithering -- settled on a policy of responsible engagement in the world that ought to have been a source of national pride. (The Clinton peace plan is still the obvious template for an eventual settlement in the Middle East.) On some issues, Mr. Gore was the better half of the team. He was less squeamish about foreign intervention, including the honorable campaign against Slobodan Milosevic. He was a visionary on the environment. His alarums about global warming have now been confirmed by President Bush's own Environmental Protection Agency -- and, oh yes, by the melting of Alaska.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before it's too late, Democrats should take Al Gore aside and tell him: Stop. Don't run. You had your chance, you blew it, now get out of the way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before it's too late, somebody Democrats listen to (which probably means somebody who can produce an obscene amount of money, if not the editorial writers of this paper) should take Al Gore aside and tell him: Stop. Don't run. You had your chance, you blew it, now get out of the way. An awful lot of influential Democrats are already saying this, but they seem to be saying it mostly to each other. Meanwhile Mr. Gore is half-heartedly engaged in the campaign foreplay of op-ed-writing, fence-mending, fund-hunting and weight loss. Will nobody step in front of this misbegotten bandwagon?</p>
        <p>Hold on a second. That's awfully presumptuous. Mr. Gore was vice president during eight years of national prosperity. He was partner in an administration that moved the Democrats to the tenable center, advanced free trade, defanged the socially divisive issue of welfare, left us budget surpluses without the need for a lot of funny bookkeeping, and -- after some early dithering -- settled on a policy of responsible engagement in the world that ought to have been a source of national pride. (The Clinton peace plan is still the obvious template for an eventual settlement in the Middle East.) On some issues, Mr. Gore was the better half of the team. He was less squeamish about foreign intervention, including the honorable campaign against Slobodan Milosevic. He was a visionary on the environment. His alarums about global warming have now been confirmed by President Bush's own Environmental Protection Agency -- and, oh yes, by the melting of Alaska.</p>
        <p>Yes, but what's the point of vision if you don't have the courage of it? Mr. Gore took a gilt-edged legacy and frittered it away in a clumsy, focus-grouped campaign. He abandoned the New Democrat center for an insincere-sounding populism. He couldn't figure out how to separate Mr. Clinton the romancer of voters from Mr. Clinton the romancer of interns, so he ducked him altogether. He soft-pedaled his views on free trade and gun control and the environment for fear of offending one voter bloc or another. It's true you have to win to realize your ideas, but for Mr. Gore it became more about the winning than the ideas. The net effect of all his calculated repositioning was that voters liked him less; they decided he was an opportunist, a phony. In short, he ran a bone-headed campaign.</p>
        <p>A bone-headed campaign he WON, don't forget. He got 537,179 more popular votes, and only lost the Electoral College thanks to a lot of well-documented funny business. The best estimate of the various investigative post-mortems was that an honest statewide recount would have awarded Florida to Mr. Gore and denied Antonin Scalia the role of American kingmaker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore never bothered to demand that statewide recount, because he preferred the cynical alternative of recounting only the Democratic counties. Kind of hoist by his own petard, wouldn't you say? In any case, given the robust state of the economy and the alarming inexperience of his rival, he should have won handily. He lost his home state, and Mr. Clinton's, for Pete's sake.</p>
        <p>Still, there are plenty of Democrats seething at the injustice and yearning for a rematch. Isn't Mr. Gore entitled to pursue his vindication?</p>
        <p>Oh, boo hoo. This isn't about Al Gore's inner peace. And it isn't a grudge match. The last thing we need now is a wallow in the past -- which a Gore campaign is almost certain to entail, dragging around as he does the whole sorry afterbirth of Florida, the Clinton mischief, his own self-reinventions. This is about whom we want to lead the country through a perilous period. Mr. Gore disqualified himself by not having the confidence of his own convictions -- to the point where we wondered if he had any convictions. Surely two prerequisites for a president are a confident sense of direction and the ability to inspire people to go there.</p>
        <p>That campaign you describe as ''populist'' was actually an appeal for economic prudence -- sequestering Social Security, focusing tax cuts on the middle class, paying down the national debt -- and a warning that a Bush administration would be a feast of special interests. If that's populist, we're all feeling a little populist now. We've got an administration characterized by blind faith in crony capitalism, a drunken spendthrift's version of supply-side economics, and a secretive, country-club executive style. The people-versus-the-powerful sloganeering was grating, but on the merits wasn't Mr. Gore right?</p>
        <p>Fair enough, though don't forget that Messrs. Clinton and Gore were aided in their prudence by a tax windfall from the phenomenal party-hearty economy of the 1990's. Mr. Bush can be blamed for a lot, but not, on the whole, for the recession and the collapse of an inflated market. Would I rather have a Gore economic team managing our way out of the current mess? Yes. But I don't think I can bear a campaign marathon of Al Gore whining, ''I told you so.''</p>
        <p>So what's the alternative? John Kerry, the ersatz J.F.K., who fancies himself a global strategist because 30 years ago he faced down a Vietcong ambush? (And, by the way, with all due respect for his exploit, how utterly weird is it that he then took out his handy 8-millimeter camera and re-enacted his heroism on film?) Surely not Joe Lieberman, Al Gore's sad-eyed second banana, who got out-debated by Dick Cheney? Dick Gephardt is too partisan, too Old Democrat, to win moderates and independents. And John Edwards, the newbie heartthrob, is untested in a year when untested will be a very, very hard sell. (Sadly for Mr. Gore, the year for untested was 2000.) Howard Dean, the appealing governor of Vermont, wins the Bruce Babbitt/Paul Tsongas prize; he'll get the pundit vote.</p>
        <p>When was the last time that, two years before the election, the assortment of candidates didn't make your heart sink a little? You want Martin Sheen, but he's not the president, he just plays one on TV. Let Mr. Gore stand down, and one of the others will rise to the occasion.</p>
        <p>Here's an idea. Why not let them sharpen their teeth on Al Gore in the primaries? As Joe Klein put it in Slate, one of two good things could happen if Mr. Gore runs: either ''another new Gore will materialize -- a looser, more gracious Gore, one with the courage of his intelligence,'' or an alternative candidate will prevail, and go on to the general election fortified by his reputation as a giant-killer.</p>
        <p>Don't bet on it. A likelier outcome is that Al Gore wins the nomination -- thanks to name recognition, the front-loading of the primary schedule and the knee-jerk reflexes of the party machinery -- without becoming a more appealing candidate in the process. We can always hope, and his friends say he's determined to run a more visceral, true-to-himself campaign this time, but he shows little sign of it yet. And as for gracious -- that's not a quality he seems to have in him. The Democratic Leadership Council, which helped launch Mr. Gore and the centrist movement, met in New York to hear from the 2004 hopefuls, and Mr. Gore was too above-it-all to show up. (He was conspicuously lunching nearby at the Regency with his book publisher.) The fact is, a lot of the fund-raisers and foot soldiers who worked their hearts out for him in 2000 don't want to work for him again. They'd still fall on bayonets for Bill Clinton, but Mr. Gore left them feeling disillusioned and unappreciated. That's not just bad manners; it's bad leadership.</p>
        <p>In any case, another new Gore? Spare me. The reason more people didn't vote for Al Gore is that they didn't like him. Mr. Gore can be an engaging man in a conversation, but he seems incapable of making an audience want to listen to him. One big reason 50 million voters went instead for an apparent lightweight they didn't entirely trust was that they didn't want to have Al Gore in their living rooms for four years. During the 2000 campaign, even my 3-year-old daughter, channeler of the zeitgeist, went around chanting the refrain: ''Al Gore is a snore.''</p>
        <p>My head says: One last chance; show us what you've really got -- somewhere in there is the right message. My gut says: Sorry, you're just the wrong messenger. Mr. Gore, Fisk University needs you.</p>
        <p>In my last column I erroneously derided Earl Butz for proposing to count ketchup as a vegetable during a downsizing of the school lunch program. As several readers pointed out, that bit of nutritional tomfoolery belonged to his successors in the Reagan administration. The particular idiocy that got Mr. Butz drummed out of office was an offensive, racist joke that was heard by a reporter, as unprintable now as it was then.</p>
        <p>E-mail: billkeller@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: billkeller@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
