<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Homes Reborn: Churches, Coops and Arks</title>
    <meta content="28FUNK$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/28/realestate/28FUNK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1404073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sausalito (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taos (Nm)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirby, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico/Taos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Sausalito</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DF133EF93BA15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Homes Reborn: Churches, Coops and Arks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Summer Homes Reborn: Churches, Coops and Arks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KIRBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirby, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Look at some intriguing vacation homes for sale or rent around country finds unusual offerings, such as restored ark in Sausalito and Homes in the Earthship 'green' community in Taos; photos; advice on finding unusual buildings to remodel (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO old buildings have souls? And if so, can they be reincarnated?</p>
        <p>A look at some intriguing vacation homes for sale or rent around the country would suggest that they can be. From a restored ark in Sausalito, Calif., to a pop star's cabin in the Idaho woods, some structures that had little, if anything, to do with conventional vacationing have been reborn as unusual vacation homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>From a restored ark to a pop star's cabin, some structures that had little to do with conventional vacationing have been reborn as unusual vacation homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO old buildings have souls? And if so, can they be reincarnated?</p>
        <p>A look at some intriguing vacation homes for sale or rent around the country would suggest that they can be. From a restored ark in Sausalito, Calif., to a pop star's cabin in the Idaho woods, some structures that had little, if anything, to do with conventional vacationing have been reborn as unusual vacation homes.</p>
        <p>For people interested in something different in a summer property, whether buying or renting, these conversions offer a refreshing change in an age of carbon-copy condominiums and dime-a-dozen time shares.</p>
        <p>Of course, reincarnation is never quick or easy. Converting old structures into comfortable, functioning vacation houses requires unyielding determination, vast pools of money and, often, years of hard work.</p>
        <p>Harris L. Safier, a real estate broker in Ulster County, N.Y., has found many buildings for clients who wanted a different kind of weekend retreat. ''I've been doing real estate around here for about 25 years now,'' he said, ''and we've sold things like railroad stations, creameries, barns, chicken coops, a wagon maker's shop, country stores, a gas station, schoolhouses and a couple of churches, all of which were converted into homes.''</p>
        <p>Those looking for unusual properties to convert should, in addition to calling real estate agents, talk to local historical societies, which may have information about such buildings, said Ralph B. Tiz, a real estate broker in Avalon, N.J. He advised making any sale contingent on being able to convert the building to residential use.</p>
        <p>''You do not want to be stuck with a church unless you want to start a new religion,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bonnie Metzger, who restored a Sausalito party boat as a home, confesses a love for hunting treasures -- and pounding nails. ''I love transforming run-down property and seeing it emerge as something that reflects its history,'' she said.</p>
        <p>For Joan and Jim Stephens, reclaiming unwanted buildings has become a way of life. ''When my husband and I first got married, we moved about 14 times,'' Ms. Stephens said. ''We lived for a while in a converted school bus. We fixed up an abandoned lodge.''</p>
        <p>After spending seven years domesticating the former retreat of the pop composer and singer Carole King, they have decided to move again -- to another run-down building.</p>
        <p>As the following examples demonstrate, the rewards of conversion can be rich. The soul of each building was enhanced in its reincarnation, its previous life providing a backdrop of intrigue, history, even humor to its current life.</p>
        <p>What Noah Never Imagined</p>
        <p>The Ark de Triumph was built for getaways but was never intended as a home. Now it is one of a handful of renovated arks in the Floating Homes community, a collection of 250 boats in Waldo Point Harbor and Kappas Marina in Sausalito, across the Golden Gate Bridge from San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The ark began life as a party boat for Victorian-era San Franciscans. The boat, actually two long arks joined in tandem, was part of a small flotilla of pleasure boats that populated Belvedere Cove, in Marin County, every summer from 1890 to 1930. A typical ark had four rooms and a kitchen, and at 1,800 square feet, the Ark de Triumph is one of the largest.</p>
        <p>Many of the arks were jointly owned by families, whose weekends were one long floating party.</p>
        <p>In 1995, Ms. Metzger bought her ark, which had been placed on pilings in the 1930's, for less than $100,000. ''It was the worst dump I'd ever set foot in,'' she said. ''The understructure was a compete disaster, pilings were loose, joints and beams were rotting. The railings were falling off. The catwalks were inaccessible. All the electricity was a jerry-built fire hazard. The floors were dry-rotted -- you could see the water through the boards.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Metzger renamed it the Ark de Triumph and spent six years tearing it apart and rebuilding it. The renovation, which cost about $175,000, included replacing the pilings and installing historically accurate railings.</p>
        <p>''When I moved in, everybody wanted to come see the ark,'' said Ms. Metzger, a painter and sculptor. ''Arks intrigue people. Arks have cachet.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Metzger has converted three rooms into a bed and breakfast. Now she is moving to Mexico and must sell. The ark is listed at $535,000, with some furnishings included. Information: (415) 331-6240.</p>
        <p>A Well-Feathered Nest</p>
        <p>Two years ago, when Barry Mutton bought an old chicken coop in Krumville, N.Y., about 100 miles north of Manhattan, for $39,000, it was filled not with chickens but with wild deer. The building had been abandoned, and it was so rickety that he planned to tear it down. But soon, the coop had a hold on him.</p>
        <p>''People thought I was absolutely crazy, and they still do,'' said Mr. Mutton, a professional builder and renovator who lives in nearby High Falls. ''It would've been easier to tear it down and build a new one. But I got too far in to turn back.'</p>
        <p>What saved the coop, which is about 70 years old, was its clever, sunny location. The chickens needed to be kept warm, but during the Depression, farmers couldn't pay for heat. ''I discovered it was aligned perfectly to gain as much solar heat as it can,'' Mr. Mutton said. ''I rarely have to use heat, even in winter.'' The secret was the south-facing sloping roof.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Mutton started his renovations, the building was considerably out of square. ''The original builder went into the woods and got his own lumber,'' he said. ''There was no need for constancy in sizing.''</p>
        <p>Another challenge was staying true to theme of a farm building, without becoming too designed or too conventional, Mr. Mutton said. ''I had to remind myself to keep a sense of humor,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After dividing the open coop into three bedrooms and two baths, Mr. Mutton salvaged parts of the original exterior for the interior, using the corrugated metal roofing for wainscoting and weathered wood panels to make walls with inlaid patterns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mutton plans to sell the coop this summer. He estimates its value at $425,000, although he has not determined an asking price. Information: (845) 687-9102.</p>
        <p>Rock 'n' Roll Ranch</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, not long after her ''Tapestry'' album became a hit, Carole King built a recording studio on a mountainside near Boise, Idaho. Now the property, which she called Welcome Home Ranch, is for sale by its current owners, Jim and Joan Stephens.</p>
        <p>There are five buildings: the main house, a guest house, a pool house, a log barn and a storage shed built over a creek (the shed has a big picture window and a loft). When the Stephenses bought the ranch in 1990, one of their tasks was peeling off the egg cartons glued to the walls of the recording studio in the basement of the main house, where Ms. King and guest musicians jammed into the night. The sound-damping cartons were one of many clues to the ranch's history.</p>
        <p>''She brought her entourage to work on construction,'' said Mr. Stephens, who traced the house's history through old photos, magazines and neighbors' recollections. ''We saw photos of dozens of teepees and trailers and campers in the meadow. Everyone lived on site.''</p>
        <p>Neighbors told him of sneaking into the woods and watching ''hippies in the hot tub, nude and smoking pot,'' Mr. Stephens said.</p>
        <p>''I think it's why the house was so poorly constructed,'' he added. ''The guy who delivered the original windows told me he was surprised by how slow the progress was, and how much fun everyone seemed to be having while working.''</p>
        <p>Patty Mitsui, a spokeswoman for Ms. King, confirmed that the singer had once owned the property but said she was traveling and not available for comment.</p>
        <p>In the main house, staircases were hewn from single logs. Carved wooden beams arch across the cathedral ceilings. One landing, carved from a tree stump, features a huge buffalo-head nickel incised into the wood. A hand-carved buffet is inscribed: ''Built for Carole Evers, 1978'' (Ms. King was married to Rick Evers).</p>
        <p>The house sat empty for most of 10 years before the Stephenses bought it. They spent another 10 years repairing it, adding a garage, pool, family room and other amenities. The ranch has been on the market for about 18 months, priced at $1.1 million. Information: (208) 713-2877.</p>
        <p>Environmentally Friendly Retreads</p>
        <p>While some buildings have been recycled as vacation homes, the Earthships of New Mexico are literally built of recycled consumer waste.</p>
        <p>Drawing on the philosophy that the environment is an element in a building's design, the Earthship community consists of 30 self-sufficient homes with renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Michael Reynolds, an architect, started Earthship seven years ago on 640 acres of scrubland just outside Taos. The houses are made with earthen mounds and walls constructed from used tires filled with dirt.</p>
        <p>''It's been a tremendous challenge over the years, getting past the stigma that these materials are generally considered by the public to be garbage,'' Mr. Reynolds said.</p>
        <p>Recycled bottles and cans are used as bricks for retaining walls, planters and interior walls. ''They have thermal mass,'' he added. ''They keep the temperature comfortable and stable year round,'' despite 100-degree summers and subzero winters.</p>
        <p>Three Earthship units are available for vacationers to rent, beginning at $130 a night or $960 a week. Two of the units are also for sale at $140,000. Information: (505) 751-0462.</p>
        <p>Each house is self-sustainable. ''There are no lines in, and no lines out,'' Mr. Reynolds said. Water is collected from rain and snow. It is recycled and reused four times: for showering, for watering indoor plants, for toilets, and for irrigating plants outdoors. Electricity is generated by wind and solar sources.</p>
        <p>''We want people to know they can have sustainable technology,'' Mr. Reynolds said, ''and still make coffee, watch TV and even blend up some margaritas.''</p>
        <p>HAVENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
