<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Shows Off Aid Projects At U.N. Development Meeting</title>
    <meta content="Y30SUMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/30/international/africa/30SUMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1419655"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D6143FF933A0575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Shows Off Aid Projects At U.N. Development Meeting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Shows Off Aid Projects at U.N. Development Meeting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States officials attending United Nations Summit on Sustainable Development in South Africa showcase series of multimillion-dollar American projects aimed at helping poor countries reduce poverty and protect their natural resources; say US plans to spend more than $1 billion over next four years to improve water efficiency on farms and factories, provide electricity to poor, help communities combat deforestation and ease hunger; American officials hope announcement will quiet relentless storm of criticism over US refusal to agree to firm time frames for reducing agricultural subsidies, reducing number of people in need of sanitation and for embracing wind and solar power; environmental groups and advocates for poor describe Americans' announcement as inadequate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving to demonstrate a commitment to the developing world, the United States showcased a series of multimillion-dollar projects today aimed at helping poor countries reduce poverty and protect their natural resources.</p>
        <p>The United States announced that it planned to spend more than $1 billion over the next four years to improve water efficiency on farms and in factories, to provide electricity to the poor, to help communities combat deforestation and to ease hunger in Africa. The European Union has also promised to expand access to water and energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moving to demonstrate a commitment to the developing world, the U.S. showcased multimillion-dollar projects on Thursday aimed at reducing poverty and protecting the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moving to demonstrate a commitment to the developing world, the United States showcased a series of multimillion-dollar projects today aimed at helping poor countries reduce poverty and protect their natural resources.</p>
        <p>The United States announced that it planned to spend more than $1 billion over the next four years to improve water efficiency on farms and in factories, to provide electricity to the poor, to help communities combat deforestation and to ease hunger in Africa. The European Union has also promised to expand access to water and energy.</p>
        <p>American officials hoped the announcement would quiet the relentless storm of criticism that has erupted here at the United Nations Summit on Sustainable Development. The United States has refused to agree to firm time frames for reducing agricultural subsidies, for reducing the number of people in need of sanitation and for embracing wind and solar power, among other things.</p>
        <p>But the Americans' announcement, which was warmly welcomed by the United Nations, was described as inadequate by environmental groups and advocates for the poor. Most of the money for the projects will come from existing programs, and critics condemned the plan as an attempt to divert attention from the reluctance of wealthy nations to reduce trade subsidies, which many economists say hurt farmers in poor countries.</p>
        <p>American officials countered that they preferred concrete programs to the deadlines and targets under negotiation. Thousands of government officials from around the globe have been struggling here to produce a plan to promote development in poor countries while protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>''Words are good; actions are better,'' said Paula Dobriansky, the State Department's under secretary for global affairs. ''Our concrete goal and objective is the reduction of poverty and the advancement of sustainable development. To us, this is a call for action, a call for initiatives that will breathe life to many of the textual discussions.''</p>
        <p>The United Nations has called for more public-private partnerships to promote development in poor countries. The wealthy countries plan to work closely with advocacy groups, universities and businesses, and expect that more money will flow to the projects through those partnerships.</p>
        <p>''It's a new approach, and the new approach has to be embraced,'' said Jan Pronk, the United Nations' special envoy to the conference.</p>
        <p>Some critics complained, however, that wealthy countries were devoting little new money to the projects. Others accused them of promoting private-sector partnerships to provide opportunities for powerful businesses.</p>
        <p>''What we need above and beyond partnerships is a real commitment from government,'' said Michael Dorsey, a director of the Sierra Club. ''The partnership avenue is a means for governments to conveniently sidestep their responsibilities. What we really want is political commitment, but it doesn't seem like we're going to get much of those things.''</p>
        <p>Government officials have agreed on 95 percent of the conference's plan for action, including a proposal to restore depleted fisheries, where possible, by 2015. But the most contentious issues -- agricultural subsidies, renewable energy and time frames for some environmental targets -- remain unresolved, probably until next week, when more than 100 presidents and prime ministers arrive for the final days of the talks.</p>
        <p>President Bush will not be coming, a decision that has disappointed officials from Europe and developing countries.</p>
        <p>Today, three American congressmen criticized the Bush administration for emphasizing partnerships over specific targets for converting from fossil fuels to renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>The three representatives -- George Miller, Democrat of California; Earl Blumenauer, Democrat of Oregon, and Dennis J. Kucinich, Democrat of Ohio -- accused the United States of being out of step with the world.</p>
        <p>But some environmentalists emphasized that the criticism of wealthy countries should not detract from the positive role that partnerships can play. The Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group, has joined forces with the United States Environmental Protection Agency, automobile companies, officials in Mexico, China and the Netherlands, and others to help poor countries eliminate lead from gasoline and sulfur from diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace, another advocacy group, and the World Business Council for Sustainable Development have come together to urge governments to tackle global warming.</p>
        <p>''Governments alone do not have all the power,'' said Jacob Scherr, who heads the international program of the National Resources Defense Council. ''If you're going to achieve sustainable development, you have to mobilize citizens, scientists, communities and corporations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
