<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1434334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1D7143CF930A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Protesters in Iraq Seek Missing Prisoners  President Saddam Hussein's decision on Sunday to open the gates of his prisons and let tens of thousands of political prisoners and common criminals go free prompted small but remarkable protests by some who lost relatives into the hands of the state security police years ago. The protests are the most visible sign of a new and potentially seismic trend: a willingness among ordinary people to speak up.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Searches Arabian Desert  The vast Arabian desert known as the Empty Quarter is being scoured by pilotless United States surveillance aircraft for signs that operatives of Al Qaeda have sought refuge among the nomadic tribes there, according to senior Yemeni officials.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Protesters in Iraq Seek Missing Prisoners  President Saddam Hussein's decision on Sunday to open the gates of his prisons and let tens of thousands of political prisoners and common criminals go free prompted small but remarkable protests by some who lost relatives into the hands of the state security police years ago. The protests are the most visible sign of a new and potentially seismic trend: a willingness among ordinary people to speak up.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Searches Arabian Desert  The vast Arabian desert known as the Empty Quarter is being scoured by pilotless United States surveillance aircraft for signs that operatives of Al Qaeda have sought refuge among the nomadic tribes there, according to senior Yemeni officials.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>9/11 Trial Opens in Germany  Mounir el-Motassadeq, a man accused by German prosecutors of being a member of Mohamed Atta's terrorist cell, reversed his earlier claims and admitted that he had attended a training camp sponsored by Osama bin Laden. But he pleaded not guilty to charges that included accessory to the murder of more than 3,000 people and denied that he was a member of Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Talks Continue at U.N.  In intense negotiations, the United States and Britain pressed the other three permanent members of the Security Council to accept a draft resolution on Iraq that includes no explicit authorization of military action but leaves the way open for Washington to go to war.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Israel Holds Off After Bombing  Israel did not retaliate for the bombing of a bus that killed 14 passengers on Monday in what officials said was a nod to American concerns that rising violence in the Middle East could disrupt plans for possible military action against Iraq.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Release at Guantanamo  Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld said a small number of the nearly 600 prisoners being held in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, would be released to their home countries because they were no longer of interest to the United States.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A15-20</p>
        <p>Maryland Bus Driver Slain; Sniper Threatens Children  A bus driver quietly pausing before his morning rounds was shot to death in Maryland, possibly the 10th person killed by a sniper who the authorities said is now threatening children.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>As if the recent setbacks in the sniper investigation were not enough, the threats to children and the slaying of a bus driver just blocks from where the shootings began left area residents feeling that events were spinning out of control.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Begins a Campaign Tour  Seeking to turn President Bush's popularity into Republican victories this fall, the White House has decided to dispatch Mr. Bush on an almost nonstop campaign between now and Election Day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Police Hunt for Migrant Killers  Arizona police are investigating whether vigilantes, self-appointed guardians of the border with Mexico, fatally shot at least two illegal immigrants in the desert last week.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Victory for Beach Access  California coastal officials said that they would move quickly to begin opening access to several beaches after the Supreme Court rejected two challenges to their ruling which guarantees public access to 1,160 miles of coast.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Hormone Research on Hold  Researchers working on hormone replacement therapy have been forced to discontinue large studies because of risks from the drugs.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Uncertainty Over Polio Vaccine  Scientists from the Institute of Medicine say that after years of study it is not clear whether the polio vaccine used in the United States from 1955 to 1963 is linked to cancer.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Talks on Global Warming  The latest round of international talks on global warming is set to begin in New Delhi, with delegates focused more on ways to adapt to changes than on cutting emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>State Senate to Vote On Gay-Rights Legislation  The Republican-led State Senate will vote for the first time on landmark gay-rights legislation in December after having blocked its passage for decades, the Senate leader said. The decision all but ensures the bill will become law and hands Gov. George E. Pataki a vital victory two weeks from Election Day to help him win over gay and lesbian voters.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pataki Opposes Toll Plan  Budgetary pressures are threatening to strain the political alliance between Gov. George E. Pataki and Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, with the governor stating that he opposes the mayor's preliminary plan to put tolls on the city's East River bridges.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Candidate's Take on Red Tape  Tom Golisano, the Independence Party's nominee for governor, has repeatedly condemned the tax and paperwork burdens that he says Albany imposes on small businesses. But helping small businesses cope with that red tape is exactly how Mr. Golisano built the fortune that is financing his run for state office.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Favorite for Arts Post  The poet, critic and anthologist Dana Gioia has emerged as the leading candidate to become the next chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts, according to sources close to the process.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter G. Bergmann  A physicist who worked with Albert Einstein and played a leading role in the advancement of Einstein's theories in the years after World War II, he was 87.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Japan Delays Banking Changes  An alliance of bankers, bureaucrats and ruling party legislators forced Heizo Takenaka, Japan's new economic czar, to postpone a plan for sweeping changes in bank regulation to deal with the country's $420 billion in bad bank loans.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cashing In on Health Care  Health costs are rising sharply while profit margins are being squeezed in other parts of the economy. The big winners include hospital networks that dominate local markets, inventors of ingenious medical devices and nurses.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Times to Buy Out Partner  The New York Times Company has signed a letter of intent to buy the Washington Post Company's 50 percent share of The International Herald Tribune for less than $75 million, dissolving a 35-year partnership.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Angels Take Series Lead  Anaheim beat San Francisco, 10-4, to take a two-games-to-one lead in the World Series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The illusory Prague connection; escalating tuition bills; keep the sidewalks ad-free; for Assembly and New York City Council.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
