<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fetch Me Barney</title>
    <meta content="21DOWD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/21/opinion/21DOWD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1386026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D8133FF932A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fetch Me Barney</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fetch Me Barney</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column imagines Pres Bush's moans and groans over his current problems with Middle East policy and domestic politics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>W. stomped around Camp David, too riled even for a restorative workout.</p>
        <p>He was ripped with Rove. Livid at Laura.</p>
        <p>''What made them think they could retire my feather pillow after 9/11?'' W. moaned, laying his head on Barney the terrier, the softest, fluffiest alternative at hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mutterings of W. as he stomped around Camp David following a week of too many Osama videos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>W. stomped around Camp David, too riled even for a restorative workout.</p>
        <p>He was ripped with Rove. Livid at Laura.</p>
        <p>''What made them think they could retire my feather pillow after 9/11?'' W. moaned, laying his head on Barney the terrier, the softest, fluffiest alternative at hand.</p>
        <p>''Karl shipped it off to Dad's presidential library, along with my foreign leader flashcards and John McCain voodoo doll.</p>
        <p>''Karl said it was gonna be cruise control from here on in, Coronation City, and I wouldn't need any extra cushioning anymore. But Karl was wrong-o. I want my pillow.</p>
        <p>''This week was a bummer. Osama's been making more videos than Britney.</p>
        <p>''Last fall, during Ramadan, I was tight with the Muslims -- eatin' dates and lamb at the White House and readin' Koranic verses. Now we don't see those guys around the White House anymore. And Osama's an even bigger rock star to every angry kid in the Arab world.</p>
        <p>''Colin may be Mr. Smooth, but he came away from the Middle East looking like Mr. Magoo, stumbling around in search of a policy we never had, snubbed by Hosni Mubarak and the Boy King of Morocco.</p>
        <p>''Then there are those rumors all over Georgetown that Cheney and Rummy had set up Colin to fail because they think he's a squishy internationalist hippie-child who might slow down the mow-down of Saddam. (Of course, the rumors are true, but did they have to get out?)</p>
        <p>''I've been feeling like a haywire traffic light, sending Sharon conflicting signals of red, green and yellow. Everyone's bellyaching that my seasoned foreign policy team is more make-it-up-as-they-go than Madeleine, Sandy and the rest of those Clinton losers.</p>
        <p>''Where has my moral clarity gone? Poppy says moral clarity always gets lost in the Middle East casbah of smoke and mirrors. That region is all nuance. I don't do the nuance thing. I hate messes, and the Middle East is the world's biggest.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to make Bill Kristol and the conservative Israeli lobby mad. Bibi is becoming more popular on Capitol Hill than me.</p>
        <p>''I just know that Saudi prince will get down to Crawford on Thursday and refuse to act like my good buddy. I'll take him on the old nature walk and show off my gorge, and Abdullah will go and ruin the photo op by preaching to me about the suffering of Palestinian innocents. The Arabs know that they get more bounce these days by standing up to us than by cooperating with us.</p>
        <p>''My polls are dropping faster than a Bible from the Devil's hand! I'm not supposed to read or care about polls. But that doesn't mean I'm not plenty hot about a 15-point drop?!? Daschle and Gephardt and those other Democratic vultures are looking at me like I'm armadillo roadkill.</p>
        <p>''And Ozone Man is back, panting for another deadlocked election, fantasizing about those hanging chads, droning about wetlands, carping about polluters. Earth-in-the-balance to Al: You lost. Scalia said so.</p>
        <p>''But what if people care about the Earth instead of carbon dioxide? The Senate trashed my energy policy, ruining my dream of rigs on the tundra and spoiling Juneau's chance to become the next Midland.</p>
        <p>''Then there was that cuckoo coup that the State Department and C.I.A. gave a wink and a nod to in some country in South America that begins with a V. Is it Veracruz? The punditry got all steamed about that, expecting me to support the democratically elected leader even though he's a Commie pinko who doesn't like big oil companies.</p>
        <p>''Who says you've got to go with the guy who gets the most votes, especially if you've got friends in high places?</p>
        <p>''My head hurts. Pillow, puh-leeze! I can't find a way out of the Middle East, and if it blows sky high, I can't invade Iraq in time for the 2004 election and I'll lose the war on terror. I could end up a one-termer, just like Poppy. How did a creep like Clinton manage two?</p>
        <p>''Hey! Wait a sec! Billy Boy says he wants a role in the Middle East. I read it in Condi's summary of the news. Billy says he could be 'conducive to peace,' whatever conducive means. Let him clean up the mess he made -- he loves chaos. Let him take the rap on this.</p>
        <p>''Whew! Good one. I'm gonna go for a run and come up with that marshals' plan for Afghanistan.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: liberties@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: liberties@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
