<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; The Fleeting Romance of the American Road</title>
    <meta content="11HAKI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/11/weekinreview/11HAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1415147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rapaille, Clotaire (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hakim, Danny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DB153AF932A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; The Fleeting Romance of the American Road</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fleeting Romance of the American Road</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on William Clay Ford Jr's opinion that American love affair with cars has gone stale because of long-running conflict between carmakers and regulators; design consultant Clotaire Rapaille says reality is that American carmakers are not producing cars Americans want anymore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICANS are falling out of love with cars.</p>
        <p>In a speech last week, none other than William Clay Ford Jr., the chairman and chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, proclaimed the end of the affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Are Americans falling out of love with cars?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICANS are falling out of love with cars.</p>
        <p>In a speech last week, none other than William Clay Ford Jr., the chairman and chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, proclaimed the end of the affair.</p>
        <p>''The love affair that people have had with automobiles has in some ways grown stale,'' he said. ''Some would say it's even dying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford chalked it up to the long running conflict between carmakers and regulators, particularly in California, where ''people used to write songs about T-Birds and Corvettes.''</p>
        <p>''Today,'' he said, ''they write regulations.''</p>
        <p>From his perspective, it will take continued effort on breakthrough environmental technologies and a more cooperative approach with regulators to turn things around. Then, he said, people might not be so offended by what their neighbors are driving.</p>
        <p>This sentiment cheered environmental activists, who think the growth of S.U.V.'s, like those Ford produces, has shifted automobiles from a symbol of American innocence to one of material and environmental excess.</p>
        <p>''He's reflecting the sort of love/hate relationship people have developed with their cars in the last couple of decades,'' said Dan Lashof, science director of the Natural Resources Defense Council's Climate Center.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, people like their individual cars, but they are very concerned with what their cars are doing to their neighborhoods and the planet,'' Mr. Lashof added.</p>
        <p>Indeed, carbon dioxide emissions from automobiles have been rising, despite technological improvements, because of the growth of S.U.V.'s and, to a lesser extent, pickups.</p>
        <p>But it would be hard to argue that Americans feel a deep-seated enviro-guilt, since S.U.V. sales continue to rise.</p>
        <p>In fact, Robert A. Lutz, vice chairman of General Motors, said last week that the average car buyer hardly cares about conserving gasoline, because it's so cheap.</p>
        <p>''We can't go in the opposite direction of our customers,'' said Mr. Lutz, the former Chrysler president, who is determined to make G.M. designs as bold as they were in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>''At $1 to $1.20 per gallon, they're to be forgiven for buying Navigators and Hummer H2's,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Further, it's equally hard to argue that people don't love automobiles anymore when sales have held up so well in a balky economy.</p>
        <p>So do Americans feel differently than they used to? For some cultural distance, we asked a Frenchman.</p>
        <p>''It's like saying Germans don't want to drink beer anymore or the Japanese don't want to east sushi,'' said Dr. Clotaire Rapaille, the founder of Archetype Discoveries, a design consulting firm that works with most of the major automakers. He helped design Chrysler's PT Cruiser, one of the few truly distinctive cars on the road.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rapaille said that, to the contrary, America's passion for cars is not waning. ''The reality,'' he said, ''is that the American carmakers aren't producing the cars people want anymore.''</p>
        <p>He put the blame on environmental engineering, safety engineering, overemphasis on aerodynamics and all sorts of mechanical factors conspiring to defang automobiles.</p>
        <p>''The automakers have been going too much into the cortex,'' Dr. Rapailled added.</p>
        <p>Why else would some of the most prominent automobiles seen in movies today be from another era?</p>
        <p>In the new action movie ''XXX,'' for instance, the star Vin Diesel drives a Pontiac GTO from the 1960's.</p>
        <p>And if Hollywood can't seem to cast female stars who are past their 30's, it also can't seem to cast Ford Mustangs that are younger than 30, like the one that Nicholas Cage tried to steal in ''Gone in 60 Seconds.''</p>
        <p>Cars with that kind of emotional pull are rare now. Much of the juice of the auto industry has gone into S.U.V.'s, and you can't really love an S.U.V. the same way.</p>
        <p>An old Mustang, for example, was like a quarterback. You expected it to have some swagger, some style.</p>
        <p>S.U.V.'s are like offensive linemen. You want them big and able to carry a load.</p>
        <p>''I've never heard anyone call an S.U.V. 'my baby,' '' Dr. Rapaille said.</p>
        <p>Falling in love with one ''is like falling in love with a tank,'' he said, adding, ''You never get the same feeling.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
