<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="02DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7D7123AF931A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andersen Chose Indictment Over an Admission of Guilt  Justice Department officials were willing to consider deferring the prosecution of Arthur Andersen, letting it avoid indictment, if the firm publicly acknowledged that it had illegally destroyed documents in the Enron inquiry and agreed to restrictions similar to probation, according to people involved in the case.</p>
        <p>But discussions of such an idea, raised in talks between the government and Andersen several weeks ago, never got off the ground because Andersen believed that such an admission would have been just as devastating as an indictment or guilty plea and also that the firm had not broken any laws. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andersen Chose Indictment Over an Admission of Guilt  Justice Department officials were willing to consider deferring the prosecution of Arthur Andersen, letting it avoid indictment, if the firm publicly acknowledged that it had illegally destroyed documents in the Enron inquiry and agreed to restrictions similar to probation, according to people involved in the case.</p>
        <p>But discussions of such an idea, raised in talks between the government and Andersen several weeks ago, never got off the ground because Andersen believed that such an admission would have been just as devastating as an indictment or guilty plea and also that the firm had not broken any laws. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>BellSouth in Brazilian Debt Dispute  BellSouth and Joseph Safra, one of Brazil's wealthiest bankers, are engaged in a dispute that may result in one of that country's largest and messiest corporate debt renegotiations. The dispute already touched off a default last week on a $375 million debt payment by BCP, a large Brazilian wireless communications company. BellSouth's stock dropped to a two-and-a-half-year low. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Ouster of Panel Chief Is Sought  After a year of urging from energy industry lobbyists, the Bush administration is seeking the ouster of Dr. Robert T. Watson, chief scientist of the World Bank, who for nearly six years has directed an international panel of hundreds of experts assessing global warming, several government officials have said. [A10.]</p>
        <p>Metromedia Fiber Near Bankruptcy  Metromedia Fiber Network, a provider of optical fiber communications networks, replaced its top executives and said that it had violated several loan agreements, moving to the brink of bankruptcy. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Bush's Antidrug Ads Strike a Nerve  The Bush administration's antidrug advertising campaign seeks to strike a chord with young people by linking drug use to supporting terrorism. But it has struck a nerve with critics who contend the message is inappropriate and goes too far. Advertising. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Late Technology Rally Lifts Nasdaq  A late rally in technology shares helped lift the Nasdaq composite index, which rose 17.27 points, or 0.9 percent, to 1,862.62. The Dow Jones industrial average closed down 41.24 points, or 0.4 percent, at 10,362.70, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 0.85 point, or 0.07 percent, to 1,146.54. [C12.]</p>
        <p>In a stock-market remake of ''Night of the Living Dead,'' shares of long-gone savings banks have sprung to life as investors speculate that the federal government will have to pay dearly for mishandling the savings and loan crisis of the 1980's. Market Place. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Construction Spending Rises 1.1%  The Commerce Department reported that construction spending rose 1.1 percent in February, to $879.4 billion at an annual rate, its fastest pace in a year. A separate report, a survey of purchasing managers, showed that manufacturing expanded in March as new orders flooded in at the fastest pace in more than 14 years. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Hyundai to Build Plant in Alabama  Hyundai Motor selected Alabama over Kentucky for its first United States plant. The $1 billion factory is expected to employ about 2,000 workers and make 300,000 cars a year, beginning in 2005. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Expanded Business Travel Coverage  The Times today introduces expanded weekly coverage of business travel, its rewards and its frustrations. The pages make their debut with ''On the Ground,'' by R. W. Apple Jr., who unpacks and unwinds in Washington. [C8-C10.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
