<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chilling Effect on the Great Global Melt</title>
    <meta content="Y18ICE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/18/science/18ICE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1360277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Antarctica</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Jet Propulsion Laboratory</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D61E38F93BA25752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chilling Effect on the Great Global Melt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chilling Effect on the Great Global Melt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New study of several inland rivers of ice that nourish vast West Antarctic Ice Sheet show that after long period of rapid movement and thinning caused by global warming flow is slowing and they are growing thicker; change means part of western Antarctica is likely to serve as frozen bank for water instead of source, countering predicted trend toward rising seas from global warming; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the biggest predicted impacts of global warming is a rise in sea level as ice on land melts. And nowhere is there more terrestrial ice than in Antarctica. If the vast West Antarctic Ice Sheet were to slide into the sea, it would raise oceans more than 13 feet.</p>
        <p>But a new study of several inland rivers of ice that nourish this sprawling frozen plain shows that after a long period of rapid movement and thinning, their flow is slowing, and as a result, they are growing thicker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A slowing of melting ice in Antarctica is slightly countering a trend toward rising seas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the biggest predicted impacts of global warming is a rise in sea level as ice on land melts. And nowhere is there more terrestrial ice than in Antarctica. If the vast West Antarctic Ice Sheet were to slide into the sea, it would raise oceans more than 13 feet.</p>
        <p>But a new study of several inland rivers of ice that nourish this sprawling frozen plain shows that after a long period of rapid movement and thinning, their flow is slowing, and as a result, they are growing thicker.</p>
        <p>The change means that this part of western Antarctica is likely to serve as a frozen bank for water instead of a source, slightly countering an overall trend toward rising seas, according to the research.</p>
        <p>In the study, described in today's issue of the journal Science, the researchers calculated that the change in the seaward flow of ice in this part of Antarctica could, by the end of the century, be the equivalent of turning off the Missouri River.</p>
        <p>The change appears to be related to the slow warming that has been going on since the end of the last ice age, 12,000 years ago, and not the accelerated warming trend in the last five decades that many scientists have ascribed in part to human activities, said the authors, Dr. Ian R. Joughin, an engineer at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in Pasadena, Calif., and Dr. Slawek Tulaczyk, a professor of earth sciences at the University of California, Santa Cruz.</p>
        <p>Along with other polar experts, Dr. Joughlin and Dr. Tulaczyk noted that other parts of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet were behaving in the opposite way, speeding up and sending more ice toward the sea, where great icebergs split from the broad ice shelf and eventually melt.</p>
        <p>As a result, the total contribution of all the Antarctic freezing and melting to the slow rise in sea levels remains unknown, said Dr. Richard B. Alley, an expert on ice and climate at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>''This teaches us more about the system,'' Dr. Alley said, referring to the new work. ''But it shouldn't affect what a coastal property owner thinks one way or the other.''</p>
        <p>Antarctica's ice sheets and the ice shelves that jut from the continent like the ragged brim of an old Panama hat are formed as snowfall in the interior eventually compresses into ice, which slowly slides downhill toward the sea.</p>
        <p>In places called ice streams, the flow can vary substantially. In some places, these ice streams exist where heat from geothermal activity transforms the underbelly of a glacier into a slick slurry of mud and water.</p>
        <p>The new study focused on several ice streams that lead into the Ross Ice Shelf, one of the broadest spots in the continent's floating frozen fringe. The scientists analyzed data collected by redirecting a Canadian satellite's radar-imaging device toward the Antarctic from its normal, northward-looking view.</p>
        <p>They found a substantial change from movement estimated in earlier studies of the same ice streams, Dr. Joughin said.</p>
        <p>If the slowdown continues at the same pace seen over the last 20 years, Dr. Joughin said, ''it could stop altogether in the next 70 or 80 years.'' He added, ''That would cause it to thicken more, because nothing is leaving.''</p>
        <p>In their paper, he and Dr. Tulaczyk said the slowing -- and eventual thickening -- of the ice might be a result of all the thinning that has occurred in the thousands of years since the last ice age.</p>
        <p>As the rivers of ice lose mass, the extreme cold at the surface can more easily migrate down through the ice and freeze any water acting as a lubricant deep beneath, causing the ice to stick to the earth and grind to a halt.</p>
        <p>In the long run, this could produce a stop-and-start rhythm, said Dr. Robert A. Bindschadler, a glaciologist at the NASA Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md.</p>
        <p>Once the ice streams start to thicken, the chill will not reach the bottom as easily, and the geothermal heat from below might melt some ice, allowing the glacier to start sliding toward the sea again, Dr. Bindschadler said.</p>
        <p>''It might cycle on and off or stay where it is,'' he said. ''But for now we can't say.''</p>
        <p>Whatever is happening in the streams feeding the Ross Ice Shelf is not happening farther north, where the Pine Island and Thwaites Glaciers are calving more icebergs than ever, said Dr. Eric Rignot, a glacier expert who works down the hall from Dr. Joughin at the NASA laboratory.</p>
        <p>''Antarctic still has pretty large uncertainties attached to it,'' Dr. Rignot said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
