<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sleep Apnea, a Noisy but Often Invisible Threat</title>
    <meta content="17BROD$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/17/health/anatomy/17BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1424325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apnea (Sleeping Disorder)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sleep Apnea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apnea (Sleep Disorder)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sleep</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1730F934A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sleep Apnea, a Noisy but Often Invisible Threat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sleep Apnea, a Noisy but Often Invisible Threat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Brody Personal Health article on sleep apnea and its potential threats to health; National Institutes of Health estimates that as many as 18 million Americans, 6 percent of population, have disorder; describes disease, its diagnosis and treatment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Holman of St. Paul is a very busy man, and he was not accustomed to having to ''let things go'' because he was too tired to do them. But tired he was, tired driving to and from work, tired during the day at the warehouse company he runs, too tired some days to play his beloved game of tennis after work, and really tired in the evening -- in bed by 8:30 to arise at 6.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Holman, an average-size 67-year-old, did nothing about his fatigue until his wife, Marna, threatened to move out of their bedroom because his snoring was keeping her awake. It was she who suggested that he might have sleep apnea. With it, breathing stops, often for a minute or longer, sometimes hundreds of times a night and resumes each time with a loud snort or snore. So at his wife's urging, Mr. Holman spent a night in the sleep laboratory at Abbott Northwestern Hospital in Minneapolis. Her suspicions were confirmed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As many as 18 million Americans have sleep apnea, though experts estimate that fewer than 10 percent of people who have it are aware of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Holman of St. Paul is a very busy man, and he was not accustomed to having to ''let things go'' because he was too tired to do them. But tired he was, tired driving to and from work, tired during the day at the warehouse company he runs, too tired some days to play his beloved game of tennis after work, and really tired in the evening -- in bed by 8:30 to arise at 6.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Holman, an average-size 67-year-old, did nothing about his fatigue until his wife, Marna, threatened to move out of their bedroom because his snoring was keeping her awake. It was she who suggested that he might have sleep apnea. With it, breathing stops, often for a minute or longer, sometimes hundreds of times a night and resumes each time with a loud snort or snore. So at his wife's urging, Mr. Holman spent a night in the sleep laboratory at Abbott Northwestern Hospital in Minneapolis. Her suspicions were confirmed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holman now sleeps with a device that assists his breathing, and both he and his wife, who feared he would fall asleep while driving and kill himself or someone else, are feeling a lot better.</p>
        <p>The National Institutes of Health estimates that as many as 18 million Americans, 6 percent of the nation, have sleep apnea. After the proliferation of sleep centers around the country and greater awareness of the condition, the diagnosis of sleep apnea increased twelvefold from 1990 to 1998.</p>
        <p>Still, experts estimate that fewer than 10 percent of people who have it are aware of it. As a result, they risk their health and their lives and possibly the lives of others.</p>
        <p>What Is Sleep Apnea?</p>
        <p>The word apnea is Greek and means ''with no breath.'' As the name of the condition implies, sleep apnea occurs only while a person sleeps. With obstructive sleep apnea, by far the most common type, the airway repeatedly becomes blocked, usually by soft tissue at the back of the throat. With central sleep apnea, no blockage occurs, but the brain fails to signal the respiratory muscles to breathe. A third type, mixed sleep apnea, is a combination of the two.</p>
        <p>In most cases of obstructive sleep apnea, the muscles of the soft palate relax at the base of the tongue and the small fleshy piece hanging at the back of the throat, or the uvula, causing the tissue to sag and block the airway.</p>
        <p>This is most likely to occur when sleeping on one's back, but it can also happen in other positions. These involuntary breathing pauses may occur as many as 20 or 30 times an hour all night long.</p>
        <p>Breathing resumes when the blood oxygen level falls low enough and the carbon dioxide level rises high enough to stimulate the brain into action. Although the afflicted person is unaware of what is happening, with each apnea episode, the brain arouses from deep, restful sleep, resulting in a night's sleep that is fragmented and of poor quality.</p>
        <p>After spending up to 10 hours in bed, the sufferers may think they got enough sleep, only to feel groggy in the morning and sleepy for much of the day.</p>
        <p>Sleep apnea is very common, as common as adult-onset diabetes. It is most common among middle-aged men who are overweight, especially those with fat necks. But it spares no age group or body size. Even some children have sleep apnea, which is a suspected cause of some cases of sudden unexplained infant death. It has been estimated that as many as 40 percent of elderly residents in nursing homes have sleep apnea.</p>
        <p>In some cases, sleep apnea seems to run in families, suggesting that it may sometimes have a genetic basis. But whatever its basis, the condition is made worse by the consumption of alcohol or use of sleeping pills, which impair the brain's arousal mechanism.</p>
        <p>In addition to the obvious risks of falling asleep while driving or operating dangerous machinery, life-disrupting consequences and serious, even life-threatening, health hazards can accompany sleep apnea.</p>
        <p>Although cause and effect are not well established, untreated sleep apnea is associated with high blood pressure, an irregular heartbeat, heart attack and stroke. The afflicted may experience headaches, weight gain, learning and memory problems, depression, irritability and impotence.</p>
        <p>Diagnosis and Treatment</p>
        <p>Mr. Holman and others are among the lucky ones for having spouses or companions who suspect something is wrong. Those who live alone may face a bigger problem: even when the snoring becomes outrageously loud, it does not fully awaken the snorers.</p>
        <p>For them, it may be up to co-workers or friends to notice that they fall asleep repeatedly at inappropriate times. Also, a personal physician will sometimes ask the right questions to unveil the possibility of a sleep disorder.</p>
        <p>The most accurate diagnosis is obtained by spending a night in a sleep laboratory hooked up to instruments that measure electrical activity of the brain, heart rate, muscle activity, eye movements, respiratory effort and oxygen levels in the blood. This test, called polysomnography, can assess the existence of sleep apnea and its severity.</p>
        <p>But even with the increase in the number of sleep centers, now some 2,200 nationwide, not everyone with a major sleep disorder has easy access to one. Also, just one night in a sleep laboratory can cost $1,000 to $2,500, and it is not always covered by medical insurance.</p>
        <p>If money is a concern, be sure to check first with your insurance company. If necessary, your personal physician may be able to intervene and obtain pretest approval for insurance coverage.</p>
        <p>With improved technology, it may also be possible to perform polysomnography at home through a remote connection to a sleep laboratory. There are also some less involved diagnostic tests that can be done at home that are almost as accurate as polysomnography.</p>
        <p>For example, the Food and Drug Administration just approved a device called NovaSom QSG, developed by Sleep Solutions, for at-home diagnosis of obstructive sleep apnea. It can be used to collect three nights of data more conveniently and at lower cost than one night in a sleep lab. Another validated F.D.A.-approved device, the Remmers Sleep Recorder, can obtain the necessary data in one night's use in the patient's home.</p>
        <p>Once diagnosed, sleep apnea should be treated by an expert. Administering oxygen or medications does not eliminate the problem. Patients should be advised to avoid alcohol, tobacco and sleeping pills, and those who are overweight should be told to lose at least 10 percent of body weight.</p>
        <p>The most common treatment -- called continuous positive airway pressure -- involves nightly use of a mask over the nose that transfers pressurized air from a blower through the nasal passages. The pressure prevents the tissues in the throat from collapsing.</p>
        <p>Most drastic are surgical procedures, including removal of tonsils and adenoids or removal of excess tissue at the back of the throat -- tonsils, uvula and part of the soft palate -- with a success rate of only 30 percent to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>The National Center on Sleep Disorders Research cautions that while laser-assisted surgery may decrease or eliminate snoring, it does not cure sleep apnea itself or reduce its attendant risks.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
