<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Havana, Film Festival Hits a Chord</title>
    <meta content="12NOTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/12/movies/12NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1447851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Havana (Cuba)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Julie Taymor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba/Havana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cuba</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Taymor, Julie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Glover, Danny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD9153AF931A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Havana, Film Festival Hits a Chord</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Havana, Film Festival Hits a Chord</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <dateline>HAVANA, Dec. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell Critic's Notebook column on scene in Havana, Cuba, as city hosts 24th Festival Internacional del Nuevo Cine Latinoamericano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Havana seems to be a tribute to combustion; huge factory chimneys exhale flames and soot into the skies. And making its surprising presence known is the four-cylinder engine. The tales about Cuba's biggest city may dwell on the hulking 1950's American Fords and Chevrolets with their robust eight-cylinder blocks shouldering their way past the numerous statues of political figures like José Martí, but Havana has a startling number of efficient little Hyundais and Fiats. A Fiat dealership is roughly a mile away from the Hotel Nacional de Cuba, headquarters of the 24th Festival Internacional del Nuevo Cine Latinoamericano.</p>
        <p>The Nacional, an old luxury hotel whose size is in keeping with the land yachts that are still plentiful here, is where almost as many Americans as there are compact economy cars are staying in connection with the festival; you would hardly know there was an American embargo in effect. Among those Americanos who can be seen during the event, which began on Dec. 3 and runs through Dec. 13, is Matt Dillon, whose newest directorial effort, ''City of Ghosts'' had its debut here. He can be seen greeting fans and proudly discussing his acquisitions: vintage record albums featuring top Cuban musical performers of the 1950's, smiling in night-black tuxedos on the covers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The presence of so many Americans at the 24th Festival Internacional del Nuevo Cine Latinoamericano didn't distract from Havana's enchanting peculiarities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Havana seems to be a tribute to combustion; huge factory chimneys exhale flames and soot into the skies. And making its surprising presence known is the four-cylinder engine. The tales about Cuba's biggest city may dwell on the hulking 1950's American Fords and Chevrolets with their robust eight-cylinder blocks shouldering their way past the numerous statues of political figures like José Martí, but Havana has a startling number of efficient little Hyundais and Fiats. A Fiat dealership is roughly a mile away from the Hotel Nacional de Cuba, headquarters of the 24th Festival Internacional del Nuevo Cine Latinoamericano.</p>
        <p>The Nacional, an old luxury hotel whose size is in keeping with the land yachts that are still plentiful here, is where almost as many Americans as there are compact economy cars are staying in connection with the festival; you would hardly know there was an American embargo in effect. Among those Americanos who can be seen during the event, which began on Dec. 3 and runs through Dec. 13, is Matt Dillon, whose newest directorial effort, ''City of Ghosts'' had its debut here. He can be seen greeting fans and proudly discussing his acquisitions: vintage record albums featuring top Cuban musical performers of the 1950's, smiling in night-black tuxedos on the covers.</p>
        <p>Given the number of Americans here this year, it's not surprising to learn that for the first time in the festival's history, no new feature-length Cuban fiction films will be shown; this means the competition films include ''Real Women Have Curves,'' the likable comedy-drama about Latinas and self-image that's set in Los Angeles and mostly in English. The presence of so many Americans can't distract from the city's enchanting peculiarities. It seems to be a place that literally causes breathlessness. The Caribbean humidity, combined with the auto exhausts, rusting metal and tobacco -- so prevalent it sometimes seems as though infants smoke cigars on elevators -- can leave you pixilated, a little lightheaded. (Flying into the city, you can almost see the ozone layer being clawed at by the output of the grunting engines.)</p>
        <p>Also a little breathtaking are the lively, friendly Cuban people, and their deep, intelligent love of the movies, which are not readily available because of the embargo and cultural restriction. Their excitement over the rare 10-day flood of films from around the world, but centering on Latin America, is evident in the voluminous old theaters where Cubans wait patiently for hours in lines that rope around the decaying city blocks.</p>
        <p>Amusingly, size counts, or did in many of the pre-revolution movie palaces, like the Yara, that dot the cityscape. It's where a thrilled crowd, including soldiers, packed the screening of ''El Crimen del Padre Amaro,'' the Mexican melodrama starring Gael García Bernal as a hot-blooded young priest drawn into a tryst with a female parishioner.</p>
        <p>The audience giggled with delight when the absurdly charismatic Mr. Bernal, with his forlorn, overripe sexiness, first loped into camera range. Whenever the joy of an audience member was too loud in this theater with its one-channel Dolby sound -- the Yara has the old-school echoey acoustics of a cave or a church -- audience shushing, a hissing that rose like heat in an old Manhattan walk-up, vibrated throughout.</p>
        <p>Like the cars and the other withering, beat-up buildings, the Yara suffers from a term that's used in viniculture: noble rot. The deteriorating theaters and other structures have only the crumbling dignity of an older generation's adherence to quality, like the vintage cars disintegrating under layers of what appears to be household latex paint.</p>
        <p>''Those cars are a symbol for me of perseverance -- people here make so much of the little they have,'' said the director Julie Taymor, who is visiting Havana for the first time with her biopic ''Frida,'' starring Salma Hayek as the Mexican artist Frida Kahlo. The movie, concentrating on Kahlo's life, her embracing of Communism and the emotionally extravagant path she cut through the Mexico of the early 20th-century, seems like a natural for this place, not only because of the subject matter but also because of the film's look. ''It's a period piece, and a lot of Havana still looks exactly like that,'' Ms. Taymor said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor, who came to Havana with the composer of the ''Frida'' score, Elliot Goldenthal, was blunt about what motivated her trip here. ''Salma and I really wanted the movie to come here,'' she said. ''There's no market -- you're not coming here to sell the film, so you're coming out of your own interest. Salma's schedule got screwed up, so Elliot and I brought ourselves. I guess Miramax didn't see the value, but I think it's a strong thing for Cubans to see American artists with interests outside American culture. And we, as a country, don't have that understanding of the arts as a social movement that Communist countries do. When we use the words 'art' and 'sophistication' about movies in America there's a disdain.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor said she was enthusiastic about the Cuban appetite for film. ''A lot of Cubans have come up to me and said they saw 'Titus,' '' Ms. Taymor said, referring to her previous film, ''Titus Andronicus.'' ''How? TV. Pirated versions. More people saw it here than in New York City.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taymor said she found the Cuban audience's reaction to ''Frida'' fascinating. ''Every single nuance got a different response,'' she said. ''All of the political figures here are on a pedestal. We made history human and they liked it. We were told they'd never seen Trotsky as a man, only as propaganda. When Geoffrey Rush, playing Trotsky, says, 'Stalin is so dull,' there was a great reaction.''</p>
        <p>The actor and social activist Danny Glover, visiting the festival without having a film here, could be seen milling with crowds at the Nacional, too. ''If you go to other festivals,'' he said, ''you don't walk around. It's because this is not a festival about business, which makes Cannes and Sundance so insular.</p>
        <p>''It's a festival about people trying to find a voice and attracts films from other Americas -- Central and South Americas -- trying to do the same thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glover said he was visiting Havana for the fifth time; he first attended the festival when he came down with Jonathan Demme to introduce ''Beloved.'' ''Cuban films like 'The Last Supper' have been my favorites for about 25 years,'' he said. ''Before I came down, I was thinking about 'Life Is a Whistle,' which is very critical in very subtle ways, one of the only ways film can be here. I first came down to meet with artists, like Flora Fong and Mandive. Those trips had nothing to do with film, but I saw that same kind of dialogue in their work.</p>
        <p>''And that's one thing about it here. When you come for the film festival, it ends up being more than an event to introduce a film, because other relationships with other kinds of artists who come out during the festival start to develop. They have for me. But you know, the whole landscape of embargo draws people away, and that's sad.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glover leaned in and smiled. ''Then again,'' he said, ''it draws certain kinds of people to Cuba, too.''</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
