<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BackTalk; Hold Your Breath and a Spear Gun For a Sport Filled With Adventure</title>
    <meta content="Y11SPE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/11/sports/othersports/11SPEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1415194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Backtalk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Striped Bass</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">West, Owen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Florida Keys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Florida Keys/Key West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Key West (Fla)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DD123AF932A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BackTalk; Hold Your Breath and a Spear Gun For a Sport Filled With Adventure</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hold Your Breath and a Spear Gun</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By OWEN WEST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">West, Owen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spearfishing for striped bass underwater is adventure sport that requires stealth and experience, not speed or strength of other extreme activities; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because life has become so automated and easy, the American adventure lust burns more brightly than it ever has. People are plunging into so-called extreme sports to kindle that base urge even as the imperatives of family mount and the number of remote controls multiply. To many, the thrill is sparked in the mountains or woods. I choose the ocean and spearfishing because there is risk, a rewarding meal waiting below the surface and an adventure that I will be able to capture for several more decades.</p>
        <p>At 32, mine is a twilight age in most sports, but I have yet to reach my peak in spearfishing. My companions are often over 60. Stalking striped bass underwater on breaths of air as large as your lungs can hold takes guile and experience, not speed or strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spearfishing is an extreme sport that offers a risk, a rewarding meal and an adventure that is not limited to the young.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because life has become so automated and easy, the American adventure lust burns more brightly than it ever has. People are plunging into so-called extreme sports to kindle that base urge even as the imperatives of family mount and the number of remote controls multiply. To many, the thrill is sparked in the mountains or woods. I choose the ocean and spearfishing because there is risk, a rewarding meal waiting below the surface and an adventure that I will be able to capture for several more decades.</p>
        <p>At 32, mine is a twilight age in most sports, but I have yet to reach my peak in spearfishing. My companions are often over 60. Stalking striped bass underwater on breaths of air as large as your lungs can hold takes guile and experience, not speed or strength.</p>
        <p>On a recent outing, we were five miles from Block Island, R.I., when Rudy Enders, 70, known as Spooky, struggled into his wetsuit as whitecaps slammed into our bow, spraying us like shotgun pellets in the 20-knot wind. But we didn't turn back; the striper run is short. My father, Bing, has a collection of these die-hards, men who spent their formative years chasing other men in black pajamas. Rudy is a former C.I.A. special operations officer who speared 400-pound fish in the 1950's, killed a great white shark in the 1970's, and whose hand was chopped up and crippled by a seven-foot moray eel off Key West, Fla.</p>
        <p>We made the 30-mile journey to Block Island instead of diving around Newport, because there are so many fish traps along that scenic shore they could be anti-submarine nets protecting the coast from imaginary U-boats. As we anchored in 30 feet of water off the beach, Rudy staggered to the gunwale in full battle dress: a thick wetsuit to combat the 52-degree water, a 25-pound weight belt to help him plummet to the bottom, the same mask, snorkel and fins that were issued him in 1953, and his six-foot speargun that is essentially an elongated cross-bow powered by rubber tubes.</p>
        <p>''I'm just going to take a look around,'' he announced, rubbing spit into his mask. Right. When they see black-suited skin divers, striped bass jet away and alert other fish as they depart. So the first diver in the water has the best chance and everyone races to get dressed.</p>
        <p>That's what we did, everyone except the boat's captain, Lloyd Sunderland, 72. Over a decade ago, Lloyd was first in the water on a day when the visibility was less than 15 feet. Lloyd saw the black oval of a small ship's compass hovering in the haze about 10 feet below the surface. He sucked in a breath and dove toward it. It will look terrific on my boat, he thought. Then the compass turned slightly and glided toward him. As Lloyd explains it, ''My stomach felt like I was on the edge of a cliff, about to fall. Then the feeling spread to my chest and I couldn't breathe. Finally my brain got the message: A compass doesn't swim. That's an eyeball.''</p>
        <p>The shark was so big -- like a small car -- that its gray body blended with the gray of the water. One flick of its tail sent Lloyd tumbling backward -- gun, mask and breath gone. Lloyd did the human thing: he set the 100-meter open ocean swim record to the boat. The other divers saw the huge shadow gliding out to sea as Lloyd flung himself over the gunwale. To this day Lloyd still dives with us, but I always beat him into the water.</p>
        <p>Since Rudy headed east, when I hit the water I slowly finned to the west. Scuba instructors say to dive with a buddy. But in the murky New England waters, spearfishermen give each other a wide berth. It's a lonely sport with no place for imagination lest the monsters that patrol the mind erode precious oxygen. I started my breathing routine, slow breaths at first, followed by a shallow, rapid-fire burst, then a final deep suck that stretched my lungs.</p>
        <p>Rapid breathing expels carbon dioxide, raising the threshold for apnea -- thirst for oxygen -- by deadening the alarm systems in the lungs that are set off by carbon dioxide. To avoid shallow-water blackout, I would surface at the first serious thirst for oxygen, spending about the same time above and below water for the next few hours.</p>
        <p>I tipped forward and flipped my legs over my head to gain some downward momentum. When my fins were underwater -- and silent -- I took two kicks. They were enough to send me on my way without using any extra oxygen. Soon I was plummeting into the dark, fingers pinching my nose to help with equalization. A boulder rose up out of the murk and I managed to tilt the big gun in time.</p>
        <p>I oriented myself and assumed an ambush position between two rocks, staring hopefully into the darkness, listening for the tell-tale whump of their massive tails. Two fish swam by, but I held my shot; as a rule, a diver never takes more than a single fish and I was hoping for something bigger. I heard the metallic snick of another diver's speargun discharge -- the sound so magnified I thought it might have been my dad, 40 feet away, or Rudy, 400 feet away -- and the stripers were gone. I stayed underwater about a minute listening for another approach, praying that, unlike the thousands before it, this would be the dive on which the monster bass would intersect my life.</p>
        <p>The steady ache of the rising carbon dioxide level set off the alarm. My time in the ambush spot was up. I rotated into the vertical and kicked for the surface. In an instant, a striper burst from behind a clump of seaweed and he was alongside me, a shimmering wall of silver splashed with dark, horizontal stripes. It was more than 40 pounds, so large that for a millisecond I took it for a shark. I tried to avoid direct eye contact --their curiosity holds a split-second longer if you appear uninterested -- but silver ghosts are mesmerizing apparitions. The striper was so close that I could have reached out and touched its shimmering flank. One second to shoot. Not enough time for the gun to get around.</p>
        <p>Its dorsal fin suddenly sprang up and, with a flick of the wide tail, it took a tight turn, gripping the water, rocketing behind me. I swiveled my head in time to see the big tail fade into the green. Thousands of dives for a moment like this. When I reached the surface and gasped, my dad heard the commotion and leisurely swam over. When I told the story, he chuckled in his snorkel. The sympathy seemed smothered.</p>
        <p>Dad speared a 50-pound world record fish almost half a century ago. How old will I be when one of us lands the 60-pounder?</p>
        <p>Backtalk Owen West, the author of the novel ''Sharkman Six'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2001), is a commodities trader at Goldman, Sachs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Owen West, the author of the novel ''Sharkman Six'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 2001), is a commodities trader at Goldman, Sachs.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
