<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Little Terror Who Wasn't; No Bomb, but Expelled Boy Still Finds Zero Tolerance</title>
    <meta content="27BOMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/27/nyregion/27BOMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1371164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Livingston (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallner, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey (USA)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD1431F934A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Little Terror Who Wasn't; No Bomb, but Expelled Boy Still Finds Zero Tolerance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Little Terror Who Wasn't</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>LIVINGSTON, N.J., Feb. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Michael Mallner, 15-year-old from Livingston, NJ, who was arrested year ago with another teen-ager, accused of carrying 'pipe bomb' to school; it turns out that 'bomb' was something less than that, and prosecutors acknowledge that boys were not out do hurt anyone; Mallner is confined to his home by court order as punishment for breaking into school; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was an audacious, chilling crime, one with the potential to rival the horrors of Columbine. At least that is how it seemed a year ago last week, when the police arrested two 14-year-old boys in this affluent suburb and accused them of trying to blow up their middle school.</p>
        <p>After the two were caught leaving the deserted school on a Saturday, the police chief spoke ominously of an ''explosive device'' that had been found on one boy, Michael Mallner. The county bomb squad was dispatched, and a battalion of television reporters stationed themselves outside Michael's home, capturing the nighttime scene as investigators removed a computer, books and items detectives described as ''bomb-making material.'' Terrified parents, recalling the bloodshed at other schools across the country, demanded stern punishment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The parents of a student expelled for a bomb threat say their son has been victimized.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was an audacious, chilling crime, one with the potential to rival the horrors of Columbine. At least that is how it seemed a year ago last week, when the police arrested two 14-year-old boys in this affluent suburb and accused them of trying to blow up their middle school.</p>
        <p>After the two were caught leaving the deserted school on a Saturday, the police chief spoke ominously of an ''explosive device'' that had been found on one boy, Michael Mallner. The county bomb squad was dispatched, and a battalion of television reporters stationed themselves outside Michael's home, capturing the nighttime scene as investigators removed a computer, books and items detectives described as ''bomb-making material.'' Terrified parents, recalling the bloodshed at other schools across the country, demanded stern punishment.</p>
        <p>That evening, Michael, who was accused of carrying a pipe bomb, was sent to a juvenile detention center in Newark, where, he says, over the next six weeks he was repeatedly attacked by other youths.</p>
        <p>Expelled from school, he now lives at home under one of the state's most rigid forms of probation for juveniles, which forbids him to leave the house without permission, and then only with a parent.</p>
        <p>But a year after an episode that seemed to confirm and inflame public fears about school violence, the case of ''the bomber boy,'' as one New York tabloid called Michael, has turned out to be somewhat less lurid.</p>
        <p>Although the police initially talked of bombs and suggested a wider plot, prosecutors later acknowledged in court that the boys were not out to hurt anyone. The device that the police initially said could ''kill or maim, or cause serious damage to a building'' was actually a motley assortment of objects, including a plastic M &amp; M's tube, a burned-out road flare and a carbon dioxide canister filled with model-rocket fuel.</p>
        <p>Those items, Michael and his family contend, were simply part of his model-rocket hobby, and the illicit foray into school was an ill-guided adventure, inspired by an open window, not a mission to harm others.</p>
        <p>In an era of homicidal students, zero-tolerance school policies and adult sentences for youthful offenders, Michael's parents, Anton and Sherry Mallner, say they believe that their son has been victimized by a system that confuses adolescent pranksters with murderous psychopaths.</p>
        <p>''If this had occurred 10 years ago, none of this would have happened to Michael,'' said Mr. Mallner, an executive at a Manhattan bank.</p>
        <p>Since the Columbine massacre, the police and schools have been understandably swift and unforgiving in their response to misconduct. When a menacing sign appears -- a scribbled threat, a weapon, an e-mail message -- there is little time to tell malevolence from mere mischief.</p>
        <p>But the last year has offered many clues that Michael Mallner is no volatile sociopath.</p>
        <p>In recent court hearings involving the terms of his open-ended probation, psychologists, probation officials and teachers have testified that Michael, now 15, is thoughtful and well adjusted, a top-notch student with excellent social skills and genuine regret for his actions.</p>
        <p>''He's a wonderful kid,'' Lenore Friedman, his history teacher, testified last month. ''He's charming, he does his work thoroughly, and he's a youngster with great compassion.''</p>
        <p>Still, no one claims that Michael is a model teenager. In Essex County Family Court last April, he pleaded guilty to criminal trespassing for entering the school; burglary for stealing keys to a display case; and vandalism, stemming from an earlier incident in which he and several friends set off a carbon dioxide cartridge inside a soda machine outside the school. The device, filled with nails, blew off a piece of the machine, but no one noticed until another boy confessed. after the later incident.</p>
        <p>In the end, prosecutors abandoned their contention that Michael's conduct was malicious. They focused their prosecution on the soda machine incident, portraying it as reckless and potentially injurious to others. (The other boy arrested in the school break-in was ordered to perform 150 hours of community service and is back in school.)</p>
        <p>''This is not a dangerous individual,'' said Jody Pope, a lawyer for the Mallner family who is seeking to have the terms of Michael's probation eased, and to have the school district take him back.</p>
        <p>''Here you have a boy who behaved irresponsibly, but for the past year, he's been mangled by the system. The punishment not only far outweighs the crime, but is beginning to damage him psychologically.''</p>
        <p>Frustrated by their experience, the Mallners decided last week to waive the anonymity the law confers on juvenile offenders and invited a reporter into their home. The Livingston police did not return calls, and prosecutors and probation officials said they could not talk about Michael, citing confidentiality rules.</p>
        <p>Robert Grady, the superintendent of Livingston schools, said the school board would not reconsider Michael's expulsion until he attended an alternative school for a period of time.</p>
        <p>The Mallners, however, refuse to send him to the schools selected by the board, saying they are for emotionally disturbed and troubled youths. Michael, who was once in the school's program for gifted youth, is neither troubled nor disturbed, they insist.</p>
        <p>''We cannot find anyone rational to deal with,'' said his mother. ''Sometimes I feel like they are just trying to drive us away from this community.''</p>
        <p>Michael admits that he was up to no good when he and his friend crawled through an open window at Mount Pleasant Middle School on Feb. 17, 2001. A self-described science nerd, Michael had been exploring model rocketry and, he concedes, a curiosity about the explosive propulsion that makes the rockets fly.</p>
        <p>Rather than set his latest homemade contraption off in the Mallners' backyard, he and three friends headed to the school sports field a block away. When they noticed the open window, Michael said, they decided to engage in some tomfoolery. Their most ambitious idea, he said, was to glue together doors and books.</p>
        <p>But once inside, Michael and a friend broke into a secretary's office and took a set of keys. They also unknowingly tripped a silent alarm. When they emerged from the building 10 minutes later, they were arrested, and during his search of the youths, an officer found the plastic tube and flare taped to Michael's pants leg. Explaining later why he had hid them, Michael said, ''I was in a furtive undercover mood.''</p>
        <p>To the authorities, the candy tube and fuel-filled cartridge constituted a pipe bomb. A search of the Mallners' home yielded a variety of items they believed were intended for Michael's device: fuses, spent shotgun shells, electrical tape and copies of Scientific American.</p>
        <p>Michael, an avid junk collector and tinkerer, said the shells were found during a family hike; the fuses, he said, were for his rockets.</p>
        <p>Slight and gawky, Michael is unabashedly bookish, painfully courteous and, these days, wise beyond his years. He dreams of being a biochemist and revels in science fiction novels, insect collecting and dismantling broken electronic equipment. He acknowledges that his actions were potentially dangerous. ''People can't see the difference between showing off, testing the boundaries and killing people,'' he said. ''I went into the school to see what I could get away with, not because I wanted to kill anyone.''</p>
        <p>Michael said the most difficult part of his punishment was the six weeks he spent at the Essex County Youth House in Newark. One cellmate, he said, beat him and tried to strangle him. Another, he said, tried to sexually assault him. After three requests to the court, Michael was placed in his own cell.</p>
        <p>Although he is back home now, Michael is far from free. He no longer wears an electronic ankle monitor, but he can leave the house only with advance permission from his probation officer. The requests, his parents said, are often denied, and sometimes the approval comes too late. He was not allowed to attend his sister's bat mitzvah, and library visits or family outings to Manhattan are often denied. He is allowed to go to Hebrew classes and the Goodwill thrift store, where he does his community service, but for now, all his primary schooling takes place at home, with tutors paid for by the district. He is not allowed to use the Internet.</p>
        <p>Padding around in his family's modest ranch house last week, Michael said he was often bored, but he expressed most concern for his stunted social life and the notion, spread by news reports last year, that he is a budding killer.</p>
        <p>''A lot of my friends are starting to date and go to parties,'' he said enviously. ''When you're stuck inside all day you don't have much to talk about with your friends. They're still nice to me, but mostly they've forgotten about me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
