<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New-Model Ford on a Risky Track</title>
    <meta content="29FORD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/29/business/yourmoney/29FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20021006T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1427616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEEDF1638F93AA1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="2948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New-Model Ford on a Risky Track</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New-Model Ford on a Risky Track</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr, Ford Motor chief executive for 11 months, wins praise for remarking management team, but many analysts remain deeply pessimistic about prospects of company, which they say needs more new car and truck models and has to reduce its labor costs to be competitive with rivals; Ford expresses deep personal commitment to turning company around; defends himself against environmentalists who have criticized him for not bucking industry's lobbying against tighter gas mileage requirements; photo of Ford; photos of two 2004 models, Five Hundred and CrosTrainer, which company hopes will help it regain market share; graph (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the lobby of Ford Motor's corporate headquarters here, there's a countdown clock that, at one moment this morning, read 260 days, 23 hours, 59 minutes and 59 seconds. That's how long William Clay Ford Jr. has to right his great-grandfather's company before its centennial on June 16.</p>
        <p>''The centennial is obviously a hugely important time for this company because it celebrates something that most American companies don't reach,'' Mr. Ford said in an interview looking back on his first 11 months as chief executive. ''As proud as I am of our history, I'm more interested in our future.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr. has managed to win over some skeptics in the industry  largely for remaking the management team  but hardly all of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the lobby of Ford Motor's corporate headquarters here, there's a countdown clock that, at one moment this morning, read 260 days, 23 hours, 59 minutes and 59 seconds. That's how long William Clay Ford Jr. has to right his great-grandfather's company before its centennial on June 16.</p>
        <p>''The centennial is obviously a hugely important time for this company because it celebrates something that most American companies don't reach,'' Mr. Ford said in an interview looking back on his first 11 months as chief executive. ''As proud as I am of our history, I'm more interested in our future.''</p>
        <p>Nearly a year after pushing out the company's hard-charging and abrasive previous chief executive, Jacques A. Nasser, Mr. Ford has managed to win over some skeptics in the industry -- largely for remaking the management team -- but hardly all of them. Many analysts remain deeply pessimistic about the company, which lost $5.5 billion last year. What Ford still lacks and desperately needs, its critics say, are more new cars and new trucks that people want to buy. Most of all, it has to reduce its costs to be competitive with rivals.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Ford took over, the company's stock price has fallen 40 percent. Although the company recently surprised Wall Street by saying it would have its second consecutive profitable quarter after four in the red, the profits are slight. And while overall auto sales are high, Ford's market share continues to fall despite its aggressive spending on incentives like interest-free financing; meanwhile, its archrival, General Motors, is tallying a slight gain in share.</p>
        <p>''The last year, there hasn't been much fun about it,'' said Mr. Ford, 45. ''Particularly the last nine months, when you wake up and wonder what land mine is going to explode today. And there was no shortage of them, obviously. But I do see light at the end of the tunnel.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford has spent much of his time simply getting the corporate house in order. Now he has to ensure that his management team will actually figure out how to cut billions of dollars in costs and make sure his plans to introduce 60 new or redesigned cars and trucks over the next three years is realized. Mr. Ford has made some progress in smoothing tense relationships with suppliers, dealers, employees and some consumers, but doubters still wonder if he is tough enough and experienced enough to finish the job.</p>
        <p>In a period of mercenary chief executives, Mr. Ford comes across as a weary father of four, which he is, trying to wrestle the family business back from the brink. But this family business is one of the world's most storied and complex. Wanting to save it runs in the genes -- and bank accounts. His extended family owns 40 percent of the voting shares.</p>
        <p>MR. FORD, who goes by Bill, first reported for work, as a product planning analyst, in 1979. That was the last year his uncle, Henry Ford II, reigned at the company, which he had revived from near bankruptcy in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>No question, Bill Ford represents change. Although he has been criticized recently by the Sierra Club for supporting the industry's lobbying against higher gasoline mileage standards, Mr. Ford is a far cry from the typical Motor City executive. He is a vegetarian in a steak-loving industry and a black belt in tae kwon do who keeps an acoustic guitar in his office. His musical taste runs to Bob Dylan, and in moments of escape, he likes going to folk clubs in Ann Arbor, where he lives. (Most auto executives gravitate to Detroit's more conservative, wealthier suburbs, like Bloomfield Hills.)</p>
        <p>For years, he has made speeches warning about global warming, the very existence of which many auto executives question. His pet project is rebuilding the sprawling River Rouge plant in Dearborn -- Henry Ford's superfactory -- with a roof covered in vegetation that would convert carbon dioxide emissions into oxygen.</p>
        <p>By most accounts, Mr. Ford preferred overseeing the company as chairman -- his previous role -- to running day-to-day operations. But by last October, his options had narrowed. The company had been devastated by mismanagement, its products were aging and its Explorer had been wounded by the Firestone tire blowout debacle. The company's manufacturing efficiencies and quality rankings lagged behind not only the Japanese but also G.M.</p>
        <p>''The situation is difficult,'' said Stephen Girsky, an analyst at Morgan Stanley, calling Ford ''the high-cost producer in a marginally differentiated commodity business.''</p>
        <p>If the automotive operations were struggling a year ago, its financial operations were arguably worse. Ford's financing unit was badly overextended because of aggressive lending to customers with shaky credit. And some of the company's blunders were downright embarrassing: it lost, for example, $1 billion for not properly hedging against price shifts in platinum used in catalytic converters.</p>
        <p>The burden weighs heavily on Mr. Ford. ''I feel like I'm a caretaker of our culture and our legacy,'' he said. ''I'm working for my children and grandchildren, and I feel I'm working for our employees' children and grandchildren as well. I think our employees have a sense that there's accountability here, that I'm not going to take the money and run.''</p>
        <p>To get things rolling, he presented a turnaround plan in January that cuts 35,000 jobs; that goal hinges on having labor unions agree to close five plants. Mr. Ford's mantra is ''back to basics'' -- focusing on Ford's core business, making cars and trucks. Mr. Nasser had wanted to make Ford a more broadly focused consumer products conglomerate.</p>
        <p>Since announcing the plan, Mr. Ford has tried to rebuild the company's image by starring in the industry's biggest personality-driven TV campaign this side of Lee Iacocca; the multimillion-dollar effort will grab about one-third of the Ford brand's total ad budget.</p>
        <p>But with Wall Street, investors and the news media, he has taken a much lower profile. ''I didn't want to go out and talk about the progress we were making until I had a coherent story to tell,'' he said. ''Only now do I feel like we're at the point where we can go out, and you'll see us more visible with investors and Wall Street. But, frankly, what we laid out was a five-year plan.''</p>
        <p>Even some bulls question the approach. ''It would be reassuring to see Bill and some of the senior people more often, to understand the texture of what's going on inside the company,'' said John Casesa, a Merrill Lynch analyst. ''Short of information, people assume the worst when you're in this kind of a turnaround situation.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Casesa gives Mr. Ford credit for rebuilding the company's entire top level of management, others say more shuffling is needed.</p>
        <p>Peter J. Pestillo, chief executive of the auto supply giant Visteon and a former top Ford executive, said: ''I think Bill is a terrific executive who is well grounded in the company. He inherited a place in significant disrepair. I don't believe he's made as many executive changes as he needs to to be effective.''</p>
        <p>To address the company's stagnating auto business in North America, Mr. Ford had looked to one of the company's few bright spots, Ford of Europe, which is in the midst of a successful turnaround. Last fall, he named Nicholas V. Scheele, that unit's chairman, president and chief operating officer.</p>
        <p>But critics wanted more, especially the analysts who said the cost cutting was not fast enough. In May, Ford announced that it would elevate another top European executive, David W. Thursfield, a respected and tough specialist in cost cutting. He heads worldwide purchasing.</p>
        <p>In mid-September, Mr. Scheele said Ford was ahead of its goal to cut costs in future vehicles by $200 each.</p>
        <p>The management that most concerned Mr. Ford was at Ford Credit, the financing arm.</p>
        <p>Problems heightened last December, when the company caught Wall Street off guard by saying its quarterly loss would be five times as much as expected. The culprit was a tide of car repossessions and delinquent loans.</p>
        <p>''The biggest fear I had in January was that Ford Credit was going to implode,'' Mr. Ford said. ''I also knew that the rest of my management team were all automotive types. Our ability to step in and fix Ford Credit was limited.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford tapped Carl Reichardt, 71, the former chief executive of Wells Fargo and a Ford board member, to oversee finances as vice chairman and Allan D. Gilmour, 68, to return as chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>Greg C. Smith, installed to run Ford Credit, said: ''We were aggressively growing some elements of our business that we are not any longer. We had started a subprime or nonprime automotive lending company called Fairlane Credit that we have stopped.''</p>
        <p>Analysts are still concerned about another practice at Ford Credit (as well as at G.M. and Chrysler): the proliferation of incentives like interest-free financing. In a report this month, Gary Lapidus of Goldman, Sachs said Ford's lending practices could put it in considerable financial disarray. Ford Credit may not be able to generate enough equity to support zero percent loans, he wrote, or consumers might stop responding to incentives, causing a sales slump.</p>
        <p>The report suggested that Ford might well face a cash crisis by mid-decade. Ford Motor disputed some of its figures in a regulatory filing.</p>
        <p>What the company does not dispute is that its cost structure is higher than that of many rivals, even G.M. Mr. Thursfield has said that the company needs to rethink its product development processes and manufacturing operations so that vehicles are designed and built at a cost in line with the competition. Mr. Thursfield has said he found the radios that Ford buys from Visteon too expensive, for example -- but largely because Ford ordered 150 different kinds of radios instead of a dozen, driving up complexity and cost.</p>
        <p>ADDRESSING the disparity will be crucial. In the plan announced in January, cost cutting accounts for half of the $9 billion in improved annual profitability the company has said it will achieve by mid-decade.</p>
        <p>''I expect us to be cash-flow positive through the '05 period, and frankly cash flow this year is coming in much better than forecast,'' Mr. Ford said. ''Cash won't be the issue. What keeps me up at night is the macroeconomic stuff I can't control.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Casesa, of Merrill Lynch, called Ford ''a very tough stock right now.''</p>
        <p>''Historically,'' he said, ''these companies get into trouble when volumes collapse. Therefore, you can model a turnaround with some confidence. At some point the environment will get better. Right now, Ford is in trouble in a relatively strong unit environment. Bulls like me would say if volumes hold up, Ford has levers it can pull that will improve its positions.'' But bears, he added, do not believe that volumes will hold up.</p>
        <p>Ford in particular lacks enough new models to compete. In the last couple of years, the market has been flooded with fresh-looking cars, S.U.V.'s and pickups from G.M., Toyota, Honda and Nissan, while Hyundai has made huge strides at the bottom end of the market.</p>
        <p>The company's turnaround projections in January also leaned heavily on expanding profits from its premier brands -- Volvo, Jaguar, Aston Martin and Land Rover -- but they are struggling. Last week, Mr. Scheele told reporters at the Paris auto show that Jaguar would have a $500 million operating loss for 2002.</p>
        <p>Next year, in one of the industry's most scrutinized introductions, Ford will offer a redesign of its F-Series pickup, the nation's best-selling automobile line. It hopes to create a pickup for all tastes with five F-Series trucks, including some with luxury interiors. F-Series is believed to be the company's most profitable line, but the new version will cost more to make, Ford has conceded.</p>
        <p>''They have a new strategy on F-Series,'' said Mr. Girsky of Morgan Stanley. ''They're trying to segment the market more aggressively than they have in the past. If it works, it has big share opportunities for them, and if not, there's cost risk.''</p>
        <p>But much of the company's hopes will be put off until 2004. The design of the aging Taurus will be freshened, but the company is putting more stock into the new Ford Five Hundred, intended to be an alternative to stylish sedans like the Nissan Altima and the Volkswagen Passat. It will be larger than a Taurus and stand higher off the ground.</p>
        <p>''I think it looks great, almost like they're taking the Taurus up a notch in terms of fit and finish,'' said Mr. Girsky, who has seen pictures of the prototype circulated to analysts. ''It looks more European than the typical midsized car sedan. The question is, 'Can you bring it in at a cost where the economics make sense?' ''</p>
        <p>Another important new product for 2004, the CrossTrainer, a blend of a station wagon and S.U.V., could be the first Big Three vehicle to compete with Subaru wagons.</p>
        <p>''We have to hang on until next summer,'' said Jerry Reynolds, owner of Ford dealerships in Texas and Oklahoma and former chairman of the Ford National Dealer Council. ''Then, the product pipeline starts to hit in areas we need it. F-Series is going to be huge. The new Expedition is doing very well, and the Explorer, which has been a mainstay, is picking up momentum.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reynolds said Mr. Ford had improved relations with dealers, spending time with them and providing a candid picture of the company's product plans. ''It's been night and day from what we had under Jacques Nasser,'' Mr. Reynolds said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford also made it a priority to mend fences with white-collar workers by scrapping a controversial grading system that denied bonuses to 10 percent of the work force; blue-collar workers have had an affinity for Mr. Ford since he rushed to the River Rouge plant after an explosion killed six workers in 1996, and many also relish a return of a Ford to a company often called ''Ford's.''</p>
        <p>One relationship that has grown strained is with environmentalists. They have criticized him for not bucking the industry's lobbying against tighter gas mileage requirements, which have not been increased much since the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''He's got to clearly lay out where we are going to be in five years, in seven years, what are our products are going to look like and what our fuel economy will be,'' said Kevin Sweeney, an environmental activist and consultant who has worked with Mr. Ford and urged him to be more assertive. ''It's reasonable to say it takes a year to figure these things out as C.E.O. Saying those things out loud would be a break from a really staid industry, and I think that would add luster to the company.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said his main objective was rescuing the company. But he also said the company remained committed to environmental goals, like increasing S.U.V. fuel economy by 25 percent by mid-decade and selling a hybrid S.U.V., powered by gasoline and electricity, next year.</p>
        <p>''The easiest thing for me would have been to be an idealist and leave this industry and go pursue pure environmental goals,'' he said. ''But as C.E.O., I have a lot of balls in the air. The environment is not going to be much enhanced if Ford Motor Company isn't a strong company.''</p>
        <p>Is Ford getting stronger? It could be worse. The Detroit Lions, the hapless football team owned by the Ford family, now has trouble even keeping games close.</p>
        <p>''It's been brutal, and I've given up everything for this job,'' he said about being C.E.O. ''I see my kids and I do this job and that's it. But that's O.K. I am getting some satisfaction now over watching this big battleship start to turn. And I'll get more satisfaction the more confirmation of that we get.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 6, 2002, Sunday  An article last Sunday about William Clay Ford Jr.'s management of the Ford Motor Company since he became chief executive last October misstated the year in which an explosion killed six workers at its River Rouge plant. It was 1999, not 1996.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 6, 2002, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about William Clay Ford Jr.'s management of the Ford Motor Company since he became chief executive last October misstated the year in which an explosion killed six workers at its River Rouge plant. It was 1999, not 1996.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
