<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mentor to Stars in Science Competitions</title>
    <meta content="03JOUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1364546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intel Science Talent Search</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">State University of New York at Stony Brook</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rafailovich, Miriam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDC1E3AF930A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mentor to Stars in Science Competitions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column on State University of New York at Stony Brook polymer researcher Miriam Rafailovich, who mentors local high school science students, some of whom are finalists in annual Intel Science Talent Search; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIRIAM RAFAILOVICH is not interested in contests. She is not motivated by competitions. She simply loves science. She thrives on research, spending long hours in a laboratory exploring the mysteries of how polymers, necklace-like strings of molecules, work with surfaces. And she delights in sharing her knowledge of its many applications, like tire safety, building better heart stents and DNA fingerprinting, with the curious high school students who crowd her office summers, evenings and weekends.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rafailovich, 43, is a mentor to science stars. On an Island that produces more young scientific achievers nationwide than any other region, a record 8 of the 40 high school seniors chosen from 300 semifinalists in the 2002 Intel Science Talent Search on Wednesday and 88 of the 300 semifinalists selected from 1,562 entries and named on Jan. 16, she oversees a chunk. One of the finalists, Mordechai Bronner, a senior at Rambam Mesivta in Lawrence, did his research in Dr. Rafailovich's lab.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIRIAM RAFAILOVICH is not interested in contests. She is not motivated by competitions. She simply loves science. She thrives on research, spending long hours in a laboratory exploring the mysteries of how polymers, necklace-like strings of molecules, work with surfaces. And she delights in sharing her knowledge of its many applications, like tire safety, building better heart stents and DNA fingerprinting, with the curious high school students who crowd her office summers, evenings and weekends.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rafailovich, 43, is a mentor to science stars. On an Island that produces more young scientific achievers nationwide than any other region, a record 8 of the 40 high school seniors chosen from 300 semifinalists in the 2002 Intel Science Talent Search on Wednesday and 88 of the 300 semifinalists selected from 1,562 entries and named on Jan. 16, she oversees a chunk. One of the finalists, Mordechai Bronner, a senior at Rambam Mesivta in Lawrence, did his research in Dr. Rafailovich's lab.</p>
        <p>''Long Island emphasizes high school research,'' said Dr. Rafailovich, a professor and director of the Garcia Center for Polymers at Engineered Interfaces, a National Science Foundation-financed seven-week summer scholar program in materials research science and engineering at the State University at Stony Brook. ''Most high schools here realize that it's important and the students have the infrastructure and support. The finals show that.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rafailovich acknowledged that there is ''huge pressure'' from the schools for the students to produce an Intel project. She immediately tells her extremely bright, highly motivated pupils that going for the gold is beside the point. ''Then they discover that science is far more than these regional competitions,'' she said. ''You are looking to do some fundamental science. If the science is good, if it's publishable, if it meets the standards of the scientific community, then maybe it will also win the Intel.''</p>
        <p>Long after the summer program ends, and sometimes after the competitions end, the students continue to pursue their research in her lab.</p>
        <p>''We don't gear the science to the contests,'' said Dr. Rafailovich, who works with her husband, Jonathan Sokolov, also a scientist. ''We are not a high school-level research lab. They have to do grown-up research. The research done in these labs is really forefront, graduate level, cutting-edge. The students come in and join in this endeavor. It's up to the student to adapt what they did in the summer to the high school competition level.''</p>
        <p>The Intel search has long been considered the most respected pre-college academic competition, sometimes referred to as the Junior Nobel Prize. Five previous winners have gone on to win Nobel Prizes; scientists and academics assert that the honor of being a finalist lasts a lifetime. The finalists chosen on Wednesday will vie for $530,000 in college scholarships during a week of competition next month.</p>
        <p>Other Long Island finalists were Michael Jacob Wagner, 17, from John F. Kennedy High School in Bellmore; Yang Li, 17, of Ward Melville High School in East Setauket; Raphael Farzan-Kashani, 17, of Great Neck North High School; Angela Soeun Kim, 17, of Great Neck South High School; Allegra Elizabeth Giovine, 18, and Jonathan Lii, 17, from Manhasset High School; and Jessica Randi Stahl, 17, of South Side High School in Rockville Centre.</p>
        <p>In the last three years, Dr. Rafailovich has mentored 19 Intel semifinalists, including 4 of her 10 applicants this year. ( About half of the Island's semifinalists did research at Stony Brook, making it one of the country's largest incubators of science talent.  Other students work at places like Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory and Brookhaven National Laboratory.) Though Dr. Rafailovich mentored 30 juniors and seniors last summer, only students entering their senior year may compete in the Intel search. Most of the juniors enter other competitions, like the Long Island Science and Engineering Fair, and repeat the research program the following summer.</p>
        <p>In December, two of Dr. Rafailovich's students from the Hebrew Academy of Long Beach, Shira Billet and Dora Chana Sosnowik, split the $100,000 prize in the National Siemens Westinghouse Science and Technology Competition, a separate, team-oriented contest started two years ago after Intel bought the rights to the original competition  sponsored by Westinghouse Electric Corporation from 1942 to 1998. Ten of the 53 Westinghouse semifinalists in the New York region did research in Dr. Rafailovich's program. And three high-school students who worked in her lab this summer received patent disclosures on their work, including Edmund Palermo, 17, of Bay Shore. His project, ''Polymer Blends with Supercritical Carbon Dioxide,'' used pressurized carbon dioxide gas instead of organic solvents to make new structural materials, like high-impact plastics that are used for car bumpers. Edmund won both the Long Island and International Science and Engineering Fair last year.</p>
        <p>On his winter break last week,  Mordechai, 17, a senior from Cedarhurst, was still fiddling in the lab with slabs of polymer molded together with a layer of carbon black in the middle. His research on fixing tread problems in tires, ''Improving Adhesion at Polystyrene and Polymethyl Methacrylate Interfaces Containing Fillers,'' included work for Exxon Mobil and led to a patent for chemical mixtures that prevent tread separation. Accompanied by Dr. Rafailovich, he gave a presentation in December -- the first by a high school student at a Material Research Society symposium in Boston -- and he  will give another at a coming meeting of the American Physical Society in Indianapolis next month. He is  working on two papers for Macromolecules, a scientific journal of the American Chemical Society.</p>
        <p>Mordechai credits his accomplishments to the soft-spoken Dr. Rafailovich. ''The work I did could not have been done without her,'' he said, recalling how she stayed with him until 3 a.m. making sure he had all the required photocopies in place to submit one of his entries and she lets him camp out at her Plainview home to get extra lab time. ''I work very hard but it's only because she treats us like we are not high school students, like we are real scientists. She always gives us the benefit of the doubt.''</p>
        <p>Working in Dr. Rafailovich's orbit is like skipping from high school to graduate school. During the summer, students are paired with graduate students, learn how to use lab equipment and spin their projects off of continuing research projects.</p>
        <p>The kind of research done in her lab, she said, can be used as senior thesis in college. It's the stuff that makes it into peer review publications, helps gain admittance to a Ph.D. program and stays on an adult résumé.</p>
        <p>Mordechai's project goes even further. ''He has developed technology that may produce a safer tire,'' Dr. Rafailovich said. ''With his output, someone could easily get a master's or even a Ph.D. His work was done on the plane of an adult scientist. The implication of his research will be looked at very seriously by the scientific community and the industrial community as a whole for improving materials.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rafailovich's approach is a combination of formal learning and independent research that squashes preconceived notions. Nearly all the students think they want to pursue medicine when they come in. ''We haven't got any premed projects here,'' she said. ''We don't do any clinical studies. Then they realize that's not all there is to science. They haven't been exposed to it.''</p>
        <p>After a few lectures on handling hazardous materials, an exam and a few organized labs with an instructor, participants are measuring thin films on an ellipsometer, learning to meticulously record and analyze data and tackling the problems of engineering materials for different applications. Three weeks into the program, the students begin testing their own hypotheses. ''Nobody invents a project in their garage,'' Dr. Rafailovich said. ''All the projects are byproducts of the team approach to something. What we try to teach the students is how to make an original contribution in a team.''</p>
        <p>While the graduate students in the group may have been working on an idea, she said, it is usually the high-school students who are willing to test a speculative new angle. ''The graduate students on the team are a little reluctant to go in a crazy direction because they have to graduate,'' Dr. Rafailovich said. ''They'll only do conventional things that have a fair measure of a guarantee of success. High school kids don't have those boundaries.'' Often, it leads to triumph.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rafailovich said the scholars program was a high-energy experience that distilled the best part of science research. Students avoid the repetition, the downtime, the wait for supplies, the grant-writing and the bureaucracy. With the brass ring in reach, they are eager and motivated.</p>
        <p>''If they don't win, it's O.K.,'' Dr. Rafailovich said. ''The science is great. And hopefully they'll come back for grad school.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
