<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush, in Adirondacks, Defends Environment Record</title>
    <meta content="Y23BUS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/23/politics/23BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1386527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adirondack Mountains</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DD1F3FF930A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush, in Adirondacks, Defends Environment Record</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush, in Adirondacks, Defends Environment Record</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, N.Y., April 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush hikes in Adirondack Mountains on Earth Day to promote his Clear Skies initiative and defend administration's environmental record against new barrage of criticism from Al Gore; is accompanied by New York Gov George Pataki; Bush initiative would impose mandatory limits on power-plant emissions of nitrogen oxide, sulfur dioxide and mercury, but grant plants flexibility in meeting those limits, including trading of emission 'allowances'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush hiked into an Adirondacks snowstorm this morning to promote his Clear Skies initiative and defend his administration's environmental record against a new barrage of criticism from Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Earth Day arrived in the mountains of upstate New York with temperatures in the 30's and a wet, heavy snow. To mark the day, Mr. Bush told a friendly audience that Clear Skies would help clean the air and reduce acid rain, one of the single biggest environmental concerns in the Adirondacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush promoted his Clear Skies initiative and defended his administration's environmental record in an Earth Day speech on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush hiked into an Adirondacks snowstorm this morning to promote his Clear Skies initiative and defend his administration's environmental record against a new barrage of criticism from Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Earth Day arrived in the mountains of upstate New York with temperatures in the 30's and a wet, heavy snow. To mark the day, Mr. Bush told a friendly audience that Clear Skies would help clean the air and reduce acid rain, one of the single biggest environmental concerns in the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>''With Clear Skies legislation, America will do more to reduce power plant emissions than ever before in our nation's history,'' Mr. Bush told an applauding crowd at the Whiteface Mountain Lodge.</p>
        <p>The president got an argument on that claim from Mr. Gore, his opponent in the bitter 2000 presidential campaign. In his own Earth Day speech, in Nashville, Mr. Gore accused the president of selling out the environment to big oil companies and recalled Mr. Bush's campaign promise to curb the emission of carbon dioxide, the gas principally implicated in global warming. Reversing that campaign pledge, Mr. Bush decided in March 2001 not to impose carbon dioxide controls, saying he feared the limits would endanger economic growth.</p>
        <p>Today, when asked about Mr. Gore's accusations as he helped restore a snowy, muddy and very cold mountain trail, the president retorted, ''Haven't paid attention to them.'' When a reporter called out that Mr. Gore was saying Mr. Bush had no environmental record, the president shot back, ''That's why I haven't paid attention to him.''</p>
        <p>The day, which seemed at times a reprise of the 2000 campaign, was blurred by more than just the snowstorm, which moved the president's speech from what would have been a spectacular outdoor setting to the more prosaic surroundings of the cafeteria at the lodge.</p>
        <p>For starters, Mr. Bush appeared with one of the few environmental groups that support him, the Adirondacks Council, as well as Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican who recently opposed some of the environmental policies that Mr. Bush promoted today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was also accompanied by Representative Sherwood Boehlert, a Republican from upstate New York who is the co-sponsor of a bill that calls for much tougher emissions standards than the Clear Skies initiative.</p>
        <p>But all parties had good reason to be here today in this midterm election year, including Mr. Bush, who told the crowd that his visit to the Adirondacks was inspirational in part because it was the playground of a favorite former president.</p>
        <p>''In this very park,'' he said, ''Teddy Roosevelt used to hang out.''</p>
        <p>Members of the Adirondacks Council said they supported the president's initiative because they viewed it as the most practical option for now in controlling acid rain, although, they said, it does not go far enough.</p>
        <p>The Clear Skies plan would impose mandatory limits on three kinds of power-plant emissions but grant the plants flexibility in meeting those limits, including the trading of emissions ''allowances.'' The initiative would reduce the emissions of nitrogen oxide, which leads to smog; sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain; and mercury, the last major toxic pollutant not regulated by the Clean Air Act, whose 1990 amendments were signed into law by Mr. Bush's father.</p>
        <p>''We think any time you've got a president behind the issue, it gives you a little momentum,'' said John F. Sheehan, an Adirondacks Council spokesman.</p>
        <p>The White House is promoting the initiative as an improvement over the Clean Air Act, one that would significantly reduce the levels of pollutants in the air over the next decade. But many other environmental groups claim the opposite, saying the proposal actually allows more emissions than under the statute.</p>
        <p>No one disputes that the Clear Skies initiative does not address carbon dioxide emissions and thus global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who is running for a third term, disagrees with Mr. Bush on another part of the administration's environmental plan. His argument is with the White House's stance on a program called ''new source review,'' which requires power plants to modernize pollution controls when the plants are upgraded. The White House has indicated it wants to relax those rules, and Mr. Pataki has written a letter to Vice President Dick Cheney objecting.</p>
        <p>Today an aide to the governor said Mr. Pataki considered the Clear Skies proposal ''an enormous step forward'' and would work with the administration on the other issues.</p>
        <p>In any case, there was not a discordant note as Mr. Pataki and Mr. Bush, two Yale graduates in khakis and hiking boots, tramped around in the fertile Republican territory of the Adirondacks and together drove numerous nails into planks to help make walkways over a muddy hiking trail along the Au Sable River.</p>
        <p>At one point, a White House aide asked watching reporters to move out of the president's way.</p>
        <p>''Get them moving,'' Mr. Bush called out cheerily. ''That way I won't have to nail so many of these things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
