<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christie Whitman's Tribulations</title>
    <meta content="27WED1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/27/opinion/27WED1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1444060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Christine Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDE1738F934A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christie Whitman's Tribulations</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Christie Whitman's Tribulations</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial, citing Admr Christie Whiman's absence when Environmental Protection Agency announced easing of clean air rules governing emissions from industrial sources and power plants, notes she lost in bid to incorporate changes in large legislative package that would impose nationwide caps on major pollutants and demand sacrifices from industry; holds she is greatly outnumbered by right-wingers and lobbyists Pres Bush has put in nearly every other key environmental post; urges her to stay in post and continue to fight pollution</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You have to wonder whether Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, is really enjoying her job. Last Friday the Bush administration announced the first big change in clean air rules in five years, easing existing regulations governing emissions from industrial sources and power plants, and threatening further rollbacks in the future. Mrs. Whitman was nowhere to be seen. The announcement was made by an assistant administrator on a Friday afternoon as the nation headed into a holiday week -- a moment, in other words, of minimum media exposure. No cameras were allowed, and Mrs. Whitman spoke through a written press release.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman of course endorsed the new rules, but this is not the way you announce something you're really excited about. Her associates offered various reasons for her absence. One was that if she had appeared in person, reporters would have focused on her and not on the revised rules, which is where she wanted their attention to be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christie Whitman is the only voice for reason on certain environmental issues, therefore it is in the country's interest that she stick around and fight the good fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You have to wonder whether Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, is really enjoying her job. Last Friday the Bush administration announced the first big change in clean air rules in five years, easing existing regulations governing emissions from industrial sources and power plants, and threatening further rollbacks in the future. Mrs. Whitman was nowhere to be seen. The announcement was made by an assistant administrator on a Friday afternoon as the nation headed into a holiday week -- a moment, in other words, of minimum media exposure. No cameras were allowed, and Mrs. Whitman spoke through a written press release.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman of course endorsed the new rules, but this is not the way you announce something you're really excited about. Her associates offered various reasons for her absence. One was that if she had appeared in person, reporters would have focused on her and not on the revised rules, which is where she wanted their attention to be.</p>
        <p>People are indeed interested in Mrs. Whitman. She arrived in Washington with strong environmental credentials but soon found herself greatly outnumbered by the lobbyists and right-wingers whom President Bush put in nearly every other key environmental post. She's had a couple of important victories -- ordering General Electric to clean up PCB's in the Hudson River, for example, and upholding Clinton-era rules on diesel exhausts. But she's lost on several big issues -- most notably on limiting global warming gases -- and been forced to fight rear-guard actions on most of the rest.</p>
        <p>The rule changes seem part of the same pattern. At issue is a provision of the Clean Air Act known as new source review. It requires power plants and industrial facilities to install modern pollution controls whenever they make a ''major modification'' and increase pollution. It is also one of the few ways the government has of getting a handle on emissions from older, coal-fired plants. Indeed, as governor of New Jersey Mrs. Whitman was a strong supporter of new source review and joined with other Northeastern states in lawsuits against Midwestern utilities that had rebuilt their plants without installing the necessary controls.</p>
        <p>There was never much doubt that Mrs. Whitman would be asked to revisit the rule when she got to Washington. Many of Mr. Bush's biggest contributors hated it, as did Vice President Dick Cheney, who ordered it rewritten as part of his energy strategy. Even so, Mrs. Whitman hoped from the beginning to incorporate the revisions in a larger legislative package that would impose nationwide caps on major pollutants and actually demand sacrifices from industry. Indeed, in July of last year she explicitly promised Congress to do just that.</p>
        <p>In time, a broad proposal called Clear Skies was sent to Congress. It has since gone nowhere. The only thing that has moved forward is the independent gutting of new source review. In short, industry has won the regulatory relief it wanted without having to swallow any new restrictions. And Mrs. Whitman, at least by the standards she set for herself, has lost.</p>
        <p>People are beginning to call on Mrs. Whitman to resign as a matter of principle. That might embarrass Mr. Bush, but only for a moment. The better course is for her to stay. We would urge her to fight harder, to make more noise and to demand that Mr. Bush throw his weight behind the Clear Skies proposal or some variation. But because she is the only voice for reason on these issues, it is in the country's interest that she stick around and fight the good fight. Those of us who are concerned about the fate of the environment will, of course, still reserve the right to complain when she fails.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
