<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Millennium Pipeline Bodes Ill for River</title>
    <meta content="24SOAP$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1443153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="SOAPBOX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ontario (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Millennium Pipeline Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matthiessen, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D71439F937A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Millennium Pipeline Bodes Ill for River</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX MATTHIESSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Matthiessen, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hudson Riverkeeper Alex Matthiessen essay offers reasons why US Commerce Department should reject proposed route of Millennium natural gas pipeline from Ontario, Canada, to Westchester County, NY; holds alternative routes deserve further review; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ENERGY has been on the minds of Westchester County residents lately. From the hazards associated with the Indian Point nuclear power plant to the proposed Millennium Pipeline , the desire to strike a balance between our region's energy needs and the negative impact large-scale energy production wreaks on environmental and community health has been at the heart of the energy debate in Westchester.</p>
        <p>The Millennium Pipeline Company, a consortium of four energy companies, is seeking final federal and state approval to build a natural gas pipeline from Ontario, Canada, to Westchester. First proposed in 1977, the pipeline was called ''millennium'' as a way to sell its alleged ability to supply natural gas to New York and other eastern states well into the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ENERGY has been on the minds of Westchester County residents lately. From the hazards associated with the Indian Point nuclear power plant to the proposed Millennium Pipeline , the desire to strike a balance between our region's energy needs and the negative impact large-scale energy production wreaks on environmental and community health has been at the heart of the energy debate in Westchester.</p>
        <p>The Millennium Pipeline Company, a consortium of four energy companies, is seeking final federal and state approval to build a natural gas pipeline from Ontario, Canada, to Westchester. First proposed in 1977, the pipeline was called ''millennium'' as a way to sell its alleged ability to supply natural gas to New York and other eastern states well into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>The proposed pipeline route snakes its way down 424 miles through upstate New York, across the Hudson River at Haverstraw Bay -- the most biologically rich stretch of the river -- and through sensitive watershed areas in Westchester, before terminating in Mount Vernon. Having received the blessing of the industry-loyal Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, the project faces a final hurdle: obtaining a certificate vouching that the pipeline is consistent with New York's Coastal Management Program. Rebuffed by New York's Department of State, Millennium is looking to the United States Department of Commerce to override the state agency's decision.</p>
        <p>Critics argue that the need for Millennium's gas has not been sufficiently demonstrated, in light of other projects like the Eastchester Expansion and the Northeast ConneXion Pipeline that would reportedly supply just as much gas and avoid many of the problems plaguing Millennium. Millennium's own environmental impact statement acknowledges that the Eastchester Expansion project, already under way, ''could serve the New York City area, providing similar pipeline capacity'' as the Millennium pipeline would, but without the coastal zone impacts. Not mentioned in the debate is the need to use energy efficiency to curb reliance on imported fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The proposed route makes little environmental sense. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission has approved routing the pipeline across Haverstraw Bay, which would mean about two miles of dredging and up to 400 feet of bedrock blasting, thus stressing critical fish populations, including that of the endangered short-nose sturgeon, which over-winter in the bay, and the dwindling Atlantic sturgeon, which use it as a feeding and nursing ground. Cutting a wide swath through Westchester woodlands and wetlands also makes no sense. Millennium would slash through a pristine 2.5-mile stretch of the New Croton Reservoir watershed, which supplies unfiltered drinking water to 900,000 people each day. The inevitable addition of phosphorous and other pollutants to reservoirs and streams would threaten the integrity of the water supply and violate the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>A number of preferable alternative routes deserve further review, including those proposed by New York's Department of State. One option is to route the pipeline down existing rights of way like the New York Thruway to a Hudson River crossing at the Tappan Zee. Another would have the pipeline stop at the existing Bowline power plant in Haverstraw. The existing Algonquin pipeline right of way could be used to take gas across from Bowline to the Indian Point nuclear plant site. As for avoiding watershed impacts, Con Edison has stated, under oath, that there are ways to take Millennium gas south into New York City without any construction in Westchester.</p>
        <p>It is increasingly clear that the health of our environment and of our communities is inextricably linked. Millennium and all interested parties must have an honest dialogue about the region's energy needs and the alternatives. And the Department of Commerce, which held a hearing on the matter last week, must abstain from overriding the Department of State's determination that the proposed Millennium Pipeline route needlessly jeopardizes critical estuarine habitat while threatening the safety of the water supply.</p>
        <p>SOAPBOX Alex Matthiessen is the Hudson Riverkeeper and executive director of Riverkeeper, an environmental organization.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alex Matthiessen is the Hudson Riverkeeper and executive director of Riverkeeper, an environmental organization.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
