<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dennis Quaid's Second Reel: The Comeback</title>
    <meta content="14QUAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/14/movies/14QUAI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1440399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quaid, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, Meg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frequency (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Traffic (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rookie, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Far From Heaven (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Quaid, Dennis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Haynes, Todd</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Moore, Julianne</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DB1F31F937A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dennis Quaid's Second Reel: The Comeback</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dennis Quaid's Second Reel: The Comeback</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Nov. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Lyman interviews actor Dennis Quaid, whose career was interrupted by decade of struggle against cocaine addiction and painful tabloid coverage of problems during marriage to actress Meg Ryan; Quaid discusses come-back that began in 2000 with leading role in movie Frequency, followed by substantial roles in Traffic, The Rookie and Far From Heaven; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dennis Quaid scooted through the kitchen of his Brentwood house, a bottle of water clasped in one hand, as he tried to corner three yapping border terriers toward the door. ''C'mon, you're in the way,'' he said. ''Try to behave.''</p>
        <p>With that same galvanic grin that made him one of the top movie stars of the 1980's in films like ''The Right Stuff'' (1983) and ''The Big Easy'' (1987), Mr. Quaid plopped down on a well-grooved sofa and gestured sheepishly to a basketball-size ink stain on an adjacent love seat. ''It's a little messy around here,'' he said. ''We've been busy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After spending a decade in the Hollywood wilderness, Dennis Quaid has been mentioned as a possible Oscar nominee for his supporting role in "Far From Heaven."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dennis Quaid scooted through the kitchen of his Brentwood house, a bottle of water clasped in one hand, as he tried to corner three yapping border terriers toward the door. ''C'mon, you're in the way,'' he said. ''Try to behave.''</p>
        <p>With that same galvanic grin that made him one of the top movie stars of the 1980's in films like ''The Right Stuff'' (1983) and ''The Big Easy'' (1987), Mr. Quaid plopped down on a well-grooved sofa and gestured sheepishly to a basketball-size ink stain on an adjacent love seat. ''It's a little messy around here,'' he said. ''We've been busy.''</p>
        <p>It is a welcome change. He spent a decade in the Hollywood wilderness following a struggle with cocaine addiction and more recently a spate of tabloid misery caused by the slow-motion breakup of his 10-year marriage to the actress Meg Ryan and her brief, gossip-generating romance with the actor Russell Crowe.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I am in the best place I've been for 13 or 14 years, really,'' Mr. Quaid said, taking a pull from the water bottle and pushing aside a silver scooter that his 10-year-old son, Jack, had left on the sofa. ''I think there's ebbs and flows and cycles to every career. Back in the late 80's I was the hot guy there for a while. And now I feel like I'm getting back there again.''</p>
        <p>He is 48 now. The elfin grin and the quick, eye-crinkling laugh are still there. But the lines are carved a little deeper in his chiseled face, the square jaw line is more gaunt with age and the gaze a little more wary. ''I don't think I appreciated it as much as I should have back then,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''I don't think I nurtured it. I think I kind of took it for granted.''</p>
        <p>It is often hard to tell exactly when a comeback began. Perhaps it was his lead role in the critically praised ''Frequency'' (2000), about a firefighter whose ham radio allows him to converse across time with his grown son. Or perhaps his supporting performance as a sleazy drug lawyer in the Oscar-winning ''Traffic'' (2000).</p>
        <p>Certainly it has all come together this year. First he starred as a middle-aged baseball pitcher in ''The Rookie,'' a well-regarded family film from Disney. More recently his name has been mentioned as a possible Oscar nominee for his supporting role in ''Far From Heaven,'' the director Todd Haynes's critically praised homage to the lush, emotional films of the 1950's director Douglas Sirk. Mr. Quaid plays a middle-class husband struggling to repress his homosexuality.</p>
        <p>''I finally think, when I did 'The Rookie' that things really started to bear fruit,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''It's not like I was living in a desert or anything like that. But all of a sudden again the scripts have started arriving at the door.''</p>
        <p>Julianne Moore, Mr. Quaid's co-star in ''Far From Heaven,'' said she ''fell in love with him to a rapturous degree'' while recently watching ''Everybody's All-American,'' a 1988 drama in which Mr. Quaid played a college football star who must come to terms with disappointing middle age.</p>
        <p>''The thing about Dennis is that he has a period feel to him at times, and a very easy and assured masculinity,'' Ms. Moore said. ''There's a classicness to Dennis that would not be at odds with one of those 1950's type of actors.''</p>
        <p>When describing why he chose Mr. Quaid for the role, Mr. Haynes also mentioned the actor's effortless masculinity.</p>
        <p>''He's getting a lot of great notices for this film, which makes me happy,'' Mr. Haynes said. ''Sometimes I get the sense that this surprises people. But I think the evidence is already there in his earlier films. I think the problem is that he hasn't really positioned himself as first and foremost a serious actor, but he really is one.''</p>
        <p>Born in Houston, Mr. Quaid spent his first 21 years in the middle-class suburb of Bellaire. He credits his years as a drama student at the University of Houston with inspiring him to take up acting, and when his older brother, Randy Quaid, came to Hollywood to work in the mid-1970's, Dennis followed.</p>
        <p>His breakthrough movie was ''Breaking Away'' in 1979, in which he played the angriest of a group of working-class townies who take on the university snobs in a bicycle race. And after ''The Right Stuff'' he found himself in a string of major studio films, including ''Innerspace'' (1987), ''Suspect'' (1987) and ''Great Balls of Fire!'' (1989).</p>
        <p>What people did not realize, he said, was that he was also slipping into cocaine addiction at the time. He said he drew on that experience in playing Frank, the repressed homosexual in ''Far From Heaven.''</p>
        <p>''I used it to find a path into this guy's life and what he was feeling,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''I have had gay friends who tried to live a secret life, and that was essentially what I was doing when I was on cocaine. You know, there's this feeling of shame, when you're trying to hide something like that, something that can't be uttered, that you don't want people to know about. It's not a good place to be.''</p>
        <p>In the film Frank sometimes lashes out angrily at his wife and others, the struggle against shame transforming into rage. Did Mr. Quaid's shame about his addiction also turn into anger?</p>
        <p>''Well, I never struck anybody,'' he said. ''No. Mostly, I was mad at God, you know? Why was I in this predicament? I knew it was all my own fault, but at the same time I wasn't thinking straight. I was caught in a place, living a life that I didn't want to live but couldn't escape.''</p>
        <p>Not until the period just before his marriage to Ms. Ryan and the birth of their son did he decide he had to get a grip on the situation.</p>
        <p>''I got into rehab, and I got over it,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''I took a year off to get my life back together. And when it came time to find a movie, it took me another year to find one.''</p>
        <p>During that two-year hiatus Hollywood had to some extent forgotten him.</p>
        <p>''Hollywood has a very short memory,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''If you're not out there in the marketplace, they move on. And so I was surprised to find it really tough going. In a way I had to start over.''</p>
        <p>There were other disappointments. He managed to land the lead in ''Come See the Paradise'' (1990), an Alan Parker drama about the internment of Japanese-Americans during World War II, which was released on the day that the gulf war started. Movie audiences were in no mood to watch a film about America confessing its sins, Mr. Quaid said. A highly praised turn as Doc Holliday in ''Wyatt Earp'' (1994) was lost in the movie's box-office failure.</p>
        <p>By 1998, though, he was beginning to get a second foothold. He starred in the successful remake of Disney's ''Parent Trap'' in 1998 and as an aging quarterback in Oliver Stone's ''Any Given Sunday'' in 1999. Those roles led directly to ''Frequency,'' ''Traffic'' and this year's twin successes.</p>
        <p>''It's been a slow build,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quaid said he and Ms. Ryan shared custody of their son and lived not far from each other, eager to keep things as normal as possible for Jack.</p>
        <p>That certainly was not the situation a year and a half ago, when the well-publicized split made the couple regulars in gossip columns, celebrity magazines and tabloid television shows.</p>
        <p>''This was my first taste of anything like that,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''It was no fun.''</p>
        <p>One day, he said, he heard a noise outside his house and discovered a van filled with cameras and recording equipment parked at the curb. Often, he said, tag-team cars of paparazzi would follow him around town. Fortunately, he said, the tabloid furor eventually died down, the followers and the vans have moved on.</p>
        <p>''They're working on Winona Ryder now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quaid was at home in Brentwood with just a few days between films. He had just finished a thriller called ''Cold Creek Manor'' outside Toronto and was set to leave for Montreal, where he was to begin work on ''Tomorrow,'' a big-budget summer blockbuster for 20th Century Fox from the director Roland Emmerich about weather chaos caused by global warming.</p>
        <p>''It's got hurricanes, flash freezes, tidal waves, tornadoes and hailstones the size of bowling balls,'' Mr. Quaid said. ''It's exactly the kind of movie I want to do now. Just a big, popcorn disaster movie. Just the kind of movie I like to go and see with my 10-year-old son.''</p>
        <p>Jack came slowly into the room, the yapping of the terriers growing louder through the gap in the kitchen door as he entered. ''Have you seen my scooter?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''You mean this one?'' Mr. Quaid replied, picking it up from the cushion beside him. ''I'll be done in a few minutes, and we can go out and do something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Quaid said he sometimes wondered why he -- apart from so many of the other young actors who came to Hollywood in the 1970's -- had been able to persevere.</p>
        <p>He grinned, a little ruefully.</p>
        <p>''You have to have a lot of tenacity,'' he said. ''And a very large capacity for rejection.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
