<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assembling a Montage of Images in Glass and Steel</title>
    <meta content="27MUSC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/27/arts/design/27MUSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1362606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georges Pompidou Center (Paris)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nouvel, Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Pompidou Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nouvel, Jean</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D9133BF934A15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assembling a Montage of Images in Glass and Steel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Assembling a Montage of Images in Glass and Steel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp reviews retrospective of works by French architect Jean Nouvel on view at Georges Pompidou Center in Paris; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY now, everyone who's not a complete chucklehead understands that the context for architecture is not confined to the microrange of a building's immediate surroundings. It extends to the macroscale of global urbanization. Rather than turning architects into street mimes, ''contextualism'' should stretch their imaginations toward the far horizons of technological innovation and cultural difference.</p>
        <p>The Jean Nouvel retrospective now on view at the Georges Pompidou Center here proves that this enlarged view of context -- Stretch Context, if you like -- is not a chimerical proposition. With each project, Nouvel reveals more and more of the micro-macro ideal. The Pompidou show makes clear that this process has now reached critical mass. It leaves little room for doubt that Nouvel has joined the top echelon of contemporary urban mythologists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A retrospective in Paris of Jean Nouvel's work shows the ingenious ways in which he relates ever fluid forms to a larger urban context.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY now, everyone who's not a complete chucklehead understands that the context for architecture is not confined to the microrange of a building's immediate surroundings. It extends to the macroscale of global urbanization. Rather than turning architects into street mimes, ''contextualism'' should stretch their imaginations toward the far horizons of technological innovation and cultural difference.</p>
        <p>The Jean Nouvel retrospective now on view at the Georges Pompidou Center here proves that this enlarged view of context -- Stretch Context, if you like -- is not a chimerical proposition. With each project, Nouvel reveals more and more of the micro-macro ideal. The Pompidou show makes clear that this process has now reached critical mass. It leaves little room for doubt that Nouvel has joined the top echelon of contemporary urban mythologists.</p>
        <p>The exhibition also makes Nouvel out to be a figure whose power to mesmerize rivals Josephine Baker's. Erotic, prolific, Nouvel throws out ideas the way Baker used to toss fruit into the audience. The diversity of his projects is as impressive as their individual merits. And if you get hit in the head with a pineapple, you can be confident that the fruit will be extra juicy.</p>
        <p>The retrospective is installed within temporary galleries of darkened nightclub chic. More floor show than museum show, perhaps, it has been attacked by the French press on the ground that the Pompidou should not have allowed Nouvel to design it. Huh? Why deny the public the chance to experience a place made by the architect whose work they have come to see?</p>
        <p>Nouvel's installation is not hobbled by consistency. It draws on a variety of media, including video , tiny transparencies, animated computer monitors and humongous color images projected on triple-height walls. This presentation portrays the extent to which the global city -- the macrocontext -- is information-based.</p>
        <p>One medium is notably absent: there are no three-dimensional models, objects that conventionally anchor architecture shows to the pragmatics of professional practice. Neither are there drawings by human hands. Another American critic visiting Paris found the show confusing. She missed seeing models. It was too dark to read the wall texts. The labyrinthine floor plan made continuity hard to follow. I suppose these count as flaws.</p>
        <p>I confess that the main ingredient I look for in architecture shows is ambience. Unlike exhibitions of painting and sculpture, these shows are invariably mediated versions of actual work. It's a privilege and often a joy to inspect models in an architect's studio, with the architect on hand to guide you through them. In a museum, I usually find it a chore. I could live without most wall texts. I don't mind getting lost in labyrinths -- it's one of the pleasures of Paris -- and the installation roots Nouvel's work in that urban milieu, just as the enveloping black walls locate him in the mythical dream space that his built works embody.</p>
        <p>The Pompidou's escalator ride, a Chagallian ascent through Paris rooftops, is the show's sublime introduction. From the summit, we float into a world of blurry images: reflections, veils, patterns, panoramas, fade-outs and dissolves. Nouvel's is an ambient, cinematic space, pieced together as if reality were an art of montage. In this mutable space, we glimpse the future promised by postmodern architecture's liberation of imagery from structure, program and mechanical function. Except that, with Nouvel, these factors (the plumbing, so to speak) are integral parts of the architectural image. So are the site conditions, the building's physical and visual context. His imagery includes these elements but is not a slave to them. It has its own order, which technical innovation and different site conditions maintain in a state of flux.</p>
        <p>As much preview as retrospective, the show gives greater prominence to works in progress and unbuilt projects than to built ones. Outstanding designs include the Carnegie Science Center in Pittsburgh, a steel and glass megastructure cantilevered over the Ohio River from a silvery cylindrical base; the Chamber of Commerce in Prato, Italy, a rectangular box wrapped with blurry glass grids; and the Dentsu Tower in Tokyo, a monumental glass skyscraper of curvilinear contour.</p>
        <p>Nouvel is having a Rousseau moment: a group of recent projects are essentially landscape designs, buildings whose ornamental vegetation changes with the seasons. Works in this genre include the Quai Branley Museum in Paris; the Museum of Evolution in Burgos, Spain; and the Société Richemont headquarters in Geneva. New Yorkers may feel a pang on viewing designs for the River Hotel, a project for Brooklyn that has met with opposition. Still, I suspect that the typology introduced by the design -- the cineplex hotel, where you can check in for a weekend of catching up on movies -- will have a future in New York and other cities.</p>
        <p>Despite the diversity of forms, there is surprising consistency in Nouvel's design motifs. Foremost among these is the screenlike curtain wall, typically glass, a material that still signifies modernity in Europe. (Glass is making a comeback in the United States, as technical innovations enlarge its expressive potential.) Often, Nouvel layers screens on screens to produce images of complexity and depth. Translucent, opaque and fritted, or fused, glass combines with reflections in surfaces that shimmer with the seductive concealment of striptease.</p>
        <p>The veil-like screen is an ecotone -- the overlap between adjacent ecosystems. In contemporary design, adjacent areas can represent mechanical and digital technology -- or the Old and New Economies, the industrial and the informational -- based on these 19th- and 21st-century systems of production. Nouvel's screens are ecotones in this sense. While their Baroque display of structural hardware is high-tech, the imagery flickering across their surfaces derives from the digital realm.</p>
        <p>In the Pompidou's darkened rooms, another ecotone becomes visible: the overlap between objective and subjective realms. The memory screen, in Freudian parlance, is a remembered place or event that assumes greater importance in hindsight than it possessed at the time. A surface for emotional projections, the screen represents the cause of effects that were actually determined by many factors, including patterns established in childhood.</p>
        <p>The Nouvel wall is a memory screen for projecting ideas and emotions associated with the idea of architecture: shelter, history, inclusion and exclusion, authority, permanence, aggression and desire. At the Arab World Institute, a wall of clear glass, facing the Seine, is etched with a ghostlike panorama of the Right Bank skyline. A high-tech version of pictures traditionally sold along the river quais, the wall is an image of urban recollection, a memory etched with the view one saw before Nouvel's building went up.</p>
        <p>The main facade, by now a Parisian landmark, is a sleek sandwich of metal and glass, its transparent skin backed by a perforated steel wall of motorized irises, designed to resemble the sun screens in Islamic buildings. A species of architecture parlante, the facade expresses the indebtedness of Western technology to Arab science.</p>
        <p>Nouvel's screens often evoke the idea that architecture itself is dissolving into the new world of mediated reality. The collective memory embodied by Gothic buildings has been substantially absorbed within the infinite expanses of cyberspace. Suppose that architecture, conceived in terms of Euclidean reality, actually reached a vanishing point with Mies van der Rohe, leaving only echoes behind. Then Nouvel will weave the echoes into an architecture as complex as any that came before. I Remember Architecture, his screens announce.</p>
        <p>But Nouvel evokes memory without nostalgia. In fact, the show illuminates the fatal turn American architecture took in the 1970's and 80's. Whatever was gained by liberating form from engineering was lost by reverting to the 19th-century equation of architecture with style. New forms were constantly referred back to the external authorities of history and tradition. With Nouvel, imagery is rooted in the internal authority of the psyche. It reflects the French view that the Sign (water; translucent glass; the elevator; the color red) exists primarily in the mental landscape. Its identity is defined by its difference from other signs (fire, stone, sidewalk, blue). The future creates styles in retrospect. Contemporaneity produces images.</p>
        <p>In recent projects, he seems to be saying, I Remember Nature. Projects like the Société Richemont headquarters may be a natural response to global urbanization and the increasing scarcity of the natural world as development accelerates. Or it may reflect necessary adjustments to the concept of nature on the mental landscape: a breakdown in the oppositional relationship between nature and culture that has led to catastrophic consequences. Take a deep breath. If global warming continues, we'll soon be growing gills and sending out high-pitched squeals. I remember cities, glug, glug.</p>
        <p>Agbar Tower, a current project, is the most breathtaking work on view. A 35-story office building, designed for a site on the outskirts of Barcelona, the tower is a breakthrough design, on account of its scale, its location in the capital city of the design universe and its crystallization of ideas Nouvel has been generating throughout his career. It sets a standard by which forthcoming proposals for lower Manhattan will be judged.</p>
        <p>The glass tower is an erotic object, an embodiment of aggression as well as desire. Nouvel's intention is not, he states, to create a New York-style skyscraper, but to make a recessive as well as an assertive gesture. The phallus is both soft and hard, in other words, aggressive in its height and unmodulated shape, yielding in the responsiveness of its skin to stark Catalonian light.</p>
        <p>The bottle-shape towers of Gaudí's Church of the Holy Family, the exquisite transparency of Mies van der Rohe's Barcelona Pavilion: ah, yes, Nouvel remembers them well. He also takes into account the residential high rises on the urban periphery, modern artifacts of the Franco era, built for a city overtaken by cars. Figuratively, the highway now leads to the airport, the sky and the etherealized city of wireless communications.</p>
        <p>Nouvel designed the tower to resemble a civic fountain, a geyser magnified to the scale of the contemporary skyline. The concept nods to the statue of Columbus, atop a pillar in Barcelona's harbor, a reminder of the era when water offered a means of disproving that the earth was flat. Water, of course, is also the medium of dreams. Like all of Nouvel's projects, the Agbar Tower sets architecture in the ecotone between inner and outer worlds. Its context includes parts of mind as yet uncharted.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
