<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Lagging on Warming</title>
    <meta content="08SUN1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/08/opinion/08SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1446950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDB113BF93BA35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Lagging on Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Still Lagging on Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial urges Bush administration to act to curb global warming, not wait for five more years of research; cites needed steps</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's Secretary of Commerce, Donald Evans, told more than 1,000 scientists, economists and other experts attending a conference on global warming last week that their task was to ''jump-start'' President Bush's new five-year program of research into the causes of global warming and possible responses. The secretary is just a bit behind the times. There is already an enormous body of research on the subject, perhaps 20 years' worth, nearly all of it pointing to the need to adopt exactly the kind of remedial steps that the Bush administration has so far refused to take. What needs jump-starting is not research but policy.</p>
        <p>Obviously we could all benefit from research. Sophisticated modeling can tell us more about global climate change and instruct us in how best to adapt. But the world does not need another excuse from Mr. Bush to delay the political steps necessary to begin slowing emissions right away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The need for swift, collective action was the premise of the Kyoto Protocol on global climate change, not further study as the Bush Administration says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's Secretary of Commerce, Donald Evans, told more than 1,000 scientists, economists and other experts attending a conference on global warming last week that their task was to ''jump-start'' President Bush's new five-year program of research into the causes of global warming and possible responses. The secretary is just a bit behind the times. There is already an enormous body of research on the subject, perhaps 20 years' worth, nearly all of it pointing to the need to adopt exactly the kind of remedial steps that the Bush administration has so far refused to take. What needs jump-starting is not research but policy.</p>
        <p>Obviously we could all benefit from research. Sophisticated modeling can tell us more about global climate change and instruct us in how best to adapt. But the world does not need another excuse from Mr. Bush to delay the political steps necessary to begin slowing emissions right away.</p>
        <p>The window is closing fast. Even now, nations are making energy investments that will be with us for years to come. The International Energy Agency predicted recently that $4.2 trillion would be spent on new electric generating plants over the next 30 years worldwide -- an average investment of $140 billion a year -- and that most of these would be using outdated, highly polluting technologies. Every year of delay locks in more outmoded investment, adds to the carbon emissions already in the atmosphere and increases the ultimate costs of protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>The need for swift, collective action was the premise of the Kyoto Protocol on global climate change, which sought to reduce annual greenhouse gas emissions to 1990 levels by 2010. Mr. Bush summarily rejected the Kyoto pact shortly after taking office. Even so, the rest of the world still looks to the United States for guidance and technology. This leaves it to a divided Congress to make the tough calls that Mr. Bush has avoided.</p>
        <p>The immediate remedies are plain enough: cleaner cars and cleaner power plants. Mr. Bush opposes any mandatory limits on carbon dioxide pollution from either source, preferring a voluntary approach. But voluntary steps have not worked with industry in the past and will not now. While some companies are eager to do something about global warming on their own, using available technologies, the private sector as a whole will not make serious investments in cleaner plants or more efficient automobiles as long as the rules favor dirtier and more profitable alternatives: aging coal-fired power plants and gas-guzzling S.U.V.'s.</p>
        <p>The rules have to change. There will undoubtedly be another effort in Congress to increase fuel economy standards. And there are two bills moving through the Senate that would reduce carbon dioxide emissions from power plants by combining mandatory caps with substantial, market-based financial rewards for operating more efficiently. The prospects for such legislation have not been improved, of course, by the election results and the ascendancy to key committee chairmanships of conservatives who, like Mr. Bush, worry about asking for any real sacrifice from industry.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Bush knows that his own clean air legislation, which seeks new controls on every major air pollutant except the gas that causes global warming, stands little chance of success unless he also addresses the issue of carbon dioxide. In other words, if he wants progress on any air pollutant, he may finally be forced to deal with the most frightening one of all. Unless he does, all the research in the world won't help a bit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
