<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cloudy Skies</title>
    <meta content="28SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/28/opinion/28SUN1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DC113EF93BA15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cloudy Skies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cloudy Skies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Bush administration is largely to blame for lack of progress toward strengthening Clean Air Act to combat smog, acid rain and global warming; holds Pres Bush's market-based plan for curbing emissions is flawed; calls energy bill approved by Senate disappointing overall, despite some good provisions; holds bill is less offensive than House bill; expresses concern that House provisions may prevail in conference</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These have not been good times for cleaner fuels and cleaner air. Despite much huffing and puffing, the Senate produced an unconvincing energy bill last week that takes only a few timid steps toward energy efficiency and alternative fuels and, for that reason, does little to reduce the country's dependence on foreign oil. Its main virtue is that it is less offensive than the House bill. Meanwhile, despite President Bush's snowy Earth Day photo-op in the Adirondacks, where he touted his Clear Skies program, his administration has failed to offer Congress an actual proposal. The result has been zero progress toward strengthening the Clean Air Act to combat smog, acid rain and global warming. For that the White House is largely to blame.</p>
        <p>The Senate is to be commended for keeping the oil companies out of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. Yet it also rejected the one idea that would have made the energy debate worthwhile: a provision aimed at improving fuel economy standards for cars and S.U.V.'s. That would have done far more to enhance the country's long-term energy security than drilling in the refuge or in any of the other ecologically sensitive areas on which the administration has cast a covetous eye.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House is largely to blame for the lack of progress toward strengthening the Clean Air Act to combat smog, acid rain and global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These have not been good times for cleaner fuels and cleaner air. Despite much huffing and puffing, the Senate produced an unconvincing energy bill last week that takes only a few timid steps toward energy efficiency and alternative fuels and, for that reason, does little to reduce the country's dependence on foreign oil. Its main virtue is that it is less offensive than the House bill. Meanwhile, despite President Bush's snowy Earth Day photo-op in the Adirondacks, where he touted his Clear Skies program, his administration has failed to offer Congress an actual proposal. The result has been zero progress toward strengthening the Clean Air Act to combat smog, acid rain and global warming. For that the White House is largely to blame.</p>
        <p>The Senate is to be commended for keeping the oil companies out of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. Yet it also rejected the one idea that would have made the energy debate worthwhile: a provision aimed at improving fuel economy standards for cars and S.U.V.'s. That would have done far more to enhance the country's long-term energy security than drilling in the refuge or in any of the other ecologically sensitive areas on which the administration has cast a covetous eye.</p>
        <p>The bill has some positives. It would provide fewer tax breaks for oil and gas companies than the House bill, and more for conservation. It has a first-ever renewable-energy mandate that would require utilities to produce a small fraction of their energy from sources like wind power. It would triple the amount of ethanol used in gasoline, a step that may or may not produce clean-air benefits, depending on which scientist you ask. And all those subsidies the bill would shovel at the coal companies might someday produce the magical ''clean coal technology'' the industry has been promising for years. But on the whole the bill is very disappointing; as a final insult, the Senate even rejected a reasonable proposal to improve the efficiency of air-conditioners.</p>
        <p>The bill now goes to a conference with the House. We shudder to think of the consequences, especially if the Senate negotiators cave in the way they did on the farm bill. In any case, what good can come of the marriage of a mediocre bill with a truly bad one? It would not be tragic if the negotiations collapsed altogether.</p>
        <p>On clean air, meanwhile, the Bush administration continues to push its Clear Skies proposal, aimed at reducing sulfur, smog and mercury emissions. The heart of the program is a market-based scheme called ''cap and trade,'' which would set national pollution limits but let individual companies figure out how to meet them. Cap and trade is a fine idea in principle, but the Bush plan is flawed.</p>
        <p>For starters, some of the government's own studies indicate that Clear Skies would achieve fewer pollution reductions than aggressive enforcement of present law. Indeed, Mr. Bush rejected a plan devised by the Environmental Protection Agency that would have reduced air pollution further and faster than Clear Skies. Even if Clear Skies achieved its national targets, it would still leave certain regions -- like the Adirondacks -- helpless against poisoned air because it would let companies choose which plants to clean up. If they chose not to upgrade their dirtiest coal-fired power plants in the Midwest, areas downwind of those plants would continue to suffer. It is precisely those plants that have done the most acid-rain damage in the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>In addition, Clear Skies fails to regulate carbon dioxide, the main global-warming gas. The president is worried about the potential costs, and his big contributors in the power industry hate the idea of such a rule. Yet several progressive utilities who call themselves the Clean Energy Group and whose voices are not much heard in the White House -- they include Consolidated Edison of New York and Public Service Electric and Gas of New Jersey -- would prefer a bill that includes carbon dioxide because they think that it would help them make more rational investments in pollution-control technology.</p>
        <p>A detailed bill sponsored by Senator James Jeffords of Vermont would regulate carbon dioxide as well as the other major pollutants. This bill is the only one with any traction in the Senate. Clear Skies, by contrast, is just a set of distant goals. As long as it remains so, it is hard to take Mr. Bush seriously.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
