<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="08FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1398773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DB123DF93BA35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>American Hostage Killed In Philippines Battle  An American missionary, Martin Burnham, and a Filipino nurse being held by the Muslim extremist group Abu Sayyaf were killed in a gun battle between their captors and Filipino soldiers being trained by American troops. The missionary's wife, Gracia Burnham, was wounded. The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff said American troops were not directly involved in the incident, which the Pentagon described as a chance encounter, not a rescue mission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Americans Remain in India  The United States has urged its citizens to leave India but most American businessmen have yet to depart, hoping that tensions between the nuclear-armed rivals India and Pakistan will dissipate.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>American Hostage Killed In Philippines Battle  An American missionary, Martin Burnham, and a Filipino nurse being held by the Muslim extremist group Abu Sayyaf were killed in a gun battle between their captors and Filipino soldiers being trained by American troops. The missionary's wife, Gracia Burnham, was wounded. The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff said American troops were not directly involved in the incident, which the Pentagon described as a chance encounter, not a rescue mission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Americans Remain in India  The United States has urged its citizens to leave India but most American businessmen have yet to depart, hoping that tensions between the nuclear-armed rivals India and Pakistan will dissipate.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Deputy Secretary of State Richard L. Armitage emerged from a meeting with Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee of India but gave no sign of a breakthrough in trying to persuade India to step back from a conflict with Pakistan. Mr. Armitage met with Pakistan's leader on Thursday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Pakistan Frees Rape Victim  A Pakistani court bowed to a demand by President Musharraf and released Zafran Bibi, who had been sentenced to death by stoning for having extramarital relations. The woman left her jail cell carrying her 7-month-old daughter, who had been conceived when her husband was in prison and was therefore described by the judge as proof of her crime. The woman has accused her brother-in-law of raping her. He has not been charged.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Killings in Israeli Settlement  Two gunmen slipped into a heavily guarded Jewish settlement south of Jerusalem and shot six people, killing two. One attacker was slain and the other escaped, an Israeli military spokeswoman said. Earlier, Israeli forces swept into Palestinian-controlled towns in the West Bank, firing machine guns and making arrests in what the army said were raids for wanted militants. The sweeps came on the eve of a visit to Washington by Prime Minister Ariel Sharon.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Gay Pride March in Jerusalem  Jerusalem had its first gay pride parade over loud protests from Orthodox Jewish politicians and some demonstrators, who condemned it as a celebration of sin.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Argentine Ex-Minister Freed  A federal appeals court ordered the release of Domingo Cavallo, a former economy minister, who was jailed more than two months ago on charges of approving illegal arms sales during the early 1990's. The investigating judge could theoretically file new charges.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>China Holding Lawyer  Beijing police have detained one of China's most prominent private lawyers, Zhang Jianzhong, for more than a month, holding him incommunicado for undisclosed reasons. In a blatant if common violation of legal procedures, he has not been allowed to consult his own lawyer or to meet with his family.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-13</p>
        <p>Experts Offer Mixed Views On Security Cabinet Post  Experts on terrorism welcomed President Bush's proposal to create a Department of Homeland Security but said it was unclear whether it would significantly improve the government's ability to sift through mounds of intelligence data to extract clues about future attacks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Bush, alluding to Congressional committee jurisdictions, predicted a difficult fight over his plan to create a new cabinet department for domestic security, saying lawmakers would have to yield some authority before it became reality.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>The White House would not say whether Tom Ridge, the president's chief adviser on domestic security, was in line to become secretary of the new department.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Suspect Mentally Competent  A court-appointed psychiatrist has concluded that Zacarias Moussaoui, who is charged in the Sept. 11 attacks, is not mentally ill, a finding that may clear the way for him to represent himself at trial.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Khalid Shaikh Mohammed, a Kuwaiti extremist identified by American investigators as a major figure in the planning of the Sept. 11 attacks, may have been in Germany in 1999, about the same time as some of the hijackers, officials said.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Romney Candidacy Challenged  The Massachusetts Democratic Party formally challenged the qualifications of Mitt Romney as the Republican gubernatorial candidate, arguing to the State Ballot Law Commission that he had not been a state resident for the necessary seven years.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Bishops and Victims Fall Out  The leader of the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops canceled plans for the leaders of the main group representing victims of sexual abuse to address the bishops' national meeting in Dallas next week because of a lawsuit the victims' group filed on Thursday against the bishops.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Biology and Parenthood  The California Supreme Court has unanimously ruled that a man who cared for a 6-year-old boy can be considered his parent, even though the man is not the boy's biological father and was never married to the boy's mother. The ruling effectively holds that biology is not the only basis for claiming parenthood.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Skakel Guilty of Murder; Could Get Life Behind Bars  A Connecticut jury convicted Michael C. Skakel, 41, of murdering Martha Moxley, 15, with a golf club 27 years ago, when they were neighbors in Greenwich. His bail was immediately revoked. Mr. Skakel, a nephew of Ethel Kennedy, could be sentenced to life in prison.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bodies Found Near Ground Zero  In the week since the recovery effort officially ended at ground zero, Fire Department and construction crews have found the remains of a dozen or so victims in nearby buildings damaged on Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Hazy Look at Mayor's Finances  Mayor Bloomberg, whose worth has been estimated at $4 billion, issued a financial disclosure statement that contained relatively few numbers.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-18</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>New Life for Disputed Drug  The F.D.A. is letting Lotronex, a prescription drug used to treat irritable bowel syndrome, go back on the market, the first such instance of a medication returning to shelves after it was taken off for safety reasons.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Lakers Defeat Nets  Defending champion Los Angeles defeated New Jersey, 106-83, to take a two games to none lead in the N.B.A. Finals. The series will now shift to New Jersey for game three in the best of seven series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Working Out Kinks in Albany  A deal to put Mayor Bloomberg in charge of New York City schools could become law early next week, three Republican senators said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Breaking With 'Early Decision'  Harvard is considering amending its admissions policy to allow it to enroll an applicant whom a competing institution has accepted under a binding ''early decision'' program.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Jobless Rate Ebbs Slightly  The unemployment rate fell to 5.8 percent in May, from 6 percent in April, offering a glimmer of hope to out-of-work Americans and further evidence of an improving economy.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Tyco Inquiry Broadened  Manhattan prosecutors investigating L. Dennis Kozlowski, the former chief executive of Tyco International, will reopen an inquiry into two transactions in which the $2.5 million home of a Tyco director was sold to the company's general counsel. Tyco's shares, meanwhile, plunged 30 percent, to $10.10.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Pointing Finger at Energy Rivals  Xcel Energy sent documents to federal regulators suggesting that three big energy competitors -- Mirant, Duke Energy and the Williams Companies -- might have schemed to drive up power prices in California. The companies denied wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New Disclosures at Adelphia  Adelphia Communications overstated both the number of its cable subscribers and its cash flow for 2001, people close to the company said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Keith Fuller  The president of the Associated Press, the world's largest news agency, from 1976 to 1985 was 79.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Insuring against terrorism; global warming follies; deceptive tans and health risks; off to the races.</p>
        <p>Column: Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B17  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B18  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>A16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
