<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tougher Rules Are Proposed For Gas Mileage</title>
    <meta content="Y13FUE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/13/business/13FUEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1448196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6D8103AF930A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tougher Rules Are Proposed For Gas Mileage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tougher Rules Are Proposed for Gas Mileage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Dec. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration proposes largest increase in automotive fuel economy in more than decade, calling for 7 percent improvement in performance of sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans; critics, including environmentalists and top Democrats, say proposal demands no more of auto industry than it has already committed itself to achieve on its own; plan is praised by some moderates, and auto executives call it challenge; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed the largest increase in automotive fuel economy in more than a decade today, calling for a 7 percent improvement in the performance of sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans.</p>
        <p>Critics, including many environmentalists and top Democrats, said the proposal demanded no more of the auto industry than it had already committed itself to achieve on its own. But the plan was praised by some moderates, and auto executives called it a challenge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House is calling for a 7 percent improvement in automobile fuel economy. Critics say the proposal demands no more than the auto industry has already committed to achieve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed the largest increase in automotive fuel economy in more than a decade today, calling for a 7 percent improvement in the performance of sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans.</p>
        <p>Critics, including many environmentalists and top Democrats, said the proposal demanded no more of the auto industry than it had already committed itself to achieve on its own. But the plan was praised by some moderates, and auto executives called it a challenge.</p>
        <p>The proposal would require automakers to increase the average fuel economy of so-called light trucks by 1.5 miles per gallon, to an average of 22.2 miles per gallon, by the 2007 model year. The administration said that would reduce gasoline consumption by 2.5 billion gallons through that year.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure everyone who doesn't know about the industry will say, 'Gee-whiz, what's a couple of tenths of miles per gallon per year?' '' said Dr. Jeffrey W. Runge, the administrator of the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, who announced the proposal in Washington. ''This is going to be challenging for the industry to meet, but we feel they can do it.''</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry, a Massachusetts Democrat who is considering challenging President Bush in 2004, was unimpressed. ''The administration is merely ratifying less than what industry is already doing on its own, without challenge or incentive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company has pledged a 25 percent improvement in the fuel economy of its sport utilities by mid-decade. General Motors and DaimlerChrysler have said they will be competitive with Ford.</p>
        <p>''Improving the average S.U.V.'s fuel economy by a paltry one and a half miles a gallon would save less than 3 percent of the oil we already import from Iraq,'' Senator Kerry said.</p>
        <p>Senator Kerry was the co-sponsor of a Senate proposal, with Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, to require a 50 percent increase in fuel economy for light trucks and for cars over 12 years. It was defeated in March by a wide margin.</p>
        <p>The administration plan calls for three annual increases in light truck fuel economy beginning in the 2005 model year. Suggestions will be accepted for 60 days, and then the regulators can impose the change without Congressional approval.</p>
        <p>Booming sales of sport utilities and pickups have become an issue at a time of escalating tension in the Middle East and growing dependence on imported oil. But proposals to improve fuel economy have long faced stiff opposition from the domestic carmakers, labor unions and sympathetic lawmakers -- in part because S.U.V. sales, in particular, have become crucial to the Big Three's profitability.</p>
        <p>Today, government officials from both parties characterized the Bush administration's plan as a way to take some action beyond what its predecessors could accomplish without offending the industry.</p>
        <p>''It is good economic news for consumers, and it illustrates the administration's commitment to address concerns about both energy security and global climate change,'' said John Graham, head of the Office of Management and Budget, which reviewed and approved the proposal. Mr. Graham said the proposal would cost automakers and consumers $373 million, but produce $794 million in fuel savings over the lives of the affected vehicles.</p>
        <p>Growing sales of sport utilities have reduced the fuel economy of the average vehicle in the United States to its lowest point in two decades.</p>
        <p>Each automaker's light trucks are now required to average 20.7 miles per gallon, though there is some flexibility to carry over credits year to year. Cars must average 27.5 miles per gallon. The government's measure overstates actual fuel economy by 18 percent, experts say.</p>
        <p>The industry takes advantage of the split standard by designing vehicles that resemble cars, like Chrysler's PT Cruiser, yet qualify as light trucks because they have attributes like a rear seat that can be folded down to form a flat bed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Runge said that he had no plans to demand better fuel economy for cars, citing a concern that automakers would meet a tighter standard by reducing the weight of cars. Doing that would put occupants of cars at greater risk in collisions with light trucks, said Dr. Runge, a former emergency room physician.</p>
        <p>Another official involved in regulatory deliberations said that the administration was considering more steps after the 2007 model year. It might revise the definition of a light truck so that carlike vehicles are not included, he said, while the light truck standards might be extended to include the biggest sport utilities, like Hummers, which are not now subject to fuel economy rules.</p>
        <p>Many environmental groups said that the administration's announced plans did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>''The Bush administration is being irresponsible, because they're failing to make the auto companies use existing technology to cut oil consumption, cut pollution and save consumers money at the gas pump,'' said Daniel Becker, the top energy expert at the Sierra Club. The proposal, he added, was ''so minuscule that it won't be felt.''</p>
        <p>Not all were as critical of the proposal to tighten so-called corporate average fuel economy requirements.</p>
        <p>''The sad fact is that this is the most meaningful step the country has taken on oil dependence since Jimmy Carter was president,'' said John DeCicco, a senior fellow at Environmental Defense, an advocacy group in New York.</p>
        <p>Big Three officials called the proposal a challenge because they are struggling to meet the current requirements while expanding their truck sales. Moreover, they worry that the plan could create an advantage for some Asian automakers.</p>
        <p>For example, the average fuel economy of Honda's light trucks last year was 24.9 miles per gallon, well above the proposed new standard. Toyota's was 22.1 miles per gallon, just short of the new proposal.</p>
        <p>According to an administration official, data submitted by the industry indicate that Nissan and G.M. will be the most hard pressed to meet the tougher standards.</p>
        <p>''This proposal represents a significant increase,'' said Eron Shosteck, a spokesman for the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, the principal industry lobbying group on Capitol Hill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
