<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TAKING THE CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="29TAKI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/29/movies/29TAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1379547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Taking the Children"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ice Age (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Et: the Extraterrestrial (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Showtime (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DA1E3BF93AA15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TAKING THE CHILDREN</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cold Paws, Warm Heart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter M Nichols reviews movies Ice Age, ET: The Extraterrestrial and Showtime, focusing on their suitability for children; photo (Taking the Children column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ice Age</p>
        <p>With the voices of Ray Romano, John Leguizamo, Denis Leary, Goran Visnjic, Jack Black  Directed by Chris Wedge  PG 75 minutes</p>
        <p>A cartoon Darwinian conflict keeps it simple and sentimental. To begin with, it's cold and getting colder, with jagged ice cliffs spreading and the ground freezing so hard a scrat (squirrel-rat) can't bury an acorn. All species are headed south, and there is competition along the trail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reviews of "Ice Age," "E.T." and "Showtime."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ice Age</p>
        <p>With the voices of Ray Romano, John Leguizamo, Denis Leary, Goran Visnjic, Jack Black  Directed by Chris Wedge  PG 75 minutes</p>
        <p>A cartoon Darwinian conflict keeps it simple and sentimental. To begin with, it's cold and getting colder, with jagged ice cliffs spreading and the ground freezing so hard a scrat (squirrel-rat) can't bury an acorn. All species are headed south, and there is competition along the trail.</p>
        <p>You've met characters like these many times. A sloth named Sid (Mr. Leguizamo) is the requisite animated motormouth, yakking incessantly and obsequiously. Manfred the mammoth (Mr. Romano), by way of ''Shrek,'' is the shambling gruff guy with the soft spot and altruistic streak. As the heavy who will eventually see the light, Diego the saber-tooth tiger (Mr. Leary) fronts for a pack of his bloodthirsty fellows. Two rhinos serve as cranky buffoons.</p>
        <p>Humans are around, one of them a baby who will become a symbolic football. After an attack by the tigers, the infant falls into the care of Manfred and Sid, who has ingratiatingly attached himself to the mammoth for protection. Manfred grumbles about the kid, but decides it's his duty to return him to his people.</p>
        <p>With them by design, if not choice, Diego is pressed into service as a guide. By himself, the tiger is no threat to Manfred, but he is leading them toward an ambush. And tigers aren't the only danger. As cave drawings indicate, humans carry spears. There's a reckoning ahead, all right, but for those wondering about global warming, rest assured. Stuck fast in an ice cube, the scrat and his acorn plop out on a tropical beach.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Since nothing in this film is in the least way original, children will be accustomed to the usual cartoon assaults and devourings.  SEX -- None.  PROFANITY -- Only one instance, a kind of sore thumb.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>AGES 3-6 -- Mothers frequently succumb in children's adventures, and so it is here when the baby's mother is swept off by a river. That and the tigers may trouble some viewers.  AGES 7-10 -- Diego the tiger has a question for the mammoth: if they save the baby, whom will the human hunt when he's grown? But Manfred's determination to defend and preserve the helpless never wavers. Even Diego learns to be a team player and help out the herd. The film buries it all in schmaltz, but the young ones will have a good time nevertheless.</p>
        <p>E.T.</p>
        <p>Henry Thomas, Robert MacNaughton, Drew Barrymore, Dee Wallace, Peter Coyote  Directed by Steven Spielberg  PG 120 minutes</p>
        <p>There's the ''E.T., phone home'' line, of course, but also recall Elliott's cry to the frog he has just saved from dissection in his school's science lab. ''Run for the river,'' he yells as the spared one revives from his chloroformed cotton ball and bounds off the worktable.</p>
        <p>Today as in 1982, Elliott (Henry Thomas) exercises his survivalist's instinct, and that's still a good thing for the famous little alien he finds hiding in a tool shed behind his house. Everything remains intact in the Spielberg classic, re-released for its 20th anniversary with some digital tweaking and a couple of scenes added. As before, the scientist Keys (Mr. Coyote) gets into the proper spirit, but other ''authorities'' are more menacing than aliens could ever be in a Spielberg film. For the revival, though, the guns have been digitally removed from their hands and replaced with walkie-talkies.</p>
        <p>Does anyone not know this story? Elliott, his brother (Robert MacNaughton) and their little sister (Drew Barrymore) scramble to keep E.T. out of official hands and take him to the rendezvous point with the mother ship that had to abandon him as humans closed in at the start of the film. There's that famous airborne bike ride against a Halloween moon. Earlier, E.T. watches ''The Quiet Man,'' his first and only John Wayne movie.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- None. But there is always the threat of it.  SEX -- None.  PROFANITY -- An exclamation or two.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>AGES 3-6 -- Scary moments are relatively mild, but some viewers could be disturbed. Parents know best.  AGES 7-9 -- One of the greatest children's films ever made is just as much so.  AGES 10-12 -- There could be some defectors in adolescence. They'll be back.</p>
        <p>Showtime</p>
        <p>Robert De Niro, Eddie Murphy, Rene Russo, Frankie R. Faison, William Shatner  Directed by Tom Dey  PG-13 95 minutes</p>
        <p>''If you commit the crime, you will do the time,'' intones the stone-faced veteran detective Mitch Preston (Mr. De Niro). Mitch happens to be lecturing a roomful of 10-year-olds, but he could be addressing Al Qaeda. Wrongdoers of any stripe are all the same to Mitch, which helps make him the perfect nonfun half of a cop team dreamed up by the television producer Chase Renzi (Ms. Russo). For her new show, Renzi wants Mitch on the street busting bad guys, and for some variety she pairs him in the squad car with a gregarious officer and aspiring actor named Trey Sellars (Mr. Murphy).</p>
        <p>Yes, it's a new kind of reality show, with Renzi and camera crew trailing the boys around Los Angeles and looking in on them at home for the intimate side. Choosing Trey pleases her boss, who says he wants a funny minority type to get the N.A.A.C.P. off his back. Mitch wants absolutely no part of this, but he is being forced into it by his own boss (Mr. Faison), who is looking for some favorable publicity for the L.A.P.D.</p>
        <p>Believe it or not, Mitch is a potter with a workshop in his apartment. His furnishings have to go, though, and the television people give his place a new look. On the job, Trey plays to the camera and tries to explain Mitch, who grimly wrecks a lot of cars chasing people. The criminals have a new kind of super gun that wrecks buildings and so forth. There is a climactic shootout. Ratings are good. The two officers develop a little respect for each other, and Mitch makes Trey a lopsided jar to keep his change in.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- A lot of shooting and smash-ups to please 14-year-old boys of all ages, none of it too graphic or in any way personally affecting.  SEX -- There isn't the energy.  PROFANITY -- They talk dirty but avoid heavy obscenity and an R rating.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>UNDER AGE 11 -- Why?  AGES 11 AND UP -- Apologies to Mr. De Niro, who never disappoints whatever the material, and Mr. Murphy, who does what he can with what he's given, but this is the dumbest movie of the month, which is saying something. Parents' decision, but disapproval wouldn't be out of order.</p>
        <p>Taking the Children</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
