<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year Later, Blake's Widow Searches for Strength</title>
    <meta content="28BLAK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/28/sports/othersports/28BLAK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Zealand</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amazon River Basin</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Macapa (Brazil)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blake, Peter (Sir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blake, Pippa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Zealand</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blake, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DF163FF93BA15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year Later, Blake's Widow Searches for Strength</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Year Later, Blake's Widow Searches for Strength</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>AUCKLAND, New Zealand, Dec. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team New Zealand welcomes Lady Pippa Blake, widow of America's Cup champion, environmentalist and explorer Sir Peter Blake, to sail in America's Cup in commemoration of Blake's death last year during robbery attempt in Amazon River; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first 90 days or so, because Sir Peter Blake was often away on an adventure in some faraway ocean, his wife hoped he might phone and tell her he was fine.</p>
        <p>That he was off winning another Whitbread Round-the-World race, stuck at sea for nine months. Or navigating around glaciers in the Northwest Passage, making a documentary aboard a boat he had bought from the family of Jacques Cousteau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sailor Sir Peter Blake was killed last year while trying to protect his crew from masked pirates who had attacked his yacht. But for his widow, "it hasn't all sunk in yet."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first 90 days or so, because Sir Peter Blake was often away on an adventure in some faraway ocean, his wife hoped he might phone and tell her he was fine.</p>
        <p>That he was off winning another Whitbread Round-the-World race, stuck at sea for nine months. Or navigating around glaciers in the Northwest Passage, making a documentary aboard a boat he had bought from the family of Jacques Cousteau.</p>
        <p>Danger Island in the Indian Ocean. Gibraltar. Perth. A renowned sailor turned environmentalist, knighted by order of Queen Elizabeth in 1995 and most noted for bringing the America's Cup to his homeland that same year and then organizing the first successful defense outside the United States in 2000, Blake could have been anywhere.</p>
        <p>''I kept thinking that would be him on the other end of the line,'' Lady Pippa Blake said. ''Gradually, after about three months, I realized that wasn't going to be. I still think sometimes, maybe, that he's off somewhere doing this or that.</p>
        <p>''It's only been a year, so it hasn't all sunk in yet.''</p>
        <p>On Dec. 5 last year, Blake was killed while trying to protect his crew from masked pirates who had attacked his yacht, Seamaster, while it was anchored near Macapá, Brazil, a small city near the mouth of the Amazon River.</p>
        <p>This week, a half-dozen Christmas cards sat propped up on a table of a 10th-floor apartment, lent by a family friend, overlooking Auckland harbor. From the window, Lady Blake and her children, Sarah-Jane, 19, and James, 16, can watch the yachts tugged daily toward the Hauraki Gulf starting line, where the names ''Pete'' and ''Blakey'' are still invoked often.</p>
        <p>If a family grows strong, a name and a legacy live on.</p>
        <p>At the time of his death, Blake, who was 53, had just returned from Antarctica and was leading a United Nations project to investigate global warming. He was working on his third documentary for blakexpeditions, the company he founded, whose mission is to protect life in, on and around the waters of the world.</p>
        <p>As a bandit held a gun to the head of one of his crewmen, Blake sprang from the cabin below, brandishing a rifle he had on board to ward off polar bears. He shot one of the attackers in the hand before the gun malfunctioned; he was shot in the back and killed.</p>
        <p>More than a year after New Zealand mourned his death, he is still very much part of the nation's consciousness. The legacy of Blake, a striking 6-foot-4 mustachioed man with tousled blond hair, known for his dry wit and belly laugh as much as for his maritime feats, grows even more luminous in death.</p>
        <p>At a popular dockside restaurant called Swashbucklers, an enormous copper bust of Blake is displayed next to the door. ''That was me mate,'' said the owner, a stout New Zealander named Ginger, as he tugged on his sailor's cap last week.</p>
        <p>Siraj Mussa, an Auckland cab driver, said he had lost interest in the America's Cup after Blake's death. ''There were a handful of people like him in history,'' Mussa said. ''Muhammad Ali, Elvis Presley, Peter Blake. Perhaps there are a few others in that category.''</p>
        <p>Several days after Blake was buried near Emsworth, England, his wife's hometown and the couple's home, 30,000 mourners turned out for a memorial service at the Auckland Domain, a large downtown park. Sarah-Jane read ''Bilbo's Last Stand,'' a poem from J. R. R. Tolkien's ''Lord of the Rings,'' and James read from his father's last log entry aboard the Seamaster.</p>
        <p>The prime minister of New Zealand, Helen Clark, said at the service, ''We identified with the story of the boy from Bayswater, who learned to sail on Auckland harbor and went on to test the limits on the world's roughest oceans, just as Sir Edmund Hillary had on the world's tallest mountain.''</p>
        <p>His friend and business partner, Alan Sefton, walks past Blake's grave several days a week on his way home, often stopping by the local pub to hear about the newest group of New Zealanders making the pilgrimage. They leave flags, flowers, kiwi fruit, even a pair of red socks, which Blake had inspired a country to wear in 1995 during the Cup.</p>
        <p>When Lady Blake returned to Blake's native land last August to christen one of Team New Zealand's black-hulled boats, people she had never met came up to her on the street, tears flowing down their cheeks, embracing her.</p>
        <p>''I knew he was a great man, but it's ironic the attention he receives now,'' she said. ''Maybe that's the way the world works, but it's extraordinary. I mean yesterday a complete stranger was driving a car and she yelled out, 'Good on ya, Pippa! Merry Christmas.' A complete stranger. It hits you quite hard, that sort of thing.''</p>
        <p>The feelings will resonate again when she returns in mid-February, as the guest of Team New Zealand, to cheer on her husband's team in the America's Cup final.</p>
        <p>''Peter was just such a huge part of the team and our life,'' said Ross Blackman, the executive director of Team New Zealand and a close family friend. ''He always wanted to be there to support us for this defense. To not have Pippa and the kids here did not feel right.</p>
        <p>''I know this sounds funny,'' he added, ''but we don't feel we are without him. His presence is here everywhere, both in name and the things we do. We're always saying, 'What would Blakey have done?' ''</p>
        <p>When Blake retired from racing and began his environmental crusade, he was arguably the world's most accomplished sailor. He set a world record sailing his catamaran, Enza, around the globe to win the 1994 Jules Verne Trophy. The trophies he raised after victories in the Fastnet Race, Sydney Hobart, the Admiral's Cup, Whitbread and the oldest and most prominent of them all, the Auld Mug, were only affirmations of his odysseys at sea.</p>
        <p>Lady Blake remembers that on their honeymoon -- a three-month voyage spent with other sailors -- she and Blake sailed through a cyclone in the Tasman Sea. Her husband had braved the Southern Ocean and the Arctic. Aboard the Enza, he once returned to England with broken ribs in a raging storm, when winds of 69 knots and waves up to 50 feet nearly capsized the catamaran.</p>
        <p>After orchestrating Team New Zealand's sweep of Prada Challenge from Italy in the 2000 America's Cup, Blake became the head of expeditions for the Cousteau Society and skipper of the group's aluminum research ketch, Antarctic Explorer. He left the society but bought the boat, which he renamed Seamaster. Aboard it, he led trips last year to Antarctica and the Amazon.</p>
        <p>On the night of Dec. 5, Blake was doing what he always did: protecting his crew. During an inquest, Robin Allen, a British crewman aboard the Seamaster, described how six men had jumped aboard the boat wearing motorbike helmets or ski masks. They demanded money, pistol-whipped one crewman and held a gun to the head of another. That's when Blake stepped in with his rifle.</p>
        <p>In England the next morning, Lady Blake received a phone call at 6 a.m. from Sefton, Blake's business manager.</p>
        <p>''I thought nothing of it because I'm quite used to getting phone calls from boats on the other side of the world,'' she said. ''And then he said: 'Pippa, I'm downstairs. Can you let me in?' And I thought, 'Something's not right.' ''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview from England, Sefton said: ''I didn't know any other way to tell her. I just said, 'Pete's dead.' ''</p>
        <p>Lady Blake, her eyes welling up, described it as ''the hardest day of my life really, having to tell the children their father was no longer alive, particularly James, because he just adored Peter.''</p>
        <p>A thin, fit woman with sandy blond hair, Lady Blake wore a denim jacket and white cotton jeans while nursing a mug of coffee on a couch.</p>
        <p>''I miss him, all the time,'' she said. ''Peter had a great sense of humor. He had these dreadful, banal sort of jokes. For instance, someone will say, 'I'm going to put the kettle on,' And he'll say, 'Will it fit?' Stupid jokes. Very dry humor.''</p>
        <p>Last June, Ricardo Colares Tavares, 23, who admitted firing two shots into Blake's back, was sentenced to 36 years 9 months in prison. Five other members of the gang received sentences from 26 to 35 years.</p>
        <p>Sefton has been in charge of keeping blakexpeditions up and running. He is hoping to come up with about $2 million before its next voyage.</p>
        <p>''Peter had achieved legendary status in his own lifetime, so, yes, it's been hard,'' Sefton said. ''When Sir Edmund conquered Everest, he was the quintessential Kiwi, an icon to four or five generations. Pete touched the same nerve ends. He was a figure to a whole new generation of Kiwis.''</p>
        <p>Lady Blake said she cries often for the man she met in 1978 when he walked into the local sailing club in Emsworth, fresh from an around-the-world challenge. A month later, she accepted his invitation to meet him in the Caribbean and sail the world.</p>
        <p>''So I ran off with a sailor and somehow became a Lady,'' she said, laughing.</p>
        <p>''I pretty much loved the life right from the beginning. Our entire married life I quite often shared Peter with teams of people. But we coped with that. I must have met him at every port in the world.''</p>
        <p>While watching the America's Cup races, Lady Blake kept thinking, ''This should be Peter doing this.''</p>
        <p>''But I don't dwell on such things,'' she said. Her eyes sometimes well around strangers who cry in front of her, but the tears never come. She tries to move on.</p>
        <p>''I feel very strongly about coming back here, but it's also quite hard because of Peter,'' she said. ''So I have to be stronger.''</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
