<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Race to Tap the Euphrates, The Upper Hand Is Upstream</title>
    <meta content="25WATE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/25/international/middleeast/25WATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="RUNNING DRY: First of four articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1418627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Euphrates River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Irrigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Irrigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Syria</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED9133CF936A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="2620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Race to Tap the Euphrates, The Upper Hand Is Upstream</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Race to Tap the Euphrates, the Upper Hand Is Upstream</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>TELL AL-SAMEN, Syria</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First of four articles in series, Running Dry, on increasing conflict and competition over world's dwindling water resources; governments of Syria, Turkey and Iraq, as example, have promised their people more water from Euphrates River than that river holds; United Nations and United States government estimate that by 2015, at least 40 percent of world's population or about three billion people will live in countries where it is difficult or impossible to get enough water to satisfy basic needs; inescapable fact about world's water supply is that it is finite; less than 1 percent of it is fresh water that can be used for drinking or agriculture, and demand for that water is rising; over last 70 years, world's population has tripled while water demand has increased sixfold, causing increasing strain especially in heavily populated areas where water is distant, is being depleted or is simply too polluted to use; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Euphrates River is close by, but the water does not reach Abdelrazak al-Aween. Here at the heart of the fertile crescent, he stares at dry fields.</p>
        <p>The Syrian government has promised water for Mr. Aween's tiny village. But upstream, in Turkey, and downstream, in Iraq, similar promises are being made. They add up to more water than the Euphrates holds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Turkey expands irrigation to its impoverished south, the flow of Euphrates water into Syria has grown consistently smaller.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Euphrates River is close by, but the water does not reach Abdelrazak al-Aween. Here at the heart of the fertile crescent, he stares at dry fields.</p>
        <p>The Syrian government has promised water for Mr. Aween's tiny village. But upstream, in Turkey, and downstream, in Iraq, similar promises are being made. They add up to more water than the Euphrates holds.</p>
        <p>So instead of irrigating his cotton and sugar beets, Mr. Aween must siphon drinking and washing water from a ditch 40 minutes away by tractor ride. Just across the border, meanwhile, Ahmet Demir, a Turkish farmer, stands ankle deep in mud, his crops soaking up all the water they need.</p>
        <p>It was here in ancient Mesopotamia, thousands of years ago, that the last all-out war over water was fought, between rival city-states in what is now southern Iraq. Now, across a widening swath of the world, more and more people are vying for less and less water, in conflicts more rancorous by the day.</p>
        <p>From the searing plains of Mesopotamia to the steadily expanding deserts of northern China to the cotton fields of northwest Texas, the struggle for water is igniting social, economic and political tensions.</p>
        <p>The World Bank has said dwindling water supplies will be a major factor inhibiting economic growth, a subject being discussed at a weeklong international conference in South Africa starting Monday about balancing use of the world's resources against its economic needs.</p>
        <p>Global warming, some experts suspect, may be adding to the strain. Droughts may be extended in already dry regions, including parts of the United States, even as wetter areas tend toward calamitous downpours and floods like those ravaging Europe and Asia this summer. In general, the world's climate may be more prone to extremes, with too much water in some areas and far too little in others.</p>
        <p>Both the United Nations and the National Intelligence Council, an advisory group to the Central Intelligence Agency, have warned that the competition for water is likely to worsen. ''As countries press against the limits of available water between now and 2015, the possibility of conflict will increase,'' the National Intelligence Council warned in a report last year.</p>
        <p>By 2015, according to estimates from the United Nations and the United States government, at least 40 percent of the world's population, or about three billion people, will live in countries where it is difficult or impossible to get enough water to satisfy basic needs.</p>
        <p>''The signs of unsustainability are widespread and spreading,'' said Sandra Postel, director of the Global Water Policy Project in Amherst, Mass. ''If we're to have any hope of satisfying the food and water needs of the world's people in the years ahead, we will need a fundamental shift in how we use and manage water.''</p>
        <p>An inescapable fact about the world's water supply is that it is finite. Less than 1 percent of it is fresh water that can be used for drinking or agriculture, and demand for that water is rising.</p>
        <p>Over the last 70 years, the world's population has tripled while water demand has increased sixfold, causing increasing strain especially in heavily populated areas where water is distant, is being depleted or is simply too polluted to use.</p>
        <p>Already, a little more than half of the world's available fresh water is being used each year, according to one rough but generally accepted estimate. That fraction could climb to 74 percent by 2025 based on population growth alone, and would hit 90 percent if people everywhere used as much water as the average American, one of the world's most gluttonous water consumers.</p>
        <p>Water tables are falling on every continent, and experts warn that the situation is expected to worsen significantly in years to come. On top of the shortages that already exist, the outlook adds to the tensions and uncertainty for countries that share water sources, like Turkey and Syria, where Mr. Aween is among those still waiting and hoping for the Euphrates to be brought to his door.</p>
        <p>A Few Miles' Difference</p>
        <p>The stories of Mr. Aween and Mr. Demir illustrate how the growing fight for water can make or ruin lives.</p>
        <p>Until last year, Mr. Demir, 42, a father of nine in Turkey, was living an itinerant life as a smuggler and a migrant laborer. But on a recent scorching afternoon, he stood sunburned and content, his striped pants rolled above his knees, bare feet squishing in Euphrates mud.</p>
        <p>''It seems like we have all the water we need,'' Mr. Demir said, leaning on his shovel and running a hand through his close-cropped hair. What has changed in this swath of southern Turkey is the arrival of irrigation. It is part of one of the world's largest water projects, an audacious $30 billion plan by Turkey's government to spread the Euphrates' gifts across a vast and impoverished region of the country.</p>
        <p>By now, Mr. Aween, the Syrian, might have been celebrating, too. Under Syria's irrigation plan, ambitious in its own right, water from the Euphrates should have reached Mr. Aween's door, less than 50 miles from Mr. Demir's.</p>
        <p>But strong doubts are emerging about whether the vast scope of Turkey's project will leave enough water for its neighbors downstream -- so much so that Syria appears to have put the brakes on its development plan.</p>
        <p>''We're still waiting,'' Mr. Aween, 40, said on behalf of his 2 wives, 3 children, and 17 brothers and sisters, who all live in a hamlet that bears the family name. He wore a loose, Arab-style outer garment and cheap plastic sandals as he hitched a rusty tanker trailer to a sputtering tractor, his water bearers. ''But the water hasn't come.''</p>
        <p>The trouble over the Euphrates can be expressed in a simple, untenable equation.</p>
        <p>As best as anyone can determine, the river, in an average year, holds 35 billion cubic meters of water. But the separate plans drawn up by Turkey, Syria and Iraq for building dams and irrigating fields would, taken together, consume nearly half again more water than the river holds.</p>
        <p>Each country has acknowledged the impossibility of marrying their schemes. But none has shown any willingness to scale back. Trying to accommodate fast-growing populations and to head off a migration to the cities, each country is still clinging to its irrigation dreams.</p>
        <p>On both sides of the Turkish-Syrian border, snapshots of those dreams still unfold on summer dawns, in fields that used to be good for little but grazing, but where new irrigation canals are now delivering Euphrates water in regular supply.</p>
        <p>Thirsty crops like cotton and sugar beets have begun to thrive. Farm incomes have tripled. Young women who turn out in sparkling dresses tend prized plants with special care, shepherding the water down each muddy row. Young boys cavort in irrigation ditches that provide relief from the intense midday heat.</p>
        <p>Now that there is water, Mr. Demir said, it would not be such a bad thing if his four sons, ranging in age from 4 months to 22 years, decided to stay and work the land -- something he could not have imagined only a year ago when farming was far harder.</p>
        <p>But in a world in which so much depends on having water, he bristled at the idea of sharing it. ''If I used any less, the others would use more,'' he said. ''I use what I need, and as for the rest, it's their business.''</p>
        <p>That kind of thinking has not helped Mr. Aween's village, not far from Tell al-Samen, where the absence of water is almost equally on display. With his family, Mr. Aween raises scraggly goats and grows whatever barley and wheat he can coax from dry, unirrigated land. It is a far cry, he said, from the lush green crops he would grow with irrigation -- the difference between sustenance and comfort.</p>
        <p>Syria and Turkey have been at odds since the late 1980's, when Turkey decided to proceed with its development project without consulting its neighbors.</p>
        <p>To Turkey, the plan was an essential step in the country's development, a means of transforming an area that is home to six million people, including many restive Kurds, into a zone of greater economic and political stability. But to Syria, which depends on the Euphrates for half its fresh water, it continues to be seen as a major threat. Iraq, the far downstream neighbor, has been mostly a bystander because of its international isolation.</p>
        <p>The basic disputes between Turkey and Syria -- over water rights and allocations -- would be familiar to any landowner who has struggled over competing claims to a stream or a well. But the fact that the parties are nations, with large armies at their disposal and large populations at stake, has added to the weight of the clash.</p>
        <p>Less powerful militarily than Turkey, Syria resorted through much of the 1990's to indirect pressure, by giving support to the terrorist leader Abdullah Ocalan, the No. 1 enemy of the Turkish government. In response, Turkish officials sometimes went so far as to warn that the flow of the Euphrates into Syria could be cut.</p>
        <p>Such talk has cooled in the last three years since the arrest of Mr. Ocalan. But the potential for trouble lingers.</p>
        <p>Over the last year, as Turkey has completed many dams and has begun to extend its irrigation, the flow of Euphrates water into Syria has grown consistently smaller. The flow has fallen below levels allowed under Turkey's only existing commitment to Syria, an interim 1987 agreement intended for the period of dam construction.</p>
        <p>Turkey has blamed drought and the overuse of the new, cheap water by farmers for the shortfall. The government says much of that can be reversed. But Turkish officials have also said they no longer see the 1987 deal as binding. The trend has raised deep concerns in Syria, which is already facing water shortages in Damascus, the capital.</p>
        <p>Both countries say they are ready to strike a deal, but cannot imagine scaling back their development plans. ''For half of Syria, the Euphrates is life,'' said Abdel Aziz al-Masri, a top official at Syria's Ministry of Irrigation.</p>
        <p>Mumtaz Turfan, the director of Turkey's department of hydraulic works, echoed the sentiment. ''Without our dams, life in Turkey would be impossible,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rising Tension, Dwindling Water</p>
        <p>It has been a decade since Syria, Turkey and Iraq sat down to formal negotiations, and their positions remain as starkly opposed now as they were then.</p>
        <p>Syria and Iraq want the water to be divided roughly in thirds. Turkey, on the other hand, claims more than half for itself. It says any sharing must take into account Turkey's status as the source of most Euphrates water and the home to a population that is half again as big as Iraq's and Syria's put together.</p>
        <p>''I am sure that if we forget about borders, we can solve the problem,'' Mr. Turfan said. Over the last 30 years, he has presided over the construction of 700 dams in Turkey, and a map that stretches across his wall details plans for 500 more.</p>
        <p>''I am providing water for 22 million people who take drinking water from our dams, and for 35 percent of our agriculture,'' he said. It would be a mistake, he suggested, for Turkey to accept less than the lion's share of the Euphrates. ''Without irrigation, we can't do anything,'' he said. ''We can't give it up and destroy our people.''</p>
        <p>Around the world, the question of water ownership has never seemed so divisive.</p>
        <p>Despite efforts by the United Nations and others, the world has yet to come up with an accepted formula on how shared waters should be divided. That situation applies to nearly 300 rivers, including the Nile, the Danube, the Colorado and the Rio Grande, all subject to major disputes.</p>
        <p>In 1997, a United Nations convention declared that international waterways should be divided reasonably and equitably, without causing unnecessary harm. But Turkey, along with China and Burundi, refused to sign the agreement, a sign of reluctance on the part of major upstream countries to cede their dominant positions.</p>
        <p>Beyond current water shortages, one reason for the tension is a lack of optimism that pressures on the world's water supply might be eased.</p>
        <p>Of course, some new technologies, including advanced irrigation techniques, innovative desalination methods and bold water-moving schemes, offer some hope.</p>
        <p>But experts say the task of making fresh water available where there is none -- from seawater, from icebergs or by moving surface water long distances -- remains too costly to be widely adopted. Most easily accessible fresh water sources have already been tapped.</p>
        <p>To those who would bend nature, there are many cautionary tales, including the Soviet-orchestrated drying up of the Aral Sea, an environmental catastrophe. Even for its project on the Euphrates, Turkey could not win World Bank support because of the plan's significant costs, including the submerging of an important archaeological site.</p>
        <p>But sometimes, as in Turkey's case, the thirst for water is greater than any such opposition. Along the Euphrates, Turkey is paying its own way, despite the financial hardship and despite the uncertainty over how its plans will affect others.</p>
        <p>In the dry heat of a Mesopotamian summer, how that tenacity is regarded depends on which way the water is flowing.</p>
        <p>In an office in Al Raqqa, a Syrian city on the banks of the Euphrates, Iliaz Dakal, a consultant to Syria's land development agency, was studying a map of his own. It depicted, in vivid green, the land that Syria is already irrigating along the river. Much more land, though, like the fields that are home to Mr. Aween, was crosshatched to show uncertainty -- its water and its fate now perhaps in Turkey's hands.</p>
        <p>''For now, thank God, we have enough to grow the wheat we need,'' Mr. Dakal said. ''But what about the future?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Demir, in his muddy Turkish field, had an answer, saying he had come to see water as a byproduct of power.</p>
        <p>''If Turkey is stronger,'' he said, ''then I get to keep my water.''</p>
        <p>Running Dry</p>
        <p>Articles in this series examine the increasing conflict and competition over the world's dwindling water resources.</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Conflict between neighbors.  MONDAY -- Controlling water for profit.  TUESDAY -- China's colossal gamble.  WEDNESDAY -- An American turnabout.</p>
        <p>The articles and a portfolio of photographs with audio commentary from Douglas Jehl are available online at nytimes.com/international.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
