<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flooding Elbe Batters Towns Along Its Path</title>
    <meta content="18FLOO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/18/international/europe/18FLOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1416922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Elbe (River)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Meissen (Germany)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dessau (Germany)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DB133DF93BA2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flooding Elbe Batters Towns Along Its Path</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Flooding Elbe Batters Towns Along Its Path</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>DESSAU, Germany, Aug. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elbe river dams break, inundating German towns upriver from Dessau; photo of rescuers in Meissen; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As dams broke upriver in Bitterfeld and Mühlberg, inundating the towns, the people of Dessau were piling sandbags today on an earthwork dam -- but it was already leaking.</p>
        <p>The water level in Dresden finally began to drop from its record depth of 30.84 feet, but only by less than half an inch. But other less notable German towns were bracing for what is being called ''the battle against the water,'' and 30,000 people living along the Elbe and its bloated tributaries have been evacuated so far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The water level in Dresden, Germany, finally began to drop, as the flood waters broke dams in other German towns upriver.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As dams broke upriver in Bitterfeld and Mühlberg, inundating the towns, the people of Dessau were piling sandbags today on an earthwork dam -- but it was already leaking.</p>
        <p>The water level in Dresden finally began to drop from its record depth of 30.84 feet, but only by less than half an inch. But other less notable German towns were bracing for what is being called ''the battle against the water,'' and 30,000 people living along the Elbe and its bloated tributaries have been evacuated so far.</p>
        <p>Emergency workers from Hesse -- young people who chose to do nonmilitary duty when drafted -- were doing a lot of the heavy work, alongside local teenagers and housewives. They labored at a U-shaped bend of the Elbe, where the water comes closest to this town, famous for the Bauhaus, the modern design school founded by Walter Gropius.</p>
        <p>Two of the airy, geometric houses Gropius built for himself and other professors in 1926 are not far away. Nor is the water.</p>
        <p>Manuel Fehl, 21, got here with the emergency team on Thursday night and worked for 36 straight hours, before getting some sleep last night on a school floor. ''It's important for the country,'' he said, with a trace of embarrassment. ''When you see the commitment of the local people, it's impressive.''</p>
        <p>But Martina Römpp, who owns 10 clothing shops in the area, is not optimistic that the river can be held. ''We live close by, where the warehouse is, and if the dam breaks we'll lose everything,'' she said, holding her two sons, 4 and 2.</p>
        <p>''No one really tells us anything about when the water will come,'' she said, but she has her car packed, ready to evacuate. ''With two kids, it will be too dangerous to stay,'' with no electricity, the water so high and the nearby sewage plant in danger. ''If something breaks here,'' she said, the Elbe combining with the smaller Mulde River, ''it's all over Dessau.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Römpp, 34, is one of the many Germans who believe that the flood is a result of environmental changes stemming from greenhouse gases. ''It's our new war,'' she said. ''We will have more of these floods from the heating of the planet.''</p>
        <p>The German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, in a tough battle for re-election, said proudly today that his government, in coalition with the environmentally friendly Greens, had reduced Germany's output of carbon dioxide by half in the last four years. Unfortunately for his chances, he has not been so successful in reducing unemployment.</p>
        <p>But politics were far from the mind of Peter Häselbarth, 45, who stood with his son, Jens, 19, and his badger, Sigi, 3, on his flooded street in Bitterfeld, 30 miles south of Dessau on the Mulde River.</p>
        <p>The water moved down Friedenstrasse, the main street, about 10 yards every 15 minutes, soaking into basements and yards. Rescue workers were using boats to move around the town.</p>
        <p>The town was once considered the environmental black hole of East Germany, a chemical center where a yellow haze hovered endlessly. Much has been done to clean it up, but still the water on Friedenstrasse had an oily stink, and emergency workers were toiling to protect the chemical plants in the town from the Mulde.</p>
        <p>Mr. Häselbarth was evacuated late Thursday night, leaving some of his other animals behind, including a pond full of fish. ''We were told we were in danger but it was too early,'' he said, so he returned today to gather more belongings, bring them up to the roof and feed the other animals. As for his fish, he said, ''maybe we'll find them in the garden when we come back again.'' But that is not likely to be for some time.</p>
        <p>An estimated 12 Germans have died in the flooding, along with 13 Czechs and about 60 people in Austria and Russia. But by comparison, more than 900 people died in the same period from seasonal floods in India and Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere upriver, workers gave up on the pretty town of Mühlberg, which was inundated when waters of the Elbe rose over a 33-foot dam. Even the local flood emergency committee had to be evacuated to higher ground in Torgau, where the Soviet Army met the American Army at the Elbe on April 25, 1945. More than 8,000 people were evacuated from around Torgau.</p>
        <p>Also upriver, an important railway bridge at Riesa broke, cutting train traffic between Berlin and Leipzig. Dresden, however, appeared to have emerged without severe damage to its cultural treasures, like the Zwinger Palace and the Semper Opera, where the basements and courtyards flooded. Further downriver, residents in Magdeburg, the next major city on the Elbe's path to the North Sea, were advised to prepare to leave.</p>
        <p>After the reunification of Germany, millions were spent rebuilding the eastern parts of the country. Mr. Schröder said the rebuilding now would have to begin again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schröder has already promised hundreds of millions of euros in aid to affected German towns; Edmund Stoiber, his political opponent, called today for a fund of 2 billion euros, nearly $2 billion. In the meantime, the Swiss donated 500,000 sacks of sand, while NATO promised aid.</p>
        <p>But for Bianca Füller, 10, and Denis Röse, 9, skipping down the street in front of the Bauhaus, the floods have meant no school since Thursday.</p>
        <p>Are they afraid? ''No,'' Bianca said. ''I live on the second floor. I'll just go home.'' Denis, not to be outdone by an older girl, said: ''I live on the third floor -- that's best.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
