<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4D6153CF937A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>North Korea Reopens Plant To Revive Nuclear Program  North Korea started to reopen a sealed plutonium reprocessing plant, the most provocative and technically important step it has taken in recent days to revive a nuclear program that experts said could produce weapons within months.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraqi Pep Rally for Kurds  The Iraqi government unleashed a salvo in the struggle for the hearts and minds of its Kurdish citizens, gathering hundreds of Muslim clerics in Kirkuk, a northern provincial capital, to issue a religious decree saying it was time to fight the Americans even as they prepare for war.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>North Korea Reopens Plant To Revive Nuclear Program  North Korea started to reopen a sealed plutonium reprocessing plant, the most provocative and technically important step it has taken in recent days to revive a nuclear program that experts said could produce weapons within months.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraqi Pep Rally for Kurds  The Iraqi government unleashed a salvo in the struggle for the hearts and minds of its Kurdish citizens, gathering hundreds of Muslim clerics in Kirkuk, a northern provincial capital, to issue a religious decree saying it was time to fight the Americans even as they prepare for war.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Iraqi warplanes shot down an unmanned Predator aircraft as it conducted a surveillance mission about 100 miles southeast of Baghdad, Defense Department and military officials said.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>U.S. Focuses on Hezbollah  Senior American officials have singled out Hezbollah as the ''A-Team'' of terrorism, more menacing than Al Qaeda. Senator Bob Graham, the chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee, suggested that Hezbollah be dealt with before Baghdad because it was the most dangerous terrorist organization on earth.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cambodian Sentenced  A former Khmer Rouge officer, Sam Bith, was convicted and sentenced to life in prison for the killings of three foreign backpackers in 1994. His conviction highlighted the failure of Cambodia to try any Khmer Rouge leaders for the deaths of more than one million people when they ruled the country from 1975 to 1979.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Plane Crash in Iran Kills 46  A Ukrainian plane carrying aeronautical experts crashed in central Iran, killing all 46 people on board. The senior Russian and Ukrainian officials were traveling to Iran for a test-flight of a plane that is being built jointly by the two countries, with assembly in Iran.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-21</p>
        <p>Republican Senators Elect Frist New Majority Leader  Bill Frist of Tennessee was unanimously elected the Republican leader of the Senate, urged by his colleagues to remake the reputation of a party that many felt had been seriously damaged by the comments of the man he replaces, Trent Lott.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats say that the replacement of Trent Lott complicates their task of taking advantage of the racial furor sparked by Mr. Lott as they try to reassert themselves in a town dominated by Republicans.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Tip Leads to Terrorism Charge  Federal agents have arrested a Yemeni man who has lived in Detroit for several years, following a tip that he was a member of Al Qaeda and planning a terror attack in Michigan. Officials played down the seriousness of the arrest.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Cities Join Environmental Suit  Oakland, Calif., and Boulder, Colo., have voted to join Greenpeace in a lawsuit charging two federal agencies with failing to conduct environmental reviews before financing projects that contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Los Angeles Liable for Spills  A federal judge in Los Angeles found the city in violation of the federal Clean Water Act, holding it liable for 297 sewage spills between January 2001 and July 2002.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Church Asks Dismissal of Suits  The Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Boston asked a judge to dismiss all of the sexual abuse lawsuits against it on religious freedom grounds. It argued that the First Amendment does not permit courts to tell churches how to conduct internal affairs.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Debate Over Heavy Book Bags  Facing an outcry from thousands of parents, school boards and state legislatures have focused America's educational debate on weight: why student's book bags have gotten so heavy, and how to lighten them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Temporary Homeless Plan In Place, and Expanding  A city program that was meant to temporarily house homeless families in individual apartments across the city, conceived as an unwanted but necessary emergency answer two years ago, has ballooned to involve more than 2,000 apartments that now accommodate roughly a quarter of the city's population of homeless families.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Homecoming at Ground Zero  The Christmas lights twinkle in the windows of her apartment at 125 Cedar Street. Elena del Rivero strung them up a couple of weeks ago in her eighth-floor loft overlooking ground zero. After 15 months, it is finally time to return to 125 Cedar Street, to live day to day in a neighborhood at once strange and familiar, to return to the building she and her fellow tenants fled after the terrorist attack on the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-16</p>
        <p>Las Vegas Guggenheim Closes  The Guggenheim Las Vegas, an exhibition hall that opened just 15 months ago, will go dark on Jan. 5 for an indefinite period while the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum in New York looks for a sponsor for the hall's next exhibition.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6-7</p>
        <p>Joe Strummer  A singer whose hoarse, bawling voice and choppy rhythm guitar were at the center of the Clash, he was 50.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>Injunction Against Microsoft  In a preliminary injunction requested by Sun Microsystems, a federal judge ruled that Microsoft must include Sun's Java programming language in the Windows operating system.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Some Leverage for United  A soft market in air travel is actually working in favor of United Airlines. The airline should be able to renegotiate the leases on its planes because, with 1,300 aircraft idled, the lessors do not want to repossess them.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Huge Write-Off for Bank  Citigroup will take a $1.5 billion after-tax charge in the fourth quarter to cover expected losses from a host of problems that have plagued the company this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>G.M. Embraces Hybrids  General Motors, long the most reticent major carmaker when it came to the prospects for hybrid vehicles, intends to offer some form of hybrid electric power on four of its major models over the next four years.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Mideast road map; Alaska's political dynasty; renewing ''Friends''; Francis X. Clines on welfare in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E12  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E16  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
