<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Will Needle Regulators Now That Enron's Muzzled?</title>
    <meta content="20DERE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/20/business/yourmoney/20DERE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1360912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Houston (Tex)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Enron Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Waxman, Henry A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DB163BF933A15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Will Needle Regulators Now That Enron's Muzzled?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who Will Needle Regulators Now That Enron's Muzzled?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Collapse of Enron Corp may deal setback to energy deregulation, which Enron lobbied for more aggressively than any of its competitors; deregulation of power industry has progressed far more slowly than Enron's vaunted influence would suggest, and one of its goals, open access to nation's transmission lines, remains stalled in many regions; questions about Enron's input on Bush administration's energy plan is also drawing Senate scrutiny; former federal regulators, lobbyists and executives of Enron's erstwhile competitors argue that Enron scandal was result not of deregulation, but of lax oversight, hubris and ambition; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DARTH VADER. That was what Enron's enemies called the company when its phalanxes of lobbyists swept through Washington and state capitals in the late 1990's, aggressively and meticulously arguing in favor of loosening the electricity industry from a century of government control.</p>
        <p>While other power companies fought deregulation as a threat to their very existence, Enron was quick to see the opportunities, and it devoted much money and labor to shaping the progress of changes on the federal and local levels. As deregulation moved ahead, Enron thrived, its core trading operations bloomed and it emerged as perhaps the most important company in the energy industry before suddenly collapsing into bankruptcy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As deregulation moved ahead, Enron thrived. Now that Enron has been silenced, what's next on the energy deregulation front?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DARTH VADER. That was what Enron's enemies called the company when its phalanxes of lobbyists swept through Washington and state capitals in the late 1990's, aggressively and meticulously arguing in favor of loosening the electricity industry from a century of government control.</p>
        <p>While other power companies fought deregulation as a threat to their very existence, Enron was quick to see the opportunities, and it devoted much money and labor to shaping the progress of changes on the federal and local levels. As deregulation moved ahead, Enron thrived, its core trading operations bloomed and it emerged as perhaps the most important company in the energy industry before suddenly collapsing into bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Now that Enron has been silenced, what's next on the energy deregulation front? The debacle in California that resulted in wide power shortages and a utility bankruptcy fanned powerful doubts about the necessity of tinkering with a system that delivers something as vital as electricity. Enron's collapse has set off murmurs on Capitol Hill, in the news media and among industry opponents of deregulation that the nationwide experiment was the cause of a financial scandal that becomes seamier by the day.</p>
        <p>Whether that will lead politicians or regulatory agencies to rein in deregulation will become evident in the coming weeks and months, as the House of Representatives discusses an electricity restructuring bill and as the Senate takes up its energy bill.</p>
        <p>''The feeling among a lot of energy companies is, 'Boy, Enron was working really hard to open up this market, and who will do this now?' '' said Jeff Keeler, a former lobbyist for Enron who now works as a consultant to energy concerns. ''Enron carried a lot of the water, and because it was out front, took a lot of the blows.''</p>
        <p>In fact, for all the self-generated hype about its influence, for all the envy of competitors and detractors, Enron, it turns out, failed to score many victories. The reinvention of the power industry has progressed far more slowly and has many more regulatory constraints than the company would have wanted. One of its goals, open access to the nation's transmission lines, is stalled in many regions.</p>
        <p>Questions have already arisen about Enron's involvement in deregulation, climate-change policy and the Bush administration's energy plan. Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat, is circulating a list of 18 items in the Bush energy policy, which was released in May, that he says have Enron's fingerprints on them. He and other members of Congress have petitioned the White House for transcripts of meetings between Vice President Dick Cheney and Enron's chairman, Kenneth L. Lay, about energy policy. The last meeting occurred just days before the Enron bubble burst. So far, the requests have been rebuffed. The General Accounting Office is considering suing the administration to force it to release the transcripts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman and another Democrat, Edward J. Markey of Massachusetts, both on the House Energy Committee, are also asking that a pending bill on electricity restructuring be delayed while Congress examines whether deregulation helped bring about the Enron fiasco.</p>
        <p>Curtis L. Hébert Jr., a former chairman of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission who is now a vice president at the Entergy Corporation, a power company in New Orleans, said: ''I think you're going to see with Enron some of the same mind-set as with the price spikes in California. You'll see a much more methodical and reasonable approach to deregulation.''</p>
        <p>IN the deregulation debate, though, one man's reasonable approach is another's morass. Entergy and the Southern Company, based in Atlanta, have resisted deregulation in their regions mainly because they wanted to hold on to their monopoly status, other power company officials and regulators said. Many industry experts say Enron's downfall tips the balance in the national debate over deregulation toward companies like Entergy and Southern, which was the second-largest contributor, after Enron, to the Republican Party in 2000.</p>
        <p>Southern's position against legislation addressing global warming may also be strengthened by Enron's demise, according to Mr. Keeler and lobbyists for other power companies. Enron backed policies that would have limited power plants' emissions of pollutants and gases thought to be linked to global warming. Enron stood to gain from such limits, because it could have developed instruments for swapping emissions credits.</p>
        <p>And because it owned natural-gas pipelines, Enron would have benefited from any push to build more power plants that used natural gas, which produces fewer emissions than coal. Opponents of emissions caps, who are rife in the domestic power industry, plan to paint any such legislation as the ''Enron bill,'' according to Inside EPA, a newsletter that monitors federal environmental policy.</p>
        <p>Former federal regulators, lobbyists and executives of Enron's erstwhile competitors argue that the Enron scandal was a result not of deregulation, but of lax oversight, hubris and ambition. ''This may not be intellectually defensible, but it's politically predictable,'' said Joe Bob Perkins, executive vice president for wholesale businesses at Reliant Energy, a power generation and trading company in Houston. ''I think it is a whole lot less likely that we will get a consensus on bills that could help deregulation.''</p>
        <p>The vast amount of work remaining on deregulation is perhaps the clearest proof that Enron's record in lobbying was mixed at best. ''I don't think it was that anything Enron wanted, they got,'' said James Hoecker, a former chairman of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.</p>
        <p>For almost 20 years, the federal government and many states with high electricity prices have been seeking to transform a power industry widely viewed as inefficient and plodding. Enron, when it was still only a natural-gas company, went through deregulation of the natural-gas industry in the 1980's, which gave it a sharper understanding than most utilities had of the issues involved in electricity restructuring. When power deregulation was being actively discussed on the state and federal levels in the mid-1990's, Enron accelerated the discussion and tried to shape it. The company has never shied away from spending whatever it took. In the first six months of 2001, Enron spent $825,000 lobbying Congress on a wide range of issues, according to a disclosure report Enron filed with Congress.</p>
        <p>Other industry lobbyists seldom met with Congressional staff members or, when they did, had little to offer but their insistence on things being done in a certain way, said one senior Congressional staff member who spoke on condition of anonymity. But Enron came in with clear, informative presentations that had a logic to them. Their experts were on hand to answer complex questions, and they followed up on requests for more information. ''Enron was very good at getting people to talk about certain things,'' the Congressional aide said. ''They were very substantive and they were assertive.''</p>
        <p>Yet Enron's success dwindled with time, partly because the company was no longer the loudest in the small chorus extolling deregulation. Competitors envied Enron's head-start and derided its know-it-all arrogance. But they soon began to emulate its sophisticated energy trading and marketing businesses. As a result, a number of companies, including Calpine, Duke Energy, Dynegy, Reliant and Williams, emerged with the money and political heft to push for deregulation.</p>
        <p>''A lot of Enron's influence had already passed even before the scandal,'' said Mary Doyle Kenkel, a Washington lobbyist for the Cinergy Corporation. ''They hadn't been as vocal or in your face in the last couple of years.''</p>
        <p>Enron wanted Congress to adopt legislation that would quicken the pace of deregulation. Yet such legislation has languished for six or seven years, and seems unlikely to pass this year. The company pushed hard for the Bush administration to include a provision in its national energy plan saying the federal government would exercise eminent domain, or seize private and state lands, to build more power lines and beef up the transmission grid. Such new transmission projects would have brought down the price of power and made it easier for Enron to compete with local utilities. But the administration, after initially arguing for such a change, backed down in the face of opposition from Western states.</p>
        <p>Enron wanted the Bush administration to adopt climate change policies. But the White House chose to ignore the issue, largely because of the arguments made by the coal industry and several utilities, led by Southern, according to power company lobbyists in Washington.</p>
        <p>Many industry observers have suggested that Enron scored a coup when President Bush appointed Pat Wood as chairman of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, succeeding Mr. Hébert. Mr. Wood ran the Public Utility Commission of Texas, and Enron endorsed his ascent. But Mr. Wood proved quickly that he had few ties to Enron. He has supported greater access to the electricity transmission grid, which Enron -- and many others -- also favored. But the effort at the commission to improve access to the network began long before he rose to the chairman's office.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Wood has taken steps that vexed Enron and other large power traders and marketers. In June, he voted to put in place a system in the Western states that prevented power prices from climbing sharply, a system that Enron and others contested. Later in the year, the commission proposed to eliminate any cap on refunds that power companies might be compelled to pay if there was evidence that they had rigged markets or gouged power buyers.</p>
        <p>''I guess a regulator who is doing his job is the one who has both sides mad at him,'' one power company executive said.</p>
        <p>ENRON'S true success may have been the ease with which it avoided scrutiny of securities regulators. The Securities and Exchange Commission paid scant attention to the partnerships that proved its undoing, mainly because Enron did not fit the definition of a traditional utility, industry experts said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, to many people, the company's collapse had little to do with electricity deregulation and more to do with how its innovation and novelty, its complex financial and information products, pushed it beyond the comprehension of regulators, analysts and shareholders.</p>
        <p>''I don't think this has anything to do with deregulation, because I didn't really see Enron as an energy company,'' said Mr. Hoecker, the former Federal Energy Regulatory Commission chairman. ''To me it was more of a dot-com, in that it was all about information, facilitating the trading of energy by others, and this was the last dot-com crash.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
