<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shark's Pearly Teeth Gnash Near 'The West Wing'</title>
    <meta content="23NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/23/arts/television/23NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20021024T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1434229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">West Wing, The (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Sorkin, Aaron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D9173CF930A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shark's Pearly Teeth Gnash Near 'The West Wing'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shark's Pearly Teeth Gnash Near 'The West Wing'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Caryn James</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James Critic's Notebook column on moment when television program West Wing jumped the shark; phrase refers to point at which series begins its downward slide; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it happened when Lily Tomlin turned up as the ditzy secretary to the President of the United States. Maybe it happened when Toby Ziegler, the communications director, lectured the president -- in Toby's increasingly pompous way -- about how he has to stop trying to prove himself to his long-dead father. Maybe it happened over the summer when nobody was looking, but it happened: ''The West Wing'' jumped the shark.</p>
        <p>An inspired phrase, ''jump the shark'' refers to the point at which a television series begins its downward slide. (The term comes from the moment in the aging ''Happy Days'' when Fonzie waterskied over a shark. Television viewers weigh in on those tragic leaps on the Web site www.jumptheshark.com and can even read a ''Jump the Shark'' book by the site's creator, Jon Hein, but neither form is as delicious as the concept itself.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first four episodes of "The West Wing" this fall have been contrived and dull  a startling tumble from the show's gripping, sophisticated heights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it happened when Lily Tomlin turned up as the ditzy secretary to the President of the United States. Maybe it happened when Toby Ziegler, the communications director, lectured the president -- in Toby's increasingly pompous way -- about how he has to stop trying to prove himself to his long-dead father. Maybe it happened over the summer when nobody was looking, but it happened: ''The West Wing'' jumped the shark.</p>
        <p>An inspired phrase, ''jump the shark'' refers to the point at which a television series begins its downward slide. (The term comes from the moment in the aging ''Happy Days'' when Fonzie waterskied over a shark. Television viewers weigh in on those tragic leaps on the Web site www.jumptheshark.com and can even read a ''Jump the Shark'' book by the site's creator, Jon Hein, but neither form is as delicious as the concept itself.)</p>
        <p>The words shark and ''West Wing'' shouldn't be turning up in the same sentence yet. But the first four episodes this fall have been contrived and dull -- a startling tumble from the show's gripping, sophisticated heights. The change was abrupt. This summer, when Rob Lowe announced he was leaving the series, it seemed like a foolish move; now it looks prescient.</p>
        <p>After three seasons any show's novelty begins to wear off, of course. And as news stories have indicated, the ''West Wing'' ratings have been hurt by competition from series that are younger, hipper and guaranteed not to make your head hurt, like ''Birds of Prey,'' with its comic-book-inspired superheroines, and the matchmaking reality game ''The Bachelor.'' (O.K., ''The Bachelor'' will give you a headache, but only if you actually try to connect it to reality.) But those are minor factors.</p>
        <p>The real problem is that Aaron Sorkin, who created and still writes ''The West Wing,'' has turned to desperate plot twists and preachier-than-ever dialogue this season. And the weak writing has been compounded by a trickier issue: as the show has tried to adapt to changes in the world around it, it has given us a fictional president who walks like a Clinton and talks like a Bush. The show's downward slide raises the question of the longevity of smart network series: do they have a shorter life span, when they get a chance to live at all?</p>
        <p>Although the decline of ''The West Wing'' seems to have happened behind our backs, the seeds were there last season when Ms. Tomlin's character, Debbie Federer, first appeared. She is so flaky that she once ran an alpaca farm. This season she told the president she was high when she first met him, and made a satiric point on her background-check questionnaire that involved harming him (you know how the Secret Service loves a good joke). She is one step away from the wacky next-door neighbor on a sitcom.</p>
        <p>This season, frantic scenes that seem intended to humanize the characters and get them out of their offices have only made them look silly. Toby (Richard Schiff) and Josh (Bradley Whitford), the assistant chief of staff, and Josh's assistant, Donna (Janel Moloney), were left behind when the presidential motorcade left a rally in the Midwest; they hitched rides, got on a train, and missed a plane home because they forgot they'd crossed a time zone. The next week the entire staff turned up at a Rock the Vote rally. Last week a flashback to the early days of the administration revealed that the press secretary, C. J. (Allison Janney), had a really bad perm.</p>
        <p>Worst of all, this season's dialogue has taken its cue not from the best the series has offered, but from its worst episode, last year's misguided season opener that acknowledged the terror attacks by locking the staffers in the White House with a class of visiting students. That gave Mr. Sorkin an excuse to preach at viewers about terrorism and racial profiling, but what's his excuse now?</p>
        <p>Toby has become the main offender. He is the voice and the conscience we are meant to respect for his uncompromising idealism, but Mr. Schiff's overwrought performance makes the character off-putting. When Senator Ritchie, the fictional President Bartlet's Republican opponent in the next election, announces that he is against needle exchange to prevent the spread of H.I.V., Toby sits at a staff meeting and in a hectoring tone tells his colleagues and the president, but mainly the television audience: ''I'd like someone to ask Ritchie if he's aware that needle exchange costs $9,000 for every infection stopped. Treating someone with H.I.V. costs $200,000. I'd like someone to ask him that.'' In a litany of clunky writing he continues this harangue as the staff walks out of the meeting, until C. J. asks, ''Is there any chance I'm going to get an opportunity to speak in this conversation?'' Toby's repetitious speech isn't poetry; it's bombast and it's wearing. Letting C. J. realize that the scene is talky doesn't change that.</p>
        <p>Martin Sheen, as President Bartlet, once had the role of the pure conscience. The character and Mr. Sheen's performance have grown far richer and more fascinating as Bartlet has displayed more flaws. He failed to tell the country he has multiple sclerosis. He ordered the assassination of the leader of Qumar, the fictional country that is the show's villain in the Middle East, and the repercussions have led to this season's most intriguing and underused plot. (Tonight, in a repeat from last season, C. J. is upset because the United States may lease an air base to Qumar, which has a lousy record on women's rights; the episode is a reminder that Mr. Sorkin is able to balance preachiness and drama.)</p>
        <p>Now the president and the series are caught in a head-spinning identity crisis. Bartlet, who arrived as a Clintonlike Democrat, still has such liberal social ideals that he recently became indignant about the country's poor record on greenhouse emissions. Yet more and more his rhetoric echoes that of the Bush administration's war on terror.</p>
        <p>On ''The West Wing,'' two pipe bombs are set off at a university in Iowa -- a fiction that effectively evokes reality without creating stiff parallels. In reaction, at a White House dinner dramatically lighted with candles, Bartlet delivers an eloquent speech that resonates with the language of real events and fears. ''We did not seek nor did we provoke an assault on our freedom and our way of life; we did not expect nor did we invite a confrontation with evil,'' he says. (If any word is associated with the Bush administration's war on terror, it's ''evil.'') ''The streets of heaven are too crowded with angels tonight. . . . This is a time for American heroes.''</p>
        <p>During the Clinton years, Bartlet functioned as an idealized version of the real president. For much of last season, he occupied an alternate universe, a contrast to the Bush White House. But Mr. Sorkin can't have it both ways. As the echoes of reality have become stronger on the show, its vision of Bartlet has become disorienting.</p>
        <p>''The West Wing'' is still one of best shows on television, but that's beside the point. It doesn't matter that a show that was once so sharp and realistic is better than a lame sitcom like ''Yes, Dear'' or a mediocrity like ''Jag.'' Mr. Sorkin cultivated a smart, thoughtful audience. Now he can't get away with insulting his viewers' intelligence by offering the ditzy secretary, the preachy communications director and the Jeckyll/Hyde presidency.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK  Correction:  October 24, 2002, Thursday  A Critic's Notebook column in The Arts yesterday about the ''West Wing'' television series misspelled the fictional reference in a characterization of the presidency portrayed on the show. Robert Louis Stevenson's characters are Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, not Jeckyll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 24, 2002, Thursday</p>
        <p>A Critic's Notebook column in The Arts yesterday about the ''West Wing'' television series misspelled the fictional reference in a characterization of the presidency portrayed on the show. Robert Louis Stevenson's characters are Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde, not Jeckyll.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
