<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Alaskan Hot Spot, Even at 50 Below Zero</title>
    <meta content="Y04ALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/04/national/04ALAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1372854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aurora Borealis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hot Springs</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska (USA)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7D61F31F937A35750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Alaskan Hot Spot, Even at 50 Below Zero</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">An Alaskan Hot Spot, Even at 50 Below Zero</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>CHENA HOT SPRINGS, Alaska, Feb. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alaska is luring vacationers in winter to view northern lights; many wintertime visitors are from Japan, where aurora borealis seems to exert almost mystical pull and where many newlyweds consider viewing of lights to be height of romance and auspicious sign for marriage; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Haruna and Taketoshi Harada thought about honeymooning in Paris. They considered Hawaii. But in the end, they journeyed here, to a frigid mountaintop near the Arctic Circle in Alaska, where they nuzzled at 2 o'clock the other morning while gazing at the starry dome of the sky. They were not disappointed.</p>
        <p>''It's like a curtain of colors, dancing across the sky,'' Mr. Harada said of the northern lights. ''Very vibrant,'' Mrs. Harada said. ''Very beautiful.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many Japanese newlyweds, a visit to Alaska in winter is the height of romance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Haruna and Taketoshi Harada thought about honeymooning in Paris. They considered Hawaii. But in the end, they journeyed here, to a frigid mountaintop near the Arctic Circle in Alaska, where they nuzzled at 2 o'clock the other morning while gazing at the starry dome of the sky. They were not disappointed.</p>
        <p>''It's like a curtain of colors, dancing across the sky,'' Mr. Harada said of the northern lights. ''Very vibrant,'' Mrs. Harada said. ''Very beautiful.''</p>
        <p>That same elation struck several other visitors to the mountain, 60 miles east of Fairbanks, despite temperatures well below zero. Kazuhiro Omura, a young medical student from Tokyo, was so happy when the ghostly green lights suddenly appeared and danced above him that he rolled in the snow, laughing. Then he lay on his back and watched the show, proclaiming in Japanese how beautiful it was.</p>
        <p>Having long marketed itself as a prime destination for summer tourists, Alaska has been surprisingly successful in recent years luring vacationers in winter as well, many of them from Japan, where the aurora borealis seems to exert an almost mystical pull and where many newlyweds consider a viewing of the lights to be the height of romance and an auspicious sign for a marriage.</p>
        <p>The area in and around Fairbanks is recognized as one of the best places on earth to see the shimmering lights. With a variety of other winter activities, including dog-mushing schools and the annual World Ice Art Championships, which begins on Tuesday in Fairbanks, the city has billed itself as a must-see at this time of year, despite the often biting cold.</p>
        <p>''Our line on that is, 'Yes, but it's a dry cold,' '' said Karen Lundquist, communications manager for the Fairbanks Convention and Visitors Bureau. ''But it is cold. It's hard, when it's 50 below, to say that it's not cold. I don't know how you get around that.''</p>
        <p>Actually, despite Fairbanks's slogan -- ''Winter: Always Guaranteed!'' -- Alaska has been subject to the same moderation of normal temperatures that much of the Northeast has experienced this year. Night temperatures here in recent weeks have reached a positively balmy zero degrees.</p>
        <p>Many Alaskans are not celebrating: they like it as cold as possible in the winter, and increasing temperatures have set off a wave of alarm about rising sea levels that could threaten coastal villages and thawing in the permafrost that could wreak havoc with roads and even huge structures like the trans-Alaska pipeline.</p>
        <p>For now, though, the visitors are coming, and no place is more popular with Japanese tourists than Chena Hot Springs, a remote old lodge reachable on a paved road from Fairbanks.</p>
        <p>For the Japanese in particular, the Alaskan wilderness seems to offer a temporary escape pod.</p>
        <p>''I love Tokyo, but in Tokyo you cannot feel nature, there are so many artificial things,'' said Mr. Omura, 22, who traveled here during his winter break with two fellow students from Jikei University, Kentaro Yamakawa and Eriko Kamada, and spent each of the last five nights searching the night skies for the northern lights.</p>
        <p>Miss Kamada said, ''Here, it is just so silent.''</p>
        <p>Despite the downturn in the Japanese economy, bookings are strong at the Chena Hot Springs Resort, with about 3,500 Japanese expected to visit this winter, said Joe Juszkiewicz, the general manager, who has hired three Japanese-speaking guides, as well as a dog-mushing instructor and marketing director who are also fluent in the language. Alaska can be reached relatively cheaply via a Korean Air Lines flight through Seoul that connects to Anchorage.</p>
        <p>At the resort, February and March are actually considered the ''high season,'' even busier than July and August, although that is still highly unusual for any tourism-related concern in Alaska. Certainly, the number of summer vacationers here, which the state's Department of Community and Economic Development estimates to be about 900,000, dwarfs the winter counterparts.</p>
        <p>Yet the number of winter travelers who describe ''vacation and pleasure'' as their primary reason for coming has more than doubled in the state's surveys over the last decade, to 45,000 in 2000-2001 from 21,800 in 1990.</p>
        <p>State tourism officials and resorts have advertised intensively in Japan. The state has also sponsored an advertising campaign in the Southwest United States for an ''Alaska Winter White Sale,'' although officials concede that their mission can be a tough sell.</p>
        <p>One major draw is the sled dog racing, including the Yukon Quest and the Iditarod. Another, of course, is the northern lights, though Alaska competes with Canada, Greenland and Norway to entice visitors to come see them.</p>
        <p>The aurora, ribbons of moving, bright lights caused by charged solar particles that congregate through magnetic pull toward the earth's poles, is not a sure thing on any given night. Cloudy skies can obscure it for days on end. But in late February and March here, the odds are pretty good for a spectacular display.</p>
        <p>That happened here this evening, sending a dozen or so tourists charging out of a snow machine that brought them to a ridge high above Chena Hot Springs.</p>
        <p>Some couples wandered off to be alone. Masaaki Tsuruoka, an air-conditioning engineer from Tokyo, quickly went to work with his camera. A few tourists quickly made for a heated yurt and fortified themselves with hot cider and ramen noodles. The three medical students from Tokyo just lay on the snow, looking up.</p>
        <p>''It is an amazing thing,'' said Kentaro Yamakawa, 23. ''Beautiful. Mysterious. I don't want it to stop.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
