<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Administration Suggests Faster Pace on Emission Worries</title>
    <meta content="Y04CLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/04/politics/04CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1445751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marburger, John H III</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDC173BF937A35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Administration Suggests Faster Pace on Emission Worries</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Administration Suggests Faster Pace on Emission Worries</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration officials, criticized on response to global warming, say future scientific findings could speed consideration of more aggressive actions to rein in emissions of heat-trapping gases; adviser Dr John H Marburger III comments at White House meeting to devise research plan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing criticism over the pace and focus of the president's policy on global warming, Bush administration officials said today that future scientific findings could speed consideration of more aggressive actions to rein in emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>Last year, President Bush set a climate policy that until 2012 would rely on voluntary measures by industries to slow growth in emissions of carbon dioxide and the other heat-trapping gases. He said more research was needed to clarify the potential environmental risks of warming before stronger measures were taken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bush administration officials said that future scientific findings could speed consideration of more aggressive actions to rein in emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Facing criticism over the pace and focus of the president's policy on global warming, Bush administration officials said today that future scientific findings could speed consideration of more aggressive actions to rein in emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>Last year, President Bush set a climate policy that until 2012 would rely on voluntary measures by industries to slow growth in emissions of carbon dioxide and the other heat-trapping gases. He said more research was needed to clarify the potential environmental risks of warming before stronger measures were taken.</p>
        <p>The possibility that that pace could quicken was conveyed by White House officials on the first day of a three-day meeting convened by the administration to devise a research plan for clarifying climate hazards and devising technologies to end emissions of heat-trapping, or greenhouse, gases altogether.</p>
        <p>''I fully expect there will be findings in the climate and technology research initiatives that will affect policy before 2012,'' said Dr. John H. Marburger III, the assistant to the president for science and technology.</p>
        <p>''This administration is open to facts,'' Dr. Marburger said, ''and the better the scientific case is for doing something, the more likely there is to be policy changes. This is not an administration that shuts off its ears and its common sense. That's why we're doing this.''</p>
        <p>More than 1,200 officials, scientists, industry lobbyists, environmental campaigners and contractors eager for new contracts for satellites and sensors packed sessions on monitoring of oceans and air and refining computer simulations of those complicated realms.</p>
        <p>The administration has been increasingly criticized over its climate policy, even though Mr. Bush last year accepted findings by a panel of American experts that most of the global warming in recent decades had been caused by human activity.</p>
        <p>Almost all other industrialized countries are supporting a treaty, the Kyoto Protocol, that would require them to reduce gas emissions below 1990 levels by 2012. The treaty awaits ratification by Russia to take legal effect. Russian leaders have pledged to do so next year.</p>
        <p>One of several European environmental officials at today's meeting said the administration's targets for slowing the increase in emissions were ''timid'' compared with trends that were already sharply dipping emissions curves in Britain.</p>
        <p>In an address at the meeting, Dr. G. O. P. Obasi, secretary general of the World Meteorological Organization, welcomed further American research, but said action was also required to cut the risk of harm from warming, some of which was already becoming evident.</p>
        <p>''We should seek to improve our scientific knowledge of climate variability and change while at the same time striving to insure that the environmental and socioeconomic conditions of present and future generations are not put at serious risk,'' Dr. Obasi said.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats, among them Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, who has made Mr. Bush's environment and energy policies issues in his possible presidential campaign, characterized the meeting as a public relations ploy.</p>
        <p>''No one will mistake another administration dog-and-pony show for real leadership,'' Mr. Kerry said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marburger and top officials from the Energy and Commerce Departments said the United States retained the global lead, by far, in climate research and was committed to significantly slowing emissions rates in the short term and eliminating emissions in the long run.</p>
        <p>A final four-year research plan is to be issued in April.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
