<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Wider Atlantic: Europe Sees a Grotesque U.S.</title>
    <meta content="Y16NAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/16/international/europe/16NATO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1392675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Diplomatic Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Reykjavik (Iceland)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland/Reykjavik</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Powell, Colin L.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D71039F935A25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Wider Atlantic: Europe Sees a Grotesque U.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Wider Atlantic: Europe Sees a Grotesque U.S.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>REYKJAVIK, Iceland, May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Secretary of State Colin L Powell encounters grumbling from European allies about various American policies and actions at meeting of North Atlantic Treaty Orgn foreign ministers in Reykjavik, Iceland; much of back talk is just that, but there is also real and deep European concern about everything from sharp differences over social policy on various issues to Bush administration's insistence that it will pursue its own course in Iraq; Pentagon and vast military machine at its command tend to intimidate Europeans, and Defense Sec Donald H Rumsfeld's brisk presentation of war in Afghanistan has often antagonized Europeans who dwell on American bombing mistakes and victims; many diplomats praise Powell, who is administration's chief representative of softer-edged, multilateralist, talk-it-over side of American foreign policy, and who spends more time than most of his colleagues in Washington consulting, reassuring and working with allies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To travel on this side of the Atlantic with Secretary of State Colin L. Powell is to catch a brief glimpse of a parallel universe: the heedless, insular, bellicose, unilateralist America seen by many European eyes.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell came to a meeting of North Atlantic Treaty Organization foreign ministers here to press Europeans to modernize their military machinery and spend more on defense, and to celebrate a momentous reconciliation with Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To travel across the Atlantic with Secretary of State Colin L. Powell is to catch a brief glimpse of the unilateralist America seen by many European eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To travel on this side of the Atlantic with Secretary of State Colin L. Powell is to catch a brief glimpse of a parallel universe: the heedless, insular, bellicose, unilateralist America seen by many European eyes.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell came to a meeting of North Atlantic Treaty Organization foreign ministers here to press Europeans to modernize their military machinery and spend more on defense, and to celebrate a momentous reconciliation with Russia.</p>
        <p>But the air was full of continental back talk, particularly from the press, reflecting widespread skeptical attitudes in Europe toward the United States. One reporter asked the NATO secretary general, Lord Robertson, whether the alliance's warmer relations with Russia might be Europe's defense against Washington's inclination to bypass it and deal only with Moscow.</p>
        <p>A Russian reporter asked Secretary Powell why the United States had ''finally agreed'' to the arms control treaty, ''because, as we know, you don't like treaties.''</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell, who for months has found himself the frontline defender of American foreign policy to often-skeptical allies, suppressed a smile and insisted: ''We do like this treaty.''</p>
        <p>Much of the back talk is just that, of course. As Lord Robertson reminded his colleagues, NATO remains one of the most durable and powerful alliances in world military history.</p>
        <p>But the grumbling also reflects real and deep European concerns about everything from sharp differences over social policy on issues like gun control and abortion, to the administration's decision to withdraw from the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty and unsign the treaty establishing the International Criminal Court, and its insistence that it will pursue its own course in Iraq.</p>
        <p>The sensitivities are such that even the British foreign secretary, Jack Straw, the envoy of the United States' closest ally, insisted during a visit to Washington last week that he and Secretary Powell take a break just 15 minutes into their meeting, so they could appear together before television cameras in time for the live evening newscasts in Britain, American officials said.</p>
        <p>''I would not force too much on the theme of unilateralism, as if it is an obsession of the Europeans,'' one European diplomat said here. ''We know there is this overarching theme, but when you look at specific details, there is an answer for some of it.''</p>
        <p>For example, the diplomat noted, in March, French bombers participated with American troops in a major military operation in eastern Afghanistan. ''It's difficult to give an answer overall as to how Europe views American policy, because American policy is multi-faceted.''</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell is the chief representative of the softer-edged, multilaterialist, talk-it-over side of American foreign policy, and spends more time than most of his administration colleagues consulting, reassuring and working with allies.</p>
        <p>On the other side, in the European view, stand officials like Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, whose brisk presentation of the war in Afghanistan has often antagonized Europeans who dwell on American bombing mistakes and victims. In general, the Pentagon and the vast military machine at its command tend to intimidate Europeans.</p>
        <p>Many diplomats here praised the efforts of Secretary Powell, who himself told reporters during the flight to Iceland on Monday: ''This may sound self-serving, but I think we're in pretty good shape.'' He cited recent resolutions of Mideast impasses, at the Church of the Nativity in Bethlehem and in Ramallah, as cases where ''I have been in near-constant contact with my European colleagues.''</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell acknowledged European annoyance at Washington's move to unsign the treaty on the International Criminal Court -- annoyance enhanced by moves last week in Congress signaling even a readiness to send troops to protect Americans from the court.</p>
        <p>But Secretary Powell insisted: ''We have worked very, very hard to try to erase this view that we are unilateralist, just doing anything we please and we don't talk to our friends about it.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the president's schedule, he has had a steady stream of visitors coming into the Oval Office, going to Crawford, coming for working visits. And they are European visitors, African visitors, they are visitors from the Middle East, and I think the president has been deeply involved in consulting with our friends around the world.''</p>
        <p>Not all of Secretary Powell's administration colleagues are so diplomatic. They note that much of Europe's military is outmoded or incompatible with American forces, and are quick to recall the widespread European unease about President Reagan's aggressive posture against the former Soviet Union in the 1980's, a stance that succeeded so well it is now beyond debate.</p>
        <p>In a speech at the Brookings Institution in Washington last week, Mr. Straw offered some reasons for the differing world views. ''Americans, correctly and rightly, consider that it is they as Americans who created the modern world's greatest democracy,'' Mr. Straw said.</p>
        <p>But Europeans, he added, tend to see ''a U.S. born out of Europe, born from those with the courage, imagination, iconoclasm to break away from the straitjacket not just of poverty but of institutional and political constraints in Europe, to form what has long represented, in an almost idealized form, the best of European values and institutions.''</p>
        <p>As an example of ''what might have been,'' Mr. Straw said, ''the U.S. is a source of more absorbing fascination to Europeans than ever an individual European country could be to the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Another overriding reality is that Europe, the European Union notwithstanding, is not a single federalized entity like the United States. When Europe itself has been united around a particular issue, as it has recently on the Middle East, it has had some success in prodding Washington to listen to its views.</p>
        <p>Mr. Straw noted in his speech that European-American relations ''have long been replete with differences,'' and that neither side should worry that disputes over steel tariffs or climate change can affect ''the fundamentals of the relationship.''</p>
        <p>''We are,'' Mr. Straw said, ''mature enough to cope with dissent and debate.''</p>
        <p>Diplomatic Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
