<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; A Foul-Weather Bet Has a Following</title>
    <meta content="17COAL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/17/business/yourmoney/17COAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1368561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Peabody Energy Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arch Coal Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consol Energy Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Massey Energy Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fording Coal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Peabody Energy Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6D6123FF934A25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; A Foul-Weather Bet Has a Following</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Foul-Weather Bet Has a Following</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD SIMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simon, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares of coal producers like Peabody Energy, Arch Coal, Consol Energy, Massey Energy and Canada's Fording Inc are languishing well below their highs of last May, but some analysts and fund managers say investment in coal will be profitable over long term; they say regulatory climate in Washington has become more favorable to coal under Pres Bush; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COAL-MINING stocks are paying a price for their emergence from obscurity a year ago. They became an unlikely glamour sector during the harsh winter of 2001 and California's energy crisis, only to plummet when the weather improved and fears of imminent power shortages subsided.</p>
        <p>Yet even as stocks like Peabody Energy, Arch Coal, Consol Energy, Massey Energy and Canada's Fording Inc. languish well below their highs for the last year, some analysts and fund managers say investments in coal will be profitable over the long term.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as coal-mining stocks languish well below their highs for the last year, some say investments in coal will be profitable over the long term.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COAL-MINING stocks are paying a price for their emergence from obscurity a year ago. They became an unlikely glamour sector during the harsh winter of 2001 and California's energy crisis, only to plummet when the weather improved and fears of imminent power shortages subsided.</p>
        <p>Yet even as stocks like Peabody Energy, Arch Coal, Consol Energy, Massey Energy and Canada's Fording Inc. languish well below their highs for the last year, some analysts and fund managers say investments in coal will be profitable over the long term.</p>
        <p>''This may take a year or two to play out,'' said Scott Kuensell, managing director of Brandywine Asset Management in Wilmington, Del., which made its first foray into Arch Coal in 1999 and last year built up a 1.4 percent stake in Peabody, the nation's biggest coal producer. ''Even on reduced earnings estimates, coal stocks look cheap to us,'' Mr. Kuensell said. ''If you were taking your first look at coal today, you'd be quite interested.''</p>
        <p>Daniel A. Roling, an analyst who covers the sector at Merrill Lynch, has reiterated ''strong buy'' recommendations for Peabody, Consol and Arch in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Still, coal stocks have been on a roller-coaster ride. They reached a peak last May, then slid through the summer until fears of supply constraints bolstered the sector last fall. The mood has soured again since Massey Energy, the fifth-biggest producer, warned in early January that a combination of mild weather, softening steel demand and the general economic recession was hurting the coal market. Bad weather is good for coal because it increases electricity demand for a variety of uses, including lighting and  heating for offices and factories.</p>
        <p>Despite the midyear dip, coal stocks were among the best performers on the New York Stock Exchange in 2001, with the Dow Jones coal index still up 64 percent over all. But the stocks have retreated since Massey's profit warning. Peabody, which went public as the market crested last May, closed at $23.95 on Friday, down from a peak of $38.05, but still above its midsummer low of $22.20.</p>
        <p>''The outlook for coal is still very good,'' Mr. Roling said. ''Utilities are saying, 'We want to dispatch the lowest-cost electricity,' and that's coal.''</p>
        <p>Still, many critics say coal-fired power plants generate enormous environmental problems, including air pollution and acid rain. ''A lot of folks make the argument that the full cost of coal, in terms of the environment and health, is not being accounted for,'' said William Spratley, executive director of Green Energy Ohio, a nonprofit group based in Columbus, Ohio, that encourages greater use of renewable energy sources. ''Where the coal industry is vulnerable is on new environmental requirements.''</p>
        <p>THE United States produces about 1.1 billion tons of coal a year from 1,400 mines, mostly in Appalachia and in the Powder River Basin of Wyoming. About 92 percent of production is used for power generation. The remainder is metallurgical, or coking, coal used in making steel.</p>
        <p>Charles Linderman, director of energy policy at the Edison Electric Institute, which represents the power generation industry, said the relative stability of the coal market, compared with other energy sources, especially natural gas, meant that ''a number of us view the future of coal differently from its past.''</p>
        <p>The California energy crisis and the surge in natural gas prices in early 2001 underscored the two biggest advantages of coal -- a relatively stable price and security of supply.</p>
        <p>The coal and electric utility industries say a cheaper fuel for large-scale power generation has yet to be found, and coal reserves in the United States are strong.</p>
        <p>''You could triple the price of coal and not price it out of the market,'' Mr. Roling said. While fears of energy shortages lifted the price of coal last year, it moved far less than the price of natural gas.</p>
        <p>During most of the 1990's, low prices and tightening environmental controls discouraged investment in new coal mines in the United States, especially in central Appalachia. The long decline of the eastern coal fields also led many miners to leave the industry.</p>
        <p>Coal's share of the power generation market has changed little in recent years, standing at about 51 to 52 percent. But nuclear plants, which account for about 20 percent of power generation in the United States, are operating close to capacity, and the prospect of new ones starting soon is remote.</p>
        <p>Natural gas units, which are relatively clean, have become popular in recent years. But gas plants are expensive to build and operate, and are relatively small, compared with coal and nuclear power stations.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Linderman, gas plants are used mainly to meet peak demand, leaving coal and nuclear power stations to do the heavy lifting of day-to-day supply. A typical coal plant generates 800 to 1,200 megawatts of electricity. The biggest gas-fired power stations have a capacity of about 750 megawatts.</p>
        <p>The regulatory climate in Washington has become more favorable to coal under President Bush, given a new emphasis on American self-sufficiency in energy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan to combat global warming, unveiled this week, avoided mandatory targets to reduce carbon dioxide emissions from power plants and other industries. Instead, Mr. Bush called for voluntary reductions. Jennifer Morgan of the World Wildlife Fund called the plan ''a valentine to the coal and oil industry.''</p>
        <p>Top federal regulators recently recommended informally that the White House relax regulations that require power plants to install new pollution control equipment when they upgrade operations. Coal and other energy producers say the rules impose billions of dollars in extra costs that block utilities from modernizing plants to make them more energy efficient.</p>
        <p>''There is a sense that this administration is not anticoal, and this has encouraged some utilities to look at new coal plants,'' said Forrest Hill of Hill &amp; Associates, a consulting firm in Annapolis, Md.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spratley at Green Energy Ohio sees a combination of natural gas, renewable energy and coal filling future needs, including any shortfall caused by the decommissioning of nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>Many coal mines capitalized on the energy scare last year by locking in a big portion of future production at high prices. Peabody has already sold 93 percent of its planned 2002 output and 66 percent of 2003 production. Massey, which has similar commitments from its customers, has predicted an average sales price of $31.50 to $32 a ton in 2002, up from $28 last year.</p>
        <p>WITH these contracts already factored into share prices and spot prices still sliding, some investors see little to excite them for now. ''Demand is down, inventories are up,'' said David Beard a New York hedge fund manager, who rode the coal wave last year by buying not only Arch and Massey, but also stocks of mining machinery, construction and railroad companies that stood to benefit from the coal renaissance. ''The fundamentals are not that great.'' He sold his holdings in Arch and Massey last year after they reached his price targets.</p>
        <p>Some investors are looking further ahead. ''At this level, the valuations are really compelling,'' said Barnett Osman, a principal at Lexington Partners, a private equity fund manager and Peabody's biggest single shareholder, with a 6.7 percent stake. Lexington invested $50 million in Peabody in 1998; the stake's value is up 65 percent.</p>
        <p>Normally, it would have taken its profits shortly after Peabody went public. But Mr. Osman sees Peabody's stock rising to $35 to $40, at least $11 above its current level. ''I don't see a lot of downside risk,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
