<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1410278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D91738F931A15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Iran Link and a Cover-Up Charged in 1994 Bombing  A witness in the case involving the bombing of the Argentine Jewish Mutual Aid Association in 1994 has said the Iranian government organized and carried out the attack and then paid Argentina's president at the time, Carlos Saúl Menem, $10 million to cover it up.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Americans Shun Overseas Jobs  The State Department is having difficulty filling hardship posts overseas, as Americans shun jobs over security and lifestyle concerns. Sixty percent of American embassies and consulates are designated hardship posts for reasons ranging from security threats to poor hospitals to oppressive weather, and those missions report a vacancy rate 50 percent higher than in richer nations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Iran Link and a Cover-Up Charged in 1994 Bombing  A witness in the case involving the bombing of the Argentine Jewish Mutual Aid Association in 1994 has said the Iranian government organized and carried out the attack and then paid Argentina's president at the time, Carlos Saúl Menem, $10 million to cover it up.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Americans Shun Overseas Jobs  The State Department is having difficulty filling hardship posts overseas, as Americans shun jobs over security and lifestyle concerns. Sixty percent of American embassies and consulates are designated hardship posts for reasons ranging from security threats to poor hospitals to oppressive weather, and those missions report a vacancy rate 50 percent higher than in richer nations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israel Backs Off Deportations  Israel appears to be backing off from its plan to deport relatives of West Bank Palestinians accused of suicide bombings to the Gaza Strip. Prime Minister Ariel Sharon said the government would abide by the legal finding that only relatives found to be directly involved in supporting suicide bombers could be deported.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Turkey Warns Against Iraq War  Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit of Turkey warned that President Saddam Hussein of Iraq has the capability to put up a long fight. Turkey, a NATO ally whose support would be vital in any operation in Iraq, opposes American military intervention there.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>U.N. Anti-Tobacco Plan  The World Health Organization has drawn up a treaty that would phase in bans on cigarette advertising and sports sponsorships by tobacco companies. The United Nations agency's member countries have been negotiating for two years to arrive at the pact by a May 2003 deadline.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Suspects Arrested in Greece  Two more suspects were charged with involvement in the string of attacks since 1975 by Greece's November 17 urban guerrilla group, including the killing of an American Air Force sergeant and a British brigadier.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>The View From the Vatican  Pope John Paul II will visit Canada for the Roman Catholic Church's World Youth Day. He has no plans to stop in the United States and address the concerns about sexual abuse by priests. To some American Catholics, that is bitterly disappointing and confusing.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Sri Lanka to Seek Support  Prime Minister Ranil Wickremesinghe of Sri Lanka said the new awareness that the American-led campaign against terrorism has brought worldwide and new resolve in his own country may help end the civil war. Mr. Wickremesinghe said he would ask the Bush administration to consider an agreement to help rebuild the country's economy.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-14</p>
        <p>Plan for Security Agency Enters the Details Phase  The drive to create a Homeland Security Department is racing quickly through the legislative process. The bill closely mirrors President Bush's original proposal to merge 22 federal agencies into a single department. Now the most contentious issues will come to the forefront.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>An Ideological Battle  President Bush wants to fill a federal appeals court seat with Priscilla Owen, a conservative judge from Texas with a strong record of opposing abortion rights. Senate Democrats and their liberal allies are certain to challenge Justice Owen's nomination, the latest in the continuing battles between Mr. Bush and the Democrats over the ideological shape of the federal courts.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Priests and Religious Orders  Leaders of the nation's 125 Roman Catholic religious orders will meet next month and confront the issue of what to do with sexually abusive priests who belong to religious orders, like the Jesuits, Franciscans and Benedictines.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>More Money for Superfund  The Environmental Protection Agency has restored money to clean up 11 toxic dump sites under its Superfund program, after having previously told local officials that they would not receive any money this year, agency officials said. Still, many other sites may not receive money that regional officials have requested.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>A Town and Its Meatpacker  A series of problems, including a huge recall, E. coli fears and a slumping stock price, are raising questions over what the future holds for ConAgra Beef Company and for residents of Greeley, Colo.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>African-American Museum  Organizers say a proposal for a comprehensive African-American museum on the Mall in Washington is closer to reality after 12 years of legislative setbacks.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Fund-Raising Frenzy  Politicians like Representative Richard A. Gephardt, Democrat of Missouri, continue to rely on the corporate sector as a steady source of campaign cash even as both major parties jockey for supremacy on the subject of who is going to overhaul Wall Street.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Child Care Gap  A new study says only one in seven parents is able to find a preschool or center-based care in California, even though spending for child care in the state has nearly quadrupled to $12 billion since 1996.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Tire Safety Concerns  Tire makers want the federal government to revisit a rule that requires tire-pressure warning lights in some new vehicles. The makers say the lights might fail to provide adequate warnings even when tire pressure is dangerously low.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Weekday Test Begins For Strained Power Grid  City officials are urging Con Ed customers across a large section of Lower Manhattan to use electricity sparingly today in an effort to prevent a power failure in the wake of Saturday's major explosion and fire at an electrical transformer on the East River.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Passaic Comeback  The Passaic River, once considered the finest rowing river in the Northeast, is poised for a rebirth. With most offending industries gone, the water quality is improving. Up and down the river, cities and suburban towns that used to treat the Passaic like a toilet are planning waterfront promenades and parks.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Caught Here and in Ghana  Data Management Internationale, a Delaware firm that has been digitizing information for New York City since March, sends some of its work to a back office in Ghana. That means just days after tickets have been written out on New York streets, they are sent as digital photographs to computers in downtown Accra, Ghana's capital, where workers try to transcribe the handwritten scrawl of New York police officers into searchable databases.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Glorifying Mafia Songs  A little-known form of Italian folk music will soon make its American debut with the release of a CD titled ''Il Canto di Malavita'' despite questions in Italy over the legality of the distribution and performance of music that glorifies the Mafia.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Els Wins British Open  Ernie Els, 32, of South Africa won the British Open in a sudden-death playoff at Muirfield in Gullane, Scotland. It was Els's third major championship. He has won the United States Open twice.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Chaz M. Holder  A triple amputee who devised a new way of making prosthetic limbs. He was 55.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>WorldCom Files for Bankruptcy  WorldCom, the telecommunications company hurt by an accounting scandal and a rapid erosion of its profits, has submitted the largest bankruptcy filing in United States history. The filing listed more than $107 billion in assets, making WorldCom's descent into insolvency more than twice the size of Enron's.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Push for Clean Cars  California's push for zero-emission vehicles could soon force automakers to sell more than 100,000 electric cars and other highly fuel-efficient vehicles in the state each year. That immediate concern has overshadowed a bill requiring automakers to cut carbon dioxide emissions by 2008 and has prompted them to spend billions of dollars developing new technologies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>C.E.O.'s Share the Pressure  America's chief executives, under pressure after several high-profile cases of malfeasance, are sharing the pressure by demanding more disclosure and accountability from the middle ranks.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Hip-Hop for Dollars  Radio stations nationwide are increasingly switching to hip-hop formats. The changes are largely propelled by economics. Hip-hop has great appeal among a group of listeners that advertisers increasingly covet: People ages 18 to 34 who have demonstrated significant spending power on disposable items.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Hurry up and wait in Congress; informant fever; Fordham's misplaced tower; Verlyn Klinkenborg on the tough summer out West.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  Weather</p>
        <p>B7  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
