<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Dept. Contractors Due for More Scrutiny</title>
    <meta content="24CONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/24/politics/24CONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1443303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Office of Management and Budget</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DB1039F937A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Dept. Contractors Due for More Scrutiny</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Energy Dept. Contractors Due for More Scrutiny</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Energy Dept next month to field first employees whose job is to supervise contractors' work because, its leader acknowledge, it has dismal record of contract management; more than 90 percent of dept's budget is paid to 100,000 outside workers; dept has relied on contractors for almost everything it does since it was founded 35 years ago; in particular, internal Energy Dept report this year concluded that agency's largest program, whch pays contractors to clean up waste left by nation's nuclear weapons programs, has been fundamentally mismanaged since its founding 13 years ago and much of $60 billion it has spent over that time was wasted; internal report's denunciation of agency practices and its prescriptions for changes echo findings by outside auditors dating back to 1990; table shows cost overruns on five major projects; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Bush administration announced this month that it intended to turn about half of the federal government's civilian jobs over to contractors, some officials at the Department of Energy reacted with rueful shakes of the head.</p>
        <p>Since it was founded 35 years ago, the department has relied on contractors for almost everything it does. More than 90 percent of its budget is paid to 100,000 outside workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Next month, the Energy Department will field the first employees whose job is to supervise contractors' work because of a dismal record of contract management.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Bush administration announced this month that it intended to turn about half of the federal government's civilian jobs over to contractors, some officials at the Department of Energy reacted with rueful shakes of the head.</p>
        <p>Since it was founded 35 years ago, the department has relied on contractors for almost everything it does. More than 90 percent of its budget is paid to 100,000 outside workers.</p>
        <p>Next month, the Energy Department will field the first employees whose job is to supervise the contractors' work because, its leaders acknowledge, it has a dismal record of contract management. The department's experience serves as a sobering counterpoint to the White House proposal.</p>
        <p>In particular, an internal Energy Department report this year concluded that the agency's largest program, which pays contractors to clean up the waste left by the nation's nuclear weapons programs, has been fundamentally mismanaged since its founding 13 years ago, and much of the $60 billion it has spent over that time was wasted.</p>
        <p>The internal report's denunciation of agency practices and its prescriptions for changes echoed findings by outside auditors dating to 1990 -- conclusions that are repeated in reports by auditors published in September, October and this month.</p>
        <p>What astonished agency employees, officials said, was that the department had finally acknowledged its problems. The office in question is the department's Environmental Management Program, formed in 1989 to clean up the radioactive waste left from cold war nuclear development programs at 114 sites nationwide. For years it has been criticized for cost overruns and delays projected to last decades.</p>
        <p>In one of the Energy Department's most infamous examples, which is far from unique, it began a program in 1985 to clean radioactive waste from 34 million gallons of liquids in storage in South Carolina. The project was to take three years and cost $32 million. Fourteen years later the department abandoned the project, saying it was unworkable because of mismanagement. By then, $500 million had been spent.</p>
        <p>Jessie Roberson, assistant secretary of energy for environmental management, said: ''I have been embarrassed by our lack of progress. We owe the taxpayers more.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberson and the department's other leaders say they are now addressing the problems. The agency says it is scrutinizing contracts more closely and training 200 people to be project supervisors. Today, no one at the department actively supervises multibillion-dollar cleanup projects that are let out to contractors.</p>
        <p>This month, department leaders also made public a plan to shorten the time by which contractors will have cleaned up all the radioactive sites nationwide -- to 2030 from 2070. Ms. Roberson, who has been with the agency or one of its contractors for 21 years, acknowledges that most administrations come in with ''plans for some new initiative or program to fix the problems.''</p>
        <p>The environmental management program engenders extraordinary criticism from within the government. The White House, in a current budget document, says the program ''is less focused on cleaning up sites and has instead turned into a local jobs program.'' A senior Office of Management and Budget official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said in an interview, ''They have spent a lot of money, but producing results seems to be an alien concept over there.''</p>
        <p>Since 1990, the General Accounting Office has classified the Energy Department's contract management as ''high risk.'' It is one of just six agencies whose procurement practices were judged dysfunctional.</p>
        <p>In the Clinton and Bush administrations, the Office of Management and Budget has described the department as among the dozen or so most troubled in government.</p>
        <p>A General Accounting Office audit published in September found that, even as agency officials spoke of change and reform, problems were actually worsening. Auditors examined a sample of 16 projects costing $200 million or more and said, ''We found no indication of improved performance.'' The number of projects for which cost estimates had at least doubled in five years and completion deadlines had slipped by at least five years had increased to 38 percent.</p>
        <p>An Energy Department inspector general's report published last month said one current cleanup project, in which price has escalated to $214 million from $64 million, had ''problems with project plans, cost estimates and project oversight.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberson observed that critical audits like that quickly lose their sting and in a perverse way even encourage agencies to stick with the offending practices. ''There has been a learned pattern of co-dependency between the department and the G.A.O and the inspector general,'' she said. ''When they identify problems, our job is to stand firm and explain the problems away. And with that posture, the problems don't get better over time. The debate could go on forever.''</p>
        <p>When Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham took office last year, he ordered three of the department's major divisions -- energy efficiency, fossil fuels and environmental management -- to examine their operations closely. But former Energy Secretary Bill Richardson and others had also ordered tough reviews.</p>
        <p>Environmental Management's review was the first one published, in February. It found that ''there is a systemic problem with the way Environmental Management has conducted its activities.''</p>
        <p>The program had estimated that cleaning up all the nuclear weapons sites would ultimately cost $300 billion and be completed in 2070. But, the internal report said, ''it is clear that on the current path, the cost of the program will continue to increase and increase, with the real possibility that the ultimate cleanup and closure goal will never be met.''</p>
        <p>''I think people were actually quite surprised that we said all this ourselves because we had denied and defended for so long,'' said Ms. Roberson, who was on the review team.</p>
        <p>Bruce M. Carnes, the department's chief financial officer, said it had decided ''that to obtain results in 70 or 75 years is not satisfactory.'' The White House agrees.</p>
        <p>The internal report and other audits this year show that the agency awards contracts to clean up radioactive sites without actually examining the property to see what the work will entail.</p>
        <p>Once a contract is awarded, the department seldom checks back. The department ''has virtually abdicated its role of owner in project oversight,'' the National Research Council said in a report last year that had been requested by Congress. That report found that half the money the department spends on contracts each year -- more than $17 billion in the last fiscal year -- is wasted and called Energy ''one of the most inefficient organizations in the federal government.''</p>
        <p>The agency's leaders all vow that the changes they are making are real and will bring results. Early this year Secretary Abraham said, ''We will no longer give contractors a license for unending cleanup and open-ended budgets.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Carnes said: ''We are serious. We are changing the tires on this car while it's driving 60 miles an hour. And this is not something that comes and goes. It's rock bottom truth.''</p>
        <p>But the senior O.M.B. official complained, ''So far, we've had more discussions about what they are planning to do than anything they have actually done.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
