<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Viewable Fast, Enforced by Knives</title>
    <meta content="10MADO$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/10/arts/design/10MADO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1439282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fasting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abramovic, Marina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Madoff, Steven Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Abramovic, Marina</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D8133EF933A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="2045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Viewable Fast, Enforced by Knives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Viewable Fast, Enforced by Knives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN HENRY MADOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Madoff, Steven Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Yugoslavian performance artist Marina Abramovic, who plans extreme work of fasting silently before public for 12 days, at Sean Kelly Gallery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the wake of terrorism, Americans, and New Yorkers in particular, have found that nothing is the same. And yet our art hasn't changed at all. Think of Goya's ''Third of May, 1808'' (1814) or Picasso's ''Guernica'' (1937) -- works that in their brilliant anguish showed a culture deepening and maturing with each fresh tragedy on its blood-soaked soil. Where is our ''Guernica,'' where is our ''Third of May''?</p>
        <p>No zone could be hotter than our new politics of immediacy, forged in the instant-and-anywhere war begun here on Sept. 11. We want to know how we can live more fully in these urgent times. So we are more than likely primed for the object lesson that Marina Abramovic, the powerful performance artist from the former Yugoslavia, brings to the Sean Kelly Gallery in Chelsea on Friday, when she mounts one of her more extreme works, fasting for 12 solid days -- if she lasts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The performance artist Marina Abramovic brings one of her more extreme works to the Sean Kelly Gallery: she will fast for 12 solid days  if she lasts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the wake of terrorism, Americans, and New Yorkers in particular, have found that nothing is the same. And yet our art hasn't changed at all. Think of Goya's ''Third of May, 1808'' (1814) or Picasso's ''Guernica'' (1937) -- works that in their brilliant anguish showed a culture deepening and maturing with each fresh tragedy on its blood-soaked soil. Where is our ''Guernica,'' where is our ''Third of May''?</p>
        <p>No zone could be hotter than our new politics of immediacy, forged in the instant-and-anywhere war begun here on Sept. 11. We want to know how we can live more fully in these urgent times. So we are more than likely primed for the object lesson that Marina Abramovic, the powerful performance artist from the former Yugoslavia, brings to the Sean Kelly Gallery in Chelsea on Friday, when she mounts one of her more extreme works, fasting for 12 solid days -- if she lasts.</p>
        <p>Ms. Abramovic, 56, intends to spend that time six feet off the ground in three connected, nearly bare and open units attached to the gallery's rear wall, each 5 1/2 feet deep by 9 feet wide, each at the end of a ladder whose rungs are 22 1/2-inch butcher knives, blades turned up, to make the point that she's not going anywhere. This will be her bathroom, living room and bedroom -- call it theater set, fishbowl or cage.</p>
        <p>There she will sit, lie and pace, clothed or naked, shower, sleep and live on nothing but water, day after day. Her bed will be a plank of oak with a chunk of rose quartz for a pillow. The artist's self-imposed rules are a grueling riff on solitary confinement or a Buddhist's way to enlightenment, and both resonate. No talking. No reading. No writing. No eating. During gallery hours, she will stare at us and we will stare back, or peer, if we want to, through a telescope specially set out, every inch of her privacy stripped.</p>
        <p>Though done in dead silence, Ms. Abramovic's raw performance has something to tell us -- or nudge us toward our own ''Guernica'' -- as an American audience, undoubtedly including artists, watches her press gingerly at the edges of her mortality.</p>
        <p>''Dramatic changes came in America after Sept. 11,'' Ms. Abramovic (pronounced ah-BRAHM-o-vich) said by telephone in heavily accented English. She was talking at midnight from Braunschweig, Germany, where she teaches performance art, though she has been based in Amsterdam since the mid-1970's. ''The whole idea of time, of what can happen in the next second, came to Americans in a way we know very well, very sadly in Europe. And this piece will be about living in the moment, in the absolute here and now.''</p>
        <p>''I'm totally nervous about doing it,'' she added. ''I made a piece with fasting once before, 12 days in 1981 for 'Nightsea Crossing,' and it becomes very intense; you feel bad, you feel sick -- your stomach, your head. But then you begin to feel clearer. You know what it's like? Like running in Central Park until you can't go on, and then a man comes up and points a gun at your head. You run like hell out of a different reserve of energy. That is what I want to get, to feel, to show -- that energy on the other side of the pain that transforms the way you see. Pain is the obstacle. It's the door each of us goes through one way or another. And you can grow from this.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Abramovic's wild disregard for limb, if not life, has fueled 30 years of performances about the thresholds of the body. A child of Communism, with a mother who became the director of the national Museum of Revolution and Art in Belgrade, a father who was an army general, and a grandfather who was a patriarch of the Serbian Orthodox Church and was purportedly murdered by the state and later granted sainthood, she grew up in a world rife with restrictions and spiritual dreams. When she began work as a student at Belgrade's Academy of Fine Arts, all the restrictions, all the state teachings to strive for the body politic (and more than a touch of martyrdom) boiled to the surface. The works were a marathon of strict instructions and bold what-ifs. In 1975, in Belgrade, when Tito still ruled Yugoslavia, she stood naked before an audience and cut a Communist star on her belly with a razor blade, whipped herself numb, then lay down for 30 minutes on a cross of ice blocks with a heater burning from above, until the crowds dragged her off.</p>
        <p>With the German-born artist who calls himself Ulay and was her partner from 1975 to 1988, the what-ifs were reeled off: how long could they slap each other before one of them stopped (20 minutes); or breathe oxygen and carbon dioxide into each other's tightly joined mouths (19 minutes); or sit without talking or eating (12 days); and on and on. In 1981, they lived for a year with Aborigines in the Australian desert, wandering without possessions in the permanent present tense of nomadic life. Then came their last what-if, in 1987, walking from opposite ends of the Great Wall of China to meet in the middle. It took 3 months, and afterward they parted ways permanently.</p>
        <p>Were they mad as hatters? Well, if they were, they had plenty of company. In the 1960's, the Viennese Actionists, as they were called, did some terrible things to their bodies, with much of the same spiritual aspiration to transcend the consciousness most of us are satisfied to tote through life. In the 70's, body art bloomed in America. Among many others, Vito Acconci, Dennis Oppenheim, Terry Fox and Chris Burden (who did his own fasting piece for three weeks, hidden on a big shelf in the Ronald Feldman gallery in 1975) explored a terrain of distilled and objectified terror that simply became too much for them. Not one of these artists here or abroad is still peering into the sharp light at the other end of knives, bullets, hunger, broken glass and electrified wires -- except Ms. Abramovic, who added pythons and boa constrictors to the arsenal of things you shouldn't play with when you're alone, as she did for her Hamburg performance of ''Dragon Heads'' in 1992.</p>
        <p>The deep psychological extremism of her work with Ulay pushed at the private limits of the self, but once again on her own, her figure bore the broader outlines of a political body. For the 1997 Venice Biennale, Ms. Abramovic sat inside a pavilion amid a nightmarish heap of bloody cow bones that evoked fresh memories of the Bosnian war across the Adriatic, weeping in the rising stench for six days while she scrubbed them white. The work, titled ''Balkan Baroque,'' won a coveted Golden Lion award at the Biennale and confirmed her as one of Europe's most significant contemporary artists.</p>
        <p>In the new American landscape, pressed by terrorism and the outlook of war, the way artists report their truths may be due for reappraisal. ''America has now caught up, tragically, with the art that Marina brings,'' said Germano Celant, senior curator of contemporary art at the Guggenheim Museum, who directed the 1997 Venice Biennale and is based in Genoa, Italy, and New York. ''We are used to blood in the streets in Europe, even on the corner where we live, spilled for political reasons. She brings that kind of witness to New York, when your own bodies now feel so much at risk. And this is unique. In an art world so fantastically good at high-tech image manipulation, she comes as a shock. She is doing this right in front of you.''</p>
        <p>The new piece, with its innocent title, ''The House With the Ocean View,'' on one hand and its nudity, knives and punishing hunger fast on the other, presses buttons near and far. The allusions are troubling. There is Franz Kafka's story ''A Hunger Artist,'' written 80 years ago, in which a world-famous performer sits in a cage, staring out at a fickle audience as he dreams of his own glory and slowly dies. Closer in time is the sting of actual history, the Irish hunger strikers in the 1970's and 80's. But Ms. Abramovic protested.</p>
        <p>''No!'' she said. ''This isn't about getting something material through political action. This is about taking away, about a way to cleanse and purify. People always see the superficial part, the punishment, but this is no different from rituals in Asian and Indian cultures, of the Tibetan monks I've spent time with every year since 1981: to go through a difficult task to come to another state of mind. I see myself as a bridge, like the Balkans, between the West and the East. I use my body as the way to get across. But it isn't about vanity.''</p>
        <p>No? Showering in front of a live audience a few feet away, with that telescope in reach, just in case someone misses a dimple? But she laughed. ''If you just want to look at this naked woman, then that's all you see. But I'm now 56. I'm not beautiful. If you look at a Renaissance painting, you see naked bodies, but the longer you look the more symbolism you see.''</p>
        <p>Balancing sensationalism with a deeper sense of purpose is a risk Ms. Abramovic's work often runs, and, inevitably, one theme we may see in ''Ocean View'' is surveillance: watching a woman's every move in her skeleton of a home, entirely exposed. How can we help but think about the cost of privacy in our new world? Hearing this, Chrissie Iles, the curator of film and video at the Whitney Museum, who has written extensively about Ms. Abramovic, said: ''But there is another way of looking at it. New Yorkers never stare. They're always averting their eyes, looking down, fearing confrontation. I think Marina gives us permission in her work to do just the opposite. That's the point. To look directly, in a sense to stare our senses in the face and feel, to pare down and focus.''</p>
        <p>There will be more of her work to focus on, from this weekend until April, at P.S. 1 in Long Island City, Queens. There, 22 videos of Ms. Abramovic's early work with Ulay will form a miniretrospective within the group exhibition ''Video Acts.''</p>
        <p>Klaus Biesenbach, the chief curator at P.S. 1, recounted that he commissioned Ms. Abramovic three years ago to make a piece called ''Luminosity'' for the reopening of Kunst-Werke, an institute of contemporary art in Berlin. She covered herself in nothing but diamond dust and balanced for three hours on a bicycle seat that shot out from a wall 17 feet high. ''It was an incredible act of will,'' Mr. Biesenbach said. ''People sat there for hours, and the crowds poured 500 yards into the street. The police had to shut the place down. Marina has that vision to mix an Eastern sense of time and a Western sense of theater, which has amazing global appeal. You witness it and you just get kicked out of your shoes.''</p>
        <p>But what will her symbolist theater of sacrifice and seeking bring this week as she performs like a monk whose begging bowl is her own body? ''I don't know how the piece will come out,'' Ms. Abramovic said with an anxious laugh. ''I haven't started preparing yet. I was just in Paris, eating fantastically. But it's always the same. I just go in and start. The question for me finally is not what I want from the work. I know this. The question is for the audience. To get something, you must give. How far do you want to go? How much do you want to feel?''</p>
        <p>Steven Henry Madoff is writing a book on the sculptor Christopher Wilmarth, who died in 1987, for Princeton University Press.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steven Henry Madoff is writing a book on the sculptor Christopher Wilmarth, who died in 1987, for Princeton University Press.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
