<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="19OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/19/science/19OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1368995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Manganese Sulfide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chromium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shellfish</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fossils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur and Sulfur Compounds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3D71E3FF93AA25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Warmer Split-Second</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Belgian researchers conclude that increasing atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide over coming decades would slow earth's rotation, lengthening the day by about millionth a second per year; researchers in England, reporting in journal Nature, conclude that tiny inclusions of manganese sulfide create chromium-depleted layer in stainless steel, which causes sulfur crust to form, locking in acid that causes further corrosion; British paleontologists find what they say is oldest sample of fossilized vomit, from ichthyosaur, containing remnants of tiny shellfish, which may have poisoned reptile; drawing (Observatory column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Warmer Split-Second</p>
        <p>Rightly or wrongly, global warming gets blamed for just about everything these days -- not enough snow, too much rain, rising sea levels, falling SAT scores, whatever.</p>
        <p>Here's a new one: global warming can make the days drag on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week's column includes items on how global warming could mean longer days, stainless steel and fossilized vomit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Warmer Split-Second</p>
        <p>Rightly or wrongly, global warming gets blamed for just about everything these days -- not enough snow, too much rain, rising sea levels, falling SAT scores, whatever.</p>
        <p>Here's a new one: global warming can make the days drag on.</p>
        <p>Belgian researchers report that increasing the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide, a greenhouse gas, over the coming decades would slow the earth's rotation, lengthening the day.</p>
        <p>The researchers used computer modeling to determine the effect of adding carbon dioxide at a rate by which the atmospheric concentration would double in 70 years. This is in line with many forecasts of the effect of human activity on the atmosphere for this century.</p>
        <p>Writing in Geophysical Research Letters, the researchers reported that the warming caused by the higher levels of carbon dioxide would produce variations in atmospheric pressure over land masses and the oceans and affect easterly and westerly winds and ocean currents. All the changes, they determined, would increase the planet's moment of inertia, decreasing its rotational velocity (just as a spinning figure skater can slow down by moving the arms away from the body).</p>
        <p>There's no need to start planning what you'll do with all the extra time, however. Global warming would lengthen the day by only about a millionth of a second per year, which in some years would be less than natural variations. All told, the researchers say, by the 22nd century a day would be about one ten-thousandth of a second longer than it is now.</p>
        <p>Ending Stainless Stains</p>
        <p>''Stainless'' steel gets that way through the addition of chromium, which oxidizes on contact with air to form a clear film that prevents the steel from rusting. Stainless steel can corrode, however, particularly in oxygen-poor conditions where a flaw in the protective layer cannot heal by oxidizing anew.</p>
        <p>Materials scientists have known that tiny inclusions, or pits, of sulfur-containing impurities, introduced in the manufacturing process, can cause stainless steel to corrode. But the exact mechanism of the corrosion has escaped them.</p>
        <p>Researchers in England have now determined how the corrosion starts. They used mass spectrometry, in which a sample is bombarded by an electron beam, to analyze the makeup of inclusions and surrounding areas. These inclusions are very small, so the mass spectrometry was performed on a scale of billionths of a meter.</p>
        <p>In manufacturing, the inclusions of manganese sulfide solidify at lower temperatures than the steel. This, the researchers report in the journal Nature, causes chromium atoms to be drawn from the still-molten steel, creating a chromium-depleted layer that is about 100-billionths of a meter thick. Water getting into this layer causes it to dissolve, creating an acidic environment that then attacks the manganese chloride. This causes a sulfur crust to form on top, locking in the acid that causes further corrosion.</p>
        <p>Knowing the process by which stainless steel corrodes, scientists can now try to determine how to prevent it. One suggestion offered by the researchers is to heat-treat the steel after it is manufactured, with the goal of infusing the chromium-depleted areas with new chromium atoms.</p>
        <p>A Stomach-Turning Find</p>
        <p>A reptile apparently had a bad case of shellfish poisoning one day about 160 million years ago, much to the delight of paleontologists.</p>
        <p>British scientists digging in a clay quarry in northern England have found what they say is the oldest sample of fossilized vomit, from an ichthyosaur, a fishlike reptile that spent most of its time in the water.</p>
        <p>The sample contains the remnants of dozens of tiny shellfish called belemnites. The scientists are convinced the sample is what they say it is (and not something else) from the way the shells are scattered.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
