<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President to Use Earth Day To Sell Environmental Plan</title>
    <meta content="Y22ENV$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/22/politics/22ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1386295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adirondack Mountains (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gore, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E4D9113FF931A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President to Use Earth Day To Sell Environmental Plan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">President to Use Earth Day to Sell Environmental Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>NASHVILLE, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>President George Bush to spend Earth Day in acid-rain-besotted Adirondack Mountains in upstate New York; is scheduled to restore hiking trail and promote his 'clear skies' initiative (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Monday is Earth Day, an annual rite of spring for the last 32 years. But this Earth Day will sound less like a love-in for Mother Earth than like an October rally in a presidential election year.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush, a former oil executive, is not normally identified with Earth Day rituals but like any president feels the need to flash some green credentials. Earth Day will find him in the acid-rain-besotted Adirondacks in upstate New York with Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This Earth Day may sound more like an October rally in a presidential election year than a love-in for Mother Earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Monday is Earth Day, an annual rite of spring for the last 32 years. But this Earth Day will sound less like a love-in for Mother Earth than like an October rally in a presidential election year.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush, a former oil executive, is not normally identified with Earth Day rituals but like any president feels the need to flash some green credentials. Earth Day will find him in the acid-rain-besotted Adirondacks in upstate New York with Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>With Whiteface Mountain as his backdrop, Mr. Bush is to help restore a hiking trail and promote his ''Clear Skies'' initiative, a proposal that the administration says will yield cleaner air than the Clean Air Act signed by his father in 1990. Protesters will be on hand to assert that his proposal would only make things worse and to complain about Mr. Bush's inaction on global warming, a phenomenon some say can be seen when, among other things, fewer of the big lakes in the Adirondacks are freezing over in the winter.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Al Gore, derided by Mr. Bush's father as Ozone Man, is planning to give a blistering speech in Nashville about what he calls Mr. Bush's environmental failures. His setting is an academic forum in his home state, where he is trying to make amends for past inattention.</p>
        <p>Whether a rerun of campaign 2000 or a harbinger of campaign 2004, the dueling events will showcase what Democrats believe is one of their most potent political issues, one that stands out as a rare piece of terra firma in a world dominated by the military imperatives of a popular Republican commander in chief.</p>
        <p>Republicans play down the environment as an electoral issue. They say that they were simply outgunned by the environmental lobby on last week's vote on whether to drill for oil in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, partly because the big oil companies cared less about it than about staving off automotive fuel-efficiency standards.</p>
        <p>Glen Bolger, a Republican pollster with Public Opinion Strategies, said a national survey that he completed last week showed the environment ranking ninth on a list of nine priorities for voters, after terrorism, the economy, education and health care.</p>
        <p>''The public is pro-environment, make no mistake about that,'' Mr. Bolger said. ''But they're not as anti-Republican or pro-environment as the Sierra Club would have you believe. Where environmental issues are hot are when it's a local issue that impacts people near their homes.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have come to similar conclusions but frame them a little differently. A recent poll conducted for the League of Conservation Voters shows that while voters approve overwhelmingly of Mr. Bush's handling of the war on terrorism, the economy and education, they do not approve of his record on the environment.</p>
        <p>If these issues do not motivate those who have already decided about candidates, they can motivate important swing voters.</p>
        <p>''The environment consistently ranks as a voting issue for independent voters, women and suburban voters, all of whom are the battleground in November,'' said Phil Clapp, president of the National Environmental Trust.</p>
        <p>The vote on drilling last week might be followed this week by another rebuff to Mr. Bush's energy policy when the Senate takes up a package of measures related to global warming. Bipartisan compromises being worked out now would reject the president's approaches to international and domestic climate-change policy and, Democrats hope, further put the president on the defensive.</p>
        <p>Polls a year ago showed Mr. Bush weighed down by the environment. The catastrophe of Sept. 11 quieted environmentalists for a time and then forced them to redirect their criticisms of the president to criticisms of his policies.</p>
        <p>But with the approach of the 2002 Congressional elections, and the difficulty Democrats face in gaining traction on other fronts, that is changing.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council is running an advertisement on Earth Day mocking what it suggests is the president's one-day-a-year homage to things green.</p>
        <p>''The ad marks a significant departure from our post-attack posture of talking more about the wishes of big, polluting corporations than about President Bush's own involvement in an unprecedented attack on 30 years of successful environmental protections,'' said Alan Metrick, the group's spokesman.</p>
        <p>Deb Callahan, president of the League of Conservation Voters, said the president's own policies in favor of the extractive industries of oil, gas and coal had helped regenerate the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>''Before 9/11, it was evident to anyone in politics that the environment was genuinely shaping up to be a top-tier issue in electoral politics in a way it had not been,'' she said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore previewed his speech on the Op-Ed page of The New York Times today, the White House said it was politics as usual. ''The president has a strong record on the environment, and the environment is one of the reasons he defeated Al Gore in the election of 2000, among other issues,'' the president's spokesman, Ari Fleischer, said. ''Even in a time of peace and prosperity, Al Gore made the same charges and still lost the election.''</p>
        <p>For accomplishments, the administration points chiefly to helping clean up brownfields in urban areas and to bringing about legal changes in the Superfund program that had been deadlocked in Congress for years.</p>
        <p>''We realize that some people may not give us credit for things we do right, but we're determined to make those right environmental policies anyway,'' one administration official said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolger, the Republican pollster, also dismissed issues like those that Mr. Gore was raising as a priority only for hard-core Democrats.</p>
        <p>''The environment resonates most strongly with the beats, the backpackers and the bangles crowd,'' he said. ''And they are pretty well on the far left of the Democratic party.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
