<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Climate Plan Is Criticized As a Risky Bet</title>
    <meta content="26CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/26/science/earth/26CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1370837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6DF1631F935A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Climate Plan Is Criticized As a Risky Bet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Climate Plan Is Criticized as Optimistic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on opposition by some scientists and economists who study climate data and policy to Pres George W Bush's new approach to politically charged issue of carbon dioxide emissions; new plan relies on voluntary efforts to slow, but not halt, growth in emissions of greenhouse gases; Bush has been saying for past year that there is no scientific justification to abide by emissions targets set forth in Kyoto Protocol; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House statement on climate change read: ''President Bush announced today that the United States has agreed with other industrialized nations that stabilization of carbon dioxide emissions should be achieved as soon as possible. The United States also agreed that it is timely to investigate quantitative targets to limit or reduce carbon dioxide emissions.''</p>
        <p>That was Nov. 7, 1989, one year after a global heat wave made the environment a top political issue and raised the prospect that people might be affecting the climate by adding carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases to the air, warming the planet as if it were inside a greenhouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the new Bush plan to deal with climate change, the urgency of a decade ago is gone. But critics argue that without limits on emissions, things will get worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House statement on climate change read: ''President Bush announced today that the United States has agreed with other industrialized nations that stabilization of carbon dioxide emissions should be achieved as soon as possible. The United States also agreed that it is timely to investigate quantitative targets to limit or reduce carbon dioxide emissions.''</p>
        <p>That was Nov. 7, 1989, one year after a global heat wave made the environment a top political issue and raised the prospect that people might be affecting the climate by adding carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases to the air, warming the planet as if it were inside a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>Twelve years later, under a new President Bush, the urgency has evaporated. On Feb. 14 the president articulated a new approach to what has become a lingering, complicated, politically charged scientific issue. It relies on voluntary efforts to slow, but not halt, the growth in emissions of greenhouse gases. Progress is to be measured by tracking the growth of emissions relative to the growth of the economy.</p>
        <p>For nearly a year, the president has been saying there is no scientific justification for the specific emissions targets set forth in the Kyoto Protocol, the climate treaty that would require participating industrialized countries to cut emissions by 2012 below their level of 1990. The administration says that when it comes to carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas, no one has yet determined how much is too much.</p>
        <p>But after analyzing details of Mr. Bush's new plan, many scientists and economists who study climate data and policy say the scientific ambiguity that the administration used to justify a limited response certainly exists, but cuts both ways.</p>
        <p>''What people sometimes forget is that the uncertainty in the science is double-edged,'' said Dr. Ronald G. Prinn, the director of the department of earth, atmospheric and planetary sciences at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>''In our own studies, we estimate about a chance in 20 that the warming in the next 100 years will exceed eight degrees Fahrenheit,'' he said. ''There's no doubt in my mind that eight degrees is something to deeply worry about. The target set by the president's policy to me looks inadequate in the face of that risk.''</p>
        <p>Under the administration's plan, carbon dioxide emissions would rise about 14 percent over the next decade -- the same increase that took place over the last decade. ''Can't we do maybe twice what we did in the last 10 years?'' Dr. Prinn asked, suggesting that the White House should move more aggressively against emissions. ''Then you'd have much more of a chance of real reductions.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, many climate experts said, rising productivity and energy efficiency have been slowing the growth of emissions compared with economic growth for more than a decade -- at the same pace Mr. Bush is proposing. Simply continuing this course, many said, is inadequate to promote the changes needed to flatten the curve of growth -- and eventually turn it downward.</p>
        <p>The debate over the new plan should reach Capitol Hill this week, when the Senate is expected to consider an energy bill with contentious provisions on oil drilling, gas-mileage standards and other policies that may affect emissions rates.</p>
        <p>Critics of the Bush approach include several members of a scientific committee assembled last year at the behest of the White House by the National Academy of Sciences to assess questions about climate change.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ralph J. Cicerone, chairman of the academy panel and chancellor of the University of California at Irvine, said the Bush administration was mistaken to view uncertainty as a cause for comfort.</p>
        <p>He said there was no longer any ambiguity about whether humans were significant contributors to global warming, and he noted that in the opening line of its report to the White House, the panel stated plainly that ''greenhouse gases are accumulating in Earth's atmosphere as a result of human activities, causing surface air temperatures and subsurface ocean temperatures to rise.''</p>
        <p>Last week, Dr. Cicerone said continued growth in emissions would make things worse. ''This situation is not sustainable, and its trajectory is toward dangers,'' he said, adding that the White House proposal ''lacks ambition and foresight'' and ''sets goals that are too timid.''</p>
        <p>The goals were far from modest when Mr. Bush's father signed the first climate treaty, in 1992. Under that treaty, industrialized nations agreed to strive to reduce their greenhouse emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000. Instead, however, global emissions continued to rise. American releases of greenhouse gases rose more than 12 percent in that period.</p>
        <p>Last fall, most industrialized nations rallied around a new treaty, the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, though they have yet to ratify it. That treaty, which the Clinton administration had signed, would require participating industrialized countries to cut emissions by 2012 below where they stood in 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush rejected the Kyoto treaty last year, saying the emissions targets were not scientifically justified. He said that the treaty unfairly required no emissions cuts of fast-growing countries like China and that it would harm the American economy.</p>
        <p>Last week, Dr. Conrad C. Lautenbacher Jr., a mathematician and retired Navy vice admiral, who is the under secretary of commerce for oceans and atmosphere, said Mr. Bush's new plan struck a reasonable balance between economic and environmental concerns. ''You're playing with a $12 trillion economy here,'' Dr. Lautenbacher said. ''There's such a large connection with our economy based on what we do and to what degree we do it that we'd be foolish not to try to understand the basic processes better.''</p>
        <p>The new policy is also attracting support from scientists who are skeptical that global warming is a serious long-term threat. More aggressive moves, they say, would harm the economy and waste resources that could be used to solve other problems. Indeed, some skeptics say Mr. Bush's policy concedes too much by even acknowledging that voluntary changes are needed.</p>
        <p>''Voluntary has a nasty habit of turning mandatory,'' said S. Fred Singer, a climatologist, who has long criticized the consensus view on warming and who heads the Science and Environmental Policy Project, a research and advocacy group financed by private contributions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Singer says recent studies have steadily whittled away at the direst predictions for warming.</p>
        <p>''Every bit of data,'' he said, ''seems to confirm that the climate sensitivity is well below even the lowest value given'' by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, an international scientific group that has issued three assessments of climate science over the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>But the lead author of one of the new studies, Dr. James E. Hansen, the director of NASA's Goddard Institute for Space Studies, says there is a difference between refining projections of change and saying global warming is not a serious problem.</p>
        <p>In a paper in a recent issue of The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Dr. Hansen and a Goddard colleague, Dr. Makiko Sato, plotted the changing concentrations of various greenhouse gases and predicted that the average global temperature would rise 1.3 degrees over the next 50 years. That is at the low end of predictions for warming generated by most computer models of climate, but more than temperatures rose over the last 100 years.</p>
        <p>The paper concluded that the warming trend was likely to be substantially slower than previously thought, given the slowing buildup of greenhouse gases other than carbon dioxide. For example, Dr. Hansen said, methane, a potent greenhouse gas that was once rapidly building in the atmosphere, has shown a sharp decline in its growth rate since 1980, for reasons scientists cannot explain.</p>
        <p>The scientists also calculated that a concerted effort to raise fuel efficiency and find ways to remove carbon dioxide from the air could well cause emissions to stop growing altogether later in the century and, eventually, to decline.</p>
        <p>But over all, Dr. Hansen said, the Goddard analysis still means that temperatures by 2050 will be more than two degrees warmer than they were at the beginning of the 20th century, when the accelerating Industrial Revolution began transforming vast stores of coal and oil into carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>''I could see keeping the warming relatively moderate, but I point out that even a two-degree warming is going to make the earth very warm compared to the history of the last millions of years,'' Dr. Hansen said.</p>
        <p>And, he noted, if emissions continue to rise just 1 percent a year -- the current rate, and the rate that would result under the policies proposed by Mr. Bush -- that adds up to a lot of greenhouse gases by later in the century.</p>
        <p>Still, Dr. Hansen said he remained optimistic that societies would rise to the challenge, adding that natural evidence of a strong human contribution to global warming was likely to pile up in the next few years -- along with a consensus for more action to counter it.</p>
        <p>''We'll be seeing how things are going well before 10 years are out,'' Dr. Hansen said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
