<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Chemistry</title>
    <meta content="27SEAVERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/27/books/review/27SEAVERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1435165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seaver, Paul S (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uglow, Jenny</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lunar Men, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Uglow, Jenny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE153DF934A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Chemistry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Lunar Men': Good Chemistry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul S. Seaver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seaver, Paul S (Prof)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul S Seaver reviews book The Lunar Men: Five Friends Whose Curiosity Changed the World by Jenny Uglow (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LUNAR MEN</p>
        <p>Five Friends Whose Curiosity</p>
        <p>Changed the World.</p>
        <p>By Jenny Uglow.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 588 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What distinguishes Jenny Uglow's study of 18th-century scientists and freethinkers, besides her skill as a writer, is her biographical approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LUNAR MEN</p>
        <p>Five Friends Whose Curiosity</p>
        <p>Changed the World.</p>
        <p>By Jenny Uglow.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 588 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $30.</p>
        <p>TO claim that the members of the Lunar Society of Birmingham ''changed the world'' in the second half of the 18th century is a pardonable exaggeration. The name came not from a shared interest in things astronomical but from the fact that the society met on the Monday nearest the full moon, when the members, after hours of eating, drinking and talking, had to find their way home in the dark. The ''lunatics,'' as Erasmus Darwin sometimes referred to himself and his fellows, were conspicuous participants in two of the defining activities of modernity -- natural philosophy or science and industry based on scientific advances. And most of them shared an optimistic belief in rationality, in spiritual or moral as well as material progress, which, they thought, would liberate humanity from superstition and authoritarianism.</p>
        <p>Although some of them became members of the Royal Society, they were not Londoners but hailed instead from the Midlands, the North and Scotland. With few exceptions they came from Dissenting backgrounds, but religion was not part of their agenda, and most thought of themselves as freethinkers, if not outright atheists.</p>
        <p>The Lunar Society is well known to historians. What distinguishes ''The Lunar Men,'' Jenny Uglow's study, besides her evident skill as a writer, is her biographical approach, her focus on individuals and their quirks, social origins, intellectual worlds and politics. Thus we see Erasmus Darwin, who was an Edinburgh-trained physician but also an inventor, a poet, a conversationalist who could not resist the facetious remark and, despite his formidable girth, a lover of women and a happy paterfamilias.</p>
        <p>Very different was Matthew Boulton, well read but not university educated, the son of a ''toy'' manufacturer (toys were small metal objects, such as buckles and candlesticks), who turned the family business into one of the largest factories in Birmingham, a man ever on the lookout for a profitable venture, but a generous man (most Lunar Society meetings were at his house). In the 1760's he was joined by James Watt, a dour Scot and a skilled instrument maker, who pioneered in the design of steam engines and was convinced that Boulton's entrepreneurial schemes would send them both to the poorhouse. Josiah Wedgwood, the scion of a Staffordshire potter, shared with the other Lunars an intense interest in chemistry, minerals, clays and glazes and, with Boulton, entrepreneurial ambitions ranging from canal building to creating a pottery business, which still exists.</p>
        <p>At the center of the group was William Small, who in the early 1760's had taught natural philosophy and mathematics at William and Mary, where Thomas Jefferson was among his students, before returning to England and a medical practice in Birmingham; it was apparently Small's capacity for friendship as much as his scientific interests that fostered this group until his death in 1775. In the 1780's these men were joined by Joseph Priestley, a chemist and freethinker, a stutterer like Darwin, but nonetheless an eloquent Unitarian minister whose radical politics were a source of endless trouble for him.</p>
        <p>In addition to these luminaries were others scarcely less distinguished: James Keir, a Scottish doctor and chemist; John Whitehurst, a Birmingham clockmaker and geologist; William Withering, who pioneered the medicinal use of digitalis; two members of the Anglo-Irish gentry, Richard Edgeworth and Thomas Day, both propagators of Rousseau's educational precepts (Day concocted the mad scheme of raising two orphan girls according to Rousseau's ideas, assuming that at least one would turn out to be an ideal wife, an experiment that failed). Connected to the Lunars through common interests were such figures as Benjamin Franklin, who was in England during the 1760's and early 70's, and John Smeaton, who adopted the term ''engineer'' for his profession and became famous for his lighthouses and bridges.</p>
        <p>It is perhaps to be expected that doctors, pottery manufacturers and metalworkers would share an interest in chemistry, but the Lunars' enthusiasms at one time or another encompassed everything from electrical phenomena to carriage design to the isolating and naming of airs (gases), ranging from carbon dioxide to oxygen and hydrogen. The success of the Montgolfier brothers' balloon flight in France led to the Lunars building both hot-air and hydrogen-filled balloons.</p>
        <p>They collected fossils and minerals from mines, caves and cliffs and, following the example of Linnaeus, set about classifying all British vegetation. Like their Renaissance forebears, they kept cabinets of curiosities, but they also possessed laboratories where they conducted their experiments in the English empiricist tradition. They were the last generation that could understand and pursue work in all the sciences, and they did so with an enviable energy.</p>
        <p>THEIR first crisis came in 1775, when Small's death led the Lunars to formalize their meetings and when the American Revolution brought their politics into high relief, for with the exception of Boulton, a loyal Tory supporter of George III's government, the others were all supporters of the American republic (Day at first opposed the Americans because of the issue of slavery -- the American claim to be fighting for liberty struck him as hypocritical -- but eventually joined the others in supporting the new republic).</p>
        <p>The French Revolution brought a second crisis. All but Boulton welcomed the revolution, and on July 14, 1791, the radical and Dissenting community of Birmingham met in a celebratory dinner. The Tories were not amused and organized what turned out to be an extended riot leading to the destruction of Priestley's Unitarian meetinghouse and then his home. Other radicals' houses were sacked and burned the next day. Although Priestley and his family escaped, to London and eventually to America, there was no return to the sunny optimism of earlier days. As Watt complained, the banishing of Priestley ''almost broke up our Lunar Society.'' It marked the beginning of the end.</p>
        <p>Uglow has given us a remarkable story of remarkable men, richly detailed and brilliantly told. She has mined the archives with telling effect, and if she gives us the Lunars in the round, she has not neglected their science. It is an exemplary work.</p>
        <p>Paul S. Seaver is a professor of history at Stanford University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul S. Seaver is a professor of history at Stanford University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
