<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Battered Taxi, a Nurse to India's Poorest</title>
    <meta content="24INDI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/24/health/24INDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1426200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rajasthan State (India)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alexander, Pauline</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Katherine Russell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3D91439F937A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Battered Taxi, a Nurse to India's Poorest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In a Battered Taxi, a Nurse to India's Poorest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE RUSSELL RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Katherine Russell</byline>
      <dateline>UDAIPUR, India</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Pauline Alexander, 76, nurse who dispenses medicine and clothing to poor villagers in drought-stricken Rajasthan, India; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent morning 20 miles from this city in the northwest Indian state of Rajasthan, Pauline Alexander and Kusum Bishwas were in the back of a rattling old taxi, cooling their hands on bottles of soda and discussing a girl who had almost died.</p>
        <p>''This 9-year-old, her tuberculosis was so bad her mother had to carry her in,'' Ms. Alexander, 76, a nurse, was saying when their taxi swerved to avoid a truck. Ms. Alexander and Mrs. Bishwas, 66, managed to avoid spilling their sodas, and Ms. Alexander finished her story.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two women make daily missions to villages with whatever help and donated medicine and clothing they can muster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent morning 20 miles from this city in the northwest Indian state of Rajasthan, Pauline Alexander and Kusum Bishwas were in the back of a rattling old taxi, cooling their hands on bottles of soda and discussing a girl who had almost died.</p>
        <p>''This 9-year-old, her tuberculosis was so bad her mother had to carry her in,'' Ms. Alexander, 76, a nurse, was saying when their taxi swerved to avoid a truck. Ms. Alexander and Mrs. Bishwas, 66, managed to avoid spilling their sodas, and Ms. Alexander finished her story.</p>
        <p>''The village girl, I thought when we returned she'd be dead,'' she said. ''But we gave her powdered milk, all the vegetables, medicine for 18 months. Now she's married.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander has been heading out on these missions for 17 years now, with whatever help and donated medicine and clothing she can muster. On this hot, dusty morning she and Mrs. Bishwas were on their way to two remote villages. The time was 8:15 and the temperature was already 85.</p>
        <p>The two women can testify to the effects of prolonged heat. For four years, their section of Rajasthan has been seared by drought, most likely a result of deforestation and increasing temperatures. In that time, ''the diseases have grown much worse,'' Ms. Alexander said.</p>
        <p>When they pulled into their first village, Peeplevas, it was 9 a.m. and the temperature was nearly 90 degrees, Twenty-five people were waiting for them at a red-roofed hut. A third were women, in veils and iron ankle bracelets. The rest were children. All were tribals, members of the scheduled caste, what used to be called outcastes. The designation has changed, but their situation has not. They are still abysmally poor.</p>
        <p>One villager ran to get a string bed. She carried it on her head and placed it on the porch, and Ms. Alexander and Mrs. Bishwas went to work. They laid out supplies on the bed: aspirin, iron tablets, multivitamins and medicines. One by one, the tribal women shyly approached.</p>
        <p>The first two complained of worms, ''a common condition because they walk barefoot,'' Ms. Alexander said. The third had a dreamy look and was speaking in a murmur. Ms. Alexander gave her aspirin for fever, took a minute to record names, illnesses and probable ages -- about 26, she was guessing -- for all three. ''They don't know what year they were born,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the car, her voice had been quavery and small. Now her bearing was commanding. ''You will take this twice a day,'' she told a woman with a cough.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bishwas, whose high bun of white hair had started to unravel in the heat, was pouring mouth-sore wash into film canisters with the capable air of a lieutenant.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander, slim, stately, with a bun that so far remained fixed, has a nursing degree from Syracuse University in New York. Born in the Himalayas to a family of Brahmins, the highest Indian caste, she arrived at Syracuse through a series of unhappy circumstances. When she was 2, her father died. Her mother converted to Christianity, and her family disowned her. Ms. Alexander's mother tried to scrape by working in a jail. Eventually, Ms. Alexander was placed in a missionary orphanage, where she had to rise each morning at 3 to start breakfast. But the nuns at the orphanage helped her obtain a scholarship to study in the United States.</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander has never lived a traditional Indian woman's life. She has taught nursing at hospitals in Fiji, set up public health clinics in Thailand and worked for World Vision in a refugee camp in the Vietnam War. In 1985, she said, she was contemplating retirement but heard a voice say, ''Your work is not finished,'' and began traveling into the villages. For the first few years, until a visitor from Britain donated taxi services, she made the trip three times a week by bus.</p>
        <p>In Peeplevas, more villagers arrived, streaming across yellow dust fields from several spots beyond the horizon. By 9:30 more then 50 people had arrived, including a few men too old to work or too sick for the hourlong journey to work as day laborers in Udaipur, or beyond. Traditionally, the men and women work the fields, but with the drought, work in the fields nearby is scarce.</p>
        <p>When the men arrived, most of the Hindu women tugged their veils over their faces. The Christians, Pentecostal converts, kept their faces uncovered.</p>
        <p>On the porch, a rhythmic litany of medical complaints could be heard. A young man said he had stomach pains. ''From chilies,'' Ms. Alexander said. ''There's been so little rain, they live on a diet of chilies and roti.'' Chilies and bread. An old man in a turban described trouble with his eyes. A teenager with a cow-herding stick and metallic pink polish on his nails had a cough.</p>
        <p>The men disappeared. The women came unveiled. The litany of complaints continued in a steady beat.</p>
        <p>A young woman with a child on her hip, holding the side of her veil in her teeth, extended her hand for a jar of cough syrup. ''She is totally blind,'' Ms. Alexander said. ''Five children. We give her a lot of clothes.''</p>
        <p>By 10 a.m., the rhythm was waning. Only stragglers remained. A teenage girl reported a discharge, a troubling sign. As the drought has forced men to travel far for work, the incidence of AIDS and other sexually transmitted diseases has increased. Testing for the diseases costs more than a villager earns all year. All Ms. Alexander could offer were vitamins.</p>
        <p>Another woman's tongue had the telltale white coat of anemia, which is also increasing as crops wither. For four years, the monsoon was scant. This year, there has been no real monsoon, only light, infrequent rain -- not nearly enough to reverse the effects of a severe drought.</p>
        <p>No one is sure what is causing the drought. Deforestation, aggravated by global warming, is suspected. But the drought's effects are beyond dispute: an arid landscape that had been lush, water tables down to 150 to 500 feet from 5 and 25 feet, sludgy puddles where lakes had been. By last June, after a string of 115-degree days, it was almost possible to walk across caked mud to Udaipur's famous Lake Palace Hotel, built to look as if it were floating.</p>
        <p>Most people in towns can still buy water and other necessities. But the villagers have suffered. The scarcity of food and work has shortened tempers and heightened domestic violence. Last winter, several days after Ms. Alexander had visited, a man in one village threw his wife into a well and drowned her.</p>
        <p>Vitamin A deficiency has increased night blindness. With fewer trees to collect rain, fewer roots are available to hold the soil in place, and the fertile topsoil has eroded. The vegetables that grow have fewer vitamins.</p>
        <p>''The diseases in the villages have worsened by 25 percent,'' said Tez Razden, an Udaipur physician. ''Malnutrition, anemia, tuberculosis, malaria, these are all common.''</p>
        <p>On the way to the next village, Pai, Ms. Alexander added to the list: ''Scabies from lack of water, conjunctivitis due to flies, diarrhea, pneumonia in winter, bronchitis and cough. Plenty of cough.''</p>
        <p>Pai looked slightly more prosperous than Peeplevas, thriving enough to have attracted the attention of a Western advertiser. ''Lifebuoy, for health,'' proclaimed the advertisement plastered onto a building.</p>
        <p>The rhythm of complaints began anew: measles, shoulder wound, upper respiratory infection.</p>
        <p>''This is a girl who had severe tuberculosis,'' Ms. Alexander said, greeting a smiling young woman in a purple sari, holding an infant son. ''When I first saw her she was 1.'' Beside the woman was someone else Ms. Alexander had known for years. ''And this is the one I talked about,'' Ms. Alexander said. A skeletal girl in a polka dot veil approached, smiling nervously.</p>
        <p>''Come, come,'' Ms. Alexander said. ''This is the one who had tuberculosis I thought would not survive.''</p>
        <p>She spread an ointment for skin rash on the woman's thin arms.</p>
        <p>''Her husband is horrible. He beats her,'' Ms. Alexander said. The girl moved on. Ms. Alexander found the log, began writing quickly, angrily. ''That woman will get tuberculosis again,'' she said. ''She doesn't get enough to eat. We brought 90 grams of powdered milk, and he drank it all, with tea.''</p>
        <p>An hour later, when the crowd was down to 20, Ms. Alexander noticed the woman again, leaning against a wall, her face covered. ''Give her the rest of the biscuits,'' Ms. Alexander said. But the woman shrank from the bag and would not take it.</p>
        <p>''Good work,'' Mrs. Bishwas said in the car going back.</p>
        <p>''Tiring work,'' Ms. Alexander said. They passed buff-colored stone walls and a goat on hind legs pulling leaves from a scrawny tree.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bishwas talked about an acquaintance in the hospital. Ms. Alexander stared out the window. Ms. Bishwas mentioned Avantika Mati, another member of their volunteer group from Udaipur, who was absent this day to tend to her grandchildren. ''She wants us to stop by,'' Mrs. Bishwas said.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Alexander's mind seemed still to be on the thin woman in Pai, and she nodded distractedly. ''That woman will get it again,'' she said. ''She will get it again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
