<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Urges U.S. to Revamp Efforts to Promote Image Abroad</title>
    <meta content="Y29INF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/29/international/29INFO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1412009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council on Foreign Relations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Council on Foreign Relations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D91338F93AA15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Urges U.S. to Revamp Efforts to Promote Image Abroad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel Urges U.S. to Revamp Efforts to Promote Image Abroad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Council on Foreign Relations says US is doing poor job of countering growing anti-American sentiment overseas and must revamp way it promotes foreign policies abroad, especially among predominantly Islamic countries; says rising tide of resentment could undermine Bush administration's efforts to fight terrorism and become obstacle if US decides to invade Iraq (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States is doing a poor job of countering growing anti-American sentiment overseas and must revamp the way it promotes its foreign policies abroad, the Council on Foreign Relations contends.</p>
        <p>In a report to be released this week, the council asserts that many countries, in particular predominantly Islamic ones, see the United States as ''arrogant, self-indulgent, hypocritical, inattentive and unwilling or unable to engage in cross-cultural dialogue.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States is doing a poor job of countering growing anti-American sentiment overseas, the Council on Foreign Relations contends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States is doing a poor job of countering growing anti-American sentiment overseas and must revamp the way it promotes its foreign policies abroad, the Council on Foreign Relations contends.</p>
        <p>In a report to be released this week, the council asserts that many countries, in particular predominantly Islamic ones, see the United States as ''arrogant, self-indulgent, hypocritical, inattentive and unwilling or unable to engage in cross-cultural dialogue.''</p>
        <p>Such a rising tide of resentment may undermine the Bush administration's efforts to fight terrorism and become an obstacle if the United States decides to invade Iraq, the report says.</p>
        <p>''The war on terror has made this whole situation far more urgent,'' Peter G. Peterson, an investment banker and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations, said in an interview. ''If we're going to fight that war effectively we'll need the cooperation of a lot of countries.''</p>
        <p>The report was written by a 35-member panel that included news executives, former diplomats and scholars of the Middle East. It recommends a sweeping overhaul of an array of exchange and broadcast programs intended to promote cross-cultural understanding and to sell America's policies abroad.</p>
        <p>The recommendations include: expanding the use of political campaign techniques, including polling, to shape attitudes toward the United States; establishing a White House unit to coordinate efforts, headed by a senior adviser to the president; and creating an independent Corporation for Public Diplomacy, modeled after the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, to develop programs to communicate American messages overseas.</p>
        <p>The report is being released at a time when support is growing in Congress for overhauling such programs. The House has already approved a bill, sponsored by Representative Henry J. Hyde, the Illinois Republican who is chairman of the International Relations Committee, that would increase spending on the programs by more than $255 million in the next two years and consolidate overseas broadcasting operations under one agency.</p>
        <p>''How is it that the country that invented Hollywood and Madison Avenue has such trouble promoting a positive image of itself overseas?'' Mr. Hyde said last week on the House floor.</p>
        <p>Similar legislation is being drafted in the Senate with the support of Senator Joseph Biden, the Delaware Democrat who is chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration is also considering plans to revamp those programs. After Sept. 11 the State Department hired Charlotte Beers, a former advertising executive, to help sell American values and policies to the Islamic world.</p>
        <p>But Karl Rove, the president's closest political adviser, is said to support a more sweeping overhaul of foreign communications operations.</p>
        <p>Washington's efforts abroad to promote public acceptance of its policies have been sharply scaled back since the end of the cold war. With the support of the Clinton administration, the Republican-controlled Congress folded the United States Information Agency into the State Department, reducing its budget and its power significantly.</p>
        <p>One result, according to the Council on Foreign Relations report, has been a ''a legacy of underfunded and uncoordinated efforts'' just when the United States needs most to burnish its image. The report cites recent independent opinion polls in which more than 60 percent of people surveyed in Jordan, Saudi Arabia and Pakistan -- all considered American allies -- expressed an unfavorable opinion of the United States.</p>
        <p>Other polls indicate that overwhelming majorities in Kuwait, Pakistan and Indonesia do not believe that American military action in Afghanistan has been morally justifiable.</p>
        <p>The report acknowledges that American policies regarding Israel are a major impediment to improving the country's image in Muslim nations. But it chides the government for not doing more to explain those policies or to express concern about the ''suffering and grievances of the Palestinian people.''</p>
        <p>It also asserts that the Bush administration has weakened its standing abroad with ''misunderstood and/or misguided'' policies that angered allies, including rejecting treaties to reduce global warming, ban antipersonnel land mines and create an International Criminal Court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson argued that having communications experts involved in the formulation of those policies might have reduced public relations disasters. ''Unfortunately, our current structure tends to create some crash landings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But skeptics, including some on the council's panel, say no amount of public relations can compensate for unpopular foreign policies.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe pleading not guilty to the innumerable and contradictory charges brought against the U.S. will be effective,'' Lewis Manilow, a panel member, wrote in a dissenting note. ''The rich hegemon will usually be unpopular, deservedly or not.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
