<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Decrees. British Bristle. Iceboxes Heaved.</title>
    <meta content="Y08BRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/08/international/europe/08BRIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1365972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="St. Merryn Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Refrigerators</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">England</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blake, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5D6173CF93BA35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Decrees. British Bristle. Iceboxes Heaved.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe Decrees. British Bristle. Dump Iceboxes.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>ST. MERRYN, England, Feb. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mountains of discarded refrigerators in Britain are visible side effect of new European law that requires discarded appliances to be taken to special plants where environmentally harmful, ozone-depleting chlorofluorocarbons are extracted from insulation foam; Britain neglected to build plants, and this oversight has brought charges of incompetence from Conservative opposition and round of finger-pointing between defensive Labor government and European Union; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The used refrigerators began appearing, as if from thin air, on the edges of Bob Partridge's farm late last fall. By Christmas, he had discovered more than 50 dumped there, cleverly secreted in deserted buildings, behind trees and under bracken across his property in this windswept corner of Cornwall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Partridge was unwilling to pay to cart them away, so he made his own modest refrigerator mountain, flinging them together in a heap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Used refrigerators are multiplying like bacteria across Britain, the very visible side effect of a new European law requiring them to be taken to special processing plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The used refrigerators began appearing, as if from thin air, on the edges of Bob Partridge's farm late last fall. By Christmas, he had discovered more than 50 dumped there, cleverly secreted in deserted buildings, behind trees and under bracken across his property in this windswept corner of Cornwall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Partridge was unwilling to pay to cart them away, so he made his own modest refrigerator mountain, flinging them together in a heap.</p>
        <p>But, as it turns out, his is a mere anthill in a vast Matterhorn of refrigerators that has been accumulating across Britain. They are everywhere these days: in warehouses, in open fields, in makeshift storage facilities, at the bottom of streets, in the woods and by the side of the road.</p>
        <p>The refrigerators are the visible side effect of a new European law that requires the discarded appliances to be taken to special plants where environmentally harmful, ozone-depleting chlorofluorocarbons are extracted from their insulation foam.</p>
        <p>Oops. Though the law went into effect Jan. 1, Britain neglected to build the plants. The oversight has brought  charges of incompetence from the Conservative opposition and a round of finger-pointing between a defensive Labor government and the European Union.</p>
        <p>The government says the first of the plants will not be up and running until late this spring, but even those will be able to handle a mere fraction of the 2.5 million or so refrigerators that Britons throw away each year.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, abandoned refrigerators -- thousands are retired each day -- are multiplying like bacteria around the country, and local authorities are frantically trying to find somewhere to put them.</p>
        <p>In the old days, refrigerators were easy to get rid of; they could simply be spruced up for resale or crushed and used for scrap. Appliance companies cheerfully hauled them off when customers bought new ones.</p>
        <p>Now the companies are refusing to do so, and Britons, unwilling to wait weeks to pay to have their refrigerators removed by local authorities, have taken to dumping them in places like Mr. Partridge's farm.</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Partridge, 79, who has been raising cattle and growing corn here for more than 50 years, did not know what to make of all the refrigerators. For some time, he has been used to people dumping trash, including major appliances, on the far reaches of his 500-acre holding. But this was an odd development.</p>
        <p>Then his wife, Betty, saw a letter in a farmers' newsletter discussing the new regulation and warning readers to watch out for stray refrigerators.</p>
        <p>''We looked at each other, and Betty said, 'You got some there,' and I said, 'Yeah, and they're growing,' '' Mr. Partridge recalled.</p>
        <p>''I blame the greens,'' he added, referring in general to environmentalists. Although he does not object in principle to protecting the environment, he said, he cannot understand why no one will remove his refrigerators -- surely an environmental blight -- since they were not his in the first place.</p>
        <p>Under the regulations, he said, he is not even allowed to use his own trucks to take the refrigerators to the local dump. ''I'd have to hire a special lorry to take them there because of the ozone layer, in case they explode or whatnot on the way,'' he said. All told, it would cost more than  $1,000, and he is not paying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Partridge is by no means the only one with problems. In the offices of the Cornwall County local government, Bert Briscoe, the councillor responsible for dealing with the refrigerator problem, is at a loss to explain where the council is going to get the money it needs for even a temporary solution. In the village of Christchurch, in eastern England, John Blake, the owner of a scrap yard, now has a pile of 3,000 refrigerators and nowhere to send them.</p>
        <p>In London, Harrods is facing the unwelcome task of informing its famously demanding customers that it will no longer cart away used refrigerators, no matter how expensive the newly purchased ones are.</p>
        <p>''It's hard for them to understand that it's the European Union, and not us,'' said Alexis Hage, general manager of the store's major appliance department. ''But if you need a fridge, you need a fridge.''</p>
        <p>It is extremely tempting to blame the British government for the refrigerator crisis. But the government argues that the European Commission is at fault, accusing it of waiting until the last minute to make clear exactly what the new regulations, drawn up in 1998, meant.</p>
        <p>''We only got clarification of that in July last year,'' complained a spokesman for the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs. ''We are by no means the only country that is in this position.'' In all, 8 of the 15 countries in the European Union stand unprepared for the new law.</p>
        <p>That may be true, but few of the other countries appear to have taken the law as seriously as Britain has, said Caroline Jackson, a Conservative member of the European Parliament from Britain and the chairwoman of the Parliament's environment committee.</p>
        <p>Taken aback by a problem it appears not to have fully appreciated, the Labor government hastily allotted $8.5 million in November to local authorities to help cover the cost of picking up and storing all the refrigerators. But local authorities say that they are likely to need at least $106 million, and the Conservatives put the figure at $283 million.</p>
        <p>As politicians argue over who is to blame, Mr. Partridge has 50 refrigerators rusting on his land.</p>
        <p>''Somebody suggested that I do some art work with them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>St. Merryn Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
