<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Air, Their Air: Most of It Is Bad</title>
    <meta content="10SMOG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/10/nyregion/10SMOG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1439334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Connecticut"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Interest Research Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Richard (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D7113EF933A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Air, Their Air: Most of It Is Bad</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Our Air, Their Air: Most of It Is Bad</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on air pollution in Connecticut, which has been ranked among top 10 states beset by smog problems in study by US Public Interest Research Group; Attorney General Richard Blumenthal, who has filed and threatens to file lawsuits against other states and cities, notes bad air knows no boundaries; efforts by state to clean up air described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR one week over the course of several summers, at a pastoral camp for asthmatic children in the Connecticut River Valley, Dr. Jonathan Fine watched children breathe. He and his staff watched the children all day, every day, noting short breaths and long ones, irregular breaths and clean ones. In a camp where the air seemed as clear as Bermuda water, here is what they found: When the readings for the pollution haze, otherwise known as smog, were low, the children had less trouble taking breaths. When the smog readings increased, the children struggled.</p>
        <p>The children may be struggling more often, because smog is increasing in the state. Connecticut made the top 10 list for states beset by smog problems in a study released in August by the United States Public Interest Research Group titled ''Danger in the Air, the 2001 Ozone Season Summary.'' The Boston office of the Environmental Protection Agency, which oversees New England, has deemed smog the foremost pollutant in Connecticut. Attorney General Richard Blumenthal has filed -- and is threatening to file -- lawsuits in an effort to stop more pollutants from entering Connecticut. From Salisbury in the northwest corner of the state, to Manchester in the east, the quality of the air has residents signing petitions, pounding placards into their lawns and calling city hall and the Department of Environmental Protection to complain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The smog in Connecticut makes the 10-worst list, with much of it drifting in from other states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR one week over the course of several summers, at a pastoral camp for asthmatic children in the Connecticut River Valley, Dr. Jonathan Fine watched children breathe. He and his staff watched the children all day, every day, noting short breaths and long ones, irregular breaths and clean ones. In a camp where the air seemed as clear as Bermuda water, here is what they found: When the readings for the pollution haze, otherwise known as smog, were low, the children had less trouble taking breaths. When the smog readings increased, the children struggled.</p>
        <p>The children may be struggling more often, because smog is increasing in the state. Connecticut made the top 10 list for states beset by smog problems in a study released in August by the United States Public Interest Research Group titled ''Danger in the Air, the 2001 Ozone Season Summary.'' The Boston office of the Environmental Protection Agency, which oversees New England, has deemed smog the foremost pollutant in Connecticut. Attorney General Richard Blumenthal has filed -- and is threatening to file -- lawsuits in an effort to stop more pollutants from entering Connecticut. From Salisbury in the northwest corner of the state, to Manchester in the east, the quality of the air has residents signing petitions, pounding placards into their lawns and calling city hall and the Department of Environmental Protection to complain.</p>
        <p>For many, air pollution is a reality best dealt with elsewhere, as long as the air looks clean. But just as the cloud from the smoking section of a restaurant fails to respect invisible boundaries, air pollution travels. It travels in such a way that New York City's smog situation often is better than Connecticut's, because the smog caused by heavy traffic in the city travels upwind to the Connecticut suburbs. And it travels so far that Mr. Blumenthal, along with other Northeast attorneys general, is suing several Midwest coal-burning plants whose pollutants have been sweeping into Connecticut with the prevailing winds.</p>
        <p>''We are a bad-air dumping ground,'' said Mr. Blumenthal, who sued New York State in the mid-1990's for air contamination and won a court order requiring officials to renovate sewage plants. ''The real problem is these air contaminants don't respect our state boundaries. They don't stop at the state borders.''</p>
        <p>Up until a year ago, no studies existed that determined smog caused respiratory disease. But a 2001 California study showed that in children who spent a significant amount of time outdoors engaged in active sports, exposure to air pollution was a risk factor in the development of asthma. The more time they spent breathing bad air, said Dr. Michelle Cloutier, the director of the asthma center at the Connecticut Children's Medical Center in Hartford, the higher their risk. Smog can cause upper as well as lower respiratory tract diseases and is responsible for decreased lung function in people with chronic lung disease.</p>
        <p>Officials and environmentalists said pollution traveling from outside the state is just adding insult to injury, that there's enough pollution generated in Connecticut to keep them busy. Power plants, incinerators, landfills, chemical manufacturing plants and other industrial sources are permitted a certain amount of pollution, monitored by increasingly sophisticated equipment.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act allowed the six oldest and most polluting power plants in Connecticut to continue using antiquated anti-pollution equipment long after newer plants had installed modern controls. Environmental and health groups formed the Connecticut Coalition for Clean Air, which lobbied Gov. John Rowland's administration for several years for stronger anti-pollution methods. He signed an executive order in December 2000 phasing in controls for the six plants over the next few years.</p>
        <p>Although the Department of Environmental Protection said power plants account for only about 10 percent of the air pollution in the state, ''they are giving them a permit to pollute a certain amount,'' said Kim DeFeo, the Connecticut field director for Toxics Action, a New England environmental group that compiles a list annually of what it deems to be the top environmental health threats in the state. ''No one is looking at the combined exposures to all these plants. Toxics exposure is determined for a 160-pound male, not for children.''</p>
        <p>Brooke Suter, one of the organizers of the Clean Air Coalition, also argued that states need to seize every opportunity to reduce their own emissions. ''In passing legislation,'' she said, ''we then lead the way and make it more possible for other states to initiate other standards that would benefit the residents of this state.''</p>
        <p>Part of the challenge is getting people, particularly suburbanites, to care about the air, when all is clear and green about them. Margaret LaCroix of the American Lung Association of Connecticut recounted a conversation she had with a person from a suburban town who claimed not one case of asthma existed in the town. Ms. LaCroix was dumbfounded.</p>
        <p>''Because these children are suburbanites, they typically have easy access to health care and are seeing a physician on a regular basis,'' she said. ''Some towns, I know, truly believe they have no asthma, but asthma is everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Health researchers fault a variety of sources for asthma, from cockroach droppings to smoke in the home. Still, study after study continue to find that smog is a major instigator, not only triggering asthma attacks, but, in high-smog areas, creating the asthma itself.</p>
        <p>When an immediate threat to residents arises, such as a stench in the air or a metallic taste to the water, people act. In Manchester, residents formed Manchester Area Residents Concerned About Health in an effort to close a Tilcon Balf asphalt plant that had installed a new burner, releasing into the neighborhood what residents described as a choking stench and soot.</p>
        <p>''I have two small children, 7 and 9,'' said Mike Ricci, an Assemblies of God minister and a 40-year resident, ''and after we would go up to Maine, we would get home, get out of the car in the driveway and be grabbed around the throat with choking air. My wife would have to wrap our babies in blankets and rush them into the house.''</p>
        <p>The Department of Environmental Protection issued an order to close the plant, which the owner appealed. The plant continues to operate, although Mr. Ricci said changes to the plant have made the neighborhood ''liveable again.''</p>
        <p>''We are confident that a thorough review of our permit, the facts, and the law will show the plant to be operating well within the air emission standards authorized by the D.E.P. permits,'' Carmine J. Abate, president of Tilcon Connecticut, wrote in an e-mail message, responding to requests for comment.</p>
        <p>Fear of just such a scene has driven Litchfield County residents to protest a proposal by the St. Lawrence Cement Company to build a cement plant in Greenport near Hudson, N.Y., on the east side of the Hudson River. The company already owns a plant on the west side of the river, which would cease operation. Groups fighting the plant claimed the plant would increase emissions significantly, and that much of those emissions would float over the northwest corner and on into the New England states. Although the company has held various public forums in the Hudson Valley, it has turned down opportunities to speak in Connecticut, said Starling Childs, the president of the Berkshire-Litchfield Environmental Council.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of claims being made both ways,'' Mr. Childs said. ''Our history is that we want to look at any project from the science, and the science we have says this plant will be emitting increased mercury, will contribute heavily to acid rain, and will be tripling production lines. It's a massive industrial city.'' St. Lawrence Cement officials denied that the plant would increase air pollution emissions. ''The plant will actually reduce emissions overall,'' said Patrick Dolberg, the company president.</p>
        <p>Smog is an invisible enemy, a stew that cooks up under the heat of the sun when nitrogen oxides mix with volatile organic compounds. This stew is most potent during ozone season, when the sun is hottest through spring and summer. States do not measure air quality each month, but rather during ozone season. Connecticut rated third in the nation for the number of times the smog reading hit an unhealthy standard for a single one-hour period in 2001. It ranked 10th in the number of days the ozone reading hit unhealthy, meaning it was above the national standard, for an eight-hour period, according to the United States Public Interest Research Group study, with data provided from the Environmental Protection Agency and state environmental departments. The number of unhealthy days has become the E.P.A.'s biggest priority in Connecticut, said David Conroy, manager of air quality planning at the agency's northeast office in Boston.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Conroy said that many Connecticut polluters have cleaned up over the years, the one population his agency has failed to curtail are consumers. Car and truck traffic is responsible for up to 50 to 60 percent of the state's smog problems.</p>
        <p>''The gains in cleaner cars are to some degree offset by people driving more cars, driving more miles per year,'' he said. Minivans and sport-utility vehicles, which have less stringent emissions standards than passenger cars, jam the roads. Mr. Conroy said he believed those emissions numbers will come down, though, when new standards go into effect in 2004.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most alarming to environmental groups is the Bush administration's proposal to roll back the Clean Air Act. Business and industry groups have long fought requirements of the New Source Review, claiming they are too expensive. The review is a part of the Clean Air Act that requires power plants and refineries to install modern emissions reduction equipment whenever they make major upgrades or repairs.</p>
        <p>For Dr. Fine, head of the Connecticut Thoracic Society, an air pollution researcher and asthma investigator who runs the pulmonary research program at Norwalk Hospital, the cumulative effects of smog are distressing. From a health perspective, he would like to see data made available neighborhood by neighborhood to be able to determine what is causing respiratory ailments.</p>
        <p>''This could be a grass-roots, as well as a nationwide, effort,'' he said. ''These ailments are all over. It doesn't get you off the hook, being in the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
