<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1374370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DF1639F933A25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-24</p>
        <p>U.S. Nuclear Plan Sees New Targets and New Arms  A secret Pentagon report, outlining a broad overhaul of American nuclear policy, calls for developing new nuclear weapons that would be better suited for striking targets in Iraq, Iran, North Korea, Syria and Libya. The report is a comprehensive blueprint for developing and deploying nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Attacks in Mideast Kill 14  At least 14 Israelis were killed in two Palestinian terror attacks -- one at a popular cafe in Jerusalem and another on a seaside promenade in Netanya. Israeli helicopters fired missiles at Yasir Arafat's office building in Gaza City, destroying it, witnesses said. No one was at the compound.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-24</p>
        <p>U.S. Nuclear Plan Sees New Targets and New Arms  A secret Pentagon report, outlining a broad overhaul of American nuclear policy, calls for developing new nuclear weapons that would be better suited for striking targets in Iraq, Iran, North Korea, Syria and Libya. The report is a comprehensive blueprint for developing and deploying nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Attacks in Mideast Kill 14  At least 14 Israelis were killed in two Palestinian terror attacks -- one at a popular cafe in Jerusalem and another on a seaside promenade in Netanya. Israeli helicopters fired missiles at Yasir Arafat's office building in Gaza City, destroying it, witnesses said. No one was at the compound.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe Goes to Polls  Zimbabweans voted in record numbers in a presidential election marked by violence and intimidation. The leading challenger, Morgan Tsvangirai, wants to unseat President Robert Mugabe.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Birthrates in Poor Nations Fall  A steady decline in births in poor nations is defying conventional wisdom, which holds that birthrates will fall when living standards improve.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Mexican Cartel Chief Arrested  Mexican authorities arrested Benjamín Arellano Félix, the chief of the nation's most powerful drug gang.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>33-39</p>
        <p>Sprawl-Weary Los Angeles Is Building Up and In  Moving away from its history of sprawl, Los Angeles is growing upward and inward and making a fledgling attempt to free itself from the automobile.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Diocese Punishes Priests  The bishop of Portland, Me., removed two priests who had admitted molesting boys long ago after a new accusation surfaced last week.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Jury Convicts Ex-Radical  Jamil Abdullah Al-Amin, the black radical known in the 1960's as H. Rap Brown, was found guilty of murdering a sheriff's deputy two years ago.</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Telescope Back in Orbit  The space shuttle Columbia released a reinvigorated Hubble Space Telescope.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>Making the N.C.A.A. Picks  National Collegiate Athletic Association officials have been working under tight security to choose the 65 teams that will compete in the men's basketball tournament.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>For Sale: Earlier SAT Scores  High school students eager for early word on their College Board results may now get it online for a $13 fee.</p>
        <p>38</p>
        <p>NATION CHALLENGED</p>
        <p>26-29</p>
        <p>U.S. Troops Lead Battle After Afghans Retreat  American troops were unexpectedly forced into fierce fighting in Afghanistan last week after an allied Afghan general retreated under fire from foes who might have been tipped off about the attack, senior military officers said.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>At a field hospital at an old Soviet airfield, British and Spanish army medics are treating both American and Afghan fighters and Taliban and Al Qaeda fighters, side by side.</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Bush to Widen Terror Net  President Bush is to announce that he will pursue the Qaeda terrorist network even in countries that do not welcome an American presence, and that inaction will not be an option in dealing with countries assembling weapons of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Securing Airline Security  Travelers are returning to the air, but many in the airline industry say that for all the visible security measure added since Sept. 11, aviation is still not yet secure enough.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A Week of Mourning  Americans mourned eight soldiers killed in battle in Afghanistan last week. Announcements of the casualties were noticeably emotional, in part because previous deaths had resulted from accidents, not battle.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Bonds of Anxiety  Officers' wives, strangers linked only by geography and bureaucracy, are forging new bonds and coping together as their husbands wage war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>41-46</p>
        <p>Fire Dept. Coping With Loss  Six months after the New York Fire Department lost 92 vehicles and 343 firefighters with 4,400 years of combined experience, only some of the questions about how to move forward have been answered.</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>An Odd Winter is Warm and Dry  This winter was the warmest and second-driest ever recorded in New York City. Climate scientists say the strangeness of the season advanced their case that climate change is real and is happening now.</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>Esther Afua Ocloo  One of Ghana's leading entrepreneurs and a prominent advocate of the role of women in economic development, she was 83.</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>46  Weather</p>
        <p>48</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
