<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="02OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/02/science/02OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1405161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slugs (Animals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snails</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iodine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sweating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mannequins (Dummies)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caffeine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Algae</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hong Kong Polytechnic University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National University of Ireland</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DF1631F931A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Killer Java</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Observatory column: Federal agriculture researchers, in report in Nature, find that caffeine can repel and kill slugs and snails; discovery may result in environmentally friendly way to control them on crops; National University of Ireland scientists, reporting in Nature, discover that aerosols can be created by sunlight acting on iodine compounds produced by marine algae; aerosols help in cloud formation and may have effect on climate change; scientists at Hong Kong Polytechnic University create mannequins that sweat, which will be used for testing fabrics and clothing under extreme conditions of temperature and activity; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Killer Java</p>
        <p>Do you feel like a slug until you have had that first cup of coffee in the morning?</p>
        <p>With luck, you don't. For a jolt of caffeine is enough to kill a slug, apparently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This weeks column includes items on caffeine as slug repellent, iodine aerosols and sweaty mannequins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Killer Java</p>
        <p>Do you feel like a slug until you have had that first cup of coffee in the morning?</p>
        <p>With luck, you don't. For a jolt of caffeine is enough to kill a slug, apparently.</p>
        <p>Federal agriculture researchers in Hawaii have discovered that caffeine can repel slugs and snails. Writing in Nature, they say that caffeine has potential as an environmentally friendly means of controlling them on crops.</p>
        <p>The researchers were trying to determine if caffeine worked on a small frog that infests potted plants. After spraying solutions of up to 2 percent caffeine, the researchers noticed that large slugs in the soil were dying.</p>
        <p>Shifting their attention to the slugs (a species known as the two-striped slug), the researchers found that in controlled tests, 48 hours after soil was thoroughly wetted with the solution, all of the slugs had left the soil, and 9 of 10 were dead.</p>
        <p>They also discovered that even very diluted caffeine solutions repelled slugs from cabbage leaves. Caffeine was similarly effective on bush snails, which eat the surface roots of orchids.</p>
        <p>Commercial snail-  and slug-control chemicals produce residues that are not allowed on food crops. Caffeine, on the other hand, is on the Food and Drug Administration's generally-recognized-as-safe list, so a caffeine-based pesticide may be more environmentally acceptable.</p>
        <p>The researchers say they do not know how caffeine kills slugs and snails, but that it appears to work as a neurotoxin, as slugs sprayed directly with caffeine display uncoordinated writhing, kind of like somebody who has had one too many double espressos.</p>
        <p>Tracking Other Aerosols</p>
        <p>Clouds don't just happen. There have to be ''seeds'' -- minute particles called aerosols -- on which water vapor can condense into tiny droplets. Airborne dust accounts for much of the supply of aerosols, but other secondary ones are made in the atmosphere by the action of sunlight on gases.</p>
        <p>Some of these gases are pollutants, but over oceans, particularly, sulfuric acid vapor, a product of the oxidation of sulfur compounds from marine algae, has been thought to play a major role.</p>
        <p>Now, scientists from the National University of Ireland and several other institutions have shown that another element, iodine, may be involved in secondary aerosol production.</p>
        <p>Using an experimental apparatus at the California Institute of Technology designed to mimic coastal atmospheric conditions, the scientists have demonstrated that aerosols can be created by sunlight acting on iodine compounds produced by algae.</p>
        <p>In their experiments, reported in Nature, sunlight splits off an iodine atom from a hydrocarbon-iodine molecule. The iodine then reacts with ozone to create iodine oxide and other iodine-containing vapors, which can condense and agglomerate into aerosols.</p>
        <p>While it is unclear how widespread this process is, it could help explain why aerosol formation has been observed over oceans even when concentrations of sulfur-containing compounds have been too low for the process to occur. Since aerosols do more than just help clouds form -- among other things, they absorb or scatter sunlight -- naturally produced iodine compounds may have a till-now-unexplored effect on climate change.</p>
        <p>Mannequins Feel the Heat</p>
        <p>Mannequins, with their impossible physiques and ice-cold stares, are unreal in more ways than one. But scientists at Hong Kong Polytechnic University have created a mannequin that, in one way at least, seems more human. It sweats.</p>
        <p>The mannequin is not designed for department store windows, to show what those fancy clothes really look like after a hot summer day. No, this creature, which has fabric skins of different degrees of permeability that can be changed to simulate different perspiration rates, is meant for testing fabrics and clothing under extreme conditions of temperature and activity.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
