<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summer Stuff That Has What It Takes</title>
    <meta content="19INDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1393440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D91139F93AA25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summer Stuff That Has What It Takes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled and Written by Marcelle S. Fischler</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KEEPING ITS COOL</p>
        <p>Ice cream melts fast in the summer sun. A ceramic ice cream cooler, shaped to hold round cardboard containers in gallon and pint sizes, keeps everything from Chunky Monkey to chocolate-chocolate chip thick and creamy. Whimsically decorated with tiny ice cream cones, the coolers are also more attractive than the supermarket packaging. Before the coolers are set on the patio table, they can be put in the freezer for 20 to 30 minutes to chill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KEEPING ITS COOL</p>
        <p>Ice cream melts fast in the summer sun. A ceramic ice cream cooler, shaped to hold round cardboard containers in gallon and pint sizes, keeps everything from Chunky Monkey to chocolate-chocolate chip thick and creamy. Whimsically decorated with tiny ice cream cones, the coolers are also more attractive than the supermarket packaging. Before the coolers are set on the patio table, they can be put in the freezer for 20 to 30 minutes to chill.</p>
        <p>''They keep the ice cream cold for up to three hours,'' said Dianna De Martino, the owner of the Culinary Connection, a kitchen shop in Great Neck.</p>
        <p>When not keeping the pineapple gelato frozen, the cooler can become a decorative holder for funky ice cream scoops with handles shaped like cows or cones; kitchen towels with images of ice cream and chocolate-dipped strawberries; containers of pastel-shaded sprinkles in wildflower, daisy, butterfly and heart shapes; or squeeze bottles filled with chocolate or strawberry sauce to coat a triple scoop. Coordinating ice cream bowls with matching spoons are also available.</p>
        <p>Ceramic ice cream coolers: gallon size, $16.99; pint size, $8.99. The Culinary Connection, 10 Grace Avenue, Great Neck; (516)829-6883.</p>
        <p>AND THE KITCHEN SINK</p>
        <p>The backyard grill no longer stands alone. Entire kitchens have gone al fresco. The barbecue entertainment island, in stucco or stone with granite or tile counter tops, can be the poolside or patio answer to fully equipped open-air cooking.</p>
        <p>''Summer comes, and you don't have to be inside to cook,'' said Steve Hess, the manager of the Woodbox Fireplace and B. B. Q. Center in Commack. ''Because of 9/11 they are staying home and fixing their backyards up and making more family-oriented entertainment centers instead of going on vacation. It can be part of an outdoor room.''</p>
        <p>Custom outdoor kitchens can have deluxe grills and rotisseries, prep areas, bar sinks, stainless-steel refrigerators, ice makers, side burners, griddles, electrical outlets and storage drawers. The propane tanks are hidden. Raised circular counters with overhangs provide space for bar-stool seating, shaded with a beach umbrella and outlined for night parties with strip lighting. And cooks who like to grill their steaks outdoors year round never have to mess up the indoor kitchen.</p>
        <p>Ben Ragucci, the owner of the Jetmore Bar-B-Que &amp; Fireplace Center in Wantagh, installed about 80 custom outdoor kitchens last year, priced from $2,900 to $18,000. ''It's to enhance the backyard,'' said Mr. Ragucci, who will install a beer tap on request. ''You can make it any size or shape you want. They are good for people who don't want to build a foundation for a brick unit. You can put them on a wood deck. You don'ts need a footing. You don't need a permit. It won't increase your taxes because it's a removable object.''</p>
        <p>A PORTABLE BREEZE</p>
        <p>A personal fan with a separate mister can cool a hot and sticky day. At the ball park, summer camp, on a picnic or lazing by the pool, the moisture and blast of air from a palm-size personal fan and atomizer no larger than a mascara dispenser act like a personal air-conditioner.</p>
        <p>Small enough to keep in a purse or pocket, the purple fan has soft aqua-colored foam blades. For a cool break, the mister and fan each slip out of the holder and can be used together or separately.</p>
        <p>Pocket Breeze Mister, $7.99. Nemo's, 3232 Long Beach Road, Oceanside; (516)764-8706.</p>
        <p>PAINTING THE LILY</p>
        <p>Like slipcovers, decoupage can be used to spruce up just about anything, from tea boxes to flower pots and even plastic watering cans. Joan Henderson's patterns include Hydrangeas with dragonflies, frogs and bright pink flowers. Just remember to wipe the paper dry after each use.</p>
        <p>Large watering can with long, slender spout, $46; small can, $36. The Culinary Connection, 10 Grace Avenue, Great Neck; (516)829-6883.</p>
        <p>FOILING MOSQUITOES</p>
        <p>One way to prevent mosquito bites without chemicals or pesticides is to trick the perpetrators. Mosquitoes think the Mosquito Trap, a two-foot-high electric contraption that looks like a trash can on a pole, is human. That's because its tank warms up to body temperature and gives off carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>''It emis the CO2 to mimic breathing,'' said Jay McCauley, a salesman at the Jetmore Bar-B-Que &amp; Fireplace Center in Wantagh. The mosquito thinks it has found its prey and lands on the trap. A fan draws the insects inside, and the machine then zaps them.</p>
        <p>The device was originally developed for stables and barns. ''With the West Nile virus, it became available for the residential market,'' said Ben Ragucci, the owner of Jetmore. ''It does the job.''</p>
        <p>The trap, described as powerful enough to keep an acre mosquito-free, is equipped with a photoelectric cell that turns the machine on at dusk and off at dawn. ''That's when the mosquitoes are out,'' Mr. Ragucci said.</p>
        <p>Mosquito Trap, $995. Jetmore Bar-B-Que &amp; Fireplace Center, 3343 Merrick Road, Wantagh; (516)826-1166.</p>
        <p>SUN-POWERED</p>
        <p>One of summer's simple pleasures is an outdoor shower, especially if the water is warm. The Solar Shower, which hooks up to a hose, makes the possible.</p>
        <p>''If you live by the beach, you get rid of all that sand,'' said Genoveva Gonzalez, A Solar Shower dealer in Baldwin. ''It's convenient, and it gives you the option of having a warm shower and having your body at the right temperature before jumping into the pool.''</p>
        <p>The shower can hold five and a half gallons of water in an insulated black polyester tube that heats water quickly in the sun and constantly refills itself as the water is used. Hot and cold handles allow for temperature adjustment. The shower is seven feet tall, with a cantilevered arm and swiveling showerhead, and it can be folded when not in use.</p>
        <p>''It's great for camping or on a boat and for all the outdoors,'' Ms. Gonzalez said. ''Wherever they ahve water running, you can make use of it. It's environmentally friendly. You could have warm water for the outdoors, and you aren't paying for it. You're using the sun.''</p>
        <p>Solar shower, $325. Solar Energy Inc., P.O. Box 553, Baldwin, N.Y. 11510; www.all-solar-products.com; (516)771-4001.</p>
        <p>ON THE BEACH</p>
        <p>Dining by the sea is a perennial summer way to entertain. When the meal has been prepared with panache, a bit of sophistication is added to the mix. The Seashore Clambake Basket is a portable yet elegant, easy and authentic way to dine on the beach or in the backyard by the pool.</p>
        <p>''It starts the season off with a kick,'' said Arlene Zibrak of Paul Evans Caterers in Westhampton Beach and Island Park. ''All the work's been done for you. The presentation is there. The diversity of the menu recreates a casual seashore picnic.''</p>
        <p>A wicker basket lined with a red and white gingham cloth includes steamed Maine lobster (a one-and-a-half pounder, removed from the shell, plus a tail), roasted garlic-and-herb jumbo shrimp, mussels steamed in chardonnay, and smoky barbecued chicken breast. There are fresh-cut vegetables with cayenne buttermilk dip, new potatoes, corn bread, sliced summer fruit and berry salad along with chocolate sandwich and oatmeal raisin cookies. Clear plastic plates and utensils are included, and the napkins are tied with red ribbons.</p>
        <p>''It's all about convenience and style,'' Ms. Zibrak said. ''It's fun to eat.''</p>
        <p>Seashore Clambake Basket, $85, serves three people. Delivery: $40. Paul Evans Caterers, Westhampton Beach; (631)288-5992.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
