<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking to the Past to Project the End of Pax Americana</title>
    <meta content="17KAKU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/17/books/17KAKU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1449372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kupchan, Charles a</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">End of the American Era, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kupchan, Charles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D8173DF934A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking to the Past to Project the End of Pax Americana</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking to the Past to Project the End of Pax Americana</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews book The End of the American Era: US Foreign Policy and the Geopolitics of the 21st Century by Charles A Kupchan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE END OF THE AMERICAN ERA  U.S. Foreign Policy and the Geopolitics of the 21st Century  By Charles A. Kupchan  391 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $27.95.</p>
        <p>The vision of the future set forth in Charles A. Kupchan's new book, ''The End of the American Era,'' is a startling and often puzzling one: he predicts that a ''decline of American hegemony will play itself out over this decade and the next,'' with the United States ''losing interest in playing the role of global protector of last resort'' and the European Union ''becoming a new center of global power.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles Kupchan charts America's role in the coming century and attempts to set forth a theory of historical change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE END OF THE AMERICAN ERA  U.S. Foreign Policy and the Geopolitics of the 21st Century  By Charles A. Kupchan  391 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $27.95.</p>
        <p>The vision of the future set forth in Charles A. Kupchan's new book, ''The End of the American Era,'' is a startling and often puzzling one: he predicts that a ''decline of American hegemony will play itself out over this decade and the next,'' with the United States ''losing interest in playing the role of global protector of last resort'' and the European Union ''becoming a new center of global power.''</p>
        <p>''The stability and order that devolve from American preponderance will gradually be replaced by renewed competition for primacy,'' he writes. ''The unstoppable locomotive of globalization will run off its tracks as soon as Washington is no longer at the controls. Pax Americana is poised to give way to a much more unpredictable and dangerous global environment. And the chief threat will come not from the likes of Osama bin Laden, but from the return of traditional geopolitical rivalry.''</p>
        <p>In these pages Mr. Kupchan -- a professor of international relations at Georgetown University and a senior fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations -- tries to articulate a hugely ambitious vision of global geopolitics; he not only aspires to chart America's role in the coming century, but also attempts to set forth a theory of historical change, ranging from the days of hunters and gatherers through the dawning of the digital era. He wants to assess the consequences of what he sees as post-cold-war complacency in American foreign policy and to promote his own brand of ''liberal internationalism'' that might guide the country toward ''multilateral engagement through international institutions.''</p>
        <p>''The End of the American Era'' attests to a wide-ranging historical intelligence and a dedicated study of strategic issues. But while Mr. Kupchan has important and timely things to say about America's time-honored traditions of unilateralism and isolationism, weaknesses in his central thesis (and his tendency to subordinate empirical evidence to that thesis) are pointed up by developments that have taken place in the wake of the terrorist attacks of 9/11 (dealt with in this book mainly in brief asides) and more pointedly in the last few months with the Bush administration's move against Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kupchan dismissively contends that ''the appropriate analogy for the battle against terrorism is the war on drugs or the effort to combat organized crime,'' and he worries that the events of last year will make it ''even less likely that the United States will bring into focus more profound, even if more distant, threats to America's well-being.''</p>
        <p>He also predicts that in the face of terrorist threats, America will ''rein in its overseas commitments in an attempt to cordon itself off from such threats,'' that in the post-cold-war era, the United States ''will no longer feel compelled to play the role of global guardian'' and will instead pursue ''a more diffident'' foreign policy, predictions that fly in the face of President Bush's aggressive new doctrine of pre-emptive action, and his determination to go after Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>At the same time the president's avowals that the United States will go it alone against Iraq if necessary underscore the relevance of the many discussions in this book about America's ''long-standing aversion to multilateral institutions'': its ''unwillingness to compromise the freedom of unilateral initiative'' and the possibly dangerous consequences of this stance. Mr. Kupchan reminds us of the Bush administration's decision to withdraw from both the Kyoto Protocol on global warming and the Antiballistic Missile Treaty and its opposition to the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty and the International Criminal Court. He describes the resentment that such stands have engendered among our allies, and he suggests that such behavior could undermine the international institutions the country ''worked so hard to put in place after World War II.''</p>
        <p>''The United States may have the luxury of being headstrong,'' he writes, ''while it still enjoys primacy; smaller states have little choice but to play along. But when America's dominance is less pronounced and other centers of power have the wherewithal to stand their ground, its unilateral impulse will serve only to guarantee the return of global geopolitical rivalry.''</p>
        <p>In the course of this book Mr. Kupchan does a nimble job of exposing the obvious flaws in Francis Fukuyama's ''End of History'' argument: a willfully sunny thesis that sees democratic states coming together in a new era of peaceful global order. But he is considerably less adept at taking apart Samuel Huntington's theory that rancorous fault lines are bound to emerge between clashing civilizations, bluntly and improbably stating that ''there is scant evidence to support the claim that other cultures will clash with the West.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kupchan's method throughout this book is to use historical analogies to shed light on contemporary problems: he draws comparisons between the unification of Germany and the emergence of the European Union, between the boom and bust of the 1920's and 30's, and current economic woes. The problem with this approach, however, is that it plays down enormous changes in the historical environment -- from the spread of democracy to advances in technology -- and it also lends itself to alarmist sentiments.</p>
        <p>For instance, in discussing the growing power of Europe and its growing estrangement from Washington, Mr. Kupchan ominously urges us to remember ''the rapid demise'' of the Roman empire, ''after the founding of a second capital in Constantinople.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kupchan believes that ''the United States cannot and should not resist the end of the American era,'' and he concludes this provocative but unconvincing book with the wildly broad assertion that the ''end of the American era'' will also mark ''the end of the era that America has played such a large role in shaping -- the era of industrial capitalism, republican democracy and the nation-state.'' It's an assertion -- like much of the more speculative theorizing in this book -- that is not supported by the marshaling of persuasive evidence.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
