<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canadian Lawmakers Advance Climate Pact as Discord Grows</title>
    <meta content="11CANA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/11/international/americas/11CANA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1447734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chretien, Jean (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2D6143AF932A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canadian Lawmakers Advance Climate Pact as Discord Grows</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Canadian Lawmakers Advance Climate Pact as Discord Grows</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Dec. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada's House of Commons overwhelmingly votes to ratify Kyoto climate change protocol; widespread disapproval by powerful provinicial governments and business groups has called into question whether accord will ever be fully put into place in Canada; Canada, one of world's largest producers of carbon dioxide emissions per capita, is one of only few large polluting nations among 100 countries to have ratified or moved toward ratification; Prime Min Jean Chretien, who strongly backs accord, had hoped vote would signify broad national support (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The House of Commons voted overwhelmingly to ratify the Kyoto climate change protocol today, but widespread disapproval by powerful provincial governments and business groups has called into question whether the agreement will ever be fully put in place in Canada.</p>
        <p>Proponents said Canada's ratification was a major step forward for the 1997 treaty. Canada, one of the world's largest producers of carbon dioxide emissions per capita, is one of only a few large polluting countries among about 100 nations to have ratified or moved toward ratification.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Widespread disapproval, however, has called into question whether the agreement will ever be fully put in place in Canada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The House of Commons voted overwhelmingly to ratify the Kyoto climate change protocol today, but widespread disapproval by powerful provincial governments and business groups has called into question whether the agreement will ever be fully put in place in Canada.</p>
        <p>Proponents said Canada's ratification was a major step forward for the 1997 treaty. Canada, one of the world's largest producers of carbon dioxide emissions per capita, is one of only a few large polluting countries among about 100 nations to have ratified or moved toward ratification.</p>
        <p>But as the debate here heated up in recent weeks, the Liberal government compromised on previous commitments to control emissions in an effort to assuage the auto and oil industries and counter a national campaign against the accord financed by the Alberta provincial government.</p>
        <p>Under Canadian law, the 195-to-77 vote today was not necessary. It takes only a vote by the cabinet to ratify international treaties. That vote, which is expected next week, is considered a formality, because all the cabinet ministers voted in favor of the resolution in the House of Commons.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Jean Chrétien, who has made the Kyoto accord a centerpiece of his agenda, hoped that approval by the House of Commons, including the votes of the opposition Bloc Québécois and the social democratic New Democratic Party, would signify broad national support. The impact of the vote, however, was reduced by a procedural vote in the House on Monday to shut off debate. Several influential Liberal lawmakers, including former Finance Minister Paul Martin, abstained from the procedural vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin, who is the leading contender to succeed Mr. Chrétien as the Liberal leader and prime minister when he steps down in early 2004, said he believed that the debate over the Kyoto accord should have continued, to build consensus before ratification went forward. Mr. Martin's abstention was viewed by Ralph Klein, the premier of Alberta, and other opponents as a signal that he would not wholeheartedly press for industrial curbs should he take over the government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein has warned that he could sue the federal government over the Kyoto accord, noting that under Canadian law the provinces have control over natural resources.</p>
        <p>Under the accord, by 2012 Canada would be required to reduce its emissions of greenhouse gases by 6 percent from 1990 levels. Of the country's total 240-megaton target for emissions reductions, business would be required to contribute 23 percent of the decreases.</p>
        <p>To meet the targets, the government has proposed measures including improving public transit, increasing parking fees in big cities and encouraging more freight transport by train.</p>
        <p>Auto companies based in Canada would be required to make new vehicles that are 25 percent more efficient by 2010, and coal-fired industries would be obliged to either reduce emissions or spend hundreds of millions of dollars a year purchasing ''emissions credits'' from countries outside Canada.</p>
        <p>Under the Kyoto protocol, countries can sell and purchase parts of their carbon monoxide emissions allotments, allowing countries that are falling behind in their obligations to purchase excess emission credits from countries that are ahead of schedule in order to meet their targets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
