<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping Momentum on the Energy Bill</title>
    <meta content="03KERR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/03/opinion/03KERR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1445492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerrey, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Domenici, Pete V (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DA1F38F930A35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping Momentum on the Energy Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Keeping Momentum on the Energy Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Kerrey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kerrey, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Bob Kerrey, president of New School Univ, on what Republicans, who control new Congress, should do about energy, and how Democrats should respond; says if Sen Pete V Domenici, new chairman of Energy Committee, has foresight to reintroduce compromise bill reached by last Congress, Democrats should put their objections aside and support it because bill will help economy and boost solid, environmentally sound energy policies; says bill is not perfect piece of legislation, but it is best opportunity now to jump-start production of renewable energy, and it is sound way to help economy; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following nearly a year of heated debate over polar bears, caribou and S.U.V.'s, a divided Congress decided to put its energy bill on hold late last month. It did so even after such politically charged issues as oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and increases in automobile mileage standards were taken off the table. Now that Republicans will control the new Congress, what will they do about energy, and how will the Democrats respond?</p>
        <p>If Senator Pete V. Domenici, the Republican from New Mexico who will take over as Energy Committee chairman, decides to load up a new energy bill with these same contentious issues, the Democrats will resist, as they did this year. But if he has the foresight to reintroduce the compromise bill reached by the last Congress, Democrats should put their objections aside and support it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the compromise energy bill reached by the last Congress is reintroduced, the Democrats should support it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following nearly a year of heated debate over polar bears, caribou and S.U.V.'s, a divided Congress decided to put its energy bill on hold late last month. It did so even after such politically charged issues as oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and increases in automobile mileage standards were taken off the table. Now that Republicans will control the new Congress, what will they do about energy, and how will the Democrats respond?</p>
        <p>If Senator Pete V. Domenici, the Republican from New Mexico who will take over as Energy Committee chairman, decides to load up a new energy bill with these same contentious issues, the Democrats will resist, as they did this year. But if he has the foresight to reintroduce the compromise bill reached by the last Congress, Democrats should put their objections aside and support it.</p>
        <p>Why? Because this bill will help the economy and boost solid, environmentally sound energy policies.</p>
        <p>The most important issue in America today is jobs, and this bill will help the private sector create lots of them. In fact, it represents one of the best economic stimulus packages the new Congress is likely to pass.</p>
        <p>By clarifying arcane rules concerning the electricity industry and repealing outdated Depression-era laws, the bill will encourage more investment in energy. Indeed, our tentative economic recovery depends on secure, sustainable and affordable energy. The bill would advance all those goals.</p>
        <p>Second, the bill can bring Americans important benefits in the form of safer, more reliable energy. It would encourage the development of ''green'' or renewable resources -- wind, solar, geothermal, biomass and small-scale hydroelectric, for example -- which today generate less than 2 percent of our nation's electricity. The other 98 percent comes from traditional sources like fossil fuels, nuclear energy and large-scale hydro projects, which carry far heavier environmental burdens.</p>
        <p>We all know that renewable energy resources are mostly pollution-free. But this isn't their only virtue. They are by definition domestically based, and for this reason contribute to our energy security. They provide fuel diversity and price stability. After all, the fuel -- the wind, the sun, heat from the core of the earth -- costs nothing. And they provide jobs. In fact, according to a study released last summer by the California Public Interest Research Group, renewable energy plants create four times the number of jobs -- in construction, operation and maintenance -- as traditional plants.</p>
        <p>While renewables have made impressive progress in closing the price gap with fossil fuels, they remain more expensive because they have greater up-front construction costs or are necessarily located in remote areas. The pricing of renewables, however, includes no adjustment for the social benefits of these emissions-free energy sources.</p>
        <p>The energy bill as currently written would change all that. It would also spur investment by providing a production tax credit for renewable electricity sources. It would also direct the federal government, the largest single purchaser of electricity in the world, to buy 10 percent of its power from renewable resources.</p>
        <p>These measures would provide a huge boost for technology development, reduce emissions of greenhouse gases and air pollution and help diversify our energy supply. With the bill, wind energy alone could provide thousands of new jobs by 2020, many of them here in New York State and the Northeast.</p>
        <p>A report issued by the government's Energy Information Agency showed that by helping to reduce our growing dependence on natural gas, the bill's provisions would pay for themselves by holding down consumer gas prices. In addition, renewables would reduce our need to import more oil from the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Is the bill a perfect piece of legislation? No, but it is the best opportunity we've ever had to jump-start production of renewable energy -- and it's a sound way to help our economy. An energy bill will remain a top priority for the administration and Congress next year. Rather than starting over from square one, Congress should resurrect the good work it's already done. Fights over polar bears, caribou, and the Arctic can all be voted on separately.</p>
        <p>Bob Kerrey, a former United States senator, is president of New School University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bob Kerrey, a former United States senator, is president of New School University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
