<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Writings That Defy Time's Toll</title>
    <meta content="26BEAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/26/arts/26BEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Public Library</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frank, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Library</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDE153EF935A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Writings That Defy Time's Toll</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Writings That Defy Time's Toll</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL FRANK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frank, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Frank reviews Victorians, Moderns and Beats: New in the Berg Collection, 1994-2001, new exhibit of manuscripts, letters, books and other items on view at New York Public Library; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Italian there are a number of vivid words for odd mixtures of things. A minestrone is of course a soup of assorted vegetables; a polpettone is a meatloaf of different ingredients; accozzaglia suggests a certain mélange of elements drawn from hither and thither and generally unmatched, or incompatible. Much of this nomenclature originates in the kitchen, where, as so often in Italy, disparate elements are artfully combined into the makings of a feast.</p>
        <p>Something similar might be said of ''Victorians, Moderns and Beats: New in the Berg Collection, 1994-2001,'' an exhibition that opens today at the New York Public Library. The title is a little misleading: among the manuscripts, letters, books, juvenilia and realia on display, Victorian material is modest, modern prolific, Beat largely weighted toward Jack Kerouac. There is no particular story being told here, other than that of a shopping spree, seven years long -- but it is shopping of a culturally significant variety, as the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature grows and stretches to preserve larger and larger swaths of the tangible record of our literary past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In "Victorians, Moderns and Beats: New in the Berg Collection, 1994-2001" at the New York Public Library, disparate elements are artfully combined into the makings of a feast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Italian there are a number of vivid words for odd mixtures of things. A minestrone is of course a soup of assorted vegetables; a polpettone is a meatloaf of different ingredients; accozzaglia suggests a certain mélange of elements drawn from hither and thither and generally unmatched, or incompatible. Much of this nomenclature originates in the kitchen, where, as so often in Italy, disparate elements are artfully combined into the makings of a feast.</p>
        <p>Something similar might be said of ''Victorians, Moderns and Beats: New in the Berg Collection, 1994-2001,'' an exhibition that opens today at the New York Public Library. The title is a little misleading: among the manuscripts, letters, books, juvenilia and realia on display, Victorian material is modest, modern prolific, Beat largely weighted toward Jack Kerouac. There is no particular story being told here, other than that of a shopping spree, seven years long -- but it is shopping of a culturally significant variety, as the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature grows and stretches to preserve larger and larger swaths of the tangible record of our literary past.</p>
        <p>Time is the great unstated theme present in these glass and steel cases. Time as one measure of a writer's reputation, and endurance. Time as the prison warden to all sentient beings, whose ideas about sexuality, politics, mental illness and justice are often painfully limited by the thinking of a particular moment, or context. Time as both an instigator of and liberator from pain that can be human, relational or professional (if only young, anxious Jack Kerouac had known the fate of ''On the Road''; if only John Cheever had realized he didn't need to envy, he would easily hold his own against the competition; if only Dylan and Caitlin Thomas had stopped fighting so hard!).</p>
        <p>Time imposing an often heart-rending poignancy on this whole enterprise of looking back: at the good-girl Sylvia Plath, making tender drawings for her sick brother (of herself she says: ''She is the one who smiles, and is always polite''); at Vanessa Bell perceiving young Virginia Woolf's fragility; at E. B. White having an insight about New York City so prescient as to make one's chest tighten at the mystery and the power of perception.</p>
        <p>A certain amount of time has to happen before these scraps of paper are deemed worthy of being collected. How does one know -- of contemporary writers -- when their moment has come? ''This is something that goes on in the head of every curator,'' says Isaac Gewirtz, who has been the Berg's custodian since last fall. ''You pay attention to reputations. You think of the established areas of concentration. You read and develop your own interests. But most curators will say you never regret what you've bought -- you regret what you haven't.''</p>
        <p>Time (or rather timing), economics, scholarship, intuition: these are the factors that mold any collection. And then there are circumstance and coincidence, an ''Aspern Papers''-like congruence of human behavior and want, detective work and attic clearing. Thus you find a friend, biographer and executor of Walt Whitman's pasting examples of the poet's writing into an album that, 150 years later, are lifted off the page to reveal, on their verso, some unknown aphoristic fragments. You find Allen Ginsberg's stepmother, on her way to an assisted-living residence, coming upon a folder of the poet's letters home. You find W. H. Auden's Italian translator sitting on a striking group of letters since the mid-1960's. And you find Caitlin Thomas's son by her companion Giuseppe Fazio, an Italian actor, in possession of Thomas's wallet. All are now in the Berg.</p>
        <p>Time lends a kind of magical sheen to a writer's juvenilia; backward-glancing and biography-reading, we think we can see the future previewed in these block-written, drawing-embellished bits and pieces. The Berg has Plath imaginatively cheering her brother: who can look at that lovingly traced dog and read those words and not think of the visceral rebellion against smiling and politeness that lay ahead in her life?</p>
        <p>There is an album kept by John Auden, the poet's brother, ''Summer Holidays 1913,'' which Mr. Gewirtz has cunningly opened to a photograph of the famously unathletic Auden practicing his climbing skills. What to make of that? Or of Christopher Isherwood dictating (to his mother) ''The Adventures of a Daddie and a Mummie'': is it possible for a 4-year-old to contain the seed of a memoirist? (''Kathleen and Frank: The Autobiography of a Family,'' his grown-up version of these adventures, appeared in 1971.)</p>
        <p>As a boy, Isherwood devised an imaginary railway, where the fare was one bobbin for every station passed during a journey. Kerouac, in his boyhood, prepared an elaborate fantasy baseball game, seen here in various iterations. Although Mr. Gewirtz cannot say exactly how the game was played, he does display tables, cards, statistics, box scores, a board against which an eraser was tossed to initiate the game, handbills and ''Baseball Chatter,'' Kerouac's newsletter that covered the exploits of managers and players on teams he named for automobiles (among them the Pittsburgh Plymouths, Boston Fords and Washington Chryslers).</p>
        <p>In its detail and obsessiveness, at least, Kerouac's fantasy baseball evokes the Brontës' imaginary chronicles of Gondal and Angria: in the play of adolescence, lifelong lessons in craft, discipline and detail would appear to coalesce.</p>
        <p>A Man of His Era</p>
        <p>Time the imprisoner. This is the powerful one. Letter writers, like diarists, are locked in an eternal present; we read their letters and diaries from the vantage point of an ever-mutating, differently informed future.</p>
        <p>You feel this gap with special ache in letters that Auden wrote to his brother John and to Aurora Ciliberto, his Italian translator, on the subject of his homosexuality.</p>
        <p>''Though reason tells me that homosexuality is a derangement of nature, and, as a Christian, I must acknowledge that to be homosexual is to be in sin,'' he writes to Ciliberto, ''I must honestly say that I have never had any feelings of guilt about the matter, nor felt in any way 'alienated' from normal people. But then I am in the fortunate position of having a vocation in life which is more important to me than personal relations.''</p>
        <p>This is Auden in one frame of mind. In another he writes to his brother that he is going to a psychoanalyst because ''I wish to improve my inferiority complex and to develop heterosexual traits.'' In still another (again to Ciliberto), he postulates that his homosexuality is linked to the fact that when his father went into the army he was 7, the age when a boy first begins to ''take notice'' of his dad.</p>
        <p>It is hard not to read these letters without wondering how Auden would think about his sexual nature in what is surely a much more enlightened, and accepting, social and psychological moment.</p>
        <p>The Pleasure of Hindsight</p>
        <p>A different kind of ache comes forward as we read Vanessa Bell describing a walk her sister Virginia Woolf (whose family nickname at the time was Goat) took with their father, when she saw a woman on a bicycle collide with a cart: ''The poor old Goat was in a dreadful state as you may think, and now she wants me to give up riding altogether, which of course I shan't do. It's very unlucky that it should always be the Goat who sees accidents.'' The unluckiness of Virginia always seeing the accidents: there's foresight for you.</p>
        <p>Hindsight brings on a wry smile elsewhere. At Aldous Huxley, when he raises the carbon dioxide levels in his blood, which results in ''swirling coloured patterns -- followed by a wonderful sense of detachment,'' as he writes to Raymond Mortimer. (We recognize this as just one of his many experiments with hallucinogenic drugs). At Anaïs Nin, who, in a reproachful (and most likely unsent) letter to her lover Henry Miller, complains, ''When you were writing the erotica and said you must stop because of your integrity you didn't think of my integrity -- you should have.'' Isn't this a case of the kettle and the pot? (''Delta of Venus,'' Nin's own erotica and her most commercially successful book, was published posthumously in 1977.)</p>
        <p>Then there's Cheever, who pits himself first against Irwin Shaw (he ''writes 17 pages a day, but he can't ski as well as I can'') and next against J. D. Salinger. After being asked by William Shawn to trim one of his New Yorker short stories, while Salinger is allowed to go on at length, Cheever calls Shawn up, he reports in a letter to a friend, and says: ''You can get that Godamned sixth-rate Salinger to write your Godamned short stories but don't expect anything more out of me. If you want to slam a door on someone's genitals find yourself another victim.'' To this we want to say (after ''ouch''), ''Dear Mr. C.: Not to worry, it turns out that there is room for all three of you on our reading docket.''</p>
        <p>The documents that stand most outside of time here are those that reveal writers thinking about their craft or at work on it, and they are among the richest. From V. S. Pritchett we hear that his real interest has been in ''character, and to reveal character layer by layer.'' His stories, he writes, ''are very compressed, so that by a word, a line or an image I can press what usually goes into a novel at great length, crystallized and intensified by being in the short form.'' From Ginsberg we hear that ''Normal speech has great rhythms'' and that ''Certain impulses like howling or screeching, &amp; certain material, demands its own form.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence Durrell, differentiating himself from Nin, observes that ''in my own case I prefer not to get too explicit, I feel I like to operate from the unconscious and not run the risk of writing theses.''</p>
        <p>Kerouac the Reviser</p>
        <p>The writer as reviser, or annotator, always compels. The myth of Kerouac's composition of ''On the Road'' -- written in three exhilarating, breathless weeks, in one draft on a single 120-foot scroll -- is here dispelled by examples of both preceding fragments and subsequent, extensively edited and rewritten typescripts. This material is part of the Berg's recently acquired compendious Kerouac archive, organized by the author himself, that joins previously collected material and now appears to include almost everything of significance but the scroll.</p>
        <p>The latter was bought at auction last year by James Irsay, owner of the Indianapolis Colts. In the interests of scholarship, it can only be hoped, he will one day see to it that the scroll joins its brothers at the Berg.</p>
        <p>Plath's copy of T. S. Eliot's ''Four Quartets'' shows her to be the most diligent of students and readers: there is an annotation on virtually every line. Eliot himself revises his opinion of Thomas Hardy (in a letter to Roy Morrell, a fellow director of Faber and Faber), though of Hardy's poetry he says he should have ''pruned down his collection to the best.''</p>
        <p>The poet Louis Zukovsky writes ''rubbish'' next to one of his own images, and from Saul Bellow there is an instructive example of the revising writer. In a fragment from ''Humboldt's Gift,'' the sentence ''Much later I visited the Ilscombe, the scene of Humboldt's death,'' Mr. Bellow changes the final phrase to ''to see where Humboldt died,'' thereby retaining the narrator, Charlie Citrine, as the agent of the sentence, and action.</p>
        <p>''The place was tacky, a sewer stink coming from the pipes,'' Mr. Bellow writes farther on; then he changes ''a sewer stink'' to ''sewer-gusts.'' The phrase is less obvious -- we expect a sewer to stink; its gusts take us by surprise. What a pro.</p>
        <p>A Fear for the Island Fantasy</p>
        <p>And now back to time -- and in time, to 1949, when E. B. White published ''Here Is New York,'' his paean to the city. The Berg has White's own uncorrected proof copy, with his pencil emendations. Here is one passage White did not especially mark, but of course we now do, and have been since Sept. 11:</p>
        <p>''The city, for the first time in its long history, is destructible. A single flight of planes no bigger than a wedge of geese can quickly end this island fantasy, burn the towers, crumble the bridges, turn the underground passages into lethal chambers, cremate the millions. The intimation of mortality is part of New York now: in the sound of jets overhead, in the black headlines of the latest edition.''</p>
        <p>''Of all targets,'' White continues, ''New York has a certain clear priority. In the mind of whatever perverted dreamer might loose the lightning, New York must hold a steady, irresistible charm.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to know what to feel in the face of such foreshadowing except humbled. Time does that, above all.</p>
        <p>Literary Lore</p>
        <p>''Victorians, Moderns and Beats: New in the Berg Collection, 1994-2001'' opens today in the Gottesman Exhibition Hall at the New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089. The show runs through July 27. Hours: Mondays and Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; and Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 11 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. Free admission.</p>
        <p>Michael Frank is a short-story writer and book critic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Frank is a short-story writer and book critic.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
