<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Keep Mosquitoes From Biting</title>
    <meta content="04HOME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/04/realestate/residential/04HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1413276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D8163BF937A3575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1367" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Keep Mosquitoes From Biting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How to Keep Mosquitoes From Biting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jay Romano's Your Home column on precautions homeowners should take to prevent mosquitoes from entering home in wake of West Nile virus outbreak; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH West Nile virus having been detected in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut and 30 other states and, as of last month, in all five boroughs of New York City, health officials are urging residents to ratchet up their precautions against mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>The lines of defense against mosquitoes range from preventive techniques such as eliminating the pools of water in which they breed to deploying electronic devices to lure and then kill them and, as a final barrier, a skin application that sends them away confused, before they can bite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's prime season, and there are many precautions homeowners can take to try to keep mosquitoes away from their property.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH West Nile virus having been detected in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut and 30 other states and, as of last month, in all five boroughs of New York City, health officials are urging residents to ratchet up their precautions against mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>The lines of defense against mosquitoes range from preventive techniques such as eliminating the pools of water in which they breed to deploying electronic devices to lure and then kill them and, as a final barrier, a skin application that sends them away confused, before they can bite.</p>
        <p>''Mosquitoes are reproducing constantly throughout the summer,'' said Dr. Michael Potter, an urban entomologist at the University of Kentucky in Lexington. ''And their reproductive cycle is very fast. If an adult lays its eggs today, you can have another generation of mosquitoes in a week.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Potter said that understanding the life cycle of mosquitoes could help residents exercise some control over how many of the insects they will be exposed to.</p>
        <p>He said that the kind of mosquito identified by health officials as the carrier of West Nile virus -- Culex pipiens, the common household mosquito -- typically laid its eggs on the surface of standing water. ''The eggs hatch and in a couple of days the hatchlings turn into wrigglers, the wrigglers turn into tumblers, and then, in another day or two, the tumblers transform into biting adult mosquitoes,'' he said. ''So if you have standing water for longer than three or four days, you've got a potential breeding ground that could soon be teeming with mosquitoes.''</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, the most significant action a homeowner can take to control mosquitoes is to eliminate standing water.</p>
        <p>''This is often easier said than done since breeding locations are not always obvious,'' Dr. Potter said. Old tires, plastic sheeting, rain gutters, birdbaths, dog dishes, flower pots, puddles, buckets and even boats can all become mosquito factories, he said, if water is allowed to stand in them. But while eliminating unwanted standing water is an effective way to control mosquito populations around a home, some standing water on a property may not necessarily unwanted. ''Ornamental ponds can also become breeding grounds for mosquitoes,'' Dr. Potter said, adding that there were several ways to deal with such areas of standing water.</p>
        <p>''Consider stocking ornamental ponds with predacious minnows,'' he said, referring to inch-and-a-half-long minnows also known as mosquito fish. Another approach with ponds is to apply a mosquito-specific insecticide that prevents the mosquito larvae from developing in the water.</p>
        <p>Products containing the insect growth-regulating substance methoprene, or the bacterium Bacillus thuringiensis var israeliensis, are harmless to fish and other aquatic organisms but lethal to wrigglers and tumblers. (Online retailers of such products -- including Altosid, Mosquito Dunks, Bactimos and Vectobac -- can be found by entering the product name in any search engine.)</p>
        <p>Another type of product that can keep ponds from becoming mosquito-breeding grounds but that do not kill the insects directly are substances known as surfactants that coat the top of the water. One such product is Agnique MMF, made by the Cognis Corporation in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>''Agnique MMF uses a nontoxic, physical action to control both disease-carrying and nuisance mosquitoes,'' said Frank Lachut, a senior technical service chemist for the company. Mr. Lachut said that when Agnique was applied to a body of water, the substance spread quickly and completely across the surface, coating it with an invisible, one-molecule-thick film that reduced the water's surface tension. Surface tension, the quality that lets water support a small amount of weight, is critical to mosquito development since mosquito larvae need surface tension to hold their breathing tubes out of the water. ''So when the little wrigglers come up and try to attach to the surface to breathe, they sink instead,'' Mr. Lachut said. ''It basically drowns them.''</p>
        <p>Those who are unsuccessful at keeping baby mosquitoes from turning into biting ones have a number of options for dealing with adult mosquitoes. One product is called the Mosquito Magnet. According to Rick Dunne, vice president of sales and marketing for American Biophysics, the device's manufacturer in East Greenwich, R.I., the Mosquito Magnet ''mimics a large mammal by emitting a plume of carbon dioxide, heat and moisture.''</p>
        <p>Once an unsuspecting mosquito gets close enough to its presumably attractive target to dine, the Mosquito Magnet vacuums the insect into a net where it dehydrates and dies.</p>
        <p>''No electric killing grid or pesticides are used,'' Mr. Dunne said, adding that the product, which sells for $495, uses electricity and propane gas to operate. (Additional information is on American Biophysics' Web site at www.mosquitomagnet.com.)</p>
        <p>Another device designed to attract and trap adult mosquitoes is the SonicWeb Biting Insect Control, manufactured by Applica Consumer Products in Miami Lakes, Fla.</p>
        <p>''The SonicWeb is the first mosquito control device that is sound driven,'' said Chris Mitchell, a spokesman for the company. ''When I say it's sound driven, I mean that we're using sound as the long-range attractant. It's sort of like a decoy in that we're mimicking a mammal's heartbeats with low-frequency sound.'' The product, which Mr. Mitchell said would provide control over about an acre, uses a glue-coated trap to catch curious mosquitoes. (The SonicWeb costs $300 and is available at some larger department stores.)</p>
        <p>A less sophisticated method involves killing mosquitoes outright with pesticides. Dr. Potter, the entomologist, said that since adult mosquitoes liked to rest in dense vegetation during the day, it might be possible to reduce their numbers by applying insecticides to the lower limbs of shade trees and to shrubs and shaded areas around foundations.</p>
        <p>Products containing pyrethroids, he said, are generally most effective and can be efficiently applied using a garden hose attached to a special sprayer on the bottle. Among the pyrethroid-based products available in home and garden centers are Ortho Bug-Be-Gone Ready Spray, Bayer Advanced Powerforce Multi-Insect Killer and Spectracide Triazicide Soil and Turf Insect Killer.</p>
        <p>(Dr. Potter added that things like citronella candles and bug zappers -- those backyard gadgets that attract mosquitoes with ultraviolet light and electrocute them loudly -- were only marginally effective, at best. ''Studies indicate that less than 5 percent of the mosquitoes killed by bug zappers are females, the only ones that actually bite,'' he said. ''The rest are nonbiting, male mosquitoes and other harmless night-flying insects.'' Citronella candles, he said, are better at providing atmosphere than repelling mosquitoes.)</p>
        <p>The last line of defense is barricading oneself indoors and making sure all windows and doors have screens. Those who venture outside might want to use topically applied mosquito repellents. Dr. Jonathan Day, a professor of medical entomology at the University of Florida Research Lab in Vero Beach, said the most effective topically applied mosquito repellent is a chemical known as diethyl toluamide, or DEET.</p>
        <p>''DEET is the gold standard that all other repellents are compared to,'' Dr. Day said, adding that the chemical was used in a number of over-the-counter insect repellents.</p>
        <p>He said that different products had different concentrations of DEET. Those with higher concentrations, he said, are not necessarily better at repelling mosquitoes, but will repel mosquitoes for longer than those with lower concentrations. So a product that contains 8 percent DEET will last for two to three hours, while a repellent with 30 percent DEET will last six to eight hours.</p>
        <p>And how does DEET work? ''The present theory is that all biting insects use exhaled carbon dioxide to find you,'' Dr. Day said, adding that rather than smell the carbon dioxide, mosquitoes detect it through receptors on their legs and antennae. ''Well, it looks like DEET also stimulates those receptors,'' Dr. Day said. ''But once they touch the DEET, they go into overstimulus mode.''</p>
        <p>While DEET is not really a repellent, he said -- mosquitoes typically touch skin DEET is on -- once they get it on their legs or antennae, they become so overstimulated they lose interest in their prey. ''The mosquito is on total information overload,'' he said. ''It will just fly away, land someplace, and sit there doing nothing for two or three hours.''</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
