<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Sierra Club criticizes Ford's chief in a campaign for fuel-efficient cars.</title>
    <meta content="Y13ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/13/business/media/13ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1400134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerrey, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanahan, Jack (Vice Adm) (Ret)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sierra Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDB173CF930A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Sierra Club criticizes Ford's chief in a campaign for fuel-efficient cars.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Sierra Club Singles Out Ford's Chief in New Campaign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Danny Hakim</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Club introduces advertising campaign that ties fuel economy to patriotism and calls for action by Ford Motor Co chairman-chief executive William Clay Ford Jr, who was once viewed by group as ally; campaign, produced by Haddow Communications, is being rolled out in dozen states; campaign includes radio spot and television ads featuring former Sen Bob Kerrey and Jack Shanahan, retired vice admiral; both men urge auto industry to take action to cut oil use; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Sierra Club introduced an advertising campaign yesterday that ties fuel economy to patriotism and calls for action by William Clay Ford Jr., the chairman and chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, who was once viewed by the group as an ally.</p>
        <p>The campaign, produced by Haddow Communications, is being rolled out in a dozen states. The campaign includes a radio spot and television ads featuring Bob Kerrey, the former Nebraska senator, and Jack Shanahan, a retired vice admiral. Both men urge the auto industry to take action to cut oil use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sierra Club introduced an advertising campaign Wednesday that ties fuel economy to patriotism and calls for action by Ford's William Clay Ford Jr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Sierra Club introduced an advertising campaign yesterday that ties fuel economy to patriotism and calls for action by William Clay Ford Jr., the chairman and chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, who was once viewed by the group as an ally.</p>
        <p>The campaign, produced by Haddow Communications, is being rolled out in a dozen states. The campaign includes a radio spot and television ads featuring Bob Kerrey, the former Nebraska senator, and Jack Shanahan, a retired vice admiral. Both men urge the auto industry to take action to cut oil use.</p>
        <p>''It's time for us to tell the auto industry that we want to break the grip of oil-producing countries and reduce our oil use,'' Mr. Kerrey said in one spot, which also showed pictures of oil fields burning in Kuwait during the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>The advertisements encourage consumers to ask dealers for a so-called freedom option package. Instead of air-conditioned seats or a sunroof, the Sierra Club wants people to buy cars with eco-friendly features like continuously variable transmissions, which obtain better mileage by using an infinite number of gears, and integrated starter-generators, which shut off engines while idling.</p>
        <p>The group said only the Toyota Prius, from Toyota Motor, and a new version of the Honda Civic, from Honda Motor, which both use hybrid engines that combine gasoline and electric power, offer the entire freedom package.</p>
        <p>But the most surprising part of the campaign is that it singles out one company, and one man, in particular -- Mr. Ford -- in a radio ad.</p>
        <p>''Now more than ever, America needs cars that get better gas mileage,'' says a narrator in the ad, which began showing in Washington yesterday.</p>
        <p>''That's why we're asking Bill Ford, head of the Ford Motor Company, to do his part and to produce more fuel-efficient cars, S.U.V.'s and pickup trucks.''</p>
        <p>In October, Mr. Ford became chief executive of the company founded by his great-grandfather. Before that he was perceived as an iconoclast, a Detroit executive with a green image who would talk about issues like global warming. Groups like the Sierra Club were quite hopeful that he would lead the company to break with the industry's lobbying against toughening fuel-economy regulations.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Ford kept the company in the trade groups that backed the industry's campaigns against higher federal gas mileage standards during a Senate debate earlier this year, souring relations with several environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Still, the Sierra Club considers General Motors and the Chrysler Group of DaimlerChrysler to be more entrenched opponents on fuel-economy legislation, so why single out Mr. Ford?</p>
        <p>''If you want somebody to lead, you go to somebody who wants to be a leader,'' said Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club. ''We think Bill Ford wants to be a leader, but there are people in his company who don't want him to be a leader.''</p>
        <p>He added that the radio ad was intended ''to up the cost of not leading'' by calling into question the image the company has fostered as being concerned about environmental issues.</p>
        <p>Ford did pledge in 2000 to improve the fuel economy of its sport utility vehicles by 25 percent over five years, leading G.M. and Chrysler to say they would match Ford. And Ford has said it will come out with what would be the first sport utility vehicle to use a hybrid engine next year. But since becoming chief executive, Mr. Ford is faced with a struggling company that lost $5.5 billion last year and has not been vocal on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>''There is no dissension within Ford over our commitment to deliver improved fuel economy,'' Mr. Ford said in a statement.</p>
        <p>''The Sierra Club chose to target Ford and me personally because we are seen as leaders,'' he added. ''I think that's ironic because I have often been criticized for being too far out front on this issue. But we will not change the course we are on and will not alter our commitment to improving the fuel efficiency of our products.''</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club intended to start running the radio spot in Detroit yesterday as well as Washington but has not yet found a local station willing to play the ad.</p>
        <p>''We felt it was inappropriate for the Sierra Club to single out an individual and attack an individual in the ad,'' said Rich Homberg, general manager of WWJ, a local news station owned by Viacom.</p>
        <p>Ford has been one of the station's advertisers, but Mr. Homberg said the decision was made on the merits of the ad.</p>
        <p>''Singling out the C.E.O. of a major automaker, especially one who was in the forefront of the issue, seems inappropriate,'' he said. ''We're one of the stations that sets the standard for journalism in this community. We didn't make this call lightly.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
