<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Montreal to Rio to Johannesburg: 15 Years of Environmental Accords</title>
    <meta content="20TREA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/20/science/earth/20TREA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1417215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MANAGING PLANET EARTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4D7103DF933A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Montreal to Rio to Johannesburg: 15 Years of Environmental Accords</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">15 Years of Environmental Accords</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on variety of strategies tried by conservationists and scientists to preserve world's native plant and animal species from exotic invaders; growing number of biologists say change should be accepted as inevitable and choices for managing nature should be based on what is desirable and undesirable, not what is native and foreign; photos; graphs; map (Special Report: Managing Planet Earth) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dozens of international accords aimed at protecting the environment have been enacted in recent decades. Some are fine-tuned, like an agreement adopted last year to save albatrosses and petrels. Others are as broad as the atmosphere, including treaties that ban ozone-destroying chemicals.</p>
        <p>At the World Summit on Sustainable Development, which starts on Monday in Johannesburg, world leaders will negotiate a declaration of new goals for this century but will not produce any formal treaty. Following are major recent environmental treaties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dozens of international accords aimed at protecting the environment have been enacted in recent decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dozens of international accords aimed at protecting the environment have been enacted in recent decades. Some are fine-tuned, like an agreement adopted last year to save albatrosses and petrels. Others are as broad as the atmosphere, including treaties that ban ozone-destroying chemicals.</p>
        <p>At the World Summit on Sustainable Development, which starts on Monday in Johannesburg, world leaders will negotiate a declaration of new goals for this century but will not produce any formal treaty. Following are major recent environmental treaties.</p>
        <p>2001 STOCKHOLM CONVENTION ON PERSISTENT ORGANIC POLLUTANTS -- Signed by the United States and most other countries last year, this convention, once it takes effect, will phase out the ''dirty dozen,'' a group of harmful, long-lived organic compounds, including DDT and dioxins.</p>
        <p>1997 KYOTO PROTOCOL -- The Kyoto climate treaty requires 38 industrial nations by 2012 to cut releases of heat-trapping greenhouse gases below 1990 levels. It was signed during the Clinton administration but rejected last year by President Bush. It serves as a rider to the Framework Convention on Climate Change, which was adopted at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro a decade ago. The Kyoto accord has been ratified by Europe, Japan and many other countries. It still requires ratification by Russia, possibly by next year, to enter into force in the nations that endorse it.</p>
        <p>1992 FRAMEWORK CONVENTION ON CLIMATE CHANGE -- This agreement, signed by the United States and almost all other countries, took effect in 1994. But it called only for voluntary measures to reduce industrial-country emissions by 2000 to 1990 levels. The measures did not work. Global emissions rose 10 percent in that span, and American emissions rose 16 percent.</p>
        <p>1992 CONVENTION ON BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY -- Adopted at the Rio summit, this treaty, which took effect in 1993, gives countries legal control of their biological resources and the right to share in profits should they be developed into drugs or other valuable products. But conservationists have recently criticized the agreement for failing to spur more preservation of threatened ecosystems.</p>
        <p>1987 MONTREAL PROTOCOL ON SUBSTANCES THAT DEPLETE THE OZONE LAYER -- This agreement, signed and ratified by most countries, including the United States, was enacted in 1989. It updated an earlier treaty, the 1985 Vienna Convention on the ozone layer. The Montreal pact sharply limits production of chlorofluorocarbons and other substances that destroy the beneficial veil of ozone in the upper atmosphere, which blocks most of the sun's harmful ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>The protocol is widely judged to have worked well. Levels of the harmful compounds have plunged, and the ozone layer is predicted to rebuild within 50 years or so. But the agreement's success occurred, in large part, because substitutes for the harmful chemicals were readily available and the problem was made vividly clear by satellite measurements.</p>
        <p>MANAGING PLANET EARTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
