<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Hopes for Gas From Gasoline</title>
    <meta content="Y14FUEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/14/business/14FUEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1375664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ztek</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hsu, Michael S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED71339F937A25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Hopes for Gas From Gasoline</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Company Hoping to Sell Fuel Cells</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WOBURN, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ztek has developed machine that makes hydrogen from gasoline; president-chief executive Michael S Hsu says unit can convert 10 gallons of gasoline into 4,000 cubic feet of hydrogen each hour; company believes it can produce units for $300,000 each if it has enough orders to reach steady level of production; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like a salesman at a party supply store, a technician at the Ztek lab here gently unfolded a Mylar balloon and inserted a little plastic hose to fill it with a gas that made it float stiffly at the end of a string. But the gas was not helium, it was hydrogen.</p>
        <p>Even more odd was the source: gasoline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 19 years of research and development, a privately held start-up says it can help put pollution-free cars on the street, and it hopes to sell its first hydrogen-making machines soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like a salesman at a party supply store, a technician at the Ztek lab here gently unfolded a Mylar balloon and inserted a little plastic hose to fill it with a gas that made it float stiffly at the end of a string. But the gas was not helium, it was hydrogen.</p>
        <p>Even more odd was the source: gasoline.</p>
        <p>Ztek's balloons were not for birthday parties but part of a demonstration of making hydrogen for fuel cells, which use that fuel to make electricity.</p>
        <p>After 19 years of research and development, the company, a privately held start-up, says its process can help put pollution-free cars on the street, and it hopes to sell its first hydrogen-making machines soon. [In fact, the State of Connecticut announced Wednesday that it had chosen Ztek as part of a demonstration project that the company hopes will be worth $500,000.]</p>
        <p>Ztek is the latest entry in a race toward a widely sought goal, a way to manufacture nature's simplest molecule, two hydrogen atoms, so it can be delivered to a fuel cell. Fuel cells are highly efficient, almost silent and emission free, making them potentially tremendously attractive for powering cars and other vehicles.</p>
        <p>President Bush seemed to accept  some of that vision in February, when he kicked the tires of a hydrogen-powered Chrysler Town and Country minivan at an event on the South Lawn of the White House. ''Fuel cells will power cars with little or no waste at all,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>But there are plenty of complications. Current processes for making hydrogen are cumbersome or not very efficient or both. The fuel does not exist in nature, and turns out to be rather hard to find in industry, too. While oil refineries make hydrogen, for use in the refining process, the molecule is so small that it would escape from conventional  pipelines.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that hydrogen can be made using renewable sources, especially solar power cells. The low-voltage direct current they produce is perfect for cooking water (H2 O) into hydrogen and oxygen. The environmentalists can imagine fields of solar cells in deserts, creating hydrogen for fleets of fuel cell vehicles. But, at the moment solar cells are expensive, and there is no efficient way to get vast amounts of remotely produced hydrogen to service stations.</p>
        <p>And there is, said the manager of the fuel cell program at one automaker, also a ''chicken and egg'' problem: no one will want to buy fuel cell cars until the fuel is available, and no one will market the fuel until there are customers driving cars that use it.</p>
        <p>At the moment, no one can make a fuel cell at a competitive cost, but the fuel cell people look at hydrogen production as the problem. In that field, ''the technology development hasn't kept pace with the desires,'' said Robert Rose, director of the United States Fuel Cell Council, a trade group. There also is another cost problem. A new book, ''Tomorrow's Energy: Hydrogen, Fuel Cells and the Prospects for a Cleaner Planet,'' by Peter Hoffmann, (M.I.T. Press, 2001) puts the cost of hydrogen at anywhere from 40 percent as expensive as gasoline to almost four times as much, per unit of energy, although the fuel cell might get more work out of each unit of energy.</p>
        <p>Enter Ztek. Its product so far is a prototype, which lives in the back of a small panel truck so it can be hauled around for demonstrations. The full-size unit would fill a bay in a service station.</p>
        <p>The company's projections of cost and efficiency are imprecise, since there is no standard estimate of how many cubic feet of gas a typical car would consume. But Michael S. S. Hsu, Ztek's president and chief executive, said that the bay-size unit could convert 10 gallons of gasoline into about 4,000 cubic feet of hydrogen each hour. Running around the clock, this would be enough to give 30 to 40 cars a day their weekly fill-up. The company believes it could produce the units for $300,000 each if it had enough orders to reach a steady level of production.</p>
        <p>The $300,000 is far from attractive commercially, but Dr. Hsu says it could be used to support a fleet as a demonstration. It is too soon to say if the technology will catch on, but it could offer a kick-start to the hydrogen vehicle business.</p>
        <p>In the prototype device, gasoline runs over a material that acts as a catalyst. In a high-temperature chemical reaction, the gasoline is broken down into hydrogen, carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>The company has a longer-term plan that would produce far more hydrogen than was in the gasoline originally. The plan would bundle the reformer, the part that converts other chemicals into hydrogen, with a fuel cell, a high-temperature model called a solid oxide cell. The solid oxide cell runs at about 1,000 degrees Celsius (1,800 degrees Fahrenheit). The waste heat can be used to heat the carbon monoxide, which is then mixed with water. There, the carbon monoxide reacts with the water, or H2 O, stealing an oxygen atom to become carbon dioxide. The H2 O, robbed of the O, becomes hydrogen gas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hsu said that by linking the reformer to the fuel cell, ''the energy required for the reformer is free.'' And the carbon dioxide could potentially be brought off in a separate stream, allowing it to be sequestered. The electricity from the solid oxide cell would be used to pressurize the hydrogen, for delivery to cars. The system, he said, would use up only 15 percent of the energy in the gasoline.</p>
        <p>Since a fuel cell will push a car more than twice as far on a unit of energy than an internal combustion engine will, this would still allow substantial gains in efficiency.</p>
        <p>[The Connecticut project announced Wednesday also involves a fuel cell and a reformer, but the main product will be electricity, not hydrogen; it will produce only as much hydrogen as the fuel cell will consume.]</p>
        <p>When Dr. Hsu began work, his approach was seen as radical, because the advocates of fuel cells were focusing on ''on-board reformers,'' essentially small refineries that would fit under the hood and convert natural gas, methanol or gasoline to hydrogen for immediate use.</p>
        <p>This made it easier to store the hydrogen, but also made a car that was tremendously complex and costly. And its inefficiency and the pollutants from the process of making hydrogen tended to cancel out the fuel cell's advantages.</p>
        <p>In the last few years, though, mainstream thinking has moved in Dr. Hsu's direction.</p>
        <p>''The auto industry and most of the oil industry would be extremely enthusiastic if a system were developed,'' said Mr. Rose of the Fuel Cell Council. ''It would make their lives easier.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
