<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Threat of Terrorism Is Shaping the Focus Of Bush Presidency</title>
    <meta content="11BUSH$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1422808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE WHITE HOUSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1531F932A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="2066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Threat of Terrorism Is Shaping the Focus Of Bush Presidency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER and DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth; Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush, who after last Sept 11 declared terrorism to be 'focus' of his untried administration, has kept that priority despite year in which economy, corporate scandals and Middle East violence have blown him off course; Bush now seems determined to use attack to justify this year's pursuit of Iraq's Saddam Hussein, even though two are clearly not yet linked in minds of his fellow Americans or European allies; linkage in Bush's mind between Osama bin Laden and Hussein has created pre-emption policy encapsulating Bush view that US must strike before it is struck again; Bush's most hawkish advisers in fact urged action against Hussein in first days after Sept 11, even absent any evidence that he was involved; adviser Condoleezza Rice insists there is no choice but to depart from Bush's campaign promise of 'humble foreign policy'; Bush begins each day by reviewing 'threat assessment,' compilation of latest US intelligence, and aides say daily reminders have sharpened and sobered him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only 48 hours after the attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon, George W. Bush first defined the role that the campaign against terrorism would play in his untried presidency. ''The nation must understand,'' Mr. Bush said somberly, speaking to reporters on a sparkling morning in the Oval Office, ''this is now the focus of my administration.''</p>
        <p>In the year since then, Mr. Bush has seen how difficult that focus has been to sustain. The economy, the corporate scandals and the violence in the Middle East have blown him off course, and are certain to again. But the terrorist threat has remained his priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only 48 hours after the attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon, George W. Bush first defined the role that the campaign against terrorism would play in his untried presidency. ''The nation must understand,'' Mr. Bush said somberly, speaking to reporters on a sparkling morning in the Oval Office, ''this is now the focus of my administration.''</p>
        <p>In the year since then, Mr. Bush has seen how difficult that focus has been to sustain. The economy, the corporate scandals and the violence in the Middle East have blown him off course, and are certain to again. But the terrorist threat has remained his priority.</p>
        <p>Today, as the White House put the nation on a heightened state of alert, Mr. Bush declared, ''Today and tomorrow we'll be reliving a horrible reminder of what is possible in the 21st century -- that is, no country is immune from attack.''</p>
        <p>That reality has shaped his presidency.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Bush seems determined to transform Sept. 11 into a milestone on the road to war with Iraq, and to use last year's attack by Osama bin Laden and the continued threat from Al Qaeda to justify this year's pursuit of Saddam Hussein. Clearly, the two are not yet linked in the minds of many Americans and most of America's allies. Before today's threat, polls showed Americans largely out of sync with the president, more worried about a jobless recovery than terrorism. But over the past year, the linkage in the president's mind between Mr. bin Laden and Mr. Hussein has grown tighter -- and given birth to a new policy of pre-emption that encapsulates Mr. Bush's view that the United States must strike before it is struck again.</p>
        <p>Iraq may be the first test of that approach, and of his ability to persuade the world that inaction will invite greater disasters. The president's most hawkish advisers in fact urged him to move against Mr. Hussein in the first days after the Sept. 11 attacks, even absent any evidence that he was involved.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush demurred at the time, White House advisers now assert that targeting Mr. Hussein was first set as a goal last fall, to be pursued as soon as the Taliban and Al Qaeda were routed from Afghanistan. They portray the president's Sept. 20 speech to Congress, when Mr. Bush outlined his administration's doctrine against terrorism, as a first step against Mr. Hussein. The next came in Mr. Bush's State of Union address in January that named Iraq as the leader of an ''axis of evil,'' along with Iran and North Korea.</p>
        <p>''There is a logical extension of what the president talked about on Sept. 20 a year ago, and in his State of the Union address, to the discussions that are taking place today,'' said Andrew H. Card Jr., the White House chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Condoleezza Rice, the president's national security adviser, acknowledges that the president's aggressive approach departs sharply from the ''humble foreign policy'' Mr. Bush talked about so often during his presidential campaign. But Ms. Rice says there is no other choice.</p>
        <p>''It's a wartime presidency,'' she said in an interview, using a phrase that Mr. Bush's aides now often toss around casually, even though it seems jarring to many Americans who see the country in a struggle with terrorists, but not a global all-out war.</p>
        <p>Others close to Mr. Bush say that his fears of another Sept. 11 are driving him so hard that they have crowded out other priorities.</p>
        <p>''He's not focused on the prescription drug bill and the farm bill, he's thinking about this,'' said Roland Betts, one of Mr. Bush's closest friends.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief political adviser, said the president has told his staff that although he wants a ''robust'' domestic agenda, ''I am not going to be able to spend as much time on it'' and that the staff will have to step in and do what he cannot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Betts added that Mr. Bush's urgency about Iraq was fueled by intelligence information and not the November midterm elections or any father-son psychodrama, a popular theory in Washington, over the first President Bush's decision not to march to Baghdad and oust Mr. Hussein during the Persian Gulf War.</p>
        <p>''He's not making this up,'' Mr. Betts said. ''This whole thing about finishing what his father left off is nonsense. He worries that these people will acquire and detonate some sort of weapon on our soil.''</p>
        <p>But unlike a year ago, when the nation and the world were with Mr. Bush as he struck back at the Taliban and Al Qaeda in Afghanistan, this time the president must do a lot of convincing. On Thursday he will make his case to the United Nations. He is confronting enormous skepticism, not only from Arabs and Europeans who warn of disaster ahead, but also from stalwart Republicans who fear he is diverting attention from a greater threat -- a resurgent Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>Without question, he is taking the biggest risk so far in his presidency.</p>
        <p>A Daily Report on Threats</p>
        <p>A key to Mr. Bush's state of mind is to know that every morning, in Washington, Camp David or on the road, he begins his working day with the ''threat assessment,'' a compilation of what United States intelligence services and law enforcement agencies pick up about potential terrorist activity. Mr. Bush, who asked for the summary in the first days after Sept. 11, is the first president to be presented daily with such an extensive, detailed catalog of the susceptibilities of the United States to terrorist attack. His advisers say it has both sharpened and sobered him.</p>
        <p>''The first reaction is, I'm glad I know about it,'' Ms. Rice said, adding that ''on the other hand, it reminds you every morning of the vulnerability.''</p>
        <p>The assessment, which runs 5 to 25 pages, includes a summarizing chart, or what White House advisers call a matrix. It lists the nature of each threat, the potential target, the method by which the United States gathered the intelligence, any corroborating information, and who has been notified, as Mr. Card put it, ''to mitigate the concern.''</p>
        <p>In the Oval Office, Mr. Bush usually reads through the threat assessment when he arrives between 6:45 and 7 a.m., then reviews it at the start of his first briefing of the day, from the Central Intelligence Agency, around 8. That briefing includes the president, Vice President Dick Cheney, Mr. Card, Ms. Rice and George Tenet, the director of central intelligence. Mr. Tenet also brings along a specialist, or briefer, to present the information.</p>
        <p>''The briefer might say, 'I want to call your attention to number three, we take this seriously, or 'We've had some information from another source that sounds similar, so we're going to see if they marry up,' '' Mr. Card said.</p>
        <p>The assessment is reviewed a second time at the start of Mr. Bush's next briefing, with the F.B.I. director, Robert S. Mueller III. That briefing, sometimes also attended by Mr. Tenet, is intended to focus on threats inside the United States, but also to force the F.B.I. and the C.I.A. to view the information as a whole -- exactly what they did not do in the months leading up to Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>White House advisers say much of what the president sees is finely grained detail, like the intelligence that led to today's decision to move to code orange for the first time, as well as broader warnings that are hard to assess.</p>
        <p>Some experienced intelligence experts say they fear that the president is being given too much information -- some of it unreliable, they say, some included because, in the words of one White House official, ''when the next attack happens, no one wants to be the one who left out the critical warning sign.''</p>
        <p>Strategy Is Pre-Emption</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides are circumspect when asked about the psychological impact of this daily barrage of threats. But from those pages has emerged a new national security strategy -- one based on pre-emption, and driven by Mr. Bush's often-expressed view that his presidency will be judged in large part by how well he neutralizes threats before they reach American shores again.</p>
        <p>The result is a tremendous shift in America's approach to dealing with enemies and allies -- a strike-first philosophy that is still a work in progress.</p>
        <p>''You can call it pre-emption, or preventative defense, or any other phrase you might read about in 'Foreign Affairs,' '' said one member of Mr. Bush's foreign policy team, who has often sat with the president in the Situation Room as he considers his options.</p>
        <p>''But it's old-fashioned self-protection -- and it comes from the president's gut,'' the adviser added. ''The example he refers to from time to time is the Cuban Missile Crisis. In his mind, it's got that urgency.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice, a former Stanford professor, insists that Mr. Bush is not creating an intellectual construct that will let the United States strike anywhere, anytime, without the sanction of the United Nations. But she insists that Sept. 11 reinforced the need for what she calls an ''organizing principle'' for how he would deal with the world, a way to adjust to an era in which, ''for less than the cost of a tank, terrorists wreaked unbelievable damage and havoc on the United States.''</p>
        <p>''The end of the cold war and Sept. 11 are kind of bookends,'' she said. ''You have a long transition in there, when people talked about, well, maybe it would be ethnic conflict that was the big threat, or the Army was just going to be for humanitarian purposes and peacekeeping.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is now convinced, she said, that ''terrorism and weapons of mass destruction, and the potential link between them, are the key threats.''</p>
        <p>This is not the kind of approach one might have expected listening to Mr. Bush in the 2000 campaign, a campaign in which terrorism and Saddam Hussein were scarcely discussed. Two years ago Mr. Bush himself was talking about an America that stuck to its knitting, that stayed out of what he dismissively called ''nation building,'' and offered no lectures or ultimatums.</p>
        <p>''I'm not so sure the role of the United States is to go around the world and say, 'This is the way it's got to be,' '' Mr. Bush said in his second debate against Al Gore.</p>
        <p>He clearly had amended that view even before Sept. 11. His early announcement that the Kyoto protocol on global warming was ''dead'' and then his withdrawal from the 1972 ABM treaty demonstrated a willingness to toss aside international accords if they got in his way. Then, stung by charges that he was a unilateralist, he tried to soften his tone, if not his belief.</p>
        <p>Then came Sept. 11. ''I think as a result of 9/11 particularly he sees the value of coalitions and friends,'' Secretary of State Colin L. Powell said in an interview earlier this summer. ''He saw the value of having people on his side.''</p>
        <p>But that attention to alliances seems episodic at best, and undercut by regular warnings that he ''reserves the right'' to act against Iraq alone. Some of Mr. Bush's Republican allies fear that in the past year the president's worldview has become an intensely dark one, that he focuses far more energy on striking out than building up, on routing despots rather than rebuilding schools.</p>
        <p>This has led to a resurgence of the cowboy images of Mr. Bush that were so prevalent before Sept. 11, and cemented in the eyes of many allies when he declined to attend the conference on sustainable development in South Africa this month.</p>
        <p>''What we are fighting,'' said one senior State Department official whose sympathies in the administration's battles lie clearly with Secretary Powell, ''is a view that he is willing to go to the U.N. to talk about whacking Saddam, but not about whether we should be driving so many SUV's, or the rest of the world's agenda. And while that view is overdrawn, it isn't entirely wrong.''</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE WHITE HOUSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
