<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming an Issue For National Parks</title>
    <meta content="01REP.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/01/travel/01REP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020915T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1420017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Park Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DE113CF932A3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming an Issue For National Parks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Global Warming an Issue for National Parks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel article on call by environmental advocacy groups, putting pressure on National Park Service, for regulations requiring park superintendents to draft specific plans for dealing with climate change over next century; groups view intense forest fires, exacerbated by drought and heat, as examples of threat global warming trends could pose to parks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN President Theodore Roosevelt established the world's first national park at Yellowstone, the idea was that with careful stewardship, nature's unspoiled expanses could be preserved forever. Nowadays scientists understand these ecosystems as giant circles of change, their evolution driven by the forces of nature but also by the actions of people.</p>
        <p>And as the parks' managers consider how the parks will look a generation, or seven generations, from now, they are increasingly aware that climate changes brought on by human activity are among the forces that may most alter some of the best known landscapes of the National Park System.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Park managers are increasingly aware that that climate changes brought on by human activity are among the forces that may most alter some of the best known landscapes of the National Park System.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN President Theodore Roosevelt established the world's first national park at Yellowstone, the idea was that with careful stewardship, nature's unspoiled expanses could be preserved forever. Nowadays scientists understand these ecosystems as giant circles of change, their evolution driven by the forces of nature but also by the actions of people.</p>
        <p>And as the parks' managers consider how the parks will look a generation, or seven generations, from now, they are increasingly aware that climate changes brought on by human activity are among the forces that may most alter some of the best known landscapes of the National Park System.</p>
        <p>Some environmental advocacy groups complain that the National Park Service is not doing enough to head off the problems. In June the Bluewater Network, an environmental advocacy group in San Francisco, filed petitions with the park service and other federal land agencies seeking more aggressive steps to mitigate damage to public lands from global warming. The group issued a report contending that by causing fires and drought, species extinction and migration, and increased risks of diseases, climate change jeopardizes the parks.</p>
        <p>The group asked the park service to write regulations requiring park superintendents to draft specific plans for dealing with climate change over the coming 100 years. It suggested, for example, that the plans consider how to shore up historic structures against flooding, how to use natural controls against invasive species that might move in as the climate changes, and whether to move park boundaries, create wildlife corridors outside the parks, or take other steps to maintain habitat for animals in the parks.</p>
        <p>The park service did not reply to a request for comment.</p>
        <p>The intense forest fires of the last 10 to 15 years, exacerbated by a decade of intense drought and heat, are widely considered a highly visible example of the kind of threat global warming trends could pose to parks.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, for example, a 2,600-acre fire in Mesa Verde National Park in Colorado destroyed housing for the park's staff, its sewage treatment plant and the roof of a million-gallon water tank, and threatened the park headquarters. The park was closed for almost two weeks and all visitors evacuated. And a 33,000-acre fire in Six Rivers National Forest in Northern California near Oregon came close to Redwood National Park and the ancient trees there that are one of the park systems' leading symbols.</p>
        <p>Even the slow, steady melting of the ice in national parks with glaciers, often cited as evidence of climate change, can result in cataclysms as the geology and hydrology of the mountains respond to new pressures. That happened in late July at Klondike Gold Rush National Historical Park in Alaska, when campers awoke to find the waters of the Taiya River swirling through their campground.</p>
        <p>Less than an inch of rain had fallen the day before, but the river rose between five and six feet in a matter of hours. Eight miles to the northwest, it turned out, a shelf of moraine next to a glacier had collapsed, dumping three-quarters of a billion cubic yards of soil and ice into the lake that sits at the bottom of the glacier.</p>
        <p>The lake's overflow, park rangers reported dryly, was a sign that the area is a ''dynamic glacial ecosystem.'' That's precisely what makes it so vulnerable to the long-term effects of climate change.</p>
        <p>Aside from what visitors to the parks see for themselves, researchers in some parks say they are already detecting subtler changes brought on by recent warming trends, which scientists say are probably caused at least in part by the emissions of greenhouse gases from burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The recent fires and glacial collapses are just what researchers are examining in the mountains of Olympic National Park and North Cascades National Park in Washington and Glacier National Park in Montana. Their project is helping identify regions that are especially vulnerable to rising temperatures, and helping park managers decide where to build roads, how to manage forest fires, how to allocate water for irrigation, and so on.</p>
        <p>The ecological questions are extraordinarily complex, and research into them will take years.</p>
        <p>In one project, for example, scientists working with the United States Geological Survey are examining how global warming, acid rain and other climate changes are affecting the soils, plants and animals in four parks and one preserve, each at a different latitude or elevation: Isle Royale National Park in Michigan, Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee, Olympic National Park in Washington, Big Bend National Park in Texas and Noatak National Preserve in Alaska.</p>
        <p>They are looking at how warming trends will affect rainfall, the melting of glaciers, changes in the tundra's permafrost, the forming of deserts and other physical changes. But in addition, they are also studying how these changes -- and resulting changes in what kinds of species thrive at each location -- interact with pollutants like acid rain and nitrates that permeate soils and waters as a result of air pollution.</p>
        <p>Their hypothesis is that the delicate balance of carbon and nitrate in the soil is likely to change under these influences, that populations of microbes living in the soil will ebb and flow, and that entire ecosystems may be altered as a result. The research is to continue until 2005.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, according to the recent report of the Bluewater Network, climate change ''threatens the ecosystems of every national park, refuge and seashore.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT  Correction:  September 15, 2002, Sunday  The Correspondent's Report column on Sept. 1, about the effects of global warming on national parks in the United States, misidentified the authority that established Yellowstone. It was Congress -- in 1872, when Ulysses S. Grant was president -- not Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 15, 2002, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Correspondent's Report column on Sept. 1, about the effects of global warming on national parks in the United States, misidentified the authority that established Yellowstone. It was Congress -- in 1872, when Ulysses S. Grant was president -- not Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
