<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If the Big One Hits the Big Easy, the Good Times May Be Over Forever</title>
    <meta content="11SUN3$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/11/opinion/11SUN3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1415171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DE123AF932A2575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If the Big One Hits the Big Easy, the Good Times May Be Over Forever</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If the Big One Hits, New Orleans Could Disappear</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Cohen Editorial Observer on grave threat that big hurricane could wipe out low-lying city of New Orleans; describes complacency of its people and inadequate preparations by government</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dot Wilson knows how bad the Big One could be. When Hurricane Betsy hit New Orleans in 1965 with 125 m.p.h. winds, leaving 75 dead in Louisiana and South Florida, she walked more than a mile in chest-high water, holding her infant daughter overhead. But when Ms. Wilson held a hurricane-preparedness teach-in recently at the community center she heads, attendance was sparse. ''A lot of people don't see storms as serious,'' she said with a sigh. But people who have been around for a while know better, she said, adding, ''We saw the bodies.''</p>
        <p>New Orleans -- home to the French Quarter's iron-latticed buildings and the Garden District's stately Greek Revival mansions, to Preservation Hall jazz and Mardi Gras parades -- may be America's most architecturally distinctive and culturally rich city. But it is also a disaster waiting to happen. New Orleans is the only major American city below sea level, and it is wedged between Lake Pontchartrain and the Mississippi. If a bad hurricane hit, experts say, the city could fill up like a cereal bowl, killing tens of thousands and laying waste to the city's architectural heritage. If the Big One hit, New Orleans could disappear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Washington needs to do more to prevent a future hurricane from filling up New Orleans like a cereal bowl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dot Wilson knows how bad the Big One could be. When Hurricane Betsy hit New Orleans in 1965 with 125 m.p.h. winds, leaving 75 dead in Louisiana and South Florida, she walked more than a mile in chest-high water, holding her infant daughter overhead. But when Ms. Wilson held a hurricane-preparedness teach-in recently at the community center she heads, attendance was sparse. ''A lot of people don't see storms as serious,'' she said with a sigh. But people who have been around for a while know better, she said, adding, ''We saw the bodies.''</p>
        <p>New Orleans -- home to the French Quarter's iron-latticed buildings and the Garden District's stately Greek Revival mansions, to Preservation Hall jazz and Mardi Gras parades -- may be America's most architecturally distinctive and culturally rich city. But it is also a disaster waiting to happen. New Orleans is the only major American city below sea level, and it is wedged between Lake Pontchartrain and the Mississippi. If a bad hurricane hit, experts say, the city could fill up like a cereal bowl, killing tens of thousands and laying waste to the city's architectural heritage. If the Big One hit, New Orleans could disappear.</p>
        <p>In Italy, where Venice is facing similar extinction, the national government has begun a $3 billion project to save the city. But in the United States, where fraudulent savings and loans get bailouts and cities fend for themselves, Washington is lying low. It has even been hard to generate concern among residents of this preternaturally carefree town. But New Orleans is, like Venice, a national treasure. Washington, Baton Rouge and New Orleans should work together, and quickly, to come up with a plan to ensure the city's survival.</p>
        <p>New Orleans's location was a triumph of romance over practicality. The French explorer who founded the city was so enraptured by this crescent-shaped stretch of the lower Mississippi that he ignored the naysayers, one of whom warned that it was ''often flooded and filled with alligators, serpents and other venomous beasts.'' The result was a beautiful city, but a waterlogged one. Burials had to be above ground because gravediggers found they quickly struck water.</p>
        <p>New Orleans has struggled with water ever since. A 475-mile system of levees and locks along the river and lake holds back the water, and a network of pumps works full time moving water up and out. But the city is sinking as the soil under it settles, and sea levels are rising. And the coastal marsh and barrier islands, which form a protective wall against hurricanes, are being eaten away.</p>
        <p>There is considerable agreement about what the Big One would look like. A Category 4 or 5 hurricane would move up from the Gulf to Lake Pontchartrain, forcing lake water over levees and into the city. If the New Orleans ''bowl'' filled, the Red Cross says, there could be 100,000 deaths. An additional 400,000 could be stranded on roofs, surrounded by a witches' brew of contaminated water. Property loss estimates run as high as $150 billion, though much of the imperiled architecture -- like the St. Louis Cathedral -- is priceless.</p>
        <p>So far, Washington has done little, and New Orleans's response has been less than satisfying. The city is focused on evacuating its 500,000 residents. But the roads leading out would flood quickly, stranding those who lingered. Then there is the thorny issue of the 100,000 residents without cars. ''When I do presentations,'' said Terry Tullier, head of the New Orleans Office of Emergency Preparedness, ''I start by saying that 'when the Big One comes, many of you will die -- let's get that out of the way.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tullier has seen computer models of Canal Street under 20 feet of water and heard that the floodwaters could stay for weeks, that the National Guard might bring in thousands of body bags -- and that New Orleans might never recover. ''In this business, we bring no good news,'' he said. ''It's full of worst-case scenarios.''</p>
        <p>One proposal for saving New Orleans calls for building a wall 20 to 30 feet high across the city to hold back the lake water. It would stop flooding in the French Quarter and other areas but could mean writing off half the city. Another idea is a $14 billion project to save coastal wetlands; that would help with the city's problems, but wouldn't solve them. The Army Corps of Engineers is studying the idea of raising the lake levees. But it will be hard to get money for these projects out of Washington, where disaster dollars are being earmarked for homeland security.</p>
        <p>There are a few voices trying to shake New Orleans out of its complacency. The Times-Picayune ran a hurricane series this summer, and academics have spoken out, Cassandra-like, for years. An advocate for the elderly recently warned that those who stayed behind in a storm could expect to be ''surrounded by water contaminated with dead animals, insects, snakes, garbage and sewage.''</p>
        <p>But getting this city of tropical instincts to take hurricanes seriously is a challenge. The New Orleans motto is ''laissez les bons temps rouler'' -- let the good times roll. And as anyone who has strolled down Bourbon Street can attest, the first meaning of ''hurricane'' here is an icy concoction of liquor and fruit juices. The city's other pull is toward languor. Blanche DuBois was describing New Orleans afternoons when she said ''an hour isn't just an hour -- but a little piece of eternity dropped in your hands.''</p>
        <p>There is no telling when the Big One will hit, but since some of the worst storms come in early September, now would be a good time to get ready. As it happens, New Orleans is about to give serious thought to hurricanes. In a few weeks, thousands will gather at the Southern Comfort New Orleans Hurricane Festival, a musical party on the Mississippi -- named after the drink.</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
