<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Geothermal Heating Systems</title>
    <meta content="22HOME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/22/realestate/22HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1450681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DA103DF931A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Geothermal Heating Systems</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Geothermal Heating Systems</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WOULDN'T it be nice if there were an abundant source of free, renewable energy that could be used to heat a house in winter, cool it in summer and provide hot water at the tap all year round?</p>
        <p>Well, some advocates say, there is: the sun. And while most people are somewhat acquainted with solar energy, far fewer are familiar with geothermal energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>While most people are somewhat acquainted with solar energy, far fewer are familiar with geothermal energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WOULDN'T it be nice if there were an abundant source of free, renewable energy that could be used to heat a house in winter, cool it in summer and provide hot water at the tap all year round?</p>
        <p>Well, some advocates say, there is: the sun. And while most people are somewhat acquainted with solar energy, far fewer are familiar with geothermal energy.</p>
        <p>''Whenever the sun is shining on the surface of the earth, heat is being absorbed,'' said Dr. James Bose, a professor of engineering technology at Oklahoma State University in Stillwater. ''And some of that heat ends up being trapped in the ground.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Bose, who is also executive director of the International Ground Source Heat Pump Association, a technical organization based at the university, said trapped heat can be tapped to provide significant energy-cost savings for homeowners. The process, known as geothermal exchange, uses electrical energy to power a ground source heat pump to transfer heat from the ground to the house in the winter and from the house to the ground in summer. And for a little more effort, a geothermal exchange system can be used to heat household water as well.</p>
        <p>''With a ground source heat pump, when you buy one unit of energy, you get another three delivered from the ground,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bose explained that a ground source heat pump -- the heart of a geoexchange system -- works on the same principal as an ordinary refrigerator.</p>
        <p>''When you put food in the refrigerator, the refrigerator takes heat out of the food and transfers it outside the refrigerator,'' he said. This can be verified by feeling the coils on the back of a refrigerator. So, Dr. Bose said, whenever a person puts something in the refrigerator, the refrigerator basically transfers the heat from that item into the room.</p>
        <p>Under ordinary circumstances, he said, there is hardly enough stored heat in objects placed in a refrigerator to produce a noticeable increase in room temperature. Moreover, because of the way a refrigerator is used, once the heat is removed from the food -- and the food is left in place -- no additional heat is produced unless additional fuel (warm food) is provided.</p>
        <p>Imagine what would happen, though, if a steady stream of food was put into and taken out of the refrigerator. The refrigerator would transfer the heat of each newly introduced piece of food from inside the refrigerator to its outside. As each cooled piece of food was removed, a new piece of relatively warm food would be added, thereby providing a continuous source of stored heat to be transferred into the room.</p>
        <p>Now, replace the food with water.</p>
        <p>''If you could circulate enough water through the refrigerator, you would ultimately end up heating the room,'' he said. ''And the only cost of the heat energy being produced is the cost of the electricity used to pump the water and run the refrigerator,'' he said. That, basically, is how a geothermal heating system works.</p>
        <p>Sara Quinn, communications and governmental affairs director for the Geothermal Heat Pump Consortium, a nonprofit advocacy organization based in Washington, said the beauty of a geoexchange system is that the energy source -- the heat stored in the ground around a house -- is basically unlimited, renewable and free.</p>
        <p>And while geoexchange systems account for only 1 percent of the heating and cooling systems installed in the country -- there are about 650,000 systems nationwide, with about 2,000 of those on Long Island -- the number of new installations has been increasing at the rate of 20 percent a year, according to Ms. Quinn.</p>
        <p>She explained that geoexchange systems rely on the nearly constant temperature maintained by the earth just a few feet below the surface. Throughout most of the United States, she said, the temperature of the ground below the frost line -- about three to five feet beneath the surface -- remains about 45 to 50 degrees in the northern latitudes and about 50 to 70 degrees in southern areas. As a result, Ms. Quinn said, in winter a geoexchange system can extract heat from ground, which is relatively warm compared with the cold outside air, and in the summer it can discharge heat into ground, which is relatively cool compared with the hot outside air.</p>
        <p>The challenge with a geoexchange system, of course, is moving heat back and forth between the house and the ground outside. And that is typically done by using water or water mixed with antifreeze.</p>
        <p>John Thulin, president of Scandia Contractors, a geoexchange heating contractor in Southampton, N.Y., said there are three basic system designs for transferring heat between the inside of a house and the outside using a liquid. One method, Mr. Thulin said, is to dig two wells on the property -- one that is used as a source of ground-temperature water supplied to the heat pump and the other that is used as a repository for water that has passed through the pump.</p>
        <p>In most cases, he said, such an ''open loop'' system can be used only where there is a reliable source of water in the ground beneath the property. (That includes virtually every property that already has a well.)</p>
        <p>When an open loop system cannot be used, Mr. Thulin said, a closed-loop system usually can.</p>
        <p>With such a system, a continuous loop of plastic tubing, sometimes coiled like a Slinky, is buried underground below the frost line and connected to the input and output sides of the heat pump. Water mixed with antifreeze is then circulated through the tubing, and the water picks up or loses heat, depending on whether the system is heating or cooling. For homes that have plenty of property around them, Mr. Thulin said, the continuous loop can be installed horizontally, just a few feet below the surface.</p>
        <p>For homes on small pieces of property -- as well as those that have topography or geology that will not allow horizontal installation -- it is possible to install a vertical loop by drilling several vertical holes in the ground into which the tubing can be installed.</p>
        <p>In most cases, it is necessary to install several hundred feet of plastic tubing in a closed-loop system, with the amount of tubing determined by the heating and cooling requirements. And for that reason, Mr. Thulin said, closed-loop systems are generally more expensive than open-loop systems.</p>
        <p>With an adequately sized system in place, Mr. Thulin said, a geothermal heat pump installed in the house can provide enough heat to run a radiant hot-water heating system or a forced-air heating system. In a house that already has a forced-air system in place, the heat pump can be connected to the existing ductwork.</p>
        <p>In summer, Mr. Thulin said, the system uses an automatic reversing valve to provide cooling instead of heating. (That is somewhat like leaving the refrigerator door open to cool the inside of the house and venting the heat it produces out a window.) In addition, he said, the heat pump can be used to help provide hot water in the house -- particularly in the summer when some of the heat being extracted from the house itself can be used to preheat water.</p>
        <p>In most cases, Mr. Thulin said, an open-loop geoexchange system can be installed in a 2,500 square-foot house with existing ductwork for about $16,000. A closed loop system would cost considerably more because of the more extensive excavation or drilling needed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bose of Oklahoma State University said that while a geoexchange system costs more than a conventional system fueled by oil or natural gas, the cost of running a geothermal system is typically 30 to 40 percent less than the cost of a system that uses fossil fuel.</p>
        <p>Additional information about geoexchange systems is available on the Internet sites of the International Ground Source Heat Pump Association (www.igshpa.okstate.edu) and the Geothermal Heat Pump Consortium (www.ghpc.org).</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
