<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christie Whitman's Loyalties Are Being Tested These Days</title>
    <meta content="31POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DF1F3BF932A05750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christie Whitman's Loyalties Are Being Tested These Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Raymond Hernandez</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Raymond Hernandez On Politics column on Environmental Protection Admr Christie Whitman's about-face as she defends Bush administration's pro-industry environmental agenda; New Jersey lawmakers warn that policies could have harsh effect on state (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christie Whitman's loyalties are being put to the test these days.</p>
        <p>As head of the Environmental Protection Agency, Mrs. Whitman's job is to implement the policies of her boss, President George W. Bush.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christie Whitman's loyalties are being put to the test these days.</p>
        <p>As head of the Environmental Protection Agency, Mrs. Whitman's job is to implement the policies of her boss, President George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>But New Jersey legislators are warning that those polices could have an especially harsh effect on the state where she was governor for eight years, a claim that her agency has denied.</p>
        <p>The situation has led some lawmakers in the state to question how much control Mrs. Whitman actually has over the administration's environmental agenda -- particularly in an administration with a pro-industry tilt that is out of step with the more balanced approach that she embraced as governor.</p>
        <p>The situation is a major reversal from a year ago, when Mrs. Whitman, a moderate, seemed like an outsider within the conservative-leaning Bush White House. The president had undercut her often enough that many people in Washington figured she would eventually resign.</p>
        <p>But now, Mrs. Whitman is out there defending the administration's move like a good soldier, and Representative Robert Menendez, a Democrat from Hudson County, for one, could not explain the change.</p>
        <p>''The actions she is taking as E.P.A. administrator fly in the face of sound policies she advocated as governor,'' he said. ''Whatever green image she once had on environmental issues has turned brown.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman did not return several calls seeking comment.</p>
        <p>The most recent clash came when word leaked that the Bush administration was planning to introduce new rules intended to discourage government lawsuits against owners of aging coal-fired plants in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The administration is apparently looking into ways of encouraging the plants to take voluntary steps to reduce emissions. But the change -- detailed in news accounts -- provoked outrage among environmentalists and politicians from a handful of Northeastern states, including New Jersey, who have long complained that pollution from these aging plants have drifted into the region and caused acid rain.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's senior senator, Robert G. Torricelli, immediately fired off a letter to Ms. Whitman demanding an explanation ''on behalf of the people she once represented.''</p>
        <p>He also noted that while she was governor, New Jersey joined a lawsuit accusing Midwestern plants of polluting the Northeast's air. In fact, he even quoted her decrying the pollution that these plants had caused in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''We've done much here in New Jersey to endure our residents can breathe clean air,'' he quoted Mrs. Whitman as saying in 1999. ''All of our efforts are fruitless, however, if New Jerseyans must breathe the dirty air coming into our state from Midwest coal-burning power plants.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Torricelli then went on to call Mrs. Whitman on her comments.</p>
        <p>''The fact that New Jerseyans deserve clean air to breathe has not changed, and the fact that these midwestern coal-mining plants are polluting our skies has not changed,'' Mr. Torricelli wrote. ''But what has changed is Commissioner Whitman's position, and that is unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''We should not play politics with public health and the environment. In New Jersey, more than 446,000 people suffer from asthma, many of them young children. The Pine Barrens are threatened by acid rain, excessive carbon dioxide is contributing to beach erosion and our marine life is suffering from increased nitrogen deposits. There is no end to the reasons why Commissioner Whitman needs to provide leadership at the federal level to protect New Jersey's citizens.''</p>
        <p>This was just the latest tussle Mrs. Whitman got in with her former New Jersey colleagues. Earlier in the month, legislators complained that the Bush administration's efforts to scale back the number of polluted sites to be cleaned under the Superfund program might hit New Jersey especially hard.</p>
        <p>The administration said it would shift the priorities of its Superfund programs, dealing with bigger and more complex sites -- even if that meant cleaning fewer of them. But New Jersey lawmakers are concerned that the state -- with the largest number of Superfund sites in the nation -- will get hurt under this approach.</p>
        <p>New Jersey lawmakers worried that the Bush administration would focus on larger sites in the West, a strong part of the President's political base, at the expense of smaller ones in old industrial states like New Jersey, where his support is already thinner than a one-pound box of chocolate.</p>
        <p>Even one of Mrs. Whitman's Republican allies from New Jersey made it clear he was keeping an eye on administration's actions.</p>
        <p>''Governor Whitman knows how important Superfund is to New Jersey and to me,'' Representative Rodney Frelinghuysen, a Republican from Morristown, recently said in a diplomatically worded statement. ''I look forward to working with her to clean up more of New Jersey's sites.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS Raymond Hernandez reports from Washington for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Raymond Hernandez reports from Washington for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
