<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Attorney General Goes To War</title>
    <meta content="16SPITZET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/16/magazine/16SPITZER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1400807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Traub, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Komansky, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pitt, Harvey L (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Komansky, David H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Spitzer, Eliot L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DD113DF935A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="3100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Attorney General Goes To War</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Attorney General Goes to War</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Traub</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Traub, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of New York State Atty Gen Eliot Spitzer, who interprets his consumer-protection mandate so expansively that he is seeking to forge, or at last shape, social policy; he is most activist attorney general currently in office; since being elected in 1998, at age 39, he has expanded scope of office by using novel approaches to law in order to go after large-scale targets--including gun manufacturers, drug companies and Midwestern polluters; he has won national recognition with his battle against Wall Street, specifically his announcement in April that Merrill Lynch research analysts publish false and misleading stock recommendations to win investment-banking business; impact has been tremendous: Merrill Lynch's chairman David Komansky publicly apologized for deception and agreed to pay $100 million fine, and Securities and Exchange Commission chairman, Harvey Pitt, stout believer in industry self-regulation, reversed himself and ordered probe of his own; state Democrats are viewing Spitzer as potential gubernatorial candidate; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few years ago, Eliot L. Spitzer, the attorney general of New York and a Democrat, was invited to speak before the Federalist Society, the legal group whose members abhor the use of courts to force political change -- at least liberal political change -- and have helped formulate the key conservative tenet that power should devolve from the central government, including the federal courts, to the states. ''I told them that I had had an epiphany and I was now a fervent Federalist,'' Spitzer said. ''Having won this job as attorney general of a state, this devolution of power was a wonderful thing: they were limiting the feds, they were shifting to us, so we could go off and sue the tobacco companies.'' Spitzer claims that his audience was ''ashen.'' This seems unlikely, but melodrama is so foreign to Spitzer's nature that perhaps he can be permitted this one moment of self-satisfied hyperbole.</p>
        <p>We are, in fact, in the midst of an era of widespread state-level judicial activism, and Eliot Spitzer is the most activist, or at least the most prominent, attorney general around. Since being elected in 1998, at age 39, Spitzer has expanded the scope of the office by using novel approaches to the law in order to go after large-scale targets -- including gun manufacturers, drug companies and Midwestern polluters -- often in concert with other state attorneys general. He has won some and lost some. But nothing Spitzer has done has remotely had the impact of the news conference he held April 8, at which he announced that research analysts at Merrill Lynch had published false and misleading stock recommendations, an act he characterized as ''an outrageous betrayal of their trust and a shocking abuse of the system.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eliot Spitzer's battle against Wall Street has won him national recognition. Will it make him governor of New York in four years?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few years ago, Eliot L. Spitzer, the attorney general of New York and a Democrat, was invited to speak before the Federalist Society, the legal group whose members abhor the use of courts to force political change -- at least liberal political change -- and have helped formulate the key conservative tenet that power should devolve from the central government, including the federal courts, to the states. ''I told them that I had had an epiphany and I was now a fervent Federalist,'' Spitzer said. ''Having won this job as attorney general of a state, this devolution of power was a wonderful thing: they were limiting the feds, they were shifting to us, so we could go off and sue the tobacco companies.'' Spitzer claims that his audience was ''ashen.'' This seems unlikely, but melodrama is so foreign to Spitzer's nature that perhaps he can be permitted this one moment of self-satisfied hyperbole.</p>
        <p>We are, in fact, in the midst of an era of widespread state-level judicial activism, and Eliot Spitzer is the most activist, or at least the most prominent, attorney general around. Since being elected in 1998, at age 39, Spitzer has expanded the scope of the office by using novel approaches to the law in order to go after large-scale targets -- including gun manufacturers, drug companies and Midwestern polluters -- often in concert with other state attorneys general. He has won some and lost some. But nothing Spitzer has done has remotely had the impact of the news conference he held April 8, at which he announced that research analysts at Merrill Lynch had published false and misleading stock recommendations, an act he characterized as ''an outrageous betrayal of their trust and a shocking abuse of the system.''</p>
        <p>The dominoes haven't stopped falling since. In one giddy two-day period, Harvey Pitt, the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission and a stout believer in industry self-regulation, announced that he had changed his mind and ordered an investigation of his own, and David Komansky, the chairman of Merrill, which until that moment had furiously rejected the allegations, publicly apologized for the deception. And then on May 21, Spitzer</p>
        <p>announced that Merrill had agreed to pay a $100 million fine; to issue a ''statement of contrition''; and to compensate its research analysts ''only for those activities and services intended to benefit Merrill Lynch investor clients,'' rather than, as had been the case, according to how much they helped the firm's investment-banking business. There is wide disagreement on Wall Street about how profoundly the settlement will alter the behavior of investment banks, but even Merrill's most staunch defenders, like Edward Fleischman, a securities lawyer and former S.E.C. official, says that Merrill and other companies are likely to change practices and policies ''because they want to be perceived by their clients as having their clients' interests first and foremost.'' Spitzer has provoked fear -- and some loathing -- on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>I first visited Spitzer in his office in downtown Manhattan a few weeks after the news conference. He greeted me with a young man's bone-crushing handshake. Spitzer is a kind of Dudley Do-Right character: earnest, a bit stiff, with one of those unvaryingly deep voices that project precocious moral authority. He has a forehead made prominent by a receding hairline and a chin you could play pinochle on -- a granite, prosecutorial chin. For all that, he gives the impression of being relatively equable -- a bit zealous, perhaps, but not driven by the furies. ''He doesn't have the extra chromosome,'' as a friend of his puts it.</p>
        <p>Spitzer was an editor of the law review at Harvard Law School, and he has the talented law student's gift of sorting particulars into bright categories. He listens to questions with the avidity of a tennis player waiting to smash back a serve, and once he knows where you're going, he starts muttering ''Right, right, right'' as he waits with diminishing patience for you to finish. When I asked Spitzer whether the new states' rights movement had in some sense made his investigation of Merrill possible, he said, ''Let's disaggregate the pieces.'' Attorney general activism, he said, probably has less to do with new legal doctrine or judicial decision-making than with ''an emotional shift'' toward deregulation and deconcentration of power that began under President Reagan and has gathered force under George W. Bush. Spitzer quoted something else he had said to the Federalists: ''Isn't it the case that there was no ideological content to the pure notion of where the decisions are made?''</p>
        <p>Of course there was; Spitzer and other attorneys general are filling a void that was intended, by the anti-Washington right, to be filled by the marketplace -- by, say, self-regulating Wall Street businesses -- not by other legal actors like state A.G.'s. James Tierney, who teaches multistate litigation at Columbia Law School and served for 10 years as the attorney general of Maine, confirms Spitzer's view (and adds that the new activism also has a great deal to do with the nationalization of the economy). Tierney considers Spitzer's investigation of Merrill and other investment banks a trailblazing action that will spur his colleagues elsewhere. ''Once the attorneys general have entered a field,'' he says, ''they don't go out.''</p>
        <p>An attorney general who interprets his consumer-protection mandate expansively can exercise a form of power that is almost more legislative than judicial. I spent a morning watching Spitzer, and I was struck by how explicitly he was seeking to forge, or at least shape, social policy. He spent an hour preparing to argue an appeal in a case his office had brought seeking to prevent gun manufacturers from distributing guns to retailers that, in turn, made guns available to criminals -- a form of judicially mandated gun control. (That Spitzer had decided to argue this extremely difficult case himself illustrates the pleasure he takes in the intellectual aspect of the law.) Spitzer had brought the case under the state's public-nuisance laws; at the time, no court had ever agreed to apply such laws to any consumer product, much less a gun. Indeed, no other state attorney general had tried to sue gun manufacturers. The case, not surprisingly, had been thrown out by a lower court. An assistant at the meeting, playing the role of judge, suggested that it was federal regulators, who monitor gun sales, that should be bringing the case. Spitzer's answer was, in effect, ''They haven't.''</p>
        <p>Later in the morning, Spitzer met with the head of his labor bureau to go over a proposal for owners of produce stores to sign a code promising to pay workers the minimum wage as well as extra wages for overtime -- in exchange for which the owners would be exempt from future litigation. He discussed with his chief deputies continuing negotiations with the owners of Midwestern utilities he had sued under an untested provision of the federal Clean Air Act. Spitzer argues that acid rain from the Midwest is drifting into New York. Peter Lehner, head of the attorney general's environmental protection bureau, reported that while the utilities no longer fear federal action from the deregulators in the Bush administration, they were deeply worried about the states. Spitzer smiled -- the expression of a man who considers himself the Federalist Society's worst nightmare.</p>
        <p>And to hear the Federalists, he is. Walter Olson, a Federalist in good standing, a senior fellow at the conservative Manhattan Institute and the author of a book soon to be published on mass litigation, says that on guns, ''Spitzer wishes to second-guess the results of the democratic process.'' Olson says that the fact that Spitzer is asking a judge to impose penalties on gun manufacturers -- including out-of-state gun manufacturers -- should cause ''the mental alarms of all conservative federalists to start ringing.''</p>
        <p>Eliot Spitzer grew up in Riverdale, a wealthy enclave in the Bronx. His mother was an English teacher and his father an engineer who made a fortune in real estate. The family dinner table was the scene of high-minded debate. The youngest of three children, Eliot was sent off to Horace Mann, a private school consisting back then almost entirely of terribly serious, intellectually combative well-to-do Jewish boys like himself. From there he went to Princeton, where he continued to be high-minded, scholarly and combative. Carl Mayer, a friend and classmate, says that he and Spitzer specialized in ''intensely fierce competitions,'' whether in running, tennis, basketball or even spaghetti-eating. As a freshman, he occasionally commuted back to the Bronx in order to serve as treasurer of the Benjamin Franklin Democratic Club.</p>
        <p>Though this was a time when student government enjoyed an extremely dim reputation at Princeton, Spitzer ran for student-body president in his sophomore year and won. He took the job very seriously and did it very well. There is a widespread view among Spitzer's old friends that politics was always his destiny. Spitzer, however, sees himself in a very different light. The pattern, he says, was a passionate interest in government, in service -- not in politics. He was thinking Cyrus Vance, not Mark Green.</p>
        <p>Spitzer went on to Harvard Law School and joined the Manhattan district attorney's office in 1986. Michael Cherkasky, who was Spitzer's boss in the labor-racketeering division, says that he recognized the young man's brilliance and ''fast tracked'' him. Spitzer masterminded one of the best-known cases of his time, an investigation into mob control of trucking in the garment district; he conceived the idea of offering Thomas Gambino, the chief suspect, a deal in which Gambino could avoid jail by agreeing to plead guilty to a criminal offense, make a $12 million restitution and promise to stay out of the business. Cherkasky describes it as an ingenious solution and a ''creative use of law enforcement.''</p>
        <p>Spitzer left the D.A.'s office in 1992 for the duly prestigious firm of Skadden, Arps but found that he was bored by private practice. The reigning attorney general, Robert Abrams, had stepped down after a run for the Senate, and an election was coming up in 1994. It was an elective office, but it was a legal office, and it had a wide ambit in social and economic issues. Spitzer decided to run. He had no important backers, no ties to the Democratic Party and no political skills. He would have been a laughable candidate save for one thing: he was rich. Spitzer spent $4 million, which buys a great deal of attention in a primary race for attorney general. Spitzer ran as a pro-death-penalty, tough-on-crime Democrat, despite the fact that A.G.'s have relatively little to do with criminal issues.</p>
        <p>He finished last in a field of four. But he almost immediately began campaigning for the next election, slogging across the state and presenting himself to county leaders, who were surprised to discover just how much this rich Harvard boy wanted one of the state's least glamorous jobs. This time around, he won the primary and beat the Republican incumbent, Dennis Vacco, in a race so close that it took six weeks for Spitzer to be declared the winner.</p>
        <p>The Merrill Case represents the convergence of a number of forces: the new state-level activism, deregulation at the federal level and Spitzer's own ambitious legal formulations and flair for public relations, a talent common to all successful prosecutors, at least in New York. Spitzer's office began its investigation last summer, and it chugged along uneventfully until January, when Spitzer discovered the e-mail messages that Merrill Lynch's analysts had been sending to one another and to the company's investment bankers. Suddenly, he felt that he had not only proof of guilt but also a mighty cudgel with which to beat the firm into submission. Those messages have now joined Sherron Watkins's letter to Kenneth Lay warning of accounting fraud at Enron as iconic documents of corporate fraud.</p>
        <p>There is a curious difference, though, in that the authors of the e-mail messages plainly felt that they were engaging in conventional, if possibly unfair, behavior. The routine behavior was using stock recommendations as a marketing device to attract investment-banking business rather than as an analytical tool for investors, though the bank publicly represented the research as just such a tool. A ringingly positive recommendation from a celebrity analyst could do wonders for a client's stock offering, though of course it would mislead the naïve investor. What made the e-mail messages so powerful is that they often caught the analysts at moments of bad conscience, as when, most famously, Henry Blodget, Merrill's celebrated Internet analyst, threatened that he would no longer ''cut companies any slack'' and thus that ''we are going to just start calling the stocks . . . like we see them, no matter what the ancillary business consequences are.''</p>
        <p>Spitzer's release of those explosive documents had precisely the effect he had calculated -- they created public outrage. Merrill's initial response was that the e-mail messages had been taken out of context and that the charges demonstrated ''a fundamental lack of understanding of how securities research works within the overall capital-raising process.'' When I first contacted Merrill, an official promised to put together a group of bankers to defend the company's position for me. But that meeting never came off. Merrill's stock lost $9 billion in value in the wake of the release of the e-mail messages, and the company gave up the fight.</p>
        <p>The reaction on much of Wall Street and in the business press was that Merrill had done nothing that merited state intervention and that Spitzer had essentially blackmailed the company into submission. An editorial in Barron's argued that ''half-wit speculators'' who purchase risky stocks on analysts' recommendations don't deserve legal protection and that Spitzer was trampling on the First Amendment rights of the analysts. Spitzer's answer was that most investors did not, in fact, understand that the analysts' recommendations were rigged, and, as he says, ''I've got a job, and it's to protect small investors.''</p>
        <p>It is also true that the regulation of the stock exchange has traditionally been left to the exchange itself and to the S.E.C. But Spitzer argued that the regulators had failed to pursue or even recognize the inherent conflict he had uncovered, and he seized on a state securities law, the Martin Act, that had been used in the past to pursue boiler-room operations and Ponzi schemes.</p>
        <p>Spitzer initially hoped to force Merrill to build a sort of church-state wall between the research and banking sides but backed off when Wall Street figures explained that research could not survive without being subsidized by banking. Spitzer continued to maintain, however, that he had to eliminate the incentives for analysts to cook their recommendations, and so the agreement he reached with Merrill not only spells out the activities for which analysts can and cannot be compensated but also establishes a ''Research Recommendation Committee'' to embed these new rules in the firm's daily decision-making.</p>
        <p>Financial authorities are not altogether persuaded that even these measures will change so deep-seated a system. John Coffee, a professor at Columbia Law School and an expert on financial law, says, ''I think at the margin it does represent significant reform,'' but adds, ''Analysts are still going to be partly a neutral umpire and partly a securities salesman.'' Coffee also notes, ''For those people who were screaming about how reckless Spitzer was, I think the industry, and Merrill specifically, can thank its lucky stars, because he had it in his power to crucify them.'' In exchange for reaching a final settlement with Merrill, Spitzer has forgone the opportunity to put Blodget and others under oath for the equivalent of public grand jury testimony. Nevertheless, he has extended his investigation to virtually all the major Wall Street banks, and Merrill's competitors are now on notice about the price they may have to pay to avoid a fate worse than Merrill's.</p>
        <p>A recent Op-Ed in The Wall Street Journal suggested that Spitzer had taken on Merrill for the same reason Rudy Giuliani had supposedly targeted insider trading -- to ''further his own career.'' Spitzer of course denies the allegation, but you cannot hurt your political standing by crusading against Wall Street at a time when millions of Americans want someone to blame for the evaporation of a chunk of their assets. (Spitzer's position is considered so impregnable that the Republicans have put up a virtually unknown judge to oppose him this fall -- an indubitable proof of political success.)</p>
        <p>Democratic officials do, in fact, view Spitzer as their very own Giuliani -- a prosecutor who wants to go far, and will. According to a vision of Spitzer's future now floating around New York Democratic political circles, this fall the Republican governor, George Pataki, will beat either Andrew Cuomo or Carl McCall, who are seeking the Democratic nomination, and then retire at the end of his third term. And in 2006, as one ranking Democrat puts it, ''it's going to be King Kong vs. Godzilla'' -- Spitzer vs. Cuomo for the Democratic nomination. ''Look for Eliot and Andrew to be always positioning themselves against each other in regard to 2006,'' he adds. Hank Sheinkopf, who was Spitzer's media consultant in the 1998 campaign, says: ''He brings the right side and the left side of the Democratic Party spectrum in one place. He's a tough competitor, extraordinarily smart, and who knows where he'll end up?''</p>
        <p>Spitzer still does not consider himself any kind of politician. In his own mind, he is the same thing he has always been: a public-spirited lawyer. ''I'm not really suited for other kinds of office,'' he told me.</p>
        <p>I asked if he meant that the rumors about 2006 were baseless. Spitzer saw that he had made a misstep, and a pained grin twisted his long jaw. He paused -- even a short pause feels long with Spitzer -- and then said mechanically, ''The only position I'm thinking about running for now is re-election.''</p>
        <p>I asked another member of Spitzer's 1998 team if I should assume that Spitzer was running in 2006. ''You shouldn't assume it,'' he said. ''You should know it.''</p>
        <p>James Traub, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about school testing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Traub, a contributing writer for the magazine, last wrote about school testing.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
