<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romania, Wooed by U.S., Looks to a Big NATO Role</title>
    <meta content="Y23ROM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/23/international/europe/23ROMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1434234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iliescu, Ion (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nastase, Adrian (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Romania</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EED7173CF930A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romania, Wooed by U.S., Looks to a Big NATO Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Romania Pins Hope for NATO Seat on U.S. Friendship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>CONSTANTA, Romania, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Romania hopes ever-closer US ties will be cemented with NATO membership as alliance considers several potential new members; country remains at rear of European development, with withered reform, thriving corruption and no market economy, but location across Black Sea from Central Asia has assumed great strategic significance since Sept 11 terorrist attacks as US has sought allies, airspace and military help with Afghanistan campaign; photo; map; pro-American strategy has at same time caused some tension with European Union, which Romania also aspires to join; European officials worry that NATO membership might not be enough to jolt regime of Pres Ion Iliescu and Prime Min Adrian Nastase into reform (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe their next mission will be against Iraq. Maybe it will just be routine naval exercises, aboard warships built in the 1980's to combat the West. Either way, the poor and once-forgotten nation of Romania looks set to join NATO, and the very happy sailors at this Black Sea port have no doubt whom to thank.</p>
        <p>''We are looking at the United States as a close friend,'' said Alex Gobjila, a young officer aboard a minesweeper here that is slated, perhaps soon, to steam out of port on NATO missions. ''It's important always to have a good friend.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The poor and once-forgotten nation of Romania looks set to join NATO, and the very happy sailors at Constanta, a Black Sea port, have no doubt whom to thank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe their next mission will be against Iraq. Maybe it will just be routine naval exercises, aboard warships built in the 1980's to combat the West. Either way, the poor and once-forgotten nation of Romania looks set to join NATO, and the very happy sailors at this Black Sea port have no doubt whom to thank.</p>
        <p>''We are looking at the United States as a close friend,'' said Alex Gobjila, a young officer aboard a minesweeper here that is slated, perhaps soon, to steam out of port on NATO missions. ''It's important always to have a good friend.''</p>
        <p>The ever-closer tie between Romania and the United States is likely to be cemented if, as expected, Romania and perhaps six other nations are invited to join NATO in November. It is but one example of how Sept. 11 has reconfigured the world, in often unexpected ways. Romania is, by any measure, at the rear of Europe's pack: reform withered here, as corruption thrived. The country still has no market economy. Its prospects to be a real part of Europe have looked, at best, long term.</p>
        <p>But Romania is across the Black Sea from Central Asia, an area that has assumed greater strategic importance since Sept. 11. In recent weeks, American officials have also traveled here to discuss how Romania might help in a coalition against Iraq (An air base just 15 miles from here was reportedly discussed).</p>
        <p>Romania decided in the defining days after the Sept. 11 attacks, and in notable ways since, to speak out quickly in solidarity with the United States. Many intellectuals and politicians here said it was a crucial, almost last-ditch, gambit to join the coveted club of the West.</p>
        <p>''We play the American card and aggressively,'' said Silviu Brucan, the nation's elder statesman and a top political thinker.</p>
        <p>After Sept. 11, America wanted allies, and Romania opened up its airspace and later sent troops to Afghanistan, acting as police officers in Kabul as well as patrolling with Americans and guarding the perimeter of an American military base in Kandahar. Then it was the only nation in Europe to support the United States' demand to exempt American peacekeepers from the new International Criminal Court.</p>
        <p>As a result, Romania, not considered a top candidate for membership a year ago, looks likely to enter the NATO summit meeting next month in Prague with the strong backing of the United States. There has been no official decision, but Bulgaria, Latvia, Lithuania, Estonia, Slovenia and Slovakia may also be invited to join an east-reaching NATO.</p>
        <p>While offering no predictions about what might happen at the NATO summit meeting, an American official here said: ''It's a country that likes America and wants a partnership with us. I'm very convinced that Romania wants not just to be a member of NATO, but a crucial member of NATO with which the United States consults.''</p>
        <p>Whether Romania would take part in any action on Iraq is an open question. Ioan Mircea Pascu, the defense minister, has been quoted as saying he does not believe that Romanian soldiers are prepared for actual combat there, but he makes clear Romania's sympathies.</p>
        <p>''You have undertaken an obligation to stay in the coalition no matter what comes,'' he said in an interview. ''You can't say, 'Now it's tough, it's difficult, I'm opting out.' ''</p>
        <p>But Romania's pro-American strategy carries risks. The friendship has caused some tension with the other club that Romania wants to join: the European Union.</p>
        <p>The union rates Romania low on the list of 12 potential candidates to join it. Many European states have also found themselves at odds with what they see as the Bush administration's go-it-alone approach to issues like global warming, trade and Iraq. European Union officials, opposed to the American position on the criminal court, were outraged that Romania broke European solidarity on the issue.</p>
        <p>Last week, in their report on expansion, European leaders took a cautious stance toward Romania and its neighbor, Bulgaria, saying they ''noted'' the nations' desire to join by 2007 and making a commitment to help them achieve that goal.</p>
        <p>''There has got to be a shifting of gears,'' said Jonathan Scheele, the European Union's chief in Romania, who praised recent changes but said the fundamentals had yet to be tackled: overhauling the economy, judiciary and public administration. ''Romania will not survive without accomplishing transition.''</p>
        <p>European officials worry that joining NATO, despite talk in the West about it being an alliance of shared democratic values, may not be enough to prod Romania to real reform. It might, some worry, serve as a publicly satisfying substitute for deeper internal change by President Ion Iliescu, and Prime Minister Adrian Nastase.</p>
        <p>''The average Romanian has very little to gain from joining NATO, which is something rarely heard,'' said Matei Paun, an investment banker who moderates an influential Internet discussion group on the Romanian economy and politics.</p>
        <p>Romania has had one of the toughest transitions of any formerly Communist state, despite old ties to Western Europe which once earned its capital, Bucharest, the title ''the Paris of the East.'' The reasons are many: the long and harsh dictatorship of Nicholae Ceausescu, who was executed in 1989; the fact that old-guard Communist officials largely took over; and the profound poverty and fear of change among many ordinary Romanians.</p>
        <p>As a result, of the 12 potential candidates for European Union membership, it has the lowest gross domestic product, the highest inflation, the least foreign investment and, by one measure, the most corruption. The nation's image, both among Romanians and abroad, is one of being more than a few steps behind: a place more of horse-drawn carts than new cars.</p>
        <p>Despite recent changes in both the government and the military, Mr. Brucan and other experts said they had long concluded that Romania could only get out of its rut if forced from the outside. Then terrorists attacked the World Trade Center and the Pentagon, and Romania's leaders made certain they were firmly on the Americans' side.</p>
        <p>''There was no gambling on corpses, as we are accused,'' said Mr. Pascu, the defense minister.</p>
        <p>Still, experts say the tragedy marked an opportunity that Romania carefully cultivated. American officials say they view Romania -- with 22 million people, the largest nation, in the unstable Balkan region -- as its anchor friendship in Europe's southeast, much as Poland has been to the north.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
