<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drought-Tolerant Plants Get Their Turn</title>
    <meta content="14CUTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1407966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5DB1530F937A25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drought-Tolerant Plants Get Their Turn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT had to happen on the Upper West Side of Manhattan: drought-tolerant wedding bouquets.</p>
        <p>''I was out front watering our plants and people would walk by and yell at me for wasting water,'' Kevin Esteban said, standing at the door of Gotham Gardens, at 325 Amsterdam Avenue. ''It's the Upper West Side. They love a good cause.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT had to happen on the Upper West Side of Manhattan: drought-tolerant wedding bouquets.</p>
        <p>''I was out front watering our plants and people would walk by and yell at me for wasting water,'' Kevin Esteban said, standing at the door of Gotham Gardens, at 325 Amsterdam Avenue. ''It's the Upper West Side. They love a good cause.''</p>
        <p>Potted fig trees, Meyer lemons, hydrangeas, geraniums, lantana, heliotrope, sages and rosemary are only a few of the jungle of plants that make this storefront a green oasis.</p>
        <p>About a month ago, a call came from friends of a bride working for the World Wildlife Fund. ''Her friends wanted a politically correct bouquet,'' said Dan Dahl, who owns the business with Mr. Esteban. ''So we said, 'We'll use succulents.' ''</p>
        <p>The florists were already known around the neighborhood for their Eco-Kyoto bouquets, created after the United States refused to sign the Kyoto climate treaty, which would reduce the fuel-burning emissions blamed for global warming.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to do something besides being lazy-boy liberals,'' Mr. Esteban, 38, said. ''So we used plants native to countries that had signed the treaty.'' They had also given 20 percent of their profits -- the bouquets cost $125 -- to the World Wildlife Fund. So when friends of the bride needed flowers, they called Gotham Gardens.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Dahl, 43, stood in the back of the cool shop, assembling a bouquet of succulents, fuzzy lambs ears, hostas and other drought-tolerant plants. His nimble fingers worked with the fleshy stems of Lampranthus deltoides, a blue-gray succulent with fleshy, triangular leaves.</p>
        <p>''Deltoides means river delta,'' said Mr. Esteban, who loves studying the origins of words. ''It's triangular, like a delta.'' He made a triangle with his forefingers and thumbs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahl now added to the mix pale green velvety lamb's ears whose plump yellow flower buds were just beginning to open, and a bit of flowering dill. Hosta leaves, char treuse with dark green margins, were the perfect complement.</p>
        <p>''There's no right or wrong thing,'' said Mr. Dahl, who started out as a fashion designer. ''I like using herbs too, like rosemary or sage. The lavenders are also good. And I love using Gloriosa lilies.'' Their twisting yellow petals, edged with blood-red, dangled from a tall vase in the shop.</p>
        <p>There are many cut flowers, grasses and seed pods here to get you out of the box, so to speak, of routine flower arrangements. And for gardeners dealing with dry hot summers, which may be the future, the arrangements suggest generous plantings in the cutting garden.</p>
        <p>Red clover, for instance, looked beautiful in another bouquet. So did globe thistles, with their blue-gray thimble-shaped flowers, and tweedia, with its velvety triangular gray-green leaves and little pale blue-petaled flowers on leggy stems perfect for arching down from a hand or vase.</p>
        <p>All the artemisias are good, with their gray foliage, Mr. Esteban said. ''These bouquets are good for outdoor weddings, especially if it's a hot day,'' he said. ''They're not going to wilt on you.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''How many white bridal bouquets can you be excited about? Hah! No wonder they throw them over their shoulders.''</p>
        <p>Some plants make a statement on their own.</p>
        <p>''If I were down South, I would use a big yucca leaf,'' Mr. Esteban said.</p>
        <p>Californians have eucalpytus at their disposal. The green fuzzy pods looked great dangling over a big vase in the shop. The huge blue thistles of cardoon, which can grow to six feet in the garden, were riveting. So was a pot of nothing more than stems of artichokes -- though if I could grow them that big, I would eat them. One tall cylindrical vase had nothing but burgundy steel grass, four-feet sharp-edged blades that give it its nickname.</p>
        <p>My favorite was a wide glass container full of the fat curving stems of golden amaranth, hanging its tassles down like Rapunzel's long hair. It begged to be stroked.</p>
        <p>''We get it from California,'' Mr. Dahl said.</p>
        <p>But amaranth, native to Mexico and Central America, can easily be grown in the garden. I've grown mine 10 feet tall, and it doesnt mind water restrictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dahl, whose arrangements used to enliven the Guggenheim Museum, has a fondness for Echeveria elegans, too, that succulent with a wide rosette of pale green leaves, that sports an arching skinny stem with tiny pink flowers.</p>
        <p>''You can leave echeveria around for weeks, just set on a table, like an object,'' Mr. Esteban said. ''When the bottom leaves start to wither, I just pull them off.'' When he notices his rosettes need water, he floats them in a dish for a few hours, and they rejuvenate.</p>
        <p>You can also root succulents in a sandy medium, and if you have a sunny room that cools off at night, you can keep them growing year round. Let them thrive on the terrace in the summer, then bring them in before frost.</p>
        <p>I was thinking about these drought-tolerant bouquets a few days later, wandering the hot, dry borders of the Peconic River Herb Farm, in Calverton, N.Y. Dozens of prairie plants, herbs and grasses were doing just fine, without any supplemental watering.</p>
        <p>Agastache, goldenrod, yarrow, day lilies, santolina, rudbeckia, sunflowers, coreopsis, salvia, verbascum, coral bells, butterfly bush and vitex were all standing right up to the heat. The Asiatic lilies were just getting ready to bloom.</p>
        <p>So take the time, on the next 90-degree day, to go see what's doing just fine in the garden or down the street at your local ecologically minded florist shop.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
