<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Couple of Detroit Doyens Go From Gas to Electric</title>
    <meta content="23PHIL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/23/automobiles/23PHIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1434184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lido Motors USA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stempel, Robert C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iacocca, Lee A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Phillips, Braden</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lido</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Iacocca, Lee A</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stempel, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DC133AF930A15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Couple of Detroit Doyens Go From Gas to Electric</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Couple of Detroit Doyens Go From Gas to Electric</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRADEN PHILLIPS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Phillips, Braden</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Stempel and Lee Iacocca, former leaders of American carmakers, are spending their retirements running small companies in electric car market; photos; Stempel, who as General Motors executive worked to make cars more environmentally friendly, is developing electric car for highway driving; Iacocca's Lido Motors is building battery-powered car for neighborhood driving (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BOB STEMPEL and Lee Iacocca, former leaders of American carmakers, spent their years in the corner office overseeing the consumption of billions of gallons of gasoline. Now, in active retirements, they have taken different turns, running small companies in the electric car market.</p>
        <p>Both men are aiming for nothing more than a niche, and neither is close to making a profit, but both are convinced that they are on the right track.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Stempel and Lee Iacocca, former leaders of American carmakers, are taking different turns, running small companies in the electric car market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BOB STEMPEL and Lee Iacocca, former leaders of American carmakers, spent their years in the corner office overseeing the consumption of billions of gallons of gasoline. Now, in active retirements, they have taken different turns, running small companies in the electric car market.</p>
        <p>Both men are aiming for nothing more than a niche, and neither is close to making a profit, but both are convinced that they are on the right track.</p>
        <p>It may come as a surprise that these two doyens of Detroit are catering to the green market, but their current focus finds some reflection in their pasts. Robert C. Stempel, 70, who led the General Motors Corporation from 1990 to 1992, has always worked to make cars more environmentally friendly. In 1966, he was part of the G.M. team that created the catalytic converter, which reduced emissions.</p>
        <p>Lee A. Iacocca, 77, ranks the development of the Mustang for the Ford Motor Company in the 1960's and the minivan for the Chrysler Corporation in the 80's among the pinnacles of his career. What ties his new venture to those successes is a focus on the baby boomer.</p>
        <p>''You've got to stay with your market, and I always said I followed the baby boomer,'' he told The Detroit News earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iacocca, a founder and president of Lido Motors USA, based in Desert Hot Springs, Calif., is building and selling the battery-powered Lido, a so-called neighborhood electric vehicle, or N.E.V. The fiberglass-bodied, street-legal, emission-free vehicle has a top speed of 25 miles an hour and is able to travel 40 miles on a six-hour charge. Lidos start at $10,000; about 500 have been sold since manufacturing began a year ago.</p>
        <p>Lido's three models -- a four-passenger sedan, a two-passenger with a utility bed and a two-passenger coupe for golf -- have mostly been sold in the Sunbelt to residents of gated communities. Mr. Iacocca says he expects the market to grow as baby boomers retire.</p>
        <p>''People are retiring early,'' he told The News. ''There are 15,000 gated retirement communities where you don't need an extra car.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stempel, chairman of Energy Conversion Devices, in Rochester Hills, Mich., is developing a prototype electric car for highway driving.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stempel could not say how much his vehicle would cost or when it would be ready, and drew a distinction with other electric efforts, which have focused on low-speed models or conversions of existing cars.</p>
        <p>''The only thing going out the door right now is money,'' he said. ''But we want to get out a practical, useful vehicle -- not an N.E.V., but a real vehicle. My history is such that I've been associated with real cars.''</p>
        <p>A leading American maker of electric cars is Global Electric Motorcars, a subsidiary of DaimlerChrysler, which has sold roughly 12,000 electric cars since 1997, two-thirds of them in the last two years. The cars are limited to 25 miles an hour and get about 30 to 35 miles a charge.</p>
        <p>IN Atlanta, eMotion Mobility plans to market a highway-worthy battery-powered-car version of the DaimlerChrysler Smart City Coupe next year in Atlanta, California and the Northeast. The car will have a range of 70 miles and a top speed of 65 to 70 miles an hour. The battery on the electric car for highway use gets 100 to 120 miles a charge. The company will start by leasing the car for individual trips.</p>
        <p>The challenge for Mr. Stempel and Mr. Iacocca is not merely to sell their respective cars but to convince people that there is a market for them. That task was made more difficult recently when Ford gave up on the Think, an electric-car venture; in 2001 General Motors abandoned its electric car, the EV1. Only Toyota has an all-electric on the market, a battery-powered version of its RAV4.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stempel said he thought that Ford and G.M. had based their decisions on factors other than the car's potential.</p>
        <p>''I have some disagreements with my former colleagues,'' he said. ''But while I'm personally in favor of electric and hybrid vehicles, C.E.O.'s today have got a full platter, with pressure on earnings, restoring morale, lifting stock prices.''</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates are glad to have the two executives in their corner.</p>
        <p>''U.S. car manufacturers aren't paying much attention to electric technology, despite the rhetoric,'' said Eric Heitz, the president of the Energy Foundation, an organization based in San Francisco that supports energy efficiency and renewable energy.</p>
        <p>''Iacocca and Stempel and others are way ahead on this,'' Mr. Heitz said. ''They're foreshadowing a new market.''</p>
        <p>But even for environmental advocates, the electric car is not the primary focus. Instead, they are focusing on hybrid electric vehicles that combine a gas-powered engine with a battery and electric motor. The hybrid is seen as being easier to sell because it does not have the mileage limitations of battery-only vehicles.</p>
        <p>According to the Electric Vehicle Association of the Americas, a Washington-based trade group, more than 31,000 hybrid electric vehicles have been sold or leased in the United States since 1999. All were made in Japan.</p>
        <p>While it pulled out of its electric-car program, Ford is behind its hybrid and plans to be the first American company to offer one sometime next year, in a special version of the Escape, its small sport utility vehicle.</p>
        <p>DESPITE the greater success of the hybrid vehicle, Mr. Stempel and Mr. Iacocca say the battery-powered car has a necessary role to play.</p>
        <p>Two large planned communities under construction in the West have incorporated N.E.V.'s into their transportation plan. Playa Vista, in Los Angeles, will have 14,000 residents and 10,000 commuters working there when it is completed. Otay Ranch, in Chula Vista, Calif., will ultimately have a population of 75,000, and the car is currently getting high marks from residents testing an N.E.V. program.</p>
        <p>The president of Playa Vista, Steve Soboroff, is encouraging residents to buy an N.E.V. He is also working with Global Electric Motorcars and eMotion Mobility to create a car-sharing plan.</p>
        <p>''We want residents to buy N.E.V.'s and make them a part of the mortgage, like refrigerators,'' he said. ''It's cheap and efficient and we'll give them priority parking, too.</p>
        <p>''After all,'' he added. ''from an urban planning perspective they allow you to increase density and decrease traffic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stempel could not agree more.</p>
        <p>''We want people to see that electric cars have a good range capability and still carry a good payload. The misperception is you have to fill it up with batteries and not carry anything,'' Mr. Stempel said. ''The hybrid will be popular, but in central city operations, in short-distance commuting, the electric car is very practical.''</p>
        <p>''You match the duty cycle with the vehicle,'' he said. ''It's like changing suits on different days. You don't necessarily want to drive the Chevy Suburban to work. That's where the electric car comes in.''</p>
        <p>THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
