<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Off the Expressway, Ancient New York; Remnants of Virgin Forests Still Stand, Even in the Bronx and Queens</title>
    <meta content="13TREE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/13/nyregion/13TREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20021115T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1407803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5D81E30F930A25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Off the Expressway, Ancient New York; Remnants of Virgin Forests Still Stand, Even in the Bronx and Queens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just Off the Expressway, Ancient New York</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tree experts say that New York State has more ancient forestland than any other state in Northeast; hikers and university researchers are exploring, discovering and mapping more and more spots of old-growth trees on wind-swept mountainsides, in wide swaths of forest, on thin rocky soil and on slivers of woods near malls and housing developments; remnants of virgin forests still stand, even in Bronx and Queens; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once you know what to look for, a very old tree is nearly as easy to spot as a very old human.</p>
        <p>Trees show their age in the color and texture of their bark, the circumference of their bases, the height of their lowest branches and the shapes of their trunks, branches and roots. The bark of an old beech, for instance, is dull, dark gray and fragile-looking, in contrast to a mature beech nearby with pale, shiny bark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the clearing of trees by farmers of centuries past, people who study trees in New York know some 500-year-old trees still exist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once you know what to look for, a very old tree is nearly as easy to spot as a very old human.</p>
        <p>Trees show their age in the color and texture of their bark, the circumference of their bases, the height of their lowest branches and the shapes of their trunks, branches and roots. The bark of an old beech, for instance, is dull, dark gray and fragile-looking, in contrast to a mature beech nearby with pale, shiny bark.</p>
        <p>Bruce Kershner, a forest ecologist and vice president of the newly created New York Old Growth Forest Association, is good at dating trees at a glance. When he stopped before the Queens Giant, a towering tulip tree with bark worn smooth up to its lowest branch, 75 feet high, he put its age at 425 to 450 years old.</p>
        <p>''This is just -- sheez,'' he said. ''Born in 1550. As tall as the younger redwoods. The oldest living thing in New York City.''</p>
        <p>New York City?</p>
        <p>Many people believe that over the past 450 years, the colonists, farmers, loggers and developers at some point cleared every woodsy patch and felled every old tree in the city.</p>
        <p>But a small group of tree-lovers know better. In Pelham Bay Park in the Bronx, wildlife and rare birds and vegetation flourish among trees that have been growing since the 1700's. A hiking trail next to Orchard Beach, which is crowded with people every summer weekend, winds through tulip trees and black birches that were saplings 300 years ago.</p>
        <p>In fact, several tree experts say, New York State has more ancient forestland than any other state in the Northeast. Hikers and university researchers are exploring, discovering and mapping more and more spots of old-growth trees on wind-swept mountainsides, in wide swaths of forest, on thin rocky soil and on slivers of woods near malls and housing developments.</p>
        <p>A few discoveries have been especially striking: 500-year-old pitch pines near Saratoga Springs and 1,700-year-old northern white cedars near Niagara. The only other equally ancient discovery east of the Mississippi is of the baldcypresses of Black River in North Carolina, which are also thought to be 1,700 years old.</p>
        <p>''Those two are duking it out for the oldest living things,'' said Robert Leverett, a Massachusetts engineer and retired Air Force major who is considered one of the foremost authorities on ancient forests.</p>
        <p>These old-growth forests are irreplaceable scientific repositories, Mr. Leverett said. ''What were the forests like when the Europeans came over?'' he asked. ''These are scientific baselines to study, say, global warming, ozone pollution, environmental effects.'' But these are places, he said, that have not been manipulated by humans.</p>
        <p>Tree-ring analysis of pencil-size core samples of old trees can reveal historical droughts, fires and weather patterns, said Neil Peterson, a scientist at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University.</p>
        <p>Until recently, only a handful of environmentalists and forestry academics knew or cared about the Northeast's ancient trees. University forestry schools, which counted big lumber companies among their major donors, taught that virgin forests and nearly all trees older than 200 years were gone, and that old trees were, if anything, a liability, Mr. Leverett said. The students took those attitudes to the federal and state forest services.</p>
        <p>But anger over the destruction of California's thousand-year-old redwoods during the 1980's stirred interest east of the Rockies. Could there be virgin forest left in the long-settled Northeast? Mr. Leverett, who identified some of the first known old-growth forests in the Northeast, said that environmental officials were skeptical, and often still are.</p>
        <p>''People at the fringes are just getting the word,'' he said. ''Some are finding it unbelievable, but the ages are there. There is an overwhelming body of data.''</p>
        <p>Now Northeastern old-growth forestry is taught at universities, Mr. Leverett said.</p>
        <p>Peter Duncan of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, said the state manages its oldest trees along with the younger ones as a matter of course.</p>
        <p>New York regarded wilderness as a treasure and a resource in the 19th century, long before most other states. Much of the woodland of the Northeast was destroyed by heavy logging during that time, but many of New York's hardwood trees were spared because they were useless as lumber, on inaccessible peaks and hillsides or far from streams used to float lumber to towns.</p>
        <p>In 1895, the state created Adirondack Park, six million acres to be protected forever as wilderness and watershed. It now has more than half a million acres of virgin forest, as much as all the rest of the Northeast, said Barbara McMartin, a mathematician who has written 23 Adirondack guidebooks. Michael Kudish, a forestry professor at Paul Smith's College in Brighton, N.Y., in the Adirondacks, said that over the past 30 years, he had mapped 97 square miles of virgin forest in the Catskills.</p>
        <p>Though virgin forest is extremely rare outside of state parks, it still exists in odd corners and on mountain peaks. Woods are often preserved on estates that have been passed down intact since the 18th or 19th centuries.</p>
        <p>And, yes, there are old trees in the five boroughs.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Kershner, the forest ecologist, squeezed through a fence around a construction site and entered the woodsy edge of Alley Pond Park in Douglaston, Queens. ''Are you ready for this?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Trucks rumbled past on the Long Island Expressway, a few hundred yards away. But the woods were dense with towering trees. He paused at one after another. ''Two hundred and eighty years, I think,'' he said of a broad, rough tulip tree. ''And see that beech? Two hundred and fifty, I'd say.''</p>
        <p>The age of the Queens Giant has not been precisely determined by laboratory analysis. Of the few city tree experts who know of it, one thinks that 350 to 400 years is a fairer guess. But the signs of its great age could not be more obvious: the long expanse of worn, or balding surface, caused by peeling layers of bark; the thick, flaring roots, like buttresses on a medieval cathedral; the weird, gnarly twists of the outer branches; higher up, the unusually craggy texture of the bark. And it is surrounded by tulips and beeches nearly as old, at 250 to 350 years, Mr. Kershner said.</p>
        <p>''If we can find it in New York City,'' he said, ''we can find it anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 15, 2002, Friday  An article on July 13 about old-growth trees in New York City misspelled the surname of a scientist at Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University who discussed tree-ring analysis. A reader's letter, received this week, pointed out that he is Neil Pederson, not Peterson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 15, 2002, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on July 13 about old-growth trees in New York City misspelled the surname of a scientist at Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University who discussed tree-ring analysis. A reader's letter, received this week, pointed out that he is Neil Pederson, not Peterson.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
