<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smokestack Visionary</title>
    <meta content="29FUELCET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="100" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/29/magazine/29FUELCELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1427328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DD1439F93AA1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smokestack Visionary</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Smokestack Visionary</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Danny Hakim</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Larry Burns, General Motors' vice president for research and development and planning, last January unveiled company's plans for car of future; prototype is called Hy-wire and debuted recently at Paris Motor Show; represents merging of hydrogen fuel cell technology with other advances resulting in car that emits only water vapor; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last January, Larry Burns, General Motors' vice president for research and development and planning, unveiled the company's plans for the car of the future. It wasn't exactly a car but the underpinnings of one, sort of a 16-foot-long, two-dimensional wine carafe on wheels -- what Burns called the ''skateboard.'' The car would come in two parts, Burns explained. The car's power and control system would be encased in the skateboard, which could be kept for decades while customers shuffled car bodies as tastes changed. And the bodies, too, would be radically different from what we know, with the windshield extending all the way down to the floor because the car's essential systems are kept underfoot.</p>
        <p>The first working prototype, dubbed Hy-wire, made its debut at the Paris Motor Show last week. Hy-wire represents a merging of technologies: the hydrogen fuel cell, a power system that creates electrical current from chemical reactions and drive-by-wire, which replaces mechanical linkages between parts with electronic ones. Taken together, the technologies would move the automobile from the machine age to the digital age and result in a car that emits only water vapor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors isn't known for being green, but Larry Burns, its fuel-cell guru, is working on the most ambitious project yet to create the future's environment-friendly car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last January, Larry Burns, General Motors' vice president for research and development and planning, unveiled the company's plans for the car of the future. It wasn't exactly a car but the underpinnings of one, sort of a 16-foot-long, two-dimensional wine carafe on wheels -- what Burns called the ''skateboard.'' The car would come in two parts, Burns explained. The car's power and control system would be encased in the skateboard, which could be kept for decades while customers shuffled car bodies as tastes changed. And the bodies, too, would be radically different from what we know, with the windshield extending all the way down to the floor because the car's essential systems are kept underfoot.</p>
        <p>The first working prototype, dubbed Hy-wire, made its debut at the Paris Motor Show last week. Hy-wire represents a merging of technologies: the hydrogen fuel cell, a power system that creates electrical current from chemical reactions and drive-by-wire, which replaces mechanical linkages between parts with electronic ones. Taken together, the technologies would move the automobile from the machine age to the digital age and result in a car that emits only water vapor.</p>
        <p>Burns, 51, earned his bachelor's degree from a Flint, Mich., university once called the General Motors Institute, but he preferred hanging out with Ann Arbor intellectuals while in school and got his doctorate from Berkeley. He says he believes there is enough evidence for carmakers to take global warming seriously. ''If it's true,'' Burns says, ''the ramifications are so significant that it's irresponsible not to be addressing it.'' It's a stance that puts him at odds with many people at G.M., among them the company's stogie-wielding vice chairman, Bob Lutz, who talks of global warming as tree-huggers' hokum and of the Kyoto Protocol as conspiracy theory. Rick Wagoner, G.M.'s C.E.O., falls somewhere in between. ''You read one article and it is and another article and it isn't,'' Wagoner says of global warming. ''I'm not a scientist. I don't think it's healthy for our industry to be exposed to a huge degree of risk here.'' For their part, environmentalists view G.M.'s quest for the ultimate green vehicle with suspicion. This is the company making a mass-market brand out of Hummer, after all, and arguing on Capitol Hill that being forced to make more efficient cars now will only undercut their work on the fuel cell for the future.</p>
        <p>''It's like Wimpy from 'Popeye,''' says Dan Becker of the Sierra Club. ''I'd gladly pay you Tuesday for a hamburger today. It's amazing G.M. gets away with it.''</p>
        <p>But G.M. insists that the environment is one key reason why it is taking Burns's project seriously. With 700 million vehicles in the world today and 1.1 billion expected by 2020, Burns says, short-term options like gas-electric hybrids or highly efficient gas cars can only delay, not halt, global warming. ''You've got to get to an endgame here,'' he says.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, environmental politics grew increasingly intense. California moved to force automakers to sell superefficient cars (and this year, it passed legislation to reduce greenhouse gases). Subsequently, the entire auto industry sped up its work on the electric car.</p>
        <p>The result, though, was frustration. In the late 1990's, G.M. scrapped its ambitious EV1 because the car could only travel 80 miles between charges. Last month, Ford gave up on its battery cars. And while Toyota continues to sell an electric S.U.V. in California, it does not do a compelling business.</p>
        <p>The question for carmakers became, What if an electric car generated its own electricity? The obvious ways to achieve that were through either the fuel cell (in which electrons are stripped from hydrogen atoms and used to form an electric current) or the gas-electric hybrid.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1990's, a high-level debate took place within G.M. to determine whether to focus on fuel cells or gas-electric hybrids. ''We did not view the hybrid as the ultimate solution to the problem,'' Wagoner says. ''In a high-fuel-cost environment, a hybrid could work. It's hard to see that happening in the U.S.''</p>
        <p>To much fanfare, Toyota and Honda began selling hybrids in the late 1990's, and each now sells tens of thousands, far more successful than electrics ever were but still small numbers. The hybrids are expensive to build, however, and what is not clear is whether they will ever make a profit.</p>
        <p>Every major automaker is working on fuel cells, but most conform to the design of normal cars. Hy-wire is not designed around an internal combustion engine, so it has no dashboard and few moving parts except for tires. Brake pedal and accelerator are replaced with electronically controlled steering using hand grips on the wheel. (One's feet wander reflexively, and it's easy to confuse twisting to speed up and squeezing to stop, but a few lazy eights around a parking lot makes it intuitive.)</p>
        <p>Not everyone at G.M. is convinced that Burns's vision will materialize. ''I just can't help remaining skeptical,'' Bob Lutz says, ''because I've lived through a series of miracle engines.'' He took pleasure in rolling his eyes at motoring revolutions of the past -- the jet engine, the Wankel engine, the orbital engine -- that are now all but discarded. ''We have to be careful not to create the impression that all of this is just around the corner.''</p>
        <p>Burns is tactful in response. ''Bob's one of my two bosses,'' he says. ''Even if he wasn't my boss, out of respect for him and his knowledge of the industry, I have to take his perspective into account.'' He adds, though, that automakers have been focused on fuel cells for less than a decade, compared with a century of dead ends on batteries, and are quickly closing the gap.</p>
        <p>Storage capacity has expanded to allow nearly 200 miles of range, far more than a battery-electric. The fact that Hy-wire's pressurized hydrogen gas tanks lie below the driver and passengers is a safety concern, so engineers are working on a spongelike form of hydrogen storage. Costs have come down by a factor of 10 in a decade, but Burns concedes another factor of 10 remains. Still, he maintains that G.M. can produce tens of thousands by 2010 and phase in broad usage by 2020.</p>
        <p>''This can be a better car all around,'' Burns says of the fuel cell. The right thing to do? Yes, he says, but it's more than that. ''At this point, it's a business issue. If we don't invent it, somebody else will.''</p>
        <p>CARS Danny Hakim reports on the auto industry for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Danny Hakim reports on the auto industry for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
