<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaving for Europe, Bush Draws On Hard Lessons of Diplomacy</title>
    <meta content="22PREX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1394406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagel, Chuck (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DA1038F931A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaving for Europe, Bush Draws On Hard Lessons of Diplomacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush is set to leave for Europe, where he is almost certain to be greeted by demonstrators who believe him a bully and by allies in campaign against terrorism who are increasingly unhappy about everything from steel tariffs to his determination to topple Pres Saddam Hussein of Iraq; Sec of State Colin L Powell and senior aides describe very different man, who has learned important lessons about diplomacy in 16 months and whose early missteps, they say, provided lessons that made possible arms agreement with Russia that will be centerpiece of his trip; Sen Chuck Hagel and some other Republicans continue to describe Bush's foreign policy as disjointed, with Bush talking about his faith in building alliances one day and warning that he will deal with Iraq with or without help of Arab states the next (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush leaves early Wednesday morning for Europe, where he is almost certain to be greeted by demonstrators who believe him a bully and by allies in the campaign against terrorism who are increasingly unhappy about everything from steel tariffs to his determination to topple Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>But as he departs, his senior aides describe a very different man, who has learned important lessons about diplomacy in 16 months and whose early missteps, they say, provided the lessons that made possible the arms agreement with Russia that will be the centerpiece of his trip.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush leaves early Wednesday morning for Europe, where he is almost certain to be greeted by demonstrators who believe him a bully and by allies in the campaign against terrorism who are increasingly unhappy about everything from steel tariffs to his determination to topple Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>But as he departs, his senior aides describe a very different man, who has learned important lessons about diplomacy in 16 months and whose early missteps, they say, provided the lessons that made possible the arms agreement with Russia that will be the centerpiece of his trip.</p>
        <p>''You need time for an administration to grow,'' Secretary of State Colin L. Powell said in an interview on Monday in his office, where he was far more candid than most administration officials in describing how Mr. Bush's approach to the world has evolved in the past year.</p>
        <p>''I think as a result of 9/11 particularly, he sees the value of coalitions and friends,'' Secretary Powell said. ''He saw the value of having people on his side.''</p>
        <p>That was all part of the education of a new American president, a man Secretary Powell describes as ''a quick learner'' who has mastered his briefing books and is now more likely than he was a year ago to rely on his own instincts. ''He had never been involved in this level of international interaction or diplomatic activity,'' Secretary Powell said.</p>
        <p>The result is a man who this week in Moscow will sound dramatically different from the George W. Bush who as a candidate declared that ''the verdict is still out'' on Russia's new president, Vladimir V. Putin. Back then, Mr. Bush talked of a ''corrupt and favored elite'' in Russia, and said relations would depend on whether Mr. Putin kept ''bombing innocent women and children'' in Chechnya.</p>
        <p>Russian troops are still fighting a guerrilla war in Chechnya, but Mr. Bush is unlikely to dwell on that as he lands in Russia for the first time. Already he has hailed Mr. Putin as a warrior against terrorism, a visionary and a friend. By next Tuesday, the two men plan to bury the arms race and make Russia a junior partner with NATO.</p>
        <p>By any measure, it is a startling turnabout, and one that aides seemed at pains to explain as they balanced acknowledgments of past mistakes against the portrait of their boss as a quick study.</p>
        <p>Secretary Powell, for instance, cited the vivid lesson that came in the ferocity of the European reaction to the president's decision to reject the Kyoto protocol on fighting global warming. ''Kyoto -- this is not talking out of school -- was not handled as well as it should have been,'' he said. ''And when the blowback came I think it was a sobering experience that everything the American president does has international repercussions.''</p>
        <p>Even today, some of Mr. Bush's Republican allies describe his foreign policy as disjointed, with Mr. Bush talking about his faith in building alliances one day and warning that he will deal with Iraq with or without the help of Arab states the next.</p>
        <p>The president, conceded Sen. Chuck Hagel, the Nebraska Republican, who ''came to office with one of the thinnest résumés in foreign policy, immediately drove himself into a lot of cul-de-sacs, and then began to find his way.''</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Bush dials around the world constantly to explain himself, yet his decisions to impose tariffs of up to 30 percent on steel imported from Europe, Russia and Asia and the ''unsigning'' of the treaty creating the international criminal court still leave his fellow leaders wondering which Bush they will be meeting this week, the man who with a wry smile talks of his new appreciation of diplomatic nuance, or the Bush who forges ahead alone if he has to.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's mixed message has so far produced more results with Russia than in the Middle East or Asia. But even in Europe, where Mr. Bush has cultivated relationships with Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany, President Jacques Chirac of France, and Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi of Italy -- all of whom he will visit this week -- his public image is still one of a leader less interested in assembling allies than pursuing his own course.</p>
        <p>''They came in with three bugaboos -- about China, about Russia, and about North Korea -- not wanting to talk to any of them,'' one of Mr. Bush's informal advisers during the campaign said of the president and his aides. ''But now he's learning to trust his instincts. And he is learning what all presidents learn -- that the world is a big place, and you can't row the boat alone.''</p>
        <p>At the White House, Mr. Bush's aides, led by his national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, insist that Mr. Bush never held views as simplistic as they were portrayed, even while she argues that his approach today is far more nuanced.</p>
        <p>''He spends far more time on these issues now,'' she said, ticking off the three national security meetings a week, the hours of morning terrorism briefings, and the succession of calls he makes to foreign leaders.</p>
        <p>For his part, Secretary Powell argued that the approach that led to the successful negotiations with Russia over reducing nuclear arsenals was shaped months before Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>It was the result, he said, of a melding of lessons learned from successes -- like the negotiations with China that won the release of the crew of an American spyplane -- as well as missteps, like the president's blunt declaration that the Kyoto protocol was ''dead.''</p>
        <p>''The learning experience of the China incident was be patient,'' Secretary Powell argued, recalling how he and others advised the president to ignore a letter from the Chinese leadership that threatened to unravel days of negotiations over the crew's return.</p>
        <p>The incident, Secretary Powell said, taught Mr. Bush the virtues of letting the State Department, the Central Intelligence Agency and the Defense Department ''shape the situation for the president for a little while,'' before he stepped in.</p>
        <p>He and Ms. Rice argued that both the China talks and the Kyoto fiasco taught Mr. Bush some lessons on how to accomplish the abandonment of the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty with Russia: Signal your moves, give the other side a lot of time to think about it, and coordinate the response.</p>
        <p>Over a period of months, they made it clear to Mr. Putin that the president would jettison the treaty if it could not be fixed, and made the final decision after the two leaders met at the Bush ranch in Crawford, Tex., in November. Mr. Putin, recognizing he had few cards to play, expressed his objections to Secretary Powell, smiled at him, ''and then began talking about the relationship beyond the ABM,'' the secretary recalled.</p>
        <p>That led to the hurried negotiations on the treaty to be signed on Friday, codifying each president's commitment to possess no more than 2,200 operational warheads by 2012.</p>
        <p>It was a lopsided negotiation, during which Mr. Putin, who cannot afford a larger nuclear force, won only one major victory: a formal treaty that binds further presidents.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Bush, this trip is mostly about demonstrating the strength of his personal relationship with Mr. Putin, quite a stretch for a president who, during the campaign, criticized Bill Clinton for investing too much in his relationship with Boris N. Yeltsin, and not enough on Russian reform.</p>
        <p>Former Defense Secretary James R. Schlesinger said Mr. Bush's new reliance on personal diplomacy reflected ''a belief that slowly overcomes all presidents after they are in office that personal relationships are more important than they seemed before they are in office.</p>
        <p>They become less interested in what their subordinates call the fundamentals of a relationship, and more interested in what other leaders tell them.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush argues that this is a fundamentally different Russia, one that has ended its constant internal debate on whether to join the West. Administration officials also argue that Mr. Putin has changed far more than Mr. Bush has in the past two years.</p>
        <p>''What we knew about him wasn't very encouraging,'' Ms. Rice recalled, when asked her own very negative characterizations of Mr. Putin during the campaign. ''I think now what we know about him is encouraging.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, she said, was determined now to make good on the promise he made Mr. Putin when they first met in Slovenia a year ago. ''He told him, 'Let's not be Brezhnev and Nixon; let's be Bush and Putin.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
