<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Stresses Business, but Disappoints Environmentalists</title>
    <meta content="Y20FOR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/20/business/20FORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1417295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zemke, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D8113DF933A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Stresses Business, but Disappoints Environmentalists</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ford Stresses Business, but Disappoints Environmentalists</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co will release its third annual corporate citizenship report after almost four-month delay; environmental groups who have seen report say company has moved from candor to caution and has offered scant goals for reducing greenhouse gas emissions or improving gas mileage; Ford Motor chairman-chief executive William C Ford Jr says difficult business conditions make it harder to achieve goals; Sierra Club executive director Carl Pope says report takes giant step in wrong direction for Ford; Deborah Zemke, Ford's director for corporate governance, comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a delay of almost four months, Ford Motor will release its third annual corporate citizenship report today.</p>
        <p>The previous reports have earned the praise of environmental groups and the disapproval of some competitors because of Ford's frank discussion of subjects like the impact of sport utility vehicles on global warming and smog-forming pollutants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmental groups who have seen Ford's corporate citizenship report said the company had moved from candor to caution and had offered scant goals for improving the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a delay of almost four months, Ford Motor will release its third annual corporate citizenship report today.</p>
        <p>The previous reports have earned the praise of environmental groups and the disapproval of some competitors because of Ford's frank discussion of subjects like the impact of sport utility vehicles on global warming and smog-forming pollutants.</p>
        <p>But the latest report comes at a time of financial distress for Ford, the second-largest automaker. Environmental groups who have seen the report said the company had moved from candor to caution and had offered scant goals for reducing greenhouse gas emissions or improving gas mileage.</p>
        <p>William C. Ford Jr., the chairman and chief executive, said ''difficult business conditions make it harder to achieve the goals we set for ourselves in many areas, including corporate citizenship.''</p>
        <p>''But that doesn't mean we will abandon our goals or change our direction,'' Mr. Ford said.</p>
        <p>Deborah Zemke, Ford's director for corporate governance, said the report had been delayed for a more thorough review because of the intense focus on corporate governance issues. She also said Ford had had its hands full with its turnaround effort.</p>
        <p>''We tried to be more complete than as bold as we had been in the past,'' she said. ''Our employees and our shareholders expect us to have a balanced perspective on the business right now, and I think they have every right to expect that.''</p>
        <p>The report says Ford improved the fuel economy of its S.U.V.'s 7 percent from the 2000 to 2001 model years, largely because it has introduced smaller S.U.V.'s like the Ford Escape and the Tribute from its Mazda brand. But the company's overall fuel economy has remained flat as less-efficient S.U.V.'s continue to account for a larger part of its product lineup.</p>
        <p>But this year's report lacked specifics on how to solve environmental problems and offered few alternatives to government regulations.</p>
        <p>Carl Pope, the executive director of the Sierra Club, said in a statement that ''this report takes a giant step in the wrong direction for Ford Motor Company, for American consumers and for the environment.''</p>
        <p>''It moves the ball backwards,'' Mr. Pope said, ''by refusing to set firm goals for the future, and raises troubling questions about Ford's commitment to improving its environmental performance.''</p>
        <p>The company's first report, released in May 2000, created a stir with its frank discussion of the S.U.V. and its environmental impact, saying that ''S.U.V. owners who use their vehicles for off-road recreation can damage the nature they and others seek to enjoy.''</p>
        <p>That a carmaker voluntarily made such an admission was groundbreaking, but it fitted with the image cultivated by Mr. Ford, whose speeches on subjects like global warming made him look like a sympathetic voice on the environment in an unsympathetic industry. In the first report, Mr. Ford joked that some regarded him as a ''Bolshevik'' when he joined the Ford board in 1988.</p>
        <p>But much has changed in the nearly two and a half years since the first report. Ford has fallen from a position of financial strength to one of weakness, losing $5.5 billion last year and embarking on a major turnaround effort in January. Toyota and Honda continue to press gains in the United States market, while Nissan and, to a lesser extent, Chrysler are making progress in their comeback efforts. Perhaps of most immediate concern is the relative strength of General Motors, which is putting pressure on Ford by leading a price war.</p>
        <p>At the same time, S.U.V. sales continue to grow, and the company depends on the profit they provide. While Mr. Ford grapples with saving his great-grandfather's company, which turns 100 next year, his once- sterling relationship with environmental groups has suffered.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists were embittered earlier this year when Ford supported the industry's lobbying campaign against a Senate effort to raise federal fuel economy requirements. An important industry trade group, supported by Ford, is also developing a legal strategy against legislation in California that would force automakers to reduce emissions of gases tied to global climate change. The Sierra Club recently focused on Mr. Ford in a radio spot, appealing to him ''to do his part and to produce more fuel-efficient cars, S.U.V.'s and pickup trucks.''</p>
        <p>In the report, Mr. Ford's personal statement is largely devoted to discussing the revival plan. Discussion of the recent Senate fight over fuel economy standards is relegated to a small box at the report's end.</p>
        <p>''It's not a candid discussion of what happened and what role Ford played in helping kill the legislation,'' said Robert K. Massie, the executive director of the Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies, an umbrella group that has affiliations with corporations like Ford and G.M.</p>
        <p>Mr. Massie said his group was reconsidering its relationship with the two automakers after the Senate debate but also said that Ford was ''still committed to the issues we care about and to transparency.''</p>
        <p>''This is a company with one foot on the accelerator and one on the brake,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
