<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Offshore Harvest of Wind Is Proposed for Cape Cod</title>
    <meta content="16WIND$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/16/science/earth/16WIND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1384496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Turbines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Cod</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Martha's Vineyard (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nantucket (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Management Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wind Management Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cape Wind Associates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ziner, Karen Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Nantucket</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Martha's Vineyard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4DF113CF935A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Offshore Harvest of Wind Is Proposed for Cape Cod</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Offshore Harvest of Wind Is Proposed for Cape Cod</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN LEE ZINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ziner, Karen Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on plan by Cape Wind Associates, joint venture between Energy Management Inc and Wind Management Inc, to build array of 170 slender turbines in Nantucket Sound that it says would generate nearly half of electrical supply for Cape Cod, Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket; critics say turbines would disturb birds, harm fisheries and scare away tourists; maps; graph; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If three wind-power proponents succeed, 170 slender turbines will one day appear in Nantucket Sound and, if the winds are right, generate nearly half the electrical supply for Cape Cod and the islands of Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket.</p>
        <p>Brian Braginton-Smith, James S. Gordon and Brian Caffyn, partners in Cape Wind Associates, want to build a ''wind farm'' on Horseshoe Shoals, a protected shallows with powerful breezes off Cape Cod. They say their wind park will deliver clean electricity, protect the environment and ease dependency on foreign oil. Advocates call the wind farm the future of renewable energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposed wind farm could represent the future of renewable energy, but critics say the turbines will disturb birds, harm fisheries and scare away tourists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If three wind-power proponents succeed, 170 slender turbines will one day appear in Nantucket Sound and, if the winds are right, generate nearly half the electrical supply for Cape Cod and the islands of Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket.</p>
        <p>Brian Braginton-Smith, James S. Gordon and Brian Caffyn, partners in Cape Wind Associates, want to build a ''wind farm'' on Horseshoe Shoals, a protected shallows with powerful breezes off Cape Cod. They say their wind park will deliver clean electricity, protect the environment and ease dependency on foreign oil. Advocates call the wind farm the future of renewable energy.</p>
        <p>But critics say the turbines will disturb birds, harm fisheries and scare away tourists. The result has been a debate about how and where to harvest the wind.</p>
        <p>Though dozens of wind farms are generating electricity across the country and off the coast of Europe, no one in the United States has ever built one of this magnitude, or at sea.</p>
        <p>Cape Wind Associates, a joint venture between Energy Management Inc. and Wind Management Inc. (a subsidiary of UPC, a European-based wind-energy company) of Boston, has submitted draft environmental plans for the wind park to state and federal agencies. A separate proposal for a single research tower is also under review.</p>
        <p>''We've really only just begun what's going to be a long, thorough and comprehensive permitting review,'' said Mark Rodgers, a Cape Wind spokesman. That began in last month, when the New England District Army Corps of Engineers started a ''scoping'' process, inviting public comment and asking Cape Wind questions about effects on the environment.</p>
        <p>Will too many birds fly into the turbines? Will vibrations affect worms, clams and other animals on or below the seabed floor? Can the towers coexist with commercial fishing vessels and recreational boaters? Will they affect ocean currents or radio and television frequencies? Will they be ugly?</p>
        <p>The turbines, as proposed, will be arrayed in a grid pattern roughly five miles long by five miles wide, a third to a half-mile apart. Each carbon-steel turbine column will rise 270 feet above the water line to a boxy hub where three blades are mounted. At the tallest blade tip, the turbines will reach nearly 40 stories.</p>
        <p>When the blades spin, they will power a turbine generator in each tower hub. Submarine cables from each pole will join at a central platform station within the wind park; two parallel main cables will carry the power to landfall at Yarmouth. There they will link with an overland cable system and deliver up to 420 megawatts to the New England regional power grid -- enough to power almost half a million homes and businesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braginton-Smith, 49, who grew up on Cape Cod and has sailed Nantucket Sound all his life, says the wind park would help protect the environment for the next generation. As the original proponent, he joined Mr. Gordon, president of Energy Management Inc., which has built natural-gas-powered generating plants throughout New England, and Mr. Caffyn, who heads Wind Management Inc., which has built wind-power projects in Italy and the United States.</p>
        <p>They formed Cape Wind Associates L.L.C. to back their project, which they estimate will cost at least $600 million. Mr. Gordon, the president of Cape Wind, said the partners would seek conventional, long-term loans through major financial institutions. They hope the wind farm will be operating by 2005.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, after Sept. 11, the country has a national priority to expedite the development of domestic energy resources,'' Mr. Gordon said. ''And five and a half miles off the coast of Hyannis, we have an awesome, inexhaustible supply of domestic energy resource -- the wind.''</p>
        <p>But the wind farm proposal has provoked opposition from fishing interests, boaters and tourism representatives, the Massachusetts Marine Trades Association, the Town of Barnstable and Three Bays Preservation, an environmental advocacy group based in that town.</p>
        <p>Among the opponents is Wayne Kurker, president of Hyannis Marina, who last summer formed the Alliance to Protect Nantucket Sound, to fight the wind farm proposal.</p>
        <p>''A good portion of us who migrated to Cape Cod came to enjoy Nantucket Sound,'' he said. ''And if Nantucket Sound becomes an industrial, electrical generation area, then it's no longer the national treasure that people currently feel it is. We look at this as our wilderness, our national park.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kurker predicts several problems, among them the spinning turbines, which he says will kill so many birds that their bodies will litter the beaches and drive away the tourists.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the Army Corps of Engineers, the Massachusetts Audubon Society outlined a number of concerns about the proposed project's effects on resident and migratory birds, including the roseate tern, an endangered species.</p>
        <p>Jack Clarke, a society official, said the group worried that the birds migrating at night might be attracted to the turbine warning lights, or become disoriented by the towers during storms.</p>
        <p>''At least half the population of East Coast seabirds spend at least six months on Nantucket Sound,'' Mr. Clarke said. ''So it's a nationally significant area.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said, ''we have to have an open mind when someone comes up with a credible, nonpolluting proposal,'' adding that the society would decide whether to support the plan after it had seen more information.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braginton-Smith said, ''According to all of the relevant evidence that we've been able to ascertain from the European models that have been operating for up to 10 years, there seems to be no significant threat to seabirds from the offshore towers.''</p>
        <p>Some environmental and advocacy organizations have offered conditional support, and Mr. Braginton-Smith said Greenpeace was ''a very positive supporter of offshore wind.''</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Gordon: ''There are a lot of people who look at wind turbines and see them as a study in power and grace and a visual testimony to us working with nature. So there are a lot of people who enjoy looking at wind turbines. For those who don't, we've significantly reduced the visual impact'' by taking them offshore. He said they would hardly be visible from land.</p>
        <p>As for noise, ''These things are so far offshore you won't notice,'' said Brian Parsons, project manager for wind-energy applications at the Department of Energy's National Renewable Energy Laboratory. ''Close up, you hear two things. You hear a swoosh, which is the aerodynamic noise of the wind going over the blades. And the second thing you hear is generator and gear-box noise -- low-level mechanical stuff.''</p>
        <p>Although you wouldn't want to build a house directly underneath the turbines, Mr. Parsons said, a few hundred yards away, ''it's hardly noticeable.''</p>
        <p>In Chilmark, a town on Martha's Vineyard, where a wind machine operated in the mid-1970's, people complained at first, said John Abrams, the contractor who installed it. ''They said it was going to be visual pollution, and it was going to be noisy and interfere with television reception, and that machine, of course, did none of those things,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the Chilmark wind machine was early technology and kept breaking down, Mr. Abrams said. ''We got tired of fixing it and took it down -- and then, you should have heard the complaints. Everyone had grown to love it. We all remember the mesmerizing effect of pinwheels when we were kids. And that's what these are like. They're beautiful. There is an emotional connection.''</p>
        <p>The Department of Energy is watching the project with interest, Mr. Parsons said, because ''it's the first serious offshore wind proposal in the United States.''</p>
        <p>''It's as simple as that,'' he said. ''We'd like to see what happens.''</p>
        <p>Particularly in New England, ''having something close offshore where it's not too far from the cities'' would avoid some troublesome siting issues for land-based wind farms, like long, expensive transmission lines. ''So if someone comes along and says, 'We want to do 420 megawatts offshore,' '' Mr. Parsons said, ''that could have a real impact.''</p>
        <p>Tim Dugan, a spokesman for the United States Army Corps of Engineers New England District in Concord, Mass., said it would take 18 months and perhaps as much as three years to complete the scoping process and necessary environmental impact statement for federal scrutiny and an environmental impact review for the state.</p>
        <p>John Saintcross, project manager for the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority, said, ''Europeans have built these kinds of facilities and are operating them now.'' From an engineering perspective, he said, ''they should be able to put these machines in the ocean floor'' and build cabling systems.</p>
        <p>A major problem, he said, is persuading the public that an offshore wind farm is a good idea. The Cape Wind Associates project would be a large installation, Mr. Saintcross said, ''but the only way to go offshore is to put in a lot of machines.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
