<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA Presses Its Search for Extraterrestrial Life</title>
    <meta content="04LIFE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/04/science/space/04LIFE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1397685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johns Hopkins University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Overbye, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Astronomy and Astrophysics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Astronomy and Astrophysics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D8133AF937A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA Presses Its Search for Extraterrestrial Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NASA Presses Its Search for Extraterrestrial Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS OVERBYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Overbye, Dennis</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA holds gathering of some 100 astronomers, physicists, chemists, geologists and biologists at Space Telescope Science Institute at Johns Hopkins University for discussions that center on new field of astrobiology; discussions and debates address questions about interstellar weather, nature and history of life on Earth and which parts of galaxy are suitable for life; plans are put forward for generation of spacecraft that will search for extraterrestrial life; photos; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One is the world of cold dark matter; the other is the world of warm wet matter. One is majestic, terrible in its bright furies of exploding stars and galaxies, abstract and far away. The other is squirmy and slithery, often gross, and as close as your fingernails.</p>
        <p>But without astronomy to provide the stage, in the form of galaxies, suns, planets, comets, sheets of cosmic radiation and that dark stuff that makes up most of the universe, there would be no place for biology, for life, to strut its stuff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent gathering at the Space Telescope Science Institute produced plans for a generation of spacecraft that will prospect the cosmos for planets, sifting pinpoints of light for the signatures of life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One is the world of cold dark matter; the other is the world of warm wet matter. One is majestic, terrible in its bright furies of exploding stars and galaxies, abstract and far away. The other is squirmy and slithery, often gross, and as close as your fingernails.</p>
        <p>But without astronomy to provide the stage, in the form of galaxies, suns, planets, comets, sheets of cosmic radiation and that dark stuff that makes up most of the universe, there would be no place for biology, for life, to strut its stuff.</p>
        <p>The pursuit of that ancient heavenly connection has lately moved near center stage at NASA, which assembled some 100 astronomers, physicists, chemists, geologists and even a few biologists at the Space Telescope Science Institute on the Johns Hopkins University campus recently to talk about extraterrestrial life.</p>
        <p>In discussions on topics like the vagaries of interstellar weather and the reflective properties of vegetation, they debated the nature and history of life on Earth, which parts of the galaxy were suitable for life and laid plans for a generation of spacecraft that will prospect the cosmos for planets, sifting pinpoints of light for the signatures of life as humans know or can imagine it.</p>
        <p>''The search for life has come up as a major issue,'' said Dr. Kenneth Nealson, a professor of geobiology at the University of Southern California, which means financing, he said, which means in turn that a lot of very smart people will be looking at the problem.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, NASA with great fanfare set up an Astrobiology Institute without walls, centered at the Ames Research Center in California and composed of 15 different research teams tied together by videoconference and telephone.</p>
        <p>The ''Astrophysics of Life'' meeting, last month, was top heavy with astronomers and cosmologists. They were in familiar territory, said Dr. Edwin Turner, himself a astronomer from Princeton, noting that, like cosmology, astrobiology is a discipline with grand questions and a paucity of data.</p>
        <p>Though spacecraft have visited, at least briefly, almost every planet and sizable moon in the solar system, Earth is still the lone proven site of life, not to mention intelligence, in the universe.</p>
        <p>''No. 2 is the most important number in this process,'' said Dr. Jill Tarter, a radio astronomer at the SETI Institute in Mountain View, Calif., which is dedicated to the search for extraterrestrial intelligence.</p>
        <p>Running through the meeting was a constant tension between the ability to develop exquisitely sensitive tools to sense life as we know it -- sensors to look for the spectral signature of plant chlorophyll, say -- and the difficulty of looking for life as we do not know it.</p>
        <p>''Everything we do here is hostage to our concept of what life is,'' said Dr. David Des Marais of NASA's Ames Research Center, and part of a committee charged by NASA with developing a road map of astrobiological research for the next decade. Dr. Nealson, of U.S.C., urged scientists to look for life in ''non-Earthcentric ways.''</p>
        <p>''Microbes here can grow on anything, eat and breathe anything,'' and the same is probably true on other planets, he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Instead of looking for specific biological signatures, astrobiologists should look for a combination of physical and chemical complexity, he said, for example, layering in ocean sediments.</p>
        <p>''Layers should never form on a lifeless planet,'' Dr. Nealson explained. ''It's the best biosignature we've got.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, NASA's road map is perhaps inevitably oriented toward finding our own biological cousins -- even though there is no agreement on how, where or even when molecular chemistry on the primordial Earth made the leap to molecular biology.</p>
        <p>''Chemistry is not life, life is not just chemistry,'' said Dr. George Cody, a chemist in the Geophysical Laboratory of the Carnegie Institution of Washington.</p>
        <p>Life as we know it starts with a planet. There are now 85 known planets orbiting other stars, said Dr. Geoffrey W. Marcy, an astronomer at the University of California at Berkeley, who discovered many of them with Dr. R. Paul Butler of the Carnegie Institute of Washington by looking for the slight gravitation tugs the planets exert on their parent stars. They are all massive gas giants like Jupiter, and so unlikely abodes for life themselves.</p>
        <p>But the apparent profusion of such stars has encouraged astronomers to think that smaller planets may be abundant as well. NASA's Kepler spacecraft, to be launched in 2007, will look for the dips in starlight caused by planets passing in front of their parent stars, and could find ''hundreds of Earths,'' said Dr. Charles Beichman of NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory.</p>
        <p>After that will be SIM, short for Space Interferometry Mission, which will infer the presence of terrestrial-size planets around stars within about 50 light-years from the wobbles of their parent stars.</p>
        <p>All this is leading up to the Terrestrial Planet Finder, planned for 2015, whose goal is to detect distant planets directly, using an occulting disk or interference techniques to separate the planet's dim light from that of its much brighter parent star.</p>
        <p>Dr. Beichman compared the challenge to ''finding a firefly next to a searchlight on a foggy night.''</p>
        <p>(The European Space Agency has its own planet finders, Eddington and Corot, in the works, culminating in a mission called Darwin, which may be combined with T.P.F.)</p>
        <p>At best, a distant planet would appear as a faint dot, a single pixel, in such instruments. What to do with those precious photons has become a cottage industry among astrobiologists. Dr. Turner of Princeton invited audience members to imagine what they could learn from Earth were it shrunk to a point. As Earth rotated, geography and weather would cause its brightness to vary. The more complex a planet's so-called light curve, he said, ''the more interesting'' the planet.</p>
        <p>Another tool astrobiologists could use to sense life on that dot is spectroscopy, breaking down the light into its component wavelengths where the signatures of individual elements and molecules in the planet's atmosphere can be seen. Atmospheric oxygen, which on Earth was produced and maintained by photosynthesis of plants and bacteria, would be the ''most reliable'' indicator, Dr. Beichman said.</p>
        <p>Another is plant leaves, whose cell structure produces a spectral feature known as ''the red edge,'' said Dr. Sara Seager, an astronomer at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton.</p>
        <p>Dr. Seager said that Galileo spacecraft had detected the ''red edge'' effect during a 1990 flyby of Earth on its way to Jupiter. In a 1993 Nature paper, a group of scientists led by the Cornell astronomer Carl Sagan concluded that the red edge combined with abundant atmospheric oxygen and radio signals constituted ''evidence of life on Earth without any a priori assumptions about its chemistry.'' The red edge also shows up strongly in spectral measurements of Earthshine reflected off the dark parts of a crescent Moon by Dr. Neville J. Woolf of the University of Arizona, reported Dr. Wesley Traub of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics.</p>
        <p>In planning their search, scientists think they can rule out at least parts of the galaxy and focus on so-called habitable zones. For one thing the elements like iron, oxygen and carbon, which form terrestrial planets and creatures, not to mention the radioactive elements that provide the internal heat for planetary geological activity, must be built up over eons by nuclear processing of primordial hydrogen and helium in stars.</p>
        <p>In fact, Dr. Guillermo Gonzalez, an astronomer from Iowa State University, pointed out that the stars known to have planets tend to have higher abundances of these elements, which astronomers call metals, than stars without planets.</p>
        <p>This nuclear processing happens faster at the cores of galaxies than on the outside, he said, leading to an abundance of metals in the center of the galaxy and a paucity at its edge.</p>
        <p>But radiation and chaotic gravitational encounters with other stars make the center of a galaxy too hazardous for complex life to survive, leaving a zone midway out from the galactic center as the favored abode. Moreover, Dr. Gonzalez suggested, the habitable zone was unlikely to include the densely packed spiral arms of the galaxy.</p>
        <p>But Dr. John Scalo, a University of Texas astronomer who is an expert on the cosmic radiation environment, argued that if the environment was too boring, it might not be driving evolution.</p>
        <p>Life needs some radiation for mutations, but not too much, he said. The most important source of these mutations, according to his calculations, he said, is from solar flares, which bathe the atmosphere with X-rays every now and then.</p>
        <p>This led him to wonder about life on planets around red dwarf, or ''M,'' stars, which are slightly smaller and fainter than the Sun (and not presently included on the target lists of SETI astronomers) but that are prone to more frequent flares. ''Is evolution accelerated on planets around M stars?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Each star has its own habitable zone, defined as the region around it in which a planet can keep liquid water, the sine qua non of life-as-we-know-it, on its surface, said Dr. James F. Kasting, a professor of geosciences at Penn State University.</p>
        <p>For Earth, the inner edge of that zone, where water vapor from evaporating oceans would ramp up the greenhouse effect, lies at 95 percent of Earth's present orbital distance. The outer edge, where the planet would freeze solid, he said, could extend as far as twice Earth's orbital radius, beyond the orbit of Mars.</p>
        <p>The outer range is uncertain, he explained, because of uncertainties in the abilities of geological activity on the planet to keep the planet warm. By some calculations, an increase of only a percent of the distance from the Sun would cause glaciers to envelop Earth, and indeed some scientists have suggested that Earth was a so-called snowball in its past when the Sun, according to standard astronomical calculations, would have been cooler.</p>
        <p>But eruptions of carbon dioxide from volcanoes or bursts of methane from emerging life would have released enough greenhouse gases into the atmosphere to warm things up, Dr. Kasting said.</p>
        <p>What acted to keep Earth warm before the emergence of life is a bit of a mystery. ''We know Earth was not a snowball most of its history,'' Dr. Kasting said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Life, according to the strongest version of the so-called Gaia principle, regulates conditions on Earth to maintain an optimal environment, but these regulatory powers have their limits, said Dr. Kevin Zahnle, an astrophysicist at the Ames Research Center. Maybe a planet has to be lucky, as well, he said.</p>
        <p>Consider the plight of Venus. On Earth, he said, Gaia had many knobs to turn, including aerosols, ice sheets and clouds. On Venus, now sweltering under thick greenhouse clouds at 800 degrees, and dry as a bone, there was little evidence that any knobs were turned.</p>
        <p>''You begin to wonder if Gaia happens,'' he said mournfully, pointing out that billions of years ago Venus had the conditions for oceans. What happened to the oceans? ''What happened to Gaia?''</p>
        <p>He ended his talk with a litany of questions. ''Do small planets die young? Do big planets evolve animals?''</p>
        <p>''Was Venus ever habitable?''</p>
        <p>''This is a sad question, I think,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
