<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="01FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1436835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DF1F3FF932A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Hunt for Al Qaeda Hindered in Pakistan  The United States hunted worldwide for leaders of Al Qaeda this summer, but support for the group among Pakistanis, elaborate secrecy and Internet communication are making it difficult to eliminate the group.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Earthquake in Italy  An earthquake in southern Italy caused the collapse of a nursery and elementary school. More than 50 children were trapped under layers of crumbled concrete, and at least 20 were killed. Two adults were also reported dead.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Hunt for Al Qaeda Hindered in Pakistan  The United States hunted worldwide for leaders of Al Qaeda this summer, but support for the group among Pakistanis, elaborate secrecy and Internet communication are making it difficult to eliminate the group.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Earthquake in Italy  An earthquake in southern Italy caused the collapse of a nursery and elementary school. More than 50 children were trapped under layers of crumbled concrete, and at least 20 were killed. Two adults were also reported dead.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Rights Group Criticizes Arafat  A report on Palestinian suicide bombings by Human Rights Watch calls the attacks crimes against humanity and criticizes the Palestinian Authority for failing to act effectively to stop them.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Israel's Political Shift  Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel recruited as his defense minister a former army chief of staff, Shaul Mofaz, who has advocated aggressive measures against Palestinians, including exiling Yasir Arafat.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>South African Extremists  South Africa's defense minister said that the government had begun searching for white extremists within the military and the police force who might be trying to ignite ''a race war'' within the country.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Bombers Sentenced in France  A special French court has sentenced two members of Algeria's Armed Islamic Group to life imprisonment for their role in three bombings that killed 8 people and wounded more than 200 in 1995.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Sri Lankan Guerrilla Sentenced  The High Court in Sri Lanka sentenced the leader of the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam guerrilla group to 200 years in prison in absentia, even as a second round of peace talks began between the rebels and the government.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>A Colossal Energy Effort  Meeting the world's rising energy needs without worsening global warming would require a concerted research and spending effort that would rival the Manhattan Project, said a diverse group of scientists and engineers.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A24-29</p>
        <p>Accused Snipers Charged In Slaying in Baton Rouge  Two days after killing a woman in Montgomery, Ala., on Sept. 21, John Muhammad returned to Baton Rouge, La., with Lee Malvo and shot a shopkeeper to death, the authorities charged.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gephardt's Dual Campaign  Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the House minority leader, is on a complicated mission with perhaps conflicting objectives, campaigning to put the Democrats in the majority in the House of Representatives, even as he eyes the party's presidential nomination in 2004.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Democrats' Mixed Message  Strategists in both parties say that Democrats are offering a scrambled message on the economy, reflecting their deep divisions over the tax cut that President Bush pushed through Congress last year.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Bush Barnstorms for G.O.P.  President Bush barnstormed across the country on behalf of Republican candidates, accusing Congressional Democrats of blocking major parts of his agenda.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Report Reveals Cold War Tests  In the latest release of once-classfied reports on chemical warfare tests during the cold war, the Pentagon said that it detonated artillery shells and rockets filled with deadly Sarin gas in Hawaii in 1967.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Union Leader to Return Funds  The president of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters, President Bush's closest friend in organized labor, has agreed to return all of $200,000 in profits he made in a stock deal that is under federal investigation.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Administrators to Leave Church  Five top administrators of the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles have announced that they will leave their posts at the end of the year.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Syphilis on Rise, Report Finds  The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention reported that syphilis, a disease that federal health officials are trying to eliminate, is on the rise in the United States for the first time in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Killing of Peaceable D.J. Bewilders Hip-Hop Fans  As investigators hunted for the killers of Jam Master Jay, a member of the rap group Run-DMC, the rap world puzzled over who would want to kill the amiable D.J., whose group rapped about sneakers and basketball, not guns and drugs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Polls Show Few Know McCall  While running for governor, H. Carl McCall never misses an opportunity to trumpet his long career serving the public. But despite decades on the political scene, Mr. McCall, the Democratic candidate, is barely known by voters, who, according to polls, may recognize his name but do not have an impression of him.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Olympic Bids Face Challenge  In their efforts to be elected the United States' candidate to host the 2012 Summer Olympics, the marketers for New York and San Francisco have had to overcome an unusual problem. They are not allowed to target their pitches to the one audience that matters: the board members of the United States Olympic Committee.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Ex-Newark Mayor Pleads Guilty  Kenneth A. Gibson, the former mayor of Newark, pleaded guilty to a single charge of federal income tax evasion as part of a plea agreement that spared him a jail sentence and a retrial on multiple fraud and bribery charges.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; E31-42</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Andre De Toth  A Hungarian-born movie and television director who was best known for ''House of Wax,'' one of the few jewels of the 1950's 3-D movie craze, he was 89.</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Webster's Hiring Under Fire  Three investigations were begun into the way William H. Webster was chosen to oversee the accounting profession. And House and Senate Democrats have called for the resignations of Mr. Webster and the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission that selected him.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Investigates Hospital  Tenet Healthcare, a for-profit hospital chain, said that one of its California hospitals had been raided by federal officials as part of an investigation into unnecessary surgeries and possible Medicare billing fraud.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>3.1% Growth in Third Quarter  The economy, driven by consumer spending, grew at a 3.1 percent rate in the third quarter, somewhat below expectations. Though gains in personal income remain healthy, the capacity of households to spend is starting to show signs of strain.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Fighting Intellectual Piracy  In the 1990's, the fight for intellectual property rights in China was mainly seen as a trade dispute between the wealthy West and the developing East. Now, Chinese artists, feeling the loss of royalties, are joining big foreign interests to try to prevent intellectual piracy.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: The mess at the S.E.C.; distant neighbors, again; the real problem in making judges; picking a substitute mayor.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E39  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>C8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
