<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sonal Pandya, Sunil Dalal</title>
    <meta content="30PAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/30/fashion/weddings/30PAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1404663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PANDYA, SONAL INDRAVADAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DALAL, DR. SUNIL SURESH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EED9123EF933A05755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sonal Pandya, Sunil Dalal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sonal Pandya and Sunil Dalal</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sonal Indravadan Pandya, the daughter of Manjula O. Pandya and Indravadan S. Pandya of Union, N.J., is to be married today to Dr. Sunil Suresh Dalal, a son of Bharti S. Dalal and Suresh T. Dalal of Hayward, Calif. Pandit Suresh M. Bhatt, a Hindu priest, is to perform the ceremony at Birchwood Manor in Whippany, N.J.</p>
        <p>The bride, 30, is the manager of the climate change program at Conservation International, an environmental preservation group in Washington. She is also a member of the national board of the Network of Indian Professionals, a business association. She graduated from Drew University and received a master's degree in conservation biology and sustainable development from the University of Maryland. Her father is an agent for Century 21 Plaza Realty, in Jersey City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sonal Pandya, Sunil Dalal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sonal Indravadan Pandya, the daughter of Manjula O. Pandya and Indravadan S. Pandya of Union, N.J., is to be married today to Dr. Sunil Suresh Dalal, a son of Bharti S. Dalal and Suresh T. Dalal of Hayward, Calif. Pandit Suresh M. Bhatt, a Hindu priest, is to perform the ceremony at Birchwood Manor in Whippany, N.J.</p>
        <p>The bride, 30, is the manager of the climate change program at Conservation International, an environmental preservation group in Washington. She is also a member of the national board of the Network of Indian Professionals, a business association. She graduated from Drew University and received a master's degree in conservation biology and sustainable development from the University of Maryland. Her father is an agent for Century 21 Plaza Realty, in Jersey City.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dalal, 30, is a biomedical engineer at BD Biosciences in San Jose, Calif. He graduated from the University of California at San Diego and received a Ph.D. in biomedical engineering from the University of Southern California. His father retired as a civil and structural engineering consultant in Hayward.</p>
        <p>Through Ms. Pandya's parents and Dr. Dalal's aunt and uncle, who knew one another because of business, their families discovered last summer that each had a child who was single and of an equally marriageable age. It seemed a promising beginning, until Dr. Dalal's uncle and aunt mentioned that their nephew lives in Hayward. The bride's mother feared that her daughter might then marry and move to California.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Pandya's father thought otherwise and secretly gave her Dr. Dalal's e-mail address, asking her not to tell her mother.</p>
        <p>''He knew I would definitely respond to someone who was intellectual,'' she said. ''And then, of course, the really big thing was that he knew Sunil's aunt and uncle were a good family.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Dalal said that he and Ms. Pandya didn't mind that their relatives were broadcasting their availability.</p>
        <p>''We're both professionals, so we don't have that much time for looking on our own,'' he said. ''So any help we could get from family and friends was appreciated.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Pandya sent a message to Dr. Dalal, who phoned her that very evening. They met a few weeks later, when Dr. Dalal traveled to Washington on business. Within four months, after seeing each other every month and exchanging e-mail messages and phone calls several times a day, they were talking about when they should marry.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dalal said that even in their first conversation, a match seemed possible.</p>
        <p>''I like an independent woman, and it was important for me that she had a career that she believes in and doesn't have to rely on her man to tell her what to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The bride, as her mother feared, is going to relocate to California. But Mrs. Pandya has decided that distance is not as important to her as her daughter's happiness.</p>
        <p>''Now I think, 'Good,' '' she said. ''The boy is good, the family is good, everything is good.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
