<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1424039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2D61F31F936A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>Fears That Al Qaeda Is Rebuilding in Pakistan  There are growing fears among Western officials in Pakistan that Al Qaeda is re-establishing its operations in middle-class neighborhoods in Karachi and other cities with the help of Pakistani militants. A senior Pakistani intelligence official said Al Qaeda might be trying to re-establish Karachi as a transit point for moving personnel, money and matériel.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Strong Words From Briton  In Britain's strongest statement yet on Iraq, the foreign secretary, Jack Straw, said in a television interview to be broadcast today that Saddam Hussein's government will have to fall if it does not comply with Security Council resolutions requiring it to rid itself of offensive weapons.</p>
        <p>21</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>Fears That Al Qaeda Is Rebuilding in Pakistan  There are growing fears among Western officials in Pakistan that Al Qaeda is re-establishing its operations in middle-class neighborhoods in Karachi and other cities with the help of Pakistani militants. A senior Pakistani intelligence official said Al Qaeda might be trying to re-establish Karachi as a transit point for moving personnel, money and matériel.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Strong Words From Briton  In Britain's strongest statement yet on Iraq, the foreign secretary, Jack Straw, said in a television interview to be broadcast today that Saddam Hussein's government will have to fall if it does not comply with Security Council resolutions requiring it to rid itself of offensive weapons.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Deputy Prime Minister Tariq Aziz said Iraq would let United Nations weapons inspectors return only under a comprehensive agreement that would prevent an attack by the United States and lift the United Nations sanctions imposed after Iraq invaded Kuwait in 1990.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Fear of Hong Kong Crackdown  A senior Hong Kong official said the government would pursue legislation to prohibit sedition and subversion. Democracy advocates criticized the move as a danger to civil liberties.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Italians Protest Against Leader  Tens of thousands of Italians protested in Rome, contending that Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi is exploiting his government role and the legislative process for personal advantage.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Austrian Withdraws Candidacy  The Austrian far-right populist Jörg Haider, who led a revolt in his Freedom Party that toppled the government last week, said he was fed up with his party and would withdraw his candidacy for its chairmanship.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>22-30</p>
        <p>Five Buffalo Men Accused Of Having Al Qaeda Ties  Five Arab-American men charged with operating an active cell of Al Qaeda in western New York received intensive weapons training in Afghanistan as recently as the summer of 2001 and had been sent back to the United States to await the order for an attack on American targets, federal law enforcement officials said.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>NPR Squeezed Out  Christian radio stations in Louisiana routed National Public Radio under a federal law that allows noncommercial broadcasters with licenses for full-power stations to push out those with weaker signals -- the equivalent of the varsity team kicking the freshmen out of the gym. This is happening all over the country.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Weapons Depot Near a Town  The Anniston Army Depot in Alabama houses 9 percent of the nation's chemical weapons stockpile, which is supposed to be destroyed by 2004. But unlike other depots, the weapons bunkers here are close to a community, and some people are worried.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Waning Demand for Logos  The demand for logos on designer clothes and accessories has declined. Some say the reasons range from a backlash against conspicuous consumption to a reaction to last year's terrorist attacks.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Boeing Pact Approved  A strike vote by the Boeing Company's largest union failed, meaning the company's latest offer to employees was automatically approved.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>A Kennedy Retools Campaign  Despite seeing her double-digit leads having evaporated in the Maryland governor's race, Maryland's Lieutenant Governor, Kathleen Kennedy Townsend, rejects the contention of her opponent, Representative Robert L. Ehrlich Jr., that the Kennedy spirit has faded in the estimate of voters.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>33-38</p>
        <p>State Study Finds Failings At Adult Homes for Mentally Ill  A Pataki administration study acknowledges widespread failings at New York's homes for the adult mentally ill, concluding that the state is allowing some mentally ill people to be exploited in a system plagued by inept, wasteful and fraudulent services.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>Department of Health officials said they would seek to fine one home in Brooklyn $56,500. The home had by far the worst violations out of 23 homes examined by inspectors.</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Global Warming Omitted  For the first time in six years, the annual federal report on air pollution trends does not have a section on global warming.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>Salvator Altchek  Known as the $5 doctor to the melting pot of Brooklyn, especially the poorer residents of affluent Brooklyn Heights, he was 92.</p>
        <p>40</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>39  Weather</p>
        <p>41  Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>36</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
