<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. vs. U.N. Court: Two Worldviews</title>
    <meta content="Y02NATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/02/international/02NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1405226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Criminal Court</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Criminal Court</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91631F931A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. vs. U.N. Court: Two Worldviews</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. vs. U.N. Court: Two Worldviews</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of looming showdown between US and other members of UN Security Council, notably Western European nations, over American refusal to join new International Criminal Court; at heart of divergence is fundamentally different visions of global organizations; Europeans, accustomed by their history to think in terms of multilateral arrangements, have always placed greater premium on international organizations, which have always been viewed with suspicion in US; emergence of US as sole military, economic and cultural superpower has only deepened resistance, especially among American conservatives, to any potential international restraints on American powers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The showdown between the United States and other members of the United Nations Security Council was the latest and strongest confirmation that the international solidarity forged after the terror attacks on Sept. 11 was probably superficial and temporary.</p>
        <p>The immediate issue at the United Nations was Washington's demand that American troops and all other United Nations peacekeeping forces be exempted from the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court, which came into existence today under the shadow of intense hostility from the Bush administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The emergence of the U.S. as the sole superpower has only deepened its resistance to international organizations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The showdown between the United States and other members of the United Nations Security Council was the latest and strongest confirmation that the international solidarity forged after the terror attacks on Sept. 11 was probably superficial and temporary.</p>
        <p>The immediate issue at the United Nations was Washington's demand that American troops and all other United Nations peacekeeping forces be exempted from the jurisdiction of the International Criminal Court, which came into existence today under the shadow of intense hostility from the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Unless either the United States or other Council members back down before midnight Wednesday, the United Nations police-training mission in Bosnia will be abruptly terminated. If the standoff continues, all other United Nations peacekeeping operations will be jeopardized as they come up for renewal, starting with the mission in Lebanon later this month.</p>
        <p>The immediate impact in Bosnia was likely to be largely organizational. Only 46 Americans serve in the police-training mission, and the entire operation was to be turned over to the European Union in six months.</p>
        <p>But the very notion of Americans threatening to pull forces out of Europe in a dispute, even if symbolic, carried troubling connotations on a Continent where the American presence had represented a shared commitment for decades.</p>
        <p>Even if all parties involved heed a call from Secretary General Kofi Annan and find a solution for the peacekeeping missions, the very fact that the United States cast a defiant veto in the teeth of its closest allies -- and that Britain and France were prepared to do likewise against Washington -- spoke of sharp differences and a growing mutual irritation.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the divergence was a fundamentally different vision of global organizations. The Europeans, accustomed by their history and geography to think in terms of multilateral arrangements, have always placed a greater premium on international organizations. To them, the end of the cold war brought an era for building international institutions and a global justice system, of which the European Union was the shining example.</p>
        <p>In the United States, international organizations like the United Nations have always been viewed with suspicion, much of it affirmed by the anti-American and anti-Israeli votes of the cold war. The emergence of the United States as the sole military, economic and cultural superpower has only deepened the resistance, especially among American conservatives, to any potential international restraints on American powers.</p>
        <p>''An 800-pound gorilla just doesn't like anything to restrict its freedom of action, unless it thinks it can control it completely,'' said Stephen M. Walt, professor of international affairs at the Kennedy School at Harvard.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, Professor Walt said, there was a sincere fear among many American officials that Americans engaged in military or other operations overseas could become subject to politicized prosecution. ''The fairly extensive role the U.S. military has taken around the world makes it leery of being tried by a tribunal whose standards we can't control,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For the Europeans, however, the American stand amounts to a double standard: one set of rules for the United States, another for the rest of the world. Several stands taken by the United States since the end of the cold war -- against the Kyoto Protocols on greenhouse gases, against biological weapons testing, against a ban on land mines -- have especially irritated the Europeans.</p>
        <p>''There you see the beginning of a real problem,'' said a senior European diplomat at the United Nations. ''If the U.S. says we are from a different nature, we cannot be compared with others, discipline is good for others, but not for the United States, then the future of humanity is at stake. If the United States believes it doesn't need to respect multilateralism and international rules, how do you get China to respect them?''</p>
        <p>The tensions were already there long before Sept. 11. But in the immediate aftermath of the terror attacks, most of the world lined up in solidarity behind the United States, and the Security Council passed resolutions requiring all United Nations members to act against terrorism.</p>
        <p>Many members hoped that the United States would become more active in multilateral organizations out of a recognition that terrorism was a universal problem requiring international effort. That sense began to erode when the United States made clear that it intended to prosecute the war on its own terms.</p>
        <p>In the vote on the Bosnia mission, the conflicting perceptions came to a head. The Europeans saw the Americans as trying to undermine a prime example of the new world order, the International Criminal Court, which was created to take action if local authorities failed to prosecute especially heinous war crimes, human rights violations or genocide.</p>
        <p>The United States saw a confirmation of a world deaf to America's genuine needs and concerns.</p>
        <p>The contest began in May, when the Bush administration formally gave notice that it would not abide by President Clinton's signature on the Rome treaty creating the court. That month, The United States demanded that a resolution extending the United Nations force in East Timor include immunity from international prosecution. The Security Council refused, and Washington gave way.</p>
        <p>This time, when the Bosnia resolution came up, no one blinked.</p>
        <p>For the Europeans, the issue is the sense that the Bush administration was actively trying to curtail a court that they regarded as a major achievement in the struggle for global justice and human rights, issues on which the United States regarded itself as the global standard.</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
