<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Called Close to Deal To Import Natural Gas</title>
    <meta content="22GAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/22/business/worldbusiness/22GAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1394273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Australia-International Relations-China</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Qatar</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cnooc Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howard, John (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Qatar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Qatar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hong Kong</location>
        <org class="online_producer">CNOOC</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6DC1338F931A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Called Close to Deal To Import Natural Gas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">China Called Close to Deal to Import Natural Gas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chinese government is close to concluding its first big contract to import liquefied natural gas, in deal worth at least $9 billion that will not only help turn Chinese energy industry into global player but will also have strategic and commercial implications for all of East Asia; three big consortiums, each including one of giant international energy companies, have emerged as finalists, offering to ship natural gas from Indonesia, Australia or Qatar; China is demanding that its offshore drilling and production company CNOOC Ltd be granted equity stake in whatever gas field becomes winning supplier for current contract; CNOOC Ltd is 70.6 percent owned by Chinese government; remaining 29.4 percent of its stock trades publicly in New York and Hong Kong; bidding has attracted particular public attention in Australia, where Prime Min John Howard is trying to build closer political, strategic and commercial ties with China (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chinese government is close to concluding its first big contract to import liquefied natural gas, in a deal worth at least $9 billion that will not only help turn the Chinese energy industry into a global player but will also have strategic and commercial implications for all of East Asia.</p>
        <p>Three big consortiums, each including one of the giant international energy companies, have emerged as finalists, offering to ship natural gas from Indonesia, Australia or the Persian Gulf nation of Qatar. The winner may gain a long-term advantage in what is expected to be one of the world's largest markets for natural gas, several people involved in the negotiations said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chinese government is close to concluding its first big contract to import liquefied natural gas, in a deal worth at least $9 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chinese government is close to concluding its first big contract to import liquefied natural gas, in a deal worth at least $9 billion that will not only help turn the Chinese energy industry into a global player but will also have strategic and commercial implications for all of East Asia.</p>
        <p>Three big consortiums, each including one of the giant international energy companies, have emerged as finalists, offering to ship natural gas from Indonesia, Australia or the Persian Gulf nation of Qatar. The winner may gain a long-term advantage in what is expected to be one of the world's largest markets for natural gas, several people involved in the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials have said a final decision could come this month. But as it has sometimes done in the past, China may instead winnow the three finalists to two this month and then conduct another round of bidding, in the hope of extracting even better terms.</p>
        <p>The winning consortium and country will be locked in a large-scale commercial embrace with China for a long time. The initial contract being let by the Chinese is for roughly $450 million worth of liquefied natural gas to be delivered each year to Shenzhen, a city adjacent to Hong Kong, for 20 to 25 years.</p>
        <p>At 3.2 million tons a year, the contract would account for nearly 3 percent of all internationally traded liquefied natural gas. China is trying to wean itself off high-pollution coal in favor of cleaner-burning gas, and its officials have said they may pursue two more contracts for another four million tons a year.</p>
        <p>China is demanding that its offshore drilling and production company, CNOOC Ltd., be granted an equity stake in whatever gas field becomes the winning supplier for the current contract. Together with the recent purchase of Indonesian oil fields for $591 million from Repsol-YPF of Spain, the natural gas deal is part of the Chinese company's transformation into a truly international energy company with broad ambitions across Asia.</p>
        <p>CNOOC Ltd. is 70.6 percent owned by the Chinese government; the remaining 29.4 percent of its stock trades publicly in New York and Hong Kong. Merrill Lynch is advising the company on this gas deal.</p>
        <p>While the United States has been active in trying to influence where Central Asian oil pipelines are built, hoping to route them through friendly countries and away from Iran, Washington has been silent on the bidding for the Chinese gas project. All three finalist nations are American allies.</p>
        <p>The bidding has attracted particular public attention in Australia, where Prime Minister John Howard is trying to build closer political, strategic and commercial ties with China. Mr. Howard flew to Beijing today, and will personally present to Chinese leaders on Wednesday his case for why China should choose a group of companies, including Royal Dutch/Shell and BHP Billiton, that are now extracting gas from Australia's North West Shelf.</p>
        <p>''I take the view that it's my responsibility, my job, to give it the best shot I can and to argue very strongly,'' Mr. Howard told reporters during a stopover in Singapore today on his way to Beijing.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Howard noted that Australia faced a ''very difficult'' challenge to win the contract. Liquefied natural gas is fairly expensive to transport overseas, because it must be kept very cold and under extreme pressure in special ships. The closest gas field being offered to the Chinese government is in Indonesia; the Australian field is next, and Qatar, which is in a partnership with Exxon Mobil, is the farthest away.</p>
        <p>BP and the Indonesian government are offering China gas from a new offshore field, mostly owned by BP, in a bay off Irian Jaya, the Indonesian half of the island of New Guinea. Oil companies traditionally have offered slightly lower prices to sign up the first customer for a new gas field, because of the risk of problems and delays.</p>
        <p>In addition to being closest to China, BP's bid may have an advantage because the company is already in a consortium with CNOOC to build the terminal in the Shenzhen area that will receive and distribute the gas. Its disadvantage is Indonesia's record of political instability: Exxon Mobil has had trouble keeping open its liquefied natural gas operation on Sumatra, at the western end of Indonesia, because of fighting with a separatist movement there, and Irian Jaya, at the eastern end of Indonesia, also has a separatist movement.</p>
        <p>Analysts say it is hard to predict how the Chinese government will balance the many issues involved in the gas contract decision. ''The important things from a Chinese perspective are the pricing and security of supply, the potential for expansion of the contract at competitive prices and the ability to participate in the equity of the project,'' said Tom Hilboldt, the director of Asian oil and gas research at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>The contract is meant to address a conundrum facing Chinese economic planners: How to supply enormous quantities of energy for the vast network of factories that has sprung up in Guangdong Province, up the Pearl River from Hong Kong. The province has virtually no oil, gas or coal deposits of its own; it now buys huge amounts of coal from the rest of China and oil from abroad, playing a big role in China's $10 billion annual bill for oil imports. China is building a gas pipeline across the width of the country from near its western border to Shanghai, but it will not carry enough gas to supply southern China's expected needs as well.</p>
        <p>Coal burning has badly fouled the air in Guangdong and Hong Kong, to official embarrassment. At the same time, railroads and other resources are tied up with the increasingly difficult job of moving mountains of coal to Guangdong. ''The transportation and storage capacity for coal compete with industrial capacity that could be used to bring in foreign currency,'' said Mark Qiu, CNOOC's chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have applauded China for trying to switch to natural gas, which contributes much less to global warming than the burning of coal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
