<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Anti-Candidate, Out to Anger the Rich</title>
    <meta content="28PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/28/nyregion/28PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1404090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Stanley Aronowitz</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aronowitz, Stanley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Green Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Aronowitz, Stanley</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DC133EF93BA15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Anti-Candidate, Out to Anger the Rich</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Anti-Candidate, Out to Anger the Rich</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hedges, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Stanley Aronowitz, Green Party's nominee for governor of New York, who is calling for higher taxes to increase money for schools, pay for campaign finance reform and establish state-subsidized health insurance; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY election year, it seems, a candidate emerges and, citing the erosion of our political system, the vapid sound bites, the fleeing from real debate, the fusion of entertainment and political campaigning, declares that it is not worth playing by the rules.</p>
        <p>Enter Stanley Aronowitz, 69, the Green Party's nominee this year for governor of New York, who, when you listen to him call for higher taxes to increase money for schools, pay for campaign finance reform and establish state-subsidized health insurance, is the anti-candidate this time around. He has set out to anger the powerful and the rich who, he says, pull the strings of the ''Cheney-Rumsfeld-Bush regime,'' stressing that the troika is listed in order of importance. And, like all of those who believe in a cause, he is willing to go down with the ship rather than compromise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stanley Aronowitz is the Green Party's nominee for governor of New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY election year, it seems, a candidate emerges and, citing the erosion of our political system, the vapid sound bites, the fleeing from real debate, the fusion of entertainment and political campaigning, declares that it is not worth playing by the rules.</p>
        <p>Enter Stanley Aronowitz, 69, the Green Party's nominee this year for governor of New York, who, when you listen to him call for higher taxes to increase money for schools, pay for campaign finance reform and establish state-subsidized health insurance, is the anti-candidate this time around. He has set out to anger the powerful and the rich who, he says, pull the strings of the ''Cheney-Rumsfeld-Bush regime,'' stressing that the troika is listed in order of importance. And, like all of those who believe in a cause, he is willing to go down with the ship rather than compromise.</p>
        <p>''My job is to start a public conversation, to show voters they have a choice and to get enough of a vote so we can stay on the ballot and speak out,'' he said. ''I am an intellectual. My work as a teacher and a writer is to elaborate on views and talk about them in detail.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronowitz drives himself to campaign gatherings around the state in his 1995 Volvo. He sleeps in the homes of supporters and keeps within his allotted daily campaign travel budget of $50 a day. Andrew M. Cuomo, a Democrat who is running without the support of most of the party establishment, has raised millions so far for his campaign. Mr. Aronowitz, who has never run for public office, has raised $25,000. The Green Party has no budget for television advertising or to hire campaign workers. The whole campaign, he estimates, will cost about $150,000.</p>
        <p>He blasts the money spent by corporations on the two major parties and those candidates, like Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who can use personal fortunes to run for office.</p>
        <p>''In many local communities we cannot get into the conversation because we have no television advertising,'' he said. ''How can parties like ours have a conversation when a $78 million expenditure by a private businessperson buys an election?''</p>
        <p>He began to admire President François Mitterrand of France once he heard him speak in Paris without notes on a range of complex political issues.</p>
        <p>''When you give stump speeches you end up boring yourself and your audience,'' he said. ''I heard Mitterrand and thought that if I ever ran for public office I would like to do it like that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronowitz wants to be the little red light blinking on citizens' dashboards to tell them the system needs repair. And if, he said, ''a few more thousand people'' get the message he will have considered the time and energy worth it.</p>
        <p>''OUR democracy is in trouble,'' he said. ''The Democratic and Republican Parties have converged. Their economic policies are not different. They believe that anything that hurts business is not a viable position.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronowitz, who teaches sociology at the City University of New York, is not, however, a man who stepped out of the cloistered garden of academia. He has always been a rebel. He was thrown out of Brooklyn College as a freshman in 1951 for leading a campus demonstration after the administration banned a radical newspaper. He was married at 19 and had two children by the time he was 23. He is on his third marriage; his wife is the writer and N.Y.U. journalism professor Ellen Willis. He has five children. He and Professor Willis live in Washington Square Village.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aronowitz worked for a decade as a steelworker in Harrison, N.J., and for seven years as an organizer for the Amalgamated Clothing Workers. Fifteen years after leaving college he went to the New School for Social Research and got a B.A. in sociology, and later got a doctorate in sociology from Union Graduate School.</p>
        <p>Ideas spill out of his head -- he speaks in long machine-gun bursts -- with a Brooklyn twang. He has always had a voracious appetite for books and relishes discussing Hannah Arendt or Herbert Marcuse as much as he does global warming. When he ended his night shift in the steel mill, he ate breakfast and went to the company library for an hour or two before going home. He started a reading group with other workers -- they read mostly novels -- and would get home at noon and sleep until his shift began again.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons I chose the steel mill, rather than an automobile factory where I could have made more money, was because when you work near furnaces you work 40 minutes on and 20 minutes off,'' he said. ''I spent part of the 20 minutes politicking, because I was a union activist. But many times I would go into the bathroom and read. At that period in my life I read American history.''</p>
        <p>''I learned as a labor organizer how to translate substantive, often difficult ideas, into the vernacular,'' he said. ''I learned to talk plain but to talk real issues.''</p>
        <p>''The Brothers Karamazov'' by Fyodor Dostoyevsky, he said, is one of his favorite pieces of fiction, along with the novels of William Faulkner. But these works, he said, were not always translatable to the crowd.</p>
        <p>''Dostoyevsky taught me about irony,'' he said. ''I have great trouble with this as a would-be politician. You cannot be a successful politician and be ironic. Our slogan -- tax and spend -- is meant to be ironic, but people don't get it. They get upset.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
