<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missionary Among the Executives</title>
    <meta content="21PROF$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/21/business/yourmoney/21PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1409988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Private Sector"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Sister Patricia Daly</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dominican Order</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cortese, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daly, Sister Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Enron Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">WorldCom Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Adelphia Communications Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Daly, Patricia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0D81E39F932A15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missionary Among the Executives</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Missionary Among the Executives</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY CORTESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cortese, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Sister Patricia Daly, Dominican nun and member of Interfaith Center for Corporate Responsibility, on her efforts to make corporations more responsible financially for damage to the environment and climate changes from global warming; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE politicians and even chief executives make righteous speeches and advocate tougher penalties for corporate misdeeds, Sister Patricia Daly is smiling. For three decades, she has been quietly forcing changes her own way. Or perhaps not so quietly.</p>
        <p>Sister Daly, 45, a Dominican nun and member of the Interfaith Center for Corporate Responsibility, leads its efforts to make corporations more liable financially for damage to the environment and climate changes from global warming. Operating frequently from the group's headquarters on the Upper West Side in Manhattan, in a square building known as ''the God Box,'' Sister Daly spends her days meeting with corporate executives, drafting shareholder resolutions and trying to put pressure on large corporations like Exxon Mobil and General Electric.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Public anger over scandals have been like manna from heaven for what Sister Patricia Daly considers the broader cause of making corporations better citizens through shareholder activism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE politicians and even chief executives make righteous speeches and advocate tougher penalties for corporate misdeeds, Sister Patricia Daly is smiling. For three decades, she has been quietly forcing changes her own way. Or perhaps not so quietly.</p>
        <p>Sister Daly, 45, a Dominican nun and member of the Interfaith Center for Corporate Responsibility, leads its efforts to make corporations more liable financially for damage to the environment and climate changes from global warming. Operating frequently from the group's headquarters on the Upper West Side in Manhattan, in a square building known as ''the God Box,'' Sister Daly spends her days meeting with corporate executives, drafting shareholder resolutions and trying to put pressure on large corporations like Exxon Mobil and General Electric.</p>
        <p>To Sister Daly, her activism is more than socially responsible investing or missionary work. ''Being a faithful member of a religious tradition doesn't always mean just showing up for services on a Saturday or Sunday,'' she said. ''It means being engaged.''</p>
        <p>Shareholder anger over scandals at Enron, Global Crossing, WorldCom, Adelphia Communications and the like have, in an odd way, been like manna from heaven for what she considers the broader cause of making corporations better citizens through shareholder activism. Not only were a record 721 shareholder resolutions filed this year, of which the Interfaith Center sponsored 144, but shareholders voted for them in record numbers. Sister Daly said she was particularly excited about gains made by resolutions that ask companies to report on their greenhouse gas emissions and what they are doing to curb them.</p>
        <p>An unprecedented 20 resolutions addressed climate change this year. More than 28 percent of shareholders at Eastman Chemical and 27 percent at American Standard supported them. At Exxon Mobil, 20 percent of shareholders voted in favor of two resolutions, one asking the company to reduce emissions and other to disclose the cost of delays in toxic chemical cleanups.; Sister Daly considered that a major victory. ''It's a real warning to them,'' she said. Although the resolutions did not pass, they will automatically remain on the annual-meeting agenda.</p>
        <p>Sister Daly's influence comes from the Interfaith Center's $110 billion in combined assets, mainly the pension funds of ministers, priests and nuns among its 275 religious organization members. The assets include substantial holdings in many large corporations.</p>
        <p>In the boom years, ''the treasury of my parish was certainly happy to see 25 percent returns,'' she said. But her attitude is that, as shareholders, ''we're part of the problem here.''</p>
        <p>Sister Daly views her work as following in the tradition of the Dominican order, founded in the 13th century by St. Dominic to fight heresies and untruths. ''We're dealing with some of the heresies and untruths of capitalism,'' Sister Daly said.</p>
        <p>But some critics say she has been too quick to accept environmentalist positions. ''I respect what the sister is doing because that is what she believes,'' said Frank Maisano, an energy consultant and former spokesman for the Global Climate Coalition, an energy industry group that disbanded after having successfully lobbied against Senate ratification of the Kyoto Protocol on greenhouse emissions. ''But I think she is somewhat misled at times by colleagues in the environmental community because they are somewhat less than honest about what industry is doing.''</p>
        <p>Others give grudging praise. ''Although we disagree with Sister Pat on her issues, she appears to be a dedicated activist and I'm sure we will have further discussions on Exxon Mobil's position,'' said Patrick Mulva, Exxon Mobil's vice president for investor relations.</p>
        <p>Sister Daly is known for tangling with chief executives at shareholder meetings. In an exchange with John F. Welch Jr. of General Electric in 1998, she challenged his resistance to taking responsibility for P.C.B. pollution from G.E. factories in New York's Hudson Valley. Sister Daly compared Mr. Welch's stance on P.C.B.'s -- chemicals also known as polychlorinated biphenyls -- to that of tobacco executives who once swore that cigarette smoke was harmless. Mr. Welch called Sister Daly's contention ''outrageous'' while she continued peppering him with well-informed questions until he abruptly moved on to the next agenda item -- a rare retreat for America's best-known corporate chief. Mr. Welch's office said he was on vacation and not available to comment.</p>
        <p>''C.E.O.'s sometimes have a difficult time dealing with Pat,'' said Seamus Finn, a colleague at the Interfaith Center.</p>
        <p>No chief executive is spared, even President Bush. Sister Daly described his recent speech criticizing Wall Street miscreants as ''without substance.''</p>
        <p>Timothy Smith, senior vice president and director for social responsibility at Walden Asset Management, a money management firm, said Sister Daly had an unusual ability to win allies from unlikely corners.</p>
        <p>''It takes a certain amount of skill to speak the language of different constituencies from Greenpeace to the State of New York to corporate boardrooms,'' Mr. Smith said. For example, Sister Daly met Bianca Jagger on the eve of a BP shareholder meeting in London and piqued her interest in organizing a boycott of Esso, a European subsidiary of Exxon Mobil, because of the company's position on global warming. Ms. Jagger then worked with Greenpeace on the Stop Esso campaign in Europe.</p>
        <p>Sister Daly grew up in Brooklyn and Queens and moved to Connecticut in her teens. She became a corporate activist in the 70's as a new member of the Sisters of Saint Dominic of Caldwell, N.J., campaigning against corporate labor practices and apartheid. ''When I entered, I knew nothing about being involved with corporations,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith of Walden recalled a shareholder meeting in the 1970's for J. P. Stevens, a textile company accused by organized labor of antiunion behavior. ''Pat was a novice. She appeared in full nun garb.''</p>
        <p>Private Sector</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
