<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="01FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1396878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DE153AF932A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Bush Administration Urges Americans to Leave India  The United States warned that ''tensions have risen to serious levels'' between India and Pakistan, urging the 60,000 Americans now in India to leave immediately and authorizing nonessential diplomats and all dependents to depart. Officials cautioned that while they gauge the chance of war as substantial, they do not see it as inescapable.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Asian Allies Cautioned  Deputy Defense Secretary Paul D. Wolfowitz, in Singapore for a three-day regional security conference, warned America's allies in Asia to keep their guard up against terrorism within their borders, cautioning that even nations with large Muslim populations are targets for attack by Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Bush Administration Urges Americans to Leave India  The United States warned that ''tensions have risen to serious levels'' between India and Pakistan, urging the 60,000 Americans now in India to leave immediately and authorizing nonessential diplomats and all dependents to depart. Officials cautioned that while they gauge the chance of war as substantial, they do not see it as inescapable.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Asian Allies Cautioned  Deputy Defense Secretary Paul D. Wolfowitz, in Singapore for a three-day regional security conference, warned America's allies in Asia to keep their guard up against terrorism within their borders, cautioning that even nations with large Muslim populations are targets for attack by Islamic extremists.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Afghan Allies Fired On  American Special Forces troops mistakenly fired on a group of friendly Afghan soldiers in a firefight in eastern Afghanistan near the Pakistani border, killing three men and wounding two. American military officials said the soldiers had been mistaken for Qaeda fighters.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Israel Raids Nablus  Israeli tanks and troops rounded up about a hundred Palestinians during a raid into Nablus and the neighboring Balata refugee camp, the birthplace and stronghold of Al Aksa Martyrs Brigades.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Mugabe Clamps Down on Media  The authorities in Zimbabwe have recently arrested 11 journalists, ordered state agencies to stop advertising in newspapers that criticize the government and canceled the broadcasting license of the only privately owned television station, moves that some see as a campaign to muzzle Zimbabwe's independent news outlets , which have been sharply critical of President Robert Mugabe.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A Move for Cheaper AIDS Drugs  Zimbabwe, which has one of the world's highest rates of H.I.V. infection, has declared the epidemic a national emergency, a move that under new international trade regulations allows the country to sidestep patents and import generic versions of AIDS drugs.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-12</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Paper Warned Of Flaws in Terror Fight  A top secret report warned top officials of the F.B.I. in the months before Sept. 11 that the bureau faced significant terrorist threats from Middle Eastern groups like Al Qaeda but lacked enough resources to meet the threat, senior government officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Judges Void Library Filter Law  A panel of federal judges struck down a law requiring libraries to filter the Internet for material harmful to minors, saying that the technology blocks so much unobjectionable material that it would violate the First Amendment rights of library patrons. The ruling did not affect the portion of the law requiring schools to install filters.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Apology From an Archbishop  Retired Archbishop Rembert G. Weakland of Milwaukee apologized to Catholics who were distressed to learn that the archdiocese had paid $450,000 to a man who accused the archbishop of sexual assault.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats Scramble in Hawaii  The leading Democratic contender for governor of Hawaii, Mayor Jeremy Harris of Honolulu, withdrew from the race, citing bad publicity that has hurt him in the polls. The decision was a boon for the top Republican candidate, former Mayor Linda Lingle of Maui, and a blow to the Democrats, who have controlled the governorship for 40 years.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Historian Resigns From Board  The historian Doris Kearns Goodwin stepped down from the board that chooses the winners of the Pulitzer Prize. The board had begun an inquiry into accusations that she copied the work of others in her 1987 book, ''The Fitzgeralds and the Kennedys.'' Ms. Goodwin said that she was not able to devote enough time to the board.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>U.S. Backs Maine Drug Law  The Bush administration told the Supreme Court that it should allow Maine to carry out a state law that tries to force drug companies to reduce the prices of prescription medicines sold in the state.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Slow Pace in Applications To Federal Victims' Fund  Fewer than 10 families of those killed in the Sept. 11 terrorism attacks have filed completed applications with the government's Victim Compensation Fund. Relatives cite the emotional difficulties of settling a victim's financial affairs and the complexity of the application. The low figure is heightening concerns that many may file lawsuits against airlines and other entities instead.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Avoiding Order to Filter Water  The Environmental Protection Agency concluded that New York City had managed to maintain the purity of its drinking water through land purchases and other moves that control what pollutants enter its upstate reservoirs. That decision means that the city will not immediately have to build a costly filtration system.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Criticism for Drug Study  An editorial in The British Medical Journal said there were ''serious irregularities'' in Pharmacia's study finding that its best-selling arthritis drug Celebrex caused fewer ulcers than other pain relievers. Pharmacia disputed that assertion.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Nets Get to NBA Finals  The New Jersey Nets defeated the Boston Celtics, 96-88, to make their first appearance in the NBA championship series.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Lakers beat the Sacramento Kings, 106-102, sending the Western Conference finals to Game 7.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>A World Cup Upset  History was turned on its head at the World Cup in South Korea when Senegal defeated France, its former colonial master.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>John B. Keane  An Irish novelist and playwright who recorded the voice of a disappearing generation , he was 73.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>S.E.C. Investigates Analysts  A Securities and Exchange Commission memorandum revealed that the S.E.C. has opened 10 inquiries in the last year into potential conflicts of interest by securities analysts. Five of the inquiries have been upgraded into formal investigations.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The Dow closed up 13.56 points, to 9,925.25, losing 1.8 percent for the week. The S.&amp;P. 500 advanced 2.48 points, to 1,067.14, but fell 1.5 percent for the week.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Challenge in Andersen Trial  The defense in Arthur Andersen's criminal case had its strongest day since the trial began last month, with two witnesses challenging government evidence that members of the firm intended to obstruct a federal inquiry by destroying thousands of documents related to Enron.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>I.B.M. to Build Supercomputer  The government awarded I.B.M. a $224.4 million contract to build a supercomputer whose mission is to improve the accuracy of weather forecasts. The award comes a month after Japan completed development of what is now the world's fastest supercomputer, built to analyze climate change.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Enron's ready access; drugs in baseball; an unexpected censor in Bosnia; one Bush helps another.</p>
        <p>Column: Bill Keller.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B15  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>A16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
