<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Mining, Some Glints, But Little That Glistens</title>
    <meta content="01INSI$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/01/business/yourmoney/01INSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1420229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lehman Brothers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Peter D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Copper, Brass and Bronze</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copper, Brass and Bronze</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDD123FF932A3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Mining, Some Glints, But Little That Glistens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Mining, Some Glints, but Little That Glistens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenneth N Gilpin Market Insight column interviews Lehman Brothers metals and mining analyst Peter D Ward about prospects for investing in industry; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is not a growth industry, but the fortunes of the mining and metals sector offer a window on the health of the global economy.</p>
        <p>For the short term, at least, the outlook does not seem promising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter D. Ward, a metals and mining analyst at Lehman Brothers, spoke last week about the industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is not a growth industry, but the fortunes of the mining and metals sector offer a window on the health of the global economy.</p>
        <p>For the short term, at least, the outlook does not seem promising.</p>
        <p>Prices for commodities like copper and aluminum are soft, and inventories are high. This has not been lost on Wall Street. With the exception of gold stocks, the sector has been in tough times.</p>
        <p>Peter D. Ward, a metals and mining analyst at Lehman Brothers, spoke last week about the industry. Following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did you issue a gloomy assessment on Alcoa last week?</p>
        <p>A. I am not seeing any real signs of huge improvements in the domestic economy through the end of this year, and Alcoa is very much a U.S. company: about two-thirds of their revenues are from here.</p>
        <p>When you look at some of their key end markets -- housing, autos and aerospace, which together represent about 45 percent of the company's revenues -- it is hard to see how things improve next year.</p>
        <p>Our auto analyst is looking for a 4 percent drop in vehicle production in 2003, compared with this year. The fall off in aerospace construction hasn't happened yet, but orders have dropped off a lot. We are looking for a 15 percent to 20 percent decline in airplane construction next year. And it is hard to see how the housing market gets much better.</p>
        <p>In addition, in the last year there have been dramatic global increases in inventories. Prices are already under pressure, and supply growth looks like it will outpace demand for several years.</p>
        <p>Q. The International Trade Commission disallowed some additional tariff protection on cold-rolled steel last week. What effect will that have on the steel industry?</p>
        <p>A. The I.T.C. decision is not that damaging to steel producers. They were already protected.</p>
        <p>We have been pretty skeptical of the steel story for some time and felt the last thing the industry needed was more protection. The world has about one billion tons of steelmaking capacity, and we really only need about 850 million tons. But governments around the world, including and especially the United States, continue to protect the high-cost producers. As long as that continues, this oversupply situation will continue.</p>
        <p>That said, the tariffs put into place this year have without question improved domestic pricing this year, and next year you will see higher contract realizations. But these tariffs are temporary, and profitability gained through short-term tariffs warrants a very low equity multiple.</p>
        <p>Q. What is your view on copper mining companies?</p>
        <p>A. The outlook for copper is actually pretty good. It is one of the few commodities where prices will stop falling and start rising, because the easy, near-surface deposits have already been depleted.</p>
        <p>Right now, copper prices are a little bit below 70 cents a pound. At that level, about 5 percent of the world's supply is cash negative, which means companies are spending more to mine it than to sell it. Even if the economy doesn't rebound, eventually you will see more production curtailments.</p>
        <p>Q. Are there copper stocks you like?</p>
        <p>A. The purest play out there is Phelps Dodge, but we are not positive on the stock because the future price of the metal is already reflected in the company's stock price. And we are also concerned about projected cost reductions, which we don't think can be realized.</p>
        <p>The copper plays we do recommend are Freeport-McMoRan Copper and Gold Inc. and Rio Tinto Zinc, which trades as an A.D.R. in this country.</p>
        <p>Freeport-McMoRan is the lowest-cost producer of copper in the world. They are the lowest because they have a huge copper and gold deposit in Indonesia. That is the problem with the stock, even though it is the greatest mining asset in the world. But investing in mining shares involves political risk. You could argue that Arizona and New Mexico have big political risks, too, because those are not easy places to operate a mine.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the prospects for coal?</p>
        <p>A. As recently as 1998, when the Kyoto Protocol was signed, I was not thrilled about coal.</p>
        <p>We don't disagree with the findings about global warming, but coal is a critical part of the energy equation in this country: over half the electricity generated in the U.S. is coal-fired power generation. It is the cheapest delivered fossil fuel.</p>
        <p>We think stocks like Arch Coal are trading at very attractive valuations. Arch is trading at less than four times our 2003 estimate of earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization. For a quality company with decades of reserves, much of which has a low sulfur content, that is a very attractive valuation.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
