<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Seek New Messenger And a Message</title>
    <meta content="17DEMS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/17/politics/17DEMS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1441494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, Howard (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Howard Dean</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED71330F934A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Seek New Messenger And a Message</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democrats Seek New Messenger and a Message</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic leaders say their party is bereft of obvious new leaders and threatened by divisive ideological battles as it struggles to determine how to deal with new Republican dominance in Washington; say election losses have left them without a platform or standard-bearer to counter powerful voice of White House; many Democratic leaders are less troubled, noting closeness of loss and narrow margin in what is about to become Republican-controlled Senate; absence of major figures atop Democratic ladder leads to flurry of activity of some lesser-known presidential contenders, including Sen John Edwards of North Carolina and Gov Howard Dean of Vermont, who see opportunity in this turmoil; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democratic leaders, in a stark assessment of the coming two years, say their party is bereft of obvious new leaders and threatened by divisive ideological battles as it struggles to determine how to deal with the new Republican dominance in Washington.</p>
        <p>In interviews, Democrats around the country said their losses had left them without a platform or standard-bearer to counter the powerful voice of the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The absence of major figures atop the Democratic ladder has contributed to a flurry of activity by some lesser-known presidential contenders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Democratic leaders, in a stark assessment of the coming two years, say their party is bereft of obvious new leaders and threatened by divisive ideological battles as it struggles to determine how to deal with the new Republican dominance in Washington.</p>
        <p>In interviews, Democrats around the country said their losses had left them without a platform or standard-bearer to counter the powerful voice of the White House.</p>
        <p>The presidential contenders who might fill that void include, thus far, only familiar faces from the past and lesser-known Democrats who have yet to capture the eye of party leaders the way Bill Clinton did a decade ago.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the White House, we don't have nothing,'' said Donna Brazile, the manager of Al Gore's 2000 presidential campaign. ''We have to get out there fighting like we've got something.''</p>
        <p>Art Torres, the California Democratic chairman, said: ''The question is, how do we get through this maze, and that gets down to the messenger and the message. Clinton was a master at that. But we don't have Bill Clinton running for office anymore.''</p>
        <p>In the Senate, 20 Democrats who are distressed about the election met privately on Wednesday to form a group that Senator Richard J. Durbin of Illinois said would push the party to be more assertive on traditionally Democratic issues, starting with the objection of many Democrats to President Bush's tax cut. That move, combined with the unhappiness across the party's left about how the Democrats fought this losing campaign, could foreshadow an ideological battle with moderates, who have largely controlled the party since Mr. Clinton's election in 1992.</p>
        <p>In the interviews, Democrats stopped short when asked to name whom they viewed as the faces of their party. ''There are several,'' said Bob Poe, the Democratic chairman in Florida, after pausing a full five seconds. ''I don't mean that to be a nonanswer. I don't think anyone has yet to emerge. But it's coming.''</p>
        <p>The problem is pronounced in Washington. The party's most prominent leaders -- Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader, and Tom Daschle, the Senate majority leader (soon to be minority leader) -- have been at least partly politically discredited by the losses on their watch, as has the Democratic chairman, Terry McAuliffe.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Clinton remains hugely popular among some Democrats, party leaders could not help noting that his presence on the campaign trail did little for some candidates. And Mr. Gore, who begins a high-profile tour this weekend to promote a book, remains, fairly or not, a symbol in many quarters of Democratic defeat and the past.</p>
        <p>The only relatively fresh face in the party leadership is Representative Nancy Pelosi, 62, who was elected to replace Mr. Gephardt as minority leader after he decided to step down. She entered the House in 1987, but is barely known outside her hometown, San Francisco, and Republicans have already tried to present her as ideologically out of step with most of the nation.</p>
        <p>The absence of major figures atop the Democratic ladder has led to a flurry of activity by some lesser-known presidential contenders who see opportunity in this turmoil.</p>
        <p>Two of them -- Senator John Edwards of North Carolina and Gov. Howard Dean of Vermont -- delivered what their advisers billed as ''major speeches'' this week that were critical of the Democratic orthodoxy and intended to present themselves as a new generation of leaders. Mr. Edwards plans a second such speech next week.</p>
        <p>''It's not enough to critique Bush,'' Mr. Edwards said. ''We have to lay out a clear vision and substantial ideas about where we want to go.''</p>
        <p>Another likely Democratic presidential contender, Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, said: ''It is up to us to approach the country with new energy and some new ideas. The most important is just to be absolutely clear to the country about the choices that the party is fighting for. I don't think it was clear enough this year.''</p>
        <p>Many Democratic leaders, noting the closeness of the loss and the narrow margin in what is about to become a Republican-controlled Senate, argued that the party's defeat was more cyclical than cataclysmic.</p>
        <p>''The reports of our demise and disarray are greatly exaggerated,'' said Representative Nita M. Lowey of New York, who leads the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''I don't know that we need to change what we stand for.''</p>
        <p>Several Democrats, including some candidates for president, argued that this would begin to change once the presidential competition engages, which could force the party to find its philosophical bearings and showcase a new line of leaders.</p>
        <p>''I hope that voice comes as we move into a campaign for the presidency,'' said Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr., Democrat of Delaware, who said he was considering running for president as well. ''But I don't see it emerging from Nancy Pelosi or Tom Daschle -- it's almost impossible for them to be able to do that.''</p>
        <p>This is hardly the first time either party has struggled to recover from an election.</p>
        <p>But except for a single six-month period at the start of Mr. Bush's administration, this is the first time since 1954 that the Democrats have been shut out of Congress and the White House. Democrats in and out of Washington expressed concern that Democrats lacked not only a platform, but also a clear idea of what they would say if they had one.</p>
        <p>Gov. Gray Davis of California, who had been discredited by party leaders when he appeared on the verge of losing re-election to a little-known Republican in an overwhelmingly Democratic state, chortled as he pointed to his eventual victory to suggest what his colleagues in Washington might have done differently.</p>
        <p>''Unlike Washington, the Democratic Party stands for something in California,'' Mr. Davis said. ''We've led America in a host of areas, including the first state to combat global warming, the first state to permit paid family leave. If you're in Congress, it's hard to go back to your constituents and say, 'Look what the Democrats have done.' You could do that in California.''</p>
        <p>Some Democrats outside Washington said they were most disturbed that a dwindling public interest in politics had filtered into their own increasingly depleted ranks. They said they were having difficulty recruiting talented young people to run -- or even to help at headquarters.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of people who I wish would run for office, but they choose not to,'' said Judy Olson, the Democratic leader in South Dakota. ''I don't know if it's really cool to be a politician these days.''</p>
        <p>''I had dinner last night with George McGovern,'' Ms. Olson said, referring to the 1972 presidential nominee, who is from South Dakota, ''and we were talking about that very thing: Who are our leaders?''</p>
        <p>In Minnesota, where Democratic leaders pressed Walter F. Mondale, the former vice president, to run after Senator Paul Wellstone died in a plane crash, Democratic leaders are engaged in their own reassessment after an embarrassing loss.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the farm team that we had 10 or 20 years ago,'' said Mike Erlandson, the chairman of the Minnesota Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party. ''Republicans have the farm team now.'' Mr. Erlandson added, ''It's true of both sides, but the leadership is getting older and voters are getting younger.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Democrats said no obvious stars had emerged in the one successful part of their election night: the election of new governors. Still, Democrats expressed hope that some of the new governors might prove to be the seeds of the farm team they were missing.</p>
        <p>Among those are Janet Napolitano of Arizona, Kathleen Sebelius of Kansas and Jennifer Granholm of Michigan. (The political future of Ms. Granholm, whom some Democrats described as one of their most impressive new faces, is limited: She was born in Canada, and thus is ineligible to be president.)</p>
        <p>The choice of Ms. Pelosi to replace Mr. Gephardt has stirred concern among the Democrats who helped steer the party to the center in the 1980's, and could fuel the ideological battle that seems to be brewing. After the party lost three presidential elections in a row, those Democrats argued for moderating views on social and national security issues to be competitive with Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's victory was seen as a validation of that view. Democrats who helped move the party then are worried that this election will encourage the left to try to pull it back.</p>
        <p>''The left in the party and the interest groups in the party always want to push the party toward their direction,'' said Al From, the executive director of the moderate Democratic Leadership Council, the organization that helped elect Mr. Clinton. ''But to me, it's not rocket science. If we want to expand our base, expand our ability to win elections, we're going to have to continue to move forward to where the voters are.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Brazile said she remained hopeful that the party would recover.</p>
        <p>''Look, I survived the 80's,'' she said. ''We felt defeated in 1984, and we felt defeated in 1988. I've lived long enough to see the Democratic Party at the top of the game, and I've seen it lose and lose big. What happened last week was a wake-up call.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
