<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Jersey Ethicist</title>
    <meta content="21KELL$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/21/opinion/21KELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1425375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Keller, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bill Keller</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6D81F30F932A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Jersey Ethicist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The New Jersey Ethicist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Keller, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Keller humorous Op-Ed column on ethical travails besetting Sen Robert Torricelli's Democratic Senatorial campaign in New Jersey (L)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the senior senator representing a large Northeastern state, I am often offered little presents from constituents -- a TV, a couple of Italian suits, a grandfather clock, a little jewelry for the girlfriend. What can I say? People just feel a special gratitude. Not long ago one constituent flipped out and started blabbing to the feds and the press. Now I'm up for re-election, and my opponent can't talk about anything else except my so-called ethics.</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>First, let's look on the bright side. The fact that you're running for re-election means you're probably not in a federal slammer. I'm guessing you got the equivalent of a manicure from the Ethics Committee. And your voters are Democrats, am I right? Jeez, they forgave the Clintons. So you're sitting pretty if you can ride it out a few more weeks. Now, a guy like you, I'm assuming you've still got a lot of friends. Take their money, buy a zillion hours of TV time, and change the subject. You could change the subject to corporate sleaze, but that's a little close to home, or you could change the subject to foreign policy but, c'mon, who cares? No, my recommendation is, change the subject to what a scary guy your opponent is. Never mind if he's a harmless, pro-choice moderate. Say he'll bring back coat-hanger abortions! He'll poison your water! He'll run an S.U.V. over your grandmother! Find some sweet-looking housewife who's willing to say she's proud of you. (I don't care what the polls say. There must be one somewhere.) Oh, and put some flags in. As for the press, my advice to you: stonewall, Jackson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An expert on ethics answers questions from two state senators, a former governor and an aging rock 'n' roll singer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the senior senator representing a large Northeastern state, I am often offered little presents from constituents -- a TV, a couple of Italian suits, a grandfather clock, a little jewelry for the girlfriend. What can I say? People just feel a special gratitude. Not long ago one constituent flipped out and started blabbing to the feds and the press. Now I'm up for re-election, and my opponent can't talk about anything else except my so-called ethics.</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>First, let's look on the bright side. The fact that you're running for re-election means you're probably not in a federal slammer. I'm guessing you got the equivalent of a manicure from the Ethics Committee. And your voters are Democrats, am I right? Jeez, they forgave the Clintons. So you're sitting pretty if you can ride it out a few more weeks. Now, a guy like you, I'm assuming you've still got a lot of friends. Take their money, buy a zillion hours of TV time, and change the subject. You could change the subject to corporate sleaze, but that's a little close to home, or you could change the subject to foreign policy but, c'mon, who cares? No, my recommendation is, change the subject to what a scary guy your opponent is. Never mind if he's a harmless, pro-choice moderate. Say he'll bring back coat-hanger abortions! He'll poison your water! He'll run an S.U.V. over your grandmother! Find some sweet-looking housewife who's willing to say she's proud of you. (I don't care what the polls say. There must be one somewhere.) Oh, and put some flags in. As for the press, my advice to you: stonewall, Jackson.</p>
        <p>I'm the other senator from that large Northeastern state. I got elected on a platform of being beholden to no one, mainly because I'm richer than God and I don't have to act like a small-time graft artist. In other words, I got elected for not being that guy. Now my staff says I should stay clear of the senior senator so the slime doesn't rub off, and anyway he only likes me for my money. But the truth is, the man pulled all sorts of wires to get me nominated, so I owe him big time. On top of which, we're looking at 51-to-49 here in the Senate, which means if Senator I-Left-My-Wallet-in-My-Other-Pants gets beat in November, the other team might actually control the place. I didn't spend $63 million of my own money to sit in the cheap seats. Should I campaign for the guy?</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Let me tell you what it's all about. Family. It's all about family. Next time around, are you going to spend another 63 extra-large of your own money to keep your nice job? No, you're going to trust the family to provide. Are you going to turn to the Republicans when you want your helping of pork for the folks back home? Of course not. The family will take care of it. You trust only blood. Well, blood and hard money.</p>
        <p>When I was the governor of a large Northeastern state, I had a reputation as someone who cared about nice open green spaces. Now I run a big agency in Washington that's supposed to protect the environment, but the people I work for want to make my state the capital of toxic waste and acid rain. Am I being used?</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Of course you are, Lady Marmalade. The real question is, are you being compensated? How's the song go? ''Hey sister, soul sister, better get that dough, sister.'' I'm guessing you're in the very low six figures, and you're not getting any younger. Give it six months more, and then go to work as a lobbyist for a nice pesticide company. It's the same job, but it pays a lot better, and you don't have to pretend.</p>
        <p>Last semester, when I was a junior at an Ivy League university in a large Northeastern state, I managed to hack into the econ department computer and download the final exam. Long story short, the school investigated and found the test in my laptop. I explained that I was merely testing the security of the computer system, and that no one was hurt. (Au contraire, I aced the exam!) They expelled me anyway. Then over the summer I read that the university admissions director was caught snooping in the computer of a rival school. Did they throw HIM into the Gulag? No, they transferred him to another office. Life is, like, so unfair!</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, PRINCETON, N.J.</p>
        <p>I'm not an Ivy League kind of guy, but I appreciate the fine moral sense your education has instilled in you. I've taken the liberty of referring your name to a securities broker of my acquaintance, who will be contacting you about career opportunities.</p>
        <p>I'm an aging rock 'n' roll singer from a large Northeastern state -- actually, the critics usually call me a working-class poet, or, you know, a troubadour. Anyway, just when my career was starting to look like endless gigs of recycled oldies, I cut a new album about the Sept. 11 thing, and it took off like, you know, a last-chance power drive. Hey, I got the covers of Time and Rolling Stone, I got MTV and ''Saturday Night Live,'' the ''Today'' show gave me the whole program, Letterman had me on two nights in a row -- I even had back-to-back shows with Koppel, the get-down king of late night. My record shot up to No. 1 on Billboard. But somehow it left me feeling, you know, forlorn -- like an ice cream truck on a deserted street, if you know what I mean. When I sit in my 19th-century farmhouse, gazing out at the organic crops, I wonder: am I climbing up the charts on the backs of all those dead people?</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, ASBURY PARK, N.J.</p>
        <p>You bleeding hearts kill me. You cashed in on the big attack? Like everybody else didn't? How many books got sold? How many careers got a bump? Americans understand that you can't let a good tragedy go to waste. What's that the president said? If somebody doesn't make a buck off it, the bad guys win, right? Allow me to quote my favorite moral philosopher, Karl Rove. Remember what he told Republican candidates back in June? ''Focus on war.'' (O.K., he's no troubadour, but the man gets to the point.) D'you think he meant, ''Let's all focus on the war and have a moment of silence and feel blue?'' Of course not, knucklehead, he meant, ''Take the war, and run the wussy Democrats into the ground with it.'' So you've got nothing to feel bad about. Then again, maybe you can do something with this. How about a new album about how bad you feel about that last album? Hey, you could call it ''The Writhing.''</p>
        <p>I'm the C.E.O. of a large family-run organization specializing in waste management. Lately we've had to do some serious downsizing, and there's been a lot of bad feeling in the organization. I don't mind admitting it all makes me depressed sometimes. My shrink says I feel guilty and should get out of the business. On top of that, my wife is on my case about laying aside more money for the future, as if I'm some kind of deadbeat don.</p>
        <p>ANONYMOUS, NORTH CALDWELL, N.J.</p>
        <p>Tell your shrink, guilty's not a feeling, it's a verdict. Until you've heard it from a jury of your peers and then exhausted all your appeals right up to the Supreme Court, put that word away. Look, business is business, and if you want to make an omelet you've got to break some eggs. My second favorite moral philosopher, ''Chainsaw Al'' Dunlap, put it this way: ''To hell with harmony.'' Now, about the wife. The other night I was reading my kid this book, ''If You Give a Mouse a Cookie.'' It's all about how people are never satisfied, you give 'em a piece of you and they won't stop until they've squeezed you empty. As I see it, the moral of the book is, when that mouse comes around, give him a dose of D-Con. I think you follow what I'm saying here.</p>
        <p>I'm a voter who lives in a large Northeastern state --</p>
        <p>Say no more, pal. You don't need an ethicist. You need an anesthetist.</p>
        <p>E-mail: billkeller@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: billkeller@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
