<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Shift Foils Area Energy Plans</title>
    <meta content="13POWE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1431430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Melville (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yaphank (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Keyspan Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American National Power</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6DC1F3BF930A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Shift Foils Area Energy Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>KeySpan and American National Power, which want to build power genrators in Melvllle and Yaphank, say they are unable to raise capital for projects without first having contracts to sell most of electricity to Long Island Power Authority; LIPA chairman says purchase agreeements would not be possible unless it is given part ownership in new plants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE the wave of the energy future, independent power plant projects that were supposed to bring competition to Long Island are on the ropes, and their developers are turning to the Long Island Power Authority for help.</p>
        <p>KeySpan, which wants to build a 250-megawatt generator on Spagnoli Road in Melville at an estimated cost of nearly $300 million, and American National Power, which wants to construct a $500 million, 580-megawatt plant in Yaphank, say they are unable to raise capital for the projects without first having contracts to sell most of the electricity to LIPA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE the wave of the energy future, independent power plant projects that were supposed to bring competition to Long Island are on the ropes, and their developers are turning to the Long Island Power Authority for help.</p>
        <p>KeySpan, which wants to build a 250-megawatt generator on Spagnoli Road in Melville at an estimated cost of nearly $300 million, and American National Power, which wants to construct a $500 million, 580-megawatt plant in Yaphank, say they are unable to raise capital for the projects without first having contracts to sell most of the electricity to LIPA.</p>
        <p>But Richard M. Kessel, the LIPA chairman, said last week that such power purchase agreements would not be possible unless LIPA was given part ownership of the new plants.</p>
        <p>If the companiessell part of the plants to LIPA, their profit margins would shrink. But if the plants aren't built, the companies would have to write off tens of millions of dollars they have already invested in the projects.</p>
        <p>LIPA had agreed to buy half the power from the Spagnoli Road plant. But KeySpan now says that LIPA, a state agency, would need to buy more for the project to proceed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said that agreeing to buy all or most of the plants' power without ownership rights would force LIPA and its customers to assume the risk in the companies' for-profit ventures. If LIPA signed purchase agreements it would be committed to paying for a large portion of the plants' output whether or not the supplies were needed, and even if cheaper electricity became available elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''When these plants first came in, they said they were merchant plants and wanted to sell on the open market,'' Mr. Kessel said. ''Now they want LIPA to enter into firm power purchase agreements to buy all or most of their power. All I'm saying is that we ought to have some ownership rights.''</p>
        <p>But LIPA was barely able to meet record demand this summer and is scrambling to secure new power supplies for next summer and beyond. It is not in a position to ignore proposed new generation.</p>
        <p>Last week officials of KeySpan and American National Power declined to comment directly on Mr. Kessel's demand for part ownership in their projects. David Manning, the KeySpan senior vice president for corporate affairs, described it as ''new.''</p>
        <p>''KeySpan has invested shareholder dollars to do all the preparatory work to keep this project on track for a startup in 2004,'' Mr. Manning said, referring to the Spagnoli Road plant. ''We believe, as does Richard Kessel, that there is a critical need for additional power.''</p>
        <p>Paul C. Parshley, a spokesman at the Marlboro, Mass., headquarters of American National Power, declined to comment on whether the company would consider selling part of its proposed Yaphank plant to LIPA. He said discussions with LIPA continued on ''a range of issues.''</p>
        <p>Finding financing for merchant plants without guaranteed customers has become nearly impossible in the wake of the Enron scandal, financial analysts said. The sagging national economy and uncertainties involving industry deregulation in New York were also factors, they said.</p>
        <p>''The capital markets are basically closed to the merchant type of business,'' said Arleen Spangler, a director in the utilities, energy and project finance group at Standard and Poor's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said the energy market had changed profoundly.</p>
        <p>''The world has changed, not just Long Island,'' he said. ''Throughout the country, the notion of merchant plants and competition is basically out the window right now. These companies cannot get the financing to build these plants unless some entity purchases all or some of the power.''</p>
        <p>The shift gives LIPA an opportunity to have the two companies compete for its business. The Yaphank plan has been approved by a state siting board, while the Spagnoli Road project has not. But transmission tie-in costs remain at issue between LIPA and American National Power. The company contends it would cost about $10 million to meet minimum standards. LIPA has said more than $150 million would be needed.</p>
        <p>The state siting board brushed aside LIPA's contention that American National Power should pay the cost of the upgrading in its decision in August allowing construction of the plant to begin.</p>
        <p>LIPA has an option to buy the older KeySpan plants that provide the bulk of its electricity. But a purchase agreement would require close cooperation between LIPA and KeySpan, a possible reason why LIPA would not lightly rebuff KeySpan's Spagnoli Road project.</p>
        <p>Which of the two projects LIPA will back may now depend on which of the companies accommodates Mr. Kessel's request for part-ownership or makes other concessions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said LIPA was ''going to have to be very aggressive about who gives us the best deal.''</p>
        <p>Energy Coalition Has a Plan</p>
        <p>Faulting the Long Island Power Authority for failing to produce an energy master plan, a coalition of more than 30 environmental and civic groups has released a plan of its own.</p>
        <p>The plan devised by the Sustainable Energy Alliance of Long Island calls for increased emphasis on energy efficiency and for the refurbishing of older generating stations before new plants are built. LIPA now depends on older power plants owned by KeySpan for most of its on-Island supplies.</p>
        <p>The alliance called on LIPA to double its spending on solar, wind and other renewable energy sources to $320 million over the next five years. It asked LIPA to commit to provide 10 percent of Long Island's electricity from renewable sources by 2010.</p>
        <p>Other recommendations included rebates for customers who reduce electric use by at least 15 percent over the previous year and penalties for excessive use of electricity during peak periods.</p>
        <p>Richard M. Kessel, the LIPA chairman, said it would consider the report.</p>
        <p>JOHN RATHER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
