<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Center of the Earth, the Mighty Bubble</title>
    <meta content="20SPAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1377201"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mineral Water</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rentschler, Kay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DF1238F933A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Center of the Earth, the Mighty Bubble</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAY RENTSCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rentschler, Kay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kay Rentschler describes how sparkling water can be used in cooking; recipes; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the glare and clamor of restaurant kitchens, chefs reach for bottles of sparkling water not just to cool their throats. Those tiny bubbles that sting and dance on the tongue also give a lilting chew to noodles and dumplings, papery crispness to tempura, a lift to dips and an acerbic attitude to desserts. Sparkling water is almost as much fun to cook with as Champagne -- but much cheaper.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is powerful stuff, laying sparkle to waters throughout history -- from ancient mineral springs to Diet Coke -- and occasioning the rise of fragile soufflés and muscular breads as well. That much I knew. I also knew that the spaetzle I make with sparkling water is light and fluffy. But why exactly? It was time to talk to some experts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the glare and clamor of restaurant kitchens, chefs reach for bottles of sparkling water not just to cool their throats. Those tiny bubbles that sting and dance on the tongue also give a lilting chew to noodles and dumplings, papery crispness to tempura, a lift to dips and an acerbic attitude to desserts. Sparkling water is almost as much fun to cook with as Champagne -- but much cheaper.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is powerful stuff, laying sparkle to waters throughout history -- from ancient mineral springs to Diet Coke -- and occasioning the rise of fragile soufflés and muscular breads as well. That much I knew. I also knew that the spaetzle I make with sparkling water is light and fluffy. But why exactly? It was time to talk to some experts.</p>
        <p>The lightening effect of sparkling water in doughs is quite basic, said Kevin Ryan, a food scientist at the University of Illinois at Urbana. When sparkling water is added to a dough or batter, its bubbles create pockets of air (trapping water droplets in the process) that expand under heat, giving the final product a lighter texture.</p>
        <p>The bubbles are critical, Mr. Ryan explained: if not for them, the vapor formed when water in the dough boils might simply escape, leaving the finished dough flat. Unlike egg-white foam, which has difficulty finding its way in a heavy dough, sparkling water moves about easily, providing an even distribution of stable bubbles that remain until the heat of cooking sets them in place.</p>
        <p>The leavening benefits of the carbon dioxide in dough are, of course, fleeting. To maintain its sparkling personality, even in the short term, the water must be very cold (the smallest increase in temperature reduces the ability of a liquid to hold gas) and the bottle opened just before use to maintain the carbon dioxide level.</p>
        <p>What this means for the cook is that time is of the essence: once the contents are no longer under pressure, the chilled water must be bound quickly into the dough. Gentle hand-folding is prudent. My own experience indicates that dough made with sparkling water has a peak performance window of about 15 minutes before the benefits of the bubbles diminish.</p>
        <p>Doughs and batters that are spooned into boiling liquid or fat and are cooked quickly profit more from being made with sparkling water than do pastas that are cut, rolled out or refrigerated at length before cooking, food experts say. It's all about timing.</p>
        <p>Sparkling water's carbon dioxide delivers more than just fizz. Its dilute carbonic acid also lowers the water's pH -- making it more acidic, and refreshingly tart. The palate experiences this acidity as refreshing; dough experiences it as a tenderizer. The effect of acid on dough is legendary: it's the reason 4-H winners put vinegar in their pie dough. Particularly in soft, fresh doughs like kreplach or matzo balls, the combined leavening and lightening effects of sparkling water can be counted on to deliver a fine toothsomeness.</p>
        <p>Carbonation can take place in many venues, from thermal springs and artesian wells to enormous gas cylinders. Though some critics say artificially manufactured carbonation is harsh and unpalatable, ultimately it is the amount of gas that makes one water nicer to sip than another (generally, less is more); if the sparkles are laced with minerals, the flavor and pH of the water change as well.</p>
        <p>Seltzer water, which is purified tap water with high levels of carbonation -- a soft drink, by industry classification -- is aggressively effervescent in the mouth, but has its place in cooking. At Oceana, Rick Moonen finishes his taramosalata with seltzer; Jim Botsacos at Molyvos follows suit with his skordalia. Both chefs like seltzer's bubbly character, which, they say, aerates their dips and makes them fluffy. (There's no persuading them that the kick from the bubbles is temporary.)</p>
        <p>''The seltzer changes the entire complexion of the emulsification,'' Mr. Moonen said, adding that the dip's surrounding flavors become clean and accessible when the seltzer is stirred in at the end.</p>
        <p>Many chefs use sparkling mineral waters like Perrier, San Pellegrino and Gerolsteiner, whose carbonation occurs naturally in the underground water itself and which are bottled at the source. In addition to their bubbles, these waters have dissolved solids and minerals, and flow with differing pH levels -- all of which can affect flavor.</p>
        <p>At Citarella the Restaurant, William Yosses makes a dessert digestive of hibiscus flowers, grapefruit oil and mint with San Pellegrino water, liking the flinty finish its high calcium content brings to the dance -- which is similar, he says, to a fine chardonnay.</p>
        <p>In the dumpling recipe here, I like Perrier or Gerolsteiner over the other waters. Boasting a bit more fizz than Pellegrino, these waters bump up the leavening properties, while their residual minerals bring a mild natural sweetness to the dumplings as well -- something a plain sparkling water like Poland Springs cannot offer. I did not care for the highly charged seltzer water in this recipe -- the leavening benefits were not superior, the dumpling flavor distinctly inferior.</p>
        <p>So pop open a bottle of your favorite water and do your own experimenting: cooking with sparkling water is like being a scientist -- or a magician -- for a day.</p>
        <p>ROASTED GARLIC AND CHEDDAR DUMPLINGS  Time: About 2 hours</p>
        <p>1 head garlic  1 cup all-purpose flour  2 tablespoons fresh minced sage</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon smoked paprika  1 1/2 teaspoons kosher salt</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper  2 tablespoons unsalted butter, melted and cooled but still fluid  1 large egg  3 to 4 tablespoons very cold sparkling mineral water  1 1/2 ounces sharp Cheddar cheese, cut into 20  1/4-inch cubes.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oven to 300 degrees. Cut off pointed end of garlic head; wrap head in aluminum foil. Roast until soft and golden, about 90 minutes. Squeeze garlic into bowl; reserve.  2. Combine dry ingredients and 1 tablespoon roasted garlic (save remaining garlic for another use) in food processor and pulse briefly to combine.  3. Stir butter and egg in small bowl. Add to processor and pulse until well-combined. Turn into mixing bowl, add mineral water, and fold gently until dough comes together; it will be soft and tacky. Cover tightly with plastic wrap and chill 10 minutes.  4. Meanwhile, boil 8 cups water in 10-inch wide, 3-inch deep covered braising pan.  5. Spray work surface next to stove lightly with water or oil. Using 2 forks dipped in cold water, lift 2 teaspoons dough and drop it onto misted surface; it will be an irregular mound with a shaggy surface. Moisten fingers with cold water and press a cheese cube lightly into center, lifting dough a bit to make pointy top. Continue with dough and cheese until you have 20 dumplings.  6. Add salt to boiling water. Moisten fingers again and quickly drop dumplings one by one into pan. Reduce heat to low. Watch dumplings, loosening if necessary from pan bottom and flipping occasionally with fork. Keep water at gentle simmer. Dumplings are done when they float to the top and insides are like soft, baked bread when tested, 5 to 7 minutes. Using slotted spoon, transfer dumplings to paper towels. Dry briefly, and transfer to parchment paper. Serve hot with ham-braised greens, beef stew or a brothy chicken or vegetable soup.</p>
        <p>Yield: 20 small dumplings.</p>
        <p>SKORDALIA  Adapted from Molyvos  Time: About 15 minutes plus 3 hours' chilling</p>
        <p>2 ounces blanched sliced almonds (about  3/4 cup)  2 large cloves garlic  1 large potato (such as a Russet), about 10 ounces, unpeeled and cooked until tender  1 cup olive oil (not extra virgin)  3 to 4 tablespoons fresh lemon juice</p>
        <p>1/2 to  3/4 cup very cold sparkling water or seltzer  Salt  1 1/2 teaspoons freshly ground white pepper.</p>
        <p>1. In food processor, pulse almonds until finely chopped. Add garlic and pulse until mixture is very fine.  2. Peel and quarter potato quickly while still very hot. Transfer to food mill positioned over food processor bowl and mill potato into almond mixture. Pulse mixture together briefly.  3. Add olive oil in slow stream while pulsing food processor. Add 2 tablespoons lemon juice, then pulse in sparkling water or seltzer. Skordalia should be very white, with a consistency of light mashed potatoes. Add more water if too thick. Season with salt and pepper and adjust seasoning, adding more lemon juice if desired. Do not overprocess. Chill 3 hours or overnight. Serve as a dip with roasted vegetables and pita triangles.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 1/2 cups.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
