<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1439078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D61431F93AA35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Iraq Resolution Passes, And Bush Repeats Warning  The United Nations Security Council unanimously passed the resolution that President Bush called a test of Saddam Hussein's willingness to disarm, and Mr. Bush said that the Iraqi president's response must be ''prompt and unconditional, or he will face the severest consequences.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>For Powell, Praise and a Risk  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell has worked hard for Security Council approval for the resolution on Iraq. However, the secretary's approach has yet to be vindicated as many conservatives are concerned about the possibility of a muddled, slow and inconclusive inspection effort in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Iraq Resolution Passes, And Bush Repeats Warning  The United Nations Security Council unanimously passed the resolution that President Bush called a test of Saddam Hussein's willingness to disarm, and Mr. Bush said that the Iraqi president's response must be ''prompt and unconditional, or he will face the severest consequences.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>For Powell, Praise and a Risk  Secretary of State Colin L. Powell has worked hard for Security Council approval for the resolution on Iraq. However, the secretary's approach has yet to be vindicated as many conservatives are concerned about the possibility of a muddled, slow and inconclusive inspection effort in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bali Blast Aimed at Americans  A suspect in the attack on a Bali disco has told interrogators that the blast was intended to hit Americans and that he regretted that many more Australians were killed, the chief of the investigation said. The investigation is pointing toward the operational leader for Al Qaeda in southeast Asia as the mastermind of the attack.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Colombia Will Toughen Laws  President Álvaro Uribe of Colombia said that the country would seek to stiffen prison sentencing procedures after the government failed to prevent the early release of a former top leader of the multi-billion-dollar Cali cartel cocaine empire. The attorney general has ordered an investigation of the judge involved.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>French Ex-Leader on Turkey  The former French president, Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, who is the man overseeing plans for the future of the European Union, said that Turkey was not a European country and that inviting it to join the Union would mean ''the end of Europe.''</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Moscow Attack on Ambassador  Maj. Gen. Francis Y. Mahama, Ghana's ambassador to Russia, and his driver were attacked in Moscow. Earlier this year General Mahama joined in an appeal to do more to protect embassy employees and other Africans from a wave of racist attacks.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-17</p>
        <p>California Woman Is Likely To Lead House Democrats  Representative Nancy Pelosi of California said that she had secured the votes she needs to become the new House Democratic leader, which would make her the first woman to head a party in Congress.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats examining some of their most disappointing losses on Tuesday say that minority voters turned out in respectable numbers and voted Democratic, but that the party apparently lost thousands of moderate white voters south of the Mason-Dixon line.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Sniper Suspects In Court  The two men charged in the sniper shootings made separate appearances in Virginia courts, where prosecutors said the only fingerprintsfound on the murder weapon were those of Lee Malvo, 17.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Asylum Extension in Question  Immigration groups and Haitian advocates had mixed reactions to President Bush's remarks about the treatment of asylum seekers and questioned whether his words would lead to the release of hundreds of refugees being detained.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Fugitive Radical Arrested  Federal authorities announced that the police in South Africa had arrested James W. Kilgore, the last fugitive from the Symbionese Liberation Army wanted in the shotgun killing of a woman 27 years ago.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Catholics Seek Disclosure  Many American Catholics who attend Mass regularly say the nation's bishops should disclose the financial cost of the priest sex scandal, a survey has found.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Court Overturns F.C.C. Rule  A federal appeals court overturned rules by the Federal Communications Commission that would require broadcasters to adopt technology to allow blind people to follow the action on television by listening to a narrator described the physical movements.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Mediation for Teenage Killers  Closed-door mediation has begun in an effort to settle the case of two teenage brothers whose convictions for killing their father were thrown out in September.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>New 9/11 Study Disputes Report on Communications  An analysis of a tape of firefighter communications at the World Trade Center on Sept. 11 conducted by officials at the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey not only contradicts the city's version of what went wrong, but also raises questions about the thoroughness of city investigations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Searching for a Lobster Killer  Researchers and many people in the lobster-fishing industry blame pesticides for a precipitous decline in Long Island Sound lobsters. But others contend that warmer waters caused by global climate change are the cause, and one scientist's discoveries may support that claim.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Plague Victim is State Official  A man in critical condition with the bubonic plague in a Manhattan hospital is a former top official of the agency in New Mexico responsible for investigating criminal cases of insurance fraud, officials there said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>High Lead Levels in Water  The New York City school system announced that it had shut off drinking fountains and posted warning signs on sinks at one in five of the city's public elementary schools after tests showed the level of lead in the water exceeded federal standards.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Books and Athletics at Williams  For more than a decade at Williams College, the sports teams have been far superior to those at any other college of its size. All the winning has made some faculty members and students uneasy and stirred a debate about whether an institution prized for its academics can harmoniously house a powerhouse athletic program.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Pitt Appeals to Wall Street  Harvey L. Pitt, in his first public speech since resigning as chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission, called on Wall Street executives to restore investor confidence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>German Bank Tries to Adapt  Commerzbank, Germany's fourth-largest bank, shares most of the problems afflicting Germany's banking system. It is expected to dismiss 1,500 workers in its effort to change from a sprawling global institution into a smaller, more domestic bank.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Down Day on Wall Street  The Dow dropped 49.11 points, to 8,537.13, but finished ahead for the week, its fifth consecutive weekly increase. Nasdaq, which fell 17.44 points, to 1,359.27, snapped a four-week winning streak.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>McDonald's Cutting Back  McDonald's said fourth-quarter earnings would fall short of earlier forecasts. The company plans to close 175 underperforming restaurants in 10 countries.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: A unified message to Iraq; pulling a party together; the taxman outgunned; Harlem's song.</p>
        <p>Column: Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B15  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
