<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush White House Starts Own High-Mileage Car Program</title>
    <meta content="Y10FUEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/10/business/10FUEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1358096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, Spencer (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DA1039F933A25752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="857" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush White House Starts Own High-Mileage Car Program</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High-Mileage Car Program Ends, and Another Replaces It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration replaces one government-backed program to build high-mileage cars with another; environmentalists say too much had been spent and too little accomplished in old project, while automakers say effort's goals had been unrealistic in first place; old program's main goal, to produce concept cars that could get 80 miles a gallon by 2004--and could be mass-produced--is far from reality; Energy Sec Spencer Abraham says project will be replaced by program that will focus almost exclusively on one of current project's furthest-off areas of research, development of vehicles powered by fuel cells; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Bush administration replaced one government-backed program to build high-mileage cars with another today, hardly anyone rushed to eulogize the old project. Environmentalists said  too much had been spent and too little accomplished, while automakers said the effort's goals had been unrealistic in the first place.</p>
        <p>The Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles, started in 1993 and championed by Vice President Al Gore, spent more than $1.5 billion in federal money. The goal was for General Motors, Ford Motor and Chrysler, now a unit of DaimlerChrysler, to work together with auto suppliers, government laboratories and universities on a range of technologies aimed at making cars more fuel efficient.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmentalists said too much had been spent and too little accomplished, while automakers said that producing a car that could get 80 miles to the gallon had been unrealistic in the first place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Bush administration replaced one government-backed program to build high-mileage cars with another today, hardly anyone rushed to eulogize the old project. Environmentalists said  too much had been spent and too little accomplished, while automakers said the effort's goals had been unrealistic in the first place.</p>
        <p>The Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles, started in 1993 and championed by Vice President Al Gore, spent more than $1.5 billion in federal money. The goal was for General Motors, Ford Motor and Chrysler, now a unit of DaimlerChrysler, to work together with auto suppliers, government laboratories and universities on a range of technologies aimed at making cars more fuel efficient.</p>
        <p>The project involved a host of government agencies -- the Departments of Commerce, Defense, Energy and Transportation, as well as the Environmental Protection Agency and NASA.</p>
        <p>Less than half of 1 percent of the money set aside for the program went to the Big Three. This year, about half of the program's $127 million budget was earmarked for various national laboratories. The Argonne National Laboratory in Illinois, for instance, receives financing for fuel cell research, and the Oak Ridge National Laboratory near Knoxville, Tenn., researches aluminum materials. Suppliers are scheduled to receive about 30 percent of the financing and universities another 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The program did create some useful technologies that showed up in vehicles on the road. Lightweight aluminum was used in the 2000 Lincoln LS and in some Cadillacs. The Jeep Wrangler has a thermoplastic roof that uses technology from the program. And some of the research into diesel-electric hybrid vehicles can be used in the gasoline-electric hybrids to be sold by the Big Three starting next year.</p>
        <p>But in the end, the program's main goal, to produce concept cars that could get 80 miles a gallon by 2004 -- and could be mass-produced -- is far from reality. United States automakers say that producing vehicles that could leap to 80 miles a gallon is not possible this decade. In fact, they even argued at a Senate hearing recently that raising fuel economy standards to 40 miles a gallon over the next half-decade would be a crippling blow to their business.</p>
        <p>By contrast, two Japanese companies, Toyota and Honda, are already selling gasoline-electric hybrid vehicles that get better than 40 miles to the gallon, though their total fleets get far less. This year, Honda plans to start selling a hybrid version of its popular Civic.</p>
        <p>Current corporate average fuel economy standards, also known as CAFE, which have not been changed significantly in more than a decade, require 20.7 miles a gallon for each company's average new light truck and 27.5 miles a gallon for the average new car.</p>
        <p>''You can build 80 m.p.g. cars, but if they cost too much, nobody is going to buy them,'' said William Noack, a spokesman for G.M.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say the project  was ultimately a failure because it was not accompanied by an increase in federal fuel-economy standards.</p>
        <p>''Al Gore said this would make CAFE obsolete,'' said Daniel Becker, director of global warming for the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>''What did it result in? Not a single, purchasable hybrid'' from the Big Three.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are equally skeptical of the Bush plan. The announcement today came as the Senate prepared to debate its energy bill. Spencer Abraham, the energy secretary, said the project would be replaced by a program that would focus almost exclusively on one of the current project's furthest-off areas of research, the development of vehicles powered by fuel cells.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham said in an interview that he had supported the partnership when he was in Congress, ''but when we came here we concluded that no one was going to produce these vehicles and no one would buy them.''</p>
        <p>Fuel cells draw power from hydrogen and ideally emit only water vapor and heat. All of the major automakers are working on fuel cell projects and say they represent the eventual end to the internal combustion engine. But most envision only a few hundred thousand such vehicles on the road by the end of the decade. Among the hurdles is outfitting service stations with hydrogen.</p>
        <p>''There is no requirement in either plan that the auto industry actually produce the vehicles for sale,'' said Mr. Becker of the Sierra Club. ''If Congress is fooled into not raising CAFE standards because of this new smoke screen, the pressure will be off Detroit again.''</p>
        <p>Secretary Abraham called his program a 21st-century approach that would eventually end the fuel economy debate, but added that it was far too early to set a timetable to require automakers actually to produce fuel cell vehicles.</p>
        <p>''You can't expect people to put vehicles on the road if you don't have the infrastructure to support it,'' he said. ''This is Day 1.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
