<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theater; An Imagination That Pulls Everyone Else Along</title>
    <meta content="10NIGH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/10/arts/theater/10NIGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1439370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Churchill, Caryl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nightingale, Benedict</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daldry, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdormand, Frances</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gambon, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Craig, Daniel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Far Away (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Number, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Stephen Daldry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Churchill, Caryl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McDormand, Frances</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDA1F3EF933A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theater; An Imagination That Pulls Everyone Else Along</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Caryl Churchill's Gripping Imagination</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENEDICT NIGHTINGALE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nightingale, Benedict</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benedict Nightingale report from London on Caryl Churchill's one-act plays Far Away and A Number; Stephen Daldry's production of Far Away will open at New York Theater Workshop with Frances McDormand; photos; his staging of A Number, starring Michael Gambon and Daniel Craig, is playing at Royal Court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF there were an award for the British dramatist who most brilliantly combines shrewd observation with technical daring, the winner would not be some 25-year-old meteor from the far horizons of the avant-garde. The hottest candidate would be the author of ''Top Girls,''  ''Cloud Nine'' and now ''Far Away'' and ''A Number'': Caryl Churchill, who is 64. Were she to write a tragicomedy for dancers set in a crumbling ozone layer, nobody would be surprised.</p>
        <p>''She's always reinventing herself,'' said Max Stafford-Clark, who has directed the premieres of many Churchill plays, including ''Top Girls'' and ''Cloud Nine.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Far Away," starring Frances McDormand, right, is one in a number of shrewd and daring plays by the British dramatist Caryl Churchill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF there were an award for the British dramatist who most brilliantly combines shrewd observation with technical daring, the winner would not be some 25-year-old meteor from the far horizons of the avant-garde. The hottest candidate would be the author of ''Top Girls,''  ''Cloud Nine'' and now ''Far Away'' and ''A Number'': Caryl Churchill, who is 64. Were she to write a tragicomedy for dancers set in a crumbling ozone layer, nobody would be surprised.</p>
        <p>''She's always reinventing herself,'' said Max Stafford-Clark, who has directed the premieres of many Churchill plays, including ''Top Girls'' and ''Cloud Nine.''</p>
        <p>The director Stephen Daldry agreed. ''She constantly expands the boundaries of theatrical writing,'' said Mr. Daldry, whose production of ''Far Away'' opens tomorrow night at New York Theater Workshop in the East Village in Manhattan, and whose staging of ''A Number'' is still here at the Royal Court. ''She has her finger on the pulse of the time,'' he added. ''Her plays always seem to prefigure the next important debate.''</p>
        <p>Whether or not Ms. Churchill is the English-speaking world's greatest female dramatist -- and she herself is on record as being appalled by a tag that combines swank, sexism and the smack of academia -- she strikes me as uniquely important. At a time when the electronic media are gradually deadening us, she can't seem to stop demonstrating the possibilities and power of live drama. More than any other writer, she has transformed the theater into what it needs to be: a gymnasium that exercises the imagination, shakes up the moral sense, stretches the spirit.</p>
        <p>The 55-minute ''Far Away,'' which stars Frances McDormand, begins in a deceptively realistic way but culminates in a vision of doom likely to seem even more eloquent in the America of 2002 than it did at the play's London opening in 2000. In this crazed future, nations are not simply taking sides with or against terrorists or rogue states. The whole animal kingdom, from crocodiles to starlings, is fighting a war in which everything in the vegetable and mineral kingdoms, from foxgloves through bleach to pins, has been enrolled as weaponry.</p>
        <p>In ''A Number'' (which runs 60 minutes), three young men, all played by Daniel Craig, come successively onto a tiny plain stage to confront Michael Gambon, playing their father. Which is the original son, which is his clone and which has been secretly created, also by cloning, by a maverick scientist? The play keeps you guessing but also thinking. ''We've staged it very simply,'' Mr. Daldry said. ''But it's multilayered. It's about free will, genetics, fathers and sons and much more.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Churchill has produced few more timely pieces than ''A Number'' or ''Far Away,'' but several that are stylistically bolder. The second half of ''Top Girls'' is perfectly naturalistic; but the first consists of a dinner party given for a Victorian lady explorer, a 13th-century Japanese courtesan and traveler, and the ninth-century Pope Joan by a modern woman who arrogantly believes that her promotion to chief of a slick employment agency matches their feats. The overall result is a feminist critique of feminism: a play that exposes the self-mutilation inherent in brash careerism.</p>
        <p>''Top Girls,'' which appeared in 1982, is probably Ms. Churchill's masterpiece, but it is closely followed by ''Cloud Nine.'' In 1979, when it was first staged, we had heard a lot less about the complexities of gender than we have now. But Ms. Churchill, ahead of the argument as usual, cast women as men and vice versa to show the principled anguish of adulterous, bisexual, homosexual and pedophile Victorians in a parody African colony -- and then transported them to contemporary London to suggest that, though we have become less repressed and more tolerant, sexuality is still hard to compartmentalize and still causes us problems and pain.</p>
        <p>Ms. Churchill, who lives in Islington in North London, with her husband, a lawyer, has made a practice in recent years of refusing to be interviewed, believing that her opinions should be no more set in stone than her imagination. But in the past, she has acknowledged that her prime concerns are the power and powerlessness of people, their longings, obsessions and dreams. She is a humanist, has described herself as a socialist and remains the dedicated foe of the class inequalities she found in Britain after spending much of her childhood in Canada, where her parents had relocated when she was 9. But she is no didact, no propagandist, and regards it as her duty to feel her way into her more unappealing characters rather than merely condemn them. As she told The Independent in 1989, her job consists of ''throwing up worries and questions and complexities which you might not have if you weren't of a particular political complexion, but not actually saying, 'Here is a political course of action.' ''</p>
        <p>Certainly, Ms. Churchill's range of subjects is broad: real estate predators in ''Owners'' in 1972, witch hunts in ''Vinegar Tom'' in 1976, law and order in ''Softcops'' in 1984, City of London traders in ''Serious Money,'' a fiercely funny satire, written largely in verse, that was hugely successful in 1987. In 1989 she wrote a road play, ''Ice Cream,'' in which an American couple were violently disabused of the idea that England is all green fields and nice pubs, and in 1997 she produced ''Blue Heart,'' a marvelously inventive study of a peculiarly English trait, emotional evasiveness.</p>
        <p>Actually, ''Blue Heart'' was a double-bill, one half involving a family nervously awaiting the return of a long-absent daughter, the other a disturbed young man conning a series of elderly women into believing he is the son they gave away for adoption. But nothing was straightforward. Again and again the family's conversation stopped, restarted from scratch, took off in new directions, and, by way of showing the fears and fantasies beneath the tension, was interrupted by unlikely intruders: an SS man, terrorists, a huge ostrich. And the words ''blue'' and ''kettle'' intruded into the awkward, painful exchanges between the ''son'' and his ''mothers,'' at first barely noticeably, finally so overwhelmingly that little but that irrelevant adjective and inapposite noun were heard.</p>
        <p>As ''Blue Heart'' showed, Ms. Churchill's mistrust of convention got increasingly marked in the 1990's. She started to work with dancers, producing ''Hotel,'' in which the stage swirled with words and movement as 14 people simultaneously acted out separate visits to the same hotel room, and ''The Skriker,'' in which an enchantress tried to lure two dim, sad London girls into a fairyland teeming with creatures with names like Black Dog and Rawheadandbloodybones.</p>
        <p>But that play, with its inference that we have lost touch with some deep, dark, inherited wisdom, wasn't just further proof of the scope of Ms. Churchill's concerns. It was a prime example of her fondness for collaboration. It may seem odd that so idiosyncratic a writer should take such relish in collective research, workshops and joint experiment, but she has persistently proved to be, in Mr. Daldry's words, ''a fantastic fellow-explorer, who comes into the rehearsal room without preconceptions and works with you to find a physical theatrical language for whatever she's written.''</p>
        <p>She has collaborated with Mr. Stafford-Clark's now-defunct Joint Stock Company, debating sexual politics with its actors for ''Cloud Nine'' and going with them to live in a remote village for ''Fen,'' which involved rural change. Now she is likely to be found working with the same director's Out of Joint, which produced ''Blue Heart,'' or the dance troupe Second Stride, which staged ''Hotel.'' Soon after the fall of Ceausescu, she and a group of drama students went to Romania, interviewed vast numbers of people and produced a documentary play called ''Mad Forest.''</p>
        <p>Shakespeare's Polonius would have had to extend his famous definition of drama if he were to embrace Ms. Churchill's work. Indeed, even to call it tragical-comical-historical-pastoral-satirical-sociological-political-apocalyptical seems an understatement. Did I begin by saying that it wouldn't be surprising if she wrote a dance piece about our damaged skies? Well, I was teasing you. In 1991 she did just that -- and the result was more ambitious than I had suggested.</p>
        <p>''Lives of the Great Poisoners'' brought together three murderers -- Medea, Dr. Crippen and an 18th-century Frenchwoman called Madame de Brinvilliers -- and the inventor Thomas Midgley, who put the lead in gasoline and CFC's, or chlorofluorocarbons, in refrigerators and had worrying plans for the ozone layer. The finished piece seemed to involve everything toxic, from polluted air to mad cows to chemical weapons. Yet it was no earnest tract. It was an eco-opera, comprising prose, verse, actors, dancers and a cappella singers. Who could and would have put it together but Ms. Churchill? Nobody.</p>
        <p>Benedict Nightingale is the chief theater critic of The Times of London.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Benedict Nightingale is the chief theater critic of The Times of London.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
