<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Horizon: More Power, Fewer Fumes</title>
    <meta content="30LIPA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1404623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yaphank (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Keyspan Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American National Power</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DD153EF933A05755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Horizon: More Power, Fewer Fumes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Power Authority and KeySpan Energy Corp enter second phase of study of combined cycle technology to increase power plant capacity while drastically reducing emissions; British-owned American National Power may receive permission from New York State to build $500 million, 580-megawatt power plant in Yaphank; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAJOR changes that would help clean up Long Island's air while increasing its electricity supplies may be on the horizon.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority and the KeySpan Energy Corporation are in the second phase of a study of using what is called combined cycle technology to increase power plants' capacity while drastically reducing emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAJOR changes that would help clean up Long Island's air while increasing its electricity supplies may be on the horizon.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority and the KeySpan Energy Corporation are in the second phase of a study of using what is called combined cycle technology to increase power plants' capacity while drastically reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>At the same time, a British-owned private energy company, American National Power, may soon receive permission from a state board to build a $500 million, 580-megawatt power plant in Yaphank. If the company goes ahead, it would be the largest new power plant built on Long Island in decades -- and kilowatt for kilowatt, the least polluting.</p>
        <p>Summer heat makes the issue of power supplies and emissions critical as LIPA and KeySpan stretch to their limits to keep the lights on and air-conditioners humming. Air quality declines as aging power plants work at capacity, emitting tons of sulfur dioxide, nitrous oxides and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>These emissions have been going up sharply. From 1995 and 2000, the most recent year for which figures were available, statistics compiled by the Environmental Protection Agency, based on measurements from five KeySpan plants' stacks, show that emissions rose 91 percent for sulfur dioxide, 64 percent for nitrous oxides and 42 percent for carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The KeySpan plants, which provide most of Long Island's electricity, are in Northport, Port Jefferson, Island Park, Glenwood Landing and Far Rockaway. LIPA has a contract to buy the power the plants produce, and it owns the transmission lines on the Island.</p>
        <p>In the process now under study, the plants would be upgraded, or repowered, using combined cycle technology, which captures waste heat to create steam to turn a second turbine, greatly increasing efficiency. The plants could burn oil or natural gas, but would likely use oil only as a backup.</p>
        <p>In separate interviews, two officials said repowering the old plants held great potential and would be a way to use existing plant sites, avoiding avoiding battles over new sites.</p>
        <p>''You are saying to a community that the plant will be basically the same size but it will be much more efficient and have lower emissions,'' said Richard M. Kessel, LIPA's chairman. ''For most communities, that's a home run.''</p>
        <p>David Manning, a KeySpan senior vice president, said, ''Repowering is not a cheap alternative, but it is environmentally sound and efficient.''</p>
        <p>But not all the T's have yet been crossed on the issue of repowering. Cost, financing, power purchase contracts, transmission requirements and future ownership of the plants are unresolved, both officials said. LIPA has an option to buy the KeySpan plants in 2005.</p>
        <p>Another problem is that during repowering, at least part of one plant would not be available in the summer, when power margins could be razor-thin.</p>
        <p>But repowering could have significant emissions benefits. An estimate by Gordian Raacke, the executive director of the Citizens Advisory Panel, an energy consumer watchdog, found that repowering KeySpan's 1,520-megawatt, four-unit Northport plant would cut sulfur dioxide emissions from 18,544 tons to 28 tons. Mr. Raacke was using figures reported in a state study three years ago, and the reduction assumes that natural gas, not oil, would be burned. Emissions of nitrous oxides would decline from 5,326 to 550 tons a year, while carbon dioxide emissions would decline from 7.3 to 3.2 tons a year.</p>
        <p>The proposed American National Power plant, which would begin operations in 2004, would burn only natural gas and would comply with air-quality regulations for new plants. ''We are meeting extremely stringent standards,'' said Guy Marchmont, the project manager. ''To a great extent we are paving the way for the next generation of projects.'' Still to be worked out is a power purchase agreement between the plant and LIPA.</p>
        <p>Proponents of repowering said that it would negate the need for new power plants. ''If you put that new technology in there, there is no reason to build more power plants on Long Island for years,'' said Todd Stebbins, the regional coordinator for the New York Public Interest Research Group.</p>
        <p>Community resistance to new plants can be fierce. KeySpan is facing heavy opposition from businesses and civic groups to plans for a 250-megawatt plant on Spagnoli Road in Melville.</p>
        <p>The future of that project was further clouded earlier this month when KeySpan informed LIPA, which had entered into a long-term contract to buy half the plant's power, that it needed more money to meet a higher-than-expected construction cost, now estimated at $275 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
