<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH PUTS TARIFFS OF AS MUCH AS 30% ON STEEL IMPORTS</title>
    <meta content="Y06STE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/06/business/06STEE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1373467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4DC1530F935A35750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH PUTS TARIFFS OF AS MUCH AS 30% ON STEEL IMPORTS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Puts Tariffs of as Much as 30% on Steel Imports</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush imposes tariffs of up to 30 percent on most types of steel imports for three years to give American producers time to consolidate and stem layoffs; unusually broad move is likely to boost prices by as much as 10 percent; exempts Mexico, Canada and developing nations; nations hardest hit are Japan, South Korea, China, Taiwan, Germany and Brazil; European nations and Japan plan challenge before World Trade Organization on grounds 'import surge' Bush cites as justification ended in 1998; imports have fallen 27.5 percent since 1998, but prices have also fallen sharply; Bush takes no action on bailout of up to $12 billion to cover pension and health care costs for retired workers from bankrupt steel companies; group representing companies that buy steel scores move, hailed by steel industry and its unions; table; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush took some of the broadest federal action in two decades to protect a major American industry today, imposing tariffs of up to 30 percent on most types of steel imported into the United States from Europe, Asia and South America. The tariffs will last three years, he said, to give American steel producers time to consolidate operations and stem layoffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's action is likely to send the price of steel up sharply, perhaps as much as 10 percent, a cost American consumers will ultimately bear in higher prices for autos, appliances and housing. The United States imports about a quarter of the steel it consumes, though Mr. Bush exempted steel made in Mexico, Canada and developing nations from the tariffs announced today. The nations hardest hit are Japan, South Korea, China, Taiwan, Germany and Brazil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking broad federal action, President Bush imposed tariffs on most types of steel imported into the United States from Europe, Asia and South America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush took some of the broadest federal action in two decades to protect a major American industry today, imposing tariffs of up to 30 percent on most types of steel imported into the United States from Europe, Asia and South America. The tariffs will last three years, he said, to give American steel producers time to consolidate operations and stem layoffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's action is likely to send the price of steel up sharply, perhaps as much as 10 percent, a cost American consumers will ultimately bear in higher prices for autos, appliances and housing. The United States imports about a quarter of the steel it consumes, though Mr. Bush exempted steel made in Mexico, Canada and developing nations from the tariffs announced today. The nations hardest hit are Japan, South Korea, China, Taiwan, Germany and Brazil.</p>
        <p>Within minutes of the White House announcement, America's European allies and Japan said they would almost certainly challenge the action before the World Trade Organization, setting the stage for a major trade fight with many of the same countries Mr. Bush is trying to hold together in the fractious coalition against terrorism.</p>
        <p>Their legal case, which could take years to litigate in Geneva, is likely to hinge on the fact that the ''import surge'' Mr. Bush declared as the justification for his action ended in 1998. Since then, foreign imports of steel to the United States have declined 27.5 percent, but the price of steel has also fallen sharply because of the simultaneous recessions in the United States and Japan, and a slowdown in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush defended his move in an appearance tonight with President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt. ''We're a free-trading nation, and in order to remain a free-trading nation, we must enforce law,'' he said. ''And that's exactly what I did. I decided that imports were severely affecting our industry, an important industry, in a negative impact, and, therefore, provide temporary relief so that the industry could restructure itself.'' [News analysis, Page C1.]</p>
        <p>But as indicated by the heated debates that have taken place inside the White House, the decision was hardly as easy as Mr. Bush made it sound today.</p>
        <p>There were strategic considerations: Mr. Bush's national security aides are concerned that relations with Europe and Asia have already been strained by Mr. Bush's rejection of the Kyoto protocol on global warming; his withdrawal from the 1972 Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty with Russia; and his description of Iraq, Iran and North Korea as an ''axis of evil.'' But in the end he decided that further damage to those ties was outweighed by the scope of the crisis in the steel industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said the president hoped to create ''breathing space'' for the industry to overhaul itself, and to force Europe and Asia to shut down excess producing capacity rather than putting the brunt of the plant closings on the United States. Critics of the approach said, however, that the industry had resisted change for decades and they doubted that these tariffs would raise prices enough for the sickest firms to stave off bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>The White House plan takes no action on a bailout of up to $12 billion to cover pension and health care costs for retired workers from bankrupt companies, an issue that now moves to Congress.</p>
        <p>The Emergency Committee for American Trade, a group representing companies that buy steel, warned this afternoon that Mr. Bush had done more harm than good to the American economy.</p>
        <p>''A 30 percent tariff won't solve the integrated steel industry's problems, but it will force other American manufacturers to move steel-intensive production overseas, close U.S. plants, and outsource U.S. parts and components in order to compete,'' it said in a statement.</p>
        <p>But the steel industry and unions representing steel workers, who had called for even higher tariffs, said they were largely satisfied with the president's action. ''This is protection in substance as well as appearance,'' Robert S. Miller, the chief executive of Bethlehem Steel, said in a telephone interview this afternoon. Bethlehem filed for bankruptcy protection on Sept. 24, and is seeking a number of joint venture partners to keep its steel production plants open.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Bush has never discussed the subject in political terms since becoming president, he must have been mindful of political commitments made during the 2000 presidential campaign, when he and his running mate, Dick Cheney, accused President Bill Clinton and Vice President Al Gore of failing to protect workers from low-priced imports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's chief political adviser, Karl Rove, sat in on the major meetings at the White House about how to deal with the steel industry's demands, and Mr. Rove met with leaders of the steel workers' unions. While officials said he never said so in the meetings, Mr. Rove and others in the White House know that the tariffs will have the greatest effects on steel producers in West Virginia, Pennsylvania and Ohio, all critical in the coming Congressional elections.</p>
        <p>One of the big winners today was Weirton Steel of West Virginia. Weirton officials praised Mr. Bush for putting 30 percent tariffs on tin sheet, one of its biggest products. The loser was South Korea, the largest exporter of the same type of steel.</p>
        <p>While economists can make general estimates about how the increase in tariffs will translate into higher prices for consumer goods, figuring out the real cost increase for, say, an individual automobile model is next to impossible. Car makers will scramble in the next few months to get their supplies from countries exempt from the tariffs.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers may move some production to Canada or Mexico, so that the steel they buy is not subject to tariffs. And because steel prices have been rising in recent months without the tariffs, it will be difficult for Mr. Bush's opponents to blame him for the increase in the price of a specific minivan, for example.</p>
        <p>Democrats today blamed Mr. Bush for doing too little, rather than too much. ''Last week the steel companies and the steel worker unions agreed that 40 percent was the minimum average tariff needed to stabilize the industry,'' Richard A. Gephardt, the Democratic leader, said in a statement today. He said he was ''disappointed'' that the tariffs average less than 30 percent.</p>
        <p>He also noted that Mr. Bush ''did nothing'' to help with the pensions and health care costs of retirees. But the White House said that action was up to Congress, and not within the president's powers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is an avowed free trader, and many members of his team -- including Lawrence Lindsey, who runs the National Economic Council, and Glenn Hubbard, the chairman of the council of economic advisers -- warned of the risks to both his free-trade credentials and the broader economy. In the past his trade representative, Robert B. Zoellick, has compared raising tariffs to raising taxes, and while White House officials sidestepped such comparisons today they admitted that the result would be greater costs to consumers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's decision was the biggest action to preserve an ailing American industry since Ronald Reagan forced several nations into ''voluntary'' restraints on their steel and auto exports in the mid-1980's. Those agreements are now illegal under W.T.O. rules. So this time Mr. Bush chose another route, invoking a provision that allows a temporary tariff ''safeguard'' for three years.</p>
        <p>While the White House made no mention of it, the order Mr. Bush signed actually imposes the highest tariffs only for one year; on flat rolled steel, for example, the 30 percent tariff goes into effect within 15 days, but drops to 24 percent next year, and 18 percent in 2004.</p>
        <p>It has other holes that importing nations will seek to exploit. Commerce Secretary Donald L. Evans -- Mr. Bush's former campaign chairman and a proponent of the tariff action -- said today that 80 developing nations would be exempted. Over the weekend, the chief executive of U.S. Steel, Thomas J. Usher, warned that many countries, particularly in Asia, would ship their steel to developing countries, relabel it, and send it on to the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also put the lowest tariffs on slab steel, an unfinished form of steel that is often used by smaller steel manufacturers to make their products. Mr. Bush's program will allow tariff-free imports of 5.4 million short tons, about equal to the imports in 2000, excluding slab steel from Canada and Mexico. That will be a boon to Russia, one of the largest producers of slab steel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
