<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Black and White Bird Turns Humans Green</title>
    <meta content="14SUN3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/14/opinion/14SUN3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1408165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Loons (Birds)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adirondack Mountains (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randolph, Eleanor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D81E30F937A25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Black and White Bird Turns Humans Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Black and White Bird Turns Humans Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR RANDOLPH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Randolph, Eleanor</byline>
      <dateline>ADIRONDACK STATE PARK, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleanor Randolph Editorial Observer column on public regard for common loon and resulting concern about mercury pollution of New York's Adirondack lakes that adversely affects birds (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some kinds of wildlife inspire more human support than others. Imperiled suckerfish, woodpeckers and red-legged frogs have managed to stall developments and spare wilderness around the country, but their advocates tend to be environmental lawyers, not ordinary nature lovers. The majestic loon, however, is another story.</p>
        <p>For people summering around the lakes of the northeastern United States and Canada, the large black and white loon is revered for its maniacal cry, its elegant look and its unfailing ability to sell any T-shirt or coffee mug emblazoned with its distinguished profile. So the news that loons are not doing so well in Adirondack State Park hits home, or in some cases, the second homes that stretch across much of this vast outback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The news that loons are not doing so well hits home, or in some cases, the second homes, in the Adirondacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some kinds of wildlife inspire more human support than others. Imperiled suckerfish, woodpeckers and red-legged frogs have managed to stall developments and spare wilderness around the country, but their advocates tend to be environmental lawyers, not ordinary nature lovers. The majestic loon, however, is another story.</p>
        <p>For people summering around the lakes of the northeastern United States and Canada, the large black and white loon is revered for its maniacal cry, its elegant look and its unfailing ability to sell any T-shirt or coffee mug emblazoned with its distinguished profile. So the news that loons are not doing so well in Adirondack State Park hits home, or in some cases, the second homes that stretch across much of this vast outback.</p>
        <p>For the last few years, a group of wildlife experts has been testing about 100 common loons in the Adirondacks to chart their whereabouts, their reproductive success and their general well-being. These experts go out at night and stun the big birds by shining lights into their flaming red eyes, then gently capture them for tagging, weighing and taking a few drops of blood. The results of three years of these tests were reported last month, and the news was not encouraging. A full 17 percent of the loons tested were at risk from mercury contamination. Farther east, the percentage is even higher.</p>
        <p>Mercury, once a convenient component of thermometers and barometers, is now recognized as a very unhealthy element for living things. Even in Lewis Carroll's day, 140 years ago, it was known that hat makers who were exposed to mercury for years on end had tremors and hallucinations -- a recognized hazard of the Mad Hatter's occupation.</p>
        <p>Loons have also been known to turn odd when overloaded with mercury from eating contaminated fish. In particular, chicks begin preening more than is usual even for the young. The affected babies can also stray too far from their regular perch on top of the mother loon, who provides her checkerboard featherbed for her young's protection. Such errant behavior can make it easy for loon predators like large fish or eagles to dine on these little balls of down, leaving fewer loons for future nocturnal vocalizing.</p>
        <p>Mercury is an especially difficult problem in some Adirondack lakes because the acidic water converts it into a more toxic form. There are a number of sources of toxic mercury in the Adirondacks, but being downwind of the Midwest's old power plants does not help. The smokestacks still spew sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxide and mercury into the atmosphere, which then scatters over lakes and forests in the Northeast and parts of Canada.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Bush administration announced plans to soften the Clean Air Act so utilities could upgrade their old plants without adding costly new antipollution equipment. The administration has also not shown signs of supporting an important acid rain bill, by Senator James Jeffords of Vermont, that would reduce emissions of airborne pollutants by 2008. The bill includes a salutary 90 percent cut in mercury emissions.</p>
        <p>Loon specialists like Dr. Nina Schoch of the Adirondack Cooperative Loon Program acknowledge that the acid rain and the mercury emissions affect a number of other birds in the northeastern lakes. But many people have a hard time getting excited about a contaminated duck.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing how attached people are to the loons,'' Dr. Schoch said. ''Protecting them sometimes becomes a way for people to begin caring more about the environment.''</p>
        <p>Question: Is there a nice lake at Camp David?</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
