<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Says Mixed Signals Have Eroded U.S. Status in the U.N.</title>
    <meta content="Y10REFO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/10/international/10REFO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1430661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council on Foreign Relations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Freedom House (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, Lee H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreier, David (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preston, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Security Council</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDE163AF933A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Says Mixed Signals Have Eroded U.S. Status in the U.N.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Panel Says Mixed Signals Have Eroded U.S. Status in the U.N.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA PRESTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Preston, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by bipartisan task force from Council on Foreign Relations and Freedom House says US has lost influence within UN because of years of ambivalence towards organization and should re-engage it forcefully to build coalition of democratic nations; its findings discussed; group was headed by California Rep David Dreier and former Indiana Democratic Rep Lee Hamilton (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States has lost influence within the United Nations because of years of ambivalence towards the organization and should re-engage it forcefully to build a coalition of democratic nations, says a report to be issued on Thursday by a bipartisan task force.</p>
        <p>As the Bush administration struggles to negotiate a resolution on Iraq through the Security Council, the group found that the United States has undermined its position in the world body by neglecting or sending mixed messages to the much larger constituency of countries active in the General Assembly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States has lost influence within the United Nations because of years of ambivalence towards the organization, says a report to be issued on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States has lost influence within the United Nations because of years of ambivalence towards the organization and should re-engage it forcefully to build a coalition of democratic nations, says a report to be issued on Thursday by a bipartisan task force.</p>
        <p>As the Bush administration struggles to negotiate a resolution on Iraq through the Security Council, the group found that the United States has undermined its position in the world body by neglecting or sending mixed messages to the much larger constituency of countries active in the General Assembly.</p>
        <p>''The United States is frequently outmaneuvered and overmatched at the U.N.,'' says the report, sponsored by the Council on Foreign Relations and Freedom House. The group was led by Rep. David Dreier, a California Republican, and Lee Hamilton, a former Democratic representative from Indiana.</p>
        <p>While many senior administration officials have been wary of the United Nations as a diplomatic sand trap that can only slow Washington down, the report advocates much deeper American involvement, including building up the United States mission and sending out American diplomats to lobby as if they were on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>''We should practice a little old-time politics,'' said Mr. Hamilton, a former chairman of the House Foreign Affairs Committee. ''We should be working the back rooms very hard to promote the democracy agenda.''</p>
        <p>Of the scores of proposals for changing the United Nations in the last decade, this is the first to focus on the behind-the-scenes influence of bloc politics. Since the end of the Cold War, most nations in the organization are now democracies, said Lee Feinstein, one of the group's directors. But the United Nations still does much of its business through five unwieldy regional groups and the Non-Aligned Movement, which ''continues to bind many democracies with highly repressive tyrannies and is an outdated obstacle'' to more efficient action, the report said.</p>
        <p>The United States could restore its reputation in the organization and win backing for its goals by forging a new alliance based on ''the effective promotion of democracy, human rights and counterterrorism.''</p>
        <p>Washington should press the General Assembly to adopt a resolution ensuring the ''right to multiparty democracy,'' the report says, and mobilize democracies to vote and work together across the traditional group boundaries.</p>
        <p>The report calls on the United States to pay its dues on time. During the 1990's, Washington's arrears became crippling to the organization and fueled resentment. Washington should also avoid long delays on appointments of American ambassadors and beef up the political section of the mission, the task force says.</p>
        <p>It recommends a more aggressive approach to the United Nations Human Rights Commission, where the United States lost its seat in 2001, then regained it a year later. The loss of the seat was ''a major setback to U.S. diplomacy,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The group also said that the United States should support the counterterrorism committee that is working to establish global guidelines to fight terrorism.</p>
        <p>The group said that the Bush administration's reluctance to sign on to international treaties, like an international criminal court and global warming, have been a ''sharp disappointment'' to many nations that rallied behind the United States in the wake of the Sept. 11 attacks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
