<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A History Told by Real Muckrakers; Digging Clues From the Slime of Long Island Sound</title>
    <meta content="24SOUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/24/nyregion/24SOUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <meta content="HUMAN NATURE: Traces in the Mud" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1514333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Human Nature"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DF1539F937A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A History Told by Real Muckrakers; Digging Clues From the Slime of Long Island Sound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A History Told by Real Muckrakers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eighth article in Human Nature series on evolving nature of Long Island Sound reports on how scientists analyse layers of muck and mud to try to understand effects of settlements along Sound's shores; natural and industrial pollution and their impact are recorded in sediment giving scientists picture of past and indication just how far Sound and marine life can recover; photo, map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 50 years ago in the water near Execution Rock, a speck of earth in Long Island Sound just east of the Bronx, an environmental crime unfolded. A ship bearing a load of polluted industrial waste -- coal, ash and mercury from any of a hundred factories around the Sound in those years -- lost or dumped its cargo. The evidence sank beneath the waves. The captain and crew moved on. Time forgot.</p>
        <p>Until now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team trying to reconstruct the last 1,000 years of the Long Island Sound's history has found a witness to an environmental crime of 50 years ago: the mud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About 50 years ago in the water near Execution Rock, a speck of earth in Long Island Sound just east of the Bronx, an environmental crime unfolded. A ship bearing a load of polluted industrial waste -- coal, ash and mercury from any of a hundred factories around the Sound in those years -- lost or dumped its cargo. The evidence sank beneath the waves. The captain and crew moved on. Time forgot.</p>
        <p>Until now.</p>
        <p>Scientists at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Conn., part of a research team that is trying to reconstruct the last 1,000 years or so of the Sound's history, say that they have found a long-silent witness: the mud.</p>
        <p>''Everything gets recorded by the sediment, and if it's there we will find it and try to build a story to explain it,'' said Johan C. Varekamp, a geochemist at Wesleyan who is working on the project with his wife and collaborator, Ellen Thomas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Varekamp and Dr. Thomas, a micropaleontologist who also teaches at Wesleyan, say they have no suspects in the Execution Rock spill, which they found entirely by chance this year in a core sample taken near the rock. In fairness, they add, it could have been an accident. The currents in the Sound, which stretches 110 miles to southern New England from the East River, are notoriously treacherous, especially in the western end. What the scientists do have is an unmistakable forensic fingerprint of the event, as though the Sound itself, victimized so many times over the centuries by human indifference or ignorance, had stored away the memory of the spill for those who would later find it.</p>
        <p>The pollution that might have seemed safely and anonymously dumped back then -- a dirty job with no one the wiser -- was perfectly preserved as a thick layer of lumpy black goo that cuts across the Wesleyan research team's excavated sediment core samples like a jagged scar.</p>
        <p>''You couldn't miss it,'' Dr. Thomas said. ''It leaped out at you.''</p>
        <p>The Sound's past is emerging as never before as scientists delve into the dark muck of history. But at the same time, so is the glimmering of its many possible futures as researchers learn just how deep the human-induced changes in the system's biology and chemistry really go.</p>
        <p>In a way, time itself has become a new environmental frontier on the Sound. With more people clustering near the coasts all over the world, unraveling the Sound's tangled past, researchers say, could provide important lessons because by fate and fluke of geography, it hit a lot of the important environmental milestones first -- through the waves of agriculture, industry, urbanization and everything after.</p>
        <p>Consider, for example, the humble ragweed. At a certain yucky point deep in the mud, the number of ragweed spores begins a sudden, sharp increase.</p>
        <p>What that signals, scientists say, is the arrival of the European colonists, who on the basis of the Sound's evidence, descended from their ships ready for some serious tree-cutting. Deforestation in Massachusetts, and later Connecticut and New York, gave the ragweed a new environmental niche, no longer shaded out by old growth canopy. It became the weed we know today, and gave the Sound's investigators a key point for their timeline: if the ragweed spores are up, it must be about 1640 to 1650.</p>
        <p>Scientists can also now tell when hat manufacturing took off in Connecticut, around the Housatonic and Still Rivers in Danbury, Conn. -- or at least when the environmental impact of the industry began hitting the Sound. Hatmakers used mercury nitrate to cure the animal pelts then considered de rigueur for headwear, and the poisonous mercury vapors caused nerve damage and dementia -- thus one explanation for the phrase, ''mad as a hatter.'' It's still a poison today, reflected in the medical advice that pregnant women or women thinking about becoming pregnant should limit their consumption of some kinds of fish.</p>
        <p>But the mercury plume that flowed down the Housatonic into the Sound also provides another time signature. It emerges in the mud about 1820. Not until 1970, long after beaver hats faded from fashion, do mercury levels in the sediment drop significantly. That's when the Federal Clean Air Act began reducing airborne pollutants.</p>
        <p>Even a disease, chestnut blight, gets its moment in the mud. It first struck the eastern United States in 1910, and so the sudden disappearance of chestnut pollen means, at least as far as the Sound is concerned, that William Howard Taft is in the White House and the Titanic is still in dry dock, being readied for its glorious maiden voyage to New York.</p>
        <p>''What you can see from a variety of indicators is that before European colonization, there was relatively little variability on the Sound -- for over 1,000 years it was largely stable,'' said Mark A. Altabet, a professor in the school of marine science and technology the University of Massachusetts at Dartmouth, who is also working on the reconstruction project. ''But then beginning in the early 1600's, some things began to change. From clearing of the land, you see more sediments; then in the 1800's, you see the first impacts of early industrialization.''</p>
        <p>But scientists are also using new research efforts in an effort to peer forward, to glimpse what the Sound might yet become.</p>
        <p>This month, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency funded what officials say was the first major diversity survey on the Sound, as scientists tried to come up with a base number of species, both native and introduced invaders. The numbers are still being counted but the goal, researchers say, is to start a new time clock -- what species are in the Sound now, with a periodic checkup to see how the environment evolves.</p>
        <p>''It gives us a basis from which to work, a starting place -- then you can follow the changes,'' said Dr. Judith Pederson, a marine ecologist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology's sea grant program and one of the leaders of the study.</p>
        <p>In many important respects, reconstructing the Sound's past revolves around a single year: 1850.</p>
        <p>The Wesleyan-led team has firmly concluded, for example, that severely diminished oxygen levels in the Sound, which can harm all sorts of marine life -- and which local and state governments have committed billions of dollars to fix through improved sewage treatment -- began to appear only in the mid-19th century, as population levels and industry began growing rapidly in and around New York City. That conclusion, which Dr. Varekamp is now preparing to publish in a scientific paper, is very likely to give important ammunition to environmentalists and political leaders who advocate sticking to the Sound's cleanup plan despite high costs and battered government budgets.</p>
        <p>Other scientists say the more they learn about the Sound's long and winding road, the more complicated the questions are about what might, or should, come next. The water is cleaner now, and will likely be even cleaner over time, they say. But what the Sound will become as a result, and what vision environmental managers should shoot for, is another question altogether.</p>
        <p>Most ecologists agree that the Sound cannot be restored to what it was in the pre-European past. The changes in shoreline alone, with the loss of most marshlands where many small creatures breed or hide, preclude that. So what should it be? What is the optimum natural state in a system that has been overwhelmingly and permanently transformed by human presence?</p>
        <p>''There's a new equilibrium now,'' said Gerard M. Capriulo, a professor of biology at Saint Mary's College of California in Moraga. ''The Sound is a different place than it was, and once you have a new equilibrium, you can't really predict it too well.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Capriulo recently completed a three-year study of how changes in the Sound's micro-organisms are spiraling through the food chain, and one of his main conclusions is that the Sound is becoming more hospitable to a creature hardly anyone loves -- the jellyfish -- and less homey to the fin fish of the past. The problem, he argued in a recently published paper, might not be so easy to fix, either.</p>
        <p>''There are tugs in all sorts of directions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Research into the Sound's past is also raising questions about what might not be possible to fix. The year 1850, for example -- Dr. Varekamp's dividing line for the beginning of the Sound's oxygen troubles -- is also important for another reason: climate change. Temperatures began climbing all over the world at about that same time, caused, most scientists say, by heat-trapping gasses produced by increased burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Many researchers on the Sound now say that they think overly warm water played an important role in the huge die-off of the Sound's lobsters in 1999. And warmer temperatures have also been shown to compound the problems of low oxygen that the sewage treatment improvements around the Sound are supposed to resolve.</p>
        <p>What might be called the politics of mud are now in play, too. Environmentalists, residents and politicians have been debating for months about a proposed natural gas pipeline under the Sound that runs to Long Island from Connecticut. Dr. Varekamp said his research, and the knowledge of what could be disturbed and released back into the water by a pipe-laying excavation, led him to speak out against the project at a public hearing this summer. The Sound's environmental ghosts, he and Dr. Thomas both say, should be left where they lay.</p>
        <p>''They're kind of out of reach now,'' Dr. Thomas said. ''Unless somebody disturbs them.''</p>
        <p>Human Nature</p>
        <p>Over many years of settlement, Long Island Sound has been a breadbasket and a dumping ground, a private playground for the wealthy and a symbol of environmental despair.</p>
        <p>But when people reached for a new definition -- a repaired, restored, managed Sound -- nature did not respond according to the rule book.</p>
        <p>For every push to achieve a certain end, the whorls of the ecosystem have pushed right back, often in unexpected ways.</p>
        <p>This is the eighth article of a summer-long series on the evolving nature of Long Island Sound. Part 9 will look for signs of one community's new relationship with the water, an emerging identity for the 21st century. But where some see hope, others say the old problems are only being painted over.</p>
        <p>Additional materials, including a preview of the last part of the series, are online at nytimes.com/lisound.</p>
        <p>Human Nature</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
