<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="04FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1540345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DC173DF937A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Court Convicts 3 In Rwandan Genocide  An international court convicted three Rwandans who ran a newspaper and a radio station of genocide for fostering a killing spree by machete-wielding gangs who killed about 800,000 Rwandans.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Court Convicts 3 In Rwandan Genocide  An international court convicted three Rwandans who ran a newspaper and a radio station of genocide for fostering a killing spree by machete-wielding gangs who killed about 800,000 Rwandans.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraqi Militia Planned  The American-led administration in Iraq has agreed with leaders of the country's top political parties to create a militia made up of troops chosen in equal numbers by the parties.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Iraqi census officials devised a plan to count the population next summer and prepare a voter roll for elections in September. But American officials say they rejected the idea, and the Iraqi Governing Council members say they never saw the plan.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Women in Indian Politics  Although India has produced strong female leaders, women still find themselves largely shut out of politics. But Hindu nationalists are harnessing the power of women -- among the candidates running for office in state elections this week is Uma Bharti, a Hindu woman.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Kyoto Accord May Not Matter  Experts on climate and diplomacy say the fate of the Kyoto Protocol itself is rapidly becoming less important than the longer-term processes it set in motion.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Snags Ahead for Europe's Unity  While the members of the European Union are looking forward to ever higher levels of integration, a series of crises have analysts wondering if unity can work at all.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Chinese Officers Warn Taiwan  Chinese military officers said China would consider a popular vote on Taiwan's political status -- which a faction of Taiwan's governing party recently urged -- as a cause for war.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Mayoral Race in Moscow  In Moscow, a billionaire businessman is waging a come-from-behind campaign for mayor against a popular incumbent.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A22-37</p>
        <p>Flurry of Political Ads Saturates Iowa Airwaves  The four major Democratic candidates competing in Iowa have run at least 4,500 television spots in Des Moines alone, which underscores the increasing belief that Iowa may be more critical than in the past in determining who ends up with the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Archbishop's House to be Sold  The Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Boston said that to help pay for an $85 million settlement to compensate hundreds of victims of sex abuse, it would sell the archbishop's residence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush to Rescind Steel Tariffs  The Bush administration plans to announce that it will rescind tariffs it imposed on imported steel, saying the temporary trade protection has allowed American steel makers to get themselves in shape.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Coroner Rules on Ohio Beating  Nathaniel Jones, a black man whose death in police custody has incited new racial tensions in Cincinnati, died primarily because of his struggle with police, a coroner said.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Shooter Has Ohio on Edge  Though officials are not using the word sniper, they announced that ballistics tests showed that four of 12 shots that have become the source of deep anxiety across central Ohio, came from the same gun.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Clues Sought in Fire Mockup  Federal investigators studied a burning mockup of the Rhode Island nightclub where 100 people were killed last February, intending not to find fault but to understand the technical causes behind the disaster.</p>
        <p>A30</p>
        <p>Panel Ponders 9/11 Suspect  A panel of federal appeals judges voiced uncertainty on whether Zacarias Moussaoui could receive a fair trial if the Bush administration continued to deny him access to captured terrorists whose testimony might bolster his defense.</p>
        <p>A36</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Panel Calls for New Rules For Electing Judges  An expert panel appointed by New York State's chief judge called for significant changes in the way judges across the state are elected, and proposed that lawyers be required to disclose in court any campaign contributions they have made to judges presiding over their cases.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>N.Y.U. Bans Video Project  New York University officials halted a student project that would have involved videotaping actors having sex, and said they would issue new guidelines for student films.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Vouchers Deemed Unlawful  A Denver judge struck down Colorado's new school voucher law, ruling that it violated the state constitution by stripping local school boards of their control over education.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH  New Cancer Drug Effective  In a study comparing two drugs designed to prevent a recurrence of breast cancer, women who switched from the standard drug tamoxifen to a newer type of treatment fared better than those who continued to take tamoxifen.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Safety Upgrade for S.U.V.'s  Fifteen automakers agreed to make design changes to S.U.V.'s and pickups sold in the United States so they are less dangerous to the occupants of passenger cars.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Boeing Far Behind Schedule  The Boeing Company is running more than a year behind schedule and billions of dollars over cost on a program to build reconnaissance satellites for the government.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>S.E.C. Proposes Regulations  The Securities and Exchange Commission proposed a new set of mutual fund regulations and announced an ambitious schedule to issue additional fund-trading rules.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A38-39</p>
        <p>Editorials: Kyoto Protocol in peril; a harder road to Irish peace; fixing Albany: how hard is it to control the vendors?</p>
        <p>Column: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Crossword</p>
        <p>E10  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
