<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ways to Save the Planet and Get Healthy, Too</title>
    <meta content="04BROD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/04/health/04BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1532592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Langholz, Jeffrey (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Kelly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">You Can Prevent Global Warming (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFD61130F937A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ways to Save the Planet and Get Healthy, Too</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ways to Save the Planet and Get Healthy, Too</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health column discusses book You Can Prevent Global Warming (and Save Money!) by Dr Jeffrey Langholz and Kelly Turner; details simple ways people can reduce greenhouse gas emissions through changes in life style; encourages recycling and other measures that could stave off global warming and its effects; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As winter weather approaches and November winds start to bite, you might be tempted to think that global warming is a myth. But you would be very wrong.</p>
        <p>The meteorological extremes of recent years -- sudden temperature changes, droughts, floods, heat waves -- may or may not be a result of an earth that is gradually warming. But it is warming, and human activities that burn fossil fuels are to blame for at least part of the increase, and perhaps most of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Relying more on human energy and less on gas-powered motor vehicles can improve health as well as the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As winter weather approaches and November winds start to bite, you might be tempted to think that global warming is a myth. But you would be very wrong.</p>
        <p>The meteorological extremes of recent years -- sudden temperature changes, droughts, floods, heat waves -- may or may not be a result of an earth that is gradually warming. But it is warming, and human activities that burn fossil fuels are to blame for at least part of the increase, and perhaps most of it.</p>
        <p>When coal, oil and gas burn, they release so-called greenhouse gases, which trap the sun's heat in the earth's atmosphere. You may also think that major industries are the primary culprits and that consequently there is little that you can do to alleviate the problem. Again, you would be wrong.</p>
        <p>A handy book by an environmental policy specialist offers 51 easy ways, many of them money saving, that all of us can adopt to minimize the release of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Most changes can be made with little compromise to the quality of modern life. In fact, they can often improve living conditions and some, like relying more on human energy and less on gas-powered motor vehicles, can improve health as well.</p>
        <p>The book, aptly titled ''You Can Prevent Global Warming (and Save Money!),'' was written by Dr. Jeffrey Langholz, at the Monterey Institute of International Studies in California, and Kelly Turner, an environmental writer. It was published this year (Andrews McMeel Publishing of Kansas City, Mo., $10.95).</p>
        <p>Cutting Back Painlessly</p>
        <p>Of the 11 greenhouse gases, one, carbon dioxide, the primary gas formed when organic matter burns, accounts for more than half the world's global warming problem. For example, a typical passenger car emits 12,000 pounds of it a year and a coal-burning power plant releases about 3 billion pounds. A second greenhouse gas, methane, is rarer but 23 times as potent in terms of global warming.</p>
        <p>HOME ENERGY -- The way you light, heat and cool your home, how you prepare and store your food and even the way you use water can have a major effect on energy savings. Switching from incandescent light bulbs to long-lasting compact fluorescent bulbs, using dimmer switches and motion sensors and turning off lights when you leave a room can greatly reduce your electrical usage and costs.</p>
        <p>Do not overchill. Keep your refrigerator at 37 to 40 degrees and the freezer at zero to 5 degrees. Turning up the temperature of every refrigerator in America by one degree would keep three million tons of carbon dioxide from entering the atmosphere each year. Discard that old spare inefficient refrigerator and save $150 a year.</p>
        <p>Show the same restraint with air-conditioning when summer returns: one degree warmer and 5.5 million tons of CO2  would be kept from the atmosphere. Rely more on cooling techniques that guzzle less energy like ceiling or window fans, evaporative coolers and dehumidifiers.</p>
        <p>Close drapes, blinds or shutters on sunny windows or install awnings or solar window screens. Ventilate and better insulate the attic and plug air leaks around windows and doors. These steps will also reduce the wasted heat in cool months.</p>
        <p>Insulate the floors above unheated basements and crawl spaces. With a greater initial investment, you can also save on cooling and heating and reduce greenhouse gases by replacing old windows, furnaces and air-conditioners. The best windows, those with low-emissivity (low-E) coatings, which restrict heat transfer, insulate five times as well as single-paned windows, Dr. Langholz and Ms. Turner report.</p>
        <p>Landscaping, too, can help you save on energy costs. A windbreak of evergreens on the north side of a house can cut heating bills by a third. And you can cut air-conditioning costs in half by plantings (bushes, high-canopy trees, vines on trellises) and wooden screens that shade the roof and sunniest walls of the house and the air-conditioners.</p>
        <p>Trees, as the authors point out, are ''nature's air-conditioners.'' In addition to providing shade, they actually cool the surrounding air by about nine degrees when their water evaporates.</p>
        <p>Of course, you do not want to defeat the purpose by plantings that use more energy than they save. Grass, for example, needs more water and maintenance than anything else you might plant. It also has to be mowed, and mowing usually requires gasoline. A rechargeable electric mower or, better yet, an old-fashioned push mower that uses your energy is far better.</p>
        <p>Consider your climate: temperate-zone plantings in the desert are both extremely wasteful and costly to the environment. To keep from wasting water, sprinklers should be fitted with automatic rain sensors and directed only at plants, not sidewalks and driveways.</p>
        <p>ENERGY-WISE TRAVEL -- Americans who can afford it tend to be highly independent and self-indulgent. Note the number of gas-guzzling S.U.V.'s on the road today, and the number of cars during rush hour that carry only the driver.</p>
        <p>Cars account for 21 percent of the world's global warming emissions. Avoid rapid accelerations and idling, keep tires properly inflated and slow down -- the faster you drive above 55 miles an hour, the more gas is used per mile. When you are ready for a new car, consider an energy-saving gas-electric hybrid, and check the fuel efficiency before you buy.</p>
        <p>Take public transportation or use a carpool whenever possible. Also consider telecommuting one day a week or more. Combine errands to reduce the number of trips and, whenever possible, shop, bank and pay bills online.</p>
        <p>Better yet, use your own power: your feet, a bicycle or person-powered scooter for trips of a mile or so. This can eliminate about one-fourth of all automotive trips.</p>
        <p>LOW-ENERGY DIET -- You can save the earth and people on it and improve your health by changing how you eat and dispose of waste. Beef cattle are the leading producers of methane (after termites), followed by sheep and pigs. Better for your health, and the earth's, is to eat more chicken and fish. Still better, eat fewer animal foods and more plant foods, especially those organically grown, a process that means fewer energy-consuming pesticides are used.</p>
        <p>Dr. Langholz and Ms. Turner note that ''the average meal travels 1,200 miles by truck, ship and/or plane to reach your dining room table.'' To reduce the energy costs of carrying foods, eat more locally grown products. Shop at farmers' markets. If possible, plant your own organic vegetable garden.</p>
        <p>Recycling More</p>
        <p>Finally, learn all you can about recycling and reusing materials. Compost all vegetable waste, including lawn trimmings and leaves, and use the resulting soil for planting. Reuse shopping bags and your own cloth bags for groceries.</p>
        <p>PACKAGING -- Buy products with the least packing and nonperishable items in bulk to save on packaging. And stop junk mail. The Direct Marketing Association's Web site can help you get off mass mailing lists for five years, for $5. It is www.thedma.org/cgi/offmailinglistdave.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
