<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="08DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1487161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDD163FF93BA35756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suit Accuses EarthLink Of Violating 2 Patents  A Silicon Valley start-up sued EarthLink, the big Internet service provider, contending that EarthLink's latest technology to block unwanted e-mail marketing, or spam, violates two of its patents.</p>
        <p>The plaintiff, MailBlocks, was granted the patents for its method of verifying senders, a type of technology known as ''challenge response.'' MailBlocks charges users $9.95 a year for the service. EarthLink is offering its customers a free challenge-response system at the end of the month. [Page C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suit Accuses EarthLink Of Violating 2 Patents  A Silicon Valley start-up sued EarthLink, the big Internet service provider, contending that EarthLink's latest technology to block unwanted e-mail marketing, or spam, violates two of its patents.</p>
        <p>The plaintiff, MailBlocks, was granted the patents for its method of verifying senders, a type of technology known as ''challenge response.'' MailBlocks charges users $9.95 a year for the service. EarthLink is offering its customers a free challenge-response system at the end of the month. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>Senators Question Wall St. Deal  Senior senators questioned whether the $1.4 billion Wall Street settlement would change attitudes at the top of the biggest brokerage firms, while regulators defended the agreement as a historic move toward reform. ''Firms are not contrite and simply consider the fines and penalties as a means to make a problem go away,'' said Richard C. Shelby, above, Republican of Alabama, at a Senate Banking Committee hearing. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors are considering revoking the bail of a former stockbroker who helped them with a sprawling investigation into organized crime on Wall Street because they fear for his safety. Market Place. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Renewed settlement talks between Morgan Stanley and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission to resolve a sex-bias case have collapsed. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Europe Seeks to Test Chemicals  Europe announced a proposal that would require manufacturers of industrial chemicals to test their products before they can be used, a change the Bush administration said could threaten the $20 billion in chemicals the United States exports to Europe each year. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Interpublic Appoints a Top Officer  Christopher J. Coughlin, a pharmaceutical executive with extensive financial credentials but no experience at an advertising agency was named as the chief operating officer of the struggling Interpublic Group of Companies. Advertising. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Suit Filed Against ChevronTexaco  A group of American lawyers representing indigenous people in Ecuador filed a $1 billion lawsuit against ChevronTexaco, asserting that it dumped toxic wastewater into open pits, estuaries and rivers from 1971-1992. Chevron denies any wrongdoing. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Drop a Bit on Profit Taking  Stocks fell as investors cashed in profits from a recent rally. The Dow Jones industrial average closed down 27.73 points, or 0.3 percent, to 8,560.63. The Nasdaq composite index fell 16.95 points, or 1.1 percent, to 1,506.76. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index declined 4.77 points, or 0.5 percent, to 929.62. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Wholesale sales rose in February, while consumer borrowing slowed in March. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Electronic Data Swings to Loss  Electronic Data Systems reported a first-quarter net loss of $126 million, or 26 cents a share, stemming from a $334 million pretax loss from a military contract. That is in contrast to net income of $354 million, or 72 cents a share, during the period a year earlier. Net revenue inched up 1.9 percent, to $5.37 billion. [C4.]</p>
        <p>68% Drop in Volkswagen Earnings  Volkswagen said first-quarter earnings tumbled 68 percent. The strength of the euro and costs to develop new models took a toll. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Judge Unlocks Scrushy's Assets  A federal judge lifted a freeze on the assets of Richard M. Scrushy, the former chief executive of HealthSouth, denying a government motion in advance of a trial for fraud. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A Market Approach to Politics  What are the consequences of government decisions involving, say, global warming or dividend tax cuts? By one theory, financial markets could be enlisted to sort out the answers. Hal R. Varian: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
