<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Adirondacks, the Road's the Thing</title>
    <meta content="03TRIP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/03/travel/escapes/03TRIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="DAY TRIP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adirondack Park</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Johnstown (Ny)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Malone (Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mountains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mountains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Adirondack Park</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DB173CF930A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Adirondacks, the Road's the Thing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Adirondacks, the Roads the Thing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on day trip along Route 30 through Adirondack Park between Johnstown and Malone, NY; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RIVERS are not improved by the presence of cars along their banks, of course, but roads are almost always made better by close association with flowing water. The southern end of Route 30 heading north out of Johnstown, N.Y., roughly 35 miles northwest of Albany, is no exception. The periodic views of the Sacandaga slipping over its rocky bottom, riffling over ledges or curving away mysteriously into the autumn canopy are lovely in the extreme.</p>
        <p>But it's more than just scenery that rivers bring to byways. Water naturally finds the path of least resistance out of the high country, and the road beside it seems to glean a bit of natural credibility from its neighbor -- a sort of highway feng shui. Rivers, after all, have been highways for as long as people have traveled. In some primordial past, when ancestral protohumans first dropped out of the trees, it seems likely that they followed a river out of the woods and onto the plains. Perhaps that is why following a river out of the sprawl and into the woods has a nostalgic quality, even if you're not sure what lies at the headwaters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Route 30 in Upstate New York winds through 130 miles of national parkland, following the flow of water through the Adirondacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RIVERS are not improved by the presence of cars along their banks, of course, but roads are almost always made better by close association with flowing water. The southern end of Route 30 heading north out of Johnstown, N.Y., roughly 35 miles northwest of Albany, is no exception. The periodic views of the Sacandaga slipping over its rocky bottom, riffling over ledges or curving away mysteriously into the autumn canopy are lovely in the extreme.</p>
        <p>But it's more than just scenery that rivers bring to byways. Water naturally finds the path of least resistance out of the high country, and the road beside it seems to glean a bit of natural credibility from its neighbor -- a sort of highway feng shui. Rivers, after all, have been highways for as long as people have traveled. In some primordial past, when ancestral protohumans first dropped out of the trees, it seems likely that they followed a river out of the woods and onto the plains. Perhaps that is why following a river out of the sprawl and into the woods has a nostalgic quality, even if you're not sure what lies at the headwaters.</p>
        <p>No matter how many times you drive it, Route 30 ends up being a surprisingly long road. As the crow flies, the distance from Johnstown, a post-industrial town of a certain age, where Route 30 enters the Adirondack Park, to Malone, where it exits, is only about 130 miles. But nowhere along its course does the road stay either straight or level for more than a few hundred yards. The park it bisects is larger than Massachusetts and contains the greatest collection of protected wilderness areas in the East. The route through it could be driven in a single long day, but it's a road worth savoring over a weekend or more.</p>
        <p>In the hamlet of Speculator, about 35 miles into the trip, the main branch of the Sacandaga River all but ends in a series of lakes and ponds, but Route 30 continues north toward Indian Lake and the heart of the Adirondack lake country. Like most of the towns in the park, Indian Lake is not much of a destination in its own right. Compared with the tidily painted 18th-century villages of Vermont, with their cheerful stores and well-groomed commons, Adirondack hamlets tend to be a bit scruffy at the edges as befits their origins as 19th-century wilderness outposts and logging camps.</p>
        <p>In Indian Lake, for instance, the most exciting thing you will be able to buy is a trail map or a ticket to ride a raft down the roaring waters of the Hudson River gorge (early April through Columbus Day).</p>
        <p>The morning I was there, I couldn't rent a kayak of the sort that would allow me to tag along with rafts in a suitably macho fashion, so I elected to continue on to the next town north, Blue Mountain Lake, stopping for a walk toward the Rock River along a snowmobile path that starts just opposite the short, sweet trail up Sawyer Mountain. Snowmobile trails can have a lovely forgotten-road quality in snowless months, though they can have mountain bikers, too. This one was grassy, rambling and wide enough for two to walk abreast and continue talking, but its main appeal was that I had not planned to stop there to take a walk.</p>
        <p>A pilgrimage up Blue Mountain -- on a trail worn to bedrock by generations of your predecessors -- to see a view marred by communications towers but still extraordinary is always in order before leaving town. It's the mountain you had glimpses of on your way into Blue Mountain Lake, and it's near the center of your journey. The trailhead is well-marked and just past the not-to-be-skipped Adirondack Museum, open from May to mid-October. But be prepared to give yourself a few hours and bottles of water; the mountain is not one of the park's tallest, at only 3,759 feet, but it's a steep trail that doesn't waste much time with switchbacks or other lung-saving dalliances. Worth it, though, to see lake after lake arranged below you in every direction, and off to the east the great range of the High Peaks.</p>
        <p>Some year-rounders complain, as they have for more than a century, that if it weren't for the park's regulations the towns along Route 30 could become rich and prosperous centers of leisure and industry. But the spartan nature of the hamlets is more than fine with most Adirondack lovers, who know the park isn't about town life anyway, but about picking up a few supplies and heading off to camp, as in the verb meaning to sleep in a tent, or to camp, as in the noun meaning a rustic pleasure palace on the shores of some crystal lake.</p>
        <p>When you are in the car, the uninspired nature of the hamlets has the effect of focusing the mind on the beauty of the drive between them. This makes sense: if you are on a road to nowhere, the road is the thing. At dawn or dusk, if you don't become stuck tailgating the wrong recreational vehicle, the rising, falling, curving glide of Route 30 through the central Adirondacks can feel birdlike in its freedom. It's almost enough fun to make you momentarily forget global warming. Almost.</p>
        <p>No matter how beautiful Route 30 is, though, a road trip through the Adirondacks is a compromised notion if it stays on the road. It's an off-road place by definition, and no matter what the advertisers (or snowmobilers) tell you, if you have to start it with a key, you are not off-road.</p>
        <p>There are countless opportunities. If the park were a great brain, Route 30 would be that line that separates the left lobe from the right. As you drive north, the high peaks and other tall mountains are on your right, which seems appropriate as climbing is usually a thoroughly right-handed rational endeavor, with the hardened mountaineers endlessly counting the summits they have conquered, and the novices huffing to the top of Marcy by sheer conscious will.</p>
        <p>On your left are the lakes, to which people return year after year as if following some instinctual pattern. There they engage in extended gazing at twinkling sunlight on the water, in fishing, in playing croquet and in other semiconscious activities. You can go either way from Route 30, or both ways.</p>
        <p>It's a great metaphor, it seems, because you need both the left and right brain to be human, just as the park needs both lakes and mountains. Plus, when you get all the way to Malone and turn around, on the way home, going south past the lakes and mountains and down the Sacandaga River, it's all reversed.</p>
        <p>DAY TRIP Paul Schneider is the author of ''The Adirondacks: A History of America's First Wilderness'' (Henry Holt, 1998).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Schneider is the author of ''The Adirondacks: A History of America's First Wilderness'' (Henry Holt, 1998).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
