<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan Gives Farmers a Role in Fighting Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="25CARB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/25/science/earth/25CARB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1538121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kansas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Defense</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Pat (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kansas</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E7DE1E3BF936A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan Gives Farmers a Role in Fighting Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Plan Gives Farmers a Role in Fighting Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>MANHATTAN, Kan.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sequestration, process of catching and holding carbon, is focus of alliance between Kansas Republican Senator Pat Roberts and Environmental Defense; pairing favors system of trading carbon credits among farmers while capping national carbon emissions in effort to combat global warming; allows for farmers to benefit from selling above ground crops and carbon below ground; moving to no-till farming is primary change which would help replenish soil and trap potentially harmful carbon gases from effecting environment; critics say trading in carbon credits would allow industries to continue or increase harmful environmental practices; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an unlikely alliance, Kansas Republicans and the advocacy group Environmental Defense are supporting an effort here that seeks to use agriculture as a weapon against global warming.</p>
        <p>While the Bush administration and some Republican lawmakers have expressed skepticism about human causes of global warming, Senator Pat Roberts, a Kansas Republican and an ardent supporter of President Bush, has helped Kansas State University win part of a $15 million grant for a group of institutions to study whether a form of farming called ''conservation tillage'' can really help combat the effects of global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an unlikely alliance, Kansas Republicans and an environmental advocacy group are both seeking to use agriculture as a weapon against global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an unlikely alliance, Kansas Republicans and the advocacy group Environmental Defense are supporting an effort here that seeks to use agriculture as a weapon against global warming.</p>
        <p>While the Bush administration and some Republican lawmakers have expressed skepticism about human causes of global warming, Senator Pat Roberts, a Kansas Republican and an ardent supporter of President Bush, has helped Kansas State University win part of a $15 million grant for a group of institutions to study whether a form of farming called ''conservation tillage'' can really help combat the effects of global warming.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Roberts said he saw evidence of global warming for himself in 1998, when he was part of a Congressional delegation that visited the South Pole.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Roberts and Environmental Defense, the group best known for fighting on behalf of wetlands and threatened species, like the red-legged frog, speculate that if farmers change the way they farm their land, they can pull carbon out of the atmosphere and help mitigate the effects of global warming, and get paid for doing so.</p>
        <p>There are already proposals to trade carbon credits like hog or cattle futures.</p>
        <p>Some big corporations operating in countries that signed the international climate treaty known as the Kyoto Protocol are planning to use the carbon credit system that the protocol established, if the protocol takes effect. They intend to pay farmers in participating countries for carbon credits while they search for other ways to cut their carbon emissions. President Bush has rejected the Kyoto agreement. Congress is now considering a system that will cap national carbon emissions and allow the trading of carbon credits among farmers.</p>
        <p>''This is an enormous opportunity for farmers,'' said Richard Sandor, who helped pioneer Chicago futures trading in the 1970's and now leads the Chicago Climate Exchange, the start-up venture that will soon begin trading the rights to emit gases associated with global warming. ''They can now grow two crops: one above the ground -- food; and one below ground -- carbon.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts wants the federal government to offer incentives to farmers who help improve the environment and replenish the soil with much-needed carbon.</p>
        <p>''It's simple: carbon in the air -- bad; carbon in the soil -- good,'' Mr. Roberts said recently in a telephone interview. ''We've got to get more out of the air and into the soil.''</p>
        <p>Catching and holding carbon is called sequestration. It keeps the carbon from being incorporated into carbon dioxide or other greenhouse gases that contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>In agriculture, sequestration involves using an array of land management techniques, like no-till farming, in which tractors do not plow the land before planting, that improve the soil and that allow plants to better absorb carbon from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>About 10 percent of Kansas farmers already practice no-till farming (largely because of the soil benefits), but experts say that this technique and some others, like the new forms of crop rotation and the use of ''cover crops'' during the winter, could help alter the environmental landscape.</p>
        <p>One way to reduce carbon in the atmosphere is to cut emissions from cars and power plants. Using agriculture to pull carbon from the atmosphere is an alternative.</p>
        <p>''It's estimated that American agriculture can offset about 20 percent of carbon emissions in the U.S.,'' said Dr. Charles Rice, a professor of soil microbiology at Kansas State, which is part of a consortium of universities studying carbon sequestration. ''If we had to switch from coal and oil to hydrogen immediately, we couldn't do it. It's not economically or technologically feasible.''</p>
        <p>There are, of course, some scientists and environmental groups, like Greenpeace, that are critical of carbon sequestration. They favor sticking to stricter controls on power plant and industrial carbon emissions as a way to combat global warming. They say land management techniques may let heavy industries off the hook and prevent them from curbing emissions.</p>
        <p>Other experts doubt that trustworthy ways can be found to measure how many tons of carbon are banked, and thus how many credits a farmer may earn.</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of permanence, some say. What if a farmer gets credits that are sold to a utility, and then the soil is mismanaged and carbon lost?</p>
        <p>But scientists and environmental experts say whether or not heavy industry curbs emissions, carbon sequestration is a powerful tool in the effort to improve degraded soils and the combat global warming.</p>
        <p>''We just see this as a tremendous opportunity for farmers and the environment,'' said Melissa Carey, a climate change policy expert at Environmental Defense. ''You can get atmospheric benefits, water quality, soil quality, local air quality benefits. That's a pretty attractive package.''</p>
        <p>In pushing the benefits of conservation tillage, and the work being done at Kansas State, Environmental Defense has also scored some big political points: an alliance that means that a prominent Republican is involved in global warming issues.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Senator Roberts is leading a spirited push here in Kansas, a state dominated by agriculture.</p>
        <p>''The Kansas prairie is a great big carbon sponge,'' Mr. Roberts said. ''If you pay the farmers to maintain these conservation projects, you'd be able to clean up the environment.''</p>
        <p>To reap these benefits, however, farmers will have to change the way they farm the land.</p>
        <p>One of the most significant changes would be moving to no-till farming. Soil experts say plowing the soil releases carbon stored underground, it degrades the soil and contributes to soil erosion and other problems.</p>
        <p>''Tillage is one of the worst things you can do to the soil,'' said Dr. Rice at Kansas State. ''Spraying the soil with a chemical is often less harmful.''</p>
        <p>By not tilling the soil, and allowing plant life and natural debris to decompose, agricultural experts say, the soil will strengthen and more readily absorb carbon from the atmosphere through plant photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>Researchers say that for centuries farmers have depleted soils by constant plowing, typically to kill weeds.</p>
        <p>By some estimates, about 50 percent of the carbon stored under agricultural lands has been lost over the last 200 years because of plowing and turning over the soils.</p>
        <p>Pulling that carbon back into the soil, and keeping it trapped there by simply planting in the dead plant debris after winter will not only improve the soils, experts say, it will help solve a host of other environmental problems as well, like soil erosion.</p>
        <p>''Soil degradation is the No. 1environmental problem,'' said Dr. Rattan Lal, a professor of soil science at Ohio State University and one of the leading authorities on carbon sequestration. ''It leads to water quality problems, soil problems and the release of greenhouse gases into the atmosphere,'' he said. ''We now have six billion people; by 2050 we'll have nine billion. To do that we'll have to double food production. And to do that we're going to have to put nutrients back into the ground. Conservation tillage is one way to feed the people, and it also leads to carbon sequestration and mitigates global warming.''</p>
        <p>Of course, farmers have been reluctant to abandon age-old traditions of plowing the soil, but new equipment and chemicals are making no-till farming more popular around the world.</p>
        <p>With conservation tillage, herbicide use to control weeds does increase, but some researchers say the additional herbicides are not more harmful because the reduction of erosion leads to less runoff and because water filters through the soil better, leading to better degradation of the chemicals.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rice has several experimental plots where he is evaluating soil from plowed land and soil from no-till land. ''Look, there's carbon trapped inside of these,'' he says after picking up chunks of no-till soil and cupping them in his hand.</p>
        <p>Researchers here and at other universities are now trying to find ways to measure carbon absorption in the soil. But they warn that even if America's agricultural land is made super-absorbent, the soils can only absorb so much carbon before they become saturated.</p>
        <p>That could take 30 or more years. But after that, researchers here say, big industry will either have to cut emissions, or find new ways to combat global warming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
