<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki, Environmentalist? Little and Late, Critics Say</title>
    <meta content="18POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/18/nyregion/18POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DB1F3AF93BA25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki, Environmentalist? Little and Late, Critics Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pataki, Environmentalist? Little and Late, Critics Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Feb. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article assesses New York Gov George Pataki administration on environment, noting promises made and lack of action taken to date on such issues as power plant emissions and compliance with 1977 Clean Air Act; while some delays have been beyond governor's control, environmentalists now question his commitment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years and four months ago, Gov. George E. Pataki said New York would impose the nation's toughest restrictions on the power plant emissions that can damage trees and lakes and set off asthma attacks. Yet no new regulations have been set.</p>
        <p>In May 2000, the Pataki administration said it would bring six coal-fired power plants in New York into compliance with the standards of the 1977 Clean Air Act. But as negotiations and a court case have dragged on, those plants are still not fixed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Delays have caused some environmentalists to question whether Gov. George E. Pataki is as fiercely committed to cleaning the air as his oratory would make it seem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years and four months ago, Gov. George E. Pataki said New York would impose the nation's toughest restrictions on the power plant emissions that can damage trees and lakes and set off asthma attacks. Yet no new regulations have been set.</p>
        <p>In May 2000, the Pataki administration said it would bring six coal-fired power plants in New York into compliance with the standards of the 1977 Clean Air Act. But as negotiations and a court case have dragged on, those plants are still not fixed.</p>
        <p>In September 2000, the governor signed a bill to bring motorized water scooters in line with California emissions standards, requiring new regulations within a year. But a draft of those regulations was released only on Feb. 5, after a lawsuit, and so final rules will not be determined until this summer, at the earliest.</p>
        <p>Some of the delays have been beyond the governor's control; for example, the new power plant rules first had to be written and sent out for public comment, where they generated an enormous response for such an issue, state officials said. And the Pataki administration said that long negotiations on the coal plants still represented progress.</p>
        <p>But the delays have caused some environmentalists to question whether Mr. Pataki is as fiercely committed to cleaning the air as his oratory would make it seem. Environmentalists have long viewed him as one of their strongest voices, and now, when his fellow Republicans in the Bush White House are moving to loosen industrial air pollution rules by permitting aging coal-fired plants to modernize without installing costly air-pollution devices, they need him more than ever.</p>
        <p>''The longer the delay, the more people are exposed to harmful pollutants,'' Peter M. Iwanowicz, director of environmental health for the American Lung Association of New York State, said of the power plant rules. ''And we are concerned that the standards might get even weaker as this thing hangs out there and industry continues to attack it.''</p>
        <p>Nationally, Mr. Pataki has appeared to be a stern opponent of the Bush administration on the clean air issue, though he has sought to align himself closely with the conservatives in his party on other issues, like budgeting. He wrote Vice President Dick Cheney last year to argue against ''weakening the air-quality protections'' of current law. And Erin M. Crotty, commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation, wrote to the Environmental Protection Agency's administrator, Christie Whitman, in January, arguing against the timetable for new federal rules.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crotty dismissed as ''totally ridiculous,'' any claim that the administration was not doing all it could on the clean air front.</p>
        <p>John Adams, president of the Natural Resources Defense Council, said Mr. Pataki had been one of the most successful politicians in the nation, on any level and in either party, in fighting for clean air and open space and against pollution. Still, he and others said, the governor's stance on those issues should be questioned.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that he is not fighting as vigorously as his oratory,'' said Val Washington, executive director of the nonprofit Environmental Advocates of New York. ''But he is still where our hope lies right now,'' she said. ''Not only for New York State but for the country; we still think that potential is there.''</p>
        <p>For their part, officials in the Pataki administration said that the new regulations on sulfur and nitrogen emissions at power plants were nearly complete. The regulations will be presented to the state environmental board on March 26, and then sent to New York's Department of State.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to be as thorough as we could be,'' Ms. Crotty said Friday, adding that the rules took longer than anticipated. Three public hearings were held on the issue. Then, 300 written and oral submissions, more than ever received for an air regulation issue, had to be analyzed. But a year ago, the Pataki administration said those rules would be put in effect in six to nine months.</p>
        <p>Back on Oct. 14, 1999, when the governor first announced that New York would impose the toughest emissions rules in the country, his aides said the new regulations would be out in less than a year. The reductions would be phased in from 2003 to 2007, the governor's aides said.</p>
        <p>At the time, many air pollution experts saw the governor's pledge as maneuvering between himself and Attorney General Eliot Spitzer for environmental political credit. A month before the governor's announcement, Mr. Spitzer announced his plans to sue the owners of power plants in upwind states whose pollutions harmed New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Pataki pledged to make the state's power plants cut sulfur dioxide emissions to 50 percent below federal standards, reducing the emissions to 130,000 tons a year, from 300,000 tons.</p>
        <p>Sulfur dioxide is a major cause of acid rain and a source of soot and mercury, an element that poisons lakes and streams. Power plants built before 1970 are subject to few emissions rules, and a handful in upstate New York that burn coal or oil account for a large share of the state's output of sulfur dioxide. Mr. Pataki also pledged to reduce nitrogen oxide emissions throughout the year, rather than only from May through September, as the federal government requires.</p>
        <p>In May 2001, with many wondering what happened to the grandiose promise, a preliminary version of the regulations surfaced. But power companies had successfully lobbied the Public Service Commission, and draft plans showed that the cuts in emissions would not be as deep as Mr. Pataki had pledged, though they would still be aggressive.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crotty, in an interview, said a three-year phase-in of the sulfur rules would begin on Jan. 1, 2005, while the rule for oxides of nitrogen would take effect on Oct. 1, 2004. She said the final regulations made no substantive changes from the draft and would include a controversial feature to allow the companies to achieve a small part of the required emissions reductions at their plants outside of New York's borders.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
