<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; The New York Process: How Not to Get Heard at a Legislative Hearing</title>
    <meta content="07FRI4$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/07/opinion/07FRI4.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Service Commission (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randolph, Eleanor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D6143BF934A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; The New York Process: How Not to Get Heard at a Legislative Hearing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The New York Process: How Not to Get Heard at a Legislative Hearing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR RANDOLPH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Randolph, Eleanor</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleanor Randolph Editorial Notebook scores New York State Senate for approving Gov George Pataki's nomination of William Flynn to Public Service Commission after only cursory examination of his qualifications (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a cubby-like conference room in the New York State Capitol's legislative office complex here, Kevin Parker of Brooklyn made history this week. As a freshman Democrat in the Republican-controlled State Senate, Mr. Parker recognized that he was at a disadvantage. Still, he saw himself as a real senator -- a sort of state-level version of Ted Kennedy or Richard Shelby -- a guy who asks good, solid questions at hearings.</p>
        <p>So at his first meeting of the Senate's Energy and Telecommunications Committee, he asked a few fairly straightforward questions of Gov. George Pataki's nominee to head the Public Service Commission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The entire committee system in Albany is notoriously fraudulent  not just in the Republican Senate but also in the Democratic-controlled Assembly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a cubby-like conference room in the New York State Capitol's legislative office complex here, Kevin Parker of Brooklyn made history this week. As a freshman Democrat in the Republican-controlled State Senate, Mr. Parker recognized that he was at a disadvantage. Still, he saw himself as a real senator -- a sort of state-level version of Ted Kennedy or Richard Shelby -- a guy who asks good, solid questions at hearings.</p>
        <p>So at his first meeting of the Senate's Energy and Telecommunications Committee, he asked a few fairly straightforward questions of Gov. George Pataki's nominee to head the Public Service Commission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker -- the only senator who had more than one query, and in fact one of only two to ask anything at all -- caused the committee hearing on the nominee, William Flynn, to go on for a full 40 minutes. At the end of the exchange the Energy Committee's chairman, James Wright of Watertown, noted, ''You have just made this the longest committee meeting we've had.''</p>
        <p>It was still early in the year, of course. But Senator Parker's behavior was definitely out of the ordinary. Asking public questions at hearings is something close to a revolutionary act in New York's State Legislature. It slows down the well-oiled slide from nomination to appointment, dragging the people's elected officials into a lot of messy democratic give and take.</p>
        <p>In fact, the entire committee system in Albany is notoriously fraudulent -- not just in the Republican Senate but also in the Democratic-controlled Assembly. Committees are window dressing. Public debate among the 212 legislators is a waste of breath. The only thing that really matters in New York State government is what the governor and the leaders of the two houses want. That's the Albany way.</p>
        <p>Perhaps a few members were feeling particularly frisky at the start of the session, however, because the next day, at a larger committee hearing of the Senate Finance Committee, Thomas Duane of Manhattan, another Democrat, decided to ask Mr. Flynn a few more questions. This time there were no jokes, only visible irritation from the Senate regulars.</p>
        <p>That was especially true when Senator Duane wanted to know Mr. Flynn's role in the dropping of manslaughter charges against the Kennedy Valve Company in connection with the grisly on-the-job death of an employee in 1995. At the time, Mr. Flynn was the chief political aide for Attorney General Dennis Vacco, who soft-pedaled the charges. As detailed in a recent New York Times article, Mr. Flynn was the direct connection to the company's lobbyist and helped maneuver the case away from tough federal prosecutors in favor of a cozier plea-bargain deal with the state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duane did not get an answer to his question. Instead the face of Senator Owen Johnson of Long Island, the G.O.P. chairman of the committee, took on a reddish hue as he ruled that such queries into Mr. Flynn's record were not relevant.</p>
        <p>And before Mr. Duane or anybody else could ask about Mr. Flynn's having failed the state bar exam (seven times), or how independent he would be from a governor who has been his political guardian, Mr. Johnson decided the hearing had gone on long enough. The Suffolk County Republican tapped his ring regally on the glass table and called the vote. Approved overwhelmingly, Mr. Flynn was swept through a crowd of smiling lobbyists and onto the Senate floor.</p>
        <p>The nomination came up for a vote there after a debate of less than 15 minutes -- still a long time by Albany standards. Mr. Duane took up most of that time re-registering his complaint about the lack of public process, and inspiring a few Republicans to tell him he was simply wrong. ''Nonsense,'' Senator Thomas Libous of Binghamton whispered loudly to reporters nearby. ''[Mr. Flynn] said he would meet privately and spend time with any of us. That stuff about process is just nonsense.''</p>
        <p>The senators from both parties either agreed or were too worn down for further protests, and Mr. Flynn was voted onto the commission, where it has apparently already been agreed that he will just as swiftly be elevated to chairman. The people's state senators had just installed the governor's appointee in one of the most powerful positions in the state with almost no public discussion.</p>
        <p>The Public Service Commission sets the rates for our electricity and some of our telephones. It might have to determine whether the definition of ''renewable energy'' like solar and wind power could be expanded to include the highly combustible idea of burning trash for energy. As chairman, Mr. Flynn will be one of the key players in the state's efforts to reduce its high energy costs and make sure there are no power shortages in the future. The commission also has a lot to do with deciding where power plants will be built.</p>
        <p>It's quite a portfolio for someone the public has never heard of, an anonymity that apparently suits most of those in power in Albany. In reality, the burden of bringing the public into state politics falls to those without power -- the minority senators like Mr. Parker and Mr. Duane or the Republicans in the Assembly. Their duty is not to cede their voices to the committee leadership but to use every public forum to expand the public record. Otherwise any efforts to open the process are, to quote Senator Libous, just nonsense.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
