<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Here's the Beef. So, Where's the Butcher?</title>
    <meta content="Y15MEA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/15/business/15MEAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Pathmark</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tyson Foods Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E5D8133AF936A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Here's the Beef. So, Where's the Butcher?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Here's the Beef. So, Where's the Butcher?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>'Case-ready' meat, which is delivered to stores with its cutting, packaging and labeling complete, is growing in popularity among retailers, but is of concern to consumers and has brought controversy; some of meat is injected with saline solution to keep its both good-looking and fresh, and some shoppers complain about taste; most of steaks and chops sold at Wal-Mart note, on their packages, that they contain up to 12 percent liquid, which may result in their shrinking on grill; union leaders anxious to preserve jobs call for regulations on case-ready meat to make shoppers more aware of what they are buying; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the summer, a new Pathmark supermarket opened in a fast-growing corner of Staten Island. From the outside, it looks unremarkable. But inside, it holds the latest in supermarket meat -- steaks and cutlets that are not merely someone's future meal, but byproducts of the industry's battle to keep up with Wal-Mart, its biggest rival.</p>
        <p>There in the meat section are small white tubs holding pale pink pork chops, their profiles distinct beneath the layer of plastic that seals them off from the world. They, too, look unremarkable except that they were not prepared by the store's butcher. This is ''case ready'' meat, which differs from traditional supermarket fare in that it is delivered, with its cutting, packaging and labeling complete, to stores in a process that has grown rapidly in popularity among retailers in the last 18 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Case-ready meat, which is delivered cut and packaged to stores, has become part of the supermarket industry's battle to keep up with Wal-Mart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the summer, a new Pathmark supermarket opened in a fast-growing corner of Staten Island. From the outside, it looks unremarkable. But inside, it holds the latest in supermarket meat -- steaks and cutlets that are not merely someone's future meal, but byproducts of the industry's battle to keep up with Wal-Mart, its biggest rival.</p>
        <p>There in the meat section are small white tubs holding pale pink pork chops, their profiles distinct beneath the layer of plastic that seals them off from the world. They, too, look unremarkable except that they were not prepared by the store's butcher. This is ''case ready'' meat, which differs from traditional supermarket fare in that it is delivered, with its cutting, packaging and labeling complete, to stores in a process that has grown rapidly in popularity among retailers in the last 18 months.</p>
        <p>It has also brought controversy. Some of the meat is injected with a saline solution to keep it both good-looking and fresh, and some shoppers complain about the taste. Many of the steaks and chops sold at Wal-Mart note, on their packages, that they contain up to 12 percent liquid. Do they shrink on the grill? Yes, say people who have cooked them. Union leaders anxious to preserve jobs have called for regulations on case-ready meat to make shoppers more aware of what they are buying.</p>
        <p>The main difference between case-ready meat and store-handled meat is that the former is cut, trimmed, packaged and labeled at a plant, not in the back room of a supermarket. The shelf life of case-ready meat is said to be longer, because the package is ''flushed'' with gas, usually combinations of oxygen and carbon dioxide, to keep everything inside looking fresh. The saline treatment ''keeps the bloom on the meat,'' as a spokesman for Wal-Mart Stores put it.</p>
        <p>Since September 2001, Wal-Mart has sold only case-ready meat. The change followed a vote by workers at a Wal-Mart supercenter in Texas who voted to join the United Food and Commercial Workers, a unit of the A.F.L.-C.I.O.</p>
        <p>Pathmark is the first supermarket chain in New York City to serve meat to shoppers this way, but New York may be the final frontier. In the last year, meat packers report a surge in orders for case-ready meat as supermarkets eagerly follow Wal-Mart's lead.</p>
        <p>Chickens have been case-ready for decades; 25 years ago, they, too were split and packaged inside the stores' back rooms. But case-ready meat is a newer development, the biggest revolution inside the meat department since 1961, when boxed beef replaced the hanging steer that had to be wheeled into the back room.</p>
        <p>Various competitive concerns have pushed stores away from the meatcutters and toward case-ready meat. The entry of Wal-Mart, the retail giant based in Bentonville, Ark., into the grocery business has made all supermarkets eager to trim costs. In recent years, Wal-Mart has made its supercenters, which combine groceries with general merchandise, the cornerstone of its expansion, and will open at least 200 new ones this year on top of the 1,258 already doing business, said a company spokesman, Tom Williams.</p>
        <p>There are no meatcutters in the Wal-Mart stores, and they are likely to disappear from supermarkets that switch to case-ready meat, said John Niccollai, president of Local 464-A of the United Food and Commercial Workers in New Jersey. But beyond that, he said, the union objects to the absence of information about the meat in stores that sell case-ready products.</p>
        <p>''This will cost us jobs, so we have a vested interest,'' Mr. Niccollai said. ''But there are also a great many concerns we have about case-ready meat. There are additives and preservatives put in it. A number of people are allergic to what they put in the meat.'' Spokeswomen for the Food Allergy Network and the American Dietetic Association said they could not confirm whether people were allergic to the substances in case-ready meat.</p>
        <p>In the New Jersey Legislature, a bill is pending that would require stores to post signs notifying shoppers if more than half the meat they sell is case-ready. Mr. Niccollai said supermarkets were largely opposed to the legislation. ''When we send our union agents into the stores and they talk with people, the people have no idea that this product they are buying was not cut and weighed and wrapped in the back room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The cost savings for Wal-Mart include the elimination of meatcutters in stores (the experienced ones typically earn $1,000 a week) as well as reduced waste and improved efficiency. ''It flows really, really well,'' Mr. Williams said. ''The biggest savings we realize is in the efficiency of handling the product and moving it. You have so much more control over what you're ordering and what you need.'' Most of Wal-Mart's meat comes from Tyson Foods, a large Arkansas-based processor that acquired IBP, a beef and pork processor, in 2001.</p>
        <p>Other supermarkets that find themselves up against Wal-Mart are turning to the same technique.</p>
        <p>''Business is really, really growing,'' said Michael Queen, chief executive of Pennexx Foods, a Philadelphia processor that supplies many supermarkets and is half owned by Smithfield Foods. Pennexx, with $60 million in sales this year, will probably triple its sales by next year, he said, as supermarkets, which he described as having ''tremendous fear of Wal-Mart,'' seek to cut costs.</p>
        <p>Of course, prepackaged meat costs more than the unadorned raw material. ''You are paying for the product and the packaging and the labor,'' said Mark Greenberg, vice president of meat for Wakefern Food, a cooperative that runs ShopRite supermarkets and buys from Pennexx, among other suppliers.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart's ubiquity has pressured all supermarket chains, putting some in unusual difficulty. The Great Atlantic and Pacific Tea Company, owner of the Food Emporium and A.&amp;P. chains, announced last month that it would be forced to examine ways of cutting costs to improve profits. ''We are probably operating in one of the worst possible retailing environments,'' A.&amp;P.'s chairman and chief executive, Christian W.E. Haub, said, alluding to ''tough choices'' that would have to be made later this year. A few months ago, Albertson's, another major supermarket chain, retreated from Houston and several other parts of Texas where it competed with Wal-Mart; Kroger and regional chains remain.</p>
        <p>Some executives say that it is not Wal-Mart, but the need to satisfy customers, that has made them introduce case-ready meat. ''Wal-Mart has done it for other reasons,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''Our position is, we are looking to determine what the customer is looking for.''</p>
        <p>Shoppers have altered their buying patterns, he added, which means they may be browsing for ground chuck at 9 o'clock in the morning on a Sunday, instead of 4 o'clock on a Friday afternoon. If there is no butcher working at that morning hour, they might be disappointed. But with case-ready meat, the product will be there waiting for them.</p>
        <p>''A lot of our stores are 24-hour stores, but the butchers aren't working 24 hours,'' he said. ''We want to make sure that when the customer comes in, the full variety is there.'' In ShopRite's 200 stores around the Northeast, case-ready is available along with store-handled meat, he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Niccollai said wholesale prices for case-ready meat were as much as 25 percent higher than for store-packaged meat. ''You're going to save money, they feel, in terms of labor because you are not paying meatcutters,'' he said. ''If you eliminate that, you can operate for less money. But what are you doing to your operation?'' He believes that customers will go elsewhere for meat.</p>
        <p>That has not been true at the Pathmark in Staten Island. ''In this store, it's all case-ready,'' said Art Whitney, Pathmark's regional manager, as he stood near the meat case. ''Over all, the acceptance is very good.'' A few shoppers have complained, he said, that the deep tubs take up too much room in their refrigerators, compared with the flat trays that chops and other kinds of meat used to come in.</p>
        <p>Chris Cossean, who was checking out a cartful of groceries in the store, is not one of them. ''I have no problem,'' she said. ''They're fine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
