<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Well-Peppered Landscape</title>
    <meta content="09CRUCES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/09/travel/09cruces.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1470804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Cruces (Nm)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harlan, Megan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico/Las Cruces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Mexico</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2DF153FF93AA35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="2420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Well-Peppered Landscape</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Well-Peppered Landscape</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEGAN HARLAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harlan, Megan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Megan Harlan travel article on visit to Las Cruces, New Mexico; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S possible to buy kachina dolls and turquoise jewelry at the Farmers and Crafts Market in Las Cruces, N.M., but it's impossible to miss the market's main theme. Chilies of all hues and heat levels glisten from bins. Other incendiary products include honey spiked with crushed chilies, jalapeño ketchup, chili marmalades and hot sauces called Salsa of Death, Sudden Death and Acid Rain. Pepper motifs are emblazoned on paintings, sculptures, blouses, earrings and underwear. Most striking are the racks of ristras -- dried ruby-red chilies strung up in big, flouncy bushels, often seen hanging from front porches around town.</p>
        <p>Though the chili symbolizes the Southwest to many, no region can lay greater claim to the three-alarm plant than the area north of Las Cruces, the Mesilla Valley of southern New Mexico. Its agricultural belt is chili central, growing a large percentage of the nation's chilies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around Las Cruces, chilies, colorful mountains, Indian petroglyphs and New Mexico's colonial history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S possible to buy kachina dolls and turquoise jewelry at the Farmers and Crafts Market in Las Cruces, N.M., but it's impossible to miss the market's main theme. Chilies of all hues and heat levels glisten from bins. Other incendiary products include honey spiked with crushed chilies, jalapeño ketchup, chili marmalades and hot sauces called Salsa of Death, Sudden Death and Acid Rain. Pepper motifs are emblazoned on paintings, sculptures, blouses, earrings and underwear. Most striking are the racks of ristras -- dried ruby-red chilies strung up in big, flouncy bushels, often seen hanging from front porches around town.</p>
        <p>Though the chili symbolizes the Southwest to many, no region can lay greater claim to the three-alarm plant than the area north of Las Cruces, the Mesilla Valley of southern New Mexico. Its agricultural belt is chili central, growing a large percentage of the nation's chilies.</p>
        <p>The landscape seems a natural for raising the formidable, heat-bearing chilies, as my husband, Matthew, and I discovered on a trip to Las Cruces and nearby Mesilla in January. The hot, high Chihuahuan Desert setting resembles Wile E. Coyote country, with red, rocky mesas studding flat expanses of prickly pear cactus, skunkbush sumac and pepperweed.</p>
        <p>A little rough terrain never scared off a true New Mexican, and Las Cruces, despite the hearty surrounding topography, recently edged out Santa Fe as New Mexico's second most populous city (though admittedly a distant second, with a population of about 78,000, after Albuquerque's 450,000). It's also a modern-day boomtown, or so suggests a May 2002 article in Forbes magazine's online version, which proclaimed Las Cruces the best small metro area for jobs and business.</p>
        <p>Signs touting this distinction also cropped up in the village of Mesilla, whose border blurs along the southwestern edge of Las Cruces, and where we stayed and spent most of our time. The first record of Spanish explorers passing through was in 1598. Dating from 1849, the village of about 2,000 boasts one of the Southwest's most beautifully preserved plazas. Indeed, Old Mesilla (as the one-square-mile downtown is called) looks as picturesque as Las Cruces -- with its sprawl of strip malls and subdivisions -- seems ready to do business.</p>
        <p>Under bright blue skies, we strolled the terra-cotta brick streets around Old Mesilla's small, pretty square, which is on the National Register of Historic Places. Flanked by tawny adobe buildings and centered around a white stucco gazebo, the quiet plaza felt like a suspended piece of territorial history, a living window to its past as a crossroads outpost.</p>
        <p>As early as the 16th century, both Mesilla and Las Cruces were the site of permanent camps, or parajes, along the Camino Real of what was then Mexico, running north to Santa Fe and south to Chihuahua, Mexico. After the territory was purchased by the United States in the 1850's, Mesilla became the hub of a cross-shaped transportation network, the site of a Butterfield stagecoach station house, the Southwest's first east-west express line.</p>
        <p>That former station house, a rough adobe southeast of the plaza, now houses La Posta, a warren of a Mexican restaurant with a chili store and aviary. Like many adobes, it appears hunched and humble from the outside, then seems to expand into vast, cool interiors.</p>
        <p>All but two of the plaza's original 19th-century buildings, with their high ceilings made of vigas, or exposed cottonwood beams, are intact, and placards detail their sometimes gruesome history. (Stories of regional lore often end with the sentence, ''And the bodies were never found.'')</p>
        <p>Most of the plaza's buildings house galleries, shops and cafes that would be at home in Santa Fe. La Zia, an Indian crafts boutique, sells lovely Pueblo wedding vases; Bowlin's Mesilla Book Center has an extensive Southwest selection, and a nearby coffeehouse serves espresso. The businesses are often operated by descendants of original settlers -- like the Fountain family's turn-of-the-century theater (which now shows independent and foreign films) graced with purple peacocks in its stained-glass windows.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this entrenched family history has kept kitsch to a minimum. That said, the Billy the Kid Gift Shop -- in the former courthouse where the cherub-faced mass murderer was sentenced to hang (he escaped), and now carrying merchandise like belt buckles and Popsicles -- looks like a cultural sanctuary for the under-12 tourist crowd.</p>
        <p>The northern end of the plaza is crowned by San Albino Church, with its tall twin bell towers and buttery-yellow brick facade. It was built in 1906 around an original adobe church, which was then removed through the front door, clump by clump.</p>
        <p>Though Mesilla's charm lives on, its heyday waned in 1881, when the area's first railroad bypassed the town for Las Cruces instead. Long ago named for the white crosses erected after Apaches slaughtered two groups of settlers -- once in the 18th century and again in 1830 -- Las Cruces today doesn't appear to dwell too much on its past.</p>
        <p>Still, a spirited effort to revive its city center has taken place along the Downtown Mall, a half-covered, rather stark concrete walkway and site of the Farmers and Crafts Market. Stores line the open-air promenade, and though many of them looked empty, new museums have recently opened, including the Las Cruces Museum of Fine Art, with its attractive loft galleries showcasing contemporary art, and the Historical Museum, which archives local history -- including old photos of the town and family artifacts -- in a refurbished adobe. When we were there, we saw an exhibition of sweeping paintings of the Organ Mountains, the landmark that seems to hover over the valley, by the New Mexican artist Clyde Gunnell.</p>
        <p>Named for the 5,500-foot-high range of orange granite spires that 19th-century settlers thought resembled a pipe organ, the Organ Mountains shift color throughout the day, reflecting sunsets and twilights in great carved burls of pinks, crimsons and smoky grays. But I prefer the name given by the early Spanish settlers -- Sierra del Olvido, the Mountains of Oblivion. From the viewpoint of the relatively lush Mesilla Valley, the Organ Mountains form a sort of gateway to a spectacular oblivion.</p>
        <p>After driving 10 miles east of town to the mountains and crossing the San Augustin Pass, we were deposited steeply into the dusty, cinnamon-red Tularosa Basin, a harsh desert microclimate within the Chihuahuan Desert, which itself loops across south-central New Mexico and runs deep into Mexico.</p>
        <p>Piercing the empty mesa-strewn view was a 50-foot-high black and white roadside missile -- and a sign telling us we had entered the White Sands Missile Range. Highway 70 traverses the 3,200-square-mile military reserve, and is often closed during tests for an hour or two (travelers can call for the schedule).</p>
        <p>The Tularosa Basin was considered so remote that in July 1945 it was the testing ground for the first atomic bomb, at the Trinity Site. The site may not draw many visitors, but the Tularosa Basin also includes a far more tranquil reserve, White Sands National Monument -- the sparkling central treasure within the concentric folds of the area's desert landscapes.</p>
        <p>After we sped another 50 miles north on Highway 70, the sunburned landscape of yucca, cactus and creosote abruptly gave way to mounds of what looked like snow, but was pure white sand. Spanning some 275 square miles, this is the world's largest gypsum dune field, and one of the Southwest's natural wonders. A fluke of geology and weather, the wintry-looking tundra was created by deposits of milky gypsum crystals enriching a lake bed that dried out about 10,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>An eight-mile scenic drive begins just past the adobe Visitor Center at the National Monument. Along the way, we stopped at wayside exhibits on natural phenomena like the thriving yucca and rosemary mint bushes.</p>
        <p>The 4.6-mile Alkali Flat hiking trail winds through radiant, towering ranges of transverse dunes. As we climbed 50 feet up one -- and then skidded down its concave face -- the sand felt wonderfully soft, much finer than regular beach sand.</p>
        <p>And in this otherworldly atmosphere, the Southwest still made itself felt: Rising above the foamy sweep of the dunes, and brilliant against the cobalt afternoon sky, were the saw-toothed red peaks of the San Andres Mountains to the west, the Sacramentos to the east.</p>
        <p>We headed to the foot of the Sacramento Mountains, another 60 miles north, to reach Three Rivers Petroglyph Site before sunset. Though the Tularosa Basin was never exactly a hotbed of settlement, the Jornada Mogollon people called it home for about 500 years, mysteriously abandoning it in 1400 A.D. They left behind one of the region's largest collections of petroglyphic art, about 22,000 glyphs along a single basalt ridge.</p>
        <p>As we picked our way across the narrow half-mile trail, it seemed as if every boulder had been used as a canvas. Sunbursts, thunderbirds, goggle-eyed humans, masked beings and animals covered in geometric designs were some of the fantastical engravings -- usually no more than a foot high -- chipped into the rock faces. The sheer, repetitive quantity of the artwork reminded me of pictograms, as if the drawings were a sprawling text in another language and another way of thinking.</p>
        <p>After our tour of the badlands, we spent our final day dawdling in Mesilla -- and, as it turned out, we had saved our favorite spot in town for last. The Double Eagle restaurant is set in an 1840's mansion, the plaza's oldest building. The enormous adobe resembles a series of treasure-filled caves. It actually houses two restaurants -- the Double Eagle, serving pricey Continental fare in posh salons and a ballroom, and the more casual, inexpensive Peppers, its delicious New Mexican food presented in a patio covered by a transparent ceiling.</p>
        <p>The dozen rooms that are open to the public energetically bring together such exotic features as Baccarat chandeliers the size of sumo wrestlers, a 30-foot oak and walnut bar from Chicago's Drake Hotel, museum-quality Pueblo folk art, a gilt-covered ceiling and a lounge decorated with turquoise snakeskin.</p>
        <p>Even the building's ghost story was good -- a Greek tragedy of a tale involving a wealthy mother, her son's affair with a maid, and scissors. ''Sometimes we find chairs tipped over,'' our waiter for the terrific Sunday buffet brunch told us gamely.</p>
        <p>Afterward, as we relaxed on a bench in La Mesilla's plaza, the sun lighted up the Organ Mountains in blazing colors, as if reflecting the fiery spirit of the place.</p>
        <p>Hot sands and hotter chilies</p>
        <p>Las Cruces is about a 50-mile drive north of El Paso's airport. The Las Cruces Convention and Visitors Bureau is at (505) 541-2444 or www.lascrucescvb.org. For information on Mesilla, (505) 524-1965 or at www.vivamesilla.org.</p>
        <p>Dining</p>
        <p>The restaurant at our inn, Mesón de Mesilla, 1803 Avenida de Mesilla, (800) 732-6025, has a changing menu of well-prepared Continental entrees like filet mignon or lobster pasta running about $25. A meal for two with wine is about $80.</p>
        <p>The Double Eagle, 2355 Calle de Guadalupe, (505) 523-6700, serves classic European fare like chateaubriand ($26.95 a person, prepared for two). The vast Sunday buffet brunch is $17.95 a person with Champagne; open daily for lunch and dinner. In the same building, casual Peppers is open for lunch and dinner, with tasty regional dishes like grilled chicken Mesilla ($7.95 lunch, $10.95 dinner), a chicken breast over sautéed onions, topped with roasted green chili and Monterey Jack cheese. A bottle of wine is about $25.</p>
        <p>Boisterous, family-friendly La Posta, 2410 Calle de San Albino, Mesilla, (505) 524-3524, features standard New Mexican dishes such as chimichangas and huevos rancheros in huge portions ($11.95 for a five-course meal). Liquor is served.</p>
        <p>Lodging</p>
        <p>We stayed at Mesón de Mesilla, 1803 Avenida de Mesilla, (800) 732-6025, fax (505) 527-4196, Web site www.mesondemesilla.com, a bed-and-breakfast with 15 attractive rooms, all with private bath. Rates are $65 to $140 with breakfast. The Kachina Suite ($92 on Friday and Saturday, $87 other days), where we stayed, has rustic Southwest furniture, including a king bed, and fireplace. An unheated pool is open all year.</p>
        <p>Lundeen Inn of the Arts, 618 South Alameda Boulevard, Las Cruces, (888) 526-3326, fax (505) 647-1334, www.innofthearts.com, is a stylish bed-and-breakfast with 11 rooms, all with private bath, named for artists including Georgia O'Keeffe and R.C. Gorman, and decorated in a theme related to the artist. Double rates range from $95 to $145, with breakfast.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>The Las Cruces Farmers and Crafts Market, (505) 541-2556, at the Downtown Mall on Main Street, is held Wednesday and Sunday mornings.</p>
        <p>The Cultural Center in the Branigan Building, 500 North Water Street, Las Cruces, (505) 541-2155, on the Internet at www.lascruces-culture.org, includes the Las Cruces Historical Museum and Las Cruces Museum of Fine Art, both with changing exhibitions, and the Log Cabin Museum. Open Tuesday to Friday 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., Saturday 9 a.m. to 1 p.m.; free.</p>
        <p>White Sands National Monument, (505) 479-6124, on Highway 70 about 50 miles northeast of Las Cruces, is open daily, except Christmas, 7 a.m. to 9 p.m. in summer, 7 a.m. to sunset other times. The visitor center provides extensive information on the site, and sells snacks (8 a.m. to 7 p.m. during summer months; otherwise 8 a.m. to 5 p.m.). Admission, $3; 16 and under, free.</p>
        <p>For a recorded schedule of Highway 70 closings for tests in White Sands Missile Range, call (505) 443-7199.</p>
        <p>Three Rivers Petroglyph Site, operated by the Bureau of Land Management, (505) 525-4300, is open year-round. Seventeen miles north of Tularosa off Highway 54, and 120 miles from Las Cruces, signs indicate the five-mile paved road to the site. Day-use fee of $2 a vehicle. There is a small visitor center.</p>
        <p>MEGAN HARLAN</p>
        <p>MEGAN HARLAN is a writer and poet who lives in San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MEGAN HARLAN is a writer and poet who lives in San Francisco.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
