<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reponses to Warning on Terror Fall Between Fear and Fatalism</title>
    <meta content="13MOOD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/13/national/13MOOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE NATIONAL MOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DD143AF930A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reponses to Warning on Terror Fall Between Fear and Fatalism</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Terror Warning Responses Range From Fear to Fatalism</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER with TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M; Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>DUNWOODY, Ga., Feb. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Americans' reactions vary greatly to Bush administration's warnings that terrorist threat has risen and that people should prepare to protect their families; retailers and manufacturers of duct tape and other elements of government's suggested 'disaster supply kit' report surges in sales of as much as 40 percent in some places; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lynn Smith dashed off a letter to her two small children, just in case: ''Mommy's with God now,'' it says. Then she dashed off to the Home Depot here for supplies to stock the safe room where she says she hopes her family will be able to ride out a terrorist attack.</p>
        <p>Lisa Gonzales lives in San Francisco with her 6-year-old daughter, but her boyfriend lives across the Golden Gate Bridge in Marin County. And that worries her. ''I don't want to be across any bridge if something happens and I'm away from my baby,'' Ms. Gonzales said. ''It scares me to think I would be away and I can't get to her.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rest of the country is not immune to the fears of terror felt by many in New York and Washington. But that fear is nowhere near as widespread, or as keenly felt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lynn Smith dashed off a letter to her two small children, just in case: ''Mommy's with God now,'' it says. Then she dashed off to the Home Depot here for supplies to stock the safe room where she says she hopes her family will be able to ride out a terrorist attack.</p>
        <p>Lisa Gonzales lives in San Francisco with her 6-year-old daughter, but her boyfriend lives across the Golden Gate Bridge in Marin County. And that worries her. ''I don't want to be across any bridge if something happens and I'm away from my baby,'' Ms. Gonzales said. ''It scares me to think I would be away and I can't get to her.''</p>
        <p>But Beth Wilhelm, a 38-year old skin care sales manager waiting for a train in downtown Denver, was less concerned. ''It might take up a little bit of my free thought, but it has not permeated my lifestyle,'' Ms. Wilhelm said of the warnings of a possible attack. ''Denver just seems like a nonthreat.''</p>
        <p>The Bush administration's warnings on Monday that the terrorist threat has risen and that people should prepare to protect their families have heightened awareness of the dangers of attack across the country. But the reactions vary greatly.</p>
        <p>In New York City and Washington, still shaken by the deadly strikes of Sept. 11, 2001, officials and residents have responded swiftly. The police in New York have increased patrols in subways, bridges and other public places, and the Pentagon ordered jeeps armed with Stinger antiaircraft missiles to patrol the nation's capital. Residents in both cities are stocking up on water, canned foods and supplies to seal their homes in case of a chemical attack.</p>
        <p>But in Southern California, where earthquake preparedness has always been a fact of life, there was no stampede to grocery stores. Nor did Ed Helton, 60, a small-business man shopping at the Costco in Glendale, feel the need to pick up the plastic sheeting and duct tape and other items that the government says could save citizens.</p>
        <p>''I'm fatalistic,'' Mr. Helton said. ''If something happens, it happens. I'll get a good bottle of cabernet and wait inside.''</p>
        <p>Retailers and manufacturers of duct tape and other elements of the government's suggested ''disaster supply kit'' did report surges in sales of as much as 40 percent in some places after the government's announcement.</p>
        <p>Jim Sinegal, chief executive of the Costco Wholesale Corporation, said in a telephone interview that stocks of duct tape that normally lasted 30 days had run out in a day and a half.</p>
        <p>''I'm in our new Salt Lake City store, and I just saw a cart with eight cases of duct tape and another with three cases of water,'' Mr. Sinegal said.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Sinegal and other executives said the greatest increases were concentrated in the Northeast, especially in the New York and Washington areas, and to a lesser extent in other major cities and coastal areas. But not in all major cities and coastal areas.</p>
        <p>In the Northwest, distance from the centers of government, finance and earlier terrorism targets may have something to do with what seems to be a collective shrug.</p>
        <p>About a hundred people a day stop by the Top Line espresso hut, a drive-through in Covington, a Seattle suburb, and the heightened sense of security does not seem to be on a lot of people's minds.</p>
        <p>''The government just keeps warning us so many times that people have stopped caring, they're trying to get on with the lives,'' said Nate Satar, who owns the hut. ''I haven't heard one person say they are scared or doing something differently.''</p>
        <p>In Chicago, Merav Elkan, an officer at the Israeli consulate, said she had endured years living in fear of terrorist attacks before moving there six years ago from Tel Aviv. But Ms. Elkan said she saw no need to stockpile supplies in her high-rise apartment on Michigan Avenue.</p>
        <p>''You feel the threat more in Israel because it is so small,'' she said. ''Here, everything is so big, how could it happen to me? Maybe I'm just not used to thinking of this place as threatened by terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Todd Curtis, 32, on his knees installing carpet in an office building north of the Loop, said: ''I'm not sure if a thin sheet of plastic is going to do anything for you. It seems like they are just getting people scared saying things like that. I think they are just trying to cover themselves.''</p>
        <p>Why some people react with alarm and others do not may depend less on geography than on whether one is young enough to have very young children, or old enough to remember wartime rationing or cold-war-era nuclear anxiety.</p>
        <p>In Decatur, Ga., Eva Talton, 61, stocked up on flashlights, water, batteries, kerosene lamps and charcoal. ''When I was born they attacked Pearl Harbor,'' she said. ''Now that I'm about to retire, it looks like we're going to war again. All this is just to be safe. I don't want to die of suffocation or burns.''</p>
        <p>Here in Dunwoody, like Decatur a suburb of Atlanta, Lynn Smith was wheeling two cartons of plastic sheeting, four rolls of duct tape and a couple of containers of foam insulation toward the checkout line at a Home Depot. ''I used to be a lot more cavalier about things when I was single, but now that I'm married with two small children, that's changed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Besides writing her 5-year-old son and 3-year-old daughter a letter to read in case she is killed in an attack, Ms. Smith said she and her husband had set up a safe room in their house with a bathroom, a battery-operated TV, food, radios and a box of toys and books for their children.</p>
        <p>She also said she had explained to the children about the ''bad men who flew the planes into the buildings,'' and that the country was likely to go to war soon to prevent that from happening again.</p>
        <p>''They've asked me whether the bad guys are going to come to Atlanta,'' Ms. Smith said. ''And I've told them I hope not. But my 5-year-old son says that even if they do, the G.I. Joe's and firemen and police will protect us from them.''</p>
        <p>In Denver, by contrast, Sarah MacKenzie, a 34-year-old bank secretary, practically rolled her eyes as she spoke of the latest threats, warnings and saber rattling. She said she had started avoiding the TV news in recent days, and laughed at the government's suggested home-protection shopping list. ''Maybe it's just a ploy to boost the economy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Todd Anselmo, 40, smoking a cigar outside his downtown Denver office, expressed a whiff of fatalism. ''I live day to day, so who cares?'' he said. ''I have my will in place. If it's going to affect me, there's not a lot I'll be able to do about it.''</p>
        <p>He laughed and added, ''It's like acid rain -- meaning, don't worry about things that are beyond your control.''</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: THE NATIONAL MOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
