<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Puts Off Its Hybrids, Letting Ford Go First</title>
    <meta content="06AUTO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/06/business/06auto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1533184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DE1439F935A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Puts Off Its Hybrids, Letting Ford Go First</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.M. Puts Off Its Hybrids, Letting Ford Go First</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Nov. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors has delayed plans to sell a hybrid vehicle similar to the Toyota Prius by two years, until 2007, according to people close to the company's product development strategy.</p>
        <p>That means that Ford, which plans to sell a hybrid version of its Escape sport utility vehicle next year, will put a light-duty, Prius-style hybrid on the road about three years before its American rival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors has delayed plans to sell a hybrid vehicle similar to the Toyota Prius by two years, until 2007.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>General Motors has delayed plans to sell a hybrid vehicle similar to the Toyota Prius by two years, until 2007, according to people close to the company's product development strategy.</p>
        <p>That means that Ford, which plans to sell a hybrid version of its Escape sport utility vehicle next year, will put a light-duty, Prius-style hybrid on the road about three years before its American rival.</p>
        <p>G.M. has previously laid out plans to offer fuel-saving electric technologies as options on as many as a dozen models this decade, if the demand for such vehicles materializes. Most of the vehicles would reduce gasoline consumption 10 percent to 15 percent. The Prius saves 50 percent or more on fuel, though its performance can vary widely depending on how and where it is driven.</p>
        <p>G.M. has shifted away from a plan to offer a hybrid system similar to that in the Prius as an option on its Saturn Vue sport utility vehicle by 2005. Instead, it will offer such a system in 2007, as an option in two 2008 model full-size sport utilities -- the GMC Yukon and the Chevrolet Tahoe. A less ambitious green version of the Saturn Vue will be introduced in 2006.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s new strategy was reported on Wednesday in The Detroit News.</p>
        <p>Hybrid vehicles save gasoline by supplementing internal combustion with electrical power. The Prius has an electric motor that takes over from the gasoline engine at low speeds, and technology that recycles energy used in braking and shuts the engine off at stops.</p>
        <p>G.M. declined to comment on its plans. Executives said privately that the company saw a better business case for hybrids on large S.U.V.'s and more potential for fuel savings by putting hybrids in the biggest gas guzzlers. The system on the Yukon and the Tahoe would probably reduce fuel consumption by about 30 percent while retaining the vehicles' towing ability.</p>
        <p>The shift is spurred by the company's most tangible hybrid program, which is building systems for buses. Last month, King County, Wash., which includes Seattle, said it would buy 235 buses outfitted with a G.M. hybrid system.</p>
        <p>Thomas G. Stephens, group vice president at GM Powertrain, said then that the buses would save as much gasoline as replacing 8,000 conventional cars with hybrids. ''What we need to do at General Motors is go after the highest fuel-consuming vehicle first,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The company thinks that the hybrid bus system can be a base for a system in big sport utility vehicles and be potentially profitable instead of a money loser. A big hurdle with hybrids is that they cost a few thousand dollars more than ordinary vehicles, though that can be offset in part by federal, and sometimes local tax deductions for such technology.</p>
        <p>Toyota and Honda introduced hybrids in the late 1990's. Automakers in Europe and Detroit, and Asian automakers like Nissan and Hyundai, have yet to sell them.</p>
        <p>''We're happy to see them putting hybrids in big trucks, but we're very disappointed seeing the Vue dropping from a full hybrid to a halfhearted hybrid,'' said David Friedman, a energy expert at the Union of Concerned Scientists, an environmental group. ''It shouldn't be an either-or situation. It should be both.''</p>
        <p>And Daniel Becker, an expert on global warming for the Sierra Club, said, ''Why is a company that's supposed to be the industry leader so far behind?''</p>
        <p>The new plan for the Saturn Vue is to equip it with a small electric starter system that allows the engine to shut off at stops, as well as advanced transmission technology for overall fuel savings of 12 percent to 15 percent.</p>
        <p>G.M. will offer a somewhat similar feature on the GMC Sierra and the Chevrolet Silverado pickup trucks this year for the commercial market and next year for retail customers. It also has plans to offer such technology in the Chevrolet Malibu.</p>
        <p>Hybrids are hardly the only environmentally friendly technology. Automakers are exploring various approaches as they brace for increases in global fuel economy and emissions requirements.</p>
        <p>European producers, including DaimlerChrysler and Volkswagen, favor advanced diesels. Though diesels are still dirtier than gasoline cars, the gap is narrowing. Diesels also get better mileage and thus have lower emissions of gases that a number of scientists think are causing a global-warming trend.</p>
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr., Ford's chairman and chief executive, appears determined to make his company the world's third auto manufacturer to sell a hybrid. Its Escape hybrid, due next summer, could be the first hybrid S.U.V., although Toyota's Lexus division plans to sell one in the fall and Ford has previously delayed the Escape.</p>
        <p>''The Escape hybrid is designed to be the cleanest S.U.V. on the planet,'' Mr. Ford said at the company's annual meeting in June, adding that it would appear in 2004.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s research and development executives are most enthusiastic about the hydrogen fuel cell, a system that uses hydrogen and air to generate electric power. Fuel-cell cars emit only water from their tailpipes.</p>
        <p>But far-reaching questions remain about how hydrogen will be produced, how it would be stored in vehicles and how the nation's gasoline stations would be retrofitted to distribute it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
