<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1508057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFD71F3FF93AA15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>France and Germany Weigh Their Postwar Roles in Iraq  The open-ended American military occupation of Iraq is forcing European powers that opposed the war, notably France and Germany, to contemplate whether and how to help with the aftereffects, as President Bush presses for a more international presence there.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Liberia Rebels Take Second City  Rebels captured Buchanan, the second-biggest city in Liberia, defeating President Charles G. Taylor's embattled forces on a new front. Kofi Annan, the United Nations secretary general, warned rebels that those who caused suffering to the Liberian people would be held accountable for war crimes.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>France and Germany Weigh Their Postwar Roles in Iraq  The open-ended American military occupation of Iraq is forcing European powers that opposed the war, notably France and Germany, to contemplate whether and how to help with the aftereffects, as President Bush presses for a more international presence there.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Liberia Rebels Take Second City  Rebels captured Buchanan, the second-biggest city in Liberia, defeating President Charles G. Taylor's embattled forces on a new front. Kofi Annan, the United Nations secretary general, warned rebels that those who caused suffering to the Liberian people would be held accountable for war crimes.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Tribunal Prosecutor Under Fire  The United Nations secretary general told the chief prosecutor for war crimes tribunals for Yugoslavia and Rwanda, Carla del Ponte, that he would recommend she be relieved of her Rwanda responsibilities, but agreed to wait while she lobbied for a chance to finish both jobs.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>U.N. Expands Forces in Congo  The Security Council unanimously passed a resolution extending the United Nations mission in Congo for a year while stiffening its mandate and strengthening its forces. It also imposed a yearlong arms embargo on all foreign and Congolese groups in the resource-rich eastern part of the country.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>G.I. Is Killed in Baghdad  One American soldier was killed and three were wounded in a bombing in Baghdad. The death was the 50th since President Bush declared an end to combat operations on May 1, and the 15th in the past eight days.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Israeli Troops Fire on Protesters  Israeli troops fired tear gas and rubber-coated bullets to thwart several hundred Palestinians, Israelis and foreign activists who were cutting through part of the security fence in the northern West Bank. Meanwhile, the authorities found the body of a missing Israeli soldier, calling his death a ''terrorist killing.''</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A Report of Abuse by Afghans  A human rights group has documented widespread extortion, armed robbery and kidnapping by police and intelligence officials and militias in Afghanistan. The report accuses the United States of supporting some of the worst offenders, and blames all countries for not intervening.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S.-Philippines Ties Are Safe  For the Bush administration, the Philippines is seen as a beachhead for American troops in the campaign against terrorism in Southeast Asia, and the mutiny by some 300 soldiers over the weekend seems unlikely to change Washington's warmth toward President Gloria Macapagal Arroyo.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-19</p>
        <p>Pentagon Develops a Game To Predict Terrorism  The Pentagon office that proposed spying electronically on Americans to monitor potential terrorists has a new experiment: an online futures trading market, disclosed by its critics, in which anonymous speculators would bet on forecasting future terrorist attacks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats Warn of Defeat  The moderate Democratic group that helped elect Bill Clinton to the White House in 1992 warned that Democrats were headed for defeat if they presented themselves as an angry, ''far left'' party fighting tax cuts and opposing the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Saudi Minister to Visit  Saudi Arabia has sent its foreign minister, Prince Saud al-Faisal, to Washington to meet with President Bush, an administration official said. The foreign minister is expected to raise with Mr. Bush his country's concern about reports that classified sections of a Congressional study about the Sept. 11, 2001, terror attacks found that senior Saudi officials had funneled hundreds of millions of dollars to organizations that might have helped pay for them.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>A Suicide or a Lynching?  A Palm Beach County judge took the extraordinary step of convening a coroner's inquest into the death of Feraris Golden, after the authorities had quickly ruled the death a suicide. Rumors began circulating that he had been lynched, and that his hands had been tied behind his back.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Judges Get a Raise  The seven Supreme Court Justices of Illinois have ordered that cost-of-living raises be paid to all state judges, including themselves. Aides to Governor Rod R. Blagojevich say this is no time for raises</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Bush Seeks Black Voters  President Bush sought to address one of his greatest political challenges, his lack of support among black voters, by speaking at the National Urban League's annual convention. Mr. Bush won only about 9 percent of the black vote in 2000.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>White House Overhauls Amtrak  The Bush administration proposed to pay for intercity passenger rail service on the same basis that it pays for mass transit, with the federal government paying part of the capital cost, but making the states pick up the rest, along with the operating deficits.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Actor's Political Future  Arnold Schwarzenegger is ''leaning strongly against'' entering the race for governor of California and will announce his decision by the end of the week. He is the most prominent of the possible Republican candidates to replace Gov. Gray Davis, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Father's Fight for Justice  The father of an Australian confined at Guantánamo Bay since his capture in Afghanistan almost two years ago urged United States officials not to try his son before a military tribunal. The son, David Hicks, 27, was with a unit of Taliban fighters that Northern Alliance troops captured in Kandahar, Afghanistan, in late 2001 and turned over to American forces.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Thousands Pay Respects To Slain Councilman  The doors of City Hall were thrown open to all who wanted to pay their respects to slain Councilman James E. Davis. Thousands did, from New York's top officials to city workers to business executives to the children who took part in Mr. Davis's marches against violence.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Skepticism About Assault  After a 41-year-old Breezy Point woman was accused of assaulting a 12-year-old Hispanic girl and charged with committing a hate crime, residents expressed disbelief that something like that could happen in their community.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Light Changes the Sound  Night on Long Island Sound might seem in some ways the most natural of moments, but scientists say that in fact night is perhaps the least natural of times, because the sky there, in the heart of the East Coast megalopolis, has been so deeply altered by artificial light.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Bob Hope  The comedian whose mastery of the comic monologue and the topical wisecrack carried him from vaudeville to Broadway musicals and then on to worldwide fame as a radio, film and television star of the first magnitude, he was 100.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Vance Hartke  The three-term Democratic senator from Indiana best known for his criticism of the American involvement in the wars in Southeast Asia, he was 84.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>Overfishing Taking Toll  Most of the earth's surface is covered by oceans, and their vastness and biological bounty were long thought to be immune to human influence. But no more. More than 70 percent of commercial fish stocks are now considered fully exploited, overfished or collapsed. And a growing number of marine species are reaching levels where extinction is considered a possibility.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Pornography Star Portraits  In Timothy Greenfield-Sanders's studio famous artists, novelists, actors and politicians come to be photographed. But now, Mr. Greenfield-Sanders has turned his attention to other stars, pornography stars to be exact, for his newest book, tentatively titled ''XXX: 30 Portraits of Porn Stars.''</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Banks Settle in Enron Case  J. P. Morgan Chase and Citigroup will pay almost $300 million in fines and penalties to settle accusations that they helped Enron conceal its true financial condition for years before the company collapsed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The settlements reached by J. P. Morgan Chase and Citigroup serve notice to other banks that they will face significant legal problems if caught engaging in transactions like the ones those banks did with Enron.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Next Stop, Baghdad  At a time when airlines are cutting service to a lot of cities, more than 20 are jockeying to land in one of the world's unlikelier destinations: Baghdad, with KLM Royal Dutch set to begin flights on Sept. 1.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rivals Pile Up on MCI  As MCI's lawyers met with federal investigators, the company came under a coordinated attack from rival phone companies, which seized on the news that MCI is the focus of a criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Land of Rising Sun Power  Striving to meet targets for reducing greenhouse gases as set out in the Kyoto Protocol, Japan now generates half of the world's solar power and has overtaken the U.S. as the leading producer of solar panels.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Facing facts about Saudi Arabia; more conservatives for the court; preserving the Corbin Building; Verlyn Klinkenborg on Bob Hope's century.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
