<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bunkered Down in Bergerac</title>
    <meta content="18BOYD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/18/opinion/18BOYD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bergerac (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyd, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">France</location>
        <location class="online_producer">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Boyd, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DC1330F93BA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bunkered Down in Bergerac</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bunkered Down in Bergerac</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Boyd</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boyd, William</byline>
      <dateline>BERGERAC, France</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Boyd Op-Ed article on heatwave in Europe describes scene in Bergerac region of southwestern France, where he fled from London in vain attempt to escape unremitting heat and unremitting talk about the weather (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the windows of our house in southwestern France I can see our two-acre vineyard of cabernet sauvignon grapes. Small but productive: we get about 7,000 bottles a year from those neat rows of vines. In the scorching temperatures that we've endured these past weeks -- daily, unchangingly in the 90's and 100's -- I've never worried about the vines: vines like heat, is the line I've repeated to myself, the hotter the better.</p>
        <p>So the other day when I saw Thierry Bernard, our young winemaker, walking through the vineyard I wasn't particularly concerned. I wandered out to meet him. He was standing in the shade of a tree glugging mineral water from a bottle and not looking very happy. ''Comment ça va, Thierry?'' I asked. He just looked at me: ''Chaud, chaud, chaud,'' was all he said. Hot, hot, hot. Even the vines were beginning to wilt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The exceptional heat has the French, like the British, talking only about the weather. The two nations, at odds for centuries, are united by a common phenomenon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the windows of our house in southwestern France I can see our two-acre vineyard of cabernet sauvignon grapes. Small but productive: we get about 7,000 bottles a year from those neat rows of vines. In the scorching temperatures that we've endured these past weeks -- daily, unchangingly in the 90's and 100's -- I've never worried about the vines: vines like heat, is the line I've repeated to myself, the hotter the better.</p>
        <p>So the other day when I saw Thierry Bernard, our young winemaker, walking through the vineyard I wasn't particularly concerned. I wandered out to meet him. He was standing in the shade of a tree glugging mineral water from a bottle and not looking very happy. ''Comment ça va, Thierry?'' I asked. He just looked at me: ''Chaud, chaud, chaud,'' was all he said. Hot, hot, hot. Even the vines were beginning to wilt.</p>
        <p>Three weeks earlier I had been in London, where the weather forecasters were announcing the impending heat wave. I hate London in hot weather. Our English house, typically, seems perversely designed not to function when it's hot: too many thick carpets and curtains, too many plump sofas and armchairs and, like a lid at the top, layers of insulation in the roof that make it cook up unendurably.</p>
        <p>And as it grew hotter, other worrying signs began to manifest themselves. Drinkers in pubs spilled noisily out onto the sidewalk, claiming it as their territory; workmen went brazenly topless; the railway system started to malfunction as rails buckled and warped (this summer, the official excuse was ''the wrong kind of heat''); conversations about the weather became tedious moans about the weather; tempers shortened noticeably. It was becoming intolerable, so I left for France with alacrity.</p>
        <p>I knew it would be hot here, too. Our housekeeper, Madame Plestan, had warned us, but I've always been able to cope in the countryside in France, even on the hottest days. After all, I was born and reared in West Africa, where there was regularly 100 percent humidity and the surrounding landscape was tropical rain forest. But I wasn't prepared for what was waiting.</p>
        <p>The French call an exceptionally hot day a ''canicule'' -- a dog day. Since I returned to France every day has been a canicule. Ninety-seven degrees was the coolest, 108 the hottest, in our little corner of the Dordogne. Now these extremes may seem modest by Saharan, or even Floridian, standards. But for southwestern France they are positively bizarre, not to say alarming.</p>
        <p>It's the lack of variation that has been so unnatural. Our weather is dominated by the Atlantic, not the Mediterranean; we are not supposed to have unending sunshine. Summer storms are the norm, mighty displays of lightning and pealing thunder and great downpours of rain and, occasionally, hail. All of which makes the countryside amazingly lush -- this is a landscape of dense, dark oak woods, of bulging hedgerows, of green pasture. There is not supposed to be anything arid or burnt-out. This summer I look around at the wilting vines and feel an uneasy sense of climate change.</p>
        <p>So how to keep our big old farmhouse cool in such temperatures? For the French, at home there is no air-conditioning. Madame Plestan showed me how it is done. You rise as early as possible, you fling open every door and window to admit what cool air the early morning provides. Then, as the sun begins to climb, you close and fasten the shutters on every door and window and switch off the lights. But you don't close the windows or doors behind the shutters -- you need currents of air to move in the darkness of your house. If you hold your hand up to the crack in your shutter the air coming through on it feels cool, even though the sunshine blasting down outside may be in the 100's.</p>
        <p>It helps having stone walls that are two feet thick, of course, but this technique keeps any house palpably cooler than the temperatures outside. In the worst heat of the afternoon, the French in the country retreat indoors to their shuttered, darkened homes and ride it out, like Londonders in the Blitz waiting for the all-clear.</p>
        <p>And it works, or at least did. In this heat wave it simply hasn't cooled down as the sun sets. On our terrace at midnight it is routinely over 90 degrees, and as the days have gone by our old house has inexorably begun to warm up. But these grumbles are nothing compared to the other problems. The plum farmers are talking of a catastrophe. The corn fields are burnt to a yellow crisp. In southern Aquitaine, some villages are completely without water and the population is being provided with 15 quarts of mineral water per person per day. Mortuaries are dangerously crammed: the heat has resulted in a death toll of 3,000, mostly older people.</p>
        <p>And the French too, like the British, now talk only about the weather, droningly, endlessly. I go into our butcher, our fishmonger, our baker and there is only one topic of conversation: La Chaleur. I could be back in London. For a brief period of time the two nations, at odds for centuries, are united by a common phenomenon.</p>
        <p>One of my diversions has been to ring up Metéo France, the national weather service, for bulletins. As the temperatures have become more extreme, so has the vocabulary. On the taped weather analysis the forecasters dourly warn of days of ''a leaden sun,'' of ''torrid, suffocating temperatures'' and even a ''stifling atmosphere where the sun crushes everything.'' The tone is minatory and worrying, and very infectious. I begin to fret about our vines.</p>
        <p>With good reason, Thierry Bernard tells me. Our vines are comparatively young, 10 years old, their root systems not fully developed. He shows me: the grapes are markedly smaller this year, the skins very thick, the bunches loosely packed. Lots of alcohol but no acidity, he says -- very hard indeed to make a good vintage for 2003. Unless it rains, of course.</p>
        <p>To save the vintage, he told me, it would have to rain over the weekend, the weekend of France's great summer public holiday, le quinze août. And indeed, a storm eventually rolled in; it poured for about an hour yesterday. Perhaps the day, if not the grapes, was saved. And what next? More sun, says Metéo France, but with more agreeable temperatures -- a mere 90 degrees. It still sounds pretty ''chaud, chaud, chaud'' to me.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor William Boyd is author, most recently, of ''Any Human Heart,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William Boyd is author, most recently, of ''Any Human Heart,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
