<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="06ART.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/06/arts/design/06ART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030607T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1494715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDA1130F935A35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="8318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums children under 12 and museum members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ''ART OF THE FIRST CITIES: THE THIRD MILLENNIUM B.C. FROM THE MEDITERRANEAN TO THE INDUS,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through Aug. 17). The most timely exhibition in years, as well as diplomatically dexterous and beautiful. It surveys the culture of the third millennium B.C., mainly centered in Mesopotamia, the crucible of Sumerian civilization, where art, architecture, law and writing developed with the rise of the earliest cities. The beginnings of a cosmopolitan art are in tiny cylinder seals and in figurines. The show is full of small objects that are monumental in concept. Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $12; $7, students and 65+ (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums children under 12 and museum members areadmitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums children under 12 and museum members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* ''ART OF THE FIRST CITIES: THE THIRD MILLENNIUM B.C. FROM THE MEDITERRANEAN TO THE INDUS,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through Aug. 17). The most timely exhibition in years, as well as diplomatically dexterous and beautiful. It surveys the culture of the third millennium B.C., mainly centered in Mesopotamia, the crucible of Sumerian civilization, where art, architecture, law and writing developed with the rise of the earliest cities. The beginnings of a cosmopolitan art are in tiny cylinder seals and in figurines. The show is full of small objects that are monumental in concept. Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $12; $7, students and 65+ (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''EGYPT REBORN: ART FOR ETERNITY,'' Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 (permanent installation). The second and final phase in the museum's reinstallation of its world-  renowned holdings of ancient Egyptian art, this dazzling display rounds up more than 600 objects -- from king-and-queen-size monuments to tiny rings and amulets -- from the predynastic period to the 18th dynasty. Together with the first phase, which opened in 1993 and covers later Egyptian art, visitors will now be able to trace the entire course of this brilliant and complex civilization from its beginnings to its absorption by the Roman Empire in 30 B.C. The heart of the new installation is an introductory gallery that provides a wonderful summation, with a survey of sculptural styles and displays of weapons, pottery, cosmetics, jewelry, furniture and funerary arts. The adjacent galleries are devoted to an extensive chronological survey. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 11 p.m. the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $6; $3, students and 62+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''MANET/VELÁZQUEZ: THE FRENCH TASTE FOR SPANISH PAINTING,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710 (through June 29). The Met has clearly called in every chip to make this show spectacular. The first rooms are a virtual survey of great Spanish painting of the 17th and 18th centuries; after that comes a virtual Manet retrospective, with some Degas and Courbet thrown in for good measure; then a virtual 19th-century American overview of the most gifted portraitists influenced by Spanish painting via Manet, Degas and Courbet: Eakins, Chase, Sargent and Whistler. The thesis of Spanish influence on French art is hardly new, but it is explored in such precise and fresh detail, discreetly, without pushing comparisons (in that respect it's not like ''Matisse Picasso'' at the Modern, notwithstanding the coincidental titled pairings) that you would have to be churlish not to leave edified and amazed. Hours and admission: See above (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''RAFAEL TUFINO: PAINTER OF THE PEOPLE,'' El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272 (through Aug. 24). Mr. Tufino was born in Brooklyn in 1930, but has spent most of his life in Puerto Rico. There are many individual images to savor in this retrospective of his paintings and prints, but it is Mr. Tufino himself who is radiant. His cosmopolitan presence in Puerto Rico and New York has encouraged generations of artists prone to view themselves as confined to a backwater, helping them to feel part of a larger world and to feel that the world they lived in is larger than they knew. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, to 9 p.m. Admission: $7; $3 for students and 65+ (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>''ANDY WARHOL: SCREEN TESTS,'' Museum of Modern Art, Queens, 4520 33rd Street, at Queens Boulevard, Long Island City, (212) 708-9400 (through Sept. 1). From 1964 to 1966, Warhol shot 500 short, silent, black-and-white films of artists, musicians, actors, writers, filmmakers, models, curators, celebrities and hangers-on at the Factory. The Modern's department of film and media has restored 277 of these screen tests, representing some 34 hours of watching time, and now 28 are being shown continuously on six screens. The subjects include Baby Jane Holzer, Salvador Dalí, James Rosenquist, Dennis Hopper, Cass Elliott and Susan Sontag -- but they are of variable interest. By shooting the films at one speed and playing them more slowly, Warhol exposed the mechanics of discomposure and charisma. Some people are fascinating as they lose it; others are not. It has nothing to do with handsomeness, histrionics, coolness, slimness, trying or giving up. The typology of charisma is as elusive as the typology of criminality. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m; to 7:45 p.m. on Fridays. Admission: $6; $4.25 for students and 65+ (Sarah Boxer).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>''AFTERSHOCK: THE LEGACY OF THE READYMADE IN POSTWAR AND CONTEMPORARY AMERICAN ART,'' Dickinson Roundell, 19 East 66th Street, (212) 772-8088 (through June 20). The readymade was the Dada brain child of Marcel Duchamp, who presides over this crowded group show of work by American artists, old and young, he has inspired. Several, like Jasper Johns and Sherrie Levine, are represented by classic pieces that retain their charisma even in an overcrowded installation (Cotter),</p>
        <p>* ''THE HEART OF THE MATTER: THE STILL LIFES OF MARSDEN HARTLEY,'' Berry-Hill, 11 East 70th Street, (212) 744-2300 (through June 27). This display of nearly 60 works is said to be the first ever devoted entirely to Hartley's still lifes. Glowingly alive, varying in style from abstraction to realism and in subject from delicate floral arrangements to the depiction of fish, a dead bird and ladies' gloves, they were painted with the same power and élan that went into his intense, vibrant landscapes (Glueck).</p>
        <p>FRANZ KLINE, C&amp;M Arts, 45 East 78th Street, (212) 861-0020 (through June 20). Kline was the archetypal Abstract Expressionist, painter of the big, explosive gesture. But his paintings are also exquisitely elegant, as this nicely installed nine-piece show of black-and-white works on paper and canvas shows. While the wide swaths of black that tumble like giant logs across ''Harleman'' suggest impulsive violence, the composition tells a story of order and chaos captured in a moment of perfect equilibrium (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SALLY MICHEL, MILTON AVERY: A PORTRAIT,'' Knoedler &amp; Company, 19 East 70th Street, (212) 794-0550 (through June 27). Also known as Mrs. Milton Avery, the widow of the artist, Sally Michel used her own name as a painter in her own right. This warm memorial tribute to Michel and Avery mounts a group of informal, private portraits of each artist done by the other. A wall of Avery by Michel, who died in January, shows him painting, napping, smoking, reading, thinking, leaning. A facing wall of portraits by Avery (1885-1965) shows Michel smiling, mothering their daughter, March, wearing a new hat and painting a portrait of her husband. This small show is an engaging celebration of a highly productive relationship (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''PUERTO RICAN LIGHT: JENNIFER ALLORA AND GUILLERMO CALZADILLA,'' Americas Society Gallery, 680 Park Avenue, at 68th Street, (212) 249-8950 (through July 20). Ms. Allora and Mr. Calzadilla are young conceptual artist-collaborators who divide their time between Puerto Rico and New York, and this bring both places together. The centerpiece is a 1965 fluorscent sculpture by Dan Flavin titled ''Puerto Rican Light (to Jeanie Blake),'' which in this case derives its illumnating power from solar energy gathered in San Juan and stored in batteries in the gallery (Cotter).</p>
        <p>CINDY SHERMAN, ''Centerfolds, 1981,'' Skarstedt Fine Art, 1018 Madison Avenue, at 78th Street, (212) 737-2060 (through June 14). A series of takeoffs on the centerfolds beloved of men's magazines, these life-size photographs, taken more than 20 years ago, portray Ms. Sherman in poses that depart from sex kitten clichés. Besides her clothes and expressions, the moods of the pictures are charged by the use of gels that cast the images in colors appropriate to their narratives; kitschy orange, eerie green. More than simple spoofs of the stereotypes promulgated by the magazines, these photographs also manage to suggest the ambiguities of women playing gender cliché roles (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* JOSEF ALBERS, ''Homage to Color,'' PaceWildenstein, 32 East 57th Street, (212) 421-3292 (through June 14). Albers (1888-1976) was a well known abstract painter and maker of stained glass. He was also a born pedagogue, who combined the analytical acuity of a biochemist and the devotional patience of a priest. The 30 paintings here are characteristic of the many chromatic studies he produced in a longterm research project to determine, through art, all the possible implications of a single word: vision. Together they offer a perfectly unecstatic demonstration of how luminous color can be (Cotter).</p>
        <p>ERIC FREEMAN, Mary Boone Gallery, 745 Fifth Avenue, (212) 752-2929 (through June 28). Painting doesn't get much more retinal than Mr. Freeman's large, sensuous compositions of tubular bands of neon-bright color. Rothkoesque but devoid of cosmic consciousness, they are so aggressively decorative that they verge on decadence (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''MARIKO MORI: WAVE UFO,'' atrium at 590 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 980-4575 (through July 31). Of late, this Japanese artist, whose past work blended science fiction, fashion and esoteric Buddhism, has been designing interactive spiritual hardware, and this pod-like container is her most ambitious piece so far. It accommodates three electrode-wired participants at a time, who are treated to a son-et-lumière projection of their brain waves, followed by an eye-rinsing aurora borealis of Ms. Mori's devising. The work is high-tech, fun while it lasts, and must have cost someone a fortune to produce (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* AMY MYERS, Danese, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 223-2227 (through June 27). Ms. Myers makes an impressive New York solo debut with this show of large drawings. The single, big, complicated, diagrammatic structures in each are made of countless draftsmanly parts meticulously arranged. They suggest many concrete things -- space ships, ectoplasmic apparitions, sexual organs, mandalas -- but remain emenations of intensely personal exercise in hard labor and serious play (Cotter).</p>
        <p>JEANNE SILVERTHORNE, McKee Gallery, 745 Fifth Avenue, (212) 688-5951 (through June 20). Rubber is Ms. Silverthorne's medium and muse. Several black, cast rubber, faux-antique picture frames containing white rubber cast in organic or Cubist forms play the sculptural against the pictorial. More interesting are installations of framed works with electrical and plumbing hardware cast in black rubber added; they are like frustration dreams about stoppages in the flow of feeling (Johnson).</p>
        <p>TOM WESSELMANN, ''The Great American 60's,'' Maxwell Davidson, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 759-7555 (through June 13). This selection of works from the 1960's includes one of the Pop Art master's classic Great American Nude apartment paintings -- real telephone and radiator included -- and seductive small studies of female body parts: pillowy lips, nubile breasts and coy painted toes (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>JULES DE BALINCOURT, ''Land of Many Uses,'' LFL Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, (212) 989-7700 (through June 14). Mr. de Balincourt's amusing, handmade paintings and sculpture look like the efforts of a self-taught neo-hippie. A life-size treehouse slyly spoofs ''Whole Earth Catalog''-style recycling and communalism. A big, grungy model of the artist's Los Angeles neighborhood periodically floods, illustrating the effects of global warming. Like Chris Johanson, Mr. de Balincourt projects a rueful awareness of the generation gap in which he's caught: between countercultural optimism and world-weary realism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ANNETTE BEZOR, Florence Lynch, 531-539 West 25th Street, (212) 924-3290 (through June 21). Primal essence or social construction? Big heads of a sexy woman painted in a simplifying, cartoonish style by this Australian artist invite meditation on the feminine mystique. With pouty lips and sultry eyes, Ms. Bezor's dream girls, derived from high art and mass media, are seductive Warholian sphinxes (Johnson).</p>
        <p>CLARINA BEZZOLA, ''Gathering,'' Cynthia Broan, 423 West 14th Street, (212) 633-6525 (through June 14). Stuffed fabric spills from a hole in each of a series of tubular ceramic objects, which are arranged on the green-painted floor around a fake-stone tower. What this tableau means as a whole remains a mystery, but the psycho-sexual import of the ejaculating cylinders is unmistakable (Johnson).</p>
        <p>BART DOMBURG, Gasser &amp; Grunert, 524 West 19th Street, (212) 807-9494 (through June 28). With a careful but not too fussy touch, this Dutch painter makes pictures of land, sea and architecture that exude a muted mournfulness. With titles alluding to the Holocaust, they are actually Gerhard Richter-style history paintings. ''Schuhprüfstrecke,'' the image of a stony plot framed by curbstone was a track where concentration camp prisoners were forced to test the durability of shoes (Johnson).</p>
        <p>OLAFUR ELIASSON, Tanya Bonakdar, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 414-4144 (through June 14). Denmark's most celebrated contemporary artist presents two installations, one elegantly spare, the other busily cluttered. The first, in which revolving drum-shaped lanterns cast slowly sweeping bands of light, is soothingly meditative. The second, ''Modelroom,'' simulates the workshop of a visionary architect, sculptor and philosopher. Scores of small domes, globes and polyhedrons stock an enclosure of obliquely angled shelves, evoking crackpot dreams of utopian rationalism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ELGER ESSER, Sonnabend, 536 West 22nd Street, (212) 627-1018 (through June 28). A former student of the balefully influential Bernd and Hilla Becher, Mr. Esser is a high-concept photographer, but his large color pictures of spectacular coastal geology are nevertheless visually stunning and romantically affecting. They also look slightly antique, as is appropriate, since they are based on descriptions and sketches of sites in Normandy by Guy de Maupassant, whom Gustave Flaubert had asked to help in his research for a novel about a pair of failed amateur geologists (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DAN FLAVIN, Paula Cooper, 534 West 21st Street, (212) 255-1105 (through June 30). Six of Flavin's most radically simplified fluorescent light sculptures turn this spacious gallery into an oasis of coolly luminous quietude that verges on ecclesiastical. Believers will feel blessed. Skeptics may reason that just about any tastefully spare arrangement of lights in such a space would have a similarly dramatic effect. Either way, the show speaks volumes about the idealism of radically materialist art in the 60's (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JOSEPH GRIGELY, ''Vox Populi,'' Cohan Leslie and Browne, 138 10th Avenue, at 18th Street, (212) 206-8710 (through June 14). Mr. Grigely, who is deaf, has made voice, speech, hearing and listening the central concerns of his art. This installation features a set of white life-size sculptures of dogs, who appear to be listening to an audio recording of people randomly conversing. ''Blueberry Surprise,'' a one-page 45,000-word transcription of notes people have written to the artist, is like a warm bath for anyone who loves the poetry of ordinary talk (Johnson).</p>
        <p>KAHN &amp; SELESNICK, ''City of Salt,'' Yancey Richardson, 535 West 22nd Street, (646) 230-9610 (through July 3). Nicholas Kahn and Richard Selesnick's latest photographic campaign looks like something produced by Monty Python under the influence of Sufism. Accompanied by long mythic texts, their panoramic, faux-antique digital prints envision Orientalist scenes of magical adventure, mind-expanding allegory and goofy absurdity. ''City of Salt,'' built of salt, sugar and clay in the gallery, is less interesting, but it does evoke the idea of lost mystic wisdom (Johnson).</p>
        <p>R. L. KAPLAN, ''Paintings from the 80's,'' Edward Thorp, 210 11th Avenue, at 24th Street, (212) 691-6565 (through June 28). This 63-year-old Brooklyn-born painter is self-taught, but his paintings don't look like Outsider art. Surrealistic, political and painted in a simplifying style, his medium-large pictures of fighting birds, gridded flags, imperial architecture, regal dogs and empty parks allegorize international politics in an enigmatic, mournful mood (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* TONY OURSLER, Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100 (through June 21). Mr. Oursler returns to the deceptively simple device that made him famous, and has his best exhibition in years. Mobile human features are video-projected in luridly over-ripe color onto simple, bulbous white sculptures. Giant mismatched eyes, fat lips and big, snaggly teeth (no noses) make up weird, comical and oddly endearing characters. Their angry, anxious, erotic and nonsensical monologues enhance feelings of emotional confusion and vulnerability (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JOEL SHAPIRO, PaceWildenstein, 534 West 25th Street, (212) 929-7000 (through July). If the sculpture of Donald Judd and Elie Nadelmann had children, they might grow up to look like the best works in Mr. Shapiro's exhibition. They are the ones beautifully fabricated in various woods: airy, floating jumbles of tenuously connected boxes that visually resolve from certain angles into figures jauntily dancing or assuming graceful yoga postures. A pair of giant bronzes, however, look ponderous and overscaled (Johnson).</p>
        <p>FRANK STELLA, Paul Kasmin, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474 (through June 28). Big, unpainted assemblages of steel pipe bent into curves, spirals and serpentine forms, as well as sheet metal and occasional punctuations of plastic materials, fill the gallery with aggressive energy. Mr. Stella's Cubist blend of biomorphic and geometric forms has a vaguely space-age look, but it is too familiar to make these works as spectacularly surprising as he wants them to be. (Johnson).</p>
        <p>THOMAS TROSCH, ''The Charming Mr. Tantalus,'' Fredericks Freiser, 504 West 22nd Street, (212) 633-6555 (through June 14). Despite its originally revolutionary impulses, Modernist painting now serves mainly to decorate the homes of the comfortably wealthy. This irony animates the zany paintings of Mr. Trosch, who, splattering and troweling garishly hued paint like a rebellious child of Pollock and Hofmann, makes satiric pictures of doll-like ladies in palatial white rooms festooned by grid and drip paintings (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JEFF WHETSTONE, ''Zoolatry,'' Wallspace, 547 West 27th Street, (212) 594-9478 (through June 21). Mr. Whetstone's understated black-and-white photographs present centered overhead views of circular containers, each holding an animal -- opossum, raccoon, bat, lizard, several kinds of snakes -- that the former zoology student caught with his own hands in the woods of Kentucky or North Carolina. He holds them long enough to photograph with his 8-by-10 camera and then releases them (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>RUDY BURCKHARDT, New York Studio School, 8 West Eighth Street, Greenwich Village, (212)673-6466 (through June 21). This show of photographs and paintings by the Swiss-born photographer and filmmaker, who immigrated here in 1935, was assembled by the poet Vincent Katz. It focuses on Burckhardt's involvement with the forests, ponds, flowers and individual trees of Deer Isle, Maine. His lovely, lyrical compositions range from a pastoral stream meandering through marsh grass to close views of lichen-covered trees. But when he tried to capture in oil what his lens recorded so well, the results are less than salubrious (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''HOMELAND,'' Art Gallery of the Graduate Center, City University of New York, 365 Fifth Avenue, at 34th Street, (212) 431-1737 (through June 29). This shrewdly entertaining group show, organized by a quintet of young curators in the Whitney Museum of American Art Independent Study Program, addresses the present American political moment. Pieces from the 1980's and 90's acknowledge a history of activist Conceptualism, but most of the work is new and includes a web project that maps out surveillance-free paths through Manhattan, a commemorative Enron monument and a Muslim call to prayer adapted from an alarm clock (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''THE NEW WORLD'S OLD WORLD: PHOTOGRAPHIC VIEWS OF ANCIENT AMERICA,'' AXA Gallery, 787 Seventh Avenue, at 51st Street, (212) 554-4818 (through July 19). From the mid-19th century onward photography played many roles in the frontier terrorities of North and South America: as a scientific intrument, a surveillance device, a definer of cultural identity and an aesthetic form. This beautiful show both documents those uses and offers a sustained meditation on the shadow-play of picture-taking and politics (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''NOGUCHI: CONTOURS,'' UBS PaineWebber Art Galleries, 1285 Avenue of the Americas, at 51st Street, (212) 713-2885 (through June 20). Organized by the Noguchi Foundation's curator, Bonnie Rychlak, this show stresses the role of the body in the sculptor's work. It spans the period 1926 to 1982, and the pieces range from portrait heads to the paper-on-silk scroll drawings that Noguchi (1904-1988) made during an early visit to China (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''RANDOM ORDER,'' White Columns, 320 West 13th Street, West Village, (212) 924-4212 (through June 15). This appealing gathering of works that personalize mathematical or scientific concepts includes Jennifer Dailey's colored dot grids; Pamela Harris's clusters of curvy marks in pastel and charcoal; Tohru Kanayama's tiny Op Art-like digital prints; Henry Brown's bright, hard-edged, geometric paintings; John O'Connor's gestural, bio-linguistic charts; Taney Roniger's finely perforated metallic panels; Marc Brotherton's painted diagrams; Roland Thompson's painted mazes; and Karla Hoepfner's painterly violations of inked graphs (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* DARIO ROBLETO, ''Say Goodbye to Substance'' Whitney Museum of American Art at Altria, 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917) 663-2453 (through July 3). Mr. Robleto, who is 31 and lives in San Antonio, makes his New York solo debut with a show that suggests a Nobel Prize-worthy science fair project. Its small, laboriously handcrafted sculptures are made from, among many other things, plaster, driftwood, homemade crystals, antibiotics, prehistoric whalebone dust, gunpowder and melted vinyl recordings of the Beatles, Black Sabbath and Tammy Wynette. Its themes include utopian thinking, space travel, pop culture and American childhood, all viewed with an attitude of sunny despair (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* ''MATTHEW BARNEY: THE CREMASTER CYCLE,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500 (through Wednesday). The most anticipated show by any American artist to emerge in a decade or more. ''Cremaster,'' Mr. Barney's nine-year, five-film project, here presented whole for the first time, is an inspired benchmark of ambition, scope and forthright provocation for art in the new century. Mr. Barney has brought to the art world a new freedom to explore narrative. He has introduced a new repertory of materials -- gooey, strange, malleable and synthetic -- that nobody thought of as germane before. Never mind that the films and many (not all) of his related sculptures, installations and photographs are very beautiful. The show, an installation itself, brings them together. The earliest ''Cremaster'' sculptures are film props, cobbled into installations that don't jell. But the latest are better: twin steel towers framed in plastic, a suite of abstract sculptures derived from automobile chassis. Vaseline and plastic combine with cement and steel -- pink and gray, rough and smooth, hard and soft -- the materials sustaining a narrative of formal eloquence. Hours: Saturdays through Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m. Admission: $15; $10, students and 65+ (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>JOHN CEDERQUIST, ''Furniture That Builds Itself,'' Franklin Parrasch, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 246-5360 (through tomorrow). Mr. Cederquist's beautifully made woodworks are simultaneously functional pieces of furniture and zany cartoons in two and three dimensions (Johnson).</p>
        <p>WENDY EWALD, ''Secret Games,'' Queens Museum of Art, Flushing Meadows Corona Park, (718) 529-9700 (through Sunday). For three decades, Ms. Ewald has been teaching and collaborating with children in some of the world's more remote and impoverished places. Ms. Ewald herself is a capable photojournalist, but the best parts of this retrospective are the photographs taken by children. Many are as beautiful, strange and heartbreaking as anything by Diane Arbus, Nan Goldin or other chroniclers of the rough poetry of real life. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; $2.50, students and 55+ (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''CHRISTIAN SCHAD AND THE NEUE SACHLICHKEIT,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200 (through Monday). Schad's career effectively lasted only 15 years, from around 1915 to 1930, and for just two or three of those years was he doing what deserves to be remembered now. Not much time. But just enough. Schad at his mordant best precisely captured an anxious culture affected by war and the threat of it: his bloodless portraits in Vienna and Berlin suggest deep unease and foreboding beneath porcelain surfaces. They are explicitly unemotional, even when they are frankly erotic, as they frequently are. His drawings, akin to some done by Dix and Grosz, shy away from the issues of class conflict that inflamed both of those other artists. To the end, Schad remained aloof. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7, students and 65+ (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''PAUL SIETSEMA: EMPIRE,'' Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3600 (through Sunday). This talented Los Angeles artist takes art-about-art to new extremes of beauty, complexity and originality, but also obscurity. The components of his ambitious New York debut include marvelous outsiderish, language-laced collage-drawings and two meticulously hand-made doll-house-like models -- one of the New York apartment of the great 20th-century art critic Clement Greenberg, the other of an 18th-century Rococo salon. These works serve as road maps to the main event: a mysterious silent film that ruminates on the inner sanctums of two kinds of anciens régimes and their visual styles while applying Greenbergian formalism in cinematic terms. A working knowledge of the critic's aesthetic principles helps. Hours: Tuesdays through Thursdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 9 p.m. Admission: $12; $9.50, students and 62+ (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''WEAVING CHINA'S PAST: THE AMY S. CLAGUE COLLECTION OF CHINESE TEXTILES,'' China Institute Gallery, 125 East 65th Street, (212) 744-8181 (through tomorrow). This gallery has a sterling record in presenting small, fine-tuned scholarly shows and this one, imported from the Phoenix Art Museum, exactly fits the description. With precious examples of silk brocades, tapestries and embroideries, including Buddhist ritual pieces, dating from the Jin to Qing dynasty, it gives a vivid sense of the material past in a powerful imperial culture (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 7, 2003, Saturday  A listing in the Art Guide in Weekend yesterday for the Dickinson Roundell gallery at 19 East 66th Street in Manhattan misstated the telephone number. It is (212) 772-8083.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 7, 2003, Saturday</p>
        <p>A listing in the Art Guide in Weekend yesterday for the Dickinson Roundell gallery at 19 East 66th Street in Manhattan misstated the telephone number. It is (212) 772-8083.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
