<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Green Old Party?</title>
    <meta content="23REIL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/23/opinion/23REIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1491107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reilly, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atwater, Lee (1951-91)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Reilly, William K</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Christine Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DC1631F930A15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Green Old Party?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Green Old Party?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William K. Reilly</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reilly, William K</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by William K Reilly, former EPA administrator and now chairman of World Wildlife Fund, recalls late Republican adviser Lee Atwater saying his appointment was about suburban women and their votes; says coverage of departure of Admr Christine Whitman, most prominent suburban woman in this Bush administration, ignores some of her achievements, adding to perception of administration as unfriendly to environment; notes that three decades of polls find Americans overwhelmingly want clean environment, but vigorous regulation is suspect if not anathema to many conservatives, and EPA decisions necessarily hit hard at Republican base (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lee Atwater, who was the Karl Rove of George H. W. Bush's 1988 presidential campaign, once explained to me why he supported one of my controversial decisions as administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency: ''To me,'' he said, ''your appointment is about suburban women. We need 'em. And they care a lot about your issue.''</p>
        <p>As Christie Whitman, the most prominent suburban woman in the Bush administration, steps down at E.P.A., the coverage primarily concerns the issues on which she was overruled. This ignores some of her significant achievements -- the ''brownfields'' legislation that will return thousands of derelict urban sites to productive use, and the decision to reduce the pollutants from diesel fuels. Yet again a Republican administration is widely seen as unfriendly to the environment, and its E.P.A. administrator as a casualty of neglect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are many good reasons for the Bush team to give the environment a higher priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lee Atwater, who was the Karl Rove of George H. W. Bush's 1988 presidential campaign, once explained to me why he supported one of my controversial decisions as administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency: ''To me,'' he said, ''your appointment is about suburban women. We need 'em. And they care a lot about your issue.''</p>
        <p>As Christie Whitman, the most prominent suburban woman in the Bush administration, steps down at E.P.A., the coverage primarily concerns the issues on which she was overruled. This ignores some of her significant achievements -- the ''brownfields'' legislation that will return thousands of derelict urban sites to productive use, and the decision to reduce the pollutants from diesel fuels. Yet again a Republican administration is widely seen as unfriendly to the environment, and its E.P.A. administrator as a casualty of neglect.</p>
        <p>There are political strategists within the party who say it doesn't matter, that environmentalists won't credit a Republican administration no matter how green, and certainly won't vote for one. That may well be true. Nevertheless, there are many good reasons for the Bush team to give the environment a higher priority.</p>
        <p>For three decades polls have consistently revealed lopsided majorities -- 80 percent-plus -- in favor of maintaining or strengthening clean air and water laws. Whether people vote the environment or not, and I admit most don't, they still want it protected and improved.</p>
        <p>The problem, of course, is that vigorous environmental protection involves regulation, which is suspect if not anathema to many conservatives. And E.P.A. decisions necessarily hit elements of the Republican base hardest: manufacturers and other businesses, farmers, land developers. In fact, the first thing an E.P.A. administrator learns is not to antagonize more than one major industry at a time: if big oil is to be hit this week, big autos had better be deferred until next week.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, there are several fronts on which the Bush administration could address growing problems that not only affect people around the world, but also threaten American economic productivity.</p>
        <p>For example, I agree that the Kyoto protocol on greenhouse gases, as drafted, is incomplete. However, the United States could come back to the table and reshape the protocol. A sustained effort to make realistic and affordable United States greenhouse gas reductions, accompanied by mandatory monitoring and reporting of emissions by our utilities and other major emitters, would have the support of key United States companies. American re-engagement in Kyoto could also help prompt fast-growing developing countries like China, which are not now constrained by Kyoto, to sign on.</p>
        <p>New studies have come out with shocking information about the depletion of the world's oceans, driven in large part by European subsidies to fleets and the scouring of the seas by Japan and other countries. It would benefit America's fishing industry, as well as the planet, to push for new marine sanctuaries and new international conservation agreements to end overfishing and phase out subsidies.</p>
        <p>America's lakes and estuaries are major sources of drinking water and vital economic generators through tourism. Washington could do more to get states, localities and nongovernmental organizations to reduce pollution runoff, control overfishing, preserve wetlands and protect shorelines. Especially vulnerable are Chesapeake Bay, Long Island Sound, the Gulf of Mexico and the Great Lakes.</p>
        <p>And while the Bush administration has played a serious role in conservation efforts in the Everglades and national parks, it could build on that to preserve more of our country's special places. For one, it could give more support to local land trusts, which can help keep family farms and ranches in business while ensuring that the land won't be turned into subdivisions.</p>
        <p>To suburban mothers -- not to mention young people, Europeans and much of the rest of the world -- to be anti-environment is to be on the wrong side of history. The Bush administration can reclaim Republican leadership on an issue that should not be seen as belonging to one ideology or one party.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency in the George H. W. Bush administration, is president of Aqua International Partners and chairman of the World Wildlife Fund.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency in the George H. W. Bush administration, is president of Aqua International Partners and chairman of the World Wildlife Fund.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
