<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="25FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1499654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D9133BF936A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>6 British Soldiers Killed By Iraqi Gunmen in South  Iraqi gunmen killed six British soldiers in southern Iraq as violence and unrest spread to areas of the country that had been largely quiet since the war ended almost two months ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The United States military has cordoned off part of an Iraqi village near the Syrian border that was hit in a deadly aerial assault last week and evicted five families whose houses were bombed in the attack.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>6 British Soldiers Killed By Iraqi Gunmen in South  Iraqi gunmen killed six British soldiers in southern Iraq as violence and unrest spread to areas of the country that had been largely quiet since the war ended almost two months ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The United States military has cordoned off part of an Iraqi village near the Syrian border that was hit in a deadly aerial assault last week and evicted five families whose houses were bombed in the attack.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A top State Department expert on chemical and biological weapons told Congress in closed-door hearings last week that he had been pressured to tailor his analysis on Iraq and other matters to conform to the Bush administration's agenda, several congressional officials said.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>The senior lieutenant to Saddam Hussein who was detained in Iraq last week had obtained Belarussian passports for himself and others, possibly including Mr. Hussein's sons, United States government officials said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Aid Package for Pakistan  President Bush offered Pakistan a tightly conditioned package of $3 billion in aid that seemed intended to bolster an unsteady ally that only two years ago was still under strict American sanctions.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Beijing Has SARS Under Control  The World Health Organization said that Beijing had effectively conquered SARS, signaling victory over the disease in the country where it originated and took the most lives.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>China and India in Border Talks  India emphasized that Tibet is part of China and China agreed to begin trading with India's northeastern state of Sikkim, as the world's two most populous countries tiptoed toward a settlement of their politically explosive border disputes.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Israeli Arabs Charged  Five Israeli Arabs were charged with funneling an estimated $10 million to the Islamic group Hamas.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Tough Medicine for Argentina  Argentina and the International Monetary Fund agreed to begin negotiating a multiyear agreement that will force the new government to make politically unpopular decisions the country has been avoiding for nearly two years.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>California Is Struggling To Resolve Budget Deficit  California's legislative leaders are nowhere near agreement on how to address the state's $38 billion two-year deficit. The constitutional deadline for passage of a state budget is less than a week away.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Child Tax Credit Delayed  Republican Senate leaders said that because of the press of Medicare legislation, there would be no agreement with the House this month to increase the child tax credit for 6.5 million low-income families.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Senate Moves to Alter Rules  Senate Republicans approved a proposal to make it easier to break filibusters that prevent votes on administration nominations. Federal judicial candidates and future Supreme Court nominees stand to gain.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Store Settles Employee Dispute  Abercrombie &amp; Fitch, the retailer for the college set, has agreed to pay $2.2 million to settle an investigation in which California accused it of illegally requiring employees to purchase and wear its apparel.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Chicago Has a Few Questions  Chicago is building and naming a park for Jean Baptiste Point DuSable. But it can't decide if he really is the city's sole founder. Or what he looked like.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Hormone's Role in Cancer  New findings from a study that linked postmenopausal hormone therapy to an increased risk of breast cancer reveal that the combination of hormones used in a common type of therapy makes tumors harder to detect.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mixed Findings for Drug  A drug that doctors had hoped might prevent prostate cancer has been found to be more effective than expected, but also potentially more dangerous.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>World Emissions Agreement  An array of industrialized and developing countries agreed on the outline of a joint research program aimed at capturing and storing carbon dioxide, the main smokestack emission linked to global warming.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>New Panel to Review Child Welfare Agency  New Jersey agreed to one of the most sweeping transfers of authority ever to a court-mandated overseer. The five-member panel will help state officials develop a detailed plan to change the state's embattled child welfare agency, setting concrete targets and time frames for improvements in at least 11 separate areas of child welfare.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Agreement Near on Budget  Mayor Bloomberg and the City Council neared a budget agreement in which the mayor agreed to cut fewer city services and the Council to scale back some demands.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Conference Votes to Expand  The presidents of universities in the Atlantic Coast Conference voted 7-2 to invite the University of Miami and Virginia Tech to join the A.C.C., according to a person with intimate knowledge of the vote. They excluded Syracuse and Boston College in a surprising last-minute move.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>New York Math Scores Voided  New York State's education commissioner, Richard P. Mills, set aside the results of last week's Math A Regents exam for seniors and juniors. Many educators had described the test, which is required for graduation, as inordinately difficult.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Colleges Respond to Ruling  Universities across the country began grappling with the meaning of the Supreme Court rulings on affirmative action.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Reduced Fat in City Meals  The New York City Education Department is reducing the fat content in the 800,000 meals it serves daily and banning sugary snacks from school vending machines.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Verizon Approves Cell Plan  Verizon Wireless will drop its opposition to a federal plan to allow callers to keep their wireless phone numbers when they switch carriers. Other mobile phone operators will probably accept the arrangement.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Oracle Amends Offer  While persisting in its hostile bid to acquire PeopleSoft, Oracle dropped one condition of the offer: its objection to PeopleSoft's latest move to acquire J. D. Edwards, a rival business software maker.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Step Toward Asbestos Fund  Senators reached a compromise that would make it easier for asbestos victims to qualify for payments from a proposed trust fund. The fund would end asbestos lawsuits and pay according to a set schedule.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Polo Ralph Lauren Gets License  A feud over the Lauren/Ralph Lauren women's line ended when Jones Apparel threw the license back to Polo Ralph Lauren.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Doing it right in Congo; Internet filters and free speech; Fixing Albany: a broken Legislature.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman and Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
