<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A List Some Carmakers Don't Covet</title>
    <meta content="18AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/18/business/18AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Volvo Ab</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2D71E3AF93BA25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A List Some Carmakers Don't Covet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A List Some Carmakers Don't Covet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many popular sports utility vehicles fare the worst in EPA's rating of vehicles according to amount of tailpipe pollutants that contribute to smog, which can worsen asthma and lead to cancer and lung damage; car makers point out that even for lowest-rated vehicles, emissions of smog-forming pollutants, such as hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide, are substantially lower than in past and that by end of decade, regulations will be phased out that currently allow medium and large sports utilities and pickups to have greater emissions of airborne pollutants than cars; critics say automakers could do more to reduce emissions right away, citing higher scores achieved by small SUV's like Honda Element and Volve XC 90; photos; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Automakers are obsessed with ratings, from customer satisfaction to how many hours it takes workers to assemble a car. But there is at least one list many do not like to talk about.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency rates every vehicle according to the amount of pollutants coming out of the tailpipe that contribute to smog, which can worsen asthma and lead to cancer and lung damage. Many popular sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks rank at the bottom on the 0-to-10 scale. Among them are a number of recently introduced -- and highly profitable -- models.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many popular sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks rank at the bottom on the Environmental Protection Agency's 0-to-10 scale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Automakers are obsessed with ratings, from customer satisfaction to how many hours it takes workers to assemble a car. But there is at least one list many do not like to talk about.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency rates every vehicle according to the amount of pollutants coming out of the tailpipe that contribute to smog, which can worsen asthma and lead to cancer and lung damage. Many popular sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks rank at the bottom on the 0-to-10 scale. Among them are a number of recently introduced -- and highly profitable -- models.</p>
        <p>Vehicles with ratings from 0 to 4 include four pickup trucks -- the Ford F-150, Chevrolet Silverado, Dodge Ram and GMC Sierra -- as well as sport utilities, including the Mercedes M class, Chevrolet Tahoe and Suburban, Cadillac Escalade, GMC Yukon and Lincoln Navigator.</p>
        <p>Toyota, which has been praised by environmentalists for its fuel-efficient hybrid car, the Prius, also sells three sport utility vehicles that receive low ratings: the Sequoia, the Land Cruiser and the LX 470 from its Lexus division.</p>
        <p>The low ratings mean that these vehicles emit at best 21 pounds of pollutants for every 15,000 miles driven, the E.P.A. says, and have 2 to 10 times the emissions of most Honda Civics. (The ratings are posted at epa.gov/greenvehicles.)</p>
        <p>Carmakers point out that even for the lowest-rated vehicles, emissions of smog-forming pollutants -- chemicals like hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide as well as soot -- are substantially lower than in the past. And by the end of the decade, regulations will be phased out that currently allow medium and large sport utilities and pickups to have greater emissions of airborne pollutants than do cars.</p>
        <p>''By next year, 2004, cars and trucks will run 99 percent cleaner than they did in the 60's,'' William Clay Ford Jr., chairman and chief executive of the Ford Motor Company, said in a speech last month.</p>
        <p>Even so, environmentalists say the air would be far cleaner were it not for the growing popularity of large vehicles. A recent study by one group, the Union of Concerned Scientists, showed that the average light truck -- a category that includes sport utilities, minivans and pickups -- emits nearly 2.5 times the smog-forming pollutants of the average car and nearly 1.5 times the global-warming gases.</p>
        <p>The critics say that automakers could do more to reduce emissions right away, pointing to small sport utilities like the Honda Element and the Volvo XC 90 that score higher in the E.P.A. ratings. The improvement can be accomplished by adding or upgrading various technologies, including the catalytic converter, or by improving fuel economy.</p>
        <p>Honda performed the best over all in the study by the Union of Concerned Scientists, in part because it makes fewer large vehicles than its competitors. A push by Ford to reduce the emissions of its vehicles ahead of the regulatory deadlines made it the highest rated of the Big Three.</p>
        <p>Of greatest concern to environmental groups is that vehicles with low scores on the E.P.A. scale also consume the most gasoline and, therefore, emit larger amounts of carbon dioxide, which many scientists consider a major contributor to global warming. While filtration and engine technology have sharply reduced emissions of smog-forming pollutants, there are no filters for carbon.</p>
        <p>''We are making progress in controlling health-threatening air pollution, the stuff that causes respiratory problems,'' said John M. DeCicco, a senior fellow at Environmental Defense, which monitors vehicle emissions. ''For greenhouse pollution, it's completely different. We're not cutting it at all, and it's growing as fast as driving is growing.''</p>
        <p>Faster, possibly, because of the popularity of bigger sport utilities and pickups.</p>
        <p>Japan's Big Three -- Toyota, Honda and Nissan -- are in the midst of an aggressive push into those categories, once the exclusive domain of the domestic Big Three. Even European automakers that made their names selling performance cars, like Porsche and BMW, view the sport utility as a staple of their American showrooms. The competition has in many ways improved these vehicles, and it has made them more affordable, as well. That has only helped sales of these most environmentally troublesome vehicles.</p>
        <p>While growth of the very largest sport utilities has stalled, over all sport utilities continue to gain market share at the expense of passenger cars and minivans. On the E.P.A. scale, small and midsize sport utilities tend to score in the 2 to 5 range and cars in the 6 to 7 range. The highest ratings are earned by cars that are the most fuel efficient, particularly those made by Honda. But small sport utilities with sophisticated engines and catalytic converters can do well, like the Honda Element, which scores 6 to 8.</p>
        <p>The bottom of the E.P.A.'s chart is dominated by the largest vehicles, though some of the giants do better than others because of different emissions control technologies. The Hummer H2 by General Motors gets a 2, while the scores for the BMW X5 sport utility range from 1 to 4. The high-performance version of the Mercedes-Benz M-Class gets a 0 rating, while all other versions score 1; that means they produce at least twice as much in smog-forming pollutants as the Ford Explorer, a 4 on the E.P.A. scale.</p>
        <p>The same vehicle can get more than one grade depending on which of several certification standards is used -- California guidelines, federal standards, or more stringent federal clean-vehicle standards for certain regions with more pollution -- and low-sulfur gasoline in California reduces emissions. So the grading system is best not taken as gospel, experts say.</p>
        <p>But the ranges into which vehicles fall give an idea of their relative contribution to pollution that can cause smog.</p>
        <p>The ratings make clear the extent to which Asian automakers -- whose showrooms long were filled with smaller, cleaner, more fuel efficient cars -- have jumped into the market for large sport utilities and pickups.</p>
        <p>Toyota already sells a full line of light trucks and derives nearly half of its sales in the United States from them, a balance not too different from G.M.'s. Earlier this month Toyota said it would increase truck production with a new pickup plant in San Antonio. The company has also said it was planning two sport utilities that will use hybrid power, which saves gas by supplementing the internal combustion engine with electric power.</p>
        <p>Nissan plans to sell its first full-size pickup, the Titan, this year, and announced last Thursday that its first full-size S.U.V., the Pathfinder Armada, would come out in the fall. Honda, which has been building more sport utilities, is said to be considering adding a small pickup truck to its lineup.</p>
        <p>Last month, the top executive of Hyundai, the Korean automaker that made its name in small cars, said the company would probably sell its first full-size sport utility by 2007 and was considering a pickup truck as well.</p>
        <p>In 1980, light trucks made up only a fifth of American auto sales. In 2001, they crept past half of the industry's sales and last year grew to 52 percent.</p>
        <p>There were 51 sport utilities on the market last September, according to George Peterson, president of AutoPacific, a market research company that conducts focus groups and surveys. He expects the number to rise to at least 85 by 2006 or 2007.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
