<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Arnold the Hummer Lover Revs Up a Green State</title>
    <meta content="24HAKI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/24/weekinreview/24HAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1514294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDC1439F937A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Arnold the Hummer Lover Revs Up a Green State</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Arnold the Hummer Lover Revs Up a Green State</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Motor City could cast a leading man for California, a state whose air policies drive automakers crazy, Arnold Schwarzenegger would make the A-list.</p>
        <p>But to environmental groups, many of which are based in the San Francisco Bay area, the notion of an unabashed Hummer lover taking over the nation's greenest state is mortifying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Detroit could cast a leading man for California, Arnold Schwarzenegger would make the list. Environmentalists say the notion of a Hummer lover as governor is mortifying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Motor City could cast a leading man for California, a state whose air policies drive automakers crazy, Arnold Schwarzenegger would make the A-list.</p>
        <p>But to environmental groups, many of which are based in the San Francisco Bay area, the notion of an unabashed Hummer lover taking over the nation's greenest state is mortifying.</p>
        <p>Viewed from Detroit, California's gubernatorial stakes are especially high, since the Golden State sets the regulatory pace for the nation.</p>
        <p>Because the state's clean-air policies predate those of the federal government, other states can pick California's tougher regulations over Washington's. A few Northeastern states, including New York, do just that, giving California effective regulatory control over about a fifth of the most lucrative auto market in the world. The state's clean air policies are also forcing the development of technologies that end up in cars nationwide.</p>
        <p>This month, there have been signs of cooperation. General Motors and DaimlerChrysler agreed to drop lawsuits against California over a landmark clean air regulation, the Zero Emission Vehicle mandate, that will put millions of low-  and zero-emission vehicles on the state's roads from 2005 to 2020.</p>
        <p>The mandate, first set in motion in 1990, has spent 13 years in regulatory limbo. But auto production cycles can't be shifted overnight, so the simple threat of the regulation forced automakers to sell or lease tens of thousands of battery-powered cars in California. It was also a potent catalyst for the development of hybrids -- fuel efficient cars that save gasoline by using some electric power -- as well as prototypes of futuristic emission-free cars powered by hydrogen fuel cells.</p>
        <p>Looking ahead, the role of the governor looms large. If the state legislature passes laws that promulgate the regulations, the details will actually be written by the California Air Resources Board, whose members serve at the behest of the governor.</p>
        <p>What would the air board look like under a Governor Schwarzenegger? That's not clear yet.</p>
        <p>''Arnold will lay out his vision for California in a time and manner that he desires over the next eight weeks,'' Rob Stutzman, a spokesman for Mr. Schwarzenegger's campaign, said in an interview last week.</p>
        <p>Of course, one could parse the Arnold oeuvre for clues to his automotive theories. Size clearly counts. Toyota paid to have its big pickup, the Tundra, displayed in ''Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines,'' but it seemed toddler-like chased by a rampaging crane. In ''Terminator 2: Judgment Day,'' the whole roof of a semi truck gets sheared off by an overpass.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups know Mr. Schwarzenegger as the biggest booster of the Hummer, the S.U.V. they love to hate.</p>
        <p>He bought his first Humvee -- the military transport that spawned the Hummer -- shortly after first Persian Gulf war made them a staple on CNN.</p>
        <p>Last August, a year before he announced his candidacy, he was billed as a guest of honor in South Bend, Ind., hometown of both Notre Dame and the Hummer. G.M. and the privately held AM General, which jointly produce and sell Hummers, were introducing the H2, a Hummer for yuppies, and had invited their most famous customer to preside over a gathering of like-minded Hummer owners. To mark the occasion, as well as his 55th birthday, Mr. Schwarzenegger received a new H2, in pewter. His blessing was important.</p>
        <p>''It keeps the true spirit of the Hummer for the soccer mom, for the executive, for the studly guys, for the fat guys, for the skinny guys,'' Mr. Schwarzenegger said during the proceedings, according to a report in The South Bend Tribune.</p>
        <p>''Everyone can have a Hummer now.''</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club, based in San Francisco, has rolled out a different welcome mat. Last month, the group launched a Web site, www.hummerdinger.com, as a catalog of their grievances against Hummers.</p>
        <p>''We don't know what his positions are but his personal lifestyle indicates someone who's pretty insensitive to environmental concerns,'' said Carl Zichella, regional staff director for the Sierra Club in California, of Mr. Schwarzenegger. The group opposes the recall and supports Gov. Gray Davis.</p>
        <p>Arianna Huffington -- Detroit's nightmare governor -- contends that S.U.V.'s help finance terrorists and has billed the recall race as the hybrid versus the Hummer. The actor Gary Coleman, another candidate, reportedly proposes helping to slake the nation's oil thirst by drilling in all of the state's parks.</p>
        <p>Auto executives in Detroit, Tokyo and Stuttgart will watch with interest, because with one major disagreement resolved, another looms large.</p>
        <p>Last year, California passed the nation's first law aimed at cutting auto emissions of greenhouse gases, highlighting how far apart the state's agenda is from that of the Bush administration. The law directs the air board to draft details of the regulation by the fall of 2004.</p>
        <p>Can the administration of a Hummer-loving governor cut greenhouse gases? ''He keeps saying, 'I like the environment, don't worry,' '' Mr. Zichella said of Mr. Schwarzenegger. ''That kind of makes you shudder. We'd love to know where he stands.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
