<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Projects To Develop Natural Gas In Qatar</title>
    <meta content="16SHEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/16/business/worldbusiness/16shel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031017T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1527644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Refineries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Qatar</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exxon Mobil</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Dutch/shell Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qatar Petroleum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timmons, Heather</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Qatar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Qatar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Exxon Mobil Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Royal Dutch Petroleum Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DD173EF935A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Projects To Develop Natural Gas In Qatar</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Big Projects to Develop Natural Gas in Qatar</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE and HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela; Timmons, Heather</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exxon Mobil and Royal Dutch/Shell are expected to announce significant investmentss in separate natural gas projects in Qatar; Exxon Mobil plans to sign agreement with Qatar Petroleum to invest more than $10 billion to develop two new liquefied natural gas facilities in Qatar's North Field; is expected to buy all natural gas that would be produced once project goes into operation in 2008, or about 2.8 billion cubic feet per day, for sale in US in 25-year contract; Royal Dutch/Shell is expected to sign $5 billion deal with Qatar's state-owned petroleum company to build one of world's largest gas-to-liquid plants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exxon Mobil and Royal Dutch/Shell are expected to announce significant investments in separate natural gas projects in Qatar in the coming days, underscoring a vast and accelerating shift within the oil industry to capitalize on the growing demand for cleaner-burning fuels the world over, particularly in the United States.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Exxon Mobil plans to sign an agreement with Qatar Petroleum to invest more than $10 billion to develop two new liquefied natural gas facilities in Qatar's prolific North Field, a person close to the negotiations said on Wednesday. Exxon Mobil owns a 30 percent stake in the project, called Qatargas II, and it would work on every aspect from producing the natural gas to building the so-called natural gas trains that would ship the gas after it is super-cooled into liquid form.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exxon Mobil and Royal Dutch/Shell are expected to announce significant investments in separate natural gas projects in Qatar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exxon Mobil and Royal Dutch/Shell are expected to announce significant investments in separate natural gas projects in Qatar in the coming days, underscoring a vast and accelerating shift within the oil industry to capitalize on the growing demand for cleaner-burning fuels the world over, particularly in the United States.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Exxon Mobil plans to sign an agreement with Qatar Petroleum to invest more than $10 billion to develop two new liquefied natural gas facilities in Qatar's prolific North Field, a person close to the negotiations said on Wednesday. Exxon Mobil owns a 30 percent stake in the project, called Qatargas II, and it would work on every aspect from producing the natural gas to building the so-called natural gas trains that would ship the gas after it is super-cooled into liquid form.</p>
        <p>Most important, Exxon Mobil is expected to buy all the natural gas that would be produced once the project goes into operation in 2008, or about 2.8 billion cubic feet a day, for sale in the United States in a 25-year contract. That would translate to about 2.8 trillion British Thermal Units, or B.T.U.'s, the common measurement of the heating value of natural gas. In 2000, the United States consumed 22.8 trillion B.T.U.'s of natural gas.</p>
        <p>Royal Dutch/Shell is expected to sign a $5 billion deal on Monday with Qatar's state-owned petroleum company to build one of the world's largest gas-to-liquid plants, which could use a relatively new technology to make cleaner-burning vehicle fuel from natural gas, people close to the deal said on Wednesday. Neither Exxon nor Shell would comment on the status of their negotiations with Qatar.</p>
        <p>Shell's investment would be the largest of any major oil company in gas-to-liquid, or G.T.L., fuel production. The technology produces an odorless, clear fuel from natural gas that works in diesel engines, but contains almost none of the pollutants that traditional fuels emit, like sulfur. The plant would also be built in Qatar's North Field and is expected to come online in 2009, producing 140,000 barrels of fuel a day.</p>
        <p>As industrialized countries struggle to reduce emissions, they are slaking their huge appetites for fuel with natural gas, which burns more cleanly than oil and coal. In the United States, demand for natural gas has rocketed as all the newest power plants have been designed to run on gas rather than other fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>But for much of this year, the American companies and consumers have had to grapple with the lowest supplies of natural gas in 25 years. Improved technology has permitted oil and gas companies to deplete gas reserves at a faster rate than before. At the same time, some large new reserves of gas in the United States remain off limits because of environmental protection efforts.</p>
        <p>Most industry experts expect domestic supplies of natural gas to remain tight for years to come. Crimped supplies have kept natural gas prices high most of this year, at or above $5 per million British thermal units. While that has pinched the economy, it has made expensive projects like those in Qatar economically feasible. And it has raised a host of questions about what dependence on foreign sources of gas would mean for the United States, given its overwhelming reliance on overseas sources of oil.</p>
        <p>Qatar, however, has been a staunch, politically stable ally of the United States. It has the world's third largest reserves of natural gas after Iran and Russia, and is negotiating with other foreign investors.</p>
        <p>Exxon Mobil already has other liquefied natural gas projects in Qatar that supply several countries. The South African company Sasol is constructing a 34,000-barrel-a-day G.T.L. plant in Qatar that is expected to come online in 2005. Together with ChevronTexaco, Sasol is negotiating with the government to build another 120,000-barrel-a-day G.T.L. plant.</p>
        <p>Gas-to-liquids technology is still new, but the move to reduce emissions could help advance the investments in Qatar, said Jamal Qureshi, an analyst with PFC Energy, a Washington consulting firm.</p>
        <p>Analysts are also optimistic about G.T.L. plants because they are one way for producers to take advantage of so-called stranded natural gas fields, those too far from a pipeline to export economically.</p>
        <p>''The G.T.L. business is turning into a very viable operation,'' said Bruce Lanni, an analyst at A.G. Edwards.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 17, 2003, Friday  An article in World Business yesterday about natural gas projects in Qatar misstated a term of Exxon Mobil's investment in one project. The company is entitled to 30 percent of the gas, not all of it. Because of an editing error, the article also misstated the amount of natural gas consumed by the United States in 2000. It was 22.8 trillion cubic feet, not British thermal units.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 17, 2003, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in World Business yesterday about natural gas projects in Qatar misstated a term of Exxon Mobil's investment in one project. The company is entitled to 30 percent of the gas, not all of it. Because of an editing error, the article also misstated the amount of natural gas consumed by the United States in 2000. It was 22.8 trillion cubic feet, not British thermal units.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
