<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rules Approved to Reduce Pollutants at Power Plants</title>
    <meta content="27ACID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/27/nyregion/27ACID.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1475695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DA1130F934A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rules Approved to Reduce Pollutants at Power Plants</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rules Approved to Reduce Pollutants at Power Plants</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Power plants in New York State will have to sharply cut their output of pollutants blamed for acid rain, smog and other environmental ills beginning next year under rules approved by state regulators; regulations, which will be phased in over next five years, are expected to reduce by tens of thousands of tons a year emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides generated by plants across state; those emissions combine in atmosphere to produce smog, while also poisoning lakes; Gov Pataki, announcing new rules, asserts they put New York ahead of rest of country in protecting air quality (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Power plants in New York State will have to sharply cut their output of pollutants blamed for acid rain, smog and other environmental ills beginning next year under rules approved yesterday by state regulators.</p>
        <p>The regulations, which will be phased in over the next five years, are expected to reduce by tens of thousands of tons a year the emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides generated by the plants across the state. Those emissions combine in the atmosphere to produce smog, while also poisoning lakes and killing fish, especially in the Adirondacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Power plants in New York State will have to sharply cut their output of pollutants blamed for acid rain, smog and other environmental ills beginning next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Power plants in New York State will have to sharply cut their output of pollutants blamed for acid rain, smog and other environmental ills beginning next year under rules approved yesterday by state regulators.</p>
        <p>The regulations, which will be phased in over the next five years, are expected to reduce by tens of thousands of tons a year the emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides generated by the plants across the state. Those emissions combine in the atmosphere to produce smog, while also poisoning lakes and killing fish, especially in the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, in announcing the rules, said that they put New York ahead of the rest of the country in protecting air quality. He said the restrictions on sulfur dioxide will be the most stringent in the nation.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and health experts said they were less sure. They said the new rules -- which seemed to be breaking new ground when Mr. Pataki proposed them in 1999 -- should have been adopted two years ago, and will still leave New York's electricity plants, by some measures, producing dirtier air than some neighboring states.</p>
        <p>They also said a provision added during the negotiations between the state and the power producers will allow plant owners to trade off emission cuts made in plants in other states to offset the New York rules, meaning that air in the immediate vicinity of the plants, where the health impact is considered greatest, might not be affected.</p>
        <p>''New York should be setting the high-water mark, but these rules are at the shallow end of the pool,'' said Jason K. Babbie, an environmental policy analyst at the New York Public Interest Research Group, and environmental and social issue lobbying group.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Pataki rejected that assessment. The new rules, they said, are very broad, requiring deep levels of cuts in sulfur dioxide pollution for all power producers. And they say that New York will also be the first state to require emissions cuts in nitrogen oxides, or NOx, on a year-round basis, not just during the summer when smog is at its worst.</p>
        <p>Once the rules are fully in place, state officials said, the annual emissions of sulfur dioxide will be reduced by 130,000 tons per year and NOx emissions will be cut by 20,000 tons a year. For sulfur dioxide, that is 50 percent below the levels specified by the federal government under the Clean Air Act's acid rain program.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists said that even though deeper cuts would be better -- 75 to 80 percent reductions, they say, is possible and should be the national goal -- New York's rules will still make a difference at a time when they say that federal action on power plant emissions has been weak.</p>
        <p>''Governor Pataki is doing what Congress has failed to do,'' said Brian L. Houseal, the executive director of the Adirondack Council, a research and lobbying group focused on New York's Adirondack Park. ''If this same level of cuts were applied nationally, acid rain damage would disappear across America.''</p>
        <p>But if it is a measure of government success that every affected party is left to one degree or another unhappy, the rules have at least achieved that. Electricity producers said that the state's own calculations suggested that the costs of achieving the new limits would drive up electricity rates for consumers, especially on Long Island, and perhaps result in thousands of lost jobs.</p>
        <p>Wholesale electricity rates statewide could rise by up to 5.4 percent as a result of the regulations, according to state estimates, and perhaps as much as 16 percent on Long Island.</p>
        <p>That does not mean, however, that an individual customer should expect to see monthly bills go up by that much since the wholesale costs are only a part of the utility equation. About one-half to one-third of a household bill comes from the wholesale price of the electricity produced, according to state figures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
