<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hearing on E.P.A. Nominee Takes an Ideological Turn</title>
    <meta content="Y24LEA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/24/politics/24LEAV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1522050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leavitt, Michael O (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Leavitt, Michael O</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDF173DF937A1575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hearing on E.P.A. Nominee Takes an Ideological Turn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hearing on E.P.A. Nominee Takes an Ideological Turn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate Democrats use confirmation hearing on Gov Michael O Leavitt of Utah, Pres Bush's choice to hed Environmental Protection Agency, as forum to sharply criticize administration's environmental record, all but ignoring nominee sitting in front of them; Leavitt, who is expected to win confirmation by Environmental and Public Works Committee and full Senate, reveals little about his intentions as administrator and makes no commitments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Democrats used the confirmation hearing today on Gov. Michael O. Leavitt of Utah, President Bush's choice for administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, as a forum to sharply criticize the administration's environmental record, all but ignoring the nominee sitting in front of them.</p>
        <p>In the packed, three-hour hearing, members of the Environment and Public Works Committee told Mr. Leavitt repeatedly that the job he was seeking was one of the worst in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senate Democrats used the confirmation hearing on Gov. Michael O. Leavitt of Utah as a forum to sharply criticize the administrations environmental record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senate Democrats used the confirmation hearing today on Gov. Michael O. Leavitt of Utah, President Bush's choice for administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, as a forum to sharply criticize the administration's environmental record, all but ignoring the nominee sitting in front of them.</p>
        <p>In the packed, three-hour hearing, members of the Environment and Public Works Committee told Mr. Leavitt repeatedly that the job he was seeking was one of the worst in Washington.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Leavitt said that he viewed himself as a problem solver, that his preferred approach was collaboration and that his main goal was clean air.</p>
        <p>''The solutions to these problems are found in the productive middle,'' he said. ''Rarely are they found at the extremes.''</p>
        <p>Democrats and Republicans expect the committee to confirm Mr. Leavitt when it meets next week and say that the full Senate will vote to confirm him.</p>
        <p>But four Democratic senators -- Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York and three who are running for president: John Kerry of Massachusetts, Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut and John Edwards of North Carolina -- have said they will bar the nomination from reaching the Senate until President Bush addressed certain issues. These include questions about why the administration removed warnings from agency press releases about the safety of the air at ground zero in New York shortly after the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>Republican aides said after the hearing that the White House was likely to work out these issues with each senator.</p>
        <p>Even environmentalists who oppose the nomination predicted that Mr. Leavitt would be confirmed.</p>
        <p>''In the long run, the odds are that Governor Leavitt will be confirmed, but not without some significant compromises from the administration,'' largely on providing information that committee members have sought, said Philip E. Clapp, president of the National Environmental Trust.</p>
        <p>In the hearing, Mr. Leavitt revealed little about his intentions as administrator and made no commitments.</p>
        <p>Swirling around him were accusations from Democrats that the Bush administration's record on the environment had been a disaster and that the administration could not be trusted on the issue. Mr. Leavitt faced almost no questions about his 11-year record as governor.</p>
        <p>In his opening remarks, Senator James M. Inhofe, the Oklahoma Republican who is chairman of the committee, predicted that the hearing would be less about Mr. Leavitt than it would be a battleground over Mr. Bush's environmental record. Mr. Inhofe recited objections raised by environmentalists about the president's policies -- chiefly, that he was a friend to polluters -- and said none of them were true.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leavitt refused to be drawn in to that debate.</p>
        <p>To a request from Senator James M. Jeffords, the Vermont independent, for information on a recent administration decision not to require pollution-control devices on old power plants, he answered, ''My objective is to have the air cleaner when I finish than when I started.''</p>
        <p>When Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon, asked Mr. Leavitt if he would freeze that rule, noting that the governor's own director of air quality in Utah had strenuously objected to it, he said that the official had changed his mind and no longer objected.</p>
        <p>The Republican members of the committee reproached the Democrats for what they said were baseless accusations about administration policies. Mr. Inhofe said at one point that the concept of global warming, a concern of the Democrats, ''could be the greatest hoax ever perpetrated on the American people.''</p>
        <p>Some senators portrayed Mr. Leavitt as bystander tossed into the Cuisinart of partisan Washington politics.</p>
        <p>''Into this political cauldron comes a good man,'' Mr. Wyden said.</p>
        <p>Senators from each party expressed befuddlement over why Mr. Leavitt sought the job, particularly given the interagency tensions that preceded the resignation of the previous administrator, Christie Whitman, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Senator George V. Voinovich, Republican of Ohio, said that Ms. Whitman ''did the very best she could, but I'm sure she was relieved and glad to leave the battle.''</p>
        <p>Senator Harry Reid, Democrat of Nevada, told Mr. Leavitt, ''Governor, you've got a lot of guts to take this job,'' adding that it would probably be impossible to override the White House if he ever thought the president was wrong. ''The fact that you decided to take this job in no way is impugning your intelligence,'' Mr. Reid assured him.</p>
        <p>And Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, warned him that he would be giving up control by leaving the governor's office. ''I've seen so many governors come here and think they could run it the way they ran their states,'' Mr. Baucus said. But Washington is different, he said, because ''you're someplace else in the pecking order'' and in Washington, the knives are longer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leavitt said that in seeking the post, he was answering the president's call.</p>
        <p>''I passionately believe that this nation deserves to have a clean and safe and healthy environment,'' he said. ''And I also believe that the United States can increase our velocity of our environmental progress. We can do it without compromising our competitive position economically in the world.''</p>
        <p>After the hearing, Mr. Leavitt told reporters who asked whether he was being naive about the difficulties of the job: ''I don't have any illusions that it's an easy job. The president's asked that I do it, and I am going to give every ounce of energy I have.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
