<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Party of One</title>
    <meta content="0323CHAFT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/magazine/23CHAFEE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chafee, Lincoln (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">chafee, lincoln (biographical sketch)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bai, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rhode Island</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Chafee, Lincoln</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7D91731F930A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="3185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Party of One</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Party of One</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Matt Bai</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bai, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Bai profile of Sen Lincoln Chafee of Rhode Island, most cutting Republican critic of Pres Bush's foreign and economic policies, especially invasion of Iraq; says problem with Chafee is that he relies largely on his vote, 1 out of 100, to counter Bush agenda, refusing to get involved in tactical maneuvering and deliberations that might prove more effective; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lincoln Chafee doesn't get a whole lot of respect from other Republicans. Senators and strategists from his party dismiss the junior senator from Rhode Island as a joke, portraying him, rather viciously, as vacant or, worse yet, borderline impaired. Some Republicans even mock Chafee when he's not around. ''It's kind of like junior-high days,'' laments Senator Chuck Hagel, a Republican from Nebraska.</p>
        <p>Of course, Chafee is an easy target; he often doesn't seem to grasp the lingo of the Senate, much less its customs. One Senate aide relates the story of a news conference at which participants were advised to ''stick to the script.'' Chafee looked puzzled, the aide recalls. ''Is there a script?'' he asked, apparently serious. ''I haven't seen it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Lincoln Chafee is against the war, the tax cut  in fact, the whole Bush agenda. It's no wonder that he's having a hard time fitting in with his fellow Republicans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lincoln Chafee doesn't get a whole lot of respect from other Republicans. Senators and strategists from his party dismiss the junior senator from Rhode Island as a joke, portraying him, rather viciously, as vacant or, worse yet, borderline impaired. Some Republicans even mock Chafee when he's not around. ''It's kind of like junior-high days,'' laments Senator Chuck Hagel, a Republican from Nebraska.</p>
        <p>Of course, Chafee is an easy target; he often doesn't seem to grasp the lingo of the Senate, much less its customs. One Senate aide relates the story of a news conference at which participants were advised to ''stick to the script.'' Chafee looked puzzled, the aide recalls. ''Is there a script?'' he asked, apparently serious. ''I haven't seen it.''</p>
        <p>He isn't just the class doofus, however. His father, John Chafee, whose seat Lincoln essentially inherited after his father's death four years ago, was the soul of the G.O.P.'s moderate faction and a revered statesman in Washington, and this in itself gives Lincoln Chafee some gravity. His vote is critical in a Senate that is almost equally divided. And at a time when the Republican ranks are remarkably well disciplined, Chafee has emerged as the most cutting Republican critic of the president's foreign and economic policies -- especially the invasion of Iraq. He was the only G.O.P. senator to vote against the October resolution authorizing Bush to use force in Iraq, and he has continued to voice his disdain, even as the rest of the party -- along with many Democrats -- has rallied to the president's side. Chafee was also the only Republican to side with the Democrats on the fight over a new Homeland Security Department and the first to push publicly for Trent Lott to step down as majority leader.</p>
        <p>On first impression, it's hard to know whether Chafee is truly the oddity everyone says he is or whether there's something studied about his eccentricity. Though he turns 50 this week, he still looks a little like the rich prep-school kid he once was, with longish hair parted in the middle and tasteful Ferragamo ties. As a younger man, he shod racehorses, and on his walls he keeps a set of chromed horseshoes and a portrait of himself on the cover of Hoof Beats magazine. When I first spoke with Chafee, on the morning after the State of the Union address in January, I noticed that he looked down a lot and that he would occasionally nod several times in quick succession, like a child accepting a scolding.</p>
        <p>But there was nothing meek about Chafee's assessment of the president's speech. Republicans on Capitol Hill were still swooning over Bush's indictment of Iraq, but Chafee remained dead set against war. ''I don't think the president has articulated his reasons consistently,'' he said. The administration, he contended, has ''just been shifting justifications throughout the debate.''</p>
        <p>When I asked about Bush's plan to make his tax cuts permanent, Chafee actually groaned. Chafee and John McCain were the only Republicans to oppose the final tax cut plan in 2001. ''It's been a mistake,'' Chafee said. ''They've had no stimulative effect.'' Bush's idea to restructure Medicare, Chafee said, was ''depressing.'' And the president's Clear Skies Initiative was designed to sound compassionate, Chafee said, but ignored the central issue of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>After a while, I asked Chafee if there were any major pieces of Bush's agenda with which he could wholeheartedly agree. He paused for about 10 seconds, with his hands pressed together prayerfully.</p>
        <p>''It's difficult,'' he said finally. ''Because he's chosen a divisive path, and it is working for the administration. On so many issues, they just pound the wedge in.''</p>
        <p>In other words, I suggested, he has a hard time finding even one point of agreement.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I do,'' Chafee answered, looking embarrassed.</p>
        <p>With most of Washington fixated on the coming war, the White House and its allies on the Hill were preparing to push through a radical program that would, among other things, rewrite the tax code, loosen more environmental rules and ensure a decade of expanding deficits. At the same time, Bush's approval ratings, while still respectable, were slouching toward the 50 percent threshold, and polls showed a plurality of Americans uneasy with the president's handling of the economy. Not quite the moment for a full-fledged coup, perhaps, but it might be enough to embolden a united front of centrist senators from both parties to make a stand against the Bush agenda.</p>
        <p>For Chafee, this is a chance to step out and lead. He finds himself torn, however, by dueling impulses handed down from his father's generation to his own. On one hand, he is very much aware that in his father's world, seniority counted for everything; you respected your elders and waited for your opportunities.</p>
        <p>But the genteel Senate of John Chafee's era is, in fact, about as relevant today as the neighborhood five-and-dime. The way Chafee sees it, everything his father cherished is now under attack, and time is short. If he waits his turn, there will be nothing left to fight for. And so Lincoln Chafee faces a choice: he can be the kind of deferential junior senator his father would have admired, or he can stand up and defend the old man's legacy.</p>
        <p>Chafee was never the kind of politician's son who inspires talk of a dynasty. After earning a degree in classics from Brown, young Linc -- captain of the wrestling team, scion of one of Rhode Island's five governing families -- wandered off to Bozeman, Mont., to earn a kind of graduate degree in, of all things, shoeing horses. Although Chafee had lost a younger sister when she was kicked in the head by a horse, he nonetheless chose a career as a farrier. Family members say that his father, a champion of the working man, liked the idea of Lincoln learning a trade. Sleeping in his corroding old Volvo, Chafee drove north to Alberta until he caught on as a regular on the Canadian racing circuit. He lived that solitary life for seven years, making few friends, until finally he returned to Rhode Island more introverted than anyone had remembered.</p>
        <p>His father, a onetime Navy secretary and governor, was an iconic leader in the Senate and an ardent champion of environmental causes. Lincoln, however, was more like his mother, Virginia, who did her best to avoid public life. During his first campaign, for delegate to the state's constitutional convention in 1984, Chafee drove out to a neighborhood in his native Warwick to knock on doors. He sat there for 20 minutes, holding a stack of palm cards with his picture on them, trying to work up the courage to get out of the car.</p>
        <p>I asked Chafee what made him decide to run for Warwick's City Council and then for mayor, an election he lost before coming back to win four terms. ''My father loved his job,'' Chafee said. ''I thought: Well, isn't that the key to life? You should love your job.''</p>
        <p>When John Chafee died from a heart attack in 1999, Lincoln, who had already announced that he would run for the seat after his father's retirement, was appointed to succeed him. Friends say he nearly turned down the appointment; stubbornly, he wanted to win the seat on his own. When the day came for his swearing in, a Senate aide found Chafee seated at his father's desk on the verge of tears. ''I didn't want to get here this way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Chafee relied heavily on Democratic disunity and his famous name to get himself elected the following year. But his defiance of the administration has since helped him build a strong following among Rhode Island's overwhelmingly Democratic electorate. And his shyness around TV cameras hasn't hurt him much in a tiny state where people aren't surprised to run into their senators at the local grocery store. Chafee may not be the most recognizable or dynamic political figure in the state, but he can hardly leave the house without seeing someone he knows; when the nightclub fire claimed almost 100 lives in West Warwick last month, the senator immediately recognized a neighbor and a few acquaintances among the dead and injured.</p>
        <p>In Washington, however, Chafee's lack of pretension and his discomfort in social situations were, from the start, seen as something else: signs of weakness. Chafee had set foot only once in the Capitol before he was elected, and he was an alien in the Senate's stifling culture. At first, if he found another senator sitting in his seat on the Senate floor, Chafee would stand in the aisle, waiting patiently and speaking to no one. An aide finally took pity on him and told him it was O.K. for him to sit somewhere else. Chafee has gone only once to the senators' dining room; though he says it led to a nice conversation with Thad Cochran of Mississippi, he has never returned. He prefers to eat lunch at his desk, with the newspaper.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, Republican insiders compared Chafee with his father and came away baffled. Two theories took hold and are often repeated: either the younger Chafee is a few votes short of a quorum or he's actually cagier than anyone realizes and enjoys being inscrutable. In fact, after you spend some time with Chafee, neither analysis seems right. He's not dim, nor does he have much capacity for guile or irony. He is, instead, a slow starter who learned early in life to ask questions, persevere and wait his turn. ''He's not a giver-upper,'' is how his mother described him to me.</p>
        <p>In his father's Senate, no one would have taken it personally if a freshman Republican from a liberal state voted against his own party. (According to a breakdown by National Journal, Chafee's voting record actually puts him ideologically at the dead center of the Senate.) But this is not his father's Senate. The Bush administration's mantra in foreign policy goes for Capitol Hill, too: ''You're either with us or against us.'' And because Chafee has been against the party's leaders almost from the start, they seized on his quirkiness and inexperience as a way of discrediting him.</p>
        <p>Predictably, this seems to have only deepened his resolve.</p>
        <p>''We all want some self-respect, and we all want to be taken seriously,'' Senator Hagel said. ''If you treat him like a U.S. senator, if you treat him like he's got a brain, if you treat him like you respect his questioning, and if there's an honest difference of opinion, then O.K. That's all any of us want. If we disagree, we disagree. But you can't go around impugning people's motives. They do that with John McCain up here, too. They do it with all of us, to some extent.''</p>
        <p>In a strange way, history seems to have cast Chafee as the unlikely foil to the swaggering president -- a kind of Bizarro Bush. The two men, roughly the same age, have a remarkable amount in common. Both the Bushes of Kennebunkport and the Chafees of Warwick hail from a powerful line of Yankee Republican senators, a tradition that spawned liberal-leaning giants like Henry Cabot Lodge and Margaret Chase Smith. Both George W. and Lincoln avoided the family business as younger men, acutely aware that they couldn't measure up to the success of their Yale-educated fathers. Both relied on their fathers' names to make late entries into politics.</p>
        <p>Chafee remained loyal to the tradition of Yankee Republicanism. But Bush took a very different path within the party. Increasingly, the South has come to dominate G.O.P. politics, and Bush, who watched his father fall prey to this tectonic shift in the party's base, built close ties to religious conservatives. As president, he hasn't simply ignored his grandfather's more liberal wing of the party; he has laid siege to it. While Chafee told me that he likes and respects the Bush family, he admitted that he feels betrayed by George W.</p>
        <p>''This president campaigned as a moderate,'' he said. '''I'm going to change the tone in Washington. I'm a uniter -- not a divider.' And that's been the biggest disappointment. It was such a surprise to see the agenda. It was so different from the campaign rhetoric.''</p>
        <p>Given all this, it is reasonable to wonder why Chafee doesn't simply flee the G.O.P. As recently as last fall, he listened over dinner as his father's old friend Senator Jim Jeffords laid out all the benefits of sitting as an independent. But Chafee is a Republican by birth, and he says he believes -- naïvely, perhaps -- that his vision of the party will endure longer than Bush's. ''The pendulum swings,'' Chafee said, ''and hopefully, it will swing back.''</p>
        <p>I asked Chafee if, in the end, it just isn't in his constitution to be anything other than a Republican.</p>
        <p>''I'll be honest with you,'' he said. ''Back in the spring of 2001, it was just this avalanche -- we had the tax cuts and were getting out of the missile-defense treaty. And I thought: I have to do something. What can I do? But the next step that had to be taken'' -- bolting the party, in other words -- ''as you say, I was just constitutionally incapable.''</p>
        <p>That leaves open the question of what Chafee is capable of doing to sway his party. Is he just a strange guy with a stubborn streak, or does he possess the ability to lead?</p>
        <p>The once powerful moderate faction in the G.O.P. has dwindled, but still, there are four Northeastern senators -- Chafee, Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, Olympia Snowe and Susan Collins, both from Maine -- who meet weekly to discuss issues and strategy over lunch or breakfast. Combined with a bloc of like-minded Democratic centrists and Jeffords, this small caucus does have enough influence in a split Senate to broker compromises on major legislation; the G.O.P. centrists helped scale back Bush's initial tax cut, and more recently, they helped end an impasse over rules for the new Homeland Security Department. Still, the moderate resistance has often crumbled under pressure from the White House. Specter, Snowe and Collins have all voted with Bush when it mattered most.</p>
        <p>Chafee's role in the moderate caucus has primarily been to articulate broad principles; he prefers to leave back-room negotiating to others. When more than a dozen senators from both parties began meeting last month to forge a more moderate alternative to Bush's deficit-expanding economic plan, Chafee refused to take part in the discussions. He told colleagues he could not in good conscience support any new deficit spending with war looming and job losses mounting. ''For me, it's hard to decide where I want to end up on this issue,'' Collins told me. ''For Linc, it's not. He knows where he wants to be. I say that with some envy.''</p>
        <p>But by holding fast to principle and excusing himself from the deliberations, Chafee also relegated himself to the role of spectator, rather than trying to have some influence on the size of the tax cuts that will, in some form, inevitably pass the Senate. He chose, in effect, to be right rather than to be effective.</p>
        <p>When I asked Chafee just what it was he was planning to do, practically, to counter the White House's agenda, he physically flinched. His vote alone, he said, is an important statement.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it will bring other people to think that voting your conscience can work,'' he went on hopefully. ''Maybe there's some leadership in that. Maybe it will accomplish the end objective, whatever that may be -- keeping the economy rolling, stopping the war in Iraq.'' This sounded so lame, even to him, that a moment later he began to argue the other side.</p>
        <p>''Yes, yes, but then it boils down to just one vote out of 100.'' He thought, reversed himself again. ''A lot comes out of a vote, though.''</p>
        <p>This went on for some time, with Chafee at turns avoiding the question and examining it, as if he himself was trying to figure out what kind of senator he really is.</p>
        <p>''If you're saying, ideally, what would I do to effect the change that I believe is best for my country?'' He creased his brow, shook his head. ''I'm trying to answer that question also.''</p>
        <p>if this were a movie, maybe Lincoln Chafee would make a lonely sojourn to Colt State Park on a still Rhode Island night, standing before the imposing bronze statue of his father, waiting for the onset of clarity. In reality, Chafee doesn't have time for spiritual searches. Congress will soon be casting decisive votes on the president's program, votes that will frame the 2004 election. And if Chafee can't figure out how to challenge the White House tactically, then he'll remain a kind of senatorial Cassandra, warning of unseen consequences while his colleagues make the deals that determine the direction of the country.</p>
        <p>Chafee may have few doubts about where he stands on these issues, but his angst over what, if anything, he should do about it is plain. On a recent morning in his Washington office, Chafee debated himself over whether to try to catch the end of a Foreign Relations Committee hearing he'd had to leave earlier in the morning. While Chafee was eager to hear the testimony of a former government analyst who opposed an invasion of Iraq, it would take 10 minutes to get to the hearing room in the next building, and by then he might have missed most of the questioning. Chafee stood frozen in his office, weighing aloud whether he should stay or go.</p>
        <p>He decided finally to make the journey, and I accompanied him through the labyrinth of hallways, watching him pause every so often amid the lunchtime rush to find his way. An elderly couple, who obviously had no idea who he was, stopped him to ask for directions, which he politely provided. Capitol guards called out to him warmly. When at last Chafee arrived at the mostly empty hearing room and slipped into his seat, the committee's chairman, Richard Lugar, the Indiana Republican, turned to him with surprise.</p>
        <p>''Senator Chafee, I see you've returned,'' Lugar said brightly. ''Does that indicate a desire to ask more questions?''</p>
        <p>I expected Chafee, as the only Republican vocally opposed to war, to engage the witness in senatorial fashion. Instead, Chafee, the junior senator, followed his instincts and deferred to his elders, just as his father might have advised.</p>
        <p>''No, no,'' Chafee responded, shaking his head at the chairman.</p>
        <p>Lugar nodded uncertainly, then proceeded to thank the witnesses and bang the gavel, adjourning the hearing. For Lincoln Chafee, another moment had passed.</p>
        <p>Matt Bai is a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article was a profile of Gary Hart.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matt Bai is a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article was a profile of Gary Hart.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
