<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 79, a Pioneer of Heart Devices Is Not About to Quit Tinkering</title>
    <meta content="09PROF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/09/health/09PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1518210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENTIST AT WORK: KURT AMPLATZ"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Minnesota</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amplatz, Kurt (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amplatz, Curtis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D9173BF93AA3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 79, a Pioneer of Heart Devices Is Not About to Quit Tinkering</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At 79, a Pioneer of Heart Devices Is Not About to Quit Tinkering</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <dateline>GOLDEN VALLEY, Minn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Kurt Amplatz, retired University of Minnesota radiology professor and inventor, is credited with numerous breakthrough techniques and devices; Amplatzer occluder, heart defect repairing device, has saved thousands of children and adults from open-heart surgery; detailed description and drawings of Amplatzer are given; Amplatz's previous work and current research with his son Curtis is outlined; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seventy-nine is an age when most men  if they reach it -- might be content to reflect on their life achievements and nurse their arthritis. But not Dr. Kurt Amplatz, an avid tennis player and inventor whose continuing contributions to pediatric cardiology have been described as legendary.</p>
        <p>On retiring as professor of radiology from the University of Minnesota in 1997, he helped found a company and is still inventing devices that simplify the repair of cardiac defects, avoiding the need for open-heart surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Kurt Amplatz, an avid tennis player, is still inventing devices that simplify the repair of cardiac defects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seventy-nine is an age when most men  if they reach it -- might be content to reflect on their life achievements and nurse their arthritis. But not Dr. Kurt Amplatz, an avid tennis player and inventor whose continuing contributions to pediatric cardiology have been described as legendary.</p>
        <p>On retiring as professor of radiology from the University of Minnesota in 1997, he helped found a company and is still inventing devices that simplify the repair of cardiac defects, avoiding the need for open-heart surgery.</p>
        <p>While escorting a reporter through his machine shop at the AGA Medical Corporation here, he remarked, ''I'll probably die on the job.''</p>
        <p>And when he does, this quiet, humble inventor will leave behind what Dr. David Hunter, a professor of radiology at the university, described as ''an almost unbelievable treasure trove of techniques and devices.''</p>
        <p>Because of the inventions that bear the Amplatz name, fragile infants and children born with life-threatening heart defects and adults who are discovered to have them can be spared risky open-heart surgery, chest wall incisions and lengthy recoveries. Instead, the defects are repaired through a catheter inserted in the groin. Most patients go home to normal lives the next day.</p>
        <p>Jenna, for example, was 6 months old when her heart murmur, caused by a hole between the upper chambers, was discovered. If the hole did not close by age 3, her parents were told, she would need open-heart surgery. But when Jenna turned 3, there was another option, an Amplatz device that could close the hole in a two-hour procedure that involved no major surgery. A day later, Jenna was home riding her tricycle.</p>
        <p>''In his eighth decade of life, Dr. Amplatz had changed the way pediatric cardiologists practice and saved thousands of children from undergoing open-heart surgery,'' said Dr. Michael Vance, an interventional pediatric cardiologist at Children's Hospital of the King's Daughters in Norfolk, Va.</p>
        <p>Adults whose congenital cardiac defects may not become apparent until much later can also benefit. Sue, 62, who was identified by her doctor only by age and given name, became easily fatigued and was told that she had heart failure from two holes between her heart's upper chambers, limiting the oxygen-rich blood her body received. She had two Amplatz devices implanted and soon regained her energy.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jack Westfall, a family physician in Aurora, Colo., was a reluctant exerciser until last year, when his wife urged him to train with her for a minitriathlon. But Dr. Westfall found himself short of breath after running more than a block, a result, it turned out, of a previously undiagnosed hole in his heart. After the implantation of an Amplatz device, Dr. Westfall was back in the running with a markedly improved ability to exercise that enabled him to train enthusiastically for the triathlon this year.</p>
        <p>Two of the Amplatzer devices have received full approval from the Food and Drug Administration, and a third has limited approval.</p>
        <p>The various Amplatzer occluders, as they are called, have been used around the world in 30,000 patients. They have closed atrial septal defects, openings in the wall between the heart's upper chambers, and patent ductus arteriosus, a prenatal connection between the pulmonary artery and aorta that sometimes fails to close after birth.</p>
        <p>Amplatzer occluders have also been used to close holes between the ventricles, the lower pumping chambers; shut gaps called patent foramen ovale between overlapping sections of the wall dividing the upper chambers; and close small holes called Fontan fenestrations made in surgery to improve circulation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Amplatz, a pioneer in coronary angiography who invented the Amplatz catheter to allow examination of coronary arteries through a vessel in the groin, has also devised a number of metal grafts. One of them can be used to repair abdominal aortic aneurysms, balloonlike bulges in the main artery that can sometimes rupture with fatal consequences.</p>
        <p>He is now collaborating with Dr. Mark Boucek, a pediatric cardiologist in Denver, who is testing another lifesaving device that he invented that can buy time for very fragile children born with hypoplastic left heart syndrome, which ultimately requires heart transplants.</p>
        <p>Born in Weistrach, Austria, where his father was the village physician, Kurt Amplatz displayed a penchant for engineering and experimentation early in life. At 10, he worked weekends with an uncle in a chemistry lab making plastics that resemble Formica. By 15, he had an experimental mouse colony and hoped to become rich by creating a rodent poison using rare earth materials.</p>
        <p>''However,'' he said in an interview here, ''the experiment was a failure. The mice didn't die. They thrived!''</p>
        <p>So he turned his attention to mechanics, making an ''explosion motor, like a car engine with pistons, valves and carburetor.'' But when he tried to start the motor, the whole thing exploded.</p>
        <p>Undeterred, he chose engineering and then chemistry and medicine as his major fields, completing medical school in 1951. But after a stressful three weeks filling in as country doctor for his vacationing father, Dr. Amplatz realized that he was not cut out to be a frontline physician. So he chose radiology, a field of medicine where, he said, ''you don't have to talk to patients and listen to all their psychosomatic problems.''</p>
        <p>And though he professed no interest in the heart, in 1957 he was invited to Minnesota to the country's first heart hospital, built by donations from performing artists, where open-heart surgery was pioneered.</p>
        <p>Toiling in a neighbor's garage, he built a device to inject dye through a catheter into the heart. The prototype, fashioned from an old nightstand and operated by a foot pedal, was followed by his design for a portable injector powered by a carbon dioxide cartridge like the ones used for soda water and air rifles.</p>
        <p>Then he moved on, spending a few years in neuroradiology, where he made a special chair for injecting air into the spinal space to fill the brain's ventricles and ease the diagnosis of tumors, a technique known as pneumoencephalography. It has since been rendered obsolete by C.T. scans.</p>
        <p>Working in uroradiology, he pioneered the removal of kidney stones through a patient's back, since superseded by an external shock wave technique called lithotripsy.</p>
        <p>About 15 years ago, he turned his attention back to the heart with the help of his son Curtis, a biologist who inherited his father's technological bent. The doctor began creating the new Amplatz devices.</p>
        <p>Doctors had been working for many years trying to find effective ways to plug holes that seriously compromise cardiac function. But nothing worked very well until Dr. Amplatz and his son devised a gadget of wire mesh and polyester fabric that could be introduced through a catheter to close off defects that limited the ability of the heart to supply oxygen-rich blood to the rest of the body and brain.</p>
        <p>The two worked in a tiny room in a warehouse that Dr. Amplatz rented for $70 a month. There, they installed a machine to weave a biologically nonreactive metal called Nitinol into wire mesh. The mesh is formed into devices consisting of two discs linked by a short waist that is filled with polyester fabric where a blood clot can form to seal off the hole.</p>
        <p>Dr. Amplatz also invented a catheter-inserted balloon to measure the size of the hole and determine how large a waist is needed to fill it.</p>
        <p>The occluder devices are loaded into a catheter, a long, narrow flexible tube that can be inserted into a blood vessel in the groin. The catheter is guided to its destination in the heart or artery with the aid of echocardiography, an ultrasonic examination. When the tip of the catheter reaches the far side of the hole, the first disc is deployed. Then the catheter is slightly withdrawn to the other side of the hole, where the second disc is deployed, leaving the waist to fill the hole.</p>
        <p>Once in place, the Amplatzer occluders resemble a doorknob mechanism, knobs on either side of a door attached to a rod that passes through a hole in the door.</p>
        <p>When the echocardiogram confirms that the occluder is in the proper place, the catheter is unscrewed from the device and removed from the body. But if an adjustment is needed, the device can be easily reconnected to the catheter and moved, Dr. Amplatz said.</p>
        <p>The ease of the procedure was impressive even to an 8-year-old in Omaha, who wrote to thank Dr. Amplatz for inventing the devices that were used to close two holes in her mother's heart, saving her from ''scary'' surgery and a prolonged recovery and, she might have added, saving her insurer a lot of money.</p>
        <p>SCIENTIST AT WORK: KURT AMPLATZ</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
