<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Columbia University Ends Its Association With Biosphere 2</title>
    <meta content="Y09BIO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/09/education/09BIOS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1518229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biosphere 2 (Oracle, Ariz)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Decision Investments</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bass, Edward P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Columbia University</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D6173BF93AA3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Columbia University Ends Its Association With Biosphere 2</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Columbia University Ends Its Association With Biosphere 2</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University says it will cut all ties with Biosphere 2, casting into doubt future of $200 million ecology experiment built by billionaire Edward P Bass in Arizona desert; lawsuit by Decisions Investments, company of which Bass is president, against university has been settled (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Columbia University said yesterday that it would cut all ties with Biosphere 2, casting into doubt the future of the $200 million ecology experiment that Edward P. Bass, the Texas billionaire and oil heir, built in the Arizona desert.</p>
        <p>Martin C. Bowen, vice president of Decisions Investments Corporation, the company that owns Biosphere 2, said in a statement that it was exploring the center's future and that in the coming months it would try to determine ''the most viable options for its use and operation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The university said that it would cut all ties with Biosphere 2, casting into doubt the future of the $200 million ecology experiment built in the Arizona desert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Columbia University said yesterday that it would cut all ties with Biosphere 2, casting into doubt the future of the $200 million ecology experiment that Edward P. Bass, the Texas billionaire and oil heir, built in the Arizona desert.</p>
        <p>Martin C. Bowen, vice president of Decisions Investments Corporation, the company that owns Biosphere 2, said in a statement that it was exploring the center's future and that in the coming months it would try to determine ''the most viable options for its use and operation.''</p>
        <p>The company and the university said they had settled a lawsuit that Decisions Investments brought in March against Columbia and Biosphere 2 Center Inc., the entity that ran the research center. Mr. Bass is president of Decisions Investments.</p>
        <p>''With the settlement of this lawsuit, our relationship with Columbia is behind us,'' Mr. Bowen said.</p>
        <p>The company and Columbia declined to provide further details, and each said no officials were available to comment.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to say what kind of scientific promise the giant structure, an eight-story steel and glass terrarium, might hold. From the day in 1991 that eight men and women and 4,000 plant and animal species were sealed with great fanfare into it as part of an experiment to simulate the earth's ecology, Biosphere 2 generated fascination and skepticism. Biosphere 1 is the earth.</p>
        <p>Critics called Biosphere 2 a ''scientific crapshoot.'' When the human guinea pigs left the structure after two years, crops had failed, noxious gases had built up, the water had turned acidic and the site was overrun by ''crazy ants'' and morning glories.</p>
        <p>But Columbia officials decided that with some modifications it might hold some promise, and its decision in 1995 to take on Biosphere 2's management seemed to confer academic legitimacy to the project.</p>
        <p>As recently as 1999, the collaboration seemed to be going well, as Columbia announced that it would invest $20 million over five years and manage it until 2010. And in 2001, the university said it would start a science and public policy graduate program at the center.</p>
        <p>But Biosphere 2's chief champion, Columbia's executive vice provost, Michael Crow, left for Arizona State University, and a new president, Lee C. Bollinger, took the helm of the university. After two panels reviewing the site offered negative evaluations, Columbia expressed questions about further investment.</p>
        <p>In March, Decisions Investments sued Columbia, saying its decision to end education programs there and its failure to hire faculty and build a new laboratory had diminished the property's value and were a breach of contract.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Decisions Investments and Columbia said that classes and tours would continue until Dec. 22 and that research would wind down. Fifty-six undergraduates are studying there this semester, including about 20 from Columbia and Barnard College; about 1,400 students have studied there in all.</p>
        <p>Robert Kasdin, senior executive vice president of Columbia, said in a statement that useful research and education had been conducted at Biosphere but that the university wanted to use its resources elsewhere.</p>
        <p>In May, the Department of Energy rejected a Columbia proposal that it turn Biosphere 2 into a federal facility for research on climate change. A review committee for the Energy Department also recommended that any requests for money for the biodome be judged through a competitive process that weighed the possibilities against those elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Joel E. Cohen, a professor of populations at Rockefeller and Columbia Universities who was part of a group that examined Biosphere for Columbia in 1996, said yesterday that Biosphere ''was not designed as a scientific facility'' and that while there had been modifications it was still not clear that it had been ''modified in a way that makes it better to spend money there than in other ways.''</p>
        <p>''Operating that facility is extremely expensive and it's a very long way from Columbia University,'' he added. ''If it were a local university that wanted to use it for education, there might be some promise there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
