<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lingering Summer Lesson; Impact of '71 Sail on Long Island Sound Continues</title>
    <meta content="01SOUN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/01/nyregion/01SOUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="HUMAN NATURE: The Reunion" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1516303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Human Nature: The Reunion"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D71438F932A3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="2077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lingering Summer Lesson; Impact of '71 Sail on Long Island Sound Continues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Setting an Early Sail to Save the Environment</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>PORT CHESTER, N.Y., Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ninth and last article in Human Nature series on Long Island Sound describes reunion of teachers and students who spent month studying water quality of Sound aboard sailing yawl in summer of 1971; experience was awakening that raised their environmental consciousness and helped to mold their lives; photo, map, drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the summer of 1971, a 36-foot sailing yawl named the Strega, carrying 11 teenage boys and three teachers, set out onto Long Island Sound for a monthlong science trip to take the Sound's environmental pulse.</p>
        <p>Thirty-two years later, Clifford Shatz -- now 46, ponytailed and balding -- still could not bring himself to call the teacher who had led the trip, Sidney DuPont, anything but ''Mr. DuPont.'' The name ''Sid,'' he said, simply could not pass his lips, try as he might.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The impact of a science trip in 1971 on Long Island Sound continues to be felt among its crew, which comprised 14 men and teenage boys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the summer of 1971, a 36-foot sailing yawl named the Strega, carrying 11 teenage boys and three teachers, set out onto Long Island Sound for a monthlong science trip to take the Sound's environmental pulse.</p>
        <p>Thirty-two years later, Clifford Shatz -- now 46, ponytailed and balding -- still could not bring himself to call the teacher who had led the trip, Sidney DuPont, anything but ''Mr. DuPont.'' The name ''Sid,'' he said, simply could not pass his lips, try as he might.</p>
        <p>Some things do not change. The deep imprints of a youthful adventure -- 400 miles of open-water sailing, science and coming-of-age -- have persisted for three decades with the members of the Strega's crew who were contacted and brought together by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>The Sound, meanwhile, has been utterly transformed. Its deep waters, stretching 110 miles from here in New York City's northern suburbs to the shores of Rhode Island, were deeply polluted in the early 1970's with raw sewage and industrial waste. Environmental regulation of what communities and companies could dump was only beginning. Water that was thick and green later became clear and blue.</p>
        <p>''It was like pea soup,'' said Chris Kelly, a scrawny 14-year-old in 1971 and now a mechanical engineer living in Manhattan. Mr. Kelly, 46, gazed down into the waters of the Byram River as a boat owned by another member of the Strega's old crew chugged from the Port Chester Yacht Club. ''You could see maybe four or five inches into the water right here,'' he said. ''Now it's, what, three or four feet.''</p>
        <p>In a very real way, the Strega's voyage never ended. Although most of the boys left the small private boarding school they attended, the Becket Academy, in East Haddam, Conn., immediately after the trip, bound for high school, they were altered by the experience, they said.</p>
        <p>Peter Orr, also 46 now, became a scientist partly because of the trip, and worked for years to restore shellfish beds in the eastern Sound -- including some of the ones he had studied on the boat. Mr. Kelly is a mechanical engineer who specializes in energy-efficiency projects intended to reduce electricity use. Mr. Shatz, who owns a food delivery company in Foxboro, Mass., said he is grooming his daughters to appreciate the wonders of nature, as Mr. DuPont did for him.</p>
        <p>Michael Kingery, 47, owner of the boat provided for the reunion of the Strega's crew, said his love of being on the water dates from those years. He still spends as much time on the Sound as he can, he said, when he's not working at his family-owned car dealership in nearby Rye. Of the 11 boys on the Strega, The Times was able to reach five, four of whom were able to attend a reunion sail.</p>
        <p>The context of the early 1970's was, of course, crucial to what happened in those four weeks at sea. The first Earth Day had been organized just a year before the Becket Academy trip, and in that atmosphere, the Strega's mission was considered news: Kids were out there studying the environment. Reporters came aboard for a day and wrote stories.</p>
        <p>But the Strega's crew members mostly now look back at the journey itself as the thing that really changed them. For 28 intense days, they were crammed onto a small boat; Mr. Kelly, for example, recalls having had to sleep atop the stove.</p>
        <p>They had to learn to sail and operate the vessel themselves, and make their own meals. That, Mr. Shatz said, was when he learned to love cooking and food, which became the focus of his career. And they had to keep daily science logs that revolved around a single probing question: what was the state of the water?</p>
        <p>When the students compiled their journals, drawings and photographs at the summer's end, their report had just three huge words on the back in deep blue ink: ''Save Our Sound.''</p>
        <p>''We were eating it, living it, breathing it, all day on the water, every day, and taking it very seriously,'' Mr. Shatz said. ''It can't not have an effect on you. Everyone must have gone away from that trip with an increased consciousness of what was going on in the environment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DuPont, 61, now the headmaster of a private school in Newport Beach, Calif., said he had an agenda on the Strega to create just that kind of world view.</p>
        <p>He grew up on the Sound in Greenwich, Conn., and saw the dismal changes in the waters he loved. Three decades later, he makes no bones about the fact that he was out to change minds and lives. An environmental perspective, he stressed to the boys, was the hallmark of an enlightened mind.</p>
        <p>''I had this mantra,'' he said, looking as tan and lean as he does in the old photographs at age 29, behind the Strega's wheel. ''I'd say, 'You're either an environmentalist, or you're very selfish or very ignorant.' I used to give that to these guys all the time -- boom, boom, boom. That's what it was all about.''</p>
        <p>But the story of the Strega also captures a singular moment, for the Sound and its teenagers, before most of the modern environmental, health and safety regulations were imposed. It was, in many ways, a wilder time. The boys went scuba diving in steaming hot discharge waters from Connecticut's nuclear power plants to assess the creatures that lived there. They casually ate what they caught, and swam when and where they wanted.</p>
        <p>The rules that have cast a net, and for some people, a shadow, over how the Sound can be used -- what fish can be taken and at what size, and what should be eaten or not -- were for the most part years in the future.</p>
        <p>Above all else, the students were teenage boys. In the logs they wrote about the obsessions of environmental science one minute, and the ancient preoccupations of youth the next.</p>
        <p>On July 31, for example, 22 days after they had set sail, Mr. Kelly described an evening on a beach near Mattituck on Long Island, with Mr. Shatz and Mr. DuPont. ''Cliff and I seined with Mr. DuPont, and we got three large blue crabs, one soft shell crab,'' he wrote. ''After dinner we met some girls.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DuPont also took a hand at the logs. He wrote of his plans to lead a science trip on the Sound each year, though he hoped that some day, in the then-far-off 1980's, there might be no need. ''Perhaps the dream of a clean Sound in the future may be the reason we will abandon our project,'' he wrote. ''Let's hope so.''</p>
        <p>It turned out, though, that the Strega's voyage in 1971 was both the first and last. Mr. DuPont left the school in 1972 and completed his Ph.D. in environmental education at the University of Connecticut in 1976. The Becket Academy itself closed in the late 70's.</p>
        <p>But the impact of the trip continues to be felt, and one place it can be detected today is in the rolling hills of northeastern Connecticut, more than 50 miles from the water, where Mr. Orr keeps a dairy farm.</p>
        <p>He was not a student at Becket in 1971, but the school allowed local boys to come on its adventure trips. So Mr. Orr, who lived not far from the campus, signed on for the Strega, Italian for ''witch.'' Once on board, he was assigned by Mr. DuPont to the ''physical water analysis committee,'' which was responsible for documenting water clarity. Part of the job involved testing with a little white disk that the students would suspend in the water. When the disk could no longer be seen, the depth was recorded.</p>
        <p>The science enthralled him, he said, as did his growing appreciation of how the pieces of the natural landscape fit together. He later studied plant biology at Pennsylvania State University and became a researcher in biotechnology for Pfizer Inc., working mainly on drought-resistant corn. Now he thinks about soil erosion and water runoff on the dairy farm, which he and his wife, Kristin, bought in the town of Thompson in 1988.</p>
        <p>''The trip taught me how science was a tool to interpret the environment,'' Mr. Orr said. But the Strega experience, he said, also made him realize, when he began farming, that the land was not really his to do with as he pleased, because it would go on -- along with whatever he had done to it for good or ill -- long after he was gone.</p>
        <p>So he altered the way the corn was planted to reduce soil erosion, and he recycles the manure from the dairy herd to use as fertilizer for the corn, to minimize chemical fertilizers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orr says those weeks on the Sound created convictions that will never go away, and that he hopes to instill in his daughters, Kies, 10, and Lily, 6.</p>
        <p>''It was one of the events in my life that helped form a pillar within me, an appreciation for natural resources,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Where the Sound goes from here, under the imprint of human nature, is less certain. Newer mysteries, like the die-off of its lobster population in 1999, have raised questions that would have been alien to the crew of the Strega in 1971.</p>
        <p>Most scientists believe that overly warm waters, perhaps from long-term climate change, stressed the lobsters. If that is true, then huge new questions are raised about how much can be managed on the Sound. Unlike the spigots of polluters and sewer plants, the input of climate cannot be adjusted with a turn of a wrench or regulator's rule.</p>
        <p>But some things are still predictable.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Kingery was driving his boat back to the Port Chester marina after touring the western Sound, Mr. DuPont suddenly stood up.</p>
        <p>''Guys, look!'' he said, pointing to a little inlet on a nearby island. The water was roiling with feeding fish, thrashing about in what appeared to be multitudes.</p>
        <p>''Stripers, probably,'' Mr. DuPont said, referring to the striped bass that have surged in numbers in the Sound in recent years. ''They're after something.''</p>
        <p>As though the years had melted away, the crew of the Strega stood as one and followed Mr. DuPont's command, gazing into the distance.</p>
        <p>Human Nature</p>
        <p>Over many years of settlement, Long Island Sound has been a breadbasket and a dumping ground, a private playground for the wealthy and a symbol of environmental despair.</p>
        <p>But when people reached for a new definition -- a repaired, restored, managed Sound -- nature did not respond according to the rule book.</p>
        <p>For every push to achieve a certain end, the whorls of the ecosystem have pushed right back, often in unexpected ways.</p>
        <p>This is the last article of a summer-long series on the evolving nature of Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>The previous articles and additional materials, including voices from the reunion of the crew of the Strega, are online at nytimes.com/lisound.</p>
        <p>Human Nature: The Reunion</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
