<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Businesses Take Initiative to Voluntarily Reduce Emissions</title>
    <meta content="01WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Outlook" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/01/business/01warm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1539747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Economy &amp; Business"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alcoa Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Alcoa Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2D7103AF932A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Businesses Take Initiative to Voluntarily Reduce Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Businesses Take Initiative to Voluntarily Reduce Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alcoa and growing number of other businesses are finding they can increase profits by cutting greenhouse gas emissions; their efforts are cited by environmental groups, efficiency experts and some business executives as evidence that Bush administration is too timid in aiming for gradual cut in rate of emission increases; even companies that forsee emissions rising with output are adopting more aggressive goals than administration (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Bush administration and the Republican leadership in Congress oppose capping emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases implicated in global warming, they argue that doing so would damage the economy. Major business lobbies in Washington like the National Association of Manufacturers support that stand.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of businesses are finding that they can cut emissions and enhance the bottom line at the same time. Many are pursuing much more ambitious greenhouse-gas reduction programs than the voluntary goals that the Bush administration favors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of businesses are finding that they can cut emissions and enhance the bottom line at the same time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Bush administration and the Republican leadership in Congress oppose capping emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases implicated in global warming, they argue that doing so would damage the economy. Major business lobbies in Washington like the National Association of Manufacturers support that stand.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of businesses are finding that they can cut emissions and enhance the bottom line at the same time. Many are pursuing much more ambitious greenhouse-gas reduction programs than the voluntary goals that the Bush administration favors.</p>
        <p>Take Alcoa, whose former chairman and chief executive, Paul H. O'Neill, left in 2001 to become President Bush's first Treasury secretary.</p>
        <p>In the spring of 1998, Mr. O'Neill warned in a speech to the aluminum industry's largest trade group that civilization could ''go down the drain'' if climate change was not taken seriously. While there was still much to learn about humanity's role in global warming, he said, the industry needed to confront its reliance on electricity generated from burning fossil fuels that yield carbon dioxide, as well as manufacturing processes that make other greenhouse gases, so known because they tend to trap heat from the sun as they accumulate in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''We shouldn't argue about it,'' Mr. O'Neill said in the speech. ''We should just get on with it.''</p>
        <p>Alcoa has already reduced its carbon dioxide emissions by more than 23.5 percent from 1990 levels while expanding its production.</p>
        <p>Others, including DuPont, International Paper, Ford Motor, American Electric Power and Motorola, have founded the Chicago Climate Exchange. Each has pledged to cut its emissions by 1 percent annually over the next four years, or to buy credits from others who have made an exchange-approved investment to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the Bush administration reckons that cutting emissions would be too costly, and instead aims to reduce the rate of emission increases gradually over the next decade. In rejecting the Kyoto Protocol, which almost all other industrial nations have supported to set caps on emissions of greenhouse gases, President Bush has objected not only to the cost but also to the fact that the agreement does not cover China, India and other big developing nations.</p>
        <p>The companies moving most aggressively in this area are quick to say that they are being driven not by altruism, but by an assessment that investments in emission reductions can end up paying for themselves in reduced operating costs. The changes are also seen as a way to make the companies more profitable.</p>
        <p>Even so, their efforts are cited by environmental groups, efficiency experts and some business executives as evidence that the federal government's policies are too timid.</p>
        <p>The overall goal of the Bush administration is to reduce annual greenhouse emissions per dollar of output by 18 percent in the decade ending in 2012, through a range of voluntary actions. Because the government expects the economy to grow by more than 18 percent in that period, the end result would be higher total emissions.</p>
        <p>At best, the cumulative total of greenhouse gases emitted over the decade in the United States would be 2 percent less than if no changes were made in current practices, according to a study released last month by the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress. The study was based on data from the Department of Energy about oil, gas and coal consumption, the main human sources of greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>''I think it's just a matter of time before tougher goals are set,'' said Paul Tebo, vice president for safety, health and environment at DuPont.</p>
        <p>Even companies that foresee emissions rising with output are adopting more aggressive goals than the administration. Pfizer, the pharmaceutical company, has pledged to cut greenhouse emissions per dollar of output by 35 percent by 2007 compared with 2000 levels.</p>
        <p>Alcoa was the only major company to give testimony before Congress in support of legislation proposed by Senators John McCain, Republican of Arizona, and Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, that would have imposed statutory caps on total emissions, although DuPont wrote a letter favoring the measure. The Senate rejected the measure by a 55-to-43 vote in October, but Mr. McCain said, ''We will be back on this issue.''</p>
        <p>The Chicago Climate Exchange, which begins trading Dec. 12, has tried to create such a market based on voluntary caps adopted by its members. But without government regulations enforcing the caps, there is much less pressure on heavy emitters to participate, and the prices they are willing to pay for allowances may be so low that there is little financial inducement for potential sellers to invest in cutting emissions.</p>
        <p>DuPont, for example, spent more than $50 million reducing emissions around the world in the 1990's, and is now recouping the investment by selling credits and its technical expertise. But almost all of its sales have been overseas, in countries like Britain that have established emissions caps in compliance with the 1997 Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>''Very few companies in this country are willing to commit to buying emission credits to be in compliance with a voluntary greenhouse gas reduction program,'' said Ethan J. Podell, an energy consultant and a former senior vice president for sales and marketing at the Chicago Climate Exchange, in testimony before the Senate Committee on Commerce, Science and Transportation.</p>
        <p>The government, and most businesses, argue that the problem with mandatory caps is that too little is known about the costs and impact of rising temperatures to set limits.</p>
        <p>''It's not a trivial task to design a set of rules that works,'' said Martin B. Zimmerman, group vice president at Ford Motor.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the accounting questions that go with curbing emissions can be daunting. When a company sells a major unit in which it has invested heavily to cut greenhouse emissions, as DuPont is planning to do with its nylon and related textile operations, does it lose all credit for the improvements?</p>
        <p>''The greenhouse gas world is different from other pollutants, because it is more complex and more international,'' said Richard Rosensweig, a strategy consultant in the environmental services unit of Natsource, a leading broker of private energy and environmental trading. ''Climate touches all sectors of the economy.''</p>
        <p>Most large companies moving aggressively to curb emissions are multinationals already planning for the eventual enforcement of caps overseas. The Kyoto Protocol obliges industrial countries to cut greenhouse gas emissions to 5.2 percent below 1990 levels by 2012. It is not yet legally binding for the nations that have signed it, but it will be if Russia follows through on its announced plans to sign it. In the meantime, many countries have already begun developing the rules they will follow to do their part.</p>
        <p>MANY of those multinationals are also cutting emissions aggressively because they see competitive benefits from moving faster than the United States. Alcoa and many other aluminum companies, for example, now say that climate concerns could benefit their industry.</p>
        <p>Their optimism is based on the high percentage of aluminum that is now recycled -- in effect retaining the original energy invested in making the metal -- and on aluminum's role in reducing fuel consumption by replacing heavy steel in cars. Alcoa calculates that if established trends in production efficiency, emissions and use of aluminum in vehicles continue, by 2017 the total tonnage of greenhouse gas emissions saved a year by using aluminum in vehicles will exceed the total amount produced by the industry.</p>
        <p>In pursuit of that projection, Alcoa is increasing its reliance on hydroelectric power and other power sources that do not emit greenhouse gases. It is also planting millions of trees, most of them on Alcoa-owned land, to soak up carbon from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Most of the gains Alcoa claims so far have come from reducing releases of perfluorocarbons, gas compounds that last far longer than carbon dioxide and thus do much more harm, pound for pound.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency estimates that over the course of a century, a given weight of perfluorocarbons has 6,500 to 9,200 times the greenhouse effect of the same weight of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Aluminum smelters generate perfluorocarbon gases when they plunge giant blocks of carbon into enclosed pots filled with molten sodium aluminum fluoride, and then run huge electric charges through the blocks into the liquid bath to separate out the aluminum. The gases build up as the available aluminum in the bath decreases, and eventually block the process. Historically, that was an indicator that it was time to start processing a new batch of material.</p>
        <p>Once they were challenged to manage releases of the gases into the atmosphere, Alcoa and other companies discovered ways to sharply reduce the amounts of gas produced, like etching grooves in the carbon blocks. Along the way, they discovered that the entire process became more efficient.</p>
        <p>''We've had triple wins so far,'' said Randy Overbey, president of Alcoa's power generating business. ''It's helped our labor productivity, the environment and the production process.''</p>
        <p>Economy &amp; Business</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
