<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="18DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D71E3AF93BA25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Great-West Lifeco Offers $4.7 Billion for Canada Life  Great-West Lifeco has agreed to acquire Canada Life Financial for almost $4.7 billion in cash and stock, topping an earlier bid by Manulife Financial. If completed, the deal would create Canada's biggest insurance company. Canada Life had earlier rejected Manulife's offer as inadequate.</p>
        <p>The battle for Canada Life comes after a series of mergers and acquisitions by life insurers. The trend has been reinforced in recent years by the conversion to shareholder ownership from mutual ownership of four of the five biggest companies, including Manulife and Canada Life. [Page C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Great-West Lifeco Offers $4.7 Billion for Canada Life  Great-West Lifeco has agreed to acquire Canada Life Financial for almost $4.7 billion in cash and stock, topping an earlier bid by Manulife Financial. If completed, the deal would create Canada's biggest insurance company. Canada Life had earlier rejected Manulife's offer as inadequate.</p>
        <p>The battle for Canada Life comes after a series of mergers and acquisitions by life insurers. The trend has been reinforced in recent years by the conversion to shareholder ownership from mutual ownership of four of the five biggest companies, including Manulife and Canada Life. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>6 Charged in Mannesmann Takeover  German prosecutors investigating bonus and severance payments made to managers and directors of Mannesmann as Vodafone was taking over the company over in 2000 said that they had charged six executives. News agencies said the six included Mannesmann's former chief executive, Klaus Esser, and Josef Ackermann, the head of Deutsche Bank. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Fiat Expected to Sell Some Units  In a quest to raise cash to shore up its car unit, Fiat is planning to sell its insurance and aerospace-components units, bankers close to Fiat said. Analysts put the likely proceeds of the sales at more than $3.2 billion. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Diet Battles Head for Television  The battle between diet groups promoting a low-fat, high-fiber regimen and those preaching a high-protein, low-carbohydrate approach is headed for TV. The Physicians Committee for Responsible Medicine plans a commercial saying that a high-protein, meat-intense diet can promote osteoporosis, kidney disease and possibly colon cancer. Advertising. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Court Sides With H.M.O. Patients  An appeals court has expanded patients' rights, ruling that consumers can sue an H.M.O. for injuries resulting from a refusal to approve necessary treatment. [Section A.]</p>
        <p>Europe's Bank Signals No Change  The president of the European Central Bank signaled that interest rates would stay as they are for a while longer, saying that the bank could not judge how an economy racked by war fears would react to fighting. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Japan's central bank kept its view of the economy unchanged for a fourth month, saying that growth was hampered by weak domestic spending and wobbly exports. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Major Foreign Markets Rise  Major stock indexes gained around the world on speculation that a war with Iraq may be delayed or averted. Stocks extended a rally that began Friday after the co-chief weapons inspector for the United Nations said more time was needed to determine any wrongdoing. Markets in the United States will reopen today after being closed for Presidents' Day. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Northwest Won't Match Fare Cut  Five airlines that tried to raise fares by $10 each way over the weekend rolled back the price increase after Northwest Airlines refused to match it. Northwest executives have said they did not think the depressed market would support fare increases. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Airline executives of the Star Alliance expressed deep concerns about the harm that military action in Iraq may do to their business as they gathered to welcome Asiana Airlines of South Korea as a new member. [C7.]</p>
        <p>An Internet High-Wire Act  Despite the lingering malaise in travel demand, a few airlines, most of them foreign, and many hotels are spending money to start accommodating the growing demand by business travelers for a good Internet connection. Joe Sharkey: On the Road. [C6.]</p>
        <p>A few groups have devised ways for the environmentally concerned travelers to mitigate their role in the output of carbon dioxide. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
