<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wind Energy Boosters Make Another Foray On East End</title>
    <meta content="12LIWIND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1526753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amagansett (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clavin, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DD133FF931A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wind Energy Boosters Make Another Foray On East End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CLAVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clavin, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Long Island Power Authority's proposal, in aftermath of August 14 blackout, to build 100-foot-tall windmill on Quail Hill Farm in Amagansett; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE Don Quixote, advocates of wind energy on the South Fork are not giving up their fixation on windmills. Their latest proposal for clean electricity, presented last month to the Amagansett Citizens Advisory Committee, calls for a 100-foot-tall windmill on the Quail Hill Farm in that hamlet.</p>
        <p>In the past, the leading proponents of wind energy were environmental groups and the Long Island Power Authority. LIPA wants to find alternate sources of electricity to address Long Island's increasing energy demand and is under a mandate from Governor Pataki to invest $160 million on new technology to promote clean energy and to reduce dependence on oil and natural gas. The South Fork, because of its higher exposure to winds, would seem a promising place for wind-generated electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE Don Quixote, advocates of wind energy on the South Fork are not giving up their fixation on windmills. Their latest proposal for clean electricity, presented last month to the Amagansett Citizens Advisory Committee, calls for a 100-foot-tall windmill on the Quail Hill Farm in that hamlet.</p>
        <p>In the past, the leading proponents of wind energy were environmental groups and the Long Island Power Authority. LIPA wants to find alternate sources of electricity to address Long Island's increasing energy demand and is under a mandate from Governor Pataki to invest $160 million on new technology to promote clean energy and to reduce dependence on oil and natural gas. The South Fork, because of its higher exposure to winds, would seem a promising place for wind-generated electricity.</p>
        <p>The Amagansett turbine project is modest when compared to the wind farm LIPA wants to construct two to six miles off the South Shore. The proposal, for 25 to 50 wind turbines spaced a quarter to a half mile apart, would generate about 100 megawatts. LIPA has put the wind farm project out to bid, and is expected to award a contract soon.</p>
        <p>Nimbyism is not an issue for offshore installations but has been a factor for land-based wind energy projects. Three years ago LIPA's chairman, Richard Kessel, ventured out to East Hampton to present a plan to construct three 50-kilowatt, 100-foot windmills at Camp Hero State Park in Montauk, producing enough electricity to power the Montauk Lighthouse and museum and contribute to the Montauk grid. But the proposal was rebuffed by residents more concerned about the windmills' threat to birds and about spoiling their view of the horizon than about renewable energy.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of the Aug. 14 blackout, the climate may be different. ''That blackout certainly gave people a moment to pause and think about what's up with our energy systems,'' said Scott Carlin, a professor of environmental studies at Southampton College. ''It was the most recent wake-up call that we have to diversify our sources of energy.'' Last year the college became home to a 10-kilowatt wind turbine that, according to Mr. Carlin, ''has been all plus for us so far.''</p>
        <p>A different approach may help too. The presentation in Amagansett was given not by Mr. Kessel or another LIPA official but by Gordian Raacke, executive director of the Citizens Advisory Panel, the LIPA watchdog organization. He has often clashed with the authority, but on the issue of wind-generated electricity, he and LIPA are on the same wavelength.</p>
        <p>''LIPA approached me about its program to site wind turbines on farmland on the North Fork, and asked would I be willing to explore one in East Hampton Town,'' Mr. Raacke recalled. ''I'm glad to do it. We've gotten dozens and dozens of calls since the blackout from people wanting to know more about solar and wind power. The blackout showed that we have to reduce stress on the transmission system. In some cases, solar or wind energy can provide power even during a blackout.''</p>
        <p>His overture differed from LIPA's Camp Hero approach. ''To me, the first step is talk to people in the community and see if it's something they would consider,'' Mr. Raacke said. ''I take a different approach than LIPA, by talking first, then planning.''</p>
        <p>Sylvia Overby, chairwoman of the Amagansett Citizens Advisory Committee, agreed that Mr. Raacke's approach sat well with the group's membership. ''I think the presentation went fine,'' she said. ''Gordian came to us with no agenda, just to provide information. He had the answers, and the answers he didn't have he promised to get us. One of the things that happened with Camp Hero is the people were told what they were getting by LIPA, and that doesn't work for us.''</p>
        <p>Accompanying Mr. Raacke to the Amagansett meeting was a representative of the Peconic Land Trust, a Southampton-based farmland preservation group. It was suggested that the pilot-project wind turbine, able to generate 50 kilowatts per hour, enough to power 12 residences, could be erected on Quail Hill Farm, owned by the trust and on the north side of Montauk Highway. The organic farm is surrounded by wooded property and fields that cannot be developed, so a turbine disturbing neighbors would not be an issue.</p>
        <p>The concept of farmland locations for windmills has already taken hold on the East End. In August 2002, Governor Pataki presided over the dedication of a 100-foot-tall windmill on the Windy Acres Farm in Calverton. It was the first fruit of a collaboration between LIPA and the Long Island Farm Bureau to use farmland for electricity-producing turbines.</p>
        <p>These are far from the traditional grist-grinding windmills of Long Island's past. The one in Calverton cost $225,000 and its blades are computer controlled for optimal efficiency.</p>
        <p>''Overall, Long Island has a fair amount of wind, and it seems logical that farms in certain places would have a few wind turbines,'' said Joe Gergela of the Farm Bureau. ''It is definitely worthy of at least exploring. At Quail Hill or other farms, we encourage seeing if the land can help produce some of the power we need.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has called for 10 percent of Long Island's energy needs should be supplied by renewable resources by 2010. The governor made it easier for farm owners to offer their land for windmills on Sept. 26, when he signed a law that exempts farmers from paying a tax penalty when they convert farmland from agricultural use to electricity generation using wind.</p>
        <p>Amagansett may be next to have a turbine next to turnips. Ms. Overby said that by the Amagansett Citizens Advisory Committee's next meeting, on Monday, Mr. Raacke will have provided answers to questions asked by members last month, and then the organization will decide whether to endorse the wind energy project.If Mr. Raacke overcomes Amagansett's ''I'm Against It'' nickname and gets the civic group's endorsement, the next step would be for LIPA to seek a permit from the East Hampton Town Board.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
