<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Procedure May Save Women In Third World From Cancer</title>
    <meta content="25CERV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/25/health/womenshealth/25CERV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1475123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cervix</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Paul D (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cervical Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DE1530F936A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Procedure May Save Women In Third World From Cancer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Procedure May Save Women in Third World From Cancer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Paul D Blumenthal, of Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, is testing one-visit procedure for women in hopes of reducing cervical cancer deaths, particularly in third-world countries; procedure is described and early on-site research shows positive results with little or no side effects; 80 percent of world's cervical cancer cases are in poor nations and combining diagnosis and treatment into one step avoids problems that can delay or deny care; eventually vaccines could eliminate all cases of cervical cancer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In African hospitals, says Dr. Paul D. Blumenthal of the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, the cervical cancer wards can be found by smell alone. Women come in when their cancers are bleeding uncontrollably or have eaten into their urethras or intestines. By then, even major surgery will not cure them. They come in to die.</p>
        <p>But now he and other public health doctors are testing a simple one-visit procedure that could save many of the thousands of women, most in the third world, who die each year of the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doctors are testing a simple one-visit procedure that could save many of the thousands of women who die each year of cervical cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In African hospitals, says Dr. Paul D. Blumenthal of the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, the cervical cancer wards can be found by smell alone. Women come in when their cancers are bleeding uncontrollably or have eaten into their urethras or intestines. By then, even major surgery will not cure them. They come in to die.</p>
        <p>But now he and other public health doctors are testing a simple one-visit procedure that could save many of the thousands of women, most in the third world, who die each year of the disease.</p>
        <p>The procedure involves washing the cervix with vinegar, peering at it with a flashlight and freezing any white spots with liquid carbon dioxide. The white spots may be precancerous lesions. Destroying them kills cervical cancer virtually at birth.</p>
        <p>The procedure is particularly promising, the doctors say, because it can be done with relatively simple equipment in one visit.</p>
        <p>Doctors from Johns Hopkins and a prominent Thai hospital tested the procedure in a study of 6,000 women in rural Thailand. The study, underwritten by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, is described in a recent issue of The Lancet, a British medical journal. Of the 707 women in the study who had visible white spots, those who received cryogenic treatment on the spot and who returned for a one-year follow-up visit, 94 percent had no lesions a year later. None had a complication requiring hospitalization, 98 percent found the pain only mild or moderate, and more than 95 percent said they were satisfied with the procedure.</p>
        <p>A parallel study of 4,000 patients in Ghana is under way, and its results so far are ''very reassuring,'' Dr. Blumenthal said.</p>
        <p>''My hat's off to him,'' said Dr. Groesbeck Parham, a professor of gynecological oncology at the University of Alabama at Birmingham who has treated women with cervical cancer in South Africa, Sudan and Zambia and runs a group called Friends of Africa that provides such care. ''His method is cheap, it's easy to learn and it's effective, and there were no deaths and no serious bleeding problems in his study.''</p>
        <p>Cervical cancer, once the leading cancer killer among American women, is now, because of Pap smears, a distant seventh, killing 4,100 a year.</p>
        <p>But 80 percent of the world's cervical cancer cases are in poor nations in Africa, Asia and South America. Each year about 470,000 new cases are reported, with about 225,000 deaths.</p>
        <p>It is the leading cancer in Zimbabwe, and in South Africa, the incidence rate is 9 cases per 100,000 white women and 40 cases per 100,000 black women, reflecting the country's wealth gap. (In the United States, it is also 9 per 100,000 whites and 19 per 100,000 blacks.)</p>
        <p>It is a killer in poor countries for a simple reason. The normal Western procedure for detecting cervical cancer is far too cumbersome and expensive for third world health care systems. In the United States, a woman normally has a Pap smear, in which cells are scraped from the cervix, put on a slide, fixed and stained with chemicals and sent to a pathology lab, which mails the results to her doctor.</p>
        <p>If they are abnormal, she sees her doctor to be examined with a colposcope, which lights and magnifies the cervix; a biopsy may be snipped and sent to a lab. If it is cancerous, she returns for surgery.</p>
        <p>In poor countries, anything can go wrong with that chain. Eexpensive imported chemicals run out, lab pathologists become overwhelmed, $3,000 colposcopes break, and so on.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pisake Lumbiganon, a professor of gynecology at Khon Kaen University in Thailand, said two decades of doing Pap smears in Thailand had not cut mortality from cervical cancer. Even when rural doctors bothered to do them, he said, it took up to four months to receive results from a Bangkok lab.</p>
        <p>In a small study he did of women whose results were positive, only about half received further treatment. The rest, he said, ''didn't get the result because of the mail problem, got the results but didn't understand the message, or understood the message but didn't have the money to come.''</p>
        <p>Health care systems are similarly broken all over the world, other doctors said.</p>
        <p>''Many patients simply don't have addresses,'' said Dr. Robert E. Bristow, a gynecological oncologist who has operated on women from Nepal to Ghana. ''In South Africa, they might live in a shantytown. In Thailand, they might live in a rural hamlet that doesn't even have a name.''</p>
        <p>In Nepal, he said, a clinic he visited had a modern electrosurgical-loop apparatus for removing lesions -- but only one disposable loop on hand.</p>
        <p>The technique Dr. Blumenthal and others are testing diagnoses and treats lesions on the same visit. He even adapted it to use carbon dioxide as a freezing agent instead of the nitrous oxide used in the West. Carbon dioxide is much cheaper, gets almost as cold, and is readily available from any soda bottling plant, he said. Nearly every country in the world has a Coke or Pepsi bottling operation.</p>
        <p>Almost all cervical cancers are caused by human papillomaviruses that are sexually transmitted. They first create lesions on the cervix that may take 10 years or more to develop into to cancer.</p>
        <p>When the cervix is washed with 5 percent acetic acid -- common vinegar -- those lesions turn white and can be seen by flashlight or even by daylight.</p>
        <p>''All you need is a room with a window,'' Dr. Bristow said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Parham recently trained traditional healers near Durban, South Africa, to perform the procedure. The only medical equipment needed was a $10 speculum; he bought vinegar and cotton balls on the drive to the village.</p>
        <p>Dr. Parham trained the healers to refer women with lesions to physicians, but Dr. Blumenthal's clinics in Thailand and Ghana train nurses to destroy lesions on the spot by touching them with a metal probe frozen by a jet of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>There is a possibility of ''overtreatment'' with the technique. Without microscopic examinations of a lesion's cells, doctors said, it is impossible to know whether one is benign -- a blocked gland or simple inflammation. But overtreatment has no health risks and adds little to the overall cost of using the procedure. Given the broken-down health systems of poor countries, Dr. Blumenthal said, ''we aim for the best intervention, not the best diagnosis.''</p>
        <p>And in this study, with only one year of follow-up, it was impossible to calculate exactly how many cancers that would have appeared in 10 or 20 years were destroyed.</p>
        <p>But suspect lesions are more common in poor countries than suspicious Pap smears are in rich ones -- about 13 percent of third world women have lesions, Dr. Blumenthal said, versus a positive Pap smear rate of about 4 percent in the United States, though it varies from lab to lab because some report a lot of ''maybes.''</p>
        <p>Vaccines giving immunity against the papilloma strains that cause about 70 percent of the world's cervical cancers are now in clinical trials, with encouraging results so far.</p>
        <p>Vaccines hold out the hope of eventually wiping out cervical cancer, but ''realistically,'' Dr. Blumenthal said, ''it will be 10 years before they're common in the developing world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
