<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1467959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0D6173CF935A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Turkey Close to Accepting More Than 60,000 G.I.'s  Turkey signaled that it was prepared to allow more than 60,000 American troops to use its bases to attack Iraq. At the same time, the Army's top general said that the military force for postwar Iraq could total several hundred thousand troops to provide security and relief aid.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American officials have identified more than 2,000 members of the Iraqi elite, including some to be tried as war criminals and many more the military will attempt to turn against Saddam Hussein. The list was assembled by government agencies, including the Central Intelligence Agency, the Pentagon and the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Turkey Close to Accepting More Than 60,000 G.I.'s  Turkey signaled that it was prepared to allow more than 60,000 American troops to use its bases to attack Iraq. At the same time, the Army's top general said that the military force for postwar Iraq could total several hundred thousand troops to provide security and relief aid.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American officials have identified more than 2,000 members of the Iraqi elite, including some to be tried as war criminals and many more the military will attempt to turn against Saddam Hussein. The list was assembled by government agencies, including the Central Intelligence Agency, the Pentagon and the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Angola is one of six swing votes that the Bush administration desperately needs to pass a Security Council resolution authorizing an attack on Iraq, and as a result, it has been besieged by American and French suitors seeking support.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Copter Crash Victims Identified  The Pentagon identified the four crew members killed in an Army helicopter crash in Kuwait. The Kuwaiti military said that sandstorms were reported in the area where the UH-60 Black Hawk went down.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>French Chef Is Found Dead  Bernard Loiseau, one of France's most celebrated chefs, was found dead beside a hunting rifle in his home. His death followed the downgrading of his restaurant by the Gault-Millau guide and suggestions it was in danger of losing one of the three stars awarded by the Michelin Guide.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Explosions in Venezuela  Explosions outside two diplomatic offices left four people wounded and many others uncertain about the prospects for a peaceful solution to the political crisis. The explosions came two days after President Hugo Chávez berated Spain and Colombia for interfering in Venezuela's internal affairs.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>French Newspaper Accused  The newspaper of the French establishment, Le Monde, has been accused of abusing its power in an investigative book that tells tales of bias, conflicts of interest, hypocrisy and business mismanagement.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Vietnamese Corruption Case  A suspected underworld kingpin and 154 other defendants went on trial in Vietnam, in a case that is testing how far the country will go to clamp down on rampant corruption. The case is the largest ever to reach the courts in Vietnam, one of the world's few remaining communist countries.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Blasts Hit Chinese Universities  Explosions ripped through canteens at two of China's most prominent universities. At least nine people were wounded. There were no immediate claims of responsibility for the blasts and the motive was unclear. Such violence is rare in China but the police were not calling it terrorism.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-22</p>
        <p>Court Orders New Hearing For Death Row Inmate  The Supreme Court ordered a new hearing for a Texas death row inmate in a broad 8-to-1 decision that warned the federal courts of appeals against shutting the door prematurely on state prisoners who seek to present constitutional challenges to their convictions or sentences.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Club Employee Cites Warning  The sound manager at the nightclub where 97 people died Thursday after a band's pyrotechnic display set it ablaze said that three months ago he had advised club owners that such displays presented a fire hazard.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Grist for Malpractice Debate  Lawmakers say the death of a 17-year-old transplant patient who received a heart and lung of the wrong blood type is influencing the Congressional debate over President Bush's proposal to alter medical malpractice laws and may prevent the plan from passing.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Governors Seek Aid Elsewhere  The National Governors Association, rebuffed by President Bush, decided to seek fiscal assistance from Congress. Some lawmakers said they would be willing to help.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Unions Vow Effort Against Bush  The A.F.L.-C.I.O. promised to do its utmost to unseat President Bush in next year's election, insisting that he is vulnerable because of growing public dismay with his economic policies.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Despair in Shuttle Inquiry  Top investigators said they expected to recover no more than about 20 percent of the space shuttle Columbia and may never tease enough information out of its debris to find the cause of the breakup.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Experts Criticize Bush Plan  A panel of experts has strongly criticized the Bush administration's proposed research plan on the risks of global warming, saying that it ''lacks most of the elements of a strategic plan.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Alcohol Sales Under Scrutiny  A study conducted by an institute affiliated with Columbia University concludes that half the alcohol purchased in the United States is sold to teenagers or binge drinkers.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>An Unexpected Choice For Trade Center Site  A key committee recommended that lower Manhattan be rebuilt along the lines of a plan that had seemed out of favor, a proposal for two soaring latticework towers. The unexpected decision appeared to set the stage for a showdown among city and state officials. The winning plan is to be announced tomorrow.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Pataki's Solution to Budget Gap  A giant, outside-the-budget health care program may play a pivotal role in helping to close an $11.5 billion shortfall in the state's regular $90 billion budget.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Extending Harbor's Watch  More surveillance cameras will be added to expand the range of the system that captured a deadly explosion off Staten Island last week. The Coast Guard will be able to automatically identify vessels 30 miles away, an official announced.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>FEMA Gets 30 Days to Respond  A House panel gave the Federal Emergency Management Agency 30 days to disclose how it intends to respond to a state report concluding that emergency plans are inadequate to protect the public in the event of a disastrous radiation leak at the Indian Point nuclear power plant in Westchester County.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C17-21</p>
        <p>Attention on Symbolic Protest  A basketball player's refusal to face the United States flag during the playing of the Star Spangled Banner, a silent protest of the country's plans for war against Iraq, has attracted protestors and national media attention to Manhattanville College.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Shows Prepare for Strike  Broadway shows started rehearsing this week with computer-generated music as they prepared for a possible strike by union musicians, whose contract expires on Sunday.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Charges Filed in Qwest Case  The Justice Department charged four former executives at Qwest Communications with fraud, accusing them of inflating revenues and profits from a project to link Arizona schools to the Internet.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>No Push for Retirement Plans  The White House has largely abandoned the overhaul and expansion of individual retirement and savings accounts less than a month after President Bush proposed it as a legislative priority.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Mixed Results at Hewlett  Hewlett-Packard reported quarterly revenues well below expectations and profits exceeding estimates, suggesting the company's merger with Compaq Computer is producing the promised cost savings.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>MusicNet to Go Online  America Online will introduce MusicNet, a service that lets users download and listen to a catalog of 250,000 songs in the strongest attempt yet to create a legitimate rival to free music-trading websites.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A New Pest-Resistant Corn  The government approved a genetically modified corn that was developed by Monsanto and is resistant to the corn rootworm, a pest that accounted for one out of seven insecticide applications in the U.S.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Statehouse pain and the president; politicians in judges' robes; stumbles on the AIDS front; real reality TV.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
