<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1534330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D81139F933A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Saudi Death Toll Grows; Attack Linked to Al Qaeda  The casualty toll in the attack against a Saudi residential compound grew to 17 dead and 122 wounded. The deputy secretary of state, Richard Armitage, visiting for talks with Crown Prince Abdullah and others, said he was certain Al Qaeda was behind the bombing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American intelligence had been warned that an attack by Al Qaeda was imminent, but the warnings did not come with sufficient details to prevent the blast.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Saudi Death Toll Grows; Attack Linked to Al Qaeda  The casualty toll in the attack against a Saudi residential compound grew to 17 dead and 122 wounded. The deputy secretary of state, Richard Armitage, visiting for talks with Crown Prince Abdullah and others, said he was certain Al Qaeda was behind the bombing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American intelligence had been warned that an attack by Al Qaeda was imminent, but the warnings did not come with sufficient details to prevent the blast.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>U.S. Opposes P.O.W. Funds  The Bush administration is seeking to block a group of American troops who were tortured in Iraqi prisons during the 1991 gulf war from collecting any of the hundreds of millions of dollars in frozen Iraqi assets awarded to them from the government of Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Eighteen people have been detained by the First Armored Division in connection with the rocket attack two weeks ago on the hotel in Baghdad where Deputy Defense Secretary Paul D. Wolfowitz was staying.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Israeli Prisoner Exchange  The Israeli cabinet narrowly approved a prisoner exchange with Lebanon's Hezbollah guerrillas that would free more than 400 Arabs in return for a kidnapped Israeli businessman and the remains of three soldiers. Some critics said that Israel was paying too high a price and fear encouraging additional kidnappings.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Spain's Royal Fairy Tale  Much of Spanish society is treating the engagement of Spain's most eligible bachelor, Prince Felipe of Asturias, to a middle-class divorced television journalist as a fairy tale. The engagement is expected to help maintain popular support.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Reward for Taylor's Capture  The United States is offering a $2 million reward for the capture of the former Liberian president, Charles G. Taylor, who has been charged with war crimes.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Japanese Coalition Holds Power  Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi's governing coalition held on to power in parliamentary elections in Japan, even as voters handed big gains to the main opposition party in voting that could help lead the country toward a two-party system.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Diplomatic Truce With Brazil  Representatives from the United States and Brazil met in Washington and worked out what officials called a set of ideas to frame the global trade talks, set to begin on Nov. 16. There was no breakthrough on the substantive issues, but they agreed to work together.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Democratic Hopes in Guatemala  Presidential elections began in Guatemala, and the people were hungry for change. Many voters expressed pleasure at their ability to vote without fear, after two generations dominated by political violence and repression.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-19</p>
        <p>With Cash Tight, States Reassess Long Jail Terms  State legislatures facing budget crises are beginning to rethink their costly approaches to crime after two decades of passing ever tougher sentencing laws and prompting a prison building boom.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Battle Over Grocery Pay  A work stoppage California is pitting 70,000 cashiers and stockers, who are trying to retain their pay and benefits, against supermarkets, which say they need to pay new workers less in order to stay competitive.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Superfund Job Is Not Yet Done  The Continental Steel site in Indiana is one in a big backlog of hazardous waste sites that has emerged in recent years. Financing for the Superfund program, which cleans toxic waste sites, has been delayed.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Gore Criticizes Terrorism Law  Former Vice President Al Gore called for a repeal of the law expanding counterterrorism powers, calling it a ''terrible mistake'' for its effect on civil liberties.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Wide Split in Medicare Debate  No issue excites more passion than a proposal for Medicare to compete with private health plans. Conservatives see it as a way to slow spending, but many Democrats say it would undermine Medicare.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Home Schooling's New Breed  More American parents are choosing to teach their children at home, according the federal Education Department. Newcomers to home schooling are fed up with the shortcomings of public education and the cost of private schools.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pay Rises for College Chiefs  Four presidents of private universities were paid more than $800,000 last year, and the era of the million-dollar college president is approaching, according to a survey by The Chronicle of Higher Education.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>Disappointment for 'Matrix'  ''The Matrix: Revolutions,'' the final installment of the science-fiction trilogy, earned $85.5 million in its first five days. Analysts had expected it to earn $90 million to $100 million.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>Pataki Pledges Crash Memorial  Governor Pataki promised a memorial to commemorate the crash of American Airlines Flight 587 in Queens almost two years ago, in which 265 people were killed.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Chinese Press Competition  One of Hong Kong's biggest newspapers is considering starting a New York City edition, which would be the city's fifth Chinese daily newspaper. Competition is already aggressive.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Rabbi Creates Kosher Museum  The founder of American Jewish Legacy has created an exhibit that offers glimpses of how Jewish dietary laws were followed from the mid-17th century into the last century.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>U.S. to Seek Ozone Exemptions  The two-decade effort to eliminate chemicals that harm the ozone layer faces a serious test as the Bush administration seeks international support for broad exemptions to a 2005 ban on a popular pesticide.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>3 Diseases Share Genetic Link  Scientists have found an unexpected genetic link among three common autoimmune diseases: psoriasis, rheumatoid arthritis and systemic lupus erythematosus.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Doubt Cast on Corn Reaction  A vocal consumer who complained about allergic reactions to a type of genetically engineered corn turns out not to have been allergic to it after all, a study reports.</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-9</p>
        <p>Mantle Family Auction  Mickey Mantle's family is planning to auction some of his memorabilia on Dec. 8.</p>
        <p>D6</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Places Seeking Jobs Rush to Outbid Each Other  Municipal and state governments are stepping up subsidies to companies that offer to bring sophisticated operations into their territories, escalating a bidding war for a shrunken pool of jobs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Printing Giant Is Made  R. R. Donnelley &amp; Sons agreed to acquire Moore Wallace for $2.8 billion in stock, creating a printing giant that manufactures everything from magazines like Sports Illustrated and TV Guide to billing and shipping labels for companies like United Parcel Service and J. C. Penney.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>J. P. Morgan Investigated  Securities regulators are investigating more than two dozen brokers at a unit of J. P. Morgan Chase to determine if they improperly sold mutual fund shares to generate increased commissions, according to a regulatory official briefed on the matter.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>News Corp. Russia Deal Seen  NTV, one of Russia's biggest national television networks, has been in discussions with the News Corporation regarding the sale of NTV's satellite business, two people said.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Race for Grid Computing  Europe is moving faster than the United States to capitalize on a process that harnesses together many personal computers, European and American officials said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Plan Could Cost Suppliers  Some consumer products companies will have to invest millions of dollars to comply with Wal-Mart's drive to have every carton and palette it receives carry a radio identification tag, according to a report.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Welfare reform for farmers; a manufactured crisis on judges; Brent Staples on California and ''Blade Runner.''</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire and Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Autos</p>
        <p>D10  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2  Bridge</p>
        <p>E5  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E6-7  Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  Weather</p>
        <p>A16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
