<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Make Money While the Sun Shines</title>
    <meta content="19NJSOAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1528531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="SOAPBOX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Deptford (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florio, James J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D9133EF93AA25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Make Money While the Sun Shines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES J. FLORIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Florio, James J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former New Jersey Gov James Florio Soapbox essay promotes production and use of ethanol, gasoline additive that is made from field corn; supports proposal to build ethanol plant in West Deptford, NJ; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PASS by a cornfield along the highway and it's quite natural to think it is nothing more than that -- a cornfield. In truth, though, what's growing there can also be a way to obtain cleaner air, promote energy independence, curb sprawl and create lots of jobs as well.</p>
        <p>All this from a field of corn?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PASS by a cornfield along the highway and it's quite natural to think it is nothing more than that -- a cornfield. In truth, though, what's growing there can also be a way to obtain cleaner air, promote energy independence, curb sprawl and create lots of jobs as well.</p>
        <p>All this from a field of corn?</p>
        <p>Yes, if the crop is used to make ethanol.</p>
        <p>Field corn -- what's fed to livestock as opposed to the sweet corn we buy at farm stands -- is the raw material for making ethanol, or ethyl alcohol. This clear liquid, when blended with gasoline, does two important things. It increases octane - helping the engine to run smoothly - and it improves the quality of what is emitted into the air from using gasoline. Demand for ethanol has grown since the federal Clean Air Act amendments of 1990. These amendments required that oxygenated fuel (a blend that increases combustion efficiency of gasoline, thereby reducing carbon monoxide emissions) be sold in places like New Jersey, where levels of carbon monoxide are considered unhealthy.</p>
        <p>The demand is expected to grow even more because of legislation requiring the phasing out of a substance called MBTE, often used instead of ethanol as a gasoline additive. Unlike ethanol, MBTE is suspected of being a threat to clean air and water.</p>
        <p>Because adding ethanol to gasoline makes the fuel more efficient, its use will help the United States reduce its reliance on foreign oil even as it helps to make the air we breathe safer. According to some estimates, the use of ethanol today reduces demand for gasoline and MBTE imports by nearly 100,000 barrels a day -- enough to cut more than $1 billion a year from the federal trade deficit. And the production of ethanol employs more than 40,000 people today.</p>
        <p>Now investors are being sought for an ethanol plant proposed to be built in West Deptford, Gloucester County. It's a good idea for much the same reason that ethanol is a good idea. And it will be a boost for New Jersey farmers and the state's efforts to stop open space from being gobbled up by development.</p>
        <p>New Jersey has lost more than a million acres of farmland to housing and commercial development over the past 40 years. One-sixth of what is left is used today to produce 10 million bushels a year of field corn for animal feed. Based on 10-year averages, New Jersey farmers can expect about $2.58 a bushel for that corn, minus transportation costs. That price has dropped by about half over the past decade -- bad news for farmers.</p>
        <p>The good news is that selling the same bushel of corn to an ethanol distilling plant would bring farmers an additional 15 to 20 cents a bushel. And having the plant so near to the farms would also reduce the transportation costs. Today, most of the nation's nearly 70 ethanol plants are in the Midwest. There are no ethanol plants in the Northeast. Having such a plant in New Jersey would mean farmers in the state could make more money growing field corn than they do now, making it easier for them to stay in the farming business. That, in turn, helps to curb sprawl as it reduces the incentives for farmers to sell out to developers.</p>
        <p>The process of making ethanol produces byproducts that add even more value. For example, converting the starch from field corn into alcohol generates a high-energy animal feed supplement that over the past 10 years has had an average price of $115 a ton. Another useful byproduct of the ethanol distilling process is carbon dioxide, which that can be marketed to makers of carbonated beverages and dry ice.</p>
        <p>All told, the proposed ethanol plant would create a market for about 40 percent of all the field corn grown in New Jersey, at prices above what farmers get now for selling and shipping the corn out of state for animal feed. Meanwhile, building the plant will create several hundred construction jobs; and its operation will require 30 to 40 fulltime workers with an annual payroll of more than $1.5 million.</p>
        <p>Any one of the benefits of ethanol -- cleaner air, reduced dependence on foreign oil, new jobs, help to farmers that in turn curbs sprawl -- would be enough to make a strong case for its expanded use and for putting a distilling plant in New Jersey. Taken together, they are a compelling package of reasons why our state should embrace this opportunity. It is rare to find public policy ideas that serve multiple goals at the same time. This is one of them, adding up to a good investment in everyone's future.</p>
        <p>SOAPBOX James J. Florio was governor of New Jersey from 1990 to 1994.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James J. Florio was governor of New Jersey from 1990 to 1994.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
