<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eruption Science: Volcanoes as Labs</title>
    <meta content="18VOLC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/18/science/18MAGM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1536260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Naples (Italy)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cascade Volcano Observatory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Museum of Natural History (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Webster, James (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Vivo, Benedetto (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0DF1E38F93BA25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="2181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eruption Science: Volcanoes as Labs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eruption Science: Volcanoes as Labs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geologist Dr James Webster and Dr Benedetto De Vivo of University of Naples (Italy) collaborate on project to try and understand why volcanoes erupt; Cascade Volcano Observatory holds half billion people worldwide live within 60 miles of active volcanoes; hopes better understanding of volcanic changes will stave off disasters; physical dynamics, chemical changes, seismic forces and high-pressure gases forming intense bubbles are key components in quest to understand volcanoes; ring of fire region described; Webster's experiment at American Museum of National History detailed; photos; drawing; chart; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tucked away in a four-foot-high, blue steel box in the American Museum of Natural History in Manhattan, a few steps from the tourists milling among the hot dog stands outside, is a 2,000-degree speck of magma -- molten rock, held under terrific pressure -- from the catastrophic eruption of Mount Vesuvius in Roman times.</p>
        <p>Yes, this is the stuff that exploded and rained down on Pompeii in A.D. 79. Dr. James Webster, geologist, and his associates gathered pumice from the slopes of Vesuvius, and now he is cooking and squeezing the material to the same temperatures and pressures it had in the seething belly of the volcano before the eruption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Geologists new work on what makes volcanoes go bang reveals frothy, viscous masses that crack and groan as they rise through irregular fissures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tucked away in a four-foot-high, blue steel box in the American Museum of Natural History in Manhattan, a few steps from the tourists milling among the hot dog stands outside, is a 2,000-degree speck of magma -- molten rock, held under terrific pressure -- from the catastrophic eruption of Mount Vesuvius in Roman times.</p>
        <p>Yes, this is the stuff that exploded and rained down on Pompeii in A.D. 79. Dr. James Webster, geologist, and his associates gathered pumice from the slopes of Vesuvius, and now he is cooking and squeezing the material to the same temperatures and pressures it had in the seething belly of the volcano before the eruption.</p>
        <p>And like some diabolical brewmaster, he has spiked the mixture with the one original ingredient the pumice was lacking: the volatile gases that had been dissolved in the Vesuvian magma, the gases whose explosive release threw ash into the stratosphere and sent deadly clouds called pyroclastic flows racing down the slopes of the volcano. Dr. Webster is, in effect, putting the fizz back into flat Champagne.</p>
        <p>His experiment poses no threat since the piece of magma is far too tiny. Still, the juxtaposition with the oblivious people outside is thought-provoking: some half a billion people worldwide live within 60 miles of historically active volcanoes, according to the Cascade Volcano Observatory of the United States Geological Survey. Around the slopes of Vesuvius alone, which erupted as recently as 1944, 2.5 million people are living in what is now Naples -- one reason that Dr. Webster's closest collaborator on the work is Dr. Benedetto De Vivo of the University of Naples.</p>
        <p>This little chemistry experiment is part of a worldwide effort to understand what makes volcanoes -- darkly famous names like Mount St. Helens and Pinatubo and Krakatau and Vesuvius -- go bang.</p>
        <p>Other researchers are studying the dynamics of the hot, pressurized bubbles that form in the magma before it erupts, much like shaken seltzer, soda or Champagne. Others are analyzing the ominous seismic signals, called long-period oscillations, that ring out from the frothy magma as it moves inside the beast.</p>
        <p>''All of those things mean that the last few years we're really making big advances in understanding how the system behaves,'' said Dr. Steve Sparks, a professor of geology at Bristol University in England, ''and the key to all of this is linking the observations to the models.''</p>
        <p>Many people picture a volcano's innards as a vertical tube like a straw drawing magma from a balloonlike well of magma, which obligingly burbles out through a crater. The geologists' new work reveals frothy, viscous masses that crack and groan as they rise through irregular fissures.</p>
        <p>The chemistry and dynamics are so complex that the same magma, in the same volcano, can either create a tremendous explosion or ooze forth sedately -- called an ''effusive'' eruption -- depending on slight differences in how fast the magma rises.</p>
        <p>''We all cringe when we see the balloon and straw because that's everybody's view of a volcano,'' said Dr. Steve McNutt, research professor of volcano seismology at the Geophysical Institute of the University of Alaska. ''We think it's quite a bit more complicated than that.''</p>
        <p>Volcanologists are not ready to say that theirs has become a predictive science, like meteorology. But the new science of volcanoes has taken great strides, the scientists say. They cite the subtle seismic blips called tornillos that were picked up from Galeras, a volcano in Colombia, before it erupted and killed nine members of a research party at the summit in 1993.</p>
        <p>''Ten years on from Galeras we know an enormous amount more about those tornillos and L.P. events,'' Dr. Sparks said, referring to long-period, or low-pitched, rumbles characteristic of active volcanoes. ''If there was another event like Galeras, it's hard to imagine that in similar circumstances the scientists would be killed.''</p>
        <p>Standing next to a tall beige cabinet filled with drawers of mineral samples at the museum, Dr. Charles Mandeville, a volcanologist there, holds two large rocks. The one in his left hand is heavy, jagged and charcoal-colored, pitted with tiny round holes. In his right is a pale gray, friable, bloblike object of about the same size that feels light enough to float on water.</p>
        <p>The rocks are at the center of a volcanological version of the nature-nurture debate. ''These two samples have identical chemistry,'' Dr. Mandeville said; they are the geologic equivalent of identical twins. And the pieces were drawn from the same magma supply and ejected from the same volcano, Mount Mazama, which exploded and formed Crater Lake in Oregon some 7,600 years ago. The dark, denser sample, he said, emerged in an effusive event that preceded the cataclysmic eruption by a few weeks or months.</p>
        <p>Like sociologists looking for environmental factors to explain criminal behavior, volcanologists around the world want to understand those striking differences.</p>
        <p>The scientists start with a general grasp of how explosive volcanoes form. They are most common around the ''Ring of Fire,'' which follows the Pacific coastline from the western limn of South America, Mexico, the United States and Canada, across the Aleutian Islands and down eastern Russia through Japan, Indonesia and New Zealand.</p>
        <p>In those places, the ocean crust, laden with water, is slowly diving beneath the much thicker crust of the continents in a process called subduction. The ocean crust heats and releases its water, which diffuses upward and soaks into the earth's hot mantle. Because water alters the chemical structure of the mantle rock and causes its melting point to fall, parts of the rock melt and, like enormous hot-air balloons in slow motion, rise through fissures in the mantle.</p>
        <p>As the magma rises, the confining pressure on it drops and the water in it begins to form bubbles. So many bubbles form that they can occupy as much as 90 percent of the volume of the magma as it moves toward the top of a volcano, said Dr. Donald Dingwell, the director of earth and environmental sciences at the University of Munich. And when the volcano erupts, he added, ''the basic explosive energy is coming from the high-pressure gas in the bubbles.''</p>
        <p>Although volcanologists now agree with that general picture, it leaves open the crucial question of why some eruptions are explosive and others -- often in the same volcano, as with Mount Mazama -- merely effusive, spitting up magma like overheated oatmeal on a stovetop.</p>
        <p>The experiments in Dr. Webster's pressure cooker on Central Park West are designed to look at one side of that multifaceted mystery. The magma from Vesuvius, an explosive volcano outside the Ring of Fire, lost its water when the bubbles burst during the Pompeii eruption. But before he seals fragments of the pumice inside a small gold capsule and places it in the cooker, he includes a source of water. The magma soaks it up, and he cools the sample carefully so that none is released.</p>
        <p>Then he and Dr. Mandeville place the sample in a microscope outfitted with an instrument called a Fourier transform infrared spectrometer, which can measure the water hidden in the structure of the rock. The results show how much water the magma soaked up at various pressures, corresponding to various depths in the earth.</p>
        <p>Because water is not the only volatile substance the magma can soak up -- sulfur, chlorine and carbon dioxide are others -- Dr. Webster repeats his experiments with different combinations of the chemicals locked in the capsule with the magma. The results show, in fact, that only trace amounts of the additional chemicals can make it much harder for the water to stay dissolved in the magma as it rises.</p>
        <p>The implication is that the potentially explosive bubbles may begin to form much farther down in the crust than previously thought, deeper than 10 miles, and play an important role in determining the type of eruption much earlier in the process.</p>
        <p>''There's growing evidence that these gases start to come out of solution at much greater depth than had been believed,'' said Dr. Paul Wallace, a volcanologist at the University of Oregon.</p>
        <p>Out on the slopes of the volcanoes, Dr. Wallace and Dr. Webster also collect small bits of glass that form in the magma as it rises and cools, trapping the volatile gases like flies in amber. The results add weight to the significance of the bubbles and the gases within them.</p>
        <p>The significance of findings like those may be illuminated by theoretical and experimental work by Dr. Dingwell, in Munich, and his colleagues. He pointed out that as the water outgasses and forms bubbles, the magma itself becomes drastically more viscous, or syrupy. A drop by a factor of 10 in the amount of water in the magma can cause its viscosity to soar by a factor of a million, Dr. Dingwell said.</p>
        <p>The magma can become so viscous that it acts like a solid, plugging its conduit and causing terrific pressure to build. The bubbles also have a hard time expanding and dissipating in the syrupy mass, meaning that they stay inside the molten rock like bits of dynamite waiting to explode.</p>
        <p>If the magma rises slowly enough, the bubbles, like air in honey, do have time to expand, coalesce and leak away through fissures in the earth. A little faster, perhaps because the subterranean forces are slightly greater, and the trapped energy remains inside the magma, now as rigid as glass.</p>
        <p>''The magma can become embrittled by losing gas,'' said Dr. Sparks of Bristol University, ''and this leads to conditions whereby the thing can explode.''</p>
        <p>Additional gases rising from fresh magma below can also make the system more unstable and prone to a huge eruption.</p>
        <p>The brittleness of the magma may help explain why the seismic jolts called long-period oscillations are indicators of an eruption, said Dr. Bernard Chouet, a geophysicist at the Geological Survey. The magma can crack as it flows, releasing gases that set off resonances -- the oscillations -- within cavities and cracklike conduits in the mountain. Then, because it is ultimately a liquid, the cracks can close up before the magma ruptures again, producing an insistent signal of disaster.</p>
        <p>That picture is far from theoretical, as Dr. Chouet used repetitive signals -- then not nearly as well understood -- to help predict the imminent eruption of Mount Redoubt, an Alaskan volcano, in December 1989. It continued to erupt in 1990.</p>
        <p>''It's a succession of fracture and healing, fracture and healing,'' Dr. Chouet said. As subtle as the signal and the physics behind it are, the potential outcome, he said, is anything but: ''It blows the top to smithereens.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
