<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reports Detail a Hypothetical Shuttle Rescue</title>
    <meta content="Y29SHUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/29/science/29SHUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1530995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Michael P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccool, William C (Cmdr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Husband, Rick D (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Laurel Salton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chawla, Kalpana (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, David M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDF1630F93AA15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reports Detail a Hypothetical Shuttle Rescue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reports Detail a Hypothetical Shuttle Rescue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD and WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E; Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia Accident Investigation Board releases papers suggesting that two astronauts might have been able to climb out of space shuttle hatch and inspect damaged left wing, if one had used other as ladder; documents discuss hypothetical ways spacecraft might have been saved (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pair of spacewalking astronauts could have climbed out of the Columbia's air hatch and inspected its damaged left wing if one of them had used the other as a ladder, according to documents released on Tuesday by the Columbia Accident Investigation Board.</p>
        <p>The documents -- hundreds of pages of material, much of it used to support the board's Aug. 26 report on the loss of the shuttle and its crew -- give a variety of new details on the accident and its aftermath.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pair of astronauts could have climbed out of the Columbia's air hatch and inspected its damaged left wing, according to documents released on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A pair of spacewalking astronauts could have climbed out of the Columbia's air hatch and inspected its damaged left wing if one of them had used the other as a ladder, according to documents released on Tuesday by the Columbia Accident Investigation Board.</p>
        <p>The documents -- hundreds of pages of material, much of it used to support the board's Aug. 26 report on the loss of the shuttle and its crew -- give a variety of new details on the accident and its aftermath.</p>
        <p>They suggest that in the estimate by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, an effort to rescue the Columbia astronauts if the damage had been identified during the flight would have carried substantial risks.</p>
        <p>Sending up another shuttle, the Atlantis, as a rescue vehicle could have been done with low to moderate risk, NASA engineers told the accident board, but transferring the Columbia astronauts to the Atlantis would have had a moderate to high risk. One problem is that the necessary training for the rescuers would have had to be crammed into two weeks, rather than the year such ''extravehicular activity'' normally takes.</p>
        <p>The new documents say the rescue option, explored by NASA after the crash at the investigators' request, would have required the astronauts to tolerate a level of carbon dioxide 75 percent higher than the level at which the agency would ordinarily end a mission. And in one analysis, NASA assumed that the astronauts would sleep 12 hours out of 24, to minimize oxygen consumption.</p>
        <p>In one sense the rescue studies were moot before they were written, because NASA did not begin looking at that option until after the Feb. 1 crash. But since the agency is exploring how to inspect its three surviving shuttles during flights and how to repair any damage found, the details may yet be instructive.</p>
        <p>NASA had previously concluded that it might have been possible to repair the wing's leading edge, damaged when struck by insulation foam on liftoff. The information released on Tuesday lays out some of the details, including how holes of different sizes might have been plugged.</p>
        <p>Another study with implications for the future was on the risk to aircraft and people on the ground of debris from a falling shuttle. The report said the risk was fairly small.</p>
        <p>The board also released a ''crew survivability report.'' Like the Aug. 26 report, it said that the astronauts were killed by ''blunt force trauma'' and hypoxia, or lack of oxygen. But it added various details.</p>
        <p>The crew compartment came apart because it was subjected to strong dynamic forces while weakened by heat, the report said. The forces were so strong that the seat belt straps were torn apart and then retracted into their rollers.</p>
        <p>The final oral communication with the captain, Col. Rick D. Husband, when he responded to a comment by ground controllers with ''Roger, uh,'' preceded the breakup of the main body of the shuttle by about 48 seconds. The crew cabin breakup came about 30 seconds after that. Through most of that period, accelerations in the crew cabin, as it was buffeted in its descent, would not have injured the crew, the report said. In the 78 seconds between the loss of oral communication and the crew cabin breakup, the shuttle fell a little more than 50,000 feet, to 148,800 feet.</p>
        <p>Investigators judged the extent of damage through a variety of techniques. For example, helmet visors were made of two kinds of plastic, only one of which melted, giving a strong indication of the peak temperature range.</p>
        <p>Repair options were also laid out. Had the Columbia astronauts looked at a hole in the wing and sought to fix it themselves, they would have had a fair chance of making the problem worse, according to the report.</p>
        <p>They might, though, have found a variety of metal parts to stuff into a bag to put in the hole, with the neck of the bag protruding, the report said. That solution ''would keep the metal in place at least until the bag burned through.'' The object would have been to keep the wing intact through a four-minute window, including the time when the shuttle passed through 30,000 feet, when the crew might have bailed out.</p>
        <p>Keeping the left wing intact would have become progressively harder as the shuttle descended, according to the report.</p>
        <p>A statistical study done for the accident investigation board by Valador Inc. found that the risk of a fatality on the ground from the shuttle's breakup was less than one per crash. The precise risk is uncertain because it is not clear how much of the debris reached the ground and how much burned up in descent. Thirty-eight percent of the Columbia's dry weight was recovered.</p>
        <p>In the Columbia's case, low population density in the area played a role in the absence of fatalities, as did the fact that some people were indoors. Much of the debris recovered on the ground had a ''low ballistic coefficient,'' meaning it was light or slow-falling enough to be blocked by roofs and other barriers, the study said.</p>
        <p>The risk to aviation was smaller than the risk to people on the ground, the study said, and most of that risk was to private planes, not airliners.</p>
        <p>''To the extent that future orbiter re-entry accidents are likely to produce similar debris impacts, public risk from shuttle re-entry may be mitigated by landing during the middle of the night, when almost everyone is inside a shelter and few aircraft are in flight,'' the study said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
