<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>January Auto Sales Fall 2% As Analysts See Tough Year</title>
    <meta content="Y04AUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/04/business/04AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nissan Motor Company Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DC1138F937A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>January Auto Sales Fall 2% As Analysts See Tough Year</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Auto Sales Down in January</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Feb. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Auto sales dropped 2 percent in January from year earlier, signaling what many analysts say will be tough year for industry; consumers are expected to benefit from new products, particularly from foreign automakers, and cheaper prices because of competition; Ford Motor sales were up 4 percent while General Motors sales fell 2 percent and Chrysler sales fell 12 percent; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Auto sales dropped 2 percent in January from a year earlier, carmakers reported today, signaling what many analysts say will be a tough year for the industry. Consumers are expected to benefit, though, from a wave of new products, particularly from foreign automakers like Nissan Motor, and cheaper prices because of the competition.</p>
        <p>Ford sales were up 4 percent, while G.M. sales fell 2 percent and Chrysler sales fell 12 percent. Sales were also down sharply from December as Detroit and particularly General Motors stepped back from lavish end-of-the-year incentives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Auto sales dropped 2 percent in January from last year, signaling what many analysts believe will be a tough year for the industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Auto sales dropped 2 percent in January from a year earlier, carmakers reported today, signaling what many analysts say will be a tough year for the industry. Consumers are expected to benefit, though, from a wave of new products, particularly from foreign automakers like Nissan Motor, and cheaper prices because of the competition.</p>
        <p>Ford sales were up 4 percent, while G.M. sales fell 2 percent and Chrysler sales fell 12 percent. Sales were also down sharply from December as Detroit and particularly General Motors stepped back from lavish end-of-the-year incentives.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the numbers would have been worse had they not been propped up by sales to fleets, which are less profitable for automakers. One of the most popular vehicles last month was the Buick Century, a staple of rental car fleets; its sales rose 174 percent.</p>
        <p>Product plans disclosed by automakers in the last few days indicated that the industry was ranging widely in its efforts to lure customers.</p>
        <p>Ford Motor executives said the company planned to produce fuel-efficient hybrid vehicles for several of its global brands this decade. Ford has already said it will sell a hybrid version of the Escape sport utility, but executives said the company might also build a hybrid Ford sedan and offer hybrid vehicles from the company's Volvo and Mazda units.</p>
        <p>General Motors, meanwhile, said that it would make a pickup version of its Hummer H2 sport utility next year. The company also surprised analysts by announcing that it had four new minivans in the works, though two are replacements of existing models. Minivans have been losing market share.</p>
        <p>Ford executives said the Escape hybrid would be available by the end of the year, as previously announced, but only to government or corporate fleet customers. The general public will have to wait until the middle of next year. Ford said it expected annual sales of 20,000 to 30,000 Escape hybrids.</p>
        <p>Hybrids supplement the internal combustion engine with electric power. While only 150,000 hybrid vehicles have been sold by Toyota Motor and Honda Motor since the late 1990's, they are increasingly figuring in the industry's product lineups.</p>
        <p>General Motors plans to enter the market in 2005 with a hybrid version of the Saturn Vue sport utility; Chrysler, a unit of DaimlerChrysler, plans to produce a small number of hybrid versions of its Dodge Ram pickup.</p>
        <p>''Ford's decision signals that the race is on to be the industry leader in clean-car technology,'' said Daniel Becker, director of the Sierra Club's program on global warming and energy.</p>
        <p>Chris Theodore, vice president for Ford, Lincoln and Mercury product development, said the company had designed its Escape hybrid system to be easily adaptable to other models.</p>
        <p>''You can plug and play almost -- that's a bit of an exaggeration -- but you can transfer the basic module to other vehicles,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A hybrid car is not to be confused with the hydrogen cars that President Bush promoted as the automotive technology of the future in his State of the Union address.</p>
        <p>All of the major automakers are working on cars powered by hydrogen fuel cells, which generate electricity through chemical reactions, but they are considered to be years away from mass production.</p>
        <p>''Fuel cells, there is a time factor involved,'' said Prabhakar Patil, the chief engineer on Ford's Escape hybrid project. ''In my estimation, mass production, 100,000 units or higher, is not going to happen for at least another 15 years. Hybrids are ready.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Patil added that the development of fuel-cell vehicles would be aided by production of hybrids, because both use electric drive systems.</p>
        <p>The Escape will operate much like the existing Toyota Prius. An electric motor will power the vehicle at low speeds, and the gas engine, generally, will take over at 20 miles per hour or more. The vehicle will also use a technology that traps energy used in braking. Ford says that it will get close to 40 miles per gallon in city driving, where the hybrid system is most effective. City mileage in current Escape models ranges from 18 to 23 m.p.g.</p>
        <p>Automakers reported that sales of sport utilities, pickups and minivans -- the crucial profit center for the auto industry -- were sluggish last month.</p>
        <p>Over all, Toyota sales fell 6 percent and Volkswagen sales fell 16 percent, while Honda sales rose 6 percent and Nissan was up 1 percent.</p>
        <p>''It was an O.K. month,'' said Paul Ballew, the chief industry sales analyst for G.M. ''If it were to persist over a quarter, then I would become concerned.''</p>
        <p>Bill Hopkins, a G.M. dealer in Marianna, Fla., a rural area about 65 miles west of Tallahassee, said the balky economy and tensions in the Middle East had weighed on buyers.</p>
        <p>''It's the uncertainty of the times,'' he said. And, he added, it was cold last month -- as low as the single digits in his area. With that kind of cold in Florida, Mr. Hopkins said, ''we can't function.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
