<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Consumers Playing the Field? Oh, Behave!</title>
    <meta content="09POWE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/09/nyregion/09POWE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1463650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D6133BF93AA35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Consumers Playing the Field? Oh, Behave!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chief Goal of Deregulation, Real Choice, Remains Elusive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chief goal of energy deregulation in New York State, to give consumers choice of electricity supplier, has not taken hold because most have not elected to change; Con Edison continues to get most business; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The original idea of energy deregulation in New York sounds like something Austin Powers might have thought up. Consumers, so the theory went, would be divorced from their old ball-and-chain utility companies, and the electricity marketplace would become a kind of giant dating game, full of come-ons and casual liaisons: no long-term commitments, no guilt.</p>
        <p>Utilities like Con Ed, which had been boring -- if dependable -- partners under the old regulated regime would become spontaneous and exciting, surfing for the best wholesale prices to pass on to their customers. Customers would move fast, too, and be able to dump their old energy providers in a heartbeat if a sexier, cheaper deal walked in the door.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The vision of a deregulated New York electricity marketplace with no long-term commitments and plenty of choice may never become reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The original idea of energy deregulation in New York sounds like something Austin Powers might have thought up. Consumers, so the theory went, would be divorced from their old ball-and-chain utility companies, and the electricity marketplace would become a kind of giant dating game, full of come-ons and casual liaisons: no long-term commitments, no guilt.</p>
        <p>Utilities like Con Ed, which had been boring -- if dependable -- partners under the old regulated regime would become spontaneous and exciting, surfing for the best wholesale prices to pass on to their customers. Customers would move fast, too, and be able to dump their old energy providers in a heartbeat if a sexier, cheaper deal walked in the door.</p>
        <p>But the divorce, as it turned out, was not final. Most residents and small businesses did not get wooed by anyone, so they missed out on the electricity singles scene. Now, more and more economists, environmentalists and consumer advocates are saying that uninhibited consumer choice, at least as it was envisioned in the mid-1990's under the state's deregulation plan, is unlikely to arrive at all.</p>
        <p>''If consumer choice isn't dead, it's certainly in emergency care,'' said Fred Zalcman, executive director of the Pace Law School Energy Project, an advocacy group that works for renewable energy and conservation. ''In the current vein, it seems inevitable that the system will fail.''</p>
        <p>The reasons for that growing conviction are far-flung, and some might seem entirely unrelated to the question of self-determination. In December, for example, Con Ed said that because investors were not building new power plants in New York City, the company would offer a 10-year commitment to buy 500 megawatts of electricity if a builder would come. And last month, Gov. George E. Pataki said that in the next decade New York would sharply raise the mixture of renewable energy, from things like solar and wind generation, required in the state's power portfolio.</p>
        <p>Both steps are likely to nudge utilities toward more long-term energy-buying contracts, and that, economists say, implies a word that can chill the spine of any free-market swinger: commitment.</p>
        <p>Because more payments to buy electricity are locked in, utilities, the argument goes, will need more customers locked in on the other side to balance the risks. They will need to know that there will be takers for the energy they will be committed to buy.</p>
        <p>Other experts say the very failure of deregulation to separate utilities and consumers is beginning to create its own consequences. When free choice only seemed delayed, they say, problems like price volatility that can make monthly electricity prices surge on hot summer days could be explained away as evidence of a bumpy transition.</p>
        <p>But with every year that residential and small-business customers really have nowhere to turn -- and nothing to suggest anything different on the horizon -- a passing phase is coming to look like a permanent condition.</p>
        <p>And a permanent condition, some consumer advocates argue, creates an obligation by the state to wade back in to reregulate or otherwise modify the system to protect small customers from a relationship they cannot escape, in the same way that the police would shield a battered spouse.</p>
        <p>What completes the circle is that many of the very measures proposed to address the problems of stalled choice would also most likely make the bonds between utility and customer unalterably permanent.</p>
        <p>Putting a ceiling on utility bills, for example, might help some people in Con Ed's territory on hot summer days (some upstate utilities already have temporary caps), but artificially low rates would also probably mean that no one could ever compete for those customers. The utility would have them, till death do they part.</p>
        <p>''I think there's been a realization that we lost some of the good aspects of the old system, so let's try to bring them back so there's more certainty and reliability,'' said Anne Reynolds, the air and energy project director at Environmental Advocates, an Albany-based conservation group that favors tinkering to protect consumers and the environment. ''The challenge is what to bring back and how to mesh it with the new.''</p>
        <p>Retail consumer choice still remains the official goal of the state's electricity policy. A spokesman for the State Public Service Commission, which oversees the state's energy system, said more long-term contracts in a utility's portfolio were a natural and expected sign of a maturing market, and not a threat to choice at all.</p>
        <p>''We don't believe, nor do we expect, that supply contracts will inhibit the growth of the competitive market and consumer choice,'' said the commission's spokesman, Edward Collins.</p>
        <p>Con Ed's vice president for energy management, Terry Agriss, also said the company remained committed to consumer choice. Of Con Ed's 3.1 million customers in New York City and its northern suburbs, just over 5 percent -- almost all of them big companies with big electricity needs -- have chosen another vendor.</p>
        <p>But increasingly, the question is coming down to semantics and definitions: what does the word ''choice'' really mean? Consumer behavior experts say that in any open system, many people will choose not to choose. They will do nothing, no matter what. And so the real question, they say, is: how many are able to choose, or, on the other hand, are prevented from choosing by economic or other barriers?</p>
        <p>It is the sort of debate that can easily veer toward the philosophical outer limits. Some environmentalists, for example, advocate what might be called ''choice where there is no choice.''</p>
        <p>Customers, they say, should be able to request renewable, or ''green,'' power through their regular utility company, which would then be required to buy and insert that amount of power into its portfolio. The Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation, which serves upstate and western New York, has been offering just that sort of choice.</p>
        <p>But offering options like that, environmentalists admit, would also tacitly acknowledge that the partnership between utility and customer was permanent. It would be freedom, but only of a kind.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council, a Manhattan-based conservation group, has also argued that Con Ed should be required -- as it would have been under the regulated system -- to figure out whether its 500-megawatt proposal to buy energy is more or less cost-effective than an option to reduce demand by 500 megawatts through investments in energy conservation.</p>
        <p>But investing in energy conservation technologies, just like the company's proposed 10-year purchase plan, would also be a long-term commitment, the group's energy experts say. And so in many ways the implications for locked-in consumers would be the same, whatever the differences might be for the environment or air quality.</p>
        <p>''I think we should try to allow as much choice as we can,'' said David R. Wooley, a spokesman for the American Wind Energy Association, which advocates a green choice within the utility monopoly. ''Because we didn't have the meltdown that California did, we have the opportunity to make some midcourse corrections to take advantage of the positive things that have happened and avoid the risks that small customers currently face.''</p>
        <p>Others say the issue is not choice, but clout. If people cannot really get away, incentives should be created to give them more control of their fate through technology.</p>
        <p>Sophisticated meters and switches are available that can give buyers great discretion about when they use electricity, and that can save them a lot of money because electricity costs a lot less at night, for example, than during the peak daylight hours, when everyone wants it.</p>
        <p>''Competition has its place even if doesn't take a huge share of the market,'' said Lee S. Friedman, a professor of public policy at the University of California. ''If it continues to prod the utilities to continue to bring technology to the market in a good way, that's a positive.''</p>
        <p>If a utility modifies its behavior and improves its service to keep customers that it might lose, has choice failed, or succeeded? That's the question, Professor Friedman said, adding, ''If the system has gotten better, isn't that the goal?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
