<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Tired Blood' Warning: Ignore It at Your Peril</title>
    <meta content="23BROD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/23/health/23BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1521724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California (Los Angeles)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Archives of Internal Medicine</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nissenson, Allen R (Dr)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anemia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Institute on Aging</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D61E3AF930A1575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Tired Blood' Warning: Ignore It at Your Peril</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">`Tired Blood' Warning: Ignore It at Your Peril</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health column discusses common disorder of anemia, details those at risk and gives possible consequences of leaving condition untreated; Dr Allen R Nissenson, University of California (Los Angeles) nephrologist and medical professor, co-authors article in Archives of Internal Medicine that stresses need to take anemia seriously and actively test for condition; link between anemia and physical decline in elderly is debated; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thanks to advertisements for the once-popular tonic Geritol, most people of a certain age know about ''tired blood,'' a disorder more accurately called anemia, involving a shortage of healthy red blood cells to carry oxygen to body tissues and cleanse them of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>It is not really the blood of people with anemia that is ''tired.'' Rather, it is anemic people themselves who commonly experience chronic fatigue. Other symptoms may include weakness, shortness of breath, impaired athletic performance, rapid heartbeat, irritability, apathy, dizziness, pale skin, headache and numb or cold hands and feet. But in many people the symptoms are too mild to be recognized and the anemia goes undetected for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attention to anemia could add years to your life and improve all-around health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thanks to advertisements for the once-popular tonic Geritol, most people of a certain age know about ''tired blood,'' a disorder more accurately called anemia, involving a shortage of healthy red blood cells to carry oxygen to body tissues and cleanse them of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>It is not really the blood of people with anemia that is ''tired.'' Rather, it is anemic people themselves who commonly experience chronic fatigue. Other symptoms may include weakness, shortness of breath, impaired athletic performance, rapid heartbeat, irritability, apathy, dizziness, pale skin, headache and numb or cold hands and feet. But in many people the symptoms are too mild to be recognized and the anemia goes undetected for years.</p>
        <p>Anemia is this country's most common blood disorder. Statistics indicate that 3.4 million Americans are anemic, but experts say this is a gross underestimate. As Dr. Allen R. Nissenson and his co-authors said recently in The Archives of Internal Medicine, anemia has been viewed for far too long as an ''innocent bystander,'' considered almost normal in certain groups, like menstruating women and the elderly.</p>
        <p>On the contrary, Dr. Nissenson, a nephrologist and professor of medicine at the University of California at Los Angeles, said in an interview. A growing body of research indicates that anemia can seriously compromise the quality of a person's life, make sick people sicker and even speed deaths, he said.</p>
        <p>It is time to take anemia much more seriously, he added, making sure people have routine blood tests and are treated to restore healthy supplies of red blood cells. The testing is done either by a finger prick or by drawing blood from a vein. The finger test usually measures the hematocrit level, or percentage of red blood cells in plasma. A normal count is 36 to 46 percent for women and 46 to 56 percent for men.</p>
        <p>A more accurate assessment measures the oxygen-carrying hemoglobin in blood, expressed as grams of hemoglobin per deciliter of blood. A normal hemoglobin for women is 12 to 13 grams and for men, 13 to 14. Hemoglobin has traditionally been measured in blood from a vein, but a finger-prick test is now available.</p>
        <p>Many Are at Risk</p>
        <p>Inadequate nutrition is the most common cause of anemia, Dr. Nissenson said. Production of hemoglobin, the oxygen-carrying protein on red blood cells, depends upon the mineral nutrient iron, most prominent in meat and poultry (especially organs like liver and kidneys) and egg yolks.</p>
        <p>To a lesser degree, it is found in green leafy vegetables, dried fruits, dried beans and peas and enriched and whole grain cereals and bread. Foods rich in vitamin C help the body to absorb iron.</p>
        <p>Also important to the production of healthy red cells are B vitamins, folic acid, B12 and B6. B12 occurs only in animal foods -- especially meat, fish, eggs and milk. Dark green leafy vegetables are the best source of folic acid; whole grains are the best source of B6.</p>
        <p>These nutrients are often in short supply among women who lose iron in menstrual blood, pregnant women, strict vegetarians, overly zealous dieters and disadvantaged people. Increasingly, the problem is found among elderly people on restricted diets.</p>
        <p>Anemia afflicts virtually everyone with kidney disease because shrinking kidneys are not able to make enough of the hormone erythropoietin, which controls the production of red blood cells in the bone marrow. In addition, many chronic diseases involving inflammation can result in anemia, including congestive heart failure, inflammatory bowel disease, rheumatoid arthritis, AIDS, liver disease and cancer.</p>
        <p>There are also hereditary anemias like sickle cell and thalassemia, and hemolytic anemias that involve the destruction of red blood cells faster than they can be replaced. Immune disorders and medicines can also bring it on.</p>
        <p>Further, anemia can result from chronic blood loss -- from an ulcer, polyp or hemorrhoid -- that may not be apparent without a stool test.</p>
        <p>Doctors have long been aware of the risk of anemia in infants and in teenage girls and women of childbearing age, but anemia is far more prevalent in people over 65, recent studies say. One concluded that the incidence of anemia among the elderly was four to six times as great as had been suspected, affecting as many as a quarter of those over 75.</p>
        <p>Serious Consequences</p>
        <p>''Higher mortality rates are almost always observed in patients with anemia,'' Dr. Nissenson and colleagues wrote. Even among patients with nearly identical medical disorders, those who are anemic tend to die faster. In one study of Medicare patients with congestive heart failure, for example, for every 1 percent decrease in the hematocrit (or percentage of red blood cells in plasma), the mortality rate rose by 1.6 percent.</p>
        <p>In a study of nearly 79,000 elderly patients hospitalized with heart attacks, blood transfusions greatly lowered the death rate among those with hematocrits of less than 33 percent upon admission to the hospital.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nissenson and colleagues pointed out that advanced age and narrowed coronary arteries might render the hearts of the elderly less able to compensate for the effects of anemia in the event of a heart attack.</p>
        <p>Likewise with dialysis patients. In a study of 20,000 such patients with chronic kidney failure, those who were more severely anemic had a death rate twice that of patients less anemic. But when anemia in dialysis patients was treated effectively, the death rate after one year was no different from those who were not initially anemic.</p>
        <p>Cancer patients also seem to do better when they are not anemic. Chemotherapy and radiation often cause anemia, which is associated with a reduced ability to control the disease and a lower survival rate.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most common consequence of anemia is an impaired quality of life, especially among older, ostensibly healthy people. In a study supported by the National Institute on Aging published in August in The American Journal of Medicine, Dr. Brenda W. J. H. Penninx and co-authors followed a group of 1,146 men and women 71 and older for more than four years.</p>
        <p>The participants performed three tests at the start and end of the study: standing balance, a timed eight-foot walk and rising from a chair. Those with hemoglobin levels just slightly below normal were one and a half times as likely to experience physical declines as those with normal hemoglobin. Those with greater degrees of anemia experienced greater declines.</p>
        <p>''Although no study yet shows that treating anemia in older people reduces the incidence of physical decline, our study certainly suggests that this may be the case,'' Dr. Penninx said.</p>
        <p>Anemia treatment is mainly determined by the cause: correcting underlying disorders, changing diets, adding nutritional supplements and for many, a costly genetically engineered drug called erythropoietin, sold as Epogen for kidney patients, and Procrit for everyone else.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
