<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Kurds and Madrid</title>
    <meta content="22SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/22/opinion/22SAFI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1529148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Barzani, Massoud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DD1F3EF931A15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Kurds and Madrid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Of Kurds and Madrid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire Op-Ed column urging Iraqi Kurds not to look Turkish gift horse in the mouth; welcomes Turkey's offer to send well-trained troops to Iraq for one year, which would do much to Muslimize and localize war on Saddam Hussein's last-ditch fighters; says that and UN vote in support of US occupation set stage for Madrid donors' conference (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My old buddies the Kurds, a long-mistreated people we freed from Saddam, are now looking a gift horse in the mouth. I hope somebody explains that American expression about shortsighted suspicion to a key leader, Massoud Barzani.</p>
        <p>The U.S.-British coalition can use a fresh force of experienced troops to patrol Iraq's porous border with Syria and help us cause die-hard terrorists to die hard. Turkey's leaders, eager to re-establish warm relations with Washington and to take part in creating a nearby democratic trading partner, offered a division of well-trained troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harmony in the U.N. is on the rise, but the Iraqi Kurds may spoil it by looking a gift horse in the mouth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My old buddies the Kurds, a long-mistreated people we freed from Saddam, are now looking a gift horse in the mouth. I hope somebody explains that American expression about shortsighted suspicion to a key leader, Massoud Barzani.</p>
        <p>The U.S.-British coalition can use a fresh force of experienced troops to patrol Iraq's porous border with Syria and help us cause die-hard terrorists to die hard. Turkey's leaders, eager to re-establish warm relations with Washington and to take part in creating a nearby democratic trading partner, offered a division of well-trained troops.</p>
        <p>This would do much to Muslimize and localize the war on Saddam's last-ditch fighters. Turkey's generous offer -- duration, one year -- would send a message to the world: pitch in and help now, while Iraq is not yet able to police and rebuild itself.</p>
        <p>The overwhelming vote in Turkey's Parliament added momentum to the effort by the U.S. and Britain in the Security Council to get U.N. backing last week for continued firm coalition control of helping Iraqis build a democratic, free-enterprise government.</p>
        <p>That unanimous U.N. vote surprised doubters everywhere. Its genesis, I suspect, was at the Bush-Putin meeting two weeks ago in Camp David. Bush lavished fulsome praise on Russia's semi-dictator for his supposed vision of freedom and the rule of law; Vladimir Putin, after gladly joining Bush in sinking the Kyoto global warming treaty, agreed not only to vote our way in the U.N. but also to broker a compromise that would induce France and Germany not just to abstain, but to grudgingly support our occupation.</p>
        <p>Just as Turkey delivered on troops, so did Putin on votes. China, as usual, wanted to be part of the majority it could see forming. But France, meekly followed by Germany, wanted an immediate, sovereign provisional government in Iraq, stripping the U.S. of control. When we said no, Putin passed along words to save Jacques Chirac's face: that the interim administration we appointed would ''embody the sovereignty'' of Iraq ''without prejudice to its further evolution'' -- thereby kicking the can of our control well into next year.</p>
        <p>The bandwagon that started in Camp David and gained speed in Ankara rolled through Damascus. Rather than be isolated, Syria -- always nervous about the Turks and suddenly worried about the Israelis -- made our U.N. resolution unanimous.</p>
        <p>That set the stage for this week's Madrid donors' conference. With the French, Germans and Russians refusing to ante up a plug dinar, and with the E.U. offering peanuts, we've been low-balling estimates of aid. But I suspect it will get into the double-digits of billions, especially since contributors can steer contracts to their own nationals.</p>
        <p>But here come Iraqi Arabs, using the Kurdish leader Barzani as their wedge to evoke faded memories of the Ottoman Empire and to look the Turkish gift horse in the mouth.</p>
        <p>Neighbors stay out, say members of the Governing Council, showing premature independence to curry voters' favor. Understandably, Turkey's prime minister, Recep Tayyip Erdogan, responds: unless invited by Iraqis, Turks will not come.</p>
        <p>Our State Department's man in Baghdad, Paul Bremer, seems to be worried about appearing overbearing. He already erred in approving an oil-for-electricity swap with Syria, the main source of terror in the Sunni triangle, and may fail to see the puissance of a force of Turks on the Iraq-Syrian border. Bremer should tell recalcitrant Kurds that they are again being used as pawns in an Arab power play, and that they should welcome a guaranteed temporary Turkish presence in non-Kurdish areas of Iraq.</p>
        <p>Kurdish leaders reached by cellphone are well aware of the danger of letting their traditional suspicion of Turks poison their well with Americans.</p>
        <p>Says one, thinking short-term: ''Our pesh merga cannot police the Sunni triangle. If you could work out a way to transport and supply the Turks by ship, without passing through Kurdish lands. . . .'' Another, thinking ahead about an alliance with the superpower, goes to the heart of the matter: ''If it takes Turkish troops to save American lives, we Kurds should be for it.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: safire@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: safire@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
