<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="28DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDB133CF93BA15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lucent Settles With S.E.C., Ending Accounting Inquiry  Lucent Technologies said it had reached a preliminary agreement with the Securities and Exchange Commission to end an investigation into its accounting practices. Lucent said the agreement, which must be approved by the S.E.C. commissioners, would not require the company to pay a fine or restate any results.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. had been investigating Lucent for about two years after the company alerted the commission that it had discovered $679 million in revenue that might have been improperly recorded. [Page C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lucent Settles With S.E.C., Ending Accounting Inquiry  Lucent Technologies said it had reached a preliminary agreement with the Securities and Exchange Commission to end an investigation into its accounting practices. Lucent said the agreement, which must be approved by the S.E.C. commissioners, would not require the company to pay a fine or restate any results.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. had been investigating Lucent for about two years after the company alerted the commission that it had discovered $679 million in revenue that might have been improperly recorded. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>Goldman Reduces Research Staff  Goldman Sachs plans to pare its research staff, a sign that investment banks are taking further aim at their research departments. After a year of scandals, the business model for Wall Street research remains unclear. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Royal Ahold Moves to Limit Damage  Royal Ahold moved to control the damage from an accounting scandal by replacing the chief executive and board of its Argentine unit and dispatching a Dutch management team to keep an eye on the division. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft Settles Taiwan Complaint  Microsoft has settled an antitrust complaint filed by the Taiwan Fair Trade Commission, but the sides differ on how much the company has conceded. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Economic Data Point in 2 Directions  Sales of new homes plunged in January at the fastest pace in nine years, while orders for durable goods posted the biggest rise in six months, according to two reports. A third report said new claims for unemployment benefits rose to 417,000, a two-month high. [C3.]</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average closed up 78.01 points, at 7,884.99. The Nasdaq rose 20.28 points, to 1,323.96. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index rose 9.73 points, to 837.28. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Loss Widens for Swiss Company  ABB, the Swiss maker of machinery, reported a loss of $787 million for 2002. The loss widened from $691 million in 2001 and was steeper than forecasts. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Labor Criticizes Bush on Iraq  After backing past administrations during the Korean, Vietnam and Persian Gulf wars, the nation's labor movement has departed from tradition and criticized President Bush's approach to a conflict with Iraq. [A14.]</p>
        <p>German Law Aiding VW Is Under Fire  The European Union is preparing to take legal action to force Germany to repeal its ''VW law,'' which protects Volkswagen from being taken over and assures the German state of Lower Saxony a major voice in the company. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Keeping a Business in the Family  Public companies controlled by families exist in many countries, but they are a particular hallmark in Canada. At many public Canadian companies, the story is the same: an aging father passes the baton to a son or daughter. At Rogers Communications for example, Edward S. Rogers Jr., above, is widely expected to succeed his father, the company's founder. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Offering Raises Less Than Planned  Endurance Specialty Holdings, a reinsurer, raised $220.8 million, as much as 15 percent less than planned, in only the third initial public offering so far this year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Seeks a Cleaner Coal Plant  The Energy Department announced plans to build an experimental power plant within 10 years that runs on coal but emits no carbon dioxide, the heat-trapping greenhouse gas that makes existing coal plants major contributors to global warming. [A22.]</p>
        <p>Donaldson and MSNBC End Talks  Sam Donaldson, the ABC News correspondent, has ended negotiations with the cable news channel MSNBC about starting a nightly news broadcast. [C5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
