<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Sea Gates Don't Work, Call Canute</title>
    <meta content="Y26ITA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/26/international/europe/26ITAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1467945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Venice Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adriatic Sea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venice (Italy)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3D7173CF935A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Sea Gates Don't Work, Call Canute</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If Sea Gates Don't Work, Call Canute</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE, Feb. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italian officials are expected to give concrete approval for construction of sophisticated system of 79 sea gates along three openings where Adriatic Sea meets lagoon in which City of Venice is located; city is sinking on soggy foundations, weakened by industrialization, and experiences perennial flooding from high tides; grand plan, which would be executed over next eight years at cost of more than $3 billion, has already been delayed for 20 years; has run into opposition from environmentalists who say it would further pollute Adriatic and are pressing case in courts; persistent flooding has resulted in shrinking of city's permanent population, to about 70,000 from 150,000 half-century ago; maps; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>November was actually the cruelest month. For about two-thirds of it, the water that usually edges and lattices this improbably liquid city sloshed amok, turning Piazza San Marco into a gargantuan puddle and other low-lying areas into shin-high wading pools.</p>
        <p>January was bad, too. Right at the start, the lagoon rose, the canals swelled and Venetians slipped back into their galoshes, while tourists teetered atop makeshift boardwalks that had been set up to bridge the dry patches, too few and far between.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After decades of debate, the Italian government may finally agree to put sea gates at the entrances to Venice's lagoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>November was actually the cruelest month. For about two-thirds of it, the water that usually edges and lattices this improbably liquid city sloshed amok, turning Piazza San Marco into a gargantuan puddle and other low-lying areas into shin-high wading pools.</p>
        <p>January was bad, too. Right at the start, the lagoon rose, the canals swelled and Venetians slipped back into their galoshes, while tourists teetered atop makeshift boardwalks that had been set up to bridge the dry patches, too few and far between.</p>
        <p>''We've had it,'' said Adreano De Giulio, the manager of a restaurant here that posts, on the wall, an ever-lengthening list of each significant flood and the heights that the tides scaled. It goes back four decades and records more than 150 days of watery misery.</p>
        <p>''It's time to do something,'' Mr. De Giulio said.</p>
        <p>Now more than ever, that feeling seems to pervade this storied but endangered architectural wonderland. But this month provided a fresh illustration of how slowly and uncertainly Venice is paddling toward a solution.</p>
        <p>In government meetings in Rome, including one today, officials were expected to give concrete approval for the construction of a sophisticated system of 79 sea gates to be placed along three openings where the Adriatic meets the lagoon in which Venice is situated.</p>
        <p>On days of exceptionally high tides, the gates would rise from the sea floor and close those openings, controlling the water level around Venice.</p>
        <p>But that grand plan, which would be executed over the next eight years and could cost more than $3 billion, keeps bucking up against opposition, and the meeting today did not yield a steady green light.</p>
        <p>Officials were still wrestling with the profound concerns of environmentalists, who assert that the project would further dirty an already polluted lagoon and are pressing their case in courts.</p>
        <p>The project has already been delayed about 20 years, during which it was researched and researched again, refined and refined anew, and batted from one Italian government to the next.</p>
        <p>''At the end, one thing I can say is that this will be one of the most studied projects in the world,'' said Flavia Faccioli, an Italian architect who is supervising the project.</p>
        <p>''If this project isn't done, or if another project isn't done, the suffering will only increase,'' Ms. Faccioli said in an interview on Monday, adding that already ''Venice has changed in a frightening way.''</p>
        <p>Built on soggy foundations that were later weakened by industrialization, Venice has been sinking for a good long while. By some estimates, the land below the city settled by 5.1 inches over the last century, while the sea rose 4.3 inches.</p>
        <p>Doors and windows that were once well above the pavement are now flush against it, because entire alleyways and squares have been raised through the years in an attempt to keep the city afloat.</p>
        <p>The ground floors of many residential buildings have been abandoned and are now simply vestibules, pitted and corroded by the saltwater that laps into them during the increasingly frequent floods.</p>
        <p>The ratio of tourists to residents is higher, in part because so many Venetians have fled for dry land, diminishing the permanent population in the historic heart of the city from about 150,000 half a century ago to about 70,000 today.</p>
        <p>''What is at stake is the use of this city as an ordinary city,'' said Paolo Costa, the mayor, who has generally supported the sea gates project but has also called for more study of the environmental impact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Costa said that without the traffic of real life through the exotic maze of Venice, it would become infinitely less enchanting.</p>
        <p>''It would be like you were in Williamsburg,'' he said, referring to the American colonial village in Virginia.</p>
        <p>Some projections for this century show that the combined effect of the sinking of Venice and the rising of the sea, worsened by global warming, would cost Venice a further 8.6 inches.</p>
        <p>Other predictions put that measurement higher, and opponents of the project cite these in saying that the sea gates, intended to work for about 100 years, would be sufficient for only 30 to 50.</p>
        <p>They also say that the gates would eventually have to be raised 100 times a year, not the half-dozen times that the project's supporters suggest. According to critics, that would prevent an adequate exchange of water between the lagoon and the sea, changing the lagoon's ecosystem.</p>
        <p>''Looking long term, there's just no hope,'' said Dr. Albert Ammerman, a Colgate University archaeologist who has looked into the problem.</p>
        <p>''You're going to have to do something radical and different,'' Dr. Ammerman said, adding that the sea gates were ''a giant toy.''</p>
        <p>But with a paucity of alternatives, Venetians seem inclined to embrace the sea gates project. A recent poll of 1,500 residents showed that 67 percent support it.</p>
        <p>They are tired of treading water.</p>
        <p>''I've got the boots,'' said Matteo Toboga, who works in a bookshop here, referring to the kinds of adjustments that Venetians make. ''But the last time I used them, they weren't high enough, and the water got in my shoes.''</p>
        <p>Many store owners, who cannot move from street level, hustle to move and protect their wares at the first bleat of sirens that signal a coming flood. ''It takes me half an hour to dismantle the gallery and move the paintings,'' said one owner, Luciano Ravagnan.</p>
        <p>''This is not mineral water we're talking about,'' he said, referring to the pollution of the lagoon. ''It ruins everything.''</p>
        <p>He said he wanted to see the sea gates installed, and had only one concern and message for government officials. ''Please,'' he said, ''don't take another 20 years.''</p>
        <p>Venice Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
