<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking Sides in the Hudson Valley; Plant Raises Issues of Pollution and Economic Change</title>
    <meta content="27PLAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/27/nyregion/27PLAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1500213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Lawrence Cement Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Hudson Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson Valley (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D91E3BF934A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking Sides in the Hudson Valley; Plant Raises Issues of Pollution and Economic Change</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking Sides in the Hudson Valley</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>HUDSON, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Lawrence Cement Co proposal to build large coal-burning cement plant near Hudson, NY, divides community there; opponents cite concerns about air pollution and acid rain, while backers cite economic benefits; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A colorful chalkboard greets diners the instant they enter the Red Dot, a hip restaurant in this antiques magnet of a river city. The board does not feature daily specials but rather a cryptic exhortation: Stop S.L.C.</p>
        <p>After only a few hours in Columbia County, a visitor becomes fully aware of what S.L.C. stands for. St. Lawrence Cement wants to build one of the largest coal-burning cement plants in the United States a few minutes away from here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposed coal-burning cement plant has raised contention around the issues of pollution and economic change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A colorful chalkboard greets diners the instant they enter the Red Dot, a hip restaurant in this antiques magnet of a river city. The board does not feature daily specials but rather a cryptic exhortation: Stop S.L.C.</p>
        <p>After only a few hours in Columbia County, a visitor becomes fully aware of what S.L.C. stands for. St. Lawrence Cement wants to build one of the largest coal-burning cement plants in the United States a few minutes away from here.</p>
        <p>Sitting on an 1,800-acre tract that runs down to the Hudson River, the plant would announce itself with a 40-story smokestack visible for miles. Opponents say the billowing plume would release millions of pounds a year of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide, two compounds linked to acid rain and smog. The company concedes that the plume could, under certain weather conditions, be six miles long.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no other proposed project for the Hudson Valley has so unnerved and galvanized as many people in recent years as this plant. After a quarter century of change, antiques, art galleries and artisanal food production have overtaken heavy industry as the most visible economic activity along the river.</p>
        <p>Those drawn to the valley by that transformation, especially the many second-home owners who have arrived in recent years, have led the charge against the plant. Unlike most not-in-my-backyard crusades, this one is rippling far beyond the Hudson's backyard. Because the emissions would drift north and east, opposition has spread to nearby states. Officials in Connecticut and Maine have spoken out against the proposal.</p>
        <p>New York State, which will have final approval over the project, must wrestle with a tough decision: whether to approve the plant, and its attendant economic benefits, over the objections of Northeastern states it has joined in the battle against emissions from coal-fired plants in the South and Midwest.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of hypocritical to be complaining about the states upwind of New York while adding to the pollutant loads on states downwind of New York,'' said Karl S. Coplan, co-director of the Pace Environmental Litigation Clinic, a program of Pace Law School, which is representing one of the opposition groups.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the plant has its supporters, from union members who want the promised jobs to local officials eager for new tax revenue. In this city, which still has nooks of poverty, there are almost as many signs for the plant as against. The company's sign plays on the words ''plant'' and ''planet,'' urging support for both.</p>
        <p>St. Lawrence disputes claims that the plant will increase pollution. Because of improvements in technology, it says, the new plant will have sharply lower harmful emission than the plant it will replace across the river in Catskill.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the new plant say it will create a sprawling new industrial city, with noisy trucks on local roads and gargantuan barges on the river, dominating the life of Hudson and altering vistas in the valley for decades. They contend that overall emissions will actually rise.</p>
        <p>St. Lawrence bought the land, which includes a 1,200-acre limestone quarry, in the early 1970's. Limestone is the key component in making cement, which is sold by the barge, truck or bag.</p>
        <p>As a visitor leaves town and drives along country roads, there is the unmistakable feeling that Columbia County is in the sway of cement-plant fever. Everywhere are signs protesting the plant. Some 35 organizations have joined the fray, with teams of lawyers and air-quality experts going head to head with the company's own well-staffed defense.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to breathe it, and I don't want to see it,'' said Honey Wilde, who relocated from New Jersey to a house on 10 acres in the town of Ghent nine years ago. ''I have a direct view of the Catskill Mountains across the river, and on a clear day I can see the trees growing on the mountains. That plume is going to prevent me from seeing that.''</p>
        <p>For St. Lawrence Cement, a Canadian company, the opposition has been an enigma, said Daniel Odescalchi, the company's spokesman.</p>
        <p>The new plant would triple the cement output of the Catskill plant, while its smokestack would be four times the height of the old stack, he said. New technology will slash emissions like sulfur dioxide by 85 percent and lead and mercury by 95 percent, according to Mr. Odescalchi. There will, however, be an increase in carbon monoxide, he said.</p>
        <p>''I thought the environmentalists would really embrace this,'' Mr. Odescalchi said. ''This is a textbook example of the Clean Air Act. If you replace an existing facility, you lose the grandfathering of plant operations, and you have to abide by all the newest and more stringent regulations.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps more significant, Mr. Odescalchi said, is the fact that the state emissions permit for the new plant would cut by a third what is now permitted at the Catskill plant. ''That's huge,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists expect emissions to increase, arguing that the important comparison is what is now coming out of the aging Catskill plant (14 million pounds per year) and the potential at the new plant (19.6 million pounds). It is irrelevant that the permit for the existing plant would allow 29 million pounds of pollutants, insists Ned Sullivan, president of Scenic Hudson, an environmental group based in Poughkeepsie.</p>
        <p>''They obviously want to be able to use the full capacity or they wouldn't be seeking these high permit levels,'' said Mr. Sullivan, who was formerly the commissioner of Maine's Department of Environmental Protection.''</p>
        <p>The company says the new plant is most likely to maintain the level currently seen at the Catskill plant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sullivan and other environmental advocates criticize the track record of St. Lawrence's majority shareholder, Holcim (pronounced wholesome). In August, Texas fined a Holcim affiliate $223,000 for violations at its cement plant in Midlothian, including multiple releases of pollutants beyond allowable levels. Mr. Odescalchi said the permits St. Lawrence is seeking from New York contain ''more realistic'' emissions projections.</p>
        <p>St. Lawrence has already drawn up a ''host community agreement'' with the town of Greenport, just south of Hudson, where the bulk of the site is located. The agreement includes a payment of $200,000 a year, on top of the $800,000 the plant is expected to pay in property taxes. The company is now negotiating an agreement with the city of Hudson. A small part of its land crosses into Hudson, giving St. Lawrence its crucial river access.</p>
        <p>Another flashpoint is the plant's aesthetic effect, particularly the 406-foot smokestack. Both sides have created visual simulations, but the results are light years apart: the stack and plume in the company's photographic simulations register as blips on the horizon, while they look monstrous in the opposition's illustrations. St. Lawrence says the plume will be visible mostly in the winter months, and its meteorological studies indicate that it will reach six miles for perhaps a couple of hours a year.</p>
        <p>The issue of job creation is another hot button. Because cement production has become so efficient, the new plant will need only 15 more workers than the existing one. Workers in Catskill will be given first chance on positions at the new plant.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Odescalchi points to the 1,600 construction jobs that he said would be created, as well as an estimated 170 jobs that would be supported through the plant's purchase of printing supplies, lumber and tires.</p>
        <p>Art Stoerzinger, a Greenport resident whose company provides janitorial services to local companies, heads a group that supports the plant, the Hudson Valley Environmental Economic Coalition. With the help of union locals, the group has collected tens of thousands of signatures throughout the valley, he said. ''You can't build a $320 million plant without having a huge economic impact on the area,'' he said. ''Many of the opponents are here for quiet enjoyment of their weekend home, and they don't want the county to change at all. But there are those of us here who have to make a living.''</p>
        <p>The fate of the project is in the hands of the New York Department of Environmental Conservation. In a letter opposing the plant in the fall, the former governor of Maine, Angus S. King Jr., reminded Gov. George E. Pataki that the two states have worked ''collaboratively for years'' on the ''transport of ozone and other pollutants across state boundaries.'' The attorney general of Connecticut, Richard Blumenthal, has also invoked the partnership with New York in the legal battle against out-of-state plants.</p>
        <p>In the coming months, perhaps even years, administrative law judges at the state agency will make recommendations on several issues to the commissioner and final arbiter, Erin M. Crotty. Those issues range from noise levels to the effect of emissions on Olana, the nearby historic site that was home to the painter Frederic E. Church.</p>
        <p>Planned hearings might help clarify a debate that has so far unfolded as a confusing clash. ''I don't think either side has given all the facts, and I'm against it,'' Ms. Wilde said. ''You have to weed out what you believe to be the truth. It's going to be a long fight.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
