<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small Thoughts for a Global Grid</title>
    <meta content="02PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/02/science/02PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1516396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENTIST AT WORK/RICHARD SMALLEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nanotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rice University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carbon Nanotechnolgies (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smalley, Richard E (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nanotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Smalley, Richard E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DD1638F931A3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small Thoughts for a Global Grid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Small Thoughts for a Global Grid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Richard E Smalley, 1996 Nobel Prize Chemistry winner, Rice University professor and Carbon Naotechnologies company chairman, speaks to researchers, students, businesses and government officials about role of technology in addressing changing energy needs; looks at world's energy future in fifty years and stresses need for more people working in physical sciences and engineering; presents 2050 population estimates of between 8 and 10 billion people and importance of embracing energy policy that will meet projected need; is expected to return to his research on self-replicating batches of nanotubes which could, among other things, act as highly efficient, lightweight conductors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not as though Dr. Richard E. Smalley, a winner of the 1996 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for his role in discovering a new form of carbon, needed another obsession when he began pondering the world's energy future a year and a half ago.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley, a 60-year-old Rice University professor, is the closest thing to a celebrity in the world of materials science.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Richard E. Smalley says that success in finding new energy sources hinges not just on policy changes but on attracting more researchers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is not as though Dr. Richard E. Smalley, a winner of the 1996 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for his role in discovering a new form of carbon, needed another obsession when he began pondering the world's energy future a year and a half ago.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley, a 60-year-old Rice University professor, is the closest thing to a celebrity in the world of materials science.</p>
        <p>He was busy with research on carbon nanotubes, the astonishingly strong cylindrical molecules that researchers created as a follow-up to the work that earned him the Nobel. He was chairman of a company trying to commercialize the nanotubes. He had classes to teach and joint custody of a young son.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he was in constant demand as a speaker on nanotechnology, the rapidly growing field of research and business revolving around materials with dimensions measured in nanometers, or billionths of a meter.</p>
        <p>But as Dr. Smalley pursued the promise of the submicroscopic world, including its potential to create new materials for generating, transmitting and storing energy, he began to suspect he knew too little about the larger world he wanted to affect.</p>
        <p>So he set out to understand what the world's energy needs were likely to be in 2050 and the role of technology in addressing them.</p>
        <p>Initially pessimistic, Dr. Smalley has become increasingly hopeful about the effectiveness of conservation programs and the potential of new technologies based on hydrogen and renewable energy sources like wind and solar power.</p>
        <p>Now, as he speaks to researchers, students, businesses and government officials, Dr. Smalley tells them that success hinges not just on policy changes but on attracting more researchers to that field.</p>
        <p>''Without a major resurgence of U.S. citizens' entering the physical sciences and engineering, the solution to the energy challenge will be too slow in coming,'' Dr. Smalley said. ''And when it does finally come, the core technology may very well be Asian.''</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Smalley says he intends to focus more on his carbon nanotube research this fall, some energy experts who have seen him in action say any retreat to the lab will be a blow to the energy debate.</p>
        <p>''He's becoming too important a voice to put it down,'' said Matthew Simmons, a Houston investment banker who specializes in work for the oil industry.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley grew up in suburban Kansas City showing no inclination for serious study, or even regular school attendance, until he excelled in a high school chemistry course. He worked for four years as a research chemist for Shell Oil after graduating from the University of Michigan before obtaining a Ph.D. from Princeton for pioneering work developing high-speed laser systems to study the behavior of molecules. He moved to Rice in 1976.</p>
        <p>His challenge today is to stay at the leading edge of research on the novel carbon materials his laboratory discovered in 1985.</p>
        <p>The field he and his research colleagues pioneered has become one of the hottest in science because such carbon exhibits so many unusual electrical, thermal and optical properties, along with extraordinary strength.</p>
        <p>The original spherical molecules discovered in 1985, which he called buckyballs because they resembled the geodesic domes designed by Buckminster Fuller, led to the creation of a large family of carbon ''fullerenes,'' including the cylindrical molecules known as carbon nanotubes. Researchers are using them to pursue, among other things, new forms of drug delivery, low-cost computer memories, superstrong construction materials and clothing and energy devices like solar cells or fuel cells.</p>
        <p>Besides teaching at Rice and running his laboratory, Dr. Smalley is chairman of Carbon Nanotechnologies, a privately held company he helped found three years ago. Dr. Smalley attends most Monday morning staff meetings, is deeply involved in filing and protecting patents and occasionally delivers talks to the research groups of potential customers like the International Business Machines Corporation, according to Dr. Robert Gower, Carbon Nanotechnologies' chief executive.</p>
        <p>''He's like a rock star in technology circles,'' Dr. Gower said.</p>
        <p>That would be plenty, especially for a man who rues his limited role in bringing up Chad, his 34-year-old son from the first of his three marriages. Dr. Smalley, a trim survivor of a tough battle with cancer, is now single and sharing custody of his second son, Preston, 6. He says he is taking fatherhood much more seriously this time around.</p>
        <p>''Preston is the real Nobel Prize,'' said Dr. Smalley, recounting with a mixture of sheepishness and delight the circumstances of his son's birth nine months after the Nobel partying.</p>
        <p>When he takes the time to talk about energy policy, Dr. Smalley says meeting the needs of 2050 will require a commitment to new technology and forward-thinking policies like the one enunciated by President John F. Kennedy in his 1961 call to put an American on the moon.</p>
        <p>''If the current administration would embrace this, it would be political poetry, like Nixon going to China,'' Dr. Smalley said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley's approach so far has focused on creating support for his vision in the government agencies that deal with energy and among business and technical groups, largely steering clear of politicians. He lacks the taste for the public limelight exhibited by Nobel winners like Linus Pauling, an outspoken opponent of the Vietnam War and later a champion of vitamin C.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley delivers his standard speech with the careful pacing and calm of a scientific paper rather than the passion of a plea. He starts with population projections for 2050, which range from 8 billion to 10 billion people, up from 6.5 billion today.</p>
        <p>He then presents a list of challenges the world faces and the observation that the problems people put highest on the list in most polls -- including water, food and the environment -- can be dealt with only if the world has adequate clean energy supplies.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley then lays out the relative roles of major energy sources and the prevailing opinion that the largest by far, oil and gas, will be declining in production before 2050, and perhaps as soon as 2020.</p>
        <p>Next, he reviews the pluses and minuses of proposed alternatives, pausing to describe technologies that will have to develop further to play an important role.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley generally slips quickly over the environmental dimensions of competing technologies because the Bush administration has taken such a strong stand against factoring climate change into policy. ''I'm trying to hold one hand behind my back and not use the climate issue,'' Dr. Smalley said.</p>
        <p>Instead, he dwells on a point calculated to alarm Americans of every political stripe -- a graph showing that so few young Americans are becoming physicists and engineers that the nation is on its way toward becoming 90 percent dependent on Asia for new energy expertise.</p>
        <p>Dr. Smalley plans to press forward looking for opportunities to shape the energy debate for another six months or so. But the discussion about energy has gotten him increasingly excited about one area of his research, the challenge of creating self-replicating batches of nanotubes that consist entirely of single-walled cylinders, which are more uniform than multiwalled tubes and thus more likely to strongly exhibit the nanotubes' most interesting properties.</p>
        <p>Strings of identical nanotubes, called clones although they are not alive, could be woven into long wires that would be more efficient conductors than copper yet far lighter, Dr. Smalley said. Working on such wire, which could make it much cheaper to move solar and wind power to places it is needed, is a way of addressing energy needs in 2050.</p>
        <p>''Working on nanotubes is the most relevant thing I can do,'' Dr. Smalley said.</p>
        <p>SCIENTIST AT WORK/RICHARD SMALLEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
