<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weekender | Millbrook, N.Y.</title>
    <meta content="30WEEK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/30/realestate/luxury/30WEEK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1492768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Millbrook (Ny)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maguire, Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Weekender</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Dutchess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0DC1F31F933A05756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weekender | Millbrook, N.Y.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Millbrook, N.Y.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELLEN MAGUIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maguire, Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Millbrook, NY, as place to live and visit; photo; map; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Harvard dismissed Timothy Leary, the psychology professor turned psychedelic drug guru, in 1963, he dropped out, at the invitation of a wealthy benefactor, to Millbrook. This polished enclave of vast estates and hundred-acre horse farms set in the lush hills of the eastern Hudson River Valley became the unlikely home of Leary's Castalia Institute, where he conducted controversial experiments with LSD. (It is also where he was arrested by G. Gordon Liddy, then with the Dutchess County Sheriff's Department, in one of several brushes with the law.)</p>
        <p>The Castalia Institute no longer exists and these days Millbrook has a different kind of research center, the Institute of Ecosystem Studies, with a director, Gene Liken, who studies a different kind of acid: acid rain. Many weekend residents are patrons. ''It's an oasis,'' said Ronald S. Gross, a corporate lawyer with a Ph.D. in botany who has an apartment in Manhattan and a house in Millbrook. ''We listen to top scientists lecture on significant issues like Lyme disease.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This polished enclave of vast estates and hundred-acre horse farms became the unlikely home of Timothy Leary's Castalia Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Harvard dismissed Timothy Leary, the psychology professor turned psychedelic drug guru, in 1963, he dropped out, at the invitation of a wealthy benefactor, to Millbrook. This polished enclave of vast estates and hundred-acre horse farms set in the lush hills of the eastern Hudson River Valley became the unlikely home of Leary's Castalia Institute, where he conducted controversial experiments with LSD. (It is also where he was arrested by G. Gordon Liddy, then with the Dutchess County Sheriff's Department, in one of several brushes with the law.)</p>
        <p>The Castalia Institute no longer exists and these days Millbrook has a different kind of research center, the Institute of Ecosystem Studies, with a director, Gene Liken, who studies a different kind of acid: acid rain. Many weekend residents are patrons. ''It's an oasis,'' said Ronald S. Gross, a corporate lawyer with a Ph.D. in botany who has an apartment in Manhattan and a house in Millbrook. ''We listen to top scientists lecture on significant issues like Lyme disease.''</p>
        <p>Otherwise, Millbrook hasn't changed much. Greek Revival homes sheltered by mature oaks and sugar maples, rare breeds of cattle grazing the open fields and a 130-acre vineyard heighten the sense of centuries-old gentility. Weekend residents shoot pheasant and quail, perfect their fly-fishing casts and visit antiques shops.</p>
        <p>Luxury cars jockey for position outside Mabbettsville Market, an upscale grocery. Inside, women in riding boots and men in spotless barn jackets queue up for espresso. Pockets remain deep, and at least five philanthropic foundations operate in Millbrook.</p>
        <p>Some local residents, however, are struggling because of the weakened economy; the Northeast Dutchess Fund of the Berkshire Taconic Community Foundation was started in 2002 with $100,000 from a publicity-shy second-home owner to help residents who lack phones, plumbing, kitchens or health insurance.</p>
        <p>Residents of the village of Millbrook and the town of Washington, of which it is a part, have Millbrook mailing addresses, and most people refer to the entire area as Millbrook. ''It's a desirable address,'' Mayor Don Briggs said with a laugh. ''Sometimes we catch residents of other towns slipping over here to get a post office box.''</p>
        <p>The Scene</p>
        <p>Ric Ocasek of the Cars, Mary Tyler Moore and Liam Neeson all have houses in Millbrook, but they are among the newcomers. Residents, full time or part time, whose families have been in Millbrook for generations keep alive events like the Millbrook Hunt and the hunt ball. The Sandanona Hare Hounds is a group that sponsors weekly beagling: hounds chase the scent of cottontail rabbits and participants follow on foot. Every summer the Millbrook Horse Trials attract Olympics-caliber riders.</p>
        <p>Other residents socialize in less tradition-bound ways.</p>
        <p>Tim Smalls, an equity trader from Brooklyn Heights who bought a 19th-century colonial on 50 acres three years ago as his weekend home, takes his family to the July fishing derby at the town park and to free concerts at the town band shell. ''It's great,'' he said. ''The local plumber sits on a blanket drinking wine next to the C.E.O. of a Fortune 500 company.''</p>
        <p>Night life is minimal. ''There's no big scene,'' said Mish Tworkowski, a jewelry designer from Manhattan. ''That forces us to spend time at home with friends, which is a beautiful thing.'' Four years ago, he and his partner, Joseph Singer, an architect, bought a crumbling creamery and an adjacent barn, once part of a 19th-century estate, and combined them to create a 2,500-square-foot second home. ''There were trees growing in the foundation walls,'' Mr. Singer said. Now their great room has 14-foot ceilings and original tongue-and-groove panels.</p>
        <p>An informal soccer league draws many foreign nationals living in town. ''When the Argentinians play the Italians, it's fierce,'' said Elizabeth Baravalle, a store owner who moved to Millbrook from Milan in 1999.</p>
        <p>Residents are proud of the recently renovated Millbrook Free Library; the capital campaign raised $2.5 million in eight months. In June, the Merritt Bookstore, which supports more than 10 book clubs and writing groups, will hold an overnight student read-athon to raise money for American Indian children nationwide.</p>
        <p>Pros</p>
        <p>Urbanites yearning for touches of small-town life can find them in Millbrook.</p>
        <p>''We know everyone in every store by name,'' said Adelaide Camillo, an arts consultant for nonprofit groups and the wife of Mr. Gross, the corporate lawyer. The couple also catch up on local news during trips to the dump. ''England has its pubs; we have the transfer station,'' Ms. Camillo said.</p>
        <p>The village clerk, Karen McLaughlin, can send her sons, who are 10 and 13, out alone for ice cream without much worry. ''Once the local police officer called to report my boys had crossed the road from between parked cars instead of at the corner,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Gardeners abound. ''Knock over a geranium pot, and you're one of Millbrook's most wanted,'' said Ms. Baravalle.</p>
        <p>Many weekenders grow their own flowers and vegetables, and the Millbrook Farmers Market operates in the summer months. ''I hit the ground on Friday afternoon with flats in my hand and that's it for the weekend,'' said Edith Kean, a landscape designer from Manhattan who has owned a second home in Millbrook for 16 years.</p>
        <p>Many credit the Dutchess Land Conservancy with preserving open lands by acquiring conservation easements from local owners; under the easements, owners retain the land but relinquish development rights. The group has protected 4,600 acres in Washington this way, according to its executive director, Rebecca Thornton.</p>
        <p>Children like the Trevor Zoo, which has more than 120 animals, including week-old red wolf pups. It is part of the Millbrook School, a private preparatory school where William F. Buckley Jr. was once a student. Wing's Castle, a private home with seven towers, a moat and mountain views built by Peter and Toni Wing using salvaged materials, is the site of an annual Shakespearean day camp for children.</p>
        <p>There are several popular restaurants in the village. Slammin' Salmon offers lunch daily, along with prepared food; the Cloud 9 Café serves breakfast and lunch; Café les Baux, a new French bistro, is open for lunch and dinner.</p>
        <p>Cons</p>
        <p>Millbrook may attract captains of industry, but Mother Nature still runs the ship. Spring is mud season. ''We have wellies in the car and wellies by the front door,'' said Mr. Tworkowski. ''If you live in your Manolo Blahniks, this is not the place for you.''</p>
        <p>Fresh produce is hard to find during winter, and long driveways that provide privacy can be difficult to clear after a large snowfall. During storms, power failures are frequent; many residents have their own generators.</p>
        <p>While Lyme disease is prevalent in many parts of the Northeast, Dutchess County has one of the highest per capita rates in the country, and residents take every precaution during outdoor activities.</p>
        <p>An air of exclusivity extends to a number of private shooting and sports clubs that have complex membership requirements and waiting lists of up to five years.</p>
        <p>Real Estate Market</p>
        <p>Housing prices rose nearly 23 percent from the end of 2000 until June 2002, when they leveled off, according to Peter Devers of George T. Whalen Real Estate (845-677-5076; www.gtwhalen.com). ''The inventory in every price range is the lowest I've seen in my 22 years of selling real estate,'' Mr. Devers said. On the market in Millbrook and Washington this week were 39 single-family houses, five condominiums and town houses and seven parcels of undeveloped land.</p>
        <p>This week, Whalen Real Estate offered a 1,500-square-foot two-bedroom cottage on 1.76 acres with a pond for $595,000 and a new four-bedroom, 3,162-square-foot house on 22 acres for $1.14 million. Diane Toland of H. W. Guernsey Realtors (845-677-5311, www.hwguernsey.com) predicted that the market would heat up along with the weather. Listings at Guernsey this week included a 2,125-square-foot split-level house with four bedrooms and views of the Catskills for $299,500 and a former home of Franklin D. Roosevelt Jr., a 6,571-square-foot shingled house with 10 bedrooms and a stable, pool and pond for $3.3 million.</p>
        <p>LAY OF THE LAND  More Than Horses and Porsches</p>
        <p>POPULATION: 4,742.  SIZE: 64 square miles.  NUMBER OF HOMES: 1,595.  MEDIAN HOUSE PRICE: $395,000.  RECENT SALES: Within the last four months, a three-bedroom, one-bathroom, 1,515-square-foot ranch on nearly an acre sold for $220,500 after 227 days on the market; a three-bedroom, two-bathroom, 3,150-square-foot hilltop house with a pond sold for $885,000 after 51 days; a four-bedroom, three-and-a-half-bathroom colonial-style farmhouse on nine and a half acres sold for $910,000 after 172 days; and a five-bedroom, five-bathroom, 4,400-square-foot colonial on 15 back-country acres sold for $1.3 million after being offered for 143 days.  DISTANCE FROM NEW YORK: 90 miles.  TRAVEL TIME: In light traffic, 90 minutes from New York. The Metro North express train from Grand Central Station takes 90 minutes to get to nearby Poughkeepsie.  GETTING THERE: Take the Taconic State Parkway north to the exit for Route 44, Millbrook, and follow Route 44 east into town.  WHILE YOU'RE LOOKING: A Cat in Your Lap (62 Old Route 82, 845-677-3051) is a comfortable bed-and-breakfast with two spacious rooms in a renovated 1840's barn and a small room off the main house, priced at $85 to $125 a night. The four rooms in the Millbrook Country House (506 Sharon Turnpike, Route 44A, 845-677-9570) are furnished with Italian antiques. Rates are $150 to $250 per night and include breakfast and afternoon tea.</p>
        <p>HAVENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
