<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Struggle to Keep the Recycling Bin Full</title>
    <meta content="23LIRECY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1537773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hempstead (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winzelberg, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DA103BF930A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Struggle to Keep the Recycling Bin Full</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID WINZELBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winzelberg, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on sharp decline in recycling by Long Island residents; officials in Hempstead, where recycling rate rose from 25 percent in 2000 to 30 percent in 2002, credit education efforts; photos; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOSE colorful plastic bins on neighborhood curbs have become part of the local landscape and filling them part of the weekly routine. Long Islanders don't usually give much thought to recycling. And in the last few years, statistics show that many may be giving it even less thought, throwing out more trash while recycling less.</p>
        <p>Overall, Long Island towns report recycling rates much lower than the goal set by the state Department of Environmental Conservation, which is to recycle at least 42 percent of all solid waste. Many towns also report recycling less than the 29.7 percent of solid waste the federal Environmental Protection Agency said was recovered nationally in 2001. The Town of North Hempstead's recycling rate has dropped sharply in recent years, and rates in Oyster Bay, Huntington and Islip have also decreased.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOSE colorful plastic bins on neighborhood curbs have become part of the local landscape and filling them part of the weekly routine. Long Islanders don't usually give much thought to recycling. And in the last few years, statistics show that many may be giving it even less thought, throwing out more trash while recycling less.</p>
        <p>Overall, Long Island towns report recycling rates much lower than the goal set by the state Department of Environmental Conservation, which is to recycle at least 42 percent of all solid waste. Many towns also report recycling less than the 29.7 percent of solid waste the federal Environmental Protection Agency said was recovered nationally in 2001. The Town of North Hempstead's recycling rate has dropped sharply in recent years, and rates in Oyster Bay, Huntington and Islip have also decreased.</p>
        <p>The North Hempstead supervisor, May Newburger, was at a loss to explain the dropoff in her town's recycling rate, which plunged from 37 percent in 1999 to 20 percent in 2002. ''I really don't know why that is,'' she said. ''We regularly send out reminders and advertise recycling. I think we're doing everything we can.''</p>
        <p>But in Hempstead, where the recycling rate rose from 25 percent in 2000 to 30 percent last year, officials credited education efforts. Richard Ronan, the sanitation commissioner, said the town had been conducting surveys of town garbage routes to see which homes are not putting out the green plastic buckets at least once a month. Those who don't will receive new buckets, to remind them to participate in the town's recycling program. The town also runs television commercials to promote its hazardous waste disposal initiative.</p>
        <p>Maureen Wren, a D.E.C. spokeswoman, discounted the declining recycling rates reported by the Long Island towns and said that ''according to the information reported by municipalities and private firms to D.E.C., the amount of materials recycled statewide continues to be stable.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence Swanson, director of the Waste Reduction and Management Institute at Stony Brook University, said images of the infamous garbage barge and the unwanted New York City trash that floated on it have long faded from people's minds, making recycling seem less urgent. ''People are tired of it,'' he said. ''You need a crisis to keep people inspired.''</p>
        <p>Although there is no state mandate for towns to recycle at a certain rate, in the 1988 Solid Waste Management Act, the D.E.C. outlined goals for municipalities to recycle between 42 and 50 percent of their garbage by the year 2000. Some Long Island town officials think that was a stretch and complain that the state and federal governments are not doing enough to create markets for recycled materials. But Dr. Swanson put the onus on local government. ''The towns would like to see a continuing source for their recyclables, but sometimes they have to eat a little bit of the cost,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Residents who try to sneak tuna cans into their regular trash could be fined, but almost none are. And going after individuals who fail to recycle is not the answer anyway, according to Gordon Gibson of Huntington, executive director of Citizens for a Livable Environment and Recycling.</p>
        <p>''We are not what counts,'' he said. ''It is the organizations in the community that counts. Every government office should recycle every scrap of office paper, because once they get their house in order, the whole thing follows. They should account for trash the same way they account for money.''</p>
        <p>There are other reasons why recycling has slowed here. Markets for recycled products like paper and scrap metal have become saturated by the increase in supply from municipalities who have jumped on the recycling bandwagon in recent years. With the smaller demand for some recyclables, it costs towns more for disposal. This was the reason New York City suspended its plastic and glass recycling program last year. Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg said ending this type of recycling would save the city about $40 million.</p>
        <p>Of course, not recycling puts that much more trash into the waste stream. With most incinerators already burning as much as they can and local landfills closed, the garbage has to go somewhere. Much of New York City's trash goes to landfills in Virginia. Over a million tons of Long Island's trash is burned at the four waste-to-energy incinerators located in Babylon, East Garden City, Huntington and Islip.</p>
        <p>Officials of American Ref-Fuel, which operates the incinerator in East Garden City, have proposed a a similar incinerator on the site of the former Shoreham nuclear plant. But the Brookhaven supervisor, John Jay LaValle, has said he opposes the plan. Currently, Brookhaven trucks its garbage to the Nassau incinerator.</p>
        <p>Some recycling advocates contend that too much waste that could be used again is going up in smoke, posing a health risk.</p>
        <p>''Mass incinerators generate extensive pollution, and it's usually very dangerous pollution, fine particulates like zinc, arsenic cadmium and lead,'' Mr. Gibson said. ''Virtually everything put in a mass incinerator can be recycled.''</p>
        <p>Kent Burton, a senior vice president with Covanta Energy, a company that operates two incinerators on Long Island, dismissed the accusation that incinerators are big polluters. ''As the E.P.A. recently expressed, waste-to-energy plants throughout the country 'produce 2,800 megawatts of electricity with less environmental impact than almost any other sources of electricity,''' he said. He added that incinerators ''save land otherwise used for disposal, destroy dangerous pathogens that threaten public health, decrease groundwater degradation, reduce greenhouse gases, significantly reduce the release of hazardous air pollutants, eliminate the release of methane from trash and control litter, noise and odor associated with burying trash in the ground.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibson complained that his town's recycling rate has fallen over the last few years, from 37.6 percent in 1999 to 33.8 percent in 2002. Still, among the seven largest towns on the Island, also including Hempstead, North Hempstead, Oyster Bay, Babylon, Islip and Brookhaven, Huntington had the highest rate of solid waste recovery.</p>
        <p>Howard Zeis, a Huntington town employee, has been working in garbage for the last 19 years, most recently at the town's walk-in recycling center on New York Avenue, where residents can dispose of things like car batteries and motor oil. ''People think it's easier to toss it out than to do anything with it,'' Mr. Zeis said. ''We need to make people more aware and make it as easy as possible for people to do the right thing.''</p>
        <p>In the towns of Southampton, Southold and Shelter Island, residents are given a choice about what to do with their garbage; hire a private carter or dispose of it themselves at pay-as-you-throw waste and recycling centers. In Southampton, about half the residents use carters and half bring their trash and recyclables to the town's four centers, according to Judith McCleery, Southampton's recycling coordinator.</p>
        <p>''It's a free market system,'' Ms. McCleery said. ''They can get the best price from the carters. If they don't like those prices, they can do it themselves.''</p>
        <p>After a 25 percent bump in recyclables collected in 1995, the first year of the program, the town's recycling rate has remained about the same, Ms. McCleery said.</p>
        <p>Southampton also offers its residents a do-it-yourself composting device for about $40, to reduce yard waste, the single largest component in Long Island's recycled garbage. The Town of North Hempstead recovered nearly 24,000 tons of yard waste last year, more than double the amount of newspaper, bottles and cans combined. In 1994, the Town of East Hampton built an indoor composting plant to process its yard waste.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make any sense to landfill yard waste when you've got thousands of gardeners who can never get enough compost,'' said Peter Garnham, a former recycling information officer for the Town of East Hampton.</p>
        <p>But who needs old tires, leaky batteries or oil-soaked rags? These items are not as easily recycled as yard waste, and it costs money to collect, sort and transport them as well. ''We spend millions of dollars a year on solid waste management,'' said Phil Nolan, director of environmental waste for the Town of Huntington. ''We get about $370 per year from each property to pay for all this.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Swanson said that over the long term, recycling will have a positive effect by not depleting natural resources. But he said the idea that recycling can turn garbage into gold is unrealistic, given the costs of collection and the volatility of markets.</p>
        <p>''The economic argument for recycling has been very detrimental to the cause,'' Dr. Swanson said. ''I don't think it will ever be a money maker, but it might offset the cost of disposal.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McCleery agreed. ''Recycling is still a cost avoidance for us,'' she said. ''Even when the markets are down, we think it pays.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
