<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1504524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFD7163CF937A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-5</p>
        <p>Iraqi Council in Place; A New Holiday Is Declared  The first interim government of Iraq has been declared and its 25 members will begin meeting today to decide on a leadership structure. As its first act, the council abolished six national holidays that had been celebrated under Saddam Hussein's rule and created a new national day, April 9, the day Baghdad fell to allied forces.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-5</p>
        <p>Iraqi Council in Place; A New Holiday Is Declared  The first interim government of Iraq has been declared and its 25 members will begin meeting today to decide on a leadership structure. As its first act, the council abolished six national holidays that had been celebrated under Saddam Hussein's rule and created a new national day, April 9, the day Baghdad fell to allied forces.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld said the United States might need to send additional troops to Iraq to quell an increasingly well organized guerrilla resistance, and warned that more American soldiers would die in attacks this summer.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The United States has called for a fund-raising conference, which will be attended by dozens of nations, in an effort to return Iraq to economic self-sufficiency. But potential donor nations are uneasy about financing a military occupation, and there will have to be more involvement by other countries in deciding how money is raised and spent.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Arab Researcher Attacked  A mob attacked an eminent Palestinian political scientist as he prepared to announce that only a small minority of Palestinians would exercise a right of return to Israel, perhaps the deepest divide between the Israelis and Palestinians, as part of a peace agreement.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israel arrested a suspected Irish bombmaker who entered the country three weeks ago and traveled to the West Bank to train Palestinians in making explosives, an official said.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Norway vs. the Glass Ceiling  Norway's Parliament, despite opposition from business groups, is expected to pass legislation soon that would force the country's largest publicly traded companies to increase the share of women on their corporate boards to 40 percent by July 2005.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Rally for Democracy  Thousands of demonstrators appealed for democracy in Hong Kong, but the government responded by announcing that it would not accelerate its four-year plan to review possible constitutional changes. The statement is the first official response to a series of rallies.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-15</p>
        <p>Worst Market in Years Limits Jobs for Teenagers  Teenagers are facing the worst summer job market in years, with the percentage of those holding summer jobs at its lowest in 55 years and the unemployment rate at its highest in a decade. They are suffering a push-down effect of the bad economy: older workers are returning to the job market and the laid-off are settling for jobs they might once have thought beneath them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Muslim Group Draws Scrutiny  Tablighi Jamaat is one of the oldest and most conservative Islamic movements in the world, describing itself as nonpolitical and nonviolent. But since the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, it has increasingly attracted the interest of federal investigators, cropping up on the margins of at least four high-profile terrorism cases.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats Criticize Bush  Democratic presidential candidates offered a near-unified assault on President Bush's credibility in his handling of the Iraq war, signaling a shift in the political winds by aggressively invoking arguments most had shunned since the fall of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Teetering in Flood's Aftermath  During one long summer 10 years ago, floodwaters swamped Chelsea, Iowa, and hundreds of communities across the Midwest, killing 50 people and damaging 50,000 homes in nine states. Still, the flood itself, residents say, brought out everything people like about living in small places. But after the waters receded, so did some of that unity.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Slave's Descendants Gather  Nearly five years after DNA testing provided evidence that Thomas Jefferson, or a close relative, fathered at least one child with a young slave named Sally Hemings, about 150 of her family's descendants gathered for their first reunion on the grounds of Jefferson's hilltop plantation, Monticello.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>E.P.A. Raises Criticism  The Environmental Protection Agency has delayed or refused to do analysis on proposals that conflict with the president's air pollution agenda, critics say. Some agency employees say they have been told either not to analyze or not to release information about mercury, carbon dioxide and other pollutants, prompting inquiries and complaints from environmental groups, as well as Democrats and Republicans in Congress.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Despite the Poor Economy, More Money Heads South  Though economic strife persists, and even with new federal restrictions on sending money abroad, recent reports show that the amount of money sent last year to Latin America from the United States increased about 18 percent, to more than $32 billion. Experts say they do not expect the volume of these remittances to decrease anytime soon.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>French-Free Bastille Party  Although there were crepes for sale and oceans of café au lait to sip, a Bastille Day party on the Lower East Side brought out nary a French national.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>More Early-College Schools  New York City is getting two more ''early-college high schools'' this fall, part of a national wave of schools designed to help minority and low-income students complete high school and get a jump on college before they graduate. Both schools will be small, with no more than 500 students, and will emphasize science.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>For Armstrong, Hello Yellow  For the first time in this centennial Tour de France, Lance Armstrong pulled on the yellow jersey of the overall leader, but it was far from a total triumph. He did not dominate the L'Alpe d'Huez showpiece stage in the Alps as he has before and he could not prevent two rivals from gaining on him. Armstrong moved up from second place to the top spot. He has a lead of 40 seconds over the Spaniard Joseba Beloki.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Benny Carter  A composer, arranger, bandleader and soloist on a variety of instruments who was unmatched in the jazz world, he was 95.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Isabelle d'Orléans et Bragance  The Countess of Paris, who was married to a pretender to the throne of France, she was 93.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>OfficeMax Nearing Deal  Boise Cascade, the paper maker and office products distributor, is near a deal to acquire OfficeMax, the chain of office supply stores, for about $1.1 billion in cash and stock, executives close to the deal say.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Moguls' Annual Retreat  Decades of deals and consolidation have made the annual Sun Valley conference of media moguls more important to the industry than ever, bringing together the handful of giants that own the Hollywood studios, television networks, cable and satellite systems and radio stations.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>When Jenny Dumped Benny  As her manager, Benny Medina helped develop Jennifer Lopez from a backup singer to a household brand. But as Mr. Medina tried to tip-toe the Hollywood line between business manager and talent agent, he and Ms. Lopez both stumbled.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Harry Potter's Internet Pirates  Harry Potter devotees around the world seem to be embracing the prospect of reading the voluminous new book on the screen, in unauthorized e-book formats.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Wi-Fi Summit Aims for Success  A number of true believers in Wi-Fi, or high-speed wireless connections, were present at an annual conference that brings together technology, media and entertainment industry leaders, in the hope of propelling the technology into success.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Ground zero developments; eliminating options at Microsoft; European welfare farmers.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Crossword</p>
        <p>E2  Weather</p>
        <p>B8  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
