<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Familiar Ground, Kerry Labors to Win Over Voters</title>
    <meta content="Y22KER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/22/politics/campaigns/22KERR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1545203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, Howard (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Howard Dean</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D9133FF931A15751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Familiar Ground, Kerry Labors to Win Over Voters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Familiar Ground, Kerry Labors to Win Over Voters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>NASHUA, N.H., Dec. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry, campaigning for Democratic presidential nomination in New Hampshire, repeatedly cites his wide experience, implicitly contrasting self with Howard Dean; seems astonished that nomination may go to Dean, man that in his eyes has not paid his dues; trails Dean by wide margin despite his long exposure on Boston television stations heavily watched in southern NH; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A bone-rattling December wind was blowing when Senator John Kerry started talking to the cameras and the notebooks gathered around him on the street in front of his presidential campaign headquarters here. Wearing a leather bomber jacket bearing the shoulder patches of the units he served with in Vietnam, he made the case he nearly always makes.</p>
        <p>''I have the experience,'' Mr. Kerry said. ''I'm ready to lead America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is something almost plaintive about Senator John Kerry these days, as if he finds it inconceivable that he is having trouble winning over his fellow New Englanders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A bone-rattling December wind was blowing when Senator John Kerry started talking to the cameras and the notebooks gathered around him on the street in front of his presidential campaign headquarters here. Wearing a leather bomber jacket bearing the shoulder patches of the units he served with in Vietnam, he made the case he nearly always makes.</p>
        <p>''I have the experience,'' Mr. Kerry said. ''I'm ready to lead America.''</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, sitting on a high metal stool in a classroom at Hopkinton High School, he spelled it out more fully, telling the students seated in a horseshoe around him about the laws he had written: flood insurance laws, crucial environmental protection laws. ''I was in Rio, in Buenos Aires, in Kyoto, in The Hague,'' he said, fighting the good fight against global warming.</p>
        <p>The night before, at a chili feed at the Peterborough Historical Society's handsome old meeting room, the senator embarked on a similar recital. ''I led the fight on health care,'' Mr. Kerry said. ''I led the fight for early childhood education and for clean air.''</p>
        <p>What he meant, but never quite said, was that his rival Howard Dean, the former governor of Vermont, had written none of those laws, attended none of those conferences, led none of those fights. The closest Mr. Kerry came was when he asked his audience at Peterborough: ''Would you hire a contractor who had never built a house to build one for you?''</p>
        <p>There is something plaintive, something almost wistful about Mr. Kerry these days, as if he finds it inconceivable that he is having so much trouble convincing his fellow New Englanders that he and not Dr. Dean has the experience needed for the presidency. Like Hubert H. Humphrey in 1968, Mr. Kerry seems astonished that though he paid his dues, the nomination may go to a man who has not done so, at least in his eyes. He hopes that he will prevail in the end, against expectations, as Mr. Humphrey did.</p>
        <p>A Democrat elected lieutenant governor of Massachusetts in 1982, then to the Senate two years later, Mr. Kerry has been in the public eye for more than 20 years, and for that entire time his face has constantly been on Boston television stations, which are heavily watched here in populous southern New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Yet he is doing far worse in this state, where the primary is set for Jan. 27, than in Iowa, where caucuses are scheduled for Jan. 19, or so the polls say. One recent New Hampshire survey has him 25 percentage points behind Dr. Dean, another has him 29 points back and a third has him 30 points down.</p>
        <p>The potentially good news for the Kerry camp has been a suggestion that Dr. Dean is starting to turn off some voters. Mr. Kerry feels obliged to assure those listening to him that he is in the contest to stay.</p>
        <p>''I am a fighter,'' he said repeatedly. ''I've been behind before. This race is by no means over. As the last weeks close, people begin to focus. Who can be elected? Who can beat George Bush?''</p>
        <p>Trying to demonstrate that he means what he says, and to finance a forthcoming advertising push, the senator borrowed $850,000 to lend his campaign on Thursday, and began seeking another loan, using his house on Beacon Hill in Boston as collateral.</p>
        <p>His strategists hope that he can do well enough in Iowa to raise his chances here -- a kind of ''slingshot effect,'' as Mary Beth Cahill, who took over a month ago as his campaign manager, likes to call it.</p>
        <p>There is ample political precedent. In 1984, for example, Gary Hart unexpectedly finished ahead of John Glenn in Iowa, at a time when he trailed Walter F. Mondale in the New Hampshire polls. Mr. Hart got a bounce of at least five or six percentage points and went on to win in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry's aides envision his finishing no worse than second in Iowa, ahead of either Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri or Dr. Dean, besting Dr. Dean here and going on to win the nomination. Of course, Mr. Mondale, not Mr. Hart, won the nomination in 1984, as did another vice president, Al Gore, in 2000, though his opponent, Bill Bradley, trimmed a 29-point margin in Iowa to 5 points in New Hampshire. And momentum is a fickle, sometime thing.</p>
        <p>Hoping to improve his chances in Iowa and thus New Hampshire, his aides say Mr. Kerry plans to spend most of the time up to caucus day in Iowa, devoting 11 to 15 days to the state, with no more than 7 here and almost no time at all in the states that vote on Feb. 3.</p>
        <p>Starting on Monday, Mr. Kerry will spend 24 consecutive hours on his bus, the Real Deal Express, crisscrossing Iowa to symbolize his commitment to that state, where voters have traditionally rewarded close attention.</p>
        <p>''Things seem to be moving in our direction there,'' said a top strategist, noting that Mr. Kerry, though in third place in the latest Iowa Poll, is 12 points behind Mr. Gephardt there and just 5 behind Dr. Dean. ''The question is, can we get them moving in our direction in New Hampshire as well?''</p>
        <p>Two days on the road with Mr. Kerry left unanswered the question of why his campaign here has not taken off. He and others blame what they see as negative coverage by The Boston Globe, as well as early organizational troubles. But the candidate himself clearly bears some of the responsibility. At Hopkinton High School, he found it hard to connect with his youthful audience, the kind of group Dr. Dean charms.</p>
        <p>Tall, lean, with a deeply lined face and expressive eyebrows, Mr. Kerry looks the part of a nominee, but often talks too long, running on for more than 23 minutes in some deliveries of his standard speech, and he finds it hard to generate electricity in a room.</p>
        <p>''It's not that he's wooden,'' said former Gov. Jeanne Shaheen of New Hampshire, an important supporter who visited Main Street shops with him in Nashua. ''He's no Al Gore. He connects well one on one, and he has humor. I don't know.''</p>
        <p>Though he told a reporter that he thought character, not issues, wins nominations and elections, Mr. Kerry clearly thinks he has several issues that can help him catch up with Dr. Dean and other Democratic rivals.</p>
        <p>At the chili feed in Peterborough and another in Keene on Thursday, he was roundly applauded when he took issue with Dr. Dean's assertion that the capture of Saddam Hussein ''did not make America safer.''</p>
        <p>Every person in the room, he said, ''would agree that the world is safer'' because of the capture.</p>
        <p>At the last stop of the day in Keene, where he arrived almost an hour late because of foggy roads, he demanded of Dr. Dean, ''How can you possibly say that America is not safer?''</p>
        <p>If Dr. Dean is nominated, he asked, ''what quote do you think you're going to see in the ads the Republicans will put on next summer?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry clearly considers Dr. Dean's comment a major gaffe that cast him as a naïve and inexperienced player in the world of foreign policy, not unlike George Romney's remark in the 1968 campaign that he had been brainwashed into supporting the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dean's pledge to entirely roll back the Bush administration's tax cut, Mr. Kerry said, showed a similar naïveté about domestic policy. That would be too hard on the middle class, Mr. Kerry argued, would reinstate an unfair marriage penalty and would do away with the 10 percent bracket. He advocated a selective rollback instead. But discussions of tax policy and Medicare reform, by their nature dry and arcane, lit no bonfires here.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
