<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1492608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EED61E31F93AA15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11, 14</p>
        <p>Troops to Stay in Iraq Until Security Improves  Allied officials said the vast majority of about 160,000 American and British troops in Iraq were likely to stay until security improved and other foreign nations eased the burden by contributing troops.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11, 14</p>
        <p>Troops to Stay in Iraq Until Security Improves  Allied officials said the vast majority of about 160,000 American and British troops in Iraq were likely to stay until security improved and other foreign nations eased the burden by contributing troops.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Bush administration made public its assessment that two mysterious Iraqi trailers were mobile units to produce deadly germs and the strongest evidence yet that Saddam Hussein had been hiding a biological warfare program.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Water Scarcity in South Africa  South African municipalities have begun working to turn inefficient water utilities into profitable operations that could attract private investment, but many poor communities still do not have access to reliable water services, or cannot afford them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.N. to Send Troops to Congo  The United Nations Security Council is expected to vote on a French proposal to send a multinational force to prevent further massacres in the northeastern Congo, and to provide medicine and other aid.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Strict Britain Asylum Laws  Britain, which receives more asylum applications than any other industrialized country, has grown less and less tolerant of new arrivals. Its government has enacted a series of laws that make it harder to enter the country and to win asylum.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Emergency Declared in Peru  President Alejandro Toledo declared a national state of emergency to control spreading protests in Peru, where thousands of travelers have been stranded as farmers try to stop farm produce from getting to Lima and other cities.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Bush to Visit Poland  President Bush's scheduled visit to Poland signals that the country has become an important ally, even a special friend -- to be distinguished from obstructionist allies in ''old Europe,'' notably France and Germany.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>Late Change in Tax Cut Bill Cuts Low-Wage Families  A last-minute revision by House and Senate leaders in the tax bill that President Bush signed will prevent millions of minimum-wage families from getting the increased child credit that is in the measure, Congressional officials and outside groups said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Bush signed into law the third tax cut in three years, dismissing criticism of the legislation's cost, fairness and effectiveness.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Reassessing Nuclear Weapons  The Bush administration, backed by Congressional sentiment favoring a new approach to nuclear weapons, is taking steps that could open the door to the development of new nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Wildlife Service Seeks Funding  The United States Fish and Wildlife Service says it will temporarily stop designating tracts of land as critical habitats under the Endangered Species Act within a matter of weeks because the program has depleted its money for this fiscal year.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Drug Kingpin Is Convicted  A federal jury in Miami convicted a Colombian drug kingpin of two counts of conspiracy for selling as much as 30 tons of cocaine a month in the United States in the late 1990s.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Video Games Improve Eye Skills  Researchers are reporting that first-person-shooter video games, the kind that require players to kill or maim enemies or monsters that pop out of nowhere, sharply improve visual attention skills.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NASA Faults Safety Inspections  Confidential interviews with shuttle workers at NASA and its contractors found no one who believed that preflight safety inspections were adequate, a member the board investigating Columbia's loss said.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Police Arrest Woman In String of Robberies  The F.B.I. arrested a 43-year-old woman accused of robbing a half-dozen banks last week in some of New York's most affluent suburbs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>State May Oversee Buffalo  The City of Buffalo is faced with having to turn over its financial operations to a state board that would oversee nearly all city spending. The city has teetered on the brink of bankruptcy for years.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Tourist Line Goes to Brooklyn  Gray Line New York Sightseeing has added a route that runs from Lower Manhattan to Downtown Brooklyn and into Prospect Heights.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Umpires Fault Monitoring  Baseball umpires said the QuesTec system, used to monitor umpires' calls of balls and strikes, forces them to adjust their strike zones from park to park.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>New Twists for Digital Music  Hackers learned how to download music using an Apple iTunes feature called Rendezvous. Last Tuesday Apple sent out an update for its iTunes software, disabling Rendezvous and limiting music access.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>Two record labels began to release discs in early April that include unprotected MP3 files along with conventional CD audio tracks.</p>
        <p>G7</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Willard Goldsmith Rouse III  A scion of a family of builders who built his own niche in the skyline of Philadelphia, he was 60.</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Moving to Limit Credit Checks  Legislators are proposing limits on the ability of credit card companies to check anyone's credit history daily and reset his interest rate based on the size of his other debts.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cross-Atlantic Crop Battle  Disagreement between European leaders and the Bush administration over genetically altered crops will be played out at a meeting of the leading industrial countries.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Investors Target Green Issues  Shareholders, spurred on by environmental and religious groups, have filed global warming resolutions with more than two dozen industrial companies this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Postwar Shopping Picks Up  Two surveys of retail sales at chain stores indicate that consumer spending is picking up, reducing the chances that the Federal Reserve will lower interest rates next month.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Updating media constraints; two deaths and no excuses; honesty about Amtrak.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E11  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>B11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
