<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Plot Tactics to Outmaneuver Cystic Fibrosis Gene</title>
    <meta content="14BROD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/14/health/genetics/14BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1456332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cystic Fibrosis</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cystic Fibrosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cystic Fibrosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DA1531F937A25752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Plot Tactics to Outmaneuver Cystic Fibrosis Gene</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Scientists Plot Tactics to Outmaneuver Cystic Fibrosis Gene</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody column on efforts to fight cystic fibrosis, disease that afflicts about 30,000 Americans; notes cystic fibrosis, result of defective protein, is chronic, progressive and ultimately fatal disease that clogs lungs and pancrease with thick, sticky mucus; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 10 million people in this country carry in all their cells one copy of a defective gene that regulates the movement of sodium, chloride and water in and out of cells.</p>
        <p>These people are, on the surface, perfectly healthy. But when two such carriers of this defective gene have children, they have a 25 percent chance that each child will inherit an abnormal gene from each parent and will be born with cystic fibrosis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>About 30,000 people in the United States have cystic fibrosis, the most common life-shortening genetic disease among Caucasians worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 10 million people in this country carry in all their cells one copy of a defective gene that regulates the movement of sodium, chloride and water in and out of cells.</p>
        <p>These people are, on the surface, perfectly healthy. But when two such carriers of this defective gene have children, they have a 25 percent chance that each child will inherit an abnormal gene from each parent and will be born with cystic fibrosis.</p>
        <p>The result of a defective protein, cystic fibrosis is a chronic, progressive and ultimately fatal disease that clogs the lungs and pancreas with thick, sticky mucus.</p>
        <p>About 30,000 people in the United States have cystic fibrosis, the most common life-shortening genetic disease among Caucasians worldwide. It occurs in 1 in 3,300 live births among whites, with a lower incidence in other groups. The incidence is highest, 1 in 2,500 births, among descendants of Northern European whites and Ashkenazi Jews.</p>
        <p>How has such a lethal gene survived the throes of evolution? Just as carriers of the sickle cell gene have a survival advantage because their abnormal gene offers some protection against malaria, some scientists believe that carriers of the cystic fibrosis gene were better able to survive the often fatal diarrhea caused by cholera.</p>
        <p>At least 800 different defects, or mutations, are known to occur in this critical gene, which causes a cell to create a protein called the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator, or C.F.T.R. Different mutations cause different disruptions of the regulator's role, and, as a result, different degrees of severity of cystic fibrosis.</p>
        <p>The most common mutations disrupt the movement of C.F.T.R. from its point of origin to its site of operation and cause a severe and ultimately fatal disease.</p>
        <p>Life-Lengthening Progress</p>
        <p>As recently as 25 years ago, most children born with cystic fibrosis died in early childhood and few survived to their teenage years. Today, most can expect to live past 30. Many finish high school and college, get jobs and have families.</p>
        <p>The difference stems from productive research, the results of persistent fund-raising efforts and pressure from parents, who established the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation in 1955.</p>
        <p>The research led to an understanding of the way cystic fibrosis causes life-threatening damage through a chain of events that involves damaged genes, abnormal tissues and malfunctioning organs.</p>
        <p>This understanding, in turn, has led to the development of preventive techniques and treatments that can attack every stage of the disease process. New treatments now in development promise even further gains.</p>
        <p>Some experts predict that within a decade, the lung damage from cystic fibrosis will be limited by periodic gene therapy in children and young adults.</p>
        <p>Better yet, some say, will be the application of techniques already technically feasible to correct the defect genetically even before a child is born, or soon enough afterward to prevent tissue damage. Only then might researchers begin to talk cautiously of cure.</p>
        <p>A Host of Therapies</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, a host of therapies to forestall complications have become the focus of survival for patients with cystic fibrosis.</p>
        <p>Respiratory physical therapy done two or more times a day to loosen the thickened mucus, enabling it to be coughed up, is essential to maintaining the ability of the lungs to transfer oxygen and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>In years past, clapping on the chest, back and sides was the only method. Now the job can be done by inhaled nebulizers, vibration vests and a flutter device that is blown into, freeing a patient from daily dependence on a lay or professional therapist.</p>
        <p>Because the thickened mucus is a breeding ground for bacteria, antibiotics are another critical factor in maintaining pulmonary health. With mucus coating the small airways in the lungs, the hair cells are unable to clear out invading bacteria.</p>
        <p>The trick has been staying ahead of the ability of micro-organisms to develop resistance by continually finding new antibiotics to which they are still susceptible. The potentially deadly infections mean frequent hospitalizations for many cystic fibrosis patients. Some have a central line implanted to aid in the frequent administration of antibiotics.</p>
        <p>Malnutrition is a constant risk because ducts clogged by mucus are unable to move digestive enzymes to sites where food is broken down and absorbed.</p>
        <p>Thus, enzyme-packed pills to aid digestion and fat-soluble vitamin supplements (A, D, E and K) are other daily requirements for maintaining the health of people with the disease.</p>
        <p>Another problem is consuming enough calories to compensate for the effort expended in breathing with congested lungs.</p>
        <p>Dehydration is yet another risk because the defective gene causes an abnormal absorption of sodium, dehydrating the lungs and making them more susceptible to infection. So people with cystic fibrosis have to be even more devoted to water bottles than aerobics instructors.</p>
        <p>Experts on cystic fibrosis emphasize two other important factors in coping with the illness: building and maintaining physical stamina and obtaining psychological support for patients and their families.</p>
        <p>The stronger people are, physically and emotionally, the better able they are to handle the complications and treatments for the disease.</p>
        <p>But eventually, despite the best therapy available, the lungs of people with cystic fibrosis become too damaged to sustain life. When that critical time appears on the horizon, a growing number of patients seek a double-lung transplant, an operation as risky as a heart transplant.</p>
        <p>Both lungs are needed to prevent the transplanted one from becoming diseased.</p>
        <p>When kidneys fail, dialysis can substitute for kidney function, but nothing similar exists for the lungs.</p>
        <p>There is no telling when lung failure will occur, necessitating a transplant. For some, like Stefanie Allen, it happened at age 11. For Charlie Tolchin, it was 28. For Michael Maggio, it was 40.</p>
        <p>About 3,700 patients are on a lung transplant waiting list nationwide. But each year only about 1,000 receive transplants. The problem stems from an acute shortage of viable organs and a limited number of medical centers with staff members skilled at the procedure.</p>
        <p>The lungs have to be big enough to sustain the recipients. For some patients who are small, it is possible to use part of the lungs from two live donors, usually relatives.</p>
        <p>The operation is expensive and risky: 5 percent of patients do not survive it. Three years after a transplant, 62 percent of the patients are still alive. The main problem is chronic rejection, which can occur despite the constant use of complication-prone immune-suppressive drugs. One complication is the development of lymphoma, a cancer of the lymph system that can be fatal, as it was for Mr. Maggio at 49.</p>
        <p>Those seeking more information or referrals to cystic fibrosis care centers throughout the country can contact the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation at 6931 Arlington Road, Bethesda, Md. 20814, by phone at (301) 951-4422 or (800) 344-4823, or check the foundation's Web site, www.cff.org.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
