<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; While America Sells Security, China Is Buying Its Dollars</title>
    <meta content="07SANG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/07/weekinreview/07SANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1541150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Balance of Payments and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wen Jiabao (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D9123DF934A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; While America Sells Security, China Is Buying Its Dollars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">While America Sells Security, China Is Buying Its Dollars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Visit to US by new Chinese leader Wen Jiabao comes at time when Wen is overseeing China's financing of big portion of US budget deficit, buying American government debt on scale once reserved for Japan; China's trade surplus with US will likely reach $120 billion this year, and globalization, word avoided by Bush administration, has diluted US economic influence to point that US Treasury is no longer central player in foreign policy that it was during Clinton administration; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last time a Chinese prime minister came to the United States, four and a half years ago, Washington was consumed by the globalization debates of the 1990's. The Treasury Department was largely in charge of China policy, and the question was not only how to get China to open its markets but also how to use market forces to speed democratization.</p>
        <p>But there is little such talk before the arrival this week of China's new premier, Wen Jiabao. If anyone is holding economic levers this time, it is Mr. Wen, who is overseeing China's financing of a big portion of the American budget deficit by buying American government debt on a scale once reserved for the Japanese. He can afford to: China's trade surplus with the United States is likely to hit $120 billion this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is no wonder that in addition to lending their billions to the United States Treasury, the Chinese are suddenly buying big-ticket American goods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last time a Chinese prime minister came to the United States, four and a half years ago, Washington was consumed by the globalization debates of the 1990's. The Treasury Department was largely in charge of China policy, and the question was not only how to get China to open its markets but also how to use market forces to speed democratization.</p>
        <p>But there is little such talk before the arrival this week of China's new premier, Wen Jiabao. If anyone is holding economic levers this time, it is Mr. Wen, who is overseeing China's financing of a big portion of the American budget deficit by buying American government debt on a scale once reserved for the Japanese. He can afford to: China's trade surplus with the United States is likely to hit $120 billion this year.</p>
        <p>Indeed, globalization is a word that rarely, if ever, shows up in presidential speeches. ''It makes him uncomfortable,'' a senior presidential aide who deals regularly with Mr. Bush on economic matters said the other day. As the aide spoke, Mr. Bush was being forced by the World Trade Organization -- under threat of $2.3 billion in retaliatory sanctions -- to lift tariffs he had put on imported steel 21 months ago.</p>
        <p>''This is a group that thinks what went wrong in the 90's is that we forgot to put American interests first,'' the aide said of the White House. ''So globalization sounds like the creation of a lot of rules that may restrict the president's choice, that dilute American influence.''</p>
        <p>The result of those suspicions is evident. The United States Treasury is no longer the central player in foreign policy that it was in the Clinton years. Its officials are still dispatched to cut off terrorists' money, to create a new currency for Iraq or to negotiate with the Chinese about letting the value of their currency rise, a development that would slow the growth of the American trade deficit. Foreign leaders say they no longer feel a need to stop by the Treasury building. Officials say Mr. Wen will visit only the White House and State Department.</p>
        <p>Even when the White House tries to pull the levers of economic diplomacy, 90's style, the effort sometimes seems half-hearted. After the war in Afghanistan, there was talk of making it far easier for Pakistan to export textiles to the United States, in hopes of weakening the appeal of Islamic extremists by creating jobs linked to America. But the United States textile lobby warned of a loss of American jobs, and the White House went silent about the idea.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Bush has revived the notion of using trade and development as an incentive to democratize the Middle East, but without specifics. The talk echoes a Clinton-era initiative directed at Israel and the Palestinians that never had much effect on the peace efforts.</p>
        <p>''It was one thing to use these tools in Asia, where the factories are humming, there was something to sell,'' said Michael Mandelbaum, a foreign affairs scholar at Johns Hopkins. ''But when you switch to promoting democracy in the Arab world, you discover that countries that still can't make a light bulb are not exactly ready to jump into the international economy.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush visited Asia in October, he spoke at every stop about the need to fight terrorism, but went through an entire economic summit in Bangkok with only a vague discussion of investment and new trading arrangements -- subjects that other nations wanted to take up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides argue that if the president's predecessors had spent more time worrying about threats like Al Qaeda and less time negotiating muddy agreements on global warming and a new international financial system, the world would be a lot safer. President Bush ''needed to focus on the most critical issues of American security first,'' Condoleezza Rice, his national security adviser, said recently. Now, she says, it is time to pursue broader goals of democracy, including in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Clinton's former aides say Mr. Bush has hurt his prospects for success not only by acting without broad international support in Iraq, but also by passing up opportunities to use economic and trade incentives to bolster American goals. ''What's missing is a coherent economic plan to back up their talk about promoting democracy,'' said Charlene Barshefsky, who was Mr. Clinton's trade representative. The administration came to office talking about a new relationship with Latin America built on trade, but that effort has faltered since Sept. 11. The administration was highly critical of how its predecessor let global trade talks spin out of control in Seattle in 1999, and then found itself, at Cancún this year, stymied by the same mix of intransigence on agricultural issues and resentment over American power.</p>
        <p>Making sure the mix of economic and security policies is right is the responsibility of Ms. Rice's National Security Council and the National Economic Council, which does not weigh in on as many international issues as it once did.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's first encounter with a major globalization issue came when he declared the Kyoto protocol on global warming dead, but promised an alternative that would include all developing countries, including China. He has not yet produced one.</p>
        <p>Similarly, economic issues with China were a low priority for a long while, says Bates Gill, a China expert at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington. ''The pocketbook issues of trade and job losses are now bigger in the manufacturing centers of the country than the administration thinks,'' he said, ''and China is often blamed, whether that is right or wrong.'' Waking up to that, Mr. Bush put limits on Chinese textiles imported here, and tariffs on low-cost Chinese-made televisions.</p>
        <p>So it is no wonder that in addition to lending their billions to the United States Treasury, the Chinese are suddenly buying big-ticket American goods, including airplanes, to relieve some of this pressure.</p>
        <p>The Chinese, in short, are playing the diplomacy of globalization hard -- knowing it gives them a lot of leverage in the United States. It may not be clear yet how effective they will be in getting their way with the Bush team, but it seems safe to say that Prime Minister Wen doesn't need to worry about getting any lectures in Washington about globalization, let alone democracy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
