<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Footwear Politics; Just Who, Really, Is a Birkenstock Voter?</title>
    <meta content="05BELL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/05/weekinreview/05BELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031012T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1524839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Footwear Politics"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, Howard (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Howard Dean</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7DF123CF936A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Footwear Politics; Just Who, Really, Is a Birkenstock Voter?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Just Who, Really, Is a Birkenstock Voter?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporters surveying crowds at rallies for presidential hopeful Howard Dean are referring to his constituents as 'Birkenstock liberals,' referring to their presumed footwear preference; Birkenstock is handy reference in world increasingly prone to thinking about shoes as infallible system of social and ideological classification; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT some point on the campaign route to Iowa and New Hampshire, the name Howard Dean yoked itself to a shoe -- specifically, to a unisex sandal already married in the public consciousness to diversions like mud baths. Birkenstock first surfaced as a political adjective this summer when reporters, surveying the crowds at Dean rallies, began to refer to Dr. Dean's constituents by their presumed footwear preference: the ''Birkenstock liberals.''</p>
        <p>But no one has given the term greater traction than Dr. Dean himself, who now sardonically invokes it as a pre-emptive thrust countering criticism of policies with which the opposition is likely to have too much fun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As codes to allegiances of class and style, shoes may be able to tell us how someone might vote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT some point on the campaign route to Iowa and New Hampshire, the name Howard Dean yoked itself to a shoe -- specifically, to a unisex sandal already married in the public consciousness to diversions like mud baths. Birkenstock first surfaced as a political adjective this summer when reporters, surveying the crowds at Dean rallies, began to refer to Dr. Dean's constituents by their presumed footwear preference: the ''Birkenstock liberals.''</p>
        <p>But no one has given the term greater traction than Dr. Dean himself, who now sardonically invokes it as a pre-emptive thrust countering criticism of policies with which the opposition is likely to have too much fun.</p>
        <p>It is not unusual for him to follow up remarks advocating wind-based renewable energy with a line like one he deployed in August at a speech in Seattle: ''I can see Karl Rove rubbing his hands together and cackling, 'Look at this liberal Birkenstock governor who is going to run against us.' Anybody here have any Birkenstocks on?''</p>
        <p>That no political analyst has sought to determine how many potential Dean voters actually own and wear Birkenstocks is irrelevant. The Birkenstock is a handy referent in a world increasingly prone to thinking about shoes as an infallible system of social and ideological classification. To say, for instance, that someone is a Manolo Blahnik woman -- ''Manolo'' now an expression in such wide use it appears on op-ed pages without exposition -- is to suggest very efficiently that she is between 28 and 45, with a post-feminist orientation and an Austenesque appetite for marrying well.</p>
        <p>Shoes can telegraph a lot about someone -- where a person has come from, landed or would like to go. And as codes to allegiances of class and style, shoes may be able to tell us how someone might vote.</p>
        <p>But what specifically, you may wonder, does it mean to designate Dr. Dean the nation's Birkenstock candidate? Inasmuch as the Birkenstock conjures up the picture of a college graduate who with no immediate penchant for enterprise moves to Colorado to spend some time skiing, the moniker obtains. Between his years at Yale and the Albert Einstein College of Medicine during the 70's, Dr. Dean, in fact, moved to Colorado to spend some time skiing.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, popular culture has ascribed to the Birkenstock lifestyle an ethos of unreconstructed liberalism to which Dr. Dean does not easily conform. Progressives to the left of the candidate, who both supports the death penalty and is a friend of the National Rifle Association, believe the shorthand is unearned. During Vermont's 2000 governor's race, Dr. Dean lost the endorsement of that state's Sierra Club to a more left-leaning competitor. One could argue that Dennis Kucinich, who has proposed a national Department of Peace should he become president, might better fit the label. And one could suggest that handlers reconstitute Dr. Dean as a Merrell hiking shoe centrist, or maybe a Democrat belonging to the L. L. Bean duck boot wing of the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>At the same time, a Birkenstock doesn't especially qualify as a Birkenstock anymore either. Recently, the company has been making an aggressive effort to market itself to the urban-dwelling and aesthetically invested.</p>
        <p>Last month Birkenstock introduced a new series of shoes called the Architect Collection. The shoes, which cost $250 and look ready for a moonwalk, were designed by Yves Béhar, who, to judge from his photo on the company's Web site, seems the sort who has never been within a washing-machine's width of anything tie-dyed. Moreover, the company has developed another new line of shoes in conjunction with the supermodel Heidi Klum, which sell at stores like Barneys.</p>
        <p>The stereotyping of Dr. Dean creates an irresistible temptation to affix metaphoric shoe choices to other presidential candidates and their followers. Taking into account Hollywood's current infatuation with Gen. Wesley Clark, Donny Deutsch, chairman of the Deutsch ad agency and an adviser to Bill Clinton during the 1992 campaign, said he would call General Clark the Gucci loafer candidate.</p>
        <p>''It's urbane, it's aspirational, and talk about a crossover shoe,'' Mr. Deutsch said. ''It works for a Wall Street banker and for some agent who is going to wear them to the office with jeans and no socks.''</p>
        <p>But apparently General Clark is in no danger of alienating the Rockport man, the Rockport being a soft-soled office-casual shoe favored by the decidedly middle class. ''The Rockport man,'' said the pollster Frank Luntz, ''is going to go for Wesley Clark because he's going to appreciate the military background.''</p>
        <p>John Kerry, the Massachusetts senator whose net worth has been estimated as high as $623 million, could pass muster as ''the John Lobb candidate,'' said Peter Arnold, a former lawyer and the executive director of the Council of Fashion Designers of America. Handmade English brogues, Lobbs can cost as much as furniture.</p>
        <p>And what of John Edwards? ''Edwards is the Bruno Magli man,'' said the pollster John Zogby. ''Stylish, slick, very Kennedy wannabe.''</p>
        <p>The most celebrated rancher in Crawford, Tex., hands down, wins the title of Tony Llama incumbent.</p>
        <p>Footwear Politics  Correction:  October 12, 2003, Sunday  An article last Sunday about footwear and politics misspelled the brand name of boots that seem closest to President Bush's personality. It is Tony Lama, not Llamas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 12, 2003, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about footwear and politics misspelled the brand name of boots that seem closest to President Bush's personality. It is Tony Lama, not Llamas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
