<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rainy Day Woman</title>
    <meta content="08DARKLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/08/books/review/08DARKLT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1495342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dark, Alice Elliott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Roxana</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sweetwater (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Roxana</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Sweetwater (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DC1F31F93BA35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rainy Day Woman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Sweetwater': Rainy Day Woman</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alice Elliott Dark</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dark, Alice Elliott</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Elliott Dark reviews book Sweetwater by Roxana Robinson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SWEETWATER</p>
        <p>By Roxana Robinson.</p>
        <p>319 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roxana Robinson's environmentalist heroine has a passion for water, if not for her husband.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SWEETWATER</p>
        <p>By Roxana Robinson.</p>
        <p>319 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>ISABEL PIERCE, the central character of ''Sweetwater,'' Roxana Robinson's fluid third novel, gives the appearance of being a thoughtful, reserved, quiet woman who won't rock any boats in her life. Yet she harbors passions; it might be said of her that still waters run deep. One of her passions is for water itself, a subject in which she has some expertise through her work as an effluent contamination specialist at the Environmental Protection Resources foundation. ''Seeping downward was the key. . . . Everything, all of nature, depended on water seeping down, through soft earth, through bogs and swamps and marshes into the groundwater. . . . The aquifer was the source of freshwater springs, of ponds and lakes, and it was created over millions of years by rainwater sinking into the earth. Deep in the mineral substrata lay great bodies of water, cold and pure, unseen, locked in silence. Far more valuable than oil or gold, these rich hidden mother lodes were the earth's real treasure.''</p>
        <p>Isabel admires the complexity of this system and works to protect it. However, at 47, she has little energy for advocating on her own behalf. Over the past several years a river of grief has seeped through her being. Her husband, Michael Green, has died, leaving her essentially alone. Their son, Ben, is away at college. She's an only child of parents who don't play a large role in her daily life. The daughter for whom she longed so fervently for years was never more than a dream; Isabel has given up even thinking about a second child. There's no evidence of close friends in her life, although she knows how to engage in companionable office relationships. She lives in Manhattan, and might have become one of many self-sufficient, single city women were it not for Paul Simmons, a divorced fellow ''do-gooder'' -- he works for a foundation that supports cancer research -- with whom she has a slight acquaintance. When they run into each other at the aptly named Dr. Lunet's optometry office, Isabel likes Paul immediately, and though she's unsure about wanting a relationship, she feels she should give him a chance. Within months, they marry. ''What she felt for Paul was quieter than what she'd felt for Michael, but . . . this kind of emotion -- calm and muted -- was what was left to her. . . . All the other things -- wildness and bliss and desperation, rage, the urgency of sex -- lay behind her. . . . What she aimed for now was loyalty and affection.''</p>
        <p>Isabel has good reason to believe she can make this work; she was loyal to Michael through years of erratic behavior and bouts of depression. Yet, in the first summer after her marriage, when she and Paul join his family at Sweetwater, their lodge in the Adirondacks, she maintains a probationary attitude toward her surroundings. Sweetwater is an idyllic spot, yet never does Isabel stake a claim to it, as in someday-this-will-all-be-mine. She is a conscientious, tentative guest who follows Paul's lead in all activities. Likewise, she is reticent and courteous with Paul's self-satisfied parents, even when her father-in-law, Douglas, bullies her about her views on conservation. Isabel presents a few facts about global warming in a manner most readers will find exceedingly polite; rich, ignorant, entitled Douglas wouldn't last a minute on Ricki or Maury or Jerry. Yet Isabel can't handle sticking up for herself and her knowledge. ''She felt oppressed by his attitude, so rigid and intolerant: it was exactly what was responsible for the devastation of the environment. But she also felt ashamed of her own response, which had been unyielding, just as rigid and intolerant as his. Inappropriate for dinner conversation with her parents-in-law or anyone else. . . . Where was her social grace, that would permit everyone to have his or her own view?''</p>
        <p>THIS assessment seems not a statement of authorial values, but another of Isabel's attempts to achieve the natural balance for which she longs. For ''Sweetwater'' is essentially a character study. We are given to observe Isabel through both her first and her second marriages -- the novel proceeds by cutting between the two -- and we quickly become intimate with her thoughts and feelings. Yet we aren't asked to identify wholly with her. Instead, we watch her, as we might watch one of Sue Miller's off-kilter heroines. Isabel's problem is clear -- she doesn't really know herself -- and she's enigmatic to the reader as well. Is she reliable and deserving of our empathy, or not? There are many aspects of ''Sweetwater'' that are more ambitious than the readable books Robinson has written in the past (her previous novels are ''Summer Light'' and ''This Is My Daughter''), but this mystery of personality seems the greatest leap attempted. The risks taken here don't all pay off, but Robinson writes big solid scenes, bubbling with tension, that hold the reader's interest. She has always shown her characters' flaws, and the dark emotions stirred up by divorce and parenthood; here she has reached farther to relate her characteristic predicaments to the larger world outside. Isabel is as polluted, with grief and guilt, as the water she worries about, but there's a deeper murkiness to her that isn't easily traceable to any of the toxic events of her life. In our last sighting of her, she's oblivious of the dramatic scene happening around her; instead, she's slumped against the supportive shoulder of her third husband, sound asleep.</p>
        <p>This seems appropriate; in a sense, she's always been snoozy, especially when it comes to men. She's not the girl who has a list in her mind of what she's looking for. She allows herself to be picked, and then she adjusts. She is therefore unprepared for what happens to her when she meets Whit, Paul's younger brother; she doesn't even recognize her response for what it is. ''It was like looking at the sun. She wanted to move away.'' Whit is a fellow conservationist who studies mountain lions in Wyoming. Isabel instinctively trusts him enough to confide what really happened on the night Michael died, a cleansing revelation. Yet she and Whit are still each as parched as the forest around them, primed to burst into flame. Is the final conflagration Isabel's fault, though? Or is it just nature taking its course? ''Sweetwater'' poses complex questions; Robinson has expanded her range by asking them.</p>
        <p>Alice Elliott Dark's most recent books are ''Think of England'' and ''In the Gloaming.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alice Elliott Dark's most recent books are ''Think of England'' and ''In the Gloaming.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
