<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australia Promoting Its Natural Gas in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="03GAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/03/business/worldbusiness/03gas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1540140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baja California (Mexico)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevrontexaco Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Dutch/shell Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exxon Mobil</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gallop, Geoff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Baja California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">ChevronTexaco Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Exxon Mobil Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Energy Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D81F3AF930A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australia Promoting Its Natural Gas in U.S.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Australia Promoting Its Natural Gas in U.S.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoff Gallop, state premier of Western Australia, is visiting US to help ChevronTexaco sell Australia's natural gas; visits Baja California, Mexico, where ChevronTexaco hopes to build terminal to receive liquefied natural gas shipped from huge $7.9 billion gas project off coast of Western Australia called Gorgon; field plus group of adjacent gas fields known collectively as Greater Gorgon, all operated by ChevronTexaco as part of consortium it leads with Royal/Dutch Shell and Exxon Mobil, represent Australia's largest known gas reserve; project is part of new growth initiative by Australia's gas export industry, which hopes to take advantage of increased global demand; most Australian gas exports have been to Japan; Australia hopes to capitalize on looming gas shortage in US; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Geoff Gallop, the state premier of Western Australia, is visiting the United States to help ChevronTexaco sell Australia's natural gas. Between meetings with oil executives in California and energy officials in Washington, he visited Baja California, Mexico, where ChevronTexaco hopes to build a terminal to receive liquefied natural gas shipped from a huge $7.9 billion gas project off the coast of Western Australia called Gorgon.</p>
        <p>That field plus a group of adjacent gas fields known collectively as Greater Gorgon, all operated by ChevronTexaco as part of a consortium it leads with Royal/Dutch Shell and Exxon Mobil, represent Australia's largest known gas reserve. With an estimated 40 trillion cubic feet, it is the equivalent of two-thirds of Canada's proven reserves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Australian gas concerns are betting they can ship gas competitively all the way across the Pacific Ocean to the West Coast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Geoff Gallop, the state premier of Western Australia, is visiting the United States to help ChevronTexaco sell Australia's natural gas. Between meetings with oil executives in California and energy officials in Washington, he visited Baja California, Mexico, where ChevronTexaco hopes to build a terminal to receive liquefied natural gas shipped from a huge $7.9 billion gas project off the coast of Western Australia called Gorgon.</p>
        <p>That field plus a group of adjacent gas fields known collectively as Greater Gorgon, all operated by ChevronTexaco as part of a consortium it leads with Royal/Dutch Shell and Exxon Mobil, represent Australia's largest known gas reserve. With an estimated 40 trillion cubic feet, it is the equivalent of two-thirds of Canada's proven reserves.</p>
        <p>The project is part of a new growth initiative by Australia's gas export industry, which hopes to take advantage of increased global demand. Most Australian gas exports to date have been to Japan, with almost none to the United States. But with a gas shortage looming in the United States, Australian gas concerns are betting they can ship gas competitively all the way across the Pacific Ocean to the West Coast.</p>
        <p>ChevronTexaco and Australian officials emphasize Australia's advantages of security and stability, a message Mr. Gallop has used successfully to pitch Australian gas in China. ''We can deliver for the Americans,'' Mr. Gallop said in a telephone interview from Perth, the capital of Western Australia, before departing for California with executives from Gorgon and other Australian natural resource companies.</p>
        <p>Gas accounts for roughly a quarter of United States energy consumption, with most piped from domestic and Canadian fields. But as demand rises, new North American supplies are getting more expensive to drill. The National Petroleum Council, an industry body, warned in a report to the Energy Department in September that the country faced a gas shortage unless it developed new sources, including liquefied natural gas imports.</p>
        <p>''Gorgon is a potential competitor for those new volumes,'' said Paul Oen, the North Dakotan who manages Gorgon for ChevronTexaco and its partners in Perth.</p>
        <p>Australia has only a fraction of the reserves of gas giants like Russia or Iran. Still, it has more gas than its 20 million people can use and is the world's fifth-largest gas exporter. ''We're overrun with gas at the moment,'' said Ian Macfarlane, Australia's minister for industry, tourism and resources.</p>
        <p>Officials say the Gorgon project, with its estimated 2.5 billion Australian dollars ($1.8 billion) in annual revenue, would generate roughly 10,000 jobs, more than 17.5 billion Australian dollars in royalties for the federal government and 2 billion Australian dollars for Western Australia's economy over the life of the project.</p>
        <p>In August, ChevronTexaco and Shell announced their intention to ship Gorgon's gas to Baja California by 2008. Shell has already received approvals to build a terminal there and ChevronTexaco hopes to do the same within the next six months.</p>
        <p>The Gorgon field was discovered off Australia's northwest coast in 1981 but has long languished in the shadow of a nearby development, the North West Shelf, which has been exporting to Japan since 1989. In addition, its gas has little of the lucrative petroleum condensates often found with natural gas but is instead mixed with a relatively high proportion of carbon dioxide that must be removed at considerable expense.</p>
        <p>Shell has a 34 percent stake in North West Shelf's operator, Woodside Petroleum of Perth, and both Shell and ChevronTexaco hold direct stakes in North West Shelf. Gorgon gained momentum in late 2001 when Chevron's merger with Texaco gave it a controlling stake. ChevronTexaco has a four-sevenths interest, Shell has two-sevenths and Exxon Mobil one-seventh.</p>
        <p>Abandoning plans to develop the fields as part of the North West Shelf and use North West's liquefaction plant on the Australian mainland, the Gorgon consortium decided to develop its fields alone.</p>
        <p>To cut costs, it decided to try to sell potential customers a stake. After failing to bring in a Korean investor, Gorgon teamed up with North West Shelf to woo China, with the help of Mr. Gallop and the Australian prime minister, John Howard. Last year, China chose North West Shelf over Qatar and Indonesia to supply it with 25 billion Australian dollars worth of gas over 25 years. And last month, the state-owned China National Offshore Oil Company signed an agreement outlining plans to sell Gorgon gas in China and to take an unspecified stake in the project.</p>
        <p>Gorgon still needs environmental approvals to build its liquefaction plant on land near the field, saying it is the only feasible site. But that land, Barrow Island, is a nature reserve.</p>
        <p>Choosing Barrow was not only about saving steps; it was about disposing of Gorgon's carbon dioxide. ChevronTexaco has been drilling for oil on Barrow for nearly 40 years, filling reservoirs with water as it extracts crude. Gorgon cannot release the carbon dioxide into the atmosphere, but it could pump it into the reservoirs, trapping it inside.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists condemn the plan, saying that it will further disturb Barrow's ecology and will encourage the introduction of other gas-related industries. Western Australia's Environmental Protection Agency has advised against using Barrow. But in September Mr. Gallop gave Gorgon approval in principle to use the island, and last month, the state's Parliament passed legislation allowing Gorgon to do so.</p>
        <p>If approvals and construction proceed as planned, Gorgon could begin shipping gas overseas in a few years. The trick will be to make sure it does so profitably.</p>
        <p>Big gas projects like Gorgon face a quandary: customers do not want to commit themselves until they are assured of supply, and developers do not want to build until they are assured of purchases. In Asia, this results in 20- to 30-year sales contracts. But the United States, with its vast pipeline network, has the world's largest spot market for gas. The only Australian gas sold in North America so far has been spare cargoes from North West Shelf.</p>
        <p>Still, in what company officials say is an expression of their confidence, ChevronTexaco and Shell have signed memorandums of understanding to buy Gorgon gas for 20 years.</p>
        <p>''The partners in this project,'' Mr. Oen said, ''have enough clout to create their own market opportunities in North America.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
