<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Environmental Rules, Bush Sees a Balance, Critics a Threat</title>
    <meta content="23ENVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1467280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED8113DF930A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="4799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Environmental Rules, Bush Sees a Balance, Critics a Threat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush has placed far-reaching stamp on environmental policy, tying it to other goals that are not always complementary, like economic growth, protection from regulation, increased energy production and deference to local control; many of policies are being put into effect not by changing law, but through less visible realm of regulation; senior advisers say they are demonstrating that it is possible to have strong economic growth and strong environmental protection, but critics say there has been significant retreat on environmental protection; summary of major changes undertaken in areas of clean air and water, land development, energy and global climate; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For two years, it has come in bursts, on issues from arsenic to wetlands: the unfolding of what President Bush, as a candidate, promised would be a new era of environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Whether rejecting a treaty on global warming, questioning Clinton-era rules on forest protection or pressing for changes in landmark environmental laws, Mr. Bush has imposed a distinctive stamp on a vast landscape of issues affecting air, water, land, energy and the global climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For two years, it has come in bursts, on issues from arsenic to wetlands: the unfolding of what President Bush, as a candidate, promised would be a new era of environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Whether rejecting a treaty on global warming, questioning Clinton-era rules on forest protection or pressing for changes in landmark environmental laws, Mr. Bush has imposed a distinctive stamp on a vast landscape of issues affecting air, water, land, energy and the global climate.</p>
        <p>What has emerged is an approach similar to President Ronald Reagan's. It seeks to tie environmental protection to other goals that are not always complementary, like economic growth, protection from regulation, increased energy production and deference to local control.</p>
        <p>''Our approach is to maximize the quality of life for America,'' said James L. Connaughton, chairman of Mr. Bush's Council on Environmental Quality, ''and that means balancing the environmental equation with the natural resource equation, the social equation and the economic equation.''</p>
        <p>Much of what Mr. Bush has done has the potential to be far-reaching, including some significant rethinking of laws that date as far back as the Nixon administration and the creation of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>He has proposed new flexibility in the enforcement of the 1972 Clean Air Act to allow old coal-fired power plants, the country's biggest polluters, to modernize without meeting present-day standards and to trade the right to pollute among themselves.</p>
        <p>He has opened more public land to energy exploration and is seeking to open more, particularly in Alaska, because of the view that federal lands are underused as a source of natural resources, and that increased American oil and gas production is the best way to ease dependence on foreign supplies.</p>
        <p>And in the arena of global warming, Mr. Bush has ruled out mandatory controls on American emissions of so-called greenhouse gases, the man-made component of climate change, in favor of voluntary measures that he says can address the problem without imposing a crippling economic cost.</p>
        <p>Many of these policies are being put into effect not by changing laws but through the less visible realm of regulation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his senior advisers say they are demonstrating that it is possible to have the best of two worlds -- that ''strong economic growth and strong environmental protection go hand in hand,'' as a White House report put it last fall.</p>
        <p>But much of what the White House has called progress has been labeled by critics, Republicans as well as Democrats, as examples of significant retreat. The White House proposals, given names like Healthy Forests and Clear Skies, have been derided as promoting exactly the opposite of what they proclaim.</p>
        <p>''Across the board,'' said Senator James M. Jeffords, the Vermont independent who until recently was the chairman of the Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works, ''we would be better off doing nothing than doing what the Bush administration wants to do, which will make things worse than they already are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Connaughton of the environmental council dismissed such critics as ''one-note Nellies of regulate, litigate, re-regulate, litigate,'' adding, ''We came into office saying we have a much broader toolbox of policy tools to use.''</p>
        <p>Protecting the environment is an important issue to the suburban swing voters whose allegiance is sought by both political parties, so it is not surprising that the White House takes pains to cast its actions as environmentally friendly.</p>
        <p>But the disconnect between this administration's claims and those of its critics has been particularly profound. Some environmental organizations regularly denounce the president's actions as representing the biggest setback in a generation.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council, for example, described Mr. Bush's policy on the environment in a recent report as a ''fundamental threat more sweeping and dangerous than any since the dawn of the modern environmental movement in 1970.''</p>
        <p>How, then, to sort out the rival assessments on issues so complicated that they are commonly referred to in shorthand, by names like Kyoto, Superfund and ANWR?</p>
        <p>By one gauge, which would see the federal government as the environment's policeman, the Bush administration has fallen short of its predecessor, with enforcement actions and fines down by at least 30 percent.</p>
        <p>By another, measuring fealty to landmark laws like the Clean Water Act, the Clean Air Act and the National Environmental Policy Act, the administration has not held the past sacrosanct, proposing or enacting changes that would, at the very minimum, make existing standards more flexible.</p>
        <p>But administration officials, including Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, reject these measures as inappropriate and inconsistent with the administration's approach. The only fair test, Mrs. Whitman said in a recent interview, would ask: ''Is the air cleaner, is the water purer, is the land better protected?''</p>
        <p>On that score, the picture is not yet clear. The most objective gauges are not always up to date. Some of the administration's most important proposals have not yet been enacted, and some changes are too recent to have had a measurable impact.</p>
        <p>But in five major areas of environmental protection -- air, water, land, energy and global climate -- it is possible to summarize the major changes during Mr. Bush's two years in office, and to compare that record with the administration's own declared standard of how it should be judged.</p>
        <p>The Air  Nontraditional Ideas, Mixed Responses</p>
        <p>In combating air pollution, the Bush administration has in some ways picked up where its predecessors left off, further tightening rules under the Clean Air Act to reduce emissions of harmful pollutants.</p>
        <p>The diesel engines that power big trucks and off-road vehicles will become subject to ever stricter pollution control regulations in the next decade, under rules the Bush administration made final, thus closing loopholes that had left some of the country's dirtiest vehicles less regulated than ordinary automobiles.</p>
        <p>In his approach to pollution from power plants, however, Mr. Bush has proved less traditional -- and, not surprisingly, more controversial.</p>
        <p>In one of his most closely watched decisions, Mr. Bush would allow electric utilities to upgrade old, dirty, coal-fired power plants without having to install costly new state-of-the-art pollution control devices. That stand, proposed as a federal rule, would affect a part of the Clean Air Act known as new source review, which was intended to accelerate the phase-out of the old plants.</p>
        <p>A separate plan, known as Clear Skies, would seek to cut emissions of three major pollutants from all power plants 70 percent by 2018, but would not impose the standard uniformly, allowing operators to trade ''pollution credits'' -- the right to pollute -- among themselves.</p>
        <p>The White House cites the Clear Skies proposal as the prime example of an innovative approach, one that it said last fall would ''bring cleaner air to Americans faster, more reliably and more effectively than under current law.'' But the response to both approaches has been mixed.</p>
        <p>The existing new source review rules require that modifications to old power plants and other industrial sites include upgrades to modern antipollution standards. Even the most ardent environmentalists concede that those rules are flawed, and have left power plant operators with little incentive to clean up their oldest, dirtiest facilities. And the shift under the Clear Skies plan toward a market-based approach to cutting power plant emissions, instead of one that depends solely on inflexible regulations, has won praise from some environmental groups.</p>
        <p>But Senator Jeffords and other critics say they are convinced that the two initiatives would ultimately lead to more pollution, not less. They say the best way to reduce air pollution would be to hold polluters to the strict terms of existing laws, not change them.</p>
        <p>Nine Northeastern states have filed lawsuits in an effort to block the new rules on power plant upgrades.</p>
        <p>''You're carving a big hole in the Clean Air Act, and history has shown that given the option to avoid spending the money on pollution control, these old coal-fired plants will take the step of evading those controls,'' said Gregory Wetstone, director of advocacy for the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>Is the air cleaner? Probably. By most broad measurements, air quality across the United States is better today than at any time in the last three decades.</p>
        <p>The White House and its critics attribute that result to the Clean Air Act, which the administration says it is merely trying to improve.</p>
        <p>''The air, along with every other aspect of the environment, is getting cleaner,'' said William L. Kovacs, a vice president of the United States Chamber of Commerce, which represents business interests and has been broadly supportive of Mr. Bush's environmental record. ''I think that has been a true statement for the last 30 years, and it will continue to be. I think Bush has been continuing along that path.''</p>
        <p>The Water  Defining Wetlands And Other Challenges</p>
        <p>One enduring impression of the Bush administration's approach to clean water was left by its decision, in its early days, to scrap a standard proposed by the Clinton administration that imposed a strict new limit on arsenic in drinking water.</p>
        <p>The decision set off a political furor, and Democrats seized upon it as evidence that the president was insensitive to public health. Ultimately, the Bush administration reinstated the Clinton standard, after determining that it met cost-benefit tests. But the example became the fodder of late-night talk shows and an early political embarrassment for the White House.</p>
        <p>Administration officials nonetheless say their stance reflects a willingness to challenge orthodoxies in considering when and whether environmental regulation is justified.</p>
        <p>''You can't ignore cost-benefits,'' Mrs. Whitman said in the interview. But, she added: ''The difficulty starts with the fact that the environment evokes such emotion in people. There's one group for whom you can never do enough, and another group for whom any time you put out a regulation, you're getting in the way of progress.''</p>
        <p>Across the broad spectrum of water issues, the administration's environmental policies have met with both kinds of criticism.</p>
        <p>Most significantly, the administration decided last month to address a 2001 Supreme Court decision by beginning its own effort to redraw the definition of what constitutes a federally protected swamp, marshland or other wetland area. The review could open up vast swatches of land for development, resulting in a 20 percent shrinkage of federal wetland acreage.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have called the action a necessary and measured response to the court ruling, which said a previous interpretation of what land was protected under the Clean Water Act had overreached.</p>
        <p>But critics have said the approach could undermine an important provision of the act. They particularly fear that the administration may use the Supreme Court's decision as an excuse to give up authority over tens of millions of acres of wetlands and streams that the decision did not raise questions about.</p>
        <p>''A lot of what can be phrased as flexibility is just saying that industry or states can do whatever they want,'' said Tim Searchinger, a senior lawyer with Environmental Defense, an advocacy group.</p>
        <p>In one notable environmental effort, in the Hudson River, the administration bucked an industry lobbying campaign and has pursued an orthodox approach to pollution. It forced General Electric to spend hundreds of millions of dollars to clean waters it had fouled, one of the largest industrial cleanups in American history.</p>
        <p>The administration has also declined to endorse several large Army Corps of Engineers projects that critics see as particularly destructive to the environment.</p>
        <p>More broadly, however, the main thrust has been in pursuit of a flexibility that the administration says will result in greater cost savings and efficiency but that critics say might simply move pollution around.</p>
        <p>A water quality trading program introduced last year by the Environmental Protection Agency and aimed at cleaning up rivers, lakes and streams would allow states, tribes and companies to buy and sell pollution credits for water, in a market-based approach that the agency has used successfully in the effort to combat acid rain.</p>
        <p>Is the water purer? On that front, the picture is unclear. The agency's most recent water quality report, issued in 2000, the year Mr. Bush was seeking the presidency, showed that the percentage of assessed waters that were polluted had increased to 45 percent in 2000 from 40 percent in 1998, and there is no clear indication of whether this has been reversed.</p>
        <p>The Land  Easing Barriers To Development</p>
        <p>On issues affecting land, the main thrust of the Bush administration's approach has been to emphasize that conservation should not bar use.</p>
        <p>In its policies on forests, endangered species and energy exploration, the administration has generally sought to scale back barriers to logging, drilling, mining and other kinds of development. It argues that previous administrations had put too much public land off limits for reasonable purposes.</p>
        <p>''We are managing our lands for the needs of the American public; part of that is managing for environmental protection,'' Gale A. Norton, the interior secretary, said in a recent interview. At the same time, she added, ''We also need to look for those things that serve the American public.''</p>
        <p>Some of the notable examples of this approach have occurred in regard to the national forests, where the administration strongly resisted a sweeping Clinton administration action putting millions of acres of forests off limits to road building. The road building ban was reinstated late last year by a federal appeals court, but the administration's lack of support has left those protections vulnerable to efforts by Congress to narrow their scope.</p>
        <p>Separately, in proposed legislation known as Healthy Forests, now before Congress, the administration has pressed to ease barriers to logging as a method of fire prevention. The central purpose of the initiative -- thinning overgrown Western forests that are prone to catastrophic fire -- has broad support from environmentalists and from the timber industry. But the environmentalists say it allows too much latitude for the removal of large trees that provide important habitat.</p>
        <p>At the same time, in several little-noticed court cases brought by developers, the administration has agreed to settlements that have significantly shrunk the areas that federal agencies had claimed as the critical habitats of endangered species.</p>
        <p>In pursuit of energy, the administration has also opened the way to increased oil and gas exploration on public lands, particularly in Colorado and Utah. It has sought to do the same in Alaska's Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, known as ANWR, a proposal that has met fierce political resistance and that Congress has declined to approve.</p>
        <p>Notably, though, the administration on two occasions scaled back drilling plans for offshore areas near the Florida coast, on the ground that local opposition (including that from Mr. Bush's brother Gov. Jeb Bush, who was running for re-election at the time) made the exploration unwise.</p>
        <p>A broader and potentially more significant change is only beginning to take shape. In a series of directives and other initiatives affecting plans for logging, highway construction and other activities, the administration has sought to streamline the review process required under the National Environmental Policy Act.</p>
        <p>The administration says those efforts are intended only to remove unnecessary bureaucratic hurdles, but critics say they would weaken a main pillar of environmental law.</p>
        <p>Is the land better protected? Across the board, the administration's proposals would allow greater access to public lands for the extraction of natural resources. The White House says that this is among the lands' many uses, and that its plans are environmentally sensible, while its opponents say the land would be despoiled.</p>
        <p>Energy  Blueprint for Change With Many Critics</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said soon after taking office that his goal was to reduce the country's dependence on foreign oil, to increase domestic production and to make energy cleaner and more affordable for all Americans. None of these things has happened.</p>
        <p>The country still imports nearly 60 percent of its oil, close to a record. American oil and gas production have remained flat, gasoline and heating fuel prices have been high, and renewable fuels still account for less than 4 percent of American consumption.</p>
        <p>The White House argues that it deserves credit for trying.</p>
        <p>With the National Energy Plan it released in the spring of 2001, it produced a broad blueprint for change, including the call for drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. But that proposal and others have not been acted on by Congress.</p>
        <p>''We have worked to enhance traditional energy sources as well as to identify new sources,'' Ms. Norton said. ''There's a long lead time in all of this, and the fact that it takes a while means that we are going about it responsibly.''</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Bush also call attention to his support for energy efficiency, in part through tightened federal standards for refrigerators and other appliances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has proposed a modest increase in fuel efficiency standards for cars and light trucks, which would be the first since 1985. In his most recent State of the Union address, he promised more federal money to promote production of hydrogen-powered cars. But that plan does not envision mass production until 2020.</p>
        <p>The president's critics say he set his sights on the wrong goal. Instead of focusing on increasing domestic production, they say, he should have aimed at reducing American energy consumption through increased conservation.</p>
        <p>The critics say the increase of 1.5 miles per gallon Mr. Bush has proposed in the corporate fuel economy standard is far too little -- particularly when more people are driving sport utility vehicles and reducing dependence on foreign oil is a national security consideration.</p>
        <p>They say the White House should do far more to encourage a switch to renewable fuels, like wind power.</p>
        <p>''The president simply hasn't been willing to cross his political backers and push hard for the rapid deployment of more fuel-efficient cars, cleaner power sources and more energy-conserving buildings,'' said Dan W. Reicher, an assistant secretary of energy in the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>More broadly, the critics argue that Mr. Bush's focus on energy production has caused him to pay too little attention to global warming and to the emission of carbon dioxide from the burning of fossil fuels, its chief man-made cause.</p>
        <p>In 2001, Mr. Bush based his decision to reject the Kyoto treaty, which called for mandatory reductions in greenhouse gas emissions, primarily on economic grounds, saying that compliance with the treaty could stifle growth.</p>
        <p>The voluntary measures he has proposed since then would aim only to slow the rate at which American emissions of greenhouse gases increase, rather than to reduce them or cap them at current levels, unless further revelations from research clarify the severity of the environmental risks.</p>
        <p>In addressing another international climate treaty, Mr. Bush has also sought more latitude for American industry. The administration is requesting exemptions for 54 companies and trade groups that want to continue using a pesticide scheduled to be phased out by 2005 under the Montreal Protocol of 1987, a treaty intended to protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Administration officials defend these policies and others as reflecting the kind of balance Mr. Bush is determined to strike.</p>
        <p>''The president does have a fundamental difference of opinion with some others,'' said Mr. Connaughton, the chairman of the White House environmental council, ''and it is that you can't have the kind of environmental improvements that Americans now demand without a growing economy that pays for the improvements. ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
