<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PASSAGE UNLIKELY FOR SEPARATE BILL ON ELECTRICAL GRID</title>
    <meta content="19ENER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/19/politics/19ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE BLACKOUT: CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markey, Edward J (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bingaman, Jeff (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD71030F93AA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PASSAGE UNLIKELY FOR SEPARATE BILL ON ELECTRICAL GRID</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Passage Unlikely for Separate Bill on Electrical Grid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congress is unlikely to pass separate proposal to improve power grid, even after biggest blackout in nation's history; lawmakers say those plans will stay within broader energy initiative that has been stalled; say blackout is symptom of larger national energy problems that should be addressed in far-reaching fashion rather than by concentrating on power transmission; say they are close to agreement on overall bill and could send one to Pres Bush by end of Sept; White House agrees on need for overall bill; Rep Edward J Markey and other House Democrats are pushing to separate power grid provision in energy bill from other, more controversial portions of bill like drilling in Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and tax breaks for oil and gas industry; say supporters of broader bill are trying to capitalize on momentum from power failure to enact other initiatives that face intense opposition; but Sen Jeff Bingaman, top Democrat on Energy and Natural Resources Comm, says he too favors taking up electricity provisions as part of larger bill; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it tries to respond to the biggest blackout in the nation's history, Congress is unlikely to pass a separate proposal to improve the power grid, instead keeping those plans within a broader energy initiative that has been stalled, lawmakers said today.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress who have been instrumental in drafting the energy policy said the blackout was a symptom of larger national energy problems that should be addressed in a far-reaching fashion rather than by concentrating on power transmission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congress is likely to keep plans to improve the power grid within a broader energy initiative that has been stalled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it tries to respond to the biggest blackout in the nation's history, Congress is unlikely to pass a separate proposal to improve the power grid, instead keeping those plans within a broader energy initiative that has been stalled, lawmakers said today.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress who have been instrumental in drafting the energy policy said the blackout was a symptom of larger national energy problems that should be addressed in a far-reaching fashion rather than by concentrating on power transmission.</p>
        <p>They said they were close to agreement on an overall bill and could send one to President Bush by the end of September.</p>
        <p>''We don't need a singular approach, we need a full market-basket approach,'' said Senator Larry E. Craig, Republican of Idaho, a senior member of the Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig's position, echoed by several Republicans and even a top Senate Democrat on energy issues, is shared by the White House, which said today that those calling for separate legislation to improve electricity transmission were engaging in political posturing.</p>
        <p>''We need comprehensive solutions, not patchwork crisis management,'' Scott McClellan, the White House spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>But some House Democrats stepped up their push to separate the power grid provisions in the energy bill from others like drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska, tax breaks for the oil and gas industry and other benefits for energy producers.</p>
        <p>''Let's show the American people that we can solve the problem that they saw last Thursday,'' said Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts, a member of the House Energy and Commerce Committee. ''They should break off the electricity issues from the other very controversial portions of the energy bill that could take months to resolve.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Markey and other Democrats said the supporters of a broader bill were trying to capitalize on the momentum from last week's power failure to enact other initiatives, some of which face intense opposition. The proposals in the bill under consideration contain dozens of lawmakers' pet projects like wind power, increasing the use of ethanol and subsidies for nuclear power plants.</p>
        <p>Senator Jeff Bingaman of New Mexico, the top Democrat on the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said he too favored taking up the electricity provisions as part of the larger bill.</p>
        <p>''I think getting it done a few weeks before the rest of the bill is not nearly as important as getting it done right,'' Mr. Bingaman said about taking separate action on the electricity provisions.</p>
        <p>The dispute over separating the electricity transmission provisions indicates that the energy policy will be under a new level of scrutiny when Congress returns after Labor Day. The blackout has catapulted the energy policy to the top of the agenda after more than two years of impasse and sporadic consideration.</p>
        <p>The debate comes as the House Energy Committee, as part of its inquiry into the blackout, prepared to send dozens of letters on Tuesday to local and federal officials asking for their views on the causes and consequences of the power failure. Mr. Bush also discussed the investigation by telephone with Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham.</p>
        <p>The House and Senate have each passed energy bills, and senior members of the energy committees will meet next month to draft a plan to submit for a final vote. Much of the work will go on behind the scenes as lawmakers bargain over the shape of the package. Before the blackout, the high-profile public fights over energy policy centered on issues like Alaska drilling, climate change and automobile fuel efficiency standards.</p>
        <p>The House measure would clear the way for the drilling -- a priority of House Republicans and the Bush administration -- while the Senate bill would not. Mr. McClellan would not say whether the president would insist on having Alaska drilling included in any final measure.</p>
        <p>But the Senate has made clear its opposition to drilling there, and some Republicans acknowledge they do not want to be put in the position of holding the energy policy hostage to the issue. Representative Joe L. Barton, a Texas Republican who is influential on energy matters, said today that he did not think Arctic drilling would be a major impediment to the bill.</p>
        <p>Though the complex electricity provisions in the bills received little public attention in the past, they have been contentious in Congress and within the industry itself. Lawmakers have differed on how far Congress and the administration should go in asserting federal authority over the power grid. The Bush administration and Republican leaders in Congress would stop short of a proposal from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission that some lawmakers from the South and West say would usurp state control of utilities. They instead favor enacting new reliability standards and giving authority to enforce them to a body like the North American Electric Reliability Council, a voluntary industry association.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bingaman said he did not know whether that would be sufficient. ''You can't have a national grid if someone at the federal level does not have authority to bring it into existence,'' he said. ''It is as if Eisenhower had said he wanted an interstate highway system in the 1950's and said he hoped the states would get together and build it.''</p>
        <p>But Republicans said they thought that Congress could quickly achieve consensus on reliability standards and enforcement and then strike a deal on an overall policy, avoiding a split between the electricity provisions and other elements.</p>
        <p>''I think the president and the country deserves a comprehensive energy bill that addresses all of our energy needs in a synergistic fashion,'' Mr. Barton said. ''The country would be better off.''</p>
        <p>THE BLACKOUT: CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
