<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Investigators Have Theory About Hole in Wing Edge</title>
    <meta content="Y02PAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/02/national/nationalspecial/02PANE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1477445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Michael P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccool, William C (Cmdr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Husband, Rick D (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Laurel Salton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chawla, Kalpana (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, David M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DF1E39F931A35757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Investigators Have Theory About Hole in Wing Edge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shuttle Investigators Have Theory About Hole in Wing Edge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leading edges of space shuttle wings, which appear more resistant to impact of piece of foam than ceramic tiles on underside, are in some ways more fragile, burning up when heated in presence of oxygen; investigators studying loss of Columbia now theorize that superhot gases rushed into left wing through hole in leading edge (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first glance, the leading edges of the space shuttle wings would appear to be much more resistant to the impact of a piece of foam than the ceramic tiles on the underside of the spacecraft.</p>
        <p>The leading edges are made of hard carbon composites that can survive temperatures up to 3,000 degrees Fahrenheit. The ceramic tiles can be crumbled with a squeeze of the hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first glance, the leading edges of the space shuttle wings would appear to be much more resistant to the impact of a piece of foam than the ceramic tiles on the underside of the spacecraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At first glance, the leading edges of the space shuttle wings would appear to be much more resistant to the impact of a piece of foam than the ceramic tiles on the underside of the spacecraft.</p>
        <p>The leading edges are made of hard carbon composites that can survive temperatures up to 3,000 degrees Fahrenheit. The ceramic tiles can be crumbled with a squeeze of the hand.</p>
        <p>But in some ways, the carbon composite material, known as reinforced carbon-carbon, is more fragile. Heated in the presence of oxygen, it burns up. The carbon atoms rapidly combine with oxygen atoms to form carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide gases that blow away, leaving almost nothing behind.</p>
        <p>Investigators examining the loss of the shuttle Columbia now theorize that superhot gases rushed into the left wing through a hole in the leading edge. That idea has increased attention on the 22 reinforced carbon-carbon panels on the left wing, some of which might have been damaged when a piece of insulating foam fell off the external fuel tank during liftoff.</p>
        <p>The quarter-inch-thick panels, manufactured by the Missiles and Fire Control unit of Lockheed Martin in Dallas, start out as black carbon sheets that are cut, layered and immersed in a carbon resin. Hence the name carbon-carbon.</p>
        <p>The material is molded into the correct shape and baked several times, turning the resin into graphite, a harder version of pencil lead.</p>
        <p>To protect the carbon from burning up in re-entry, a layer of silicon carbide one-fiftieth of an inch thick is applied to the carbon composite. If the silicon carbide shell cracks, oxygen can flow in and start eating away at the carbon underneath.</p>
        <p>The shuttle Atlantis sustained such damage on a flight in November. After it landed, technicians discovered a hole in the leading edge about one-tenth of an inch by one-seventh of an inch. Through an X-ray, workers found that beneath that small hole was a considerably larger cavity, where the reinforced carbon-carbon had been eaten away. The surviving silicon carbide on top was brittle and easily flaked away.</p>
        <p>Oxidation can create ''a void in the surface that translates down to the lower levels,'' Dr. Sheila E. Widnall, a member of the Columbia Accident Investigation Board, said at its news conference on March 11.</p>
        <p>If the falling foam had hit a previously weakened part of the leading edge, the impact could have shattered the silicon carbide, exposing a large section of the underlying carbon composite. When the Columbia re-entered the atmosphere, the ultrahot gases could have burned through the composite, opening a hole.</p>
        <p>Small pinholes have been found to form on the shuttle's leading edges after about 12 flights, but not on the nose cones, which are also made of reinforced carbon-carbon.</p>
        <p>In 1999, Dr. Nathan S. Jacobson of NASA's Glenn Research Center in Cleveland and Dr. Donald M. Curry of the Johnson Space Center in Houston found the cause was probably paint flakes. As a shuttle sits on the launching pad, paint flakes fell from the tower and drifted onto the wings, embedding in crevices along the leading edge. Zinc oxide reacts with the glass coating on top of the silicon carbide, opening up the holes.</p>
        <p>In 2000, Dr. Curry and other researchers conducted experiments on what would happen if a micrometeorite punched a hole through the leading edge. They found that at 2,800 degrees Fahrenheit, oxidation of the carbon tripled the diameter of the hole in about eight minutes.</p>
        <p>Less reactive materials are available. The X-38, a lifeboat for the space station that has been canceled, would have used carbon fibers embedded in silicon carbide.</p>
        <p>Richard M. Saburro, president and chief executive of Starfire Systems in Malta, N.Y., which manufactured some of the silicon carbide used in the X-38, said the silicon carbide composites had passed tests that showed that it could offer the same sort of heat shield as reinforced carbon-carbon and that it could be used on the shuttle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
