<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="20FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1498330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF1F38F933A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Strong Evidence Suggests Saddam Hussein Is Alive  American intelligence analysts believe that Saddam Hussein is much more likely to be alive than dead, a view that has been strengthened in recent weeks by intercepted communications between fugitive members of the Saddam Fedayeen and the Iraqi intelligence service, according to American officials.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Strong Evidence Suggests Saddam Hussein Is Alive  American intelligence analysts believe that Saddam Hussein is much more likely to be alive than dead, a view that has been strengthened in recent weeks by intercepted communications between fugitive members of the Saddam Fedayeen and the Iraqi intelligence service, according to American officials.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A soldier from the 804th Medical Brigade was killed when the military ambulance in which he was traveling came under fire. Two other soldiers were wounded, according to a statement from the United States Central Command.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Food Talks With Europe Fail  Talks between the United States and the European Union over opening Europe to genetically modified foods broke down in Geneva, the Bush administration announced.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iran Urged to Allow Inspections  The International Atomic Energy Agency asked Iran to allow stricter inspections of nuclear reactor sites that the United States has said are being used to develop atomic weapons. Iran rejected the request.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Mideast Talks Gain Steam  Negotiations on several fronts of the American-led peace plan picked up pace, though without any breakthroughs, on the eve of a visit by Secretary of State Colin L. Powell.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Israeli soldiers and police officers scuffled with Jewish settlers as they dismantled a small hillside settlement.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Shimon Peres, just weeks shy of his 80th birthday, was elected as temporary leader of Israel's Labor Party, which suffered its worst electoral defeat earlier this year.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Milosevic War Crimes Trial  Prosecutors at the war crimes trial of Slobodan Milosevic have produced what may prove to be crucial evidence in support of their case that the former Yugoslav president is guilty of genocide in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-21</p>
        <p>Officials Reveal Terror Plot Against the Brooklyn Bridge  Federal law enforcement officials said that they had uncovered a plot by Al Qaeda operatives, using an Ohio truck driver as a scout, to destroy the Brooklyn Bridge and other targets as recently as March.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Findings on Academy Released  A military panel inquiring into reports of sexual assault at the Air Force Academy in Colorado Springs said in Washington that it had found no evidence of campus officials' ignoring or otherwise mishandling reported attacks on cadets.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Bulger Speaks About Brother  William M. Bulger, the president of the University of Massachusetts, testified publicly for the first time in eight years about his brother, one of the nation's most wanted men.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Charges Dropped in Bombing  The Air Force dropped all criminal charges against two American fighter pilots who killed four Canadian soldiers in a mistaken bombing in Afghanistan last year.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Fire Destroys 200 Homes  A wind-propelled wildfire that roared through the upper reaches of the Coronado National Forest destroyed as many as 200 homes near Tuscon, Ariz.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Clerics Push for Tax Credit  Several of the nation's most prominent Protestant leaders implored President Bush to seek increased child tax credits for minimum-wage families.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Recommendations for U.S.O.C.  An outside commission examining the ethical lapses at the United States Olympic Committee reported that the organization's fractious 124-person board of directors should be replaced by a largely independent, nine-member panel.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Building Damaged on 9/11 Is Deemed Beyond Repair  The Deutsche Bank building in Lower Manhattan, among the last remaining buildings damaged in the Sept. 11 terrorist attack whose fate has not been decided, has been deemed beyond repair and is expected to be taken down.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Little Progress in Albany  Governor Pataki and legislative leaders failed to reach agreements on a host of major bills with the legislative session drawing to a close.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Crimes Improperly Downgraded  More than 200 crimes reported last year on the West Side were improperly downgraded in police statistics to misdemeanors, making the area seem safer than it really was, police officials said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-26; E27-34</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Edison Schools Win Round 1  Preliminary test scores showed that student achievement has improved at schools across Philadelphia run by Edison, a pioneer in the private management of public schools.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Narrowing the Reading Gap  The nation's lowest performing fourth graders showed steady progress through much of the 1990's, while the scores of high school seniors consistently declined, an assessment revealed.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Officials Say Test Was Too Hard  Administrators across New York State charged that the Regents exam in mathematics offered this week was too difficult, and many high school seniors may be barred from graduating because they failed.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14, 16</p>
        <p>Move to Restore Media Rules  The Senate began the process of reversing the recent decision by federal regulators to loosen media ownership rules and enable the nation's largest newspaper and broadcasting conglomerates to expand.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A National 'Do Not Call' List  The Federal Trade Commission will begin taking requests from consumers who want their phone numbers made off-limits to telemarketers, who could be fined up to $11,000 for each violation.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Decision on McDonald's Beef  McDonald's plans to ask its meat suppliers to cease using some antibiotics that promote growth in healthy animals and to reduce the use of other antibiotics that protect animals against disease.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Censorship on global warming; more than black and white; a retailer is dressed down; putting ''America'' on the map.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof and Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E32  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E25  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B4  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
