<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enel of Italy Looks to U.S. To Expand</title>
    <meta content="02ENEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/02/business/worldbusiness/02ENEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1485487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enel Spa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sylvers, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arcelli, Marco</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Stock Exchange</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7D9163CF931A35756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enel of Italy Looks to U.S. To Expand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Enel of Italy Looks to U.S. to Expand Utility</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SYLVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sylvers, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Italy's Ene SpA, largest electric utility by market value in world, says there are some very good opportunities in US and if conditions are right will consider acquisitions; utility specializes in renewable energy; incoming chief executive Marco Arcelli comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For now, few Americans have heard of Enel, though millions have seen its handiwork. The company, Italy's former electricity monopoly, supplied the power that lighted the giant crystal apple that descended in Times Square to greet the new year.</p>
        <p>But Enel has ideas about introducing itself to America in a much bigger way, by concentrating on one of its strengths: renewable energy. Enel, the largest electric utility by market value in the world, is also among the world's leading producers of power from renewable resources, and it is confident that it can do so profitably where others have struggled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few Americans have heard of Enel, Italy's former electricity monopoly. But Enel plasns to introduce itself to America in a big way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For now, few Americans have heard of Enel, though millions have seen its handiwork. The company, Italy's former electricity monopoly, supplied the power that lighted the giant crystal apple that descended in Times Square to greet the new year.</p>
        <p>But Enel has ideas about introducing itself to America in a much bigger way, by concentrating on one of its strengths: renewable energy. Enel, the largest electric utility by market value in the world, is also among the world's leading producers of power from renewable resources, and it is confident that it can do so profitably where others have struggled.</p>
        <p>''There are some very good opportunities in the U.S., and if the conditions are right we will consider acquisitions,'' said Marco Arcelli, who will become chief executive of Enel's American operations next week, a month before his 32nd birthday.</p>
        <p>''Some American utilities are busy selling assets and cleaning up their balance sheet,'' Mr. Arcelli said in an interview. ''This is a situation we can take advantage of.''</p>
        <p>When the company was deregulated and taken public in 1999 (the Italian state still holds two-thirds of the stock), Enel was ordered to sell some assets in Italy to provide openings for competitors. Over the last three years, it has parted with 15,000 megawatts of generation capacity in Italy, enough to supply 20 million families. In the process, it has built up a huge store of cash.</p>
        <p>And its operations keep adding to the pile. Enel said last month that it expected to generate a total of 14 billion euros ($15.6 billion) in free cash flow, after interest and taxes have been paid.</p>
        <p>Planned sales of real estate assets this summer will probably yield another 3 billion euros, analysts said; the bidding process on the assets is already under way. And Enel has said that its telecommunications unit, Wind -- No. 2 in Italian fixed-line phone service after Telecom Italia and a major mobile phone operator -- is no longer one of its core businesses and may be sold.</p>
        <p>What to do with all that cash? Buy outside Italy. Mr. Arcelli said the most likely places for acquisitions were in the Western and Northeastern United States, markets where Enel already has a presence through CHI Energy, which it acquired in late 2000 for $312 million. While other American markets, especially Florida, appeal to Enel, Mr. Arcelli said, its first preference is to expand where it already knows the laws and regulators.</p>
        <p>CHI Energy, which is based in Stamford, Conn., produces electricity in 16 states, including New York, California, Washington and Vermont, using renewable resources like wind, water or methane from landfills.</p>
        <p>Enel has also bought or built power plants elsewhere since deregulation, notably in Bulgaria and Spain, and diversified into telecommunications and natural gas distribution. It is the fifth-largest commercial power producer in the world. But though it has slimmed down to controlling just half the Italian power market, the company remains fundamentally an Italian business, deriving about 70 percent of its revenue from selling wattage to Italians.</p>
        <p>But where many other publicly traded utilities have dabbled in renewable energy, Enel has embraced it, generating 2,000 megawatts of ''green power'' in Italy and another 700 megawatts elsewhere, mainly from hydropower and geothermal plants. CHI's operations in the United States account for 400 megawatts of the total.</p>
        <p>One challenge for Mr. Arcelli, who worked at General Electric for five years and is fluent in English, is to bring CHI Energy into closer harness with Enel, which has so far done little to integrate its American unit with the parent company.</p>
        <p>''Part of my move to the U.S. is to push the integration with Enel,'' Mr. Arcelli said. ''We recognize that there are differences, but we want people over there to think Enel day and night.''</p>
        <p>Still, even an aggressive buying spree in the United States will not shift Enel's center of gravity across the Atlantic, Mr. Arcelli said. ''How big we get in the U.S. will depend on the opportunities we find, but we will remain a European company and our core will always be in Italy.''</p>
        <p>The company has lost considerable favor with Italian investors since its initial public offering in November 1999. Many first-time investors were encouraged by the company, the government and Italy's banks to buy shares in the 18 billion euro offering, only to have them sink in value by nearly one-quarter since then. The offering also included American depository receipts, which represent five ordinary shares and trade on the New York Stock Exchange; they rose slightly today, to close at $29.84. About 3 percent of Enel's total equity is held by American mutual funds.</p>
        <p>To raise its profile in the United States, Enel is considering rechristening CHI Energy with a name like Enel Inc. or Enel North America, Mr. Arcelli said. ''A friend of mine in the U.S. last week said to me that Enel is the biggest company nobody's ever heard of,'' he said. ''That is something we would like to change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
