<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Plans Crackdown On Dirty Diesel Engines</title>
    <meta content="Y16ENV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/16/politics/16ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1481370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soot</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur and Sulfur Compounds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Jennifer 8</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources Defense Council</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD91E3BF935A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Plans Crackdown On Dirty Diesel Engines</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">E.P.A. Backs Stricter Guidelines</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER 8. LEE and ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C; Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency proposes rules that would deeply cut soot, sulfur and smog-forming polluion from diesel engines in construction, farm and other industrial equipment; rules would phase in over 10 years both cleanup of high-sulfur diesel fuel and far stricter emission controls on engines; Bush administration says shift would cost about $1.5 billion a year, which would be more than offset by savings of some $16 billion to $80 billion a year from prolonged lives and avoided health-care costs; Admr Christie Whitman holds threat to public health is clear and costs justified; environmentalists laud proposals, which get muted support from affected industry groups; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed rules yesterday that would deeply cut the soot, sulfur and smog-forming pollution from diesel engines in construction, farm and other industrial equipment.</p>
        <p>Over the next decade, the proposed rules would phase in both a cleanup of the high-sulfur diesel fuel consumed by such engines and far stricter requirements for emissions controls on the engines themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency proposed rules that would deeply cut the smog-forming pollution spewing from diesel engines in nonroad equipment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush administration proposed rules yesterday that would deeply cut the soot, sulfur and smog-forming pollution from diesel engines in construction, farm and other industrial equipment.</p>
        <p>Over the next decade, the proposed rules would phase in both a cleanup of the high-sulfur diesel fuel consumed by such engines and far stricter requirements for emissions controls on the engines themselves.</p>
        <p>Shifting to cleaner diesel for the nonroad fleet would cost about $1.5 billion a year over the next 27 years, but that would be more than offset by savings estimated at $16 billion to $80 billion a year from prolonged lives and avoided health-care costs, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>The proposed changes were lauded by environmentalists often at odds with the Bush administration and received muted support from affected industry groups.</p>
        <p>The rules, proposed by the Environmental Protection Agency, could be adjusted before they start taking effect next spring. But Christie Whitman, the E.P.A. administrator, said the threat to public health was clear and the costs were justified.</p>
        <p>The country's 850,000 bulldozers, tractors, portable generators and other nonroad diesel vehicles are greatly outnumbered by trucks and buses, but because of dirtier fuel and engines they are the dominant mobile source of tiny soot particles that cause thousands of deaths a year, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>''Just one large bulldozer produces 800 pounds of pollution per year -- the equivalent of 26 cars,'' Mrs. Whitman said yesterday at a Washington event to announce the rules.</p>
        <p>The agency estimates that about 30,000 deaths are caused by soot each year and estimates that the proposed standards would, when fully enacted, reduce that number by 9,600 a year.</p>
        <p>Groups representing engine manufacturers, fuel refiners and other businesses affected by the new rules said the changes would be difficult and expensive, but many said reductions in diesel pollution were clearly needed.</p>
        <p>''We must continue the nation's progress towards cleaner fuels with an eye toward maintaining both fuel supply and the health and diversity of the domestic refining industry, which faces tough challenges,'' said Bob Slaughter, the president of the National Petrochemical and Refiners Association.</p>
        <p>The administration, accustomed to sharp criticism from private environmental groups over other environmental policies, yesterday received praise instead.</p>
        <p>''When this becomes law, it will be the biggest public health step since lead was taken out of gasoline more than 20 years ago,'' said Richard Kassel, a senior lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, which has been lobbying for the regulations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kassel and others involved with negotiations largely credited Mrs. Whitman for the scope of the plan, saying she had made curbing diesel pollution a priority since her days as New Jersey's governor.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman had already pushed through rules that would clean the fuels and engines of trucks and buses and a separate program intended to clean up diesel pollution from school buses, which is seen as a health threat to children.</p>
        <p>For nearly a year, lobbyists and experts from both camps met repeatedly with agency officials to suggest changes as details of the draft rules came together.</p>
        <p>People involved with the talks said the nonroad diesel rules emerged with relative ease, particularly when compared with the battles being waged over other environmental issues, like competing plans for cleaning power plants.</p>
        <p>Support for the initiative within the administration went beyond the agency. At the White House Office of Management and Budget, where many environmental standards have gone through months of review and whittling, the standards sailed through in just weeks, Mr. Kassel and others said.</p>
        <p>The Office of Management and Budget, which previously had only reviewed environmental rules after they were drafted, last fall changed to a more active role, meeting with the agency as the rules evolved.</p>
        <p>A senior White House official said the main reason the plan was quickly approved was the clear-cut nature of the hazard.</p>
        <p>''It takes a significant health risk and cuts it dramatically,'' this official said.</p>
        <p>Officials and experts said the rules would have a significant impact. In rural regions, tractors, combines, and other farm equipment produce substantial pollution, while in suburbs and cities, heavy construction equipment is often surrounded by a choking haze.</p>
        <p>The proposed standards would focus on two fronts: cleaning the fuel and the engines. Sulfur in fuel sold for nonroad engines would be reduced from the current level of 3,000 parts per million to 500 parts per million in 2007 and 15 parts per million in 2010. The lower-sulfur fuel would also be required for diesel-powered small boats.</p>
        <p>Sulfur emissions are a significant environmental problem in their own right, helping form some small sooty particles and contributing to acid rain. But sulfur also interferes with catalytic converters and other emissions-controls systems, preventing them from being installed on engines using dirtier fuel. Once the fuels are cleaner, then tighter requirements could come into force for new engines, agency officials said.</p>
        <p>Various rules would apply to engines from 3 to 3,000 horsepower, with the strictest reductions required in those over 75 horsepower.</p>
        <p>By the time the new engine and fuel regulations are fully in force in 2013, soot emissions from these engines will be reduced 95 percent and smog-forming nitrogen oxides emissions will be reduced 90 percent.</p>
        <p>The new engine standards would be phased in through 2013. But given the lag time as older equipment is retired and replaced, the full environmental impact will not be felt until 2030, agency officials said.</p>
        <p>The Diesel Technology Forum, an industry group representing engine manufacturers and fuel suppliers, said that its members faced significant technical and commercial challenges because hundreds of different engine designs and companies would be affected.</p>
        <p>''There are something like 1,763 manufacturers of off-road equipment, compared to 22 or so for on-highway vehicles,'' said Allen Schaeffer, the group's executive director.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman said the decade-long timetable was intended to accommodate industry concerns. ''We recognize the enormous challenges with industry,'' she said. ''We don't want to put anyone out of business.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
