<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DA1530F932A05753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1063" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Russia Freezes Oil Shares; Putin Drops Key Adviser  Prosecutors froze stock worth billions of dollars in Russia's richest company, raising the stakes in their investigation of its imprisoned chief executive. The move came as President Vladimir V. Putin replaced his chief of staff.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hussein Active, U.S. Says  Senior American officials said recent intelligence reports indicated that Saddam Hussein was acting as a catalyst or even a leader in Iraq's armed opposition, probably from a base near Tikrit.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Russia Freezes Oil Shares; Putin Drops Key Adviser  Prosecutors froze stock worth billions of dollars in Russia's richest company, raising the stakes in their investigation of its imprisoned chief executive. The move came as President Vladimir V. Putin replaced his chief of staff.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hussein Active, U.S. Says  Senior American officials said recent intelligence reports indicated that Saddam Hussein was acting as a catalyst or even a leader in Iraq's armed opposition, probably from a base near Tikrit.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.N. Removes Staff From Iraq  Recent explosions and terrorist threats in Baghdad have left the city on edge, and Secretary General Kofi Annan has asked non-Iraqi staff of the U.N. to leave the country.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Iraq Contractors Favored Bush  Executives, employees and political action committees from the 70 companies that got government contracts for work in either Iraq or Afghanistan contributed slightly more than $500,000 to President Bush's 2000 election campaign.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Rice Critical of Clinton  Condoleezza Rice said the Clinton administration had ignored evidence of growing terrorist threats against the United States.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Sharon Under Investigation  Israel's prime minister, Ariel Sharon, was questioned in connection with two possible cases of political corruption involving him and his two sons. Mr. Sharon has denied any wrongdoing and so far no criminal charges have been filed.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Tory Launches Campaign  Michael Howard formally began his campaign to take over Britain's opposition Conservatives and position himself as the sole Tory candidate for the elections for prime minister, which are likely to be held in 2005.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Korean Talks Back On  North Korea said it was ready to enter new negotiations about its nuclear weapons program, but if it finds the terms unfavorable, it could well backtrack once again.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-20</p>
        <p>Justice Department Edited Parts of Diversity Report  An internal report that harshly criticized the Justice Department's diversity efforts was edited so heavily when it was posted on the department's Web site two weeks ago that half of its 186 pages, including the summary, were blacked out.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rain Slows California Fires  Residents of Southern California looked skyward with relief rather than dread for the first time in a week, although fires continued to consume thousands of acres of diseased woodland and tinder-dry brush.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Judicial Nominee Action Stalled  Senate Republicans failed to overcome a filibuster blocking the vote on the nomination of Charles W. Pickering, left, to a federal appeals court seat. Judge Pickering is the fourth of President Bush's judicial candidates to be blocked by Democrats.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Senate Vote on Global Warming  The Senate defeated a bill to combat global warming by restricting the emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping greenhouse gasses, by a vote of 55 to 43.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Suspect Agrees to Guilty Plea  The man suspected of being the Green River killer has agreed to plead guilty next week to the murders of 48 women, in a deal sparing him execution, The Associated Press has learned.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Dean's Position on Gun Control  Howard Dean's position on gun control is posing a problem for him and other Democratic contenders as they struggle with an issue that many say helped cost their party the White House in 2000.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>In J.F.K.'s Car, in Dallas, in '63  Nellie Connally, the last surviving occupant of the car in which president John F. Kennedy was killed, is telling her story in a memoir that grew from notes scrawled out 10 days after the event.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Parking Garage Collapses, Killing 3 in Atlantic City  Five levels of a 10-story parking garage under construction a block off the Boardwalk in Atlantic City collapsed, killing three people and injuring more than 20, the authorities said. One person was missing.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Little Interest in Referendum  The referendum to end party primaries and make party affiliation an afterthought in local races has dominated conversations in the political arena, but there are few signs that voters care much about the issue.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Player in Disease Research  A laboratory at Columbia has helped turn the university's school of public health into a major player in research on the infectious disease outbreaks and bioterror threats that have been the focus of the world's attention in the last few years.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Activity at Trade Center Site  The nearly completed temporary PATH terminal at the World Trade Center is a three-dimensional reminder that before the trade center was anything else -- civic emblem, compass point, mass cemetery -- it was a hub of movement.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-36; E37-46</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Cloned Cows' Milk Deemed Safe  Milk and meat from cloned animals are safe to eat, the Food and Drug Administration has tentatively concluded, a finding that could eventually clear the way for such products to reach supermarket shelves.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Economy Growth Strong  The economy expanded at the fastest rate since 1984 during the three months ended in September, offering hope that the long economic malaise has finally ended.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Enron Executive Admits Guilt  A former chief of two divisions of Enron pleaded guilty to insider trading.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Spitzer Blames the S.E.C.  Eliot Spitzer, the attorney general of New York, is calling for heads to roll at the Securities and Exchange Commission over the mutual fund trading abuses.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Strong Offers Reimbursements  Richard S. Strong said he would reimburse his firm's mutual funds for any losses caused by his personal trades. The move was an effort to ease fallout from charges of improper trading.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Microsoft Wooing Google  Google recently began meeting with bankers to prepare for its initial public offering as it was still exploring a merger with Microsoft.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: New tries for Middle East peace; a crucial case for the Supreme Court; starving children in plain sight; endorsements for the City Council.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E33  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E35  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
