<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ECONOMIC PULSE: The West; California Ups and Downs Ripple in the West</title>
    <meta content="06PULS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/06/national/06PULS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030107T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1454396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Economic Pulse"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arizona</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Silicon Valley (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DD143EF935A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="3000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ECONOMIC PULSE: The West; California Ups and Downs Ripple in the West</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Ups and Downs Ripple in the West</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Calif., Jan. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Latest article in series, Economic Pulse, examines how ups and downs of California's wobbly economy are rippling across West; southern California is faring relatively well, with unemployment below national average, personal income growth outpacing nation and military contractors riding wave of Pentagon and domestic security spending; but San Francisco Bay Area is still reeling from dot-com collapse; skilled and formerly wealthy workers are fleeing to find jobs elsewhere and analysts worry that it could be years before next new thing revitalizes Silicon Valley; one economist expects California to lag US economy, primarily because it is being dragged down by Bay Area; viewed as whole, California accounts for one-sevenths of nation's total output; its huge economy exerts strong gravitational pull on neighboring states; Arizona, Nevada and Hawaii all are heavily dependent on tourism and on California's market for their manufactured goods; when California suffers, they traditionally tend to suffer as well; this time, Arizona is faring slightly better; it offers potential employers lower wages, ample land, fewer taxes and less government regulation than California; photos; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rafael Pineda barely feels California's economic pain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pineda, 18, whose family emigrated from Mexico 11 years ago, has a job as a cashier at Bed Bath and Beyond in fast-growing San Bernardino County. He attends community college and sees a boundless future in the ministry or teaching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>California, which accounts for roughly one-seventh of the nation's total output, reflects the wobbly national economic picture.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rafael Pineda barely feels California's economic pain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pineda, 18, whose family emigrated from Mexico 11 years ago, has a job as a cashier at Bed Bath and Beyond in fast-growing San Bernardino County. He attends community college and sees a boundless future in the ministry or teaching.</p>
        <p>''California is where you can make a name for yourself and make money and be successful in any area you want,'' he said during a lunch break recently. ''I know the state has some problems now, but it can turn around in an instant.''</p>
        <p>About 350 miles north in the San Francisco Bay Area where tens of thousands of refugees from the dot-com collapse have yet to pick up the pieces, the mood is decidedly darker. Just ask Gerrold Kaplan, an Internet pioneer who said he made and then lost most of $500 million when the dot-com bubble burst.</p>
        <p>''I like to joke that I used to be retired,'' he said mordantly. ''Now I'm just unemployed. It's very relaxing.'' He has been out of work since 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pineda and Mr. Kaplan are in many ways emblematic. For California's is a tale of two economies.</p>
        <p>Southern California, particularly the counties south and east of Los Angeles, is faring relatively well, with unemployment below the national average, personal income growth outpacing the nation and military contractors riding a wave of Pentagon and domestic security spending. The film industry set box-office records last year, and consumers took advantage of low interest rates to invest in new homes and automobiles.</p>
        <p>But the San Francisco Bay Area remains mired in a technology slump, with skilled and formerly wealthy workers fleeing to find jobs elsewhere and analysts worried that it could be years before the next new thing revitalizes Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>''It's like two separate countries,'' said Sung Won Sohn, chief economist for Wells Fargo bank.</p>
        <p>''For the time being,'' he said, ''California will lag the U.S. economy, primarily because it's being dragged down by the Bay Area.''</p>
        <p>Viewed as a whole, California, which accounts for roughly one-seventh of the nation's total output, reflects the wobbly national economic picture.</p>
        <p>Employers are investing little and hiring less, waiting for the promised recovery that always seems to be six months away. Consumers, who propped up the economy through much of last year, are cooling off their credit cards. And the state's government, facing a $35 billion budget hole, is preparing to lay off thousands of workers, drastically cut spending and raise taxes.</p>
        <p>As a result, Californians' fabled optimism has taken a sharp blow.</p>
        <p>In early 2001, before the technology crash and the terrorist attacks, 70 percent of California residents said the state was enjoying good economic times. Eighteen months later, that view had turned upside down, with just 20 percent of Californians describing the state as prospering, according to a survey last fall by the Field Institute.</p>
        <p>Ring of Gold</p>
        <p>The brightest spot in the state economy is the ring of fast-growing counties around Los Angeles where Mr. Pineda lives -- San Bernardino, Riverside, Orange and San Diego. Unemployment in these counties ranges from 4 to 5.5 percent, kept low by an expansion in retail and business services, along with the growth of biotechnology companies and a burst of spending on Pentagon research and development. The statewide unemployment rate is 6.4 percent.</p>
        <p>But in Silicon Valley the news is bleak.</p>
        <p>The technology industries in the Bay Area continue to shed jobs, with employment falling by 87,000 people last year. An estimated 40,000 people have left Silicon Valley in the past year in search of work elsewhere. Unemployment in precincts once seen as a model of the new, technological future, has jumped from less than 2 percent in 2000 to nearly 7 percent at the end of this year. In some areas, it is much worse.</p>
        <p>''In my neighborhood, I would personally estimate that there's probably 40 percent unemployment among senior executives,'' said Mr. Kaplan, 50, who lives in Hillsborough, a wealthy enclave south of San Francisco. He has been out of work since his latest company, Egghead.com, crashed in 2001.</p>
        <p>He tries to make light of the problems in his neighborhood, noting that there is a lot of managerial talent on the sidelines of his daughters' soccer league.</p>
        <p>''One of the rituals of the league is that each team has a big banner with the names of the kids,'' Mr. Kaplan said. ''These things have gotten distinctly better because the parents have so much time on their hands. They've become wonderful hand-embroidered pieces of folk art.''</p>
        <p>His black humor does little to disguise the fact that the economic indicators for San Francisco and the area southward to San Jose are almost unrelievedly grim.</p>
        <p>Housing prices have fallen, in some cases by as much as 25 percent over the past two years, but the median home price in the Bay Area is still $540,000. That leaves housing unaffordable to all but about 18 percent of residents. By contrast, 43 percent of working families in Riverside and San Bernardino Counties can afford an average home there, which costs less than $200,000.</p>
        <p>Another measure of the Bay Area's distress is the acres of empty office space.</p>
        <p>In early 2000, at the height of the technology boom, the vacancy rate was less than 2 percent, according to the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco. Today, the figure is approaching 20 percent. The value of commercial construction permits statewide fell 22.5 percent from October 2001 to October 2002.</p>
        <p>No one knows when -- or if -- the turnaround will begin. ''The Bay Area is waiting patiently for that tech bounce-back that may never come,'' said Edward Leamer, director of the Anderson Forecast at the University of California at Los Angeles. ''It has priced itself out of virtually any other economic function.''</p>
        <p>He noted that technology operates in decade-long cycles and that the current slump could last until an innovation comes along to spark another boom -- perhaps in biotechnology or wireless communications. The personal computer, software and the Internet are now mature technologies, unlikely to reignite the region.</p>
        <p>Spinoff Affects Neighbors</p>
        <p>California's huge economy -- it is the fifth or sixth largest in the world, either just ahead of or just behind France, depending on the exchange rate -- exerts a strong gravitational pull on neighboring states.</p>
        <p>Arizona, Nevada and Hawaii all are heavily dependent on tourism and on California's market for their manufactured goods. When California suffers, they traditionally tend to suffer as well.</p>
        <p>This time, however, California's troubles have had some benefits for Arizona, which offers potential employers lower wages, ample land, fewer taxes and less government regulation. And California's 35 million consumers are an easy drive away.</p>
        <p>Officials from Arizona's Department of Commerce have actively sought to lure California businesses to locate or expand in Arizona, with some success. Michele Pino, director of economic development for the state, said 31 companies had moved operations from California to Arizona in the past three years.</p>
        <p>One of those companies is Catalytica Energy Systems, a developer of low-emissions gas turbines for producing electrical power. The company is based in Mountain View, Calif., north of San Jose in the heart of Silicon Valley. But when company officials decided to expand from research into production, they looked outside of California.</p>
        <p>''The economic climate has changed a great deal in California,'' Megan Meloni, manager of investor relations for the company, said. ''When we decided to move into commercial manufacturing, Phoenix offered a more cost-effective way to do that.''</p>
        <p>The new facility, in Gilbert, Ariz., went on line in early 2001, employing 34 people. Catalytica's headquarters and engineering departments remained in Mountain View.</p>
        <p>Over all, Arizona has fared slightly better than the rest of the nation in the current slowdown, but only marginally. Statewide unemployment was 5.8 percent in November, compared with the national rate of 6 percent, but electronics and aerospace are adding jobs.</p>
        <p>Construction is soft because of overbuilding in the late 1990's; the office vacancy rate in Phoenix is higher than in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Nevada is recovering from a downturn in tourism that hit immediately after Sept. 11, 2001. Business travel remains soft. Tourism and gambling revenues are still down, but the number of visitors has been growing slowly as the fears of terrorism diminish.</p>
        <p>''One reason for that is we get a significant amount of visitor traffic by car,'' said Keith Schwer, director of the University of Nevada at Las Vegas's center for business and economic research.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwer described Nevada as ''muddling through'' and hoping for a rebound in the second half of 2003. The only parts of the Nevada economy showing healthy growth are business and personal services and health care, which is not surprising because the state has become one of the nation's hottest retirement havens.</p>
        <p>The greatest risks to Nevada's economy, Mr. Schwer said, are war with Iraq or another terrorist strike. ''As we saw last year and during the first gulf war, that sets off a cocooning effect,'' he said. ''People are afraid to travel and decide to stay home. We're still way off in foreign visitors.''</p>
        <p>Nevada also has serious state budget problems, with a deficit amounting to 10 percent of its annual spending. In the 1980's, Nevada cut homeowners' taxes and raised the state sales tax, making the state dependent on consumption by residents and visitors. That revenue has plunged over the last year and officials are looking for ways to come up with $800 million to balance the state budget over the next two years, Mr. Schwer said.</p>
        <p>The Hawaiian Response</p>
        <p>Hawaii, because of its heavy dependence on tourism, presents a particular challenge. The state has suffered a nearly decade-long slump, largely because of the protracted recession in Japan, whose free-spending tourists enriched Hawaii throughout the 1980's. As the tourists from Asia and the Americas have vacationed closer to home, residents of Hawaii have fled the islands in large numbers looking for work elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Linda Lingle, the newly elected Republican governor of Hawaii, is trying to diversify the islands' economy and lure the refugees back.</p>
        <p>Officially, unemployment in Hawaii is 4 percent. But Ms. Lingle said that number masked a deep economic malaise.</p>
        <p>''More than 100,000 people left Hawaii in the 1990's for the mainland,'' she said in a telephone interview from Honolulu. ''Many of the people who are still here are no longer looking for jobs, so they don't show up in the unemployment numbers.''</p>
        <p>Tourism generates a quarter of the state's income, but it is highly dependent on conditions across the water. Like Nevada, Hawaii experienced a steep drop in tourist arrivals after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks. The visitors are only now starting to come back, according to state statistics. The hotel occupancy rate fell from 76 percent in 2000 to 70 percent in 2001 and it is not expected to be much better in 2002. During the boom years in Japanese tourism in the mid-1980's, occupancy rates reached 80 percent and above.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Lingle said the state had to diversify or forever be subjected to these sharp swings. She said that the island's unique environment offered opportunities to expand in biotechnology, pharmaceuticals, astronomy, ocean sciences, filmmaking and renewable energy. She plans to ask the Legislature to approve tax credits and money to finance a new marine science center to induce businesses to expand in Hawaii.</p>
        <p>She also hopes to loosen state regulation and to dismantle a culture of political cronyism -- a legacy of 40 years of Democratic rule -- which she said had put a stranglehold on growth.</p>
        <p>''Hawaii has a reputation as a place where you have to know someone to get things done,'' she said. ''We have to convince people we're changing and actually make those changes.''</p>
        <p>The Business of War</p>
        <p>While the possibility of war poses a threat to tourism-based economies like those of Hawaii and Nevada, it could benefit California's military and aerospace contractors.</p>
        <p>The region's military complex suffered enormously a decade ago when the cold war ended, losing 137,000 high-paying jobs in California alone. The cuts caused a slump that lasted through the first half of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>But the biggest defense buildup since the Reagan administration has given the weapons business new life. Projects such as the missile defense shield and the Joint Strike Fighter are expected to create jobs and pour billions of dollars into Northrop Grumman, Lockheed Martin, Honeywell, Boeing and scores of subcontractors.</p>
        <p>''This spending could not have come to Southern California at a more opportune time,'' Mr. Sohn, the Wells Fargo economist, wrote recently. ''Technology companies that were part of the dot-come boom are now switching gears to try and get a piece of the growing national defense pie.''</p>
        <p>Another staple of the California economy, agriculture, has been blessed and cursed with several good growing seasons. Production is up, but prices are falling for many commodity crops. Bulk wine grapes, for example, are selling for $65 a ton in the spot market, compared with more than $200 two years ago. The glut means great bargains at the supermarket for consumers, but growers are suffering.</p>
        <p>''There is a blessed overabundance,'' Karen Ross, president of the California Association of Winegrape Growers, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross said lower prices for grapes allowed California wineries to compete on more favorable terms with Australia, Chile and South Africa for low-shelf wine buyers, those looking for bottles in the $6 to $10 range.</p>
        <p>The motion picture industry set a box office record last year, selling more than $9 billion worth of tickets. Television is enjoying a modest rebound in advertising revenue. Theme parks are struggling to attract visitors, but attendance is up compared with the immediate post-9/11 period.</p>
        <p>One business that seems utterly immune to the vagaries of the broader economy is pornography, which is centered in the San Fernando Valley. It may be semi-subterranean, but it generates an estimated $4 billion to $10 billion a year and employs thousands of workers, rain or shine.</p>
        <p>''Adult entertainment is doing well, from all we've heard,'' an economist at the Los Angeles Economic Development Corporation, Jack Kyser, said. ''You can't really measure it because state employment data captures only about a half to a quarter of people employed in the industry. So many of the people involved in that business are independent contractors.''</p>
        <p>Budget.com</p>
        <p>One of the great uncertainties in California as the new year begins is how state officials will address a budget shortfall of $35 billion over the next 18 months. The state has used most of the one-time gimmicks available to it -- like borrowing against payments under the nationwide settlement with tobacco companies -- and is now being forced to measure virtually every state operation for deep cuts.</p>
        <p>California's fiscal distress is largely related to the steep drop in revenues from taxes on capital gains and stock options from the technology boom. The state's take from such taxes plunged from $17 billion in 2000 to less than $5 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan, the Internet pioneer, said that at the peak of his earnings in the late 1990's he was paying the state more than $5 million a year in taxes. Now the state won't get a penny from him.</p>
        <p>''My adjusted gross income this year is negative,'' he said. ''I will pay no taxes, and rightfully so.''</p>
        <p>Businesses and consumers are bracing for tax increases to make up part of the shortfall, and some economists say they fear that higher taxes will make it harder for California, which already has a reputation as antibusiness, to attract new employers.</p>
        <p>Yet despite all of the problems, millions still consider California a golden land. The state's population continues to grow at a rate of 1.5 percent a year through boom and bust, and entrepreneurs still fantasize about striking it rich in the mother lode of American markets. McDonald's was inspired by a hamburger stand in San Bernardino. Hewlett-Packard was born in a garage in Palo Alto.</p>
        <p>Siua Taufa, 50, who moved here 25 years ago from the Pacific island of Tonga, is a supervisor in an Ontario distribution center for a women's clothing chain. His dream is to start a warehousing operation of his own, taking advantage of the rapid growth of the so-called Inland Empire east of Los Angeles and the area's close proximity to Mexico.</p>
        <p>''I'm doing everything I can to survive, but I'm optimistic,'' Mr. Taufa said.</p>
        <p>When asked if he thought California would soon emerge from its current slowdown, he looked briefly at his wife, Nandy, and said, ''That's a very hard question to answer, but we're hoping for the best.''</p>
        <p>Economic Pulse  Correction:  January 7, 2003, Tuesday  A front-page article yesterday about California's economy misspelled the given name of a former technology executive who has been unemployed for months. He is Jerrold Kaplan, not Gerrold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 7, 2003, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about California's economy misspelled the given name of a former technology executive who has been unemployed for months. He is Jerrold Kaplan, not Gerrold.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
