<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tony Blair's Troubles</title>
    <meta content="07THU1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/07/opinion/07THU1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6D61631F934A3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tony Blair's Troubles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tony Blair's Troubles</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain has long been America's closest ally. But more than any previous British prime minister, Tony Blair has made himself a crucial factor in Washington's foreign policy debates. For Americans unwilling to accept the White House's flimsily backed assertions of imminent danger from Iraq, Mr. Blair offered his supposedly independent intelligence dossiers. For those unswayed by the administration's belligerent rhetoric, Mr. Blair stepped forth with a mellifluous moral summons to action. When Washington appeared most vulnerable to charges of unilateralism and bypassing the United Nations Security Council, there was Mr. Blair, providing living proof that the United States didn't stand alone. Polls found that Mr. Blair was the international leader Americans respected most, at times ranking him higher than Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The White House therefore has every reason to be concerned about the British prime minister's growing credibility problems at home. Mr. Blair's grip on office doesn't seem threatened. But his once legendary ability to sway public opinion has taken a large, and largely self-inflicted, hit. The next time Washington needs to borrow some of his credibility to broaden domestic support for its international policies, he may have little to spare. We credit the sincerity of Mr. Blair's beliefs, but are troubled by the unworthy, and ultimately counterproductive, ways he used to advance them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British Prime Minister was America's friend in need, but he would do well to step out of Bush's shadow now and repair some of his damaged credibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Britain has long been America's closest ally. But more than any previous British prime minister, Tony Blair has made himself a crucial factor in Washington's foreign policy debates. For Americans unwilling to accept the White House's flimsily backed assertions of imminent danger from Iraq, Mr. Blair offered his supposedly independent intelligence dossiers. For those unswayed by the administration's belligerent rhetoric, Mr. Blair stepped forth with a mellifluous moral summons to action. When Washington appeared most vulnerable to charges of unilateralism and bypassing the United Nations Security Council, there was Mr. Blair, providing living proof that the United States didn't stand alone. Polls found that Mr. Blair was the international leader Americans respected most, at times ranking him higher than Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The White House therefore has every reason to be concerned about the British prime minister's growing credibility problems at home. Mr. Blair's grip on office doesn't seem threatened. But his once legendary ability to sway public opinion has taken a large, and largely self-inflicted, hit. The next time Washington needs to borrow some of his credibility to broaden domestic support for its international policies, he may have little to spare. We credit the sincerity of Mr. Blair's beliefs, but are troubled by the unworthy, and ultimately counterproductive, ways he used to advance them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair is still admired in America. But polls show that most British voters no longer trust him to level with them. Some of his government's prewar intelligence claims about Iraq have been exposed as unsubstantiated. None of the unconventional weapons cited by the government have yet been found. Postwar problems have been worse than predicted.</p>
        <p>Most damaging has been a nasty scrap with the BBC over a story claiming that Mr. Blair's spokesman ''sexed up'' intelligence findings about how quickly Iraq could start firing its chemical and biological weapons. The underlying facts remain in dispute, but the crisis deepened after last month's suicide of David Kelly, a Defense Ministry weapons expert the Blair government identified as the BBC's likely source. A judicial inquiry is now under way into the circumstances behind Mr. Kelly's suicide.</p>
        <p>Depending on the inquiry's outcome and future developments in Iraq, Mr. Blair's credit could begin to rebound. He can make that more likely by distancing himself from American-style spin operations. He could also more openly challenge Washington on a number of important issues on which his views are known to diverge from Mr. Bush's. These include the need for a wider United Nations role in Iraq, the urgency of international action on global warming and the moral imperative of curbing the American and European farm subsidies that condemn developing countries to poverty.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
