<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Voluntary Pacts to Curb Greenhouse Gases</title>
    <meta content="Y13ENV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/13/politics/13ENVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Hexafluoride</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perfluorocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Jennifer 8</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources Defense Council</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D7173AF930A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Voluntary Pacts to Curb Greenhouse Gases</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Voluntary Pacts Reached to Curb Greenhouse Gases</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER 8. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush administration announces several modest agreements with number of industries for voluntary controls on emissions of gases linked to global warming; seeks to stave off pending state and federal proposals for mandatory ceilings; environmental groups and Democrats seize upon limited curbs as evidence that voluntary policies will not produce substantive results; critics note that many of announced emissions targets are pegged to 'intensity,' which is defined as amount of such gases per unit of economic production, rather than absolute volume emissions; opponents of regulation are also critical, seeing voluntary policies as precursors for mandatory ceilings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Administration officials announced several modest agreements with a number of industries today for voluntary controls on emissions of gases linked to global warming. The agreements, a result of aggressive meetings with industry executives, are an effort to stave off pending state and federal proposals for mandatory ceilings.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups and Democrats have seized upon the limited curbs as evidence that voluntary policies will not produce substantive results.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Administration officials announced modest agreements with several industries to voluntarily control the emissions of greenhouse gas linked to global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Administration officials announced several modest agreements with a number of industries today for voluntary controls on emissions of gases linked to global warming. The agreements, a result of aggressive meetings with industry executives, are an effort to stave off pending state and federal proposals for mandatory ceilings.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups and Democrats have seized upon the limited curbs as evidence that voluntary policies will not produce substantive results.</p>
        <p>The industry commitments ended up being less substantive than the White House first sought, which is a reason the announcement, originally scheduled for the White House last week, ended up taking place in the Department of Energy's cafeteria with cabinet members, conservation groups and industry representatives said.</p>
        <p>Some industries have promised to curb their output of heat-trapping gases, which include carbon dioxide, sulfur hexafluoride and perfluorocarbon. Among the 12 major industrial sectors that joined in the announcement are electrical utilities, petroleum, mining, steel, semiconductors and automobiles.</p>
        <p>Critics note, however, that many of the announced emissions targets are pegged to ''intensity,'' which is defined as the amount of such gases per unit of economic production, rather than the absolute volume emissions. Most emissions regulations are pegged to net output. In the case of the Kyoto Protocols, the international pact on global warming, they are pegged to actual reductions compared with 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>''It's an accounting trick in our view,'' said Dan Lashof, the science director at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group. ''Any pollution pegged to economic activity is unprecedented and unwarranted.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of regulation were also critical, but for another reason. They see the voluntary policies as precursors for mandatory ceilings.</p>
        <p>''It's incoherent,'' said Myron Ebell, a climate expert at the Competitive Enterprise Institute, which is an advocate for free markets. ''It's like saying, 'We're opposed to capital punishment, but don't worry about the gallows we have built in the front yard.' ''</p>
        <p>Utilities, which account for about 40 percent of United States emissions of heat-trapping gases, pledged to reduce their intensity by 3 percent to 5 percent. The chemical industry agreed to reduce intensity of the gases by 18 percent in 2012, as compared with 1990 levels. The automobile industry pledged reductions in the intensity of its manufacturing emission rates but not the vehicle emission rates by at least 10 percent by 2012 compared with 2002.</p>
        <p>Last year, President Bush announced that he wanted to reduce the amount of such gases per unit of gross domestic product by 18 percent. Critics say using the overall economy as a measure of gas emissions is deceptive because the parts of the economy that are growing tend to be service sectors, where emissions are less of a problem.</p>
        <p>Administration officials concede that the overall amount of greenhouse gas emissions is not likely to fall within the next decade.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to get smaller immediately,'' said Christie Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>But Mrs. Whitman said industries would get the capital to invest in more environment-friendly technologies. ''As they develop the technology, they will in fact see an actual reduction,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The agreements are part of the White House's broader campaign to highlight President Bush's environmental initiatives, an area where polls show him politically vulnerable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
