<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Florida Communities, in Indiana</title>
    <meta content="18INDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/18/realestate/luxury/18INDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030725T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1505260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tryon Farm (Ind)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beachwalk (Ind)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indiana</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Celebration (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seaside (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodkin, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Seaside</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Indiana</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DD133CF93BA25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Florida Communities, in Indiana</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Florida Communities, in Indiana</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS RODKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rodkin, Dennis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on communities of Tryon Farm and Beachwalk on southeast edge of Lake Michigan in Indiana, which have been modeled after Disney's planned communities of Celebration and Seaside, both in Florida; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Indiana coastline -- yes, there is such a thing -- is a precious commodity, just 40 miles skirting the extreme southeast edge of Lake Michigan, much of it thick with industrial sites, steel mills and a nuclear power plant, along with long stretches of towering sand dunes.</p>
        <p>Contrast that with the sweeping, resort-dotted shorelines of nearby Michigan and Wisconsin, and even the prime lakefront property of Illinois, north of Chicago, and you quickly understand why some Indiana homeowners want to make the most of what they have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former auto manufacturing hub about 50 miles east of Chicago makes you feel as if you've been transported to Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Indiana coastline -- yes, there is such a thing -- is a precious commodity, just 40 miles skirting the extreme southeast edge of Lake Michigan, much of it thick with industrial sites, steel mills and a nuclear power plant, along with long stretches of towering sand dunes.</p>
        <p>Contrast that with the sweeping, resort-dotted shorelines of nearby Michigan and Wisconsin, and even the prime lakefront property of Illinois, north of Chicago, and you quickly understand why some Indiana homeowners want to make the most of what they have.</p>
        <p>So maybe it shouldn't be that much of a surprise to come across the communities of Tryon Farm and Beachwalk, both built in the shadow of Michigan City -- a former auto manufacturing hub about 50 miles east of Chicago -- and feel as if you've been transported to Florida.</p>
        <p>The illusion is deliberate. That's because the models for these towns can, in fact, be found in the Sunshine State: Celebration, a Disney-developed planned community located just outside Orlando, and Seaside, a picture-pretty postcard of a Gulf Coast town on the Florida Panhandle that was the setting for the film ''The Truman Show.'' Both are prime examples of what has been called New Urbanist architecture -- an attempt to give modern developments the feeling of small-town life through strict building codes.</p>
        <p>Though they share many similarities, Tryon Farm and Beachwalk are not mirror images of each other, and, in fact, are the products of two different Chicago developers. Tryon Farm is probably best described as a cross between pastoral and contemporary, its eco-friendly architecture built to sit lightly among the prairies, pastures and woods of the area. Beachwalk looks back to an era of Victorian seaside villages with candy-colored houses lining sandy streets just a dune and a two-lane road away from Lake Michigan.</p>
        <p>At Beachwalk, Brian and Lisa Eberhart savor the six-minute walk from their weekend cottage to the wide, serene Lake Michigan beach. The cottages that line the narrow street are painted lemon and mint and lilac and cantaloupe, each with its own white picket fence and some with silvery metal roofs. Beachwalk's name is appropriate. Only one of the houses actually faces Lake Michigan; the development is on the inland side of Michigan City's Lake Shore Drive. Residents get to the beach via a boardwalk that starts at Lake Shore Drive, across from Beachwalk's entrance, and then runs about 500 feet through the dunes to the beach.</p>
        <p>Beachwalk is an idealized old-timey seashore community where, as Brian Eberhart, an orthodontist from Mishawaka, Ind., put it, ''Every house has a front porch and every front porch has people sitting out waving to you as you go by.'' Mr. Eberhart, the father of 11-year-old Alayna and 9-year-old Caroline, said that Beachwalk was ''a place where you can let the kids roam a little more freely than you maybe allow them at home.''</p>
        <p>Tryon Farm, a 170-acre former dairy farm, is about a mile from the beach and consists of single-family and attached houses ranging from 400 to 3,500 square feet. Its developers, Ed and Eve Noonan, call the project a ''conservation community,'' meaning that it has been built with an eye toward preserving the land. Houses are clustered on small lots; large stretches of open space are shared by the homeowners. Lawns and hard-surface roads are virtually nonexistent, reducing the use of lawn chemicals and road salt and fostering native plants and natural drainage instead of relying on curbs and gutters. Still in the planning stages is a group of low-slung houses to be built with wildflower-sod roofs to mimic the terrain.</p>
        <p>In 2001, Liz Reyes, the director of a housing advocacy group in Chicago, bought a home in Tryon -- three rooms stacked atop one another, the center of three units in a four-story building designed to look like a barn. She said that the setting was quite different from the one she left behind on the gritty South Side of Chicago.</p>
        <p>''I can be outside every day, walking around the wetland and the other open land, and I meet all the neighbors casually,'' Ms. Reyes said. ''We work in the garden together and just meet up when we're out for a walk. When I lived in Chicago, in a big building, I didn't even know the people in the apartment next to mine.''</p>
        <p>Prices in Tryon Farm range from $118,000, for an attached two-story house of less than 1,000 square feet, to a little more than $400,000 for a contemporary wood-sided 2,200-square-foot house in a wooded setting at the edge of a fallow cornfield.</p>
        <p>Beachwalk is more expensive. A new 2,000-square-foot house with four or five bedrooms and assorted decks and screened porches is $400,000. The high end is about $700,000, which recently was paid for a 4,500-square-foot L-shaped house with 360-degree views from its site atop a high dune. Tryon Farm's 170 acres now have only 28 houses and condominiums; a total of 150 is planned.</p>
        <p>Both the prices and the houses used to be smaller at Beachwalk. (Eighty-four houses have been built on its 160 acres; plans call for the total to reach 300.) Back in the early 1990's, the developer, Tom Moss, envisioned the former sand mine as a cluster of small, homey cottages used largely by their owners.</p>
        <p>But renting the houses out on a weekly basis became popular, so there has been a shift toward big group-worthy houses that can accommodate an extended family of a dozen or 15 people. They still look like Victorian beach houses, but they are just two to three times the size of the first cottages, with as many as seven bedrooms, and kitchens and living rooms big enough to accommodate two or three families at a time.</p>
        <p>Tryon Farm doesn't have much of a weekly rental market; residents there are split almost evenly between full-timers and weekenders.</p>
        <p>Both projects' developers set out to build more than mere summer homes. True to New Urbanist principles, both Mr. Moss and the Noonans tried to cultivate a community atmosphere by putting houses close together, giving them porches and other social spaces out front, and generally encouraging people to walk around their neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>''A lot of second homes are about family closeness, which is nice,'' Mr. Moss said. ''But in addition you ought to be able to go outside and interact with the community, not be trapped inside your own property line.''</p>
        <p>Residents in both communities say that when they arrive, the outer world tends to disappear. ''We don't leave much, because we're here to enjoy what's right here,'' Ms. Reyes said. ''We stop and talk on the walking paths, see each other in the garden, and make big dinners together in groups.''</p>
        <p>HAVENS  Correction:  July 25, 2003, Friday  An article last Friday about new communities on the Indiana shore of Lake Michigan misstated the industrial history of Michigan City, Ind. It once made railroad cars, not automobiles. The article also incorrectly described a power plant in the area. It uses fossil fuels, not nuclear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 25, 2003, Friday</p>
        <p>An article last Friday about new communities on the Indiana shore of Lake Michigan misstated the industrial history of Michigan City, Ind. It once made railroad cars, not automobiles. The article also incorrectly described a power plant in the area. It uses fossil fuels, not nuclear.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
