<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is New York Shivering, Or Sniveling?; In Historical Context, This Snap's Just Chilly</title>
    <meta content="26COLD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/26/nyregion/26COLD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1459524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Janny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DF1539F935A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1061" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is New York Shivering, Or Sniveling?; In Historical Context, This Snap's Just Chilly</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is New York Shivering, or Sniveling?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Yorkers may be shivering during current cold snap, but it is far from coldest January on record; average temperature is 29 degrees; colder Januaries are on record and longer periods of consecutive bone-chilling days were recorded in 1961 and 2000; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>And now a few counterintuitive facts about our little cold snap:</p>
        <p>As of late last week, January 2003 was only the 36th coldest January on record for New York City. Averaging 29 degrees, this January has been downright balmy compared with, say, January 1918, when the average was 21.7 degrees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With not a single low temperature this month setting a record, January's cold snap can only be called slightly chilly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>And now a few counterintuitive facts about our little cold snap:</p>
        <p>As of late last week, January 2003 was only the 36th coldest January on record for New York City. Averaging 29 degrees, this January has been downright balmy compared with, say, January 1918, when the average was 21.7 degrees.</p>
        <p>Not a single low temperature has set a record. The lowest temperature so far this month was an un-record-shattering 7 degrees on Jan. 18 in Central Park. That would not be a record for any day in Januaries past.</p>
        <p>Nor has this string of chilly days been the longest on record in New York City. The temperature has not risen above freezing since Jan. 13, but that stretch of days falls short not only of the 16-day record set in 1961 but also of a 13-day run logged as recently as winter 2000. And this year's snap was expected to end this weekend, with temperatures climbing in the high 30's today.</p>
        <p>Those sobering truths, courtesy of meteorologists at Pennsylvania State University, seem to have escaped the notice of New Yorkers in recent days. Instead, they have busily hung on the histrionics of broadcast weatherpeople, comparing their travails to those of characters in Jack London stories and loudly indulging in the kind of banal weather jabber one might once have assumed they left their smaller towns to escape.</p>
        <p>What gives?</p>
        <p>New Yorkers pride themselves on their ability to flourish in one of the more grueling urban environments in the world. Some are also famous for a supposedly contrarian frame of mind. But when the temperature drops below freezing and newscasters start piling up adjectival phrases like ''bone chilling,'' legions of New Yorkers suddenly fall apart.</p>
        <p>Who has not seen them and heard them hunting down long underwear as though they were stockpiling protein bars for the apocalypse, threatening in exasperation to leave the country, parroting dubious wind chill factors and ''real feel'' statistics from all-news radio, and commiserating boisterously with strangers for whom they would not usually have the time of day?</p>
        <p>''It's like all of a sudden people forgot that it's supposed to be cold in winter,'' said Danny Koch, who runs the Town Shop, a lingerie store on the Upper West Side of Manhattan that carries long underwear. ''When I was a kid, the Hudson River used to freeze over every other year or so. Now, it's like we're living in some tropical climate: 'Can you believe . . . ?' ''</p>
        <p>True, it has been a couple of years since New York City was this cold for this long. The last two winters were mild, memories are short and people have gotten used to the idea of global warming. And New York's population is transient: Tens of thousands of recent arrivals were not even here for the last extended freeze, the one in 2000.</p>
        <p>But even many longer-term residents appear to be ill equipped, sartorially and psychically, for cold weather. They package their stroller-bound children in plastic, like cutlets in the fridge; then they themselves sally forth without so much as a hat. Some New Yorkers are too hip for L. L. Bean, too preoccupied to use a zipper. Some choose a cigarette for warmth.</p>
        <p>''People in New York spend a lot of money on things that have to be hidden when it's cold,'' said Mitchell L. Moss, director of the Taub Urban Research Center at New York University. ''Like their hair, their earrings, their makeup. New York is a very visual city. Cold weather eliminates that part of your life, because you have to cover up all the things you're promoting about yourself.''</p>
        <p>As Professor Moss sees it, New York is a pedestrian city, which leaves New Yorkers exposed to the elements in a way that the denizens of automobile-oriented cities are not. In addition, he says, tall buildings create wind tunnels. ''The urban construction patterns of New York City aggravate the cold air and make it even more difficult to maneuver.''</p>
        <p>Without snow, cold weather is especially hard on New Yorkers, Professor Moss suggests. A snowstorm offers an aesthetic thrill and an opportunity for heroics. Without snow, cold weather serves up neither. It is also antithetical to New York's culture of constantly chatting, he said. Cold inhibits talk.</p>
        <p>''There's no joy in the cold here,'' Professor Moss said. ''Cold weather is something you endure. It's not something you have to conquer. We're energized by hurdles. But the cold is just a drain on our energies.''</p>
        <p>New York City has an illustrious weather history. In January 1857, the coldest month of the 19th century, Long Island Sound was icebound for 30 days, a weather historian, David M. Ludlum, wrote in The Encyclopedia of the City of New York. Twelve inches of snow fell on Jan. 18 and 19 that year. Temperatures hovered at zero degrees before dropping on Jan. 24 to minus 9.</p>
        <p>More recently, in the winter of 1993-4, snow and ice remained on the ground for more than two months. Snowfall totaled 53.4 inches and the average temperature in January was 5.9 degrees below normal.</p>
        <p>It helps to remember that even those statistics are unimpressive to people in places like International Falls, Minn., proud holder of the title ''The Icebox of the Nation.'' There, insulated coveralls are all the rage. Tom Shilts, the director of the public library , says schoolchildren play outside during recess until the wind chill factor is minus 30.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've hit zero since maybe last weekend,'' Mr. Shilts said in a telephone interview late last week on a day when he said the temperature that morning had been minus 18. ''It's not gigantic news, no. It's cold out. But it's not like anybody's keeping track.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
