<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Attacked for Letting States Lead on Climate</title>
    <meta content="11CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/11/science/11CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1542199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milan (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Jennifer 8</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, Harlan L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDE173CF932A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Attacked for Letting States Lead on Climate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">White House Attacked for Letting States Lead on Climate</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN and JENNIFER 8. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C; Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>States that have taken action to curb emissions of heat-trapping gases criticize Bush administration officials for citing those efforts at global warming talks in Milan as evidence of American resolve on issue; say their efforts are no substitute for federal action; criticize Harlan L Watson, Bush administration's chief climate negotiator at talks, taking credit for their actions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several times at the talks now going on in Milan over a global warming treaty, Bush administration officials have portrayed states' actions to curb heat-trapping gases as evidence of American resolve.</p>
        <p>But in this country, officials in many of those same states are strongly criticizing the administration's statements, saying their efforts are no substitute for federal action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>White House officials have praised states actions to curb heat-trapping gases, but states are saying their efforts are no substitute for federal action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several times at the talks now going on in Milan over a global warming treaty, Bush administration officials have portrayed states' actions to curb heat-trapping gases as evidence of American resolve.</p>
        <p>But in this country, officials in many of those same states are strongly criticizing the administration's statements, saying their efforts are no substitute for federal action.</p>
        <p>The focus of the criticism is a speech in Milan last Thursday by Dr. Harlan L. Watson, the administration's chief climate negotiator. Listing a variety of initiatives begun by states and communities, Dr. Watson said they were like ''laboratories where new and creative ideas and methods can be applied and shared with others and inform federal policy, a truly bottom-up approach to addressing global climate change.''</p>
        <p>But in Washington State, Gov. Gary Locke, a Democrat, said the administration was using state initiatives as cover for its own inaction.</p>
        <p>''The states are taking action for one simple reason: because the federal government is not,'' Mr. Locke said. ''For the White House to say it is looking for leadership from the states is just an excuse to delay and procrastinate. We are limited in what the states can do. We need a national policy to address global warming.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials and some industry groups say Mr. Watson had it just right, that having the states take the lead is in the best federalist tradition.</p>
        <p>Still, even some groups often critical of environmental regulations said the speech would cause trouble for the administration at home.</p>
        <p>''It's not surprising that the administration, when it goes in front of an international body like this, is going to brag about all the initiatives undertaken on global warming at the state level,'' said Jerry Taylor, director of natural resources studies for the libertarian Cato Institute. ''What's the alternative? To go and say we're taking no significant steps and don't intend to in the near future?''</p>
        <p>The speech's text is at www.state .gov/g/oes/rls/rm/2003/26894.htm.</p>
        <p>Some Republican governors are distancing themselves from the administration's Milan position without directly criticizing it.</p>
        <p>''They have not yet taken climate change on as a real issue and developed policies,'' said a senior aide to one such governor, George E. Pataki of New York. ''We are going to keep pushing them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has led an effort to institute a 2005 regional cap for heat-trapping emissions for states from Maryland to Maine, and is pursuing New York legislation similar to California's new law requiring curbs in such emissions from cars. Mr. Pataki also supports a federal limit on emissions of carbon dioxide, the dominant heat-trapping gas, from power plants as part of a broader cleanup of the plants.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration opposes mandatory limits on the gases and state efforts to curtail such emissions from cars. None of Mr. Pataki's proposals involving mandatory curbs were among the projects described by Dr. Watson, who focused on voluntary plans like inventories of the gases.</p>
        <p>Erin M. Crotty, Mr. Pataki's environment commissioner, declined yesterday to discuss the Bush administration's position. ''I'll just say from our perspective New York will continue to be a leader,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Milan meeting, which ends tomorrow, is intended to gauge countries' progress under the 1992 Framework Convention on Climate Change, and to hash out details of the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, an amendment to the original pact requiring cuts in gas emissions by industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>The 1992 treaty calls for voluntary action to avoid ''dangerous'' human interference with the climate. President Bush has said he intends to adhere to that treaty, but has rejected the Kyoto pact because it does not apply to China and other developing countries and because he says it could hurt the nation's economy. Last week, Russia also indicated that it would reject the treaty.</p>
        <p>The American delegation in Milan has faced withering criticism throughout the meeting for its position on the Kyoto treaty, and American officials said that Dr. Watson's comments were intended to illustrate that the country was doing things now to deal with warming.</p>
        <p>''We're continually getting criticized that we're not doing anything practically at any level except pie-in-the-sky far-out research stuff which won't have any near-term impact,'' an American representative at the meeting said.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Dr. Watson said his statement was meant to reflect that ''there is a broad effort going on in the United States on many levels to address global climate change.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Watson, a physicist, heads a National Security Council committee on climate policy and has participated in international climate talks for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>Among domestic climate initiatives he described in Milan were programs in 13 states requiring utilities to produce increasing amounts of power using nonpolluting sources like the wind and the sun. President Bush signed one such program into law as governor of Texas.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, environmental groups pointed out that the administration had successfully sought to exclude similar federal standards from its energy bill, which fell short of passage last month.</p>
        <p>Many officials and private groups working on climate policy argue that scattered state and local actions are not an effective way to deal with gases, like carbon dioxide, that flow every time a fossil fuel is burned, stay aloft for up to a century and drift throughout the atmosphere. A dozen states and three cities recently filed suit against the administration in an effort to compel it to regulate greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants a situation where there are 50 different states dealing with climate on their own,'' said Joel Levin, the vice president for business development of the California Climate Action Registry. This nonprofit group, created under state legislation, enlists companies to tally and register their emissions of greenhouse gases, a prelude to cutting emissions and getting credit for the change.</p>
        <p>''It's fine that action starts at the state level, but it can't stay that way indefinitely,'' Mr. Levin said. ''It's a global issue. The thing about CO2  is it's not a local problem. The CO2  emitted in Los Angeles has just as much impact in Bangladesh as in L.A. That's why people are trying to address it on a global level.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
