<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poisoned by Exhaust Fumes, Nascar's Mast Faces Life Minus Cars</title>
    <meta content="Y02AUT$18" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/02/sports/othersports/02AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mast, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Stock Car Auto Racing</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mast, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DC1238F931A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poisoned by Exhaust Fumes, Nascar's Mast Faces Life Minus Cars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Exhaust Fumes Force a Driver Into Retirement</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rick Mast is first and only race car driver to publicly announce he has been poisoned by carbon monoxide as result of racing, forcing him out of profession; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rick Mast, a stock-car driver who has probably attracted as much national attention in the last two weeks as he did in his 15-year Nascar career, has gone home to Rockbridge Baths, Va., and is figuring out what to do with the rest of his life.</p>
        <p>He turns 46 in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rick Mast became the first driver in the 54-year history of Nascar to say he was retiring because of acute and chronic carbon monoxide poisoning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rick Mast, a stock-car driver who has probably attracted as much national attention in the last two weeks as he did in his 15-year Nascar career, has gone home to Rockbridge Baths, Va., and is figuring out what to do with the rest of his life.</p>
        <p>He turns 46 in March.</p>
        <p>''Some days,'' he said pleasantly in a telephone interview last week, ''are better than others.''</p>
        <p>Mast gained fame Jan. 22 for becoming the first driver in the 54-year history of Nascar to say he was retiring because of acute and chronic carbon monoxide poisoning.</p>
        <p>Too much exposure to exhaust makes him sick. As other drivers have begun preparing for the Daytona 500 on Feb. 16, the awaited Winston Cup season opener, the illness has forced Mast to look for something far from his first love, cars and engines.</p>
        <p>He compares the feeling to having food poisoning or, as he said, ''the worst hangover you've ever had in your life.'' He tried mowing his grass this summer, fell ill 30 minutes later, and was laid up for four or five days.</p>
        <p>Mast was a guest of honor at a Labor Day parade near his home and got sick from riding behind another car. In December, he thought he could handle toying around with four-wheelers in his shed. He got sick again.</p>
        <p>Mast, who won more than $9 million but no races in 364 Winston Cup starts, had stopped driving in May because of what was then called an undisclosed illness. Rumors tend to hurtle around Winston Cup garages, and it was whispered that Mast was poisoned.</p>
        <p>A series of at least 10 tests confirmed it, but Mast did not make his affliction public until late last month at a news conference at a hotel in Charlotte, N.C. Gary Nelson, the managing director of competition for Nascar, joined Mast.</p>
        <p>''We felt it was time for us to confirm that we've got testing under way,'' Nelson said last week from his office in Concord, N.C.</p>
        <p>Mast's announcement caused a commotion outside the sport as well. Mast said he heard that the radio broadcaster Paul Harvey talked about him and that a newspaper in Jamaica ran a news story about him.</p>
        <p>Referring to other drivers, Mast said: ''It makes all those guys think, 'If it could happen to Rick, it could happen to me.' ''</p>
        <p>The response from other drivers, while sympathetic, has generally been more staid, and apparently with good reason. Rides are hard to get, especially in the competitive Winston Cup series. No one wants to be labeled as a sissy.</p>
        <p>''I think drivers sometimes try to ignore when someone is hurt or having problems,'' Jeff Burton, another Winston Cup driver from Virginia, said. ''They try to ignore it because that makes it go away.''</p>
        <p>Mast said: ''I know a lot of my buddies are going through symptoms the same as me, and they're a whole lot younger than I am.''</p>
        <p>He did not name names. Later, he said: ''People say it's a macho sport. It's not really a macho sport, but the drivers do try to protect their territory.''</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide adds to the mystery. It is a tasteless, odorless, colorless gas. The symptoms of carbon monoxide poisoning -- severe headaches, nausea, dizziness, confusion -- are not unlike symptoms of other ailments.</p>
        <p>''People get headaches every day,'' Nelson said.</p>
        <p>Although Nelson said physicians retained by Nascar are still not sure exactly how prevalent carbon monoxide poisoning is, it is certainly one of many risks in a dangerous sport. Exhaust can leak into the cockpit of a car that has been damaged in a wreck.</p>
        <p>And some drivers may be more susceptible to poisoning than others. Ken Schrader, 47, who has driven a Winston Cup car since 1984, owns a racetrack and has raced almost anything with wheels, said Mast's symptoms sound unfamiliar to him.</p>
        <p>''It just doesn't affect me,'' Schrader said. ''Mondays after a race I feel like I've been hit by a baseball bat'' -- because of the physical pounding a driver takes -- ''but I've had no ill effects from the heat and carbon monoxide.''</p>
        <p>Mast has been around engines most of his life. He raced for the first time at 16, in a 1957 Chevrolet at two speedways near his home.</p>
        <p>He remembers working on cars, with their engines on -- in garages with the doors and windows closed. Mast thinks the fumes had a cumulative effect, though he has no way to be sure.</p>
        <p>''The problem with this stuff is that it's pretty obscure and pretty rare,'' Mast said. ''There's not a lot of data out there about it.''</p>
        <p>A racecar, particularly the driver's compartment, is built to withstand punishment. But the sealed crash panels between the engine and the cockpit can be damaged, and toxic fumes can leak inside a car, even though it is supposed to be well ventilated.</p>
        <p>Tony Stewart, the defending Winston Cup champion, was said to be woozy and in need of oxygen after wrecking during a race Oct. 20 at Martinsville Speedway, a notoriously grueling half-mile track in Virginia, but the symptoms quickly disappeared.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Spencer, 45, another veteran driver, thought he might have been poisoned late last season during a fiery wreck in a race at Homestead, Fla.</p>
        <p>Testing, done with an instrument that resembles a Breathalyzer, showed that Spencer was poisoned, Nelson said, but only at about 15 percent of the level to warrant serious concern.</p>
        <p>''I think I get less of the carbon monoxide than the full-face helmet guys because I've got a lot more circulation,'' Spencer said in an interview with The Associated Press. ''You have to have the air circulating and moving. You cannot sit there in that dirty air.''</p>
        <p>Matt Kenseth, a teammate of Burton's, said: ''I've never really been tested for how much carbon monoxide I have in my system. There are sometimes after races where you don't feel good or you've got a headache at night, but whether that's from sitting in the same place or the noise or carbon monoxide or heat, I don't have the answer for that.''</p>
        <p>Nelson said Nascar was studying the effectiveness of a catalyst, developed by NASA, that converts carbon monoxide into carbon dioxide, a harmless gas. He said filters designed to remove particles probably do not work, because carbon monoxide is not in particle form.</p>
        <p>A hypothesis has also been advanced that carbon monoxide poisoning is much more likely at short tracks -- speed bowls ringed by thousands of seats -- because there is nowhere for the dirty air to go.</p>
        <p>Nelson disputes that. Even a short track is as big as a football stadium, and no tracks are enclosed. A plume of smoke from a skidding racecar dissipates rapidly, he said. There simply tend to be more wrecks on short tracks because the cars are closer together.</p>
        <p>''I think it's more the product of damaged cars,'' Nelson said.</p>
        <p>As disappointed as Mast is that his driving career is over, he is glad that he may be able to help others. At least people are more aware of the problem. When he was first stricken, he had no idea what was wrong with him.</p>
        <p>He thought he had the flu, or had eaten something bad. By the time of The Winston, an all-star race in May, he felt, as he said, ''deathly ill.'' He had fractured his ribs, ankle, foot and shoulder at times in his career, but this was far more debilitating.</p>
        <p>''It finally got to the point where I absolutely, physically could not do my job,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said he feels about 80 percent these days. He runs two businesses, neither involving engines, and is mulling offers to write a book and to be a racing commentator.</p>
        <p>Mast already knows the best way to avoid being stricken again. Without the slightest trace of irony, he said, ''Just steer clear of it.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
