<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tracking termites by monitoring their digestive problems and using hot chili peppers to kill them.</title>
    <meta content="12PATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/12/technology/12PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1488353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Patents"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Termites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capsaicin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mustard</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gophers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riordan, Teresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">neumann, robert h</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">sutherland, donald (inventor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DF133FF931A25756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tracking termites by monitoring their digestive problems and using hot chili peppers to kill them.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Using Termite Flatulence Against Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Teresa Riordan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riordan, Teresa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terry Clark patents method of detecting and killing termites outside home by monitoring methane they expel; Robert H Neumann patents use of capsaicin, substance that makes chili peppers hot, to kill termites; Donald Sutherland (who is not related to actor of same name) patents method for killing gophers and other rodents by filling their burrows with foam containing ground-up mustard seeds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TERRY CLARK, whose family runs a pest-control empire in Lodi, Calif., believes he has a better way to find termites: monitoring the methane they expel.</p>
        <p>''Termites eat a lot of roughage, so they have a huge gas problem,'' Mr. Clark said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Terry Clark, whose family runs a pest-control empire in Stockton, Calif., believes he has a better way to find termites: monitoring the methane they expel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TERRY CLARK, whose family runs a pest-control empire in Lodi, Calif., believes he has a better way to find termites: monitoring the methane they expel.</p>
        <p>''Termites eat a lot of roughage, so they have a huge gas problem,'' Mr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>Many different technologies -- from sonar to X-rays -- have been deployed to detect termites, with varying success. What makes termites so insidious is that they can munch their way through the innards of a house undetected.</p>
        <p>Some winged termites swarm to the surface in the spring (one reason, Mr. Clark noted, that April is National Pest Control Month). But often termites are so stealthy that for a long time the homeowner does not see so much as a wood crumb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark, 40, a vice president of Clark Pest Control, is by no means the first to try methane detection. In 1982, four scientists from three continents collaborated on a paper published in Science magazine that estimated that flatulence from termites might be responsible for as much as 30 percent of the methane in the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Since then, the level of termite-produced methane (and its possible contribution to global warming) has been a matter of fierce scientific contention.</p>
        <p>The pest-control industry, however, seems to agree that the presence of methane is a legitimate way to track termites. Some specialists use trained beagles to detect it. And some hand-held electronic termite ''sniffers'' are already on the market.</p>
        <p>But those are supposed to detect methane within the house, Mr. Clark said, while his system is designed to detect and kill termites before they even get to the house.</p>
        <p>To monitor termite activity, Mr. Clark will ring a house with a couple of dozen of his devices, which are shaped somewhat like giant plastic tacks and pushed into the ground.</p>
        <p>The flat disklike top shades the ground, giving termites, which are thermally sensitive, the impression that a nice juicy piece of cellulose might be sitting on the ground above. At the top is a methane sensor -- which Mr. Clark did not invent and which he buys off the shelf. Inside the spike end of the device is a wood stake with a cardboard collar.</p>
        <p>''Cardboard is the junk food of termites,'' Mr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>But this is no free meal. If the pest control expert sees, on his monthly rounds, that the methane has collected, the cardboard and wood stake can be infused with a mild poison called Premise, which the termites haul back to stock the colony larder.</p>
        <p>Would this approach work with other pests? After all, ''cockroaches are no slackers when it comes to producing methane,'' May R. Berenbaum observed in her book ''Buzzwords: A Scientist Muses on Sex, Bugs and Rock 'n' Roll.'' So far, however, no patents appear to have been granted for such a concept.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark is skeptical of this approach when it comes to cockroaches.</p>
        <p>''Cockroaches are not as well hidden as termites,'' he said. ''You know when they are there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark received United States patent 6,526,692 in March.</p>
        <p>About 70 miles southwest of Mr. Clark, in San Carlos, Calif., Robert H. Neumann wields an entirely different weapon in the war against termites: hot chili peppers.</p>
        <p>To be more precise, Mr. Neumann recently received his third patent for the use of capsaicin -- the oily, alkaline substance that makes peppers hot -- as a natural pesticide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neumann, 42, who works as a pest control inspector for Franz Termite Control, said he first came up with the idea after talking to a California Highway Patrol officer who was giving a lecture to termite inspectors on transporting hazardous chemicals.</p>
        <p>During a break, the officer described how he had subdued a suspect with pepper spray, and the proverbial light bulb went off over Mr. Neumann's head. The next day he brought some termites home, mixed up a chili pepper concoction and sprayed them. The capsaicin inflames their membranes, killing them almost instantly.</p>
        <p>''Some of my friends saw what I was doing and laughed, saying I was spending too much time on bugs and needed a vacation,'' Mr. Neumann recalled.</p>
        <p>They are not laughing anymore, he said. His patents are the basis for Kapto Inc., a new biopesticide company in Belmont, Calif. It has two products for pest-control professionals that, pending approval from the Environmental Protection Agency, are expected to be on the market in about four months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neumann was granted patent No. 6,523,298.</p>
        <p>Since he moved to a ranch in the foothills of the Canadian Rockies with his wife 18 years ago, Donald Sutherland has been waging a fierce battle against a very different kind of pest -- gophers.</p>
        <p>''I tried shooting them, trapping them, electrocuting them, poisoning them,'' said Mr. Sutherland, who is not related to the actor of the same name.</p>
        <p>''It's like mosquitoes,'' Mr. Sutherland said. ''For every one you kill, two more come around.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sutherland said strychnine poisoning was effective but not humane. Moreover, it is bad for the environment because it kills not only the gophers but also ''hawks and the coyotes and the neighbor's dog.'' (Although the creatures plaguing his ranch are commonly called gophers, technically they are Richardson's ground squirrels, Mr. Sutherland points out.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Sutherland speculated that he might be able to suffocate the gophers by filling a burrow with foam. The foam, similar to what firefighters use to put out fires, would be environmentally friendly, Mr. Sutherland surmised, since its main ingredient was a surfactant commonly found in shampoos.</p>
        <p>It seemed to work, putting a test gopher to sleep for 20 minutes. ''Trouble was, after that, he revived and scampered off no worse for the experience, except maybe a little cleaner,'' Mr. Sutherland said.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Sutherland tried adding different substances to the foam. None of them worked -- until he tried ground-up mustard seeds. ''It was just like magic,'' Mr. Sutherland said. The gophers stopped breathing after one minute and were dead within three minutes. Autopsies indicate that the mustard paralyzes the rodent's respiratory tract.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month Mr. Sutherland, who is 76, received United States patent 6,558,684 for his idea. He and his partner, David Schmunk, have already licensed exclusive North American rights to Exit Holdings, of Phoenix, a company formed to make and sell a rodenticide based on the patent.</p>
        <p>The mustard foam is also an effective rat eradicator, Mr. Sutherland said. The Chinese Association for the Control of Rodents and Sanitary Insects, a quasi-governmental agency in Beijing, has ordered enough of the foam to treat 50,000 rat burrows.</p>
        <p>That may sound like a lot, but apparently it is a bucket in the ocean. ''There are lots of rats in China,'' Mr. Sutherland said. ''Probably billions of burrows.''</p>
        <p>Patents</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
