<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back in Fray, Gore Urges Voters to Fire Bush</title>
    <meta content="Y08GOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/08/national/08GORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/US Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Gore, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DC1431F93BA3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back in Fray, Gore Urges Voters to Fire Bush</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Back in Fray, Gore Urges Voters to Fire Bush</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Vice Pres Gore wades back into presidential politics with speech at New York University accusing Bush administration of promoting 'false impressions' about need to go to war in Iraq and cut taxes; charges Bush with distortion on foreign, economic and environmental policy; repeats that he is not in campaign but speech raises Democratic eyebrows; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Vice President Al Gore waded back into presidential politics yesterday with a speech accusing the Bush administration of having promoted ''false impressions'' about the need to go to war in Iraq and to cut taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, speaking at New York University before more than 500 people invited by a political advocacy group and the campus chapter of the College Democrats, said Mr. Bush had engaged in a pattern of distortion when it came to foreign, economic and environmental policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Vice President Al Gore waded back into presidential politics with a speech accusing the president of having promoted "false impressions" about the need to go to war and to cut taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Former Vice President Al Gore waded back into presidential politics yesterday with a speech accusing the Bush administration of having promoted ''false impressions'' about the need to go to war in Iraq and to cut taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, speaking at New York University before more than 500 people invited by a political advocacy group and the campus chapter of the College Democrats, said Mr. Bush had engaged in a pattern of distortion when it came to foreign, economic and environmental policy.</p>
        <p>''The president's mishandling of and selective use of the best evidence available on the threat posed by Iraq is pretty much the same as the way he intentionally distorted the best available evidence on climate change, and rejected the best available evidence on the threat posed to America's economy by his tax and budget proposals,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>The speech was Mr. Gore's first major policy address since he announced in December that he would not run for president in 2004. Yesterday, he said again that he would not enter the campaign, but the timing of the speech -- as the campaign season heats up -- raised eyebrows in Democratic circles.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Mr. Gore asked Moveon.org, an Internet-based advocacy group that protested the war, to organize the event as a way for him to address the direction of the country, his assistants and officials at Moveon.org said.</p>
        <p>''He did make clear he was not going to run, but his feeling was there was sentiment not being put in words in terms of patterns and practices of the Bush administration and he felt he was in position to make that case,'' said Eli Pariser, the international campaigns director of Moveon.org. ''Some of the candidates have to be more guarded.''</p>
        <p>An adviser said Mr. Gore was not seeking to ''take oxygen'' from the candidates or to criticize them but ''to provide a road map and direction on some issues he feels are appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore devoted two lines of praise for the candidates, none by name, toward the end of his 40-minute speech. ''I am not going to join them,'' Mr. Gore said. ''But later in the political cycle I will endorse one of them.''</p>
        <p>For someone who is now a college lecturer and business consultant, the appearance created a fair amount of political buzz -- former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo of New York said on a radio show on Wednesday that Mr. Gore should get in the race -- and it had all the trappings of a campaign event. Nearly 100 members of the national and international news media registered to cover it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seemed to relish the opportunity to step from the sidelines and assess the opponent who defeated him in the bitterly contested 2000 election. And his language was generally harsher than that of the Democratic contenders.</p>
        <p>''Too many of our soldiers are paying the highest price for the strategic miscalculations, serious misjudgments and historic mistakes that have put them and our nation in harm's way,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>He credited Mr. Bush for having removed Saddam Hussein but lamented what he called the lack of ''honesty and integrity'' in the debate leading to the war. He noted that no nuclear weapons had been found in Iraq and no direct link between Mr. Hussein and Al Qaeda established. He suggested that a hidden motivation for the war was securing access to oil.</p>
        <p>After musing aloud about whether Mr. Bush's advisers had steered him wrong, Mr. Gore said, ''I've just about concluded that the real problem may be the president himself and that next year we ought to fire him and get a new one.''</p>
        <p>He called on Mr. Bush to ''rein in'' Attorney General John Ashcroft and the ''gross civil rights abuses'' he said were taking place under the Patriot Act. He likened a proposed Defense Department surveillance program to George Orwell's ''1984.'' A White House spokeswoman, addressing reporters near Mr. Bush's ranch near Crawford, Tex., dismissed Mr. Gore's complaints. Americans, said the spokeswoman, Claire Buchan, know ''the president's commitment to the security of the United States and to winning the war on terror and to securing our economic security.''</p>
        <p>Christine Iverson, a spokeswoman for the Republican National Committee, said Mr. Gore's record on terrorism was less than perfect. ''It's almost as if he were not vice president when the terrorists attacked the U.S.S. Cole, military barracks overseas and the World Trade Center for the first time,'' Ms. Iverson said, referring to the 1993 bombing.</p>
        <p>Four Democratic candidates -- former Governor Howard Dean of Vermont, Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, Senator John Edwards of North Carolina and Senator Bob Graham of Florida -- issued statements praising the speech.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
