<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conan the Green</title>
    <meta content="11SAT1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/11/opinion/11SAT1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1526293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D9153FF932A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conan the Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Conan the Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds that initial examination of California Governor-Elect Arnold Schwarzenegger's views on environment provides victory for optimism; asserts that Schwarzenegger's appointments for key environmental posts will be critical</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The actor who owns Hummers that average 10 miles to the gallon has now been elected governor of a state that has long provided national leadership on environmental issues, especially those like clean air and more fuel-efficient automobiles. Can Arnold Schwarzenegger and California's environmental impulses coexist?</p>
        <p>The prospects are better than one may have thought. Much will depend on the people he chooses for key posts, not least the chairmanship of the powerful California Air Resources Board, whose mandates over the years have driven Detroit to make cleaner cars and the refiners to make cleaner fuels. As with all politicians, much will also depend on whether he means what he says and acts on it. Still, his comments and campaign literature not only hearten conservationists but put him sharply at odds with the Bush administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arnold Schwarzenegger may be at odds with President Bush when it comes to the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The actor who owns Hummers that average 10 miles to the gallon has now been elected governor of a state that has long provided national leadership on environmental issues, especially those like clean air and more fuel-efficient automobiles. Can Arnold Schwarzenegger and California's environmental impulses coexist?</p>
        <p>The prospects are better than one may have thought. Much will depend on the people he chooses for key posts, not least the chairmanship of the powerful California Air Resources Board, whose mandates over the years have driven Detroit to make cleaner cars and the refiners to make cleaner fuels. As with all politicians, much will also depend on whether he means what he says and acts on it. Still, his comments and campaign literature not only hearten conservationists but put him sharply at odds with the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>The biggest difference is on global warming, an issue the administration has been slighting for three years. A new California law will require automakers to meet lower targets for emissions of carbon dioxide, the main global-warming gas. The automobile industry, joined by the White House, complains that the law is a backdoor way of increasing fuel economy, historically a federal prerogative. Mr. Schwarzenegger has embraced the new law and says he will defend it against all legal challenges.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, he promises that by 2020 one-third of California's power will be generated by renewable sources like wind and solar power. The Bush administration, in contrast, has been lobbying fiercely against a much weaker provision contained in the energy bill now before Congress. Mr. Schwarzenegger also says he is not at all pleased with the administration's recent efforts to weaken the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The differences on issues other than clean air are equally pronounced. Mr. Bush supports measures that could lead to oil exploration and drilling in sensitive coastal areas. Mr. Schwarzenegger is firmly opposed. The administration would greatly increase logging in California's Sierra Nevada, thereby upending a carefully drafted agreement to balance the needs of nature and commerce. The governor-elect would leave the deal undisturbed.</p>
        <p>There have been missteps. A sloppy answer left the impression that Mr. Schwarzenegger would abolish California's Environmental Protection Agency to eliminate bureaucratic duplication. This was quickly corrected. Parts of his agenda are naïve. Like Mr. Bush, he seems fixated on hydrogen as the fuel of the future. He may well be right over the long term, but his vision of a network of hydrogen fueling stations along California's highways by 2010 is unrealistic, if not utopian. He is not above gimmickry, promising to retrofit his Hummers with hydrogen, something only a Hollywood star could afford. The leader of his transition team, Representative David Dreier, has a dismal voting record on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>So far, however, there is much to like, and, unlike Mr. Bush, Mr. Schwarzenegger comes to office unbeholden to corporate interests. It will be intriguing to see how this plays out, especially with the governor's fellow Republicans in Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
