<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Finds Atmospheric Decline in Pesticide Harmful to Ozone</title>
    <meta content="Y16OZON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/16/science/16OZON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1512289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methyl Bromide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methyl Bromide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DB1430F935A2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Finds Atmospheric Decline in Pesticide Harmful to Ozone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Study Finds Atmospheric Decline in Pesticide Harmful to Ozone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers from National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration find signficant drop in atmospheric levels of methyl bromide, pesticide that is being phased out because it damages planet's protective ozone layer; say drop is attributable to mandatory curbs on chemical under 1987 Montreal Protocol, treaty aimed at restoring ozone layer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government scientists have measured a significant drop in atmospheric levels of methyl bromide, a versatile pesticide that is being phased out of use because it damages the planet's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The scientists say the drop, 13 percent since 1998, is attributable to mandatory curbs on the chemical under the Montreal Protocol, a 1987 treaty aimed at restoring the layer, which blocks ultraviolet radiation that could otherwise raise cancer rates and harm ecosystems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists say the drop in atmospheric levels of methyl bromide, 13 percent since 1998, is attributable to mandatory curbs on the chemical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Government scientists have measured a significant drop in atmospheric levels of methyl bromide, a versatile pesticide that is being phased out of use because it damages the planet's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The scientists say the drop, 13 percent since 1998, is attributable to mandatory curbs on the chemical under the Montreal Protocol, a 1987 treaty aimed at restoring the layer, which blocks ultraviolet radiation that could otherwise raise cancer rates and harm ecosystems.</p>
        <p>The researchers, from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, describe the findings in yesterday's issue of the journal Geophysical Research Letters.</p>
        <p>Methyl bromide, while less common than Freon and other restricted ozone-damaging substances, breaks down in the air and releases bromine, which disperses into the stratosphere and vigorously attacks ozone molecules.</p>
        <p>But for decades methyl bromide has also been a popular, cheap means of sterilizing soils, grain silos and shipments of perishable goods.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists welcomed the new findings but expressed concern about recent proposals by the United States and other countries to continue and expand certain uses of methyl bromide past 2005, when, under the Montreal pact, a ban is to take effect in industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>This year the Bush administration is seeking exemptions to the ban on behalf of dozens of strawberry and tomato farmers, golf-course owners and other users of methyl bromide who say no inexpensive alternatives exist.</p>
        <p>Federal agriculture officials also want to expand its use in fumigating imported wood packaging and shipping pallets that may contain Asian longhorn beetles or other pests.</p>
        <p>But David D. Doniger, a policy director for the Natural Resources Defense Council, said the exemptions were unnecessary and would cause a rise in methyl bromide use after a steady drop. A variety of pesticides are listed by the federal government as substitutes for methyl bromide, Dr. Doniger said, adding that fumigation of imported goods could be ended if shippers were required to heat wood to kill pests or switch to other kinds of packaging.</p>
        <p>The new study projects continued steep declines in methyl bromide in the air as long as use of the chemical continues to drop.</p>
        <p>Those projections do not take into account the possibility of substantial use under exemptions to the Montreal treaty, said Dr. Stephen A. Montzka, the government chemist who led the study.</p>
        <p>''Without continued worldwide adherence to the restrictions outlined in the protocol,'' Dr. Montzka said, ''these trends could slow and delay the recovery of stratospheric ozone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
