<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memo to the Democrats: Quit Being Losers!</title>
    <meta content="19DEMOCRT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/19/magazine/19DEMOCRATS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1457545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carlson, Tucker</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/US Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/National Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DD1531F93AA25752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="3112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memo to the Democrats: Quit Being Losers!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Memo to the Democrats: Quit Being Losers!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tucker Carlson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carlson, Tucker</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tucker Carlson, pundit and co-host of CNN's Crossfire, offers advice to Democratic party in wake of losses in November elections ; says Democrats must find realistic positive agenda rather than criticizing Bush economic policy; says party must take strong stand for defense of country; suggests Democrats begin building privately financed parallel political establishment in form of think tanks, similar to those that helped form Republican agenda; suggests use of straightforward language, which public sees as sign of honesty; concludes party will lose in 2004 so it might as well run honest campaign; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This fall, for the second time in a row, the Democratic Party lost an election it should have won. Democrats offered no rationale for why they should be running the country and no vision for how they would run it. The party got the drubbing it deserved. I enjoyed watching.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, I found the Democrats' distress faintly unsettling. One-party government makes me nervous. It's too efficient. There isn't enough gridlock. Worst of all, the arguments tend to be boring. Like drunks and children, ineffectual political parties make for frustrating debate partners. Even if you're wrong, you still beat them. Every country deserves at least two functioning parties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pundit from the other side generously offers advice to a party that could use some help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This fall, for the second time in a row, the Democratic Party lost an election it should have won. Democrats offered no rationale for why they should be running the country and no vision for how they would run it. The party got the drubbing it deserved. I enjoyed watching.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, I found the Democrats' distress faintly unsettling. One-party government makes me nervous. It's too efficient. There isn't enough gridlock. Worst of all, the arguments tend to be boring. Like drunks and children, ineffectual political parties make for frustrating debate partners. Even if you're wrong, you still beat them. Every country deserves at least two functioning parties.</p>
        <p>With that in mind, I have some ideas for how Democrats can help their party be taken seriously again. Why should Democrats listen to advice from someone who represents the right on a television talk show? Partly because there are lessons worth learning from the many years Republicans spent as the minority party and partly because, why not? Nothing else seems to be working.</p>
        <p>For Democrats to win back Congress and the White House in 2004, they must: a) arrange for the current president to mess up horribly, preferably by losing a war or driving the economy into stagflation, and b) pick a national political leader with the stature, political skill and clarity of vision to take advantage of the opportunity. None of this will be easy. More than anything, it will require luck, the most underrated factor in politics. That may take awhile.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Democrats should forget about running on economic issues alone. In the months before the midterm elections, the entire Democratic strategy seemed to consist of criticizing Bush's economic policy by insulting Harvey Pitt, the former chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission. Not only was this a lame argument; it was bad politics. Did any voter really believe that the health of the economy hangs on staff changes at the S.E.C.? Did the average person even know who Harvey Pitt was?</p>
        <p>In general, Democrats have spent relatively little time over the past two years telling voters why Bush's policies are bad for the country. They've attacked Bush the man quite a bit, but when was the last time you heard an elected Democrat explain precisely, with numbers, not slogans, how the Bush tax cuts have damaged the economy? Do you know anything about the Democratic economic stimulus plan? Is there one? And what exactly do the Democrats think about fighting terrorism and the coming war with Iraq? They need to figure it out quickly.</p>
        <p>Democrats won't start winning elections until they convince the public that they're capable of responding vigorously to threats from abroad. At this point voters are skeptical. A USA Today/CNN/Gallup poll taken the week of the midterms showed Republicans beating Democrats by 30 points on the question Which party is ''tough enough on terrorism''? Numbers like these mean political death, but so far Democrats haven't even tried to overcome them. ''If we try and make defense, foreign policy, the overriding issue,'' Representative Martin Frost of Texas told fellow Democrats in the fall, ''we will lose, because the country is with the president on that issue.''</p>
        <p>In other words, nod when Bush talks about Iraq, then change the subject to taxes. The hope is that 2004 will be a replay of 1992, when the Democrats were able to neutralize the president's foreign policy success with attacks on his economic stewardship. But 2004 won't be 1992. Of course, if there's a recession, the Democrats should blame Bush for it and exploit it for all it's worth. But around the next election, American forces, and America itself, will still be at risk. Recession or not, war is likely to be the overriding issue. The Democratic Party needs something to say about it.</p>
        <p>Ideally, Democrats would campaign on fresh, new, daring ideas about America's role in the world. In real life, fresh, new, daring ideas are rare. Even when you find them, it takes years to refine a crackpot theory into a workable policy. Democrats would be better off stealing Bush's positions, then making them stronger -- becoming more Bush than Bush.</p>
        <p>There's nothing embarrassing about this. Appropriating the rhetoric of your enemies is among the oldest traditions in politics. Bill Clinton used Republican language and symbols to transform his party's image from soft on crime to ferociously pro-law enforcement. As a candidate, Clinton executed a brain-damaged criminal. As president, he promised more cops, signed a crime bill and in general talked like John Walsh.</p>
        <p>These days almost all Democrats are law-and-order Democrats. Relatively few with national aspirations even oppose capital punishment. One of the few who does is Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts (though since Sept. 11, Kerry has said he would make an exception for terrorists). Last year, I asked Kerry about it. Yes, I oppose the death penalty, he said. On the other hand, ''I have killed people in war -- personally.'' Kerry may be liberal, but he'd like you to know that he's a Schwarzenegger liberal.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Party needs to establish this same sort of tougher-than-thou credibility on foreign policy. The problem is that ''Democrats are really freaked out by anti-Americanism,'' says Peter Beinart, editor of The New Republic. ''They're a little like Canadians in that they have difficulty going to sleep at night knowing that people hate them.'' Fighting terrorism requires exerting American power. Exerting power makes people hate you. Hence the Democrats' bind. Beinart recommends ''a Sister Souljah moment with the U.N.,'' a high-profile news event that Democrats can use to show they really don't care what France thinks.</p>
        <p>That might help. So would amping up the rhetoric in the war on terrorism. Democrats cringed when Bush used cowboy language to describe the fight against Al Qaeda. They'd be smart to come out with their own, bloodthirstier version: ''I won't rest until Osama bin Laden's head is resting -- on a stake.'' Try that as a slogan. Out-gunsling Bush.</p>
        <p>Kerry, my pick for the most promising of the Democratic candidates, has been moving in this direction. The fighting in Afghanistan was just cooling off when Kerry declared the operation in Tora Bora a disaster. Kerry turned out to be right, but what was interesting was his diagnosis: not enough force. The Pentagon, he said, should have used American soldiers, rather than local militia, to chase Al Qaeda into the mountains. The mission failed because the military was too timid, too afraid to risk American lives. When was the last time you heard a Democrat say that?</p>
        <p>When it comes to guarding America, Democrats should prove they're more vigilant than the president. They can do it in obvious ways -- more money for port security -- and in not so obvious ones, like tightening border controls, an issue on which Bush, who has pledged to increase immigration, is vulnerable. Democrats can't hope to take a tougher position on Iraq than the president has. But they can outflank him on the rest of the Middle East. In a debate over foreign policy, Democrats have one advantage over Bush: they can sound as bellicose as they like without actually having to conduct diplomacy. They should remind voters that Hamas and Hezbollah still exist, still hate America and still pose an arguably greater threat to the United States than Saddam Hussein does. They should take a harder line on Syria, Iran, Pakistan and Saudi Arabia, all of which have received a temporary pass while America's attention has been focused on Iraq. The next time the Bush administration allows North Korean missiles to pass unmolested to their destination in Yemen, Dick Gephardt should stage a protest in front of the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>From there he should head to the steps of the Department of Energy, to unveil his party's plan to develop alternative energy sources. Cynics will expect the usual dopey ''No Nukes, Go Solar'' slogans of the 70's. Gephardt should surprise them by framing the issue from the right, as a matter of urgent national security: energy independence as a weapon in the war against terrorism. He ought to make open-minded noises about nuclear power, just to prove he's serious. In the months after Sept. 11, Gephardt called for another Manhattan Project to develop new energy sources, like hydrogen fuel cells. He hasn't said much about it since. He should.</p>
        <p>And he should hurry. It can't be long before the president comes out with his own plan to develop alternatives to fossil fuels. Imagine it: an oilman pledges to wean America from oil. It's brilliant. Bush will do it. He isn't stupid. Which is something else Democrats ought to remember.</p>
        <p>Democrats have a lot of planning to do. The great thing about being in the minority is that you have the time to think deeply about how government should be run. Ideas become important when you're out of power, mostly because they're all you have.</p>
        <p>Just ask the Republicans. The G.O.P. lost control of Congress during the Great Depression and didn't regain it for any length of time until the Clinton administration. At its nadir, during the 75th Congress, the Republican Party held just 105 seats in the entire legislative branch, 89 in the House and 16 in the Senate. For 60 years, Republicans had some free time on their hands. They used it to decide what they believed. Between Barry Goldwater's defeat and Ronald Reagan's victory, the Republican Party arrived at a kind of ideological clarity. Republicans decided they were against Communism and for smaller government. Reagan's 1980 campaign ads were some of the least confusing ever made: strong defense, lower taxes. Lower taxes, strong defense. You couldn't miss the message, and voters didn't.</p>
        <p>A pair of bullet points do not make a governing agenda, of course. But then, a lot of the time those who govern don't make the governing agenda. This is the problem with wielding political power in Washington: the job is so demanding and complicated and immediate that the big picture gets tiny. Ideas get lost. ''The urgent overwhelms the important,'' in the words of Ed Feulner, longtime president of the Heritage Foundation.</p>
        <p>The aim of the Heritage Foundation and other conservative think tanks is to help Republicans keep track of the important details. In 1980, Feulner and others at Heritage produced a blueprint to help Reagan run the executive branch, a 3,000-page book called ''Mandate for Leadership.'' No one claims that Reagan read the whole thing, but someone in the White House apparently did. Among the 2,000 recommendations in ''Mandate for Leadership'' was advice on handling labor disputes with air-traffic controllers. Heritage's position was, Don't tolerate strikes.</p>
        <p>Over the past 20 years, virtually every big Republican idea and many small ones -- school choice, welfare reform, enterprise zones, Social Security privatization -- have originated in think tanks, rather than on Capitol Hill. Think tanks have sponsored some of the most important conservative books and published some of the best conservative magazines.</p>
        <p>By the time the Republicans took over Congress in 1994, there were scores of conservative think tanks ready to help them govern. One of these was the Project for the Republican Future, a tiny operation run by William Kristol, Dan Quayle's former chief of staff. In January 1994, Kristol decided to derail the Clinton health care plan. He and his staff issued a position paper titled ''How to Oppose the Health Plan -- and Why.'' Aimed at Republicans on the Hill, the paper contended that any compromise with the president on health care would be bad for American medicine and bad for the G.O.P. Kristol argued that Republicans should stonewall Clinton while presenting their own less severe alternatives for reform. Kristol's memo gave Republicans heart. They resisted the Clinton health plan, HillaryCare failed and by the election it was Democrats who were suffering.</p>
        <p>Democrats often complain that conservatives benefit from a privately financed parallel political establishment. They're right. And they should build their own.</p>
        <p>And while they're at it, they ought to rediscover their sense of humor. Liberals used to be funny. They edited magazines like National Lampoon. They had a claim on cool. Then something happened. They became sour and earnest and neurotic about secondhand smoke. The Democratic Party became the that's-not-funny-young-man party, the party of no fun. National Lampoon folded. At least one of its editors became a conservative and started writing for The American Spectator.</p>
        <p>If you began reading The American Spectator in the mid-90's, you probably remember it for obsessive, slightly kooky (sometimes very kooky) investigative journalism that wasn't all that interesting unless you hated Bill Clinton for a living. But before Clinton, believe it or not, it was a very funny magazine. In the summer of 1989, The Spectator published an article titled ''A Call for a New McCarthyism,'' by P.J. O'Rourke, late of National Lampoon. O'Rourke opened by conceding that the liberals were absolutely right, that the Reagan years had in fact been a replay of the darkest days of the 1950's. ''Indeed,'' he wrote, ''we are experiencing anew many of the pleasures and benefits of that excellent decade: a salubrious prudery, a sensible avariciousness, a healthy dose of social conformity, a much-needed narrowing of minds and a return to common-sense American political troglodytism.'' According to O'Rourke, the only thing missing from the 80's was a good old-fashioned witch hunt. So he started one: ''The fun part of McCarthyism is, as it always was, making out the enemies list.'' O'Rourke's list included ''fuzzy-minded one-worlders, pasty-faced peace creeps and bleeding-heart bed-wetters'' like Sting and Susan Sarandon and Amy Carter.</p>
        <p>O'Rourke wrote the article for the same reason the Fox News Channel calls itself ''fair and balanced'' -- to drive liberals crazy. It worked. Years later, when the essay was expanded into a book, an outraged reviewer at Library Journal huffed that O'Rourke was trying to revive ''the ghosts of Joe McCarthy and Richard Nixon.'' Bait taken.</p>
        <p>It's both the job and the privilege of the minority party to gleefully torment its more powerful opponents. Democrats seem to have forgotten this. Ever read The American Prospect? The closest thing to humor in a recent issue is an account of how the media were mean and unfair to Al Gore during the last election. It's a serious article. The comedy is purely unintentional.</p>
        <p>For politicians, humor is freedom. Late last year, Al Gore finally seemed to learn this. But it was too late. Hours after his winning appearance on ''Saturday Night Live,'' he retired from politics. For most of his career, Gore suffered from the opposite problem: he was a terrible straight man. He never seemed to be telling the truth, even when he may have been. He came off as a dissembler, and this as much as anything doomed his 2000 presidential bid.</p>
        <p>Democrats have forgotten how much the public loves straightforward language. Voters love it even more than accurate language. I first became convinced of this in the spring of 1999, when I went to Austin, Tex., to profile George W. Bush. The day I arrived, Bush held a news conference to explain his views on the war in Kosovo. He proceeded to mangle almost every word. Bush referred to ''Mylo-sovack'' (commonly known as Milosevic), then talked at some length about the ''Kosovanians'' and our allies ''the Grecians.'' I was shocked. This may work in Texas, I thought, but the rest of the country won't tolerate this level of inarticulateness in a presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the rest of the country didn't care. If anything, voters interpreted Bush's dyslexia as candor. At least he's not slick was the idea. After a decade of Clinton-Gore, that's how desperate the public was for an honest candidate.</p>
        <p>Will the Democrats get one in 2004? To find out, I called Howard Dean, the former longtime governor of Vermont and newly announced candidate for the White House. Parties are often revived by insurgents from within them -- Reagan, Gingrich -- and Dean is nothing if not an insurgent. Plus, I'd heard that he's a straight-shooter.</p>
        <p>He is. While other candidates divulge their positions on uncomfortable social issues almost parenthetically, Dean leads with his. He is for needle exchanges, unrestricted abortion and civil unions between homosexuals, and he's happy to tell you about it. Most politicians squirm at the mention of partial-birth abortion. Not Dean. ''Partial-birth abortion is a manufactured issue,'' he says. ''It's [expletive]. Partial-birth abortion essentially doesn't exist.'' And even if it does, ''it isn't any of Congress's business.''</p>
        <p>Dean isn't surprised by the Trent Lott scandal. The Republican Party is fundamentally hostile to blacks and Hispanics, he says, riddled as it is with ''institutional racism.'' It's also full of liars. ''I find the Republican Party pretty bankrupt intellectually,'' Dean says, adding that he doesn't read anything written by conservatives. Nothing? ''No.'' Are there any conservatives who are intellectually honest? ''I don't think so. I can't think of any.'' He sounds cheery as he says this.</p>
        <p>Dean's tone has changed a few hours later when he calls back and leaves this message: ''Tucker, this is Howard Dean. I was talking to some staff folks after I got off the phone with you, and they were worried about my term 'institutional racism.' Probably that might have been not the right word to use. I was a little nervous now that the word 'racist' was such a charged word that it might have been better if I talked about 'intolerance' and 'divisiveness.' If you could give me a call back, that would be great.''</p>
        <p>Damn. The consultants. They've gotten to him already. Dean hasn't even had a chance to say anything truly outrageous, and already the campaign professionals, sworn enemies of colorful language, are telling him to tone it down, advising him to dilute his essential Howard Dean-ness. Fire them, I thought. Send them back to Washington before it's too late.</p>
        <p>Of course, in a deeper sense, it's already too late. Dean, like the other Democrats running for president in 2004, is unlikely to become president, consultants or not. Which is all the more reason to run an honest campaign. Relax. Say what you think. Tell an off-color joke now and then. Have a good time. No one wants to watch a suffering candidate. Voters will like you if you like what you're doing. You probably won't win the election. You might as well enjoy running.</p>
        <p>Tucker Carlson is the co-host of ''Crossfire'' on CNN.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tucker Carlson is the co-host of ''Crossfire'' on CNN.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
