<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Edging Closer To Gassing the Geese</title>
    <meta content="07NJGOOSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1517867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geese</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fish and Wildlife Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DB163BF934A3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Edging Closer To Gassing the Geese</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>CRANFORD</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on plan put forward by US Fish and Wildlife Service to pass much of responsibility for managing goose problem to states, streamline federal permit process and give more flexibility to local officials; measures in New Jersey, whose goose population has grown to 90,000, would include nest and egg destruction, expanded hunting season and gassing of geese; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRUCE ESPOSITO, a 51-year old musician from Elizabeth, was relaxing on a park bench in Nomahegan Park here one recent sunny afternoon. The problem was, so were the gaggle of geese who waddled brazenly around him, undeterred by cyclists and strollers and the fact that 700 of their brethren in this and two other Union County parks had been rounded up and gassed two months ago.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what to tell you; they do make a mess out of the park, that's for sure,'' said Mr. Esposito. ''This guy who just cycled by, he said 'Shoot 'em all.'''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BRUCE ESPOSITO, a 51-year old musician from Elizabeth, was relaxing on a park bench in Nomahegan Park here one recent sunny afternoon. The problem was, so were the gaggle of geese who waddled brazenly around him, undeterred by cyclists and strollers and the fact that 700 of their brethren in this and two other Union County parks had been rounded up and gassed two months ago.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what to tell you; they do make a mess out of the park, that's for sure,'' said Mr. Esposito. ''This guy who just cycled by, he said 'Shoot 'em all.'''</p>
        <p>People frustrated by goose droppings in parks and on their lawns might agree with the cyclist -- especially since more humane measures like setting off fireworks and chasing geese with border collies have not seemed to do much good. But a plan announced two weeks ago by the federal government to ease restrictions on controlling resident Canada geese could put more teeth in the efforts to eradicate them.</p>
        <p>The United States Fish and Wildlife Service of the Department of the Interior wants to pass on much of the responsibility for managing the goose problem to the states, streamlining the federal permit process and giving more flexibility to local officials.</p>
        <p>That population has been growing 5 to 6 percent a year over the last 15 to 20 years, according to Nicholas Throckmorton, a spokesman for the Wildlife Service. As a result, there are 3.2 million geese in the United States -- and 90,000 in New Jersey alone.</p>
        <p>But those numbers might soon start to change. In New Jersey, the State Department of Environmental Protection could be authorized as early as next spring to grant permission to municipalities, farmers, golf courses and others to reduce the goose populations. The new rule is outlined in an environmental statement that the Wildlife Service has reopened for a 60-day period of public comment, ending Oct. 20.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, measures to eradicate the geese would continue to include nest and egg destruction, an expanded hunting season and other strategies like rounding up and gassing the birds.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Throckmorton, Wildlife Service officials have come to believe that the goose problem can be attacked more efficiently at the local level. ''The thinking is that under the current system of issuing permits to the states, the resident Canada goose population is still increasing,'' he said. ''This proposed ruling will hopefully reduce the resident goose population in areas where there is a problem.''</p>
        <p>This year, the Federal government issued 68 permits to New Jersey, up from 57 in 2000, said Terri Edwards, a spokeswoman for the Northeast region of the Wildlife Service in Hadley, Mass. In comparison, New York received 51 permits and Pennsylvania 26.</p>
        <p>David Dobias, chief of the permits branch of the Northeast region, said his small staff tries to get permits out within 60 days but often fails to do so. Asked how long the process normally takes, he replied, ''I would be embarrassed to say.''</p>
        <p>Carl W. Block, past president of the New Jersey State League of Municipalities, said mayors throughout the state were experiencing ''geese overload.''</p>
        <p>''For towns up and down the coast and especially throughout the state, resident Canadian geese have turned into an absolute problem, both from a health and from a regulatory standpoint,'' said Mr. Block, s the mayor of Stafford Township.</p>
        <p>The plan may hold the answer, he added, noting, ''Whatever solutions the towns or counties will be looking for, they should be able to be granted more expeditiously.''</p>
        <p>But like many environmentalists, Jeff Tittel, director of the New Jersey chapter of the Sierra Club, says the effort is misguided.</p>
        <p>''I think the Federal government laid a goose egg,'' Mr. Tittel said. ''One of the reasons we have a goose population that's not migrating is because of how we maintain and manage our lands.''</p>
        <p>Acres of closely cropped grass on industrial campuses, golf courses and parks dotted with bodies of water attract the geese, he added, ''creating this kind of suburban landscape that causes the geese population to stay and multiply.''</p>
        <p>Officials of the State Department of Environmental Protection are exploring the plan, which could cost the state ''hundreds of thousands of dollars'' to administer, said Jack Kaskey, an agency spokesman.</p>
        <p>''Our major concern right now is if we're going to take over the program it will need money to implement it,'' Mr. Kaskey said. ''Otherwise, it will be a financial burden on the taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>Most likely, the new rules would make it easier to take extreme measures like gassing the geese. Earlier in the summer, Union County obtained a permit to gas 2,700 of the birds in Nomahegan Park here, Rahway River Park in Rahway and Echo Lake Park in Mountainside and Westfield.</p>
        <p>The county contracted the services of the wildlife services division of the federal Department of Agriculture, whose agents over a two-day period rounded up about 700 geese and put them in specially designed vehicles where they were killed with carbon dioxide. Their carcasses were then left at an undisclosed landfill.</p>
        <p>George Devanney, the Union County manager, said the action was taken as a last resort after the county tried other measures that included using a border collie, sending a noisy remote-controlled boat into ponds, and shaking the eggs.</p>
        <p>''You can't enjoy the park when you're walking through geese feces,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The plan drew criticism from animal rights groups that tried to stop the kill and from radio personalities who poked fun at New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''Initially we faced a fair amount of criticism,'' said Charles Sigmund, the Union County parks and recreation director. ''But once the program concluded, the support of our actions was overwhelming.''</p>
        <p>The other day there were still geese in Nomahegan Park honking away.</p>
        <p>''It does seem rather inhumane,'' Bob Laukaitis, a 58-year old financial planner from Cranford said of the gassing, as he looked up from his park bench and paperback mystery. ''But I don't see how you can solve this problem. Personally, I wouldn't have done it myself. I would have left them alone.''</p>
        <p>But up on Park Drive, a short distance behind him, Adele Falkowski, also of Cranford, said she supported the new regulation. She was leaving her daughter's house where a foot-high fence had been put up to keep the geese away. ''Well, I'll tell you, anything that will do the job,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A few doors away at 2 Park Drive, Dan DeMarco, the coach of the Union High School Jayvee baseball team, was playing catch with his 7-year old nephew, Anthony.</p>
        <p>''If they stay in the park, it wouldn't be a problem, but how do we keep them in the park and not coming onto personal property, where it could be unsanitary and harmful to kids?'' Mr. DeMarco asked. ''I'm not in favor of how they did it but if there was no other way to control them, I'm in favor of it.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
