<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="19OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/19/science/19OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iron (Nutrient)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coral</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Algae</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Juan De Fuca Ridge</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mentawai Islands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Massachusetts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Australian National University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indonesian Institute of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahefi, Kazem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lovley, Derek R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marine Biology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marine Biology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7D91230F93AA2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Surviving the Heat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Massachusetts researchers Kazem Kahefi and Derek R Lovley isolate Strain 121, bacteria-like organism that is able to withstand 266 degrees and was collected in Juan de Fuca Ridge in northeastern Pacific; reporting in journal Science, they find organism uses iron for metabolic energy in similar way that humans use oxygen for respiration; Australian National University and Indonesian Institute of Sciences researchers, in journal Science, present theory that 1997 death of coral reef off Mentawai Islands was caused by chain of events in which iron, deposited from rampant Indonesian fires, fertilized red algae causing it to bloom profusely and suffocate coral; Indian and American paleontologists announce discovery of fossils of new dinosaur species; found in western India, 30-foot-long, horned meat-eater is named Rajasaurus narmadensis; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surviving the Heat</p>
        <p>Think it's hot, eh? Had enough of 90-degree days? Tired of coming back from lunch to have a colleague ask if you have been splashing around in a fountain, when it's just sweat that's soaking through your shirt?</p>
        <p>Sorry, but you don't know hot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This week's column includes items on Strain 121, the newly discovered species of Archaea, causes of coral death and a new dinosaur species.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surviving the Heat</p>
        <p>Think it's hot, eh? Had enough of 90-degree days? Tired of coming back from lunch to have a colleague ask if you have been splashing around in a fountain, when it's just sweat that's soaking through your shirt?</p>
        <p>Sorry, but you don't know hot.</p>
        <p>Strain 121, however, does. It has set an unofficial record for extreme living, thriving at temperatures about 40 degrees above the boiling point of water.</p>
        <p>Strain 121 is the temporary name for a newly discovered species of Archaea, those single-celled bacteria-like organisms that are often found in extreme environments (it will get a species name when it is more completely described). It was collected in water samples from a hydrothermal vent 7,000 feet down along the Juan de Fuca Ridge in the northeastern Pacific. Hydrothermal vents spew mineral-rich water that is super hot and are home to many unique and bizarre organisms.</p>
        <p>Kazem Kashefi and Derek R. Lovley of the University of Massachusetts isolated Strain 121, which is about a micron in diameter, during studies to culture organisms that use iron for metabolic energy, much the way people and other creatures use oxygen. Iron respiration -- in which ferric iron is reduced (meaning it gains an electron) to become ferrous iron, creating the mineral magnetite -- may have been the first form of respiration during the early evolution of single-celled organisms.</p>
        <p>The researchers, who described their findings in Science, found that Strain 121 both reduced iron and grew at temperatures ranging from 185 to 250 degrees (250 Fahrenheit is 121 centigrade, thus the name). The previous record was held by another Archaea, Pyrolobus furmarii, which could thrive up to 235 degrees. Strain 121 even survived several hours at 266 degrees, and then grew when transferred to cooler water.</p>
        <p>The Bloom of Death</p>
        <p>Iron plays a critical role in life, as Strain 121 shows. But it can also play a role in death. Consider what happened to an Indonesian coral reef, for example.</p>
        <p>The reef, a diverse habitat with more than 100 coral species near the Mentawai Islands off southwest Sumatra, died in late 1997. In itself that is not completely unusual: many Indian Ocean reefs died or were damaged in 1997 and 1998 due to rising ocean temperatures (attributed to global warming) combined with El Nino.</p>
        <p>But the Mentawai die-off was different, researchers from the Australian National University and the Indonesian Institute of Sciences report in Science. For one thing, surface temperatures remained relatively cool in that part of the ocean.</p>
        <p>In seeking a cause, the researchers examined samples of corals of the genus Porites, which give clues to their life, and death, in the chemical makeup of their skeletons. Around the time the coral died, the skeletons showed changes in concentration of carbon isotopes, indicating a large algal bloom. This coincides with reports of a massive red tide, or bloom, at the time. All that algae would have suffocated the coral.</p>
        <p>But what caused the red tide? The researchers suggest that widespread wildfires in Indonesia in 1997 were to blame. The fires produced huge plumes of smoke and ash containing, among other things, a lot of ferric iron -- 11,000 metric tons of it by some estimates. The researchers say that when the smoke and ash settled on the ocean, the iron acted like a fertilizer, causing the algal bloom.</p>
        <p>Naming a Meat-Eater</p>
        <p>Indian and American paleontologists have announced a new dinosaur species, identified from 65-million-year-old bones uncovered nearly two decades ago in western India.</p>
        <p>The dinosaur, which was about 30 feet long and had a horn on top of its skull, has been named Rajasaurus narmadensis. It walked on two legs and was a meat-eater, with a taste for its fellow beasts: bone of titanosaurs were found with it.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
