<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; Pataki's Eye Is Wandering to Washington, Critics Say</title>
    <meta content="24PATA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1475013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Federal Budget</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6D71430F937A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; Pataki's Eye Is Wandering to Washington, Critics Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo examines New York Gov George Pataki's re-emphasis of his conservative roots following election in which he courted traditional Democratic base, including labor unions and Hispanics; as state faces worst fiscal crisis since 1930's, Pataki has been reticent in appealing for aid from Washington; critics say he is trying to ingratiate himself with Bush administration because he is angling for job in Washington; true test will come in 2004 presidential election, in which some top Republicans say he can deliver state to Bush; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since he was re-elected overwhelmingly to his third term in November, Gov. George E. Pataki of New York has been talking and acting like a politician who has his sights set on Washington, according to strategists and lawmakers in both political parties.</p>
        <p>After campaigning as a social liberal and going out of his way to gain the support of New York's traditional Democratic base, including labor unions and Hispanic voters, Mr. Pataki, a Republican, seems to have made a postelection political shift that has caught the attention of politicians here and in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever since he was re-elected overwhelmingly to his third term in November, Gov. George E. Pataki of New York has been talking and acting like a politician who has his sights set on Washington, according to strategists and lawmakers in both political parties.</p>
        <p>After campaigning as a social liberal and going out of his way to gain the support of New York's traditional Democratic base, including labor unions and Hispanic voters, Mr. Pataki, a Republican, seems to have made a postelection political shift that has caught the attention of politicians here and in New York.</p>
        <p>In his words and in his actions, Mr. Pataki has been re-emphasizing his conservative roots, not only taking a hard line against tax increases and government spending -- something his aides say is necessary given the state's dire fiscal condition -- but also anchoring himself to themes that keep him in step with the mainstream of his party.</p>
        <p>In speeches, news briefings and letters to contributors, he has gone on the offensive in the annual Albany budget wars, declaring his opposition to broad-based tax increases because, he says, they drive out jobs -- the same message the Bush administration has adhered to.</p>
        <p>He has also refused to criticize President Bush's proposal to cut federal taxes, even though New York Democrats say the elimination of a tax on dividends would cost New York State millions of dollars. The governor argues that a tax cut on dividends would help bolster the financial-services sector.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Pataki and his advisers have emphasized his anti-tax stance, pointing out that he is among a small number of governors who has not proposed broad-based tax increases to close an enormous gap -- about $11.5 billion for New York.</p>
        <p>On another front, he has espoused a second theme embraced by the national Republican Party: Virtually every public event he has held in the last few weeks has been about domestic security and law enforcement.</p>
        <p>He has also derided liberals in a recent flurry of letters to supporters; wrote an opinion piece for a newspaper supporting Miguel Estrada, a politically polarizing candidate whom President Bush nominated for a federal judgeship, and held an effusive ceremony in Albany honoring an influential Bush adviser who headed the Federal Emergency Management Agency, which many Democrats said botched the recovery effort in New York after Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>He has also refused to put the Bush administration on the spot on issues that he apparently cares deeply about, including acid rain and the Indian Point nuclear power plant.</p>
        <p>Most of all, though, his critics point out, the governor has been extremely low-key in appealing for aid from his allies in Washington, even as New York faces the worst fiscal crisis since the Great Depression, sees its economy lag behind the rest of the nation's and bears the ever-growing cost of defending itself against future terrorist attacks.</p>
        <p>Democrats, still smarting from the governor's ability to lure away part of their political base, are accusing the governor of putting the state's interests behind his own political ambitions and his concerns for the well-being of the national Republican Party.</p>
        <p>''He obviously has no interest in running for re-election in New York, because he's alienating the very same constituencies he courted during the last election,'' said Representative Jerrold L. Nadler, a Democrat from Manhattan. ''He's doing everything he can to ingratiate himself with the Bush administration and burnish his conservative credentials. The question is 'why.' ''</p>
        <p>Even some of the governor's Republican allies in Albany are beginning to question his motives. ''He's auditioning for a job in Washington,'' said one senior Republican in the State Legislature. ''To the degree he pushes for anything, it's behind the scenes. He's not going to publicly pressure the White House.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's advisers dismiss the claim that he is angling for a job in Washington, calling it preposterous. They point out he just devoted a great deal of effort to being re-elected, and now has four years to think about what he is going to do next. Meanwhile, they say, he is completely focused on shepherding the state through these difficult times.</p>
        <p>Talk of political motives, they said, is just sour grapes from Democrats who are trying to deflect attention from their own inability to achieve much of anything in a Congress they lost in the last election.</p>
        <p>They also contend that the governor has a deceptively understated style and has done a great deal through back channels: snagging Governors Island from the federal government, convincing the Bush administration to give New York greater flexibility in how it uses disaster aid, landing the 2004 Republican National Convention for New York City.</p>
        <p>There is, they said, no ideological shift on Mr. Pataki's part, noting that he has always been fiscally conservative. And, politically, they said, he has long supported Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The governor's spokeswoman, Lisa Dewald Stoll, said, ''While others criticize, the governor is going to continue to work cooperatively with the Bush administration to ensure New York gets what it deserves. Governor Pataki is not interested in headlines. He is interested in results.'' And, she said, he is frequently on the phone with senior administration officials, including the homeland security chief, Tom Ridge, pressing the state's case.</p>
        <p>The governor's low-key style has been recognized by influential party leaders. ''He is loyal and a team player,'' said Gov. Marc Racicot of Montana, the chairman of the National Republican Committee. ''He has been willing to do things for us that are not necessarily glamorous.''</p>
        <p>But the Assembly speaker, Sheldon Silver, and other Democrats have been saying that all the good will cultivated by the governor is doing no good for New York State, and they have been calling upon him to use his clout to get more federal aid and other support.</p>
        <p>''After the governor was re-elected, he determined to become a part of the national Republican Party and moved to the far right,'' said Mr. Silver, Mr. Pataki's main political rival in Albany. ''You have to wonder what his motives are.''</p>
        <p>Despite such goading, Governor Pataki has not changed his style. Last Friday, appearing on a New York City radio show, he deflected a question about getting additional aid from Washington and instead returned to his preferred theme: that terrorist threats are all around and his first priority is the public's safety, not money.</p>
        <p>The governor had responded much the same way a day earlier, at an event in Grand Central Terminal in which he announced heightened security on commuter rail lines to New York City. Asked whether he planned to go to Washington soon to meet with top administration officials to ask for financial assistance, as Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, also a Republican, had done a day earlier, he said: ''I'm certainly talking to the administration, first of all, about security, and also about the financial consequences'' of providing that security. But, he continued, ''our priority now is protecting the people of New York City and New York State.''</p>
        <p>For years, people close to the governor have hinted he has had an interest in running for national office or serving in a high-level position in a Republican administration. Indeed, in recent interviews, people close to him continue to make a case that he is a viable candidate beyond New York, if he ever decides to wade into national politics.</p>
        <p>But the governor's decision to play to a more conservative audience nationally may be hurting him in heavily Democratic New York. A recent poll conducted by Quinnipiac University showed his approval rating had fallen to a seven-year low of 49 percent, down from 62 percent last fall, just before he won re-election.</p>
        <p>The true test of whether the governor's play to the right will sell in New York may come soon: top Republicans in New York have been floating the idea that New York may be winnable for President Bush in 2004.</p>
        <p>At the very least, say people close to the governor, an all-out Republican effort to make New York appear competitive would unnerve the Democrats and force them to pour more campaign time and money into a state that Democrats have long assumed they could win easily.</p>
        <p>By this calculus, Mr. Pataki's stock in the national party would rise instantly, giving him a greater opportunity to land a high-ranking position in a second Bush term, if not a spot on the national ticket as Mr. Bush's running mate.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's beyond the realm of possibility,'' said one prominent New York Republican strategist who is close to the governor. ''It would be a tremendous coup for the governor if he could put New York in play.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver said he does not necessarily buy that scenario. But at the same time, he said, most people did not believe that Mr. Pataki could defeat Mario M. Cuomo, a national Democratic icon, in the 1994 race for governor.</p>
        <p>''He's always been a dreamer,'' Mr. Silver said, recalling that Mr. Pataki was an obscure state senator from Peekskill when he toppled Mr. Cuomo. ''Don't underestimate the man. He won when nobody thought he could.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
