<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A campaign by the Sierra Club chides General Motors about the Hummer's gas mileage.</title>
    <meta content="Y29ADC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/29/business/media/29ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1508060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hummer (High Mobility Multipurpose Vehicle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sierra Club</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7D61F3FF93AA15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A campaign by the Sierra Club chides General Motors about the Hummer's gas mileage.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sierra Club Site Parodies Hummer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Danny Hakim</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Club to unveil Website that satirizes General Motor's Hummer sport utility vehicle, which has been assailed by conservationists and others as gas-guzzler; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROBERT LUTZ, the cigar-wielding vice chairman and product czar for General Motors, has said that G.M. needs to stir passion by making ''love them or hate them'' vehicles.</p>
        <p>The Hummer, the current ''it'' sport utility vehicle in the creeping culture war over the S.U.V., certainly fits the bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A campaign by the Sierra Club chides General Motors about the Hummer's gas mileage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROBERT LUTZ, the cigar-wielding vice chairman and product czar for General Motors, has said that G.M. needs to stir passion by making ''love them or hate them'' vehicles.</p>
        <p>The Hummer, the current ''it'' sport utility vehicle in the creeping culture war over the S.U.V., certainly fits the bill.</p>
        <p>In the latest in a string of exchanges in which environmental groups and the auto industry have parried parody with parody, the Sierra Club today will unveil www.hummerdinger.com, a satirical broadside against G.M.'s Hummer brand. The Web site, created by a boutique ad agency in St. Louis called the Experiment, is in the mold of The Onion, the popular humor Web site that features deadpan delivery of absurdist news items.</p>
        <p>''G.M. celebrates Hummer's state-of-the-art 1950's engine technology with some of today's hottest stars'' reads the headline of what Hummerdinger.com bills as its top story, adding that Fabian, Pat Boone and Frankie Avalon have been lined up as pitchmen.</p>
        <p>The site includes a quiz to see if you're a ''Hummer hunk,'' a list of special accessories that include a custom horn that plays ''Ride of the Valkyries,'' and a place to send a chiding note to G.M. by e-mail.</p>
        <p>''The Hummer's tagline is 'Like Nothing Else.' But it should be 'Pollutes Like Nothing Else,' '' Daniel Becker, director of the Sierra Club's global warming and energy program, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>What does G.M. have to say to all of this?</p>
        <p>''If you look at what Hummer is, in terms of its impact on the fuel emissions that vehicles put out, its sales are 0.5 of 1 percent of the U.S. vehicle market,'' said Pete Ternes, a spokesman for Hummer. ''So if you consider that little factoid, what they're trying to do is use the popular image of Hummer to promote their cause, which is a P.R. tactic. There are much bigger fish to fry.''</p>
        <p>Hummers are the commercial version of the Humvee military transport, featured on television in Middle Eastern conflicts from the first Persian Gulf war right up to the current conflict in Iraq. Humvees and Hummers are manufactured by AM General, a privately held company in South Bend, Ind., but G.M. owns the rights to the Hummer brand.</p>
        <p>Hummer's relatively new H2 sport utility, a yuppie-friendly Hummer that starts at about $50,000, has been Detroit's hottest-selling luxury item for the last year. But there have been some signs of a cooling off.</p>
        <p>Until recently, the H2 was the only vehicle Detroit seemed to be able to sell without any incentives. But this month, G.M. began offering discounts to clear out its 2003 models, it said, before the 2004 models go on sale in September.</p>
        <p>''This model year close-out was part of the business plan from the beginning,'' said Wendy Orthman, a Hummer spokeswoman. ''It's a normal part of the business.''</p>
        <p>H2's supply has increased from only 13 days ahead of demand in the first months it went on sale a year ago to a more moderate 60- to 70-day supply. The company sold 2,445 H2's last month, its lowest sales for a full month.</p>
        <p>''We're up from that this month,'' Mr. Ternes said. ''We expect someplace closer to 3,000'' in July.</p>
        <p>Peter DeLorenzo, a former Detroit ad man who is now a consultant for the Chrysler Group, said of parody ads like Hummerdinger: ''The fringes are the only place where it matters. Ultimately, people buy what they want to buy depending on their financial situation and what turns them on. I don't think the battle between the pro-S.U.V. people and the anti-S.U.V. people, in the end, matters at all.''</p>
        <p>Michael Bernacchi, a marketing professor at the University of Detroit Mercy, said anti-S.U.V. campaigns, cumulatively, compelled the industry to keep such issues in mind.</p>
        <p>''It forces dialogue,'' he said, adding ''nobody can put together any car today without people in the company being devil's advocates about what the reaction is going to be.''</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club previously attacked the Ford Excursion, a 19-foot-long, 3 1/2-ton S.U.V. that it called the Ford Valdez -- and crowed last year when Ford said it would discontinue the vehicle. More recently, Arianna Huffington, the pundit and columnist, backed a TV campaign linking S.U.V.'s with financing terrorism because of their high gas consumption. And a small evangelical group started a ''What Would Jesus Drive?'' campaign that was much discussed.</p>
        <p>On the industry side, a wave of advertising in Capitol Hill publications and newspapers in crucial states surrounded a failed Senate effort last year to increase fuel economy standards. In one ad, a farmer was depicted worrying that increasing fuel economy would mean hauling hay in subcompact cars instead of pickups.</p>
        <p>More recently, an S.U.V. group run by one of the industry's leading public relations firms ran a ''What Would Jesús Drive?'' campaign featuring a man named Jesús Rivera who drives an S.U.V.</p>
        <p>For G.M., Hummers are a profit center in an era of rapidly diminishing profits -- and jobs -- in the automaking business.</p>
        <p>For environmental groups, the Hummer is an extreme example of what they see as a broader problem. With growing S.U.V. sales, the fuel economy of the average new vehicle sold in the United States fell to 20.4 miles a gallon in the 2002 model year, the last year for which complete sales data is available. That was a 22-year low.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of Hummerdinger.com is an animated video parody of the entrancing Hummer TV ads. One scene shows a Hummer driver strangled by anaconda-like gas pump hoses as money flies out of his pockets. In another, a bald, jowly figure labeled ''G.M executive'' steps in front of the Hummer's window mileage sticker, bellowing, ''You don't need to see that.''</p>
        <p>The depiction is wrong on two counts. G.M.'s top executives have their hair largely intact. And Hummers are so heavy they fall outside of the normal fuel economy regulations that govern cars and most S.U.V.'s. G.M. is not even required to post the mileage of Hummers.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
