<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mystic Seaport's New Home for Artifacts</title>
    <meta content="05MYST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1453911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mystic Seaport Museum (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wojtas, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3DD123FF936A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mystic Seaport's New Home for Artifacts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE WOJTAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wojtas, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Mystic Seaport's newly opened $16 million Collections Research Center which, within year, will house all of museum's artifacts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many years, tens of thousands of artifacts, like boat models, figureheads, paintings and even a jacket made from walrus intestine, were hidden away in the attics and basements of Mystic Seaport.</p>
        <p>Those days are over as the Seaport recently opened its $16 million Collections Research Center in a portion of a former velvet mill across the street from the museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many years, tens of thousands of artifacts, like boat models, figureheads, paintings and even a jacket made from walrus intestine, were hidden away in the attics and basements of Mystic Seaport.</p>
        <p>Those days are over as the Seaport recently opened its $16 million Collections Research Center in a portion of a former velvet mill across the street from the museum.</p>
        <p>Within a year, all the museum's artifacts, which include one million photographs and 100,000 sheets of ship's plans, will be cataloged and stored in climate-controlled rooms. The center also was built to protect the artifacts from fire and theft. The center, which is open only to researchers, also has video and audio production suites, an extensive photography area and space for the Seaport's merchandising program.</p>
        <p>During the grand-opening tour of the center in November, J. Revell Carr, the former Seaport president who oversaw much of the project's development, pointed out that the museum built its shipyard 30 years ago so it could properly care for its more than 550 boats.</p>
        <p>''The rest of the collection warranted that same kind of world-class care so that's why we needed this,'' Mr. Carr said. ''It's what should be here and now it is.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the museum's collection is so vast that 85 percent of the items are not on public display.</p>
        <p>One researcher who has had a look at the new center is Margherita Desy, the curator of the U.S.S. Constitution Museum in Boston.</p>
        <p>Ms. Desy, a former Seaport employee, remembers the days of searching attics and cellars for items. Now, when she was looking at ship models that her museum hopes to borrow for a new exhibition, she found it exciting to walk down a corridor, look through large windows and see the items in the Seaport's collection.</p>
        <p>''This is a kind of one-stop research shopping,' she said. ''It's what a lot of museums strive for because it's difficult for researchers to bounce from facility to facility and collection to collection. But here everything you need is under one roof.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Desy said word of the center has begun to spread among members of the Council of American Maritime Museums.</p>
        <p>''Now that it's open everyone is eager to come and use it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Collections Research Center, is the first phase of an ambitious project to turn the four-acre mill into the American Maritime Research and Education Center.</p>
        <p>Further plans call for renovating the remaining two-thirds of the building to create a hall where 500 boats that are now in storage could be placed on display indoors.</p>
        <p>While the Collections Research Center is not open to museum visitors to tour, the Seaport hopes a watercraft hall would have a public component.</p>
        <p>The first phase of the project was financed by federal and state grants as well as contributions from foundations and numerous individuals. It took two and a half years years to complete. Today, 30 staff members and 50 volunteers work in the center.</p>
        <p>Visitors enter a large lobby and walk down gleaming hallways decorated with maritime photographs and paintings from the Seaport's vast collection.</p>
        <p>Off to the sides are huge rooms containing the artifacts. In one, wooden ships' figureheads weighing up to two tons each stand in metal racks. A few feet away metal cabinets hold drawers full of scrimshaw, 1,400 pieces in all. Massive whale bones and jaws lie in another rack.</p>
        <p>In another section 1,000 half models of ships are mounted on wire mesh panels. The museum's 1,200 paintings hang on sliding panels. Two thousand models of ships, some of them as long as eight feet, sit on shelves.</p>
        <p>The museum's 400 sailing trophies, which had been hidden away in protective bags, are being polished and put on shelves. There are also thousands of pieces of glassware, sea chests, bottles, carvings, tools and pieces of art.</p>
        <p>All organic items, such as those made from wood, paper or textiles, have to be fumigated process before being placed in the center. The items must remain in a large tent filled with carbon dioxide for three to four weeks to kill any insect infestation.</p>
        <p>''We need to be sure before we put any item in the C.R.C.,'' Bill Peterson, the senior curator, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson, who has worked at the museum for 30 years, said that in the past if a researcher wanted to see a specific item such as a chronometer, a museum staffer would bring it to the person. To see the entire collection of chronometers, they would have to walk across the grounds to where the items were stored.</p>
        <p>In the new center, researchers can look at different types of artifacts without having to trek from building to building.</p>
        <p>''It has greatly enhanced how we do our work,'' Mr. Peteron said. ''The collection is right next to the collections information where it wasn't before. It's not only a big boost for us that work here but the people who use the collections.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Peterson said Seaport staffers were skeptical that the project would become a reality.</p>
        <p>''For people like me who've been here a long time it's a dream come true,'' he said. ''It just makes my job so much easier as curator to really be able to take care of things in the proper manner.</p>
        <p>William Cogar, the Seaport's vice president for collections and research, said the Collections Research Center was an important step in transforming the museum into the American Maritime Research and Education Center.</p>
        <p>''For people here and abroad who want to research American maritime history and culture we want them to know that Mystic Seaport is the place to do that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cogar said the new facility is among the best there is for historical artifacts and likened it to what exists at Colonial Williamsburg in Virginia.</p>
        <p>''As they do for that subject we do for American maritime history,'' he said. ''It's so wonderful to have a place where everything is its place.''</p>
        <p>Visiting the center last month with Mr. Carr was Representative Robert R. Simmons, a Republican in the Second District. He said the $3 million in federal funds given to the Seaport for the project was a good investment and that he would be seeking more to finish the mill.</p>
        <p>''The collection of objects and the historical record here is unparalleled in the world,'' Mr. Simmons said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
