<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Photos Bolster Idea of Water, and Possibly Life, on Mars</title>
    <meta content="Y20MARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1466310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Odyssey (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christiansen, Philip (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDB143DF933A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Photos Bolster Idea of Water, and Possibly Life, on Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA issues new theory and revised interpretation of earlier observations, bolstering idea that Mars has more water than previously thought and encouraging speculation about possibility of life on planet; identifies melting snow deposits in photographs taken by Mars Odyssey spacecraft as likely cause of many of planet's deep gullies; recent studies by other scientists, showing that both Martian polar regions are capped almost entirely with ice, noted; Dr Philip Christiansen, planetary scientist at Arizona State University who is proponent of new theory, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new theory and a revised interpretation of earlier observations have bolstered the idea that Mars has more water than previously thought and encouraged speculation about the possibility of life on the planet.</p>
        <p>The new theory, identifying melting snow deposits as the likely cause of the many deep gullies on the planet, was announced yesterday at a briefing at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in Washington. Photography from the Mars Odyssey spacecraft, orbiting the planet, inspired the suspected relation between melting snow and the gullies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new theory and a revised interpretation of earlier observations have bolstered the idea that Mars has more water than previously thought and encouraged speculation about the possibility of life on the planet.</p>
        <p>The new theory, identifying melting snow deposits as the likely cause of the many deep gullies on the planet, was announced yesterday at a briefing at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in Washington. Photography from the Mars Odyssey spacecraft, orbiting the planet, inspired the suspected relation between melting snow and the gullies.</p>
        <p>A week ago, other scientists reported new studies showing that both Martian polar regions are capped almost entirely with ice, enlarging the planet's known reservoir of water. Until recently, the huge southern cap was thought to be predominantly, if not entirely, frozen carbon dioxide, or dry ice.</p>
        <p>In yesterday's report, Dr. Philip Christensen, a planetary scientist at Arizona State University in Tempe, proposed that many of the eroded gullies on Mars were probably carved by water from melted snow flowing beneath a thick covering of packed snow. As a protective blanket, the covering was said to have warmed the deeper snow, thawing some of it and sheltering the flowing water from refreezing or evaporating in the thin atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Christensen said spacecraft photographs showed many gullies on the slopes of craters in the planet's midlatitudes. They appeared to be emerging from under remnants of extensive snowpacks.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Christensen explained, snow on Mars is most likely to accumulate most heavily on the coldest, pole-facing slopes, as seen in the photographs. The snow would presumably collect over the landscape through a period of deep cold, then would melt as the climate warmed.</p>
        <p>''Melting begins first in the most exposed area right at the crest of the ridge,'' he said. ''This explains why gullies start so high up.''</p>
        <p>Over time, geologists said, the flowing water left deep cuts in the surface in places thought improbable, like the crests of hills. Among the suggested explanations were seeping groundwater, pressurized flows of groundwater or carbon dioxide and mudflows from collapsing permafrost. None of these gained much support.</p>
        <p>But Dr. John Mustard, a planetary geologist at Brown University, called the melting-snow hypothesis ''very interesting and compelling'' and said it presented a ''fundamentally new perspective'' on the origin of Martian gullies.</p>
        <p>The research report is to be published soon in the journal Nature, but is already available on the journal's Web site (www.nature.com/nature).</p>
        <p>Biologists were particularly encouraged by the interpretation. One of them, Dr. Lynn Rothschild of NASA's Ames Research Center in Mountain View, Calif., said the ''possibility of liquid water on Mars right near the surface'' was intriguing evidence that some forms of life could exist on the planet.</p>
        <p>Dr. Christensen said of the gully landscapes, ''If life ever existed on Mars, I can think of no places where it would be more interesting to look for it.''</p>
        <p>In separate research, scientists at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena said they had found evidence to correct a decades-old model of what the Martian polar caps were like.</p>
        <p>When the first spacecraft flew close to Mars, in 1965, it determined that the planet's atmosphere was largely carbon dioxide. Scientists concluded that the two huge polar ice caps were frozen carbon dioxide. Even after a Viking spacecraft in the 1970's showed that the north polar caps contained water ice under a veneer of dry ice, scientists continued to believe that the south polar cap was dry ice.</p>
        <p>Now there is evidence to the contrary. Dr. Andrew Ingersoll of Caltech and his graduate student Shane Byrne reported in the Feb. 14 issue of the journal Science that new spacecraft data revealed that both polar caps were made mostly of frozen water.</p>
        <p>Examining pictures and infrared measurements of the polar caps, the researchers found wide and deep pits in the upper layer of frozen carbon dioxide. The pits penetrated to lower ice, which was too warm to be dry ice and so must be frozen water, the scientists said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
