<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="25FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1507054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0DF133FF936A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>DeLay to Visit Middle East With Doubts on Road Map  Tom DeLay, the House Majority Leader, will travel to the Middle East and take a message of grave doubt that the region is ready for a Palestinian state, as called for in the peace plan strongly advocated by the Bush administration and Europe.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Releases Hussein Photos  The United States released pictures to persuade the Iraqi public that Uday and Qusay Hussein were dead. A spokesman said many Iraqis remain so nervous about a Hussein dynasty comeback that they believe any conspiracy theory.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>DeLay to Visit Middle East With Doubts on Road Map  Tom DeLay, the House Majority Leader, will travel to the Middle East and take a message of grave doubt that the region is ready for a Palestinian state, as called for in the peace plan strongly advocated by the Bush administration and Europe.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Releases Hussein Photos  The United States released pictures to persuade the Iraqi public that Uday and Qusay Hussein were dead. A spokesman said many Iraqis remain so nervous about a Hussein dynasty comeback that they believe any conspiracy theory.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Three American soldiers were killed in an ambush south of Mosul. The ambush undermined hopes that the killing on Tuesday of Saddam Hussein's two sons would quell violence against American forces.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Vice President Dick Cheney mounted a counterattack against Democratic critics of the Iraq war, arguing that it would have been irresponsible to ignore Saddam Hussein's weapons program.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Foreign Minister Dominique de Villepin of France saluted the killing of Saddam Hussein's sons but said their deaths might prompt revenge attacks against American and other occupation forces.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.S. Rift Over Force for Liberia  The nation's two top military officers warned of dangers facing any American military involvement in Liberia. The descriptions of the risks of intervention exposed a rift between the military and Secretary of State Colin L. Powell, who favors sending forces to the country.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>France Revises Pension Law  The French Senate and the National Assembly approved a law that would force the French to work longer before becoming eligible to retire on a full pension. The campaign for the law by France's center-right government infuriated workers and union leaders, setting off strikes.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-15</p>
        <p>Joint Terror Report Cites Agency Failures  A report by the House and Senate intelligence committees criticized the performance of the F.B.I. and C.I.A. before the September 2001 terrorist attacks. It said the agencies did not heed repeated warnings that Al Qaeda intended to strike.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Recall Vote Set for October  California embarked on a rare 77-day election campaign as the lieutenant governor set Oct. 7 as the date for a recall vote on Gov. Gray Davis, left, and Republicans and Democrats turned up the political heat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Guard Testifies in Sniper Case  A prison guard testified that Lee Malvo, the younger of two suspects in the sniper shootings in the Washington area last fall, told him that he shot a teenage victim to anger Chief Charles A. Moose of the Montgomery County, Md., police.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Climate Plan Released  The White House released a comprehensive proposal to coordinate current efforts, and develop new ones, to study climate change.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Some Movement on Medicare  House and Senate negotiators reached a tentative agreement on some of the less contentious items in a bill to provide prescription drug benefits under Medicare.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Gay Marriage Opposition  Opposition to gay marriage has dropped significantly among Americans in recent years, according to a new poll by the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Earlier Human Migration Seen  Scientists studying the genetic signatures of Siberians and American Indians have found evidence that the first human migrations to the New World from Siberia probably occurred no earlier than 18,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Northeast States Agree To Reduce Emissions  Ten states in the Northeast, led by New York, have agreed to begin talks about creating what would be the first market-based compact in the nation aimed at reducing carbon dioxide emissions from power plants.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>New Jersey Boy Steals Bus  A 9-year-old boy from a rural town stole a schoolbus and took it on a 10-minute cruise down U.S. Route 40 and through his neighborhood. He has also taken a car, a riding lawn mower, and at least 20 bicycles, the police chief said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Ephedra Ban Is Backed  The commissioner of the Food and Drug Administration told House subcommittees that major-league baseball should ban use of the herbal stimulant ephedra, which was linked to the death of a young Baltimore Orioles pitcher in February.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Tyson Pleads Not Guilty  Mike Tyson pleaded not guilty to New York State charges in the beating of two men in a Brooklyn hotel lobby last month.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>Change on Martha's Vineyard  Black-owned shops and restaurants in Oak Bluffs, Mass., have closed and many black families are selling their homes to whites. Some see this shift as a loss of a heritage.</p>
        <p>F1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; E31-38</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Stanley H. Fuld  A judge who was known for his concern for civil liberties during the 27 years he served on New York State's highest court, he was 99.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10, 18</p>
        <p>Microsoft Looks to Future  Microsoft outlined a new corporate structure designed to help it weather a period of slow growth in the computer industry and disputed the idea that the information technology boom has ended for good.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>European Automakers Struggle  DaimlerChrysler and Peugeot reported sharply lower profits and investors prepared for a bleak summer for the European auto industry to continue when Volkswagen issues its earnings report on Friday.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Textile Companies Seek Help  A coalition of apparel industry groups struggling to compete with exports from China petitioned the federal government for new protections.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Roche Agrees to Buy Igen  Roche Holding agreed to buy Igen International for $1.26 billion -- and then give nearly the whole company back to Igen's shareholders in return for a perpetual license to certain patented technology.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: Before and after Sept. 11; wrong battle on TV diversity; the ''free trade'' fix is in; nature's lessons in Yosemite.</p>
        <p>Column: Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E25  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E29  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
