<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Some of It Will Be Their Legacy': The Data That Survived Disaster</title>
    <meta content="04MISS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/04/science/space/04MISS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030205T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Michael P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccool, William C (Cmdr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Husband, Rick D (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Laurel Salton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chawla, Kalpana (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, David M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E4D91038F937A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Some of It Will Be Their Legacy': The Data That Survived Disaster</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Some of It Will Be Their Legacy': The Data That Survived Disaster</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Feb. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers say that although space shuttle Columbia was lost, much of scientific data its crew members colected was not, and it will be their lasting legacy; review of scientific experiments undertaken by astronauts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though the space shuttle Columbia was lost, much of the scientific data its crew members collected was not, and it will be their lasting legacy, researchers said today.</p>
        <p>Many experiments, specimen and data sets vanished in the destruction of the shuttle, but scientists said the astronauts had transmitted a wealth of information from a number of experiments back to Earth during the 16-day research mission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though the space shuttle Columbia was lost, much of the scientific data its crew members collected was not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though the space shuttle Columbia was lost, much of the scientific data its crew members collected was not, and it will be their lasting legacy, researchers said today.</p>
        <p>Many experiments, specimen and data sets vanished in the destruction of the shuttle, but scientists said the astronauts had transmitted a wealth of information from a number of experiments back to Earth during the 16-day research mission.</p>
        <p>''We got about half of our data, more than enough to publish at least a couple of papers,'' said Dr. Paul D. Ronney of the University of Southern California, the lead scientist of a team that had a flame-making experiment aboard. ''The crew, which we got to know very well before the mission, did a terrific job.''</p>
        <p>The amount and quality of data retrieved from the mission vary greatly according to the field of study. Medical and biological experiments that depended upon returning specimens for examination or comparison with control samples on the ground were hardest hit, experts said. Work in the physical sciences and other fields that allowed data to be downloaded immediately tended to fare better.</p>
        <p>For example, a camera instrument to study the effects of dust storms on climate, called Meidex for Mediterranean Israeli Dust Experiment, was able to return much of the data it gathered, including night images of electromagnetic phenomena glowing above thunderstorms.</p>
        <p>During this mission, NASA restricted many of the television events it normally allows so that this communication capacity could be used for larger data downloads, a move that helped salvage information from many experiments.</p>
        <p>Ron D. Dittemore, the director of the space shuttle program, said the crew executed its science program perfectly. ''The folks on the ground were just ecstatic with the amount of science that they were reaping,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many experiments, including several designed to study stresses like bone and muscle loss that space flight puts on the body, were lost.</p>
        <p>One study, overseen by Dr. Arny Ferrando of the University of Texas Medical Branch in Galveston, was to measure how quickly bodies in space created new muscle and broke it down. The astronauts had blood drawn before breakfast, then 12 hours later, to trace an amino acid produced when muscles break down.</p>
        <p>The astronauts were supposed to go through this process twice before the launching, twice during the flight and twice after landing. Everything they ate, all medications they took, all exercise they did and where the women were in their menstrual cycles was to be logged.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the university said yesterday that no experiment data was sent to Earth.</p>
        <p>Despite these losses, Mr. Dittemore said data from other experiments were saved. ''Some of it was downlinked to the ground prior to entry,'' he said. ''Some of it will be their legacy.''</p>
        <p>That legacy includes data for the Solse-2 experiment, which tested two instruments to measure ozone levels in the Earth's atmosphere. When the experiment flew previously aboard a shuttle in 1997, problems limited the amount data that was gathered.</p>
        <p>This time, ''Everything just worked great,'' said Ernest Hilsenrath of NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., a leader of the experiment.</p>
        <p>The researchers have about half of the data that was sent down in real-time; the other half, which the researchers would have picked up after the shuttle landed, is lost.</p>
        <p>Current meteorological satellites look straight down, measuring total ozone concentrations. By looking at the edge of the planet, the Solse-2 instruments could deduce levels of ozone at different altitudes, by looking at the scattered light. Ozone scatters and absorbs specific wavelengths of light.</p>
        <p>''This was a demonstration test of how ozone is going to be routinely measured in future meteorological satellites,'' Mr. Hilsenrath said.</p>
        <p>Just from the pattern of stars it sees, a spacecraft using the StarNav navigation system being developed at Texas A&amp;M University can figure out where it is and where it is headed. The instrument, about the size of a shoebox, sent almost all of the data it was intended to gather. ''By and large, it was successful,'' said Dr. John L. Junkins, director of the Center for Mechanics and Control at Texas A&amp;M.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ronney at U.S.C. said his experiment, which used a combustion enclosure aboard the shuttle to produce the weakest flames possible, proved successful although he lost the high-resolution videotape the astronauts took of the flames. Scientists study weak combustion in hopes of finding ways to make engines more fuel efficient and less polluting.</p>
        <p>''We burned the weakest flame ever burned and the leanest mixture of fuel to air ever,'' he said, ''We were very pleased.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stein Sture of the University of Colorado said his experiment on how wet granular materials, like sand, behave under pressure was completed early in the flight and that he received all of his data. The experiment, which flew in space twice before, could help in understanding damage caused by earthquakes.</p>
        <p>''The experiment worked well and we got all of our data,'' Dr. Sture said. ''We will be eternally thankful to those astronauts.''</p>
        <p>Dr. J. Thomas McKinnon of the Colorado School of Mines in Golden said he also got most of his data from a water mist experiment designed to study ways to extinguish fires in spacecraft as well as on the ground. ''We loss some data; there are some gaps in what was downlinked,'' he said, ''But most of the value of the experiment is intact.''</p>
        <p>Dr. McKinnon also praised the dedication of the astronaut investigators, particularly Dr. Kalpana Chawla and Col. Ilan Ramon, the jet pilot who was Israel's first astronaut. ''They were working through their lunch breaks and on their own time,'' he said. ''They were just amazing, dedicated people.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gerard M. Faeth of the University of Michigan, who also used the combustion facility to do fire research on ways to reduce soot from burning, said his team had recovered only half its data because of problems with transmitting it. This was the third time the experiment had flown, and it had been refined for this mission, he said. ''Still, I'd call the experiment successful because we had a better quality data set than the other times,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Faeth and other researchers said they would acknowledge the astronauts' work in subsequent publications and presentations on their experiments.</p>
        <p>''They were our colleagues, part of our laboratories,'' he said of the astronauts. ''The price paid for this data was very high -- seven lives loss -- and we are grateful. These were people we liked a lot.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 5, 2003, Wednesday  A chart in Science Times yesterday with an article about the science experiments aboard the space shuttle Columbia reversed two images in some copies. A diagram by NASA should have appeared with text describing the shuttle's observations of the ozone layer; a photograph of Earth from Columbia should have appeared with a description of research on dust storms and climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 5, 2003, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times yesterday with an article about the science experiments aboard the space shuttle Columbia reversed two images in some copies. A diagram by NASA should have appeared with text describing the shuttle's observations of the ozone layer; a photograph of Earth from Columbia should have appeared with a description of research on dust storms and climate change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
