<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Lifts Market Share On Sales Burst In December</title>
    <meta content="Y04AUT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/04/business/04AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1453721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFD81F3FF937A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Lifts Market Share On Sales Burst In December</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.M. Raises Market Share and Increases Sales by 36%</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors Corp, intent on increasing its market share for second consecutive year, slashed prices in December that lifted sales 36 percent and helped it accomplish its goal; GM's share of US market, as high as 60 percent in early 1960's, stands at 28.7 percent; GM had its best December on record and posted 14.4 percent increase compared with month year earlier; Ford Motor Co posted gain of 8.2 percent for December and Chrysler unit of DaimlerChrysler reported 1 percent gain; graphs; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors, intent on increasing its market share for the second consecutive year, turned to a fire sale last month that lifted sales 36 percent and helped it accomplish its goal, according to figures released today.</p>
        <p>The back-to-back annual gain in market share was the first since 1976, but it was made possible by zero percent financing deals and reliance on less profitable sales to corporate and rental fleets. Now Wall Street and Detroit are wondering whether several years of outsize vehicle sales, propped up by increasingly large incentives from the Big Three, will make a feast or famine of 2003. Added to that is the uncertain economy and the potential for war in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>General Motors, intent on increasing its market share, turned to a fire sale that lifted sales and helped it accomplish its goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>General Motors, intent on increasing its market share for the second consecutive year, turned to a fire sale last month that lifted sales 36 percent and helped it accomplish its goal, according to figures released today.</p>
        <p>The back-to-back annual gain in market share was the first since 1976, but it was made possible by zero percent financing deals and reliance on less profitable sales to corporate and rental fleets. Now Wall Street and Detroit are wondering whether several years of outsize vehicle sales, propped up by increasingly large incentives from the Big Three, will make a feast or famine of 2003. Added to that is the uncertain economy and the potential for war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>''I think the industry is on a terrible treadmill,'' said John Casesa, an analyst for Merrill Lynch, who expects industry sales to fall to 16.2 million cars and trucks this year from 16.8 million in 2002, which was the fourth-best year on record for United States sales.</p>
        <p>''They used big discounts in December, and now they have to deal with the aftermath in January,'' Mr. Casesa added.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s share of the United States market, as high as 60 percent in the early 1960's, stands at 28.7 percent. For the industry, G.M.'s big month led to the best December on record and a 14.4 percent increase compared with the month a year earlier, according to Ward's AutoInfoBank, a company in Southfield, Mich., that tracks auto sales.</p>
        <p>For December, Ford posted a gain of 8.2 percent and the Chrysler unit of DaimlerChrysler reported a 1 percent increase, but it was G.M. that had the blowout month.</p>
        <p>''G.M. had an excellent year in 2002 on all fronts,'' John Smith, group vice president for North American vehicle sales, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Mack McPherson, sales manager at Burt Chevrolet in Englewood, Colo., a suburb of Denver, said his dealership sold 246 new Chevy cars and trucks last month, compared with fewer than 200 in October and November. It was propelled by huge sales for the Suburban and Tahoe sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>''They put zero percent on those two vehicles around the 18th or 20th, and they took off,'' he said. ''People just went crazy.''</p>
        <p>''Getting all those commercials, and zero percent, and the cash back, that drives the market,'' he said. ''As soon as people hear that, they say, 'Honey, it's time to go buy a car.' ''</p>
        <p>Suburbans, Tahoes and other light trucks -- a government classification that includes sport utility vehicles, trucks and minivans -- outsold passenger cars for the second consecutive year.</p>
        <p>In 1980, only about a fifth of sales came from light trucks. The growth of light trucks, particularly S.U.V.'s, has increased the gas consumption of the average automobile despite advances in technology and has led environmentalists into an increasingly adversarial relationship with Detroit over issues like emissions of greenhouse gases and smog-forming pollutants.</p>
        <p>It has also had considerable safety implications; light trucks have a higher death rate for their own occupants because of their tendency to roll over, and they pose increased dangers when they collide with passenger cars.</p>
        <p>But light trucks are Detroit's chief profit center at a time of only modest profitability and fierce competition from abroad.</p>
        <p>Of particular concern for analysts is the disparity in what the Big Three and foreign automakers spend on incentives. G.M. spent $2,431 a vehicle for the year through November, and that almost certainly rose in December. By comparison, Toyota spends $526 a vehicle on incentives, according to the Autodata Corporation. G.M. announced an extensive new round of incentive offers today, including many five-year, zero percent offers and financing as low as 1.9 percent on six-year deals.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, this is just kind of more of the same,'' said Rod Lache, an analyst for Deutsche Bank. ''The auto industry lowers prices and the market responds, but I don't think this is a good thing for automakers. These guys are going for volume instead of profitability, and that's not constructive for the industry.''</p>
        <p>Jim O'Connor, the head of the Ford division of Ford Motor, said: ''Affordability has been very favorable for consumers, and I think it will continue to drive retail sales. Some people might be skittish about some uncertainties, perhaps in the Mideast, but you certainly can't prove it when you look at vehicle sales.''</p>
        <p>Ford also spent heavily on incentives last month, though Mr. O'Connor said the company spent about 25 percent less than G.M. Officials at Chrysler said they also decided not to match G.M.'s incentives.</p>
        <p>''The industry went in to kind of an incentive spending spree during the month of December,'' said Gary E. Dilts, Chrysler's senior vice president for sales. ''We elected not to participate at the highest level of that spending spree. That's bad news if you're counting the sales tickets in the month of December, it's good news if you're managing the profitability of the Chrysler Group.''</p>
        <p>Diane Swonk, an economist at Bank One, said the big month ''shows what we knew all along, that the consumer that everyone thought couldn't hold it up was an Atlas and shouldered the burden of the economy.'' Ms. Swonk took advantage of the deals and traded in her Saturn for a CTS, the flashy, sharp-edged new sedan from Cadillac. She says she thinks sales will fall to about 15.8 million cars and trucks this year.</p>
        <p>''There's got to be some givebacks, but that's what we all said last year,'' she added.</p>
        <p>She says she does believe, though, that earnings can hold up because of productivity gains.</p>
        <p>Mr. Casesa is less optimistic. He predicts G.M.'s earnings will fall to $3 a share this year from a projected $6.67 a share last year and that Ford's earnings will decline to 30 cents a share this year from an estimated 45 cents last year.</p>
        <p>David Healy, an analyst at Burnham Securities, said G.M. ''did achieve their goal of two years in a row of higher market share; on the other hand I think they pulled in some of their January volume into December and as a result January sales could be kind of sick.''</p>
        <p>Paul Ballew, G.M.'s chief industry sales analyst, said, ''We do believe there is a bit of payback as we've stressed previously though we don't want to overstate that.''</p>
        <p>Over all, sales in 2002 fell 2 percent from 2001, which was the second-best year, with 17.2 million vehicles sold. Several foreign automakers had their best years ever, including BMW, with sales up 20 percent; Honda, which posted a 3.3 percent rise; and Toyota, whose sales were up 1 percent. By comparison, G.M.'s sales fell about 1 percent, while Ford's dropped 8.8 percent and Chrysler's declined 3 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
