<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will Calgary Be the Next Kuwait?</title>
    <meta content="14TALW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/14/opinion/14TALW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1511830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Talwani, Manik (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venezuela</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFD91F31F937A2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will Calgary Be the Next Kuwait?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Will Calgary Be the Next Kuwait?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Manik Talwani</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Talwani, Manik (Prof)</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Prof Manik Talwani says largest deposits of oil in world are in Venezuela and Canada, but they consist of forms of 'heavy oil' that require expensive process to be converted into so-called syncrude; says expanding heavy oil production to make it significant part of American energy strategy will require huge investment; says policy makers must decide whether risks of global market instability and foreign-policy consequences of relying on Middle Eastern oil are severe enough to make switching to heavy oil a priority; says payoff is clear, not only for Canada and Venezuela but also for American energy security and foreign policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America has many reasons for its risky involvement in Middle East politics, but there is no question that dependence on imported oil plays a very large role. The fact is, however, that the largest deposits of oil in the world are not in the Middle East -- or in Russia or off West Africa or in the Caspian Sea area, for that matter. They are in two Western Hemisphere countries: Venezuela and Canada.</p>
        <p>The catch is that they consist of bitumen and other forms of ''heavy oil'' -- petroleum buried in sand deposits that requires a special refining process to be converted into so-called syncrude. This conversion is expensive, but the end product has all the favorable qualities of conventional light oil. And these heavy oil deposits occur in mindbogglingly large quantities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Venezuela and Canada have vast deposits of "heavy oil" which, while expensive to refine, could decrease American dependence on Middle East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America has many reasons for its risky involvement in Middle East politics, but there is no question that dependence on imported oil plays a very large role. The fact is, however, that the largest deposits of oil in the world are not in the Middle East -- or in Russia or off West Africa or in the Caspian Sea area, for that matter. They are in two Western Hemisphere countries: Venezuela and Canada.</p>
        <p>The catch is that they consist of bitumen and other forms of ''heavy oil'' -- petroleum buried in sand deposits that requires a special refining process to be converted into so-called syncrude. This conversion is expensive, but the end product has all the favorable qualities of conventional light oil. And these heavy oil deposits occur in mindbogglingly large quantities.</p>
        <p>Along the north shore of the Orinoco River in Venezuela, in an area known as the Faja de Orinoco, the Venezuelan national oil company estimates that 1.2 trillion barrels of heavy oil lie within a few thousand feet of the surface. A representative of Total, the oil giant, said that as of now only 5 percent to 10 percent of the oil can be recovered. Yet he estimated that technical improvements could raise recovery rates to around 25 percent. If so, this would eventually mean some 300 billion barrels of usable crude.</p>
        <p>Canada's deposits are even larger: estimates range from 1.6 trillion to 2.5 trillion barrels of bitumen (which is also called ''oil sands'' or ''tar sands''). About 9 percent of the deposits are relatively close to the surface and should have very high recovery rates -- at least 50 percent and possibly up to 90 percent. Combining this with a very modest 5 percent recovery rate for the deeper bitumen, and the country's total potential reserves can be estimated at 174 billion to 271 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>Thus the total potential of the two countries nearly equals the 600 billion barrels remaining in the Middle East reserves. The problem, of course, is that harvesting and converting the heavy oil would require huge investments and improvements in technology by the international oil conglomerates. Being viscous, it is difficult to get out of the ground and to transport. It is expensive to upgrade, and refining it produces more sulfur dioxide as well as carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases than production and refining of conventional oil.</p>
        <p>Heavy oil will probably never be as cheap as Middle East crude -- but it is much closer to home, geologists know exactly where it is, and one big producer is our politically stable northern neighbor. So should the United States make the Western Hemisphere's heavy oil reserves a focus of its long-term energy strategy?</p>
        <p>Consider the alternatives. We now import more than half of our annual requirement of seven billion barrels. Domestic oil reserves are about 28 billion barrels and thus can, by themselves, supply the nation's need for only about four years. Estimates for the recoverable oil in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, should we decide to exploit it, range from 4 billion to 12 billion barrels, enough for 6 to 20 months. Clearly, even if Americans suddenly all switched to Toyota Priuses, domestic reserves could not supply their needs for long.</p>
        <p>Another course -- moving toward cleaner, renewable sources of energy -- would be great, but is unlikely to happen soon. Popular opinion is strongly against nuclear fission, and we are decades from making solar energy or any other alternative a significant factor in our supply.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, we will not wean ourselves from imported oil for decades. And heavy oil has some things to recommend it. Oil reserves are rapidly dwindling in the Middle East, and Saudi Arabia alone keeps producing nine million barrels a day. By contrast, just two million barrels of heavy oil are produced each day, and there's plenty of it.</p>
        <p>And technological advances are being made (the price of Canadian bitumen has dropped by two-thirds since the 1970's). These include the use of satellite technology to measure minute amounts of ground upheaval in shallow reservoirs, and the pumping of steam into the reservoirs to make the oil less viscous (a technique that is constantly being improved through new seismic monitoring technology). There is also a promising new strategy for transportation: mixing the heavy oil with conventional lighter oil, which can then be sent through a pipeline to an upgrading facility.</p>
        <p>Of course, expanding heavy oil production to make it a significant part of our energy strategy will require a huge investment. For example, oil companies have estimated that achieving just an additional 200,000 barrels a day of converted Venezuelan heavy oil would take some $3 billion in research and new refining capacity. Extrapolating such figures is hard to do, but a back of the envelope calculation indicates that it could take more than $100 billion to bring Venezuelan daily production up to Saudi levels.</p>
        <p>Thus American policy makers may have to decide whether the risks of global market instability and the foreign-policy consequences of relying on Middle Eastern oil are severe enough to make switching to heavy oil a priority. Doing so would mean persuading the oil giants to make huge investments. Federal subsidies would have to be a consideration, although more subtle changes in our tax code and import rules could be tried to give the companies proper incentive. Washington would also have to make solid trade agreements with Venezuela and Canada to guarantee long-term access, and would have to come up with new industrial regulations that take environmental concerns into account.</p>
        <p>There is no way to put a price tag on this idea. But the payoff is clear, not only for Canada and Venezuela, but also for American energy security and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Manik Talwani is a professor of geophysics at Rice University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Manik Talwani is a professor of geophysics at Rice University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
