<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Extreme Weather, Defensive Gardening</title>
    <meta content="20CTYC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/20/garden/20CUTT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1505845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DB113CF933A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Extreme Weather, Defensive Gardening</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Extreme Weather, Defensive Gardening</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE weather this year has forced me to start keeping records. If I don't end up with documentation of global warming, I will at least end up with better notes on how to grow eggplant.</p>
        <p>After record snowfalls, followed by early rains, spring-blooming trees and shrubs never looked better. And those crabapples, lilacs, viburnums and magnolias seemed to last for weeks longer than usual. Then came torrential downpours and cold days -- followed by extreme heat. Last week, a violent shower with high winds toppled two of my cousin's 300-year-old locust trees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The weather this year has wreaked havoc on gardens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE weather this year has forced me to start keeping records. If I don't end up with documentation of global warming, I will at least end up with better notes on how to grow eggplant.</p>
        <p>After record snowfalls, followed by early rains, spring-blooming trees and shrubs never looked better. And those crabapples, lilacs, viburnums and magnolias seemed to last for weeks longer than usual. Then came torrential downpours and cold days -- followed by extreme heat. Last week, a violent shower with high winds toppled two of my cousin's 300-year-old locust trees.</p>
        <p>But my biggest failure this summer has been those stunted little plants I bought at a farm stand because I had failed to start eggplant from seed. They looked healthy enough when I jammed them into the cold clay between pounding rainstorms. I knew the soil was too wet, because it formed a hard gooey ball when I grabbed a handful and squeezed. But I had to be away the next week and felt pressed to get those roots in the ground. So I went down to the raised bed, making holes every foot or so, dropping in a bit of light, dry compost first.</p>
        <p>When I returned a week later, the eggplants were struggling in soil that looked like concrete. Some pepper plants, which I had put out in the same wave of impatience, had lost all their little white blossoms from the cold nights. Seed potatoes were slow to sprout, and when they did, I had to help out by prying bits of clay away from their tender shoots.</p>
        <p>When flea beetles attacked the eggplants, chewing tiny holes in their felt-like leaves, I thought back to remedies I had used years ago, when my first garden was devastated by these tiny hard-backed insects. Nothing, including extremely rank garlic juice, worked until I hooked up my vacuum cleaner to a very long extension cord and went after them with the hose.</p>
        <p>Because my garden is now a football field's length from an electrical outlet, I decided to try an organic bug repellent made from the seeds of the neem tree, which is native to India and whose leaves have also long been used as a pesticide and disinfectant. After mixing the oil-based solution with water and donning rubber gloves, per the instructions, I carefully spritzed the plants' stems and leaves in the early morning.</p>
        <p>I don't know if it was the oil, or the attention I began giving my sickly plants -- pulling the weeds, cultivating the soil a bit to loosen up those clods, dosing it with a bit of seaweed fertilizer -- but they have begun to perk up and put out new leaves.</p>
        <p>I could have avoided the pesticide altogether had I draped the seedlings with Reemay, or spun polyester, immediately after planting. The spun fabric allows air, light and water to reach the plants, but screens out a many insects, including little moths and butterflies that lay their eggs on the undersides of leaves. The white veils make the garden look a bit like a hospital ward, but at certain times of year they can save a crop and eliminate the use of pesticides, even organic ones, which have their price. Neem oil, for example, is toxic to bees and aquatic organisms.</p>
        <p>The best approach, of course, is no pesticides at all, and this crop of flea beetles was a strong indicator of what my vegetable plot truly lacks: good soil, a diverse planting of flowers and herbs to attract beneficial insects, and better timing on the part of the gardener.</p>
        <p>I neglected to rake in lime last fall, and clay soil tends to be acidic. It also would benefit from about four inches of compost dug into every raised bed, or better yet, a cover crop of some member of the pea family, like clover, vetch or alfalfa. These legumes are known as nitrogen-fixers, because they are able to absorb gaseous nitrogen through bacteria on their roots, making it available to plants as well as fertilizing the soil. Turning these crops into the soil also adds organic matter, which feeds earthworms and micro-organisms, lightening it up in the process. Instead, I had jumped the gun and planted in leaden soil.</p>
        <p>THE zinnias sat for weeks as if shell-shocked. One valiant basil plant is now growing beneath a tomato plant. The rest of the seeds never germinated. The sunflowers, three rows on the north end of the vegetable patch, took a while to germinate but are thriving. Now I hope for a late frost, since they will be so late in flowering.</p>
        <p>The spinach and arugula, which I had planted on a balmy day in early March, in a well-prepared bed near the kitchen, provided a bounty of early greens. But great timing wasn't the only factor: that soil is also teeming with earthworms and it drains well, thanks to years of compost and fall doses of manure.</p>
        <p>So now I know: the soil in my vegetable plot is far too heavy and acidic for growing healthy plants. I also need to plant drifts of flowers and herbs -- coneflowers, yarrow, flowering buckwheat, milkweed, Queen Anne's lace, asters, bee balm, borage and salvia -- to attract an army of tiny predators to protect my crops.</p>
        <p>And this year, instead of planting second crops in August, I'll test the soil, add enough lime to bring up the alkalinity and wait a week. Then I'll put in a cover crop of vetch or red clover.</p>
        <p>Come spring, I'll turn it over, wait a month for that green matter to start decomposing -- and grab another handful of soil. If it's as crumbly as chocolate cake, I'll know I'm off to a good start. And if the rains come, I will just have to wait.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
