<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Martin Not Ready To Retire Just Yet</title>
    <meta content="29OPEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/29/sports/tennis/29open.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1515583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Todd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verkerk, Martin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4D81F39F93AA1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Martin Not Ready To Retire Just Yet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Retirement? It's Not for Martin, at Least Not Yet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Todd Martin says he is not ready to retire from professional tennis; defeats Martin Verkerk to advance to third round of US Open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His graying temples are well on their way to becoming gray hair. His footwork bears an increasing resemblance to just plain work, yet despite all the hints his American peer group has been dropping in the past week, Todd Martin is not ready to join the middle-aged rush for the door.</p>
        <p>He already looks like a soccer dad, and his infant son might make him one in the years to come, but for now, Martin remains content to put his flat returns and still-penetrating serve to the test against the younger set, then rehash the day's sweaty events in complete, well-constructed sentences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Todd Martin is the best American player of his generation who never quite became a tennis star, and he is back in the third round of the U.S. Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His graying temples are well on their way to becoming gray hair. His footwork bears an increasing resemblance to just plain work, yet despite all the hints his American peer group has been dropping in the past week, Todd Martin is not ready to join the middle-aged rush for the door.</p>
        <p>He already looks like a soccer dad, and his infant son might make him one in the years to come, but for now, Martin remains content to put his flat returns and still-penetrating serve to the test against the younger set, then rehash the day's sweaty events in complete, well-constructed sentences.</p>
        <p>A two-time Grand Slam singles finalist, Martin is the best American player of his generation who never quite became a tennis star, and he is back in the third round of the United States Open. Martin advanced yesterday after an occasionally shaky but ultimately successful match in Arthur Ashe Stadium against 16th-seeded Martin Verkerk, the Dutchman who charmed and served his way out of anonymity into this year's French Open final.</p>
        <p>Martin's 6-3, 6-4, 6-7 (5), 7-6 (9) victory was one of the exclamation points in a season that has been full of periods of doubt. But for a player who is 33 years old and ranked 93rd in the world, it is difficult to avoid polite questions that include the ''r'' word, particularly when Pete Sampras and Michael Chang have already retired this week.</p>
        <p>''I'm sort of in a constant state of reassessment; whether I do well or don't do well here, it's on my mind,'' said Martin, who is older than everyone in the men's draw except top-seeded Andre Agassi, who is two months older. Agassi advanced more convincingly last night, with a 7-6 (1), 6-1, 6-4 victory over Andreas Vinciguerra, a baseliner from Sweden.</p>
        <p>Agassi will play Yevgeny Kafelnikov of Russia, a former Australian Open and French Open champion, in the next round. Agassi knows Kafelnikov well enough to call him ''Y-man.'' Martin will next face a young American on the rise, Robby Ginepri, who upset 23rd-seeded Wayne Ferreira of South Africa, 6-2, 6-4, 6-7 (0), 6-2.</p>
        <p>It was another day of constant sunshine. Some of those closest to the ozone layer in the vast upper reaches of Arthur Ashe stadium put up parasols. It was also a day for huge attendance numbers: the combined total of 56,183 fans was a record. Most importantly, it was a day of compelling matches.</p>
        <p>Lleyton Hewitt, who won the United States Open two years ago and is seeded sixth this year, dropped the first set against Hyung Taik Lee of South Korea, then needed four match points in the fourth set to close out his victory.</p>
        <p>Jelena Dokic, seeded 22nd, appeared to have her nerves and her second-round encounter with Mary Pierce under control when she saved a match point in the second set, then jumped to a 5-1 lead in the third.</p>
        <p>But Dokic, who has dropped out of the top 10 this year, still found a way to lose in three sets, bolstering Pierce's continuing comeback from injuries and giving further evidence of Dokic's disarray.</p>
        <p>She has decided to distance herself this season from her volatile father, Damir, who has clashed with tennis authorities and journalists and who influenced Jelena's decision to leave Australia, where she trained as a youngster, for their native Yugoslavia. Instead of living with her parents in Belgrade, she has moved to Monte Carlo and tried out two coaches: first Steffi Graf's former mentor Heinz Gunthardt and now Borna Bikic. But Dokic's results have regressed. She looks rather world weary, or perhaps she is simply weary after playing 31 tournaments this year, more than anyone else ranked in the top 80.</p>
        <p>''There are events that go on off the court,'' she said. ''You know, sometimes this can affect a player. I usually deal with this fine, but it's new territory for me. It's all come at the same time in the same year. I work hard still. I love to play. Hopefully, it will come back.''</p>
        <p>Pierce, who once had to distance herself from her own volatile father, Jim, is still trying to prove that she can come back. One of the game's biggest hitters, she has struggled with ankle, shoulder and back injuries since winning the 2000 French Open and has had difficulty controlling her weight.</p>
        <p>''I had to start basically from zero a year or two ago,'' Pierce said. ''When I won the French Open, I just felt like I was starting to scratch the surface of coming into myself and my potential, so I just feel like I haven't really done everything that's in me to accomplish in tennis.''</p>
        <p>Since reuniting with her former coach Sven Groeneveld this spring, she has reached the fourth round at Wimbledon and the third round here. Second-seeded Justine Henin-Hardenne and sixth-seeded Jennifer Capriati advanced easily yesterday. Henin-Hardenne defeated Silvia Talaja of Croatia, 6-1, 6-2, and Capriati overwhelmed Martina Sucha of Slovakia, 6-1, 6-1.</p>
        <p>It was hardly a disastrous day for the Slovaks. Their best men's player, Karol Kucera, eliminated 24th-seeded Mardy Fish in straight sets. Fish arrived in New York on a roll after reaching the final in Cincinnati and losing a tight match to Andy Roddick. But against the smooth-moving Kucera, he failed to capitalize on any of his four set points in the second-set tie breaker. Though Kucera was treated for a sore back at 2-2 in the third set, he still closed out the victory, and gave Fish, Roddick and the Americans a preview of how competitive their Davis Cup match could be next month against the Slovaks.</p>
        <p>The Slovaks have built a new outdoor stadium in Bratislava for the match, which will be played on clay. ''We are very excited to have the Americans come, especially to come on our clay,'' said Kucera's teammate Dominik Hrbaty, who lost in straight sets yesterday to 11th-seeded Paradorn Srichaphan.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
