<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Bustling North Pole, Here Today, Gone Tomorrow</title>
    <meta content="28POLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/28/international/28POLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1484608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camp Borneo (Arctic Ocean)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Positioning System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Positioning System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7DB133DF93BA15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Bustling North Pole, Here Today, Gone Tomorrow</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At the Bustling North Pole, Life Is a Merry-Go-Round</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>CAMP BORNEO, in the Arctic Ocean, April 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Risk-takers are crisscrossing, probing and camping out in increasing numbers on North Pole's shifting ice veneer; northward rush has been simplified by satellite phones and global-positioning devices that allow trekkers and scientists to know their position even when compasses spin uselessly; sun rises in Mar and sets in Sept, and icescape shifts moment to moment; Camp Borneo, floating way station run by entrepreneurs from Russia and France since 1992, attracts tourists and scientists as both Everest-style base bamp and hub for researchers studying shifting climate and ocean patterns; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most things about the top of the world are as they have been for ages. It remains a frigid realm where milling floes of ice form a white cap atop an ocean that is two miles deep.</p>
        <p>Unlike the South Pole, where 29 countries have set up bases for research and hegemony on snow-cloaked terra firma, up here all is as fleeting as the sparkles from the fine ice crystals -- ''diamond dust,'' some visitors call it -- that coat surfaces and float in shadows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Humans, ever the adaptive, inquisitive, risk-taking species, are crisscrossing, probing and camping out in increasing numbers at the North Pole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most things about the top of the world are as they have been for ages. It remains a frigid realm where milling floes of ice form a white cap atop an ocean that is two miles deep.</p>
        <p>Unlike the South Pole, where 29 countries have set up bases for research and hegemony on snow-cloaked terra firma, up here all is as fleeting as the sparkles from the fine ice crystals -- ''diamond dust,'' some visitors call it -- that coat surfaces and float in shadows.</p>
        <p>On a globe or map the geographic pole may be a dot, but up close it is a shifting sea-ice carousel that guarantees any visitor is granted only a short stay. If you camp at the pole today, you will be four or five miles away tomorrow.</p>
        <p>But the North Pole is rapidly becoming busy. Humans, ever the adaptive, inquisitive, risk-taking species, are crisscrossing, probing and camping out in increasing numbers on the ice veneer, particularly in the window from mid-March to early May, when winter's cold has ebbed but summer's thaw has not yet turned surfaces into knee-deep slush.</p>
        <p>The northward rush has been simplified by satellite phones and global-positioning devices that allow trekkers and scientists to know their position even where compasses spin uselessly, the sun rises in March and sets in September, and the icescape shifts moment to moment.</p>
        <p>Since 1992, almost everyone who ventures to the pole first stops at this seasonal, floating way station, run by entrepreneurs from Russia and France for tourists and scientists as both an Everest-style base camp and a hub for researchers studying shifting climate and ocean patterns.</p>
        <p>It has rows of domed red and yellow tents with thermostat-controlled heat, two Russian helicopters and a runway big enough to accommodate 20-ton planes coming from northern Canada, Siberia and Norway. The mess hall has four stacked white microwave ovens and a Nescafe espresso machine.</p>
        <p>Any notion that this is a comfortable place, however, is jettisoned when one spots the slug-loaded shotguns set here and there, lest a polar bear seeking seals stumble upon a skier or oceanographer. Of course there is the cold, which even now rarely rises above 5 below zero.</p>
        <p>Even as Camp Borneo, 60 miles from the North Pole, has grown busier -- half a dozen Muscovite skydivers showed up on Saturday to jump at the pole -- another long-term presence has blossomed. On Friday, senior Russian officials flew to an ice camp several dozen miles east of the pole to inaugurate a new polar drifting ice station that would be home to several scientists for the coming year.</p>
        <p>Today, the Russian Orthodox Easter, started with a daylight-midnight round of vodka and Cognac drinking. Then several British trekkers retired to the camp manager's tent to watch the film ''Studio 54'' on the flat-screen television.</p>
        <p>Others wandered the edges of the widening ''lead'' of open water that curled halfway around the camp. A seal popped its head up several times, providing the only glimpse of the north's rare wildlife for days and bringing talk of polar bears, which follow the scent of seals from miles away.</p>
        <p>Late in the day, however, everyone dropped everything to gawk as Natalya Liberman, 39, the runner-up in the 2002 Mrs. Russia contest, swept out of her red tent in a floor-length white fur coat and sparkling tiara to pose on the ice.</p>
        <p>A visit to the pole was the grand prize in the contest, but the victor did not want to go, giving the honor to Mrs. Liberman, who flew north with the contingent of Muscovite skydivers.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union maintained an unbroken string of staffed drifting ice stations from 1937 until 1991, when the government collapsed. They provided valuable data on ocean trends in the Arctic, and American polar scientists said today that the revival of the program would help improve climate forecasts.</p>
        <p>Both Camp Borneo and the research station face a continual threat from the ever shifting ice around the pole. Ridges erupt and rise and leads miles long appear where solid surfaces had sat silent just hours before. Several times in the last decade, camp operators, warned by only minutes of quakelike rumbles, had to scramble to move tents before leads opened beneath them.</p>
        <p>Shifting Arctic ice has become a prime focus of scientists trying to understand the possible ramifications of global warming. There have been late-summer retreats of the polar ice cap for 24 years, although a lack of long-term data means no one can yet say if the change is a result of some natural cycle or is linked to rising concentrations of heat-trapping greenhouse gases in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>To try to fill the information gap, a team led by oceanographers from the University of Washington has gone to the pole for the last three years to place instruments on and under the ice to measure temperature, salinity, solar radiation and other conditions.</p>
        <p>''Because of the ice, satellites can't see down below a few inches,'' said Dr. Jamie Morison, the leader of the North Pole Environmental Observatory, as the project is called. ''Some data you have to get by going places.''</p>
        <p>In one spot 30 miles from the pole, divers from the university melted a hole through nine feet of ice and then plunged into the 28-degree water to retrieve a two-mile-long string of instruments left a year ago to record ocean conditions.</p>
        <p>Scientists remain a minority at Camp Borneo, however. About 200 visitors have been coming each season since the late 1990's, said Christian de Marliave, a outdoorsman from Paris who was a co-creator of the camp 10 years ago and still manages many of its often hectic affairs. Camp Borneo -- pronounced BAR-nee-oh in Russian -- was the call sign of a Russian radio operator in the far north and was transferred to the camp's radio.</p>
        <p>Tourists and adventure seekers spend $9,000 to $15,000 to pop Champagne corks and pose briefly on the ice or ski for a week across the ragged frozen seascape.</p>
        <p>Many are drawn by the same force that pulled hundreds of explorers to ice-locked deaths over the last three centuries. Some crave risks, crossing the shifting ice on skis, dropping in on parachutes, diving beneath it with scuba gear.</p>
        <p>No devices exist to predict where leads will form, so adventurers bound for the pole have adopted various approaches to getting past obstacles. Some carry cold-water dry suits and jump in and swim, towing their gear. Some ski around the gap, or use their towed sleds like boats. Others say if you wait overnight, a fresh skin of ice usually forms, allowing free passage.</p>
        <p>The ice often wins out.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, one of the Russian helicopters returned to camp with six South Korean skiers who had to abandon their effort to ski from the Russian coast to the pole when a flight they had arranged to meet them in mid-May was canceled.</p>
        <p>Other visitors come to ''collect'' the pole like a medal. Earlier this month 11 people entered the first North Pole marathon. The victor, Martin Tighe, a slender, perpetually smiling Briton working in Attleboro, Mass., trained in an ice-cream freezer.</p>
        <p>Friday was the busiest day yet: 34 skiers shuttled back from the pole in a packed helicopter.</p>
        <p>Geoff Somers, a British guide who arrived at the camp after guiding two skiers for 17 days on the ice, said they had to shift camp twice during the night when leads suddenly started opening beneath them. ''You can't sleep easy up here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then there was the polar bear. Mr. Somers was half asleep when he heard sounds outside. Presuming it was one of his clients, he ''unzipped the tent fly and as close as me to you was this bear.'' Two rifle warning shots did not scare it, and they simply waited until it wandered away.</p>
        <p>Charlie Vincent, 43, a retired metals trader from London visiting here, said the real allure for him came mainly from the things that were not there -- people, the noise of modern life, the comforts of home.</p>
        <p>''To be so quiet and hear all of nature at work,'' he said. ''Nature's at work every day of your life, but it's muffled.''</p>
        <p>Alain Hubert, a Belgian adventurer, agreed. He set up his parasail and glided away from camp, bouncing over ridges like a surfer riding a wave. ''Here the wind is usually the enemy, but I make it my friend,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Even the staid scientists acknowledge that they are drawn by the opportunity to stand on a spot where time and direction are arbitrary -- the camp is on Moscow time because Russians run it -- and geography is ephemeral.</p>
        <p>A few yards from the hole cut by the engineers and divers who dealt with the underwater instruments, a candy-striped barber-style pole had been erected.</p>
        <p>At its base was a sign reading ''North Pole is here,'' with a slash through the ''is,'' replaced by the word ''was.''</p>
        <p>Within a week, the new instruments set beneath the ice and other automated arrays set out near Camp Borneo will be the only evidence that anyone had come and gone. The skiers and scientists will be on their way home.</p>
        <p>The camp will be broken down like a traveling circus and stored until next spring.</p>
        <p>Left alone, the polar cap will continue to shift and grate.</p>
        <p>Already it is restless.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, just 50 yards from where the helicopters were parked, two butting ice plates crumbled along their interface, which was miles long. As helicopter crewmen, scientists and visitors gawked, a chorus of ticks and pops and huffs and cracks and muffled booms rose in a percussive crescendo.</p>
        <p>The ice heaved and slabs and blocks the size of mattresses and refrigerators and delivery trucks rearranged themselves.</p>
        <p>Then, just as quickly, all grew quiet again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
