<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1464861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Correction Stories</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hemingway, Ernest (1899-1961)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">It Just Catches (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1D7153AF937A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Correction of garbled Feb 13 correction of Feb 12 review of play It Just Catches by Ernest Hemingway, regarding song listed in program</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.S. and Britain Drafting Resolution to Punish Iraq  The Bush administration is writing a resolution with Britain that they expect to present to the United Nations Security Council next week declaring that Saddam Hussein has failed to disarm and must now face unspecified ''consequences,'' senior administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American intelligence has obtained new evidence of movements by agents of Al Qaeda indicating that they may be poised to carry out two major attacks, including one inside the United States. Officials said the intelligence shows that the activities may have gone beyond the planning stages for two distinct plots.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.S. and Britain Drafting Resolution to Punish Iraq  The Bush administration is writing a resolution with Britain that they expect to present to the United Nations Security Council next week declaring that Saddam Hussein has failed to disarm and must now face unspecified ''consequences,'' senior administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American intelligence has obtained new evidence of movements by agents of Al Qaeda indicating that they may be poised to carry out two major attacks, including one inside the United States. Officials said the intelligence shows that the activities may have gone beyond the planning stages for two distinct plots.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan told the Security Council that the U.N. is planning to feed up to 10 million Iraqi civilians and care for at least 2.6 million refugees in the wake of war in Iraq. Mr. Annan met with the Council ambassadors to appeal for $120 million for contingency planning.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>A Shaken Alliance  The Bush administration's preparations for a possible war with Iraq have provoked a rift far beyond the normal disagreements that sometimes take place among allies. Something deep and fundamental in the different views of Europe and the United States seems to have been brought to the surface by the Iraqi crisis.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>European intellectuals tend to draw a distinction between the American government and the American people. But there is a sense that many of America's most admirable qualities have been so trampled in the debate over war as to have been rendered toothless or even nonexistent.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>On such fundamental issues as the death penalty or social welfare, Europe and America have taken divergent paths and built societies with increasingly different worldviews. The Iraq crisis has sharpened those differences and exacerbated the sense of trans-Atlantic estrangement.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Israeli Outrage at Belgium  Israeli officials reacted with anger to a decision by Belgium's highest court that Belgium could try Prime Minister Ariel Sharon for war crimes once he leaves office. Israel recalled its ambassador from Brussels, while Benjamin Netanyahu summoned Belgium's ambassador to Israel to receive a protest.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Support for Zimbabwe  The presidents of Nigeria and South Africa are urging the Commonwealth nations to reinstate Zimbabwe -- and thus its leader, President Robert Mugabe -- to full membership. Membership was suspended after Mr. Mugabe won a new term in elections widely regarded as rigged.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Mexican Butterfly Recovery  A little more than a year after the largest known die-off of monarch butterflies occurred in the mountains of Mexico, researchers say the monarchs that migrate there appear to have recovered to near normal population levels.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-28</p>
        <p>Panel Cites Hole in Skin As Shuttle Disaster Cause  The panel investigating the loss of the space shuttle Columbia said a hole developed in its aluminum skin, allowing superheated gas to flow into the left wing and cause the ship's destruction.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The group of more than 1,500 emergency volunteers who rushed to the East Texas area to help retrieve debris from the space shuttle Columbia disbanded.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>The senior Democrat on the House space subcommittee charged that NASA was ''rapidly losing credibility'' because of its unwillingness to allow an independent and credible investigation of the space shuttle Columbia disaster.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Poll Shows Qualms on War  Even after the administration's aggressive case for going to war soon in Iraq, a majority of Americans favor a delay to give United Nations weapons inspectors more time to complete their work so that any military operation wins the support of the security council.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Leaders from some of the 90 city councils that have adopted resolutions opposing military action against Iraq warned that the costs of war would devastate already crippled municipal budgets and deprive citizens of crucial services.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Spending Bill Passed  Congress approved a giant spending bill, ending a fight that began last summer over the level of financing for federal agencies.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Antitax Fervor Fades  At least 24 states are considering ways to raise taxes even as President Bush is pushing for permanent federal income tax cuts to stimulate the economy.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Top Bush Adviser Resigns  Bobby Jindal, a key figure on Medicare policy in the Bush administration, announced that he was resigning to return home to Louisiana. He is considered a potential Republican candidate for governor there.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Deadlock on Judgeship  The Senate remained deadlocked over a filibuster by Democrats against a Bush administration appeals court nominee.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Mock Assault on Indian Pt. Planned for this Summer  For the first time since the Sept. 11 attacks, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission will resume mock armed assaults on nuclear plants, including a simulated invasion of the Indian Point nuclear power plant in Westchester County this summer.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Curriculum Exemption Formula  After weeks of public anticipation, Chancellor Joel I. Klein unveiled his formula for picking the roughly 200 New York City schools that will be exempt from the system's new mandatory curriculum. The formula is a complicated methodology that is meant to ensure a mix of schools from rich and poor neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Death Penalty Reversal Probed  All 12 cases in the New York region in which Attorney General John Ashcroft has ordered federal prosecutors to seek the death penalty involve black or Hispanic defendants, newly released data show. The new information has moved prosecutors into a wider debate about the fairness of the federal death penalty.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>New Treatment for AIDS  Infection with a common harmless virus seems to slow the progress of H.I.V. and prolong the survival of AIDS patients, according to new evidence reported by scientists.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-38; E39-50</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Kemmons Wilson  A businessman who, after being angered by the shabby lodgings he encountered on a family vacation in 1951, founded the Holiday Inn motel chain, he was 90.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Auto Makers Pledge Safety  The auto industry's main lobbying group said automakers would develop voluntary standards to make cars safer when hit by larger vehicles and to make sport utilities and pickups less dangerous.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Enron's Tax Shelters  Tax officials told the Senate Finance Committee that Wall Street banks, acting on the advice of leading lawyers and accounting firms, helped Enron devise shelters that let the company operate tax-free for years while exaggerating its reported profits by billions.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Jackson Thrills Networks  In a two-week period beginning Feb. 6, specials about Michael Jackson will have taken up at least 10 hours in network prime time as networks scramble to seek an edge during sweeps month.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bankers Fight Lending Laws  The banking industry has stepped up a fight to block state laws aimed at curbing unscrupulous mortgage lending, warning that the rules could seriously disrupt the marketplace.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: Elusive Qaeda connections; the antiwar non-march; weak response on global warming; flowery thoughts.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof, Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E34  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E37  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
