<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1543392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DB103CF936A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1198" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-23</p>
        <p>Saddam Hussein Captured; Iraqis Rejoice at His Fall  Saddam Hussein, once the all-powerful leader of Iraq, was arrested without a fight by American soldiers who found him crouching in an eight-foot hole at an isolated farm near Tikrit, haggard, dirty and disoriented. News of the arrest sent joyous Iraqis into the streets.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-23</p>
        <p>Saddam Hussein Captured; Iraqis Rejoice at His Fall  Saddam Hussein, once the all-powerful leader of Iraq, was arrested without a fight by American soldiers who found him crouching in an eight-foot hole at an isolated farm near Tikrit, haggard, dirty and disoriented. News of the arrest sent joyous Iraqis into the streets.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Bush hailed the capture as a turning point in the history of Iraq, but warned Americans that the violence against United States forces occupying the nation would continue.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Six hundred American soldiers and special operations forces backed by tanks, artillery and Apache helicopter gunships surrounded two rural farmhouses, and found Mr. Hussein near one of them, less than 11 hours after receiving a decisive tip.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A sense of unity was restored among many world leaders as they welcomed the seizure of one of the Middle East's most brutal dictators and expressed hope for a new chapter of stability and reconciliation in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>The capture could rob Democrats of an issue they have increasingly challenged President Bush on, Democats said. Its impact could fall particularly heavily on the candidacy of Howard Dean.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>The capture let American intelligence agencies shine after many months of failures and frustrations. In their inquiries, a trail that grew from small bits of information led to the former dictator's lair.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>A careful plan was in place for the announcement of Saddam Hussein's capture, devised over the course of months. Its developers say the plan was intended to dispel any possible doubt among Iraqis and a skeptical Arab world that he was in American hands.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A car bomb exploded outside the police station in a town 60 miles west of Baghdad, killing at least 17 people. Whether such attacks will continue at the recent level of intensity is one of the questions raised by Mr. Hussein's capture.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Saddam Hussein is expected to become the principal defendant before a special Iraqi-led criminal tribunal, Iraqi and American officials said. He stands to be prosecuted for war crimes, crimes against humanity and possibly for genocide for his actions against Iraqi Kurds and marsh Arabs.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>An Attempt to Kill Musharraf  President Pervez Musharraf of Pakistan survived an assassination attempt when a large bomb detonated on a bridge just 30 seconds after his motorcade crossed over. It was the most serious attempt on his life since he sided with the United States in the campaign against terrorism.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Searching for the Next Step  Europe struggled to figure out how to proceed after a summit meeting failed to adopt a draft constitution. The leaders of 25 current and imminent European Union countries stumbled over the problem of how to apportion voting power among large and small states.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Pollution Plan to Expand  The Bush administration is pushing clean air policies through regulation rather than legislation. The regulations, which the E.P.A. intends to release this week, concern three of the main pollutants released from burning fossil fuels: mercury, sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Shifting Focus to the Uninsured  Congressional Republicans, including the Senate majority leader, Bill Frist, left, and the Bush administration say they are planning a new initiative to help provide health insurance to people under 65 who have no coverage. Officials say they are considering several proposals, including tax credits.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Las Vegas Corruption Scandal  A corruption case in Las Vegas has derailed the careers of two rising stars in Nevada Democratic politics and promises a twist in the city's relationship with legalized vice. The case, known as Operation G-Sting, involves the efforts of a nude-dance-club kingpin, Michael Galardi, to rewrite the law in Las Vegas and San Diego to benefit his clubs.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>William V. Roth Jr.  A longtime Republican senator from Delaware who gave his name to a popular tax-sheltered retirement account and a 1981 tax cut, he was 82.</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Disapproval for Governor Who Admitted to Lying  Connecticut residents are expressing anger and disappointment after Gov. John G. Rowland's apology and admission that he lied about who paid for improvements to his lakeside cottage.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>328 Bears Killed in Hunt  Nearly two-thirds of the 328 bears killed in New Jersey's six-day bear hunt were female, raising concern with many of the hunt's opponents.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Traffic Matters at Ground Zero  A vital debate about the layout of the streets around the World Trade Center site has been occurring while the public is transfixed by the struggle over the Freedom Tower.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Objects of Debate  Traditional Afghan rugs showing a crudely rendered interpretation of the Sept. 11, 2001, attack on the World Trade Center have stirred strong feelings in an East Village parking-lot bazaar where they are being peddled.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Queens Fire Kills Boy, 6  A 6-year-old boy was killed and his mother and 11-year-old sister were critically burned in a fire that swept through their Queens apartment, the authorities reported.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-9, 11</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>Opera Chairman Resigns  The chairman of New York City Opera, Irwin Schneiderman, a lawyer who has led the opera's efforts to leave Lincoln Center for ground zero, said that he would step down. He will be succeeded by Susan L. Baker, co-chairwoman of the board's strategic planning committee.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>U.N. Delegates Agree On Internet Governance  Delegates at the United Nations conference on the Internet agreed that a working group should be set up to examine whether to introduce more international oversight of the Internet's administrative bodies.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Alliance Settlement  The Securities and Exchange Commission and the New York attorney general's office are working out the final details of a settlement with Alliance Capital over improper trading in its mutual funds, senior people briefed on the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Technology to End Chip Errors  Researchers in France have developed a semiconductor memory technology that could eliminate an important barrier to shrinking the size of computer chips.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Hollinger Chairman Interview  Conrad Black, the embattled chairman of Hollinger International, will have his first interview with the Securities and Exchange Commission on Dec. 22 regarding fees paid to him and his chief lieutenants.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Disney Goes Online for Ouster  Roy E. Disney, the nephew of Walt Disney, has started a Web site in the hope of touching off a grass-roots campaign to oust Michael D. Eisner, the chief executive of the Walt Disney Company.</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: The capture of a dictator; new hope on immigration; a fight against corruption; in city streets, an unwelcome sentry.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire and Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Autos</p>
        <p>D10  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2  Bridge</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  Weather</p>
        <p>B12</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
