<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="01DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1523850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDA1F3DF932A35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Lack of Hiring Appears To Be Biggest Economic Ill  A lack of hiring, rather than a wave of layoffs, appears to be the main problem afflicting the American economy.</p>
        <p>Even as unemployment continued to mount, the number of jobs being eliminated last year fell below the level in late 1990's, according to a new government report. But the number of jobs that businesses created in 2002 dropped to its lowest level since 1995. Compared with the size of the economy, the rate of hiring was even slower than during the weak recovery of the early 1990's. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Lack of Hiring Appears To Be Biggest Economic Ill  A lack of hiring, rather than a wave of layoffs, appears to be the main problem afflicting the American economy.</p>
        <p>Even as unemployment continued to mount, the number of jobs being eliminated last year fell below the level in late 1990's, according to a new government report. But the number of jobs that businesses created in 2002 dropped to its lowest level since 1995. Compared with the size of the economy, the rate of hiring was even slower than during the weak recovery of the early 1990's. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>F.C.C. to Enforce No-Call Registry  Michael K. Powell, the chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, said the agency would enforce the national do-not-call registry despite logistical complications caused by a federal judge's ruling. Under the federal regulations, telemarketers who call phone numbers on the registry face fines of up to $11,000 for each violation. [C10.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Emission Trading Starts Slowly  The Chicago Climate Exchange received prices for carbon dioxide emissions that averaged less than $1 a metric ton. That was one-tenth the price of trades of carbon dioxide emissions allowances in Europe. [C10.]</p>
        <p>New Vision for Biomedical Research  The Bush administration announced a new vision for biomedical research, intended to give patients swifter access to discoveries while fostering greater collaboration between the government and private industry. [A16.]</p>
        <p>American Electric Power Is Sued  The Commodity Futures Trading Commission filed a lawsuit against American Electric Power, accusing the company of falsely reporting prices in an effort to manipulate the natural gas market from at least November 2000 through October 2002. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Consumer Confidence Declines  The Conference Board's consumer confidence index dropped to 76.8 in September, from a revised 81.7 in August. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Japan Ministry of Finance Sells Yen  The yen fell against the dollar in New York trading after Japan's Ministry of Finance sold yen to stem a gain that had pushed the currency to its highest since December 2000. The transactions, conducted through the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, indicated that Japan is concerned that a too-rapid rise in the yen will hurt an economy recovering from its third recession in a decade. [C15.]</p>
        <p>Australia Damaged by Drought  Australia has suffered the worst drought in a century, which has lowered farm incomes almost by half, to 7.2 billion Australian dollars ($4.9 billion), in the year ended June 30, according to estimates by the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Japan Bank Lifts Outlook for Year  The Mitsubishi Tokyo Financial Group doubled its profit expectations for the full year as a mending economy reduced the number of bad loans in its portfolio and the costs of writing them off. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Profit Rises 2.8% at Pepsi Bottling  The Pepsi Bottling Group said that its third-quarter earnings rose 2.8 percent. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Merck Lease Gives College Security  Emmanuel College in Boston has leased land on its campus to Merck for a research laboratory. In return, the college has swelled its endowment, using some of the money to build a student center. Commercial Real Estate. [C8.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
