<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Bad Boys of Illusion Turn Into Psychic-Busters</title>
    <meta content="24TVWK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/24/arts/television/24TVWK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1459124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="TV WEEKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Showtime</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jillette, Penn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E5DD1F30F937A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Bad Boys of Illusion Turn Into Psychic-Busters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Bad Boys of Illusion Turn Into Psychic-Busters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ron Wertheimer</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last thing you want from Penn &amp; Teller is sincerity.</p>
        <p>But that's what they're peddling on their new series, which begins tonight on Showtime. The bad boys of illusion have diverted their manic energy into debunking what they call frauds: alternative medicine, self-help fads, alien abductions, ESP. Tonight's episode is devoted to dumping cold water on self-proclaimed mediums who say they schmooze with the dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a new series on Showtime, Penn &amp; Teller, the bad boys of illusion, show their distaste for self-help fads, alien abductions and ESP.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last thing you want from Penn &amp; Teller is sincerity.</p>
        <p>But that's what they're peddling on their new series, which begins tonight on Showtime. The bad boys of illusion have diverted their manic energy into debunking what they call frauds: alternative medicine, self-help fads, alien abductions, ESP. Tonight's episode is devoted to dumping cold water on self-proclaimed mediums who say they schmooze with the dead.</p>
        <p>Alas, no real water is dumped here. Instead of entertaining like Laurel and Hardy on speed, Penn &amp; Teller have morphed into Bill Kurtis with attitude, fronting and narrating this mildly interesting report on psychics.</p>
        <p>The new role may work for Penn Jillette, the big one. But you'll recall that his partner, who goes by one name, doesn't speak. So with no water being dumped on him, Teller has little to do but shrug knowingly. You may be inclined to do the same.</p>
        <p>The one thing that distinguishes this report from a somber examination on A&amp;E or the Discovery Channel is the language. The series's title includes what used to be called a barnyard epithet. Lest you try in your sophisticated urbanity to overlook that, Penn proclaims: ''You'll notice more obscenity than we usually use. That's not just because it's on Showtime and we want to get some attention. It's also a legal matter. If one calls people liars and quacks, one can be sued.'' Cussing them out, however, ''is pretty safe.'' Pretty tired, too.</p>
        <p>He explains that his distaste for psychics, including the television stars John Edward and James Van Praagh, is personal. ''There's nothing more precious to me than my memories of my mom and dad,'' Penn says with no hint of a wink.</p>
        <p>''These performance artists,'' he says, turning that term into a sneering insult, are exploiting grief ''for a buck and a little unearned fame.''</p>
        <p>Experienced debunkers of the paranormal explain how psychics use people's gullibility against them, skillfully eliciting the very information they seem to be pulling from thin air. Some who've received messages from beyond say they've found relief in these encounters, but Penn declares, ''You don't heal a broken heart by pretending it's not broken.''</p>
        <p>This 13-week series promises to investigate creationism, global warming, feng shui, Ouija boards and aphrodisiacs. The final episode is to shine a light on end-of-the-world predictions. If Penn &amp; Teller aren't wrong about that one and the world continues to spin, maybe these guys can get back to their explosive antics.</p>
        <p>Sometimes it's better to light one firecracker than to curse the darkness, no matter how many barnyard epithets you can muster.</p>
        <p>PENN &amp; TELLER</p>
        <p>Showtime, tonight at 11, Eastern and Pacific times; 10, Central time</p>
        <p>Directed by Star Price; Marc Wolper, Randall Moldave, Eric Small and Mr. Price, executive producers; Penn Jillette and Teller, co-executive producers; Robert Shontell, segment director; Patti Duce, production coordinator; written by Mr. Jillette, Teller, David Wechter and John McLaughlin; created by Randall Moldave and Eric Small; Kevin O'Brien, director of photography; Eric Wise, editor; music by Gary Stockdale.</p>
        <p>TV WEEKEND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
