<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="20FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1458112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D71530F933A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>U.S. Could Allow Safe Haven for Hussein  Even as they rejected calls for delay before confronting Saddam Hussein militarily, three officials of the Bush administration hinted that they would consider allowing him to find a safe haven if that would avoid a war.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>U.S. Could Allow Safe Haven for Hussein  Even as they rejected calls for delay before confronting Saddam Hussein militarily, three officials of the Bush administration hinted that they would consider allowing him to find a safe haven if that would avoid a war.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraq told the top two United Nations arms inspectors that it had found four more empty chemical weapons warheads similar to the 12 discovered last week. The disclosure came in a meeting between Iraqi officials and the inspectors, who returned to Baghdad to urge the government to intensify cooperation with inspection teams.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>In Israel, More Conflicts  An Israeli court set a trial date for a Palestinian leader on charges of involvement in attacks that killed 26 people, though he contends it does not have the right to try him. In Hebron, the funeral of a settler who was killed in an attack by Palestinian gunmen turned into a conflict over where to bury him and then a full-scale riot.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel accused European states of bias in favor of the Palestinians, criticizing their role in an American-backed plan for Middle East peace.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Iran Cleric Backs Dissident  A high-ranking reformist cleric denounced the house arrest of a dissident who has challenged the authority of Iran's supreme religious leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, and called on other high-ranking clerics to press for his release.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Libya Set to Win Rights Post  Libya, long accused by human rights activists of major abuses, is set to win the chairmanship of the United Nations' top rights body despite strong opposition from the United States.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Hope in Korea Nuclear Crisis  The United States and North Korea inched closer toward a resolution of a crisis over nuclear weapons development with American offers of economic cooperation and North Korean calls for dialogue.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Russia Helped U.S. in Spying  Russian intelligence officers secretly placed sophisticated nuclear monitors provided by the C.I.A. inside the Russian Embassy in the North Korean capital, Pyongyang, in an effort to detect signs of activity from the weapons program during the 1990's.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A15-17</p>
        <p>30 Years After Roe Ruling, New Trends but No Answers  The rate of abortions has come almost full circle since Roe v. Wade, declining to its lowest level since 1974. Increasingly, the common denominator for women who have abortions is poverty.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Aides on Affirmative Action  The two highest-ranking African-Americans in the Bush administration took differing positions on the affirmative action case before the Supreme Court. Condoleezza Rice, the national security adviser, praised the president's stance against the University of Michigan's use of race in its admissions program. Secretary of State Colin L. Powell refused to do so.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Democrats Show Confidence  There is a growing sense among Democrats and some Republicans that President Bush's re-election is not certain.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Ships to Carry Bulk of Supplies  More than 95 percent of the fuel, ammunition and matériel that would be used in an attack against Iraq, would flow into the Persian Gulf region by ship, military experts say. And the cargo fleet is more prepared to move quickly than in the past.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>More Anti-War Protests  A band of demonstrators against action in Iraq tried without success to provoke mass arrests a block from the White House a day after widespread anti-war protests.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Call for Action on Warming  Senior Bush administration officials are traveling the country collecting written promises from industries to curb emissions of gases linked to global warming in an effort to show that President Bush's voluntary climate strategy can work.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Mayor Promotes His Plan  Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg visited four churches in Harlem to talk up his plan to overhaul the city's public school system, honor the memory of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., and speak directly to New Yorkers about his policies days after a poll showed that his approval rating had dropped sharply.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>I.R.S. Says City Broke Laws With Pension Systems  The Internal Revenue Service has found that New York City violated federal tax laws by withdrawing $177 million over seven years from municipal pension systems and using it to pay its own operating expenses, according to a tentative settlement agreement reached between the city and the federal agency.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Medicaid Limits Possible  The Bush administration recently presented state Medicaid directors across the country with a unattractive option: letting them limit coverage of emergency services for the poor. Gov. George E. Pataki has been pleading with the White House to shoulder a greater portion of the state's Medicaid burden for more than a year.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>3 Killed at Home for Elderly  A visitor to an apartment building for the elderly in Newark fatally stabbed two residents, then was fatally shot by the police when he refused to drop his knife, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Unexpected E-Mail Messages  Users of a roommate-matching service in Manhattan say that after signing up with the service they began receiving e-mail messages from a Holocaust-revisionist Web site run by the service's founder.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>Raiders Will Meet Buccaneers  Oakland beat the Tennessee Titans, 41-24, winning the American Football Conference championship. Tampa Bay beat the Philadelphia Eagles, 27-10, winning the National Football Conference championship and their first appearance in the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6-7</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-14</p>
        <p>Golden Globe Award Winners  The 60th annual Golden Globe Awards were presented in Beverly Hills. ''Chicago'' won the award for best comedy or musical. ''The Hours'' was named the year's best dramatic film. Nicole Kidman won the award for best actress in a drama.</p>
        <p>E3</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>Kmart Chief to Step Down  Kmart's chief executive, James B. Adamson, who was hired to lead the company out of its financial distress, is stepping down, Kmart said. He will be suceeded by Julian C. Day, the chain's president and chief operating officer. Kmart is struggling financially and its bankruptcy reorganization is incomplete.</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Ford Opens Factory in China  The Ford Motor Company, striving to catch up in what has become the world's fastest-growing market for automobiles, officially opened its first car factory in China. An executive vice president said the Chinese auto market was likely to overtake Germany's in size and perhaps Japan's in the next three to five years.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Silicon Valley Job Losses  Silicon Valley lost 127,000 jobs, or about 9 percent of its employment, from the first quarter of 2001 to the second quarter of 2002, according to a report to be published by a nonprofit group formed to promote the area.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Slow Holiday Book Sales  Disappointing sales numbers contributed to a dismal holiday season for book retailers, particularly chain stores. There may be too many books from the same authors, or the public's tastes may be changing.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New U.S. Chief for Sega  The Sega Corporation has chosen Tetsu Kayama, the company's chief operating officer, to become head of its American business. He succeeds Peter Moore, who quit.</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: The freedom of equality; a stirring in the nation; no news is bad news; China's relentless repression.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire and Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E13  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E14  Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  Weather</p>
        <p>B8  Metro Diary</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
