<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="01FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DF113CF932A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1216" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Both Sides in Iraq Debate Are Hardening Positions  The Bush administration said Iraq could prevent war only by both disarming and sending Saddam Hussein into exile. Russia's foreign minister threatened to veto a United Nations resolution that said Iraq had missed its last chance to avoid war. The hardening of both positions increases pressure on six publicly uncommitted Security Council members.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The prime ministers of Britain and Spain dismissed Iraq's promise to destroy its missiles and said the threat of war had to be maintained to force compliance. They were confident of getting support in the Security Council for a resolution they presented with the United States.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Both Sides in Iraq Debate Are Hardening Positions  The Bush administration said Iraq could prevent war only by both disarming and sending Saddam Hussein into exile. Russia's foreign minister threatened to veto a United Nations resolution that said Iraq had missed its last chance to avoid war. The hardening of both positions increases pressure on six publicly uncommitted Security Council members.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The prime ministers of Britain and Spain dismissed Iraq's promise to destroy its missiles and said the threat of war had to be maintained to force compliance. They were confident of getting support in the Security Council for a resolution they presented with the United States.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Experts say the chances that Saddam Hussein could be persuaded to step down or be toppled by a coup are remote, and many question whether any new government in Iraq could create the deep change Washington is determined to see.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Alarm Over North Korea  President Bush's top intelligence officials described the situation in North Korea as a crisis after spy satellites revealed tests in a reprocessing facility that could produce weapons-grade plutonium.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Change by Palestinians  The Palestinian Authority's top finance official said the authority'smoney would be managed by a publicly accountable board. The efforts would be the most prominent of several changes urged by the United States, the United Nations and others.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Refugees Rushing Into Britain  A record 110,700 people sought asylum in Britain in 2002, which is expected to inflame concerns over immigration policy and increase pressure on the government to stem the flow. Britain and Italy were the only two countries in the European Union that had an increase in applicants.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>New Czech President  Vaclav Klaus will replace his old rival, Vaclav Havel, as president of the Czech Republic. The election of Mr. Klaus, a former prime minister, exposed deep divisions among the ruling Social Democrats, who failed to elect their own candidate to the largely symbolic presidency.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-16, 20</p>
        <p>Border Inspectors to Look For Radioactive Materials  Senior Bush administration officials said all travelers arriving in the United States would be screened by federal border inspectors for radioactive materials to stop terrorists from bringing nuclear material across the border.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Court Upholds Pledge Ruling  The federal appeals court that outraged much of the country last summer when it declared the Pledge of Allegience unconstitutional because of the words ''under God'' refused to reconsider that ruling.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Warning Label for Ephedra  The federal government moved to curtail the use of ephedra, the dietary supplement, proposing new labels to warn consumers that it could cause heart attack and death.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Club Soundproofing Examined  The nightclub where a fire killed 97 people last week passed a local fire inspection in December despite its walls being covered with a highly flammable soundproofing foam that fire safety experts have called an enormous fire threat.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NASA Chief Disputes Claim  The NASA administrator, Sean O'Keefe, said he emphatically disagreed with the idea that nothing could have been done to save the space shuttle Columbia or its crew if NASA officials had known it was in trouble.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Conviction in '66 Killing  A jury of nine whites and three blacks found Ernest Avants, 72, a former Klansman, guilty of murdering Chester White in Natchez, Miss., in 1966. Deliberations took three hours. The trial took three days.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Police Chief Is Indicted  A grand jury indicted the police chief of San Francisco and nine others in connection with a fight outside a bar in November that involved off-duty police officers and accusations of a cover-up that followed.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Judge Disqualified for Review  A third judge in Louisiana has been disqualified for conflict of interest in the case of Wilbert Rideau, a rehabilitated inmate who has been in prison since 1961 on robbery and murder convictions and is awaiting release.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton May Serve On Jury in Assault Trial  The jury selection questionnaires in a case involving a gang shooting were supposed to be anonymous, but there was a glaring clue to the identity of one juror in federal court in Manhattan. Where it asked for previous jobs held, he filled in: president of the United States.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ID for Remains of 2 Hijackers  The city medical examiner's office has identified the remains of two of the terrorists who attacked the World Trade Center, a spokeswoman said. The remains were removed from Memorial Park, where thousands of unidentified remains are stored.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>City Requests Shelter Evictions  The city, arguing that the homeless have no right to shelter if they violate rules, asked a five-judge appellate panel in State Supreme Court in Manhattan to allow 30-day evictions of troublemaking single adults from homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Strike Planned at Yale  Nearly 5,000 workers at Yale University, including janitors, cafeteria workers, secretaries and graduate teaching assistants, plan to go on strike on Monday.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Knicks Retire Ewing's Number  Patrick Ewing's number, 33, was retired as his jersey was raised to the rafters of Madison Square Garden during halftime of the Knicks game against the Orlando Magic.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Knicks beat the Magic, 118-110, in double overtime.</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-20</p>
        <p>Unabridged Works of Everyone  The directors of the new Alexandria Library in Egypt have joined an American artist and software engineers in an ambitious effort to make virtually all of the world's books available at a mouse click.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Consumer Confidence Waning  Americans are now more worried about their job prospects than at any time since 1993, raising the risk that consumer spending will slow even if the United States quickly resolves its standoff with Iraq.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bayer Executive Testifies  A top executive at Bayer, the maker of a cholesterol drug that was taken from the market after it was linked to more than 30 deaths were linked, tried to defend the company as a lawyer for an injured patient questioned him about dozens of internal memos and e-mail messages.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Victory for Winemakers  The Treasury Department approved a request by winemakers that they be allowed to make health claims on their bottles.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New Claim Against Taubman  Simon Property Group, the nation's largest owner of shopping malls, contended in a court filing that restructuring giving the Taubman family voting power to block any sale of Taubman Centers was prompted by a failed takeover bid by the Rouse Company in 1998.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Still After Global Crossing  A Hong Kong company seeking to acquire Global Crossing is considering ways to restructure its proposed deal after its bid for approval from a federal multiagency regulatory organization met strong resistance.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Rebuked on global warming; cloning countdown; under the radar; Francis X. Clines on the National Zoo inquiry.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B18  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B20  Crossword</p>
        <p>B19  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
