<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paid Notice: Deaths  TAPLIN, FRANK E. JR.</title>
    <meta content="DN051403" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Classified" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Paid Death Notices" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1488968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAPLIN, FRANK E. JR.</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Paid Death Notice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Paid Death Notices</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D91E3FF937A25756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paid Notice: Deaths  TAPLIN, FRANK E. JR.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. On May 11th, 2003 in Princeton, NJ. A memorial service will be held Sunday, June 8 at 4 PM in the Princeton University Chapel, Princeton. In lieu of flowers, contributions in his name may be made in support of environment, music, education or human rights.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The staff and trustees of Environmental Defense mourn the passing of our friend and longtime trustee, Frank E. Taplin Jr. Frank joined our board in 1990 and immediately devoted himself to the challenge of raising support for a traveling exhibition on Global Warming with the American Museum of Natural History, an exhibition that has since introduced millions of museum visitors to the urgent issue of climate change. Upholding a tradition of philanthropy at the Metropolitan Opera and other institutions, Frank went on to become the very active honorary chair of our 21st century campaign which surpassed its $25,000, 000 goal. His environmental legacy will be an enduring one, as will be the way he inspired us to see the art in an unspoiled mountain meadow or to hear the music of its songbirds. Those of us who had the pleasure of gathering around the piano as Frank brought us together in song will not soon forget the love and joy he found in music and good company. We extend our condolences to his loving wife Peg and their children and step-children. He will be missed. Board of Trustees of Environmental Defense</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank Jr. The Board of Directors, musicians and staff of The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center mourn, with great sadness, the passing of our Founding Director, first President and longtime Emeritus Board member, Frank Taplin. We will always be deeply grateful to Frank for his very deep love of chamber music and his decisive role in establishing its integral place at Lincoln Center. Over the nearly 35 years of his involvement with our organization, his personal commitment to the music of our time was a particular inspiration, embodying as it did his optimistic belief in the future of our art. We are proud to be able to perpetuate his tradition of forwardlooking generosity through the Frank E. Taplin Jr. Commission Fund, which he helped establish. Rarely are the qualities of grace and energy so harmoniously combined in one true gentlman as they were in him. We will miss him very much. Donaldson Pillsbury, Chairman Peter Frelinghuysen, President David Shifrin, Artistic Director Norma Hurlburt, Executive Director</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The musicians, trustees and staff of Marlboro Music mourn the loss of their longtime friend and one of the most significant figures in Marlboro history, and extend affection and sympathy to his wife Peggy and his family. In the early years, as a trusted advisor to Rudolf Serkin, Frank gave tirelessly of himself by organizing the board and administration, and laying the groundwork for a secure financial foundation. He was a trustee from 1960, Marlboro's first Chairman of the Board from 1964-1970, and Chairman Emeritus. Throughout his long association, he was devoted to Marlboro's musicians and its artistic ideals, and was a close friend to us all. His and Peggy's dedication to Marlboro Music led them to establish a summer residence there, where they generously hosted events each summer for the entire music school community. We celebrate Frank's life and his invaluable contributions. We will dearly miss his wise counsel, humor, compassion and love of music and life.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. It is with deep sadness that the Board, staff and friends of Lincoln Center mourn the loss of Frank E. Taplin Jr. An eloquent, committed member of Lincoln Center's board since 1972, he served as Vice Chairman from 1981-1984, and as Director Emeritus since 1988. A champion of the arts, Frank was a longtime supporter of Lincoln Center and many of its resident organizations, playing a leadership role at the Metropolitan Opera and the Chamber Music Society, where he was its first president. He will be greatly missed. We offer our sincere condolences to his wife, Peg, and his children and step-children. Bruce Crawford, Chairman Reynold Levy, President Martin E. Segal June Noble Larkin Co-Chairman of the Director's Emeriti Council Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, Inc.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Board of Directors and staff of Third Street Music School Settlement are deeply saddened by the death of a dear friend and patron of the School. Frank always spoke of Third Street as ''a giant sprinkler watering the soils of raw talent and enabling seeds to sprout into blossoms of many varieties, colors and shapes.'' We extend heartfelt condolences to his wife, Peg, our longtime Board member and his entire family. Mrs. Stephen M. Kellen, Chairman Gerald D. Cohen, President Barbara E. Field, Executive Director</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Board of Trustees and The Sarah Lawrence College community note with profound sorrow the death of Frank E. Taplin Jr., caring Trustee of The College for over thirty years and Chairman of The Board from 197377. He was a constant source of strength and encouragement, a wise and inspiring leader, and a delightful and talented friend. We shall miss him deeply, and extend our love and sympathy to his wife, Peg, and all his family. Margot C. Bogert, Chairman Of The Board Michele Tolela Myers, President</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The American - Scandinavian Foundation expresses sorrow at the passing of our longtime Trustee whose enthusiasm, dedication and generosity was a source of endless inspiration. We extend deepest condolences to Peg and his family. Kristjan T. Ragnarsson, MD, Chairman Edward P. Gallagher, President</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Executive Club of the Princeton family YMCA records with sadness the death of our longtime Advisory Committee Member. We extend to his beloved wife Peg and family our deepest sympathy. Millard M. Riggs, Jr., Chair Quentin E. Lyle, President</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. On May 11th, 2003 in Princeton, NJ. A memorial service will be held Sunday, June 8 at 4 PM in the Princeton University Chapel, Princeton. In lieu of flowers, contributions in his name may be made in support of environment, music, education or human rights.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The staff and trustees of Environmental Defense mourn the passing of our friend and longtime trustee, Frank E. Taplin Jr. Frank joined our board in 1990 and immediately devoted himself to the challenge of raising support for a traveling exhibition on Global Warming with the American Museum of Natural History, an exhibition that has since introduced millions of museum visitors to the urgent issue of climate change. Upholding a tradition of philanthropy at the Metropolitan Opera and other institutions, Frank went on to become the very active honorary chair of our 21st century campaign which surpassed its $25,000, 000 goal. His environmental legacy will be an enduring one, as will be the way he inspired us to see the art in an unspoiled mountain meadow or to hear the music of its songbirds. Those of us who had the pleasure of gathering around the piano as Frank brought us together in song will not soon forget the love and joy he found in music and good company. We extend our condolences to his loving wife Peg and their children and step-children. He will be missed. Board of Trustees of Environmental Defense</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank Jr. The Board of Directors, musicians and staff of The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center mourn, with great sadness, the passing of our Founding Director, first President and longtime Emeritus Board member, Frank Taplin. We will always be deeply grateful to Frank for his very deep love of chamber music and his decisive role in establishing its integral place at Lincoln Center. Over the nearly 35 years of his involvement with our organization, his personal commitment to the music of our time was a particular inspiration, embodying as it did his optimistic belief in the future of our art. We are proud to be able to perpetuate his tradition of forwardlooking generosity through the Frank E. Taplin Jr. Commission Fund, which he helped establish. Rarely are the qualities of grace and energy so harmoniously combined in one true gentlman as they were in him. We will miss him very much. Donaldson Pillsbury, Chairman Peter Frelinghuysen, President David Shifrin, Artistic Director Norma Hurlburt, Executive Director</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The musicians, trustees and staff of Marlboro Music mourn the loss of their longtime friend and one of the most significant figures in Marlboro history, and extend affection and sympathy to his wife Peggy and his family. In the early years, as a trusted advisor to Rudolf Serkin, Frank gave tirelessly of himself by organizing the board and administration, and laying the groundwork for a secure financial foundation. He was a trustee from 1960, Marlboro's first Chairman of the Board from 1964-1970, and Chairman Emeritus. Throughout his long association, he was devoted to Marlboro's musicians and its artistic ideals, and was a close friend to us all. His and Peggy's dedication to Marlboro Music led them to establish a summer residence there, where they generously hosted events each summer for the entire music school community. We celebrate Frank's life and his invaluable contributions. We will dearly miss his wise counsel, humor, compassion and love of music and life.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. It is with deep sadness that the Board, staff and friends of Lincoln Center mourn the loss of Frank E. Taplin Jr. An eloquent, committed member of Lincoln Center's board since 1972, he served as Vice Chairman from 1981-1984, and as Director Emeritus since 1988. A champion of the arts, Frank was a longtime supporter of Lincoln Center and many of its resident organizations, playing a leadership role at the Metropolitan Opera and the Chamber Music Society, where he was its first president. He will be greatly missed. We offer our sincere condolences to his wife, Peg, and his children and step-children. Bruce Crawford, Chairman Reynold Levy, President Martin E. Segal June Noble Larkin Co-Chairman of the Director's Emeriti Council Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, Inc.</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Board of Directors and staff of Third Street Music School Settlement are deeply saddened by the death of a dear friend and patron of the School. Frank always spoke of Third Street as ''a giant sprinkler watering the soils of raw talent and enabling seeds to sprout into blossoms of many varieties, colors and shapes.'' We extend heartfelt condolences to his wife, Peg, our longtime Board member and his entire family. Mrs. Stephen M. Kellen, Chairman Gerald D. Cohen, President Barbara E. Field, Executive Director</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Board of Trustees and The Sarah Lawrence College community note with profound sorrow the death of Frank E. Taplin Jr., caring Trustee of The College for over thirty years and Chairman of The Board from 197377. He was a constant source of strength and encouragement, a wise and inspiring leader, and a delightful and talented friend. We shall miss him deeply, and extend our love and sympathy to his wife, Peg, and all his family. Margot C. Bogert, Chairman Of The Board Michele Tolela Myers, President</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The American - Scandinavian Foundation expresses sorrow at the passing of our longtime Trustee whose enthusiasm, dedication and generosity was a source of endless inspiration. We extend deepest condolences to Peg and his family. Kristjan T. Ragnarsson, MD, Chairman Edward P. Gallagher, President</p>
        <p>TAPLIN-Frank E. Jr. The Executive Club of the Princeton family YMCA records with sadness the death of our longtime Advisory Committee Member. We extend to his beloved wife Peg and family our deepest sympathy. Millard M. Riggs, Jr., Chair Quentin E. Lyle, President</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
