<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Missing Energy Strategy</title>
    <meta content="23SUN3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/23/opinion/23SUN3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1474607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alaska</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE5DF1F31F930A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Missing Energy Strategy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Missing Energy Strategy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial praises Senate for defeating Pres Bush's latest attempt to open Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration, but warns that energy bills now being drawn up in Congress offer no more hope than 2002 models for developing innovative policies that point toward cleaner, more efficient and less oil-dependent energy future</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate struck a blow for the environment and for common sense last week, defeating President Bush's second attempt in less than a year to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration. Credit goes to the Democrats, who mainly held firm in a close 52-to-48 vote, and to a small, sturdy group of moderate Republicans, which now includes Norm Coleman, a Minnesota freshman who wisely chose not to renege on his campaign promise to protect the refuge despite an aggressive sales pitch from senior Republicans and the White House.</p>
        <p>The pitch included the usual hyperbole from the Alaska delegation, which typically inflates official estimates of economically recoverable oil in the refuge by a factor of four. It also included a new but equally spurious argument minted for the occasion, namely that rising gas prices and the war in Iraq made drilling more urgent than ever. In truth, Arctic oil will have no influence on gas prices until it actually comes out of the ground, and even then it is likely to reduce American dependence on foreign oil by only a few percentage points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate struck a blow for the environment and for common sense by defeating President Bush's second attempt to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate struck a blow for the environment and for common sense last week, defeating President Bush's second attempt in less than a year to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil exploration. Credit goes to the Democrats, who mainly held firm in a close 52-to-48 vote, and to a small, sturdy group of moderate Republicans, which now includes Norm Coleman, a Minnesota freshman who wisely chose not to renege on his campaign promise to protect the refuge despite an aggressive sales pitch from senior Republicans and the White House.</p>
        <p>The pitch included the usual hyperbole from the Alaska delegation, which typically inflates official estimates of economically recoverable oil in the refuge by a factor of four. It also included a new but equally spurious argument minted for the occasion, namely that rising gas prices and the war in Iraq made drilling more urgent than ever. In truth, Arctic oil will have no influence on gas prices until it actually comes out of the ground, and even then it is likely to reduce American dependence on foreign oil by only a few percentage points.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless it is much too soon for the environmental community or its Senate champions, like Joseph Lieberman, John McCain and James Jeffords, to rest on their well-earned laurels. Drilling proposals will almost certainly resurface, most likely in energy bills now on the drawing boards in both the House and Senate. Beyond that, neither the White House nor the Republican leadership shows any appetite for developing what America really needs: innovative policies that point toward a cleaner, more efficient and less oil-dependent energy future. Instead, the White House and its Congressional allies continue to push a retrograde strategy -- of which Arctic drilling was just one component -- that faithfully caters to President Bush's friends in the oil, gas and coal industries and remains heavily biased toward the production of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>On this score, the energy bills now being drawn up on Capitol Hill offer no more hope than the 2002 models. Last year's energy plan, which mercifully expired in a conference committee, was top-heavy with subsidies for industry and light on incentives for energy efficiency, alternative fuels and other forms of conservation. The news from the relevant Congressional committees suggests more of the same. Just last week, Edward Markey of Massachusetts offered his colleagues on the House energy committee a proposal to increase fuel economy standards for cars and light trucks, including S.U.V.'s, by about 20 percent by 2010. This is not an unreasonable goal, given Detroit's technological capabilities, and would save 1.6 million barrels a day, more than double the recent imports from Iraq and far more than the Arctic refuge could produce in the same time frame. The committee crushed the idea.</p>
        <p>The last two years have given the country plenty of reasons to re-examine its energy policies: a power crisis in California, the attacks of 9/11 and now a war in the very heart of the biggest oil patch in the world. It is plainly time to move forward in a systematic way with new ideas. But the best we can do, it appears, is to beat back bad ones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
