<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="29DIGEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED91630F93AA15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Putnam Investments Accused of Fraud  Federal and state regulators filed civil lawsuits against Putnam Investments and two of its former managers, accusing them of fraud. They are the first such accusations against a mutual fund company and some of its executives in a widening investigation into the trading of fund shares.</p>
        <p>The case against Putnam involves its practice of allowing investors to trade rapidly in and out of shares, even though its policy was to prohibit such trades, the Securities and Exchange Commission said in the suit. Regulators also contend that Putnam engaged in securities fraud by failing to disclose to shareholders or to its board a series of personal trades by its managers that harmed shareholders. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Putnam Investments Accused of Fraud  Federal and state regulators filed civil lawsuits against Putnam Investments and two of its former managers, accusing them of fraud. They are the first such accusations against a mutual fund company and some of its executives in a widening investigation into the trading of fund shares.</p>
        <p>The case against Putnam involves its practice of allowing investors to trade rapidly in and out of shares, even though its policy was to prohibit such trades, the Securities and Exchange Commission said in the suit. Regulators also contend that Putnam engaged in securities fraud by failing to disclose to shareholders or to its board a series of personal trades by its managers that harmed shareholders. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Sony to Eliminate 20,000 Jobs  Nobuyuki Idei, the chairman of Sony, announced a three-year plan that includes laying off 20,000 workers, ending production of older-model TV sets in Japan, cutting the numbers of parts and suppliers, and starting a venture to make flat screens. The plan is intended to save $3 billion in annual operating costs by 2006. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>More Settlements by Microsoft  Microsoft agreed to pay $200 million to settle consumer class-action lawsuits in five states and the District of Columbia. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Southwest Airlines to Expand  Southwest Airlines plans to start flying from Philadelphia in May with up to 14 flights, the first expansion by the low-cost airline into a new city in two and a half years. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Goldman Tries to Avoid Conflicts  Executives and investment bankers at Goldman Sachs will stop serving as directors of other companies in a shift intended to head off any conflicts of interest. [C8.]</p>
        <p>F.D.A. Bans Sale of a Steroid  The Food and Drug Administration banned the sale and use of a newly detected steroid, tetrahydrogestrinone, or THG, and said it would help prosecute any companies making or selling it. [D1.]</p>
        <p>States Address Global Warming  At least half of the 50 states are addressing global warming as mandatory programs on the federal level have largely stalled. They are doing so either through legislation, lawsuits against the Bush administration or programs initiated by governors. [A20.]</p>
        <p>No Challenges Expected to Merger  The decline in Bank of America shares has reduced the value of its $48 billion bid for FleetBoston, but analysts said Bank of America's deal was unlikely to be challenged. The banks inserted provisions into their agreement that would make it expensive for a hostile offer for FleetBoston. Also, analysts said hostile takeovers for banks were rarely successful. Market Place. [C9.]</p>
        <p>A Software Patent Is Disputed  The World Wide Web Consortium is asking the director of the Patent and Trademark Office to invalidate a software patent that the group contends threatens the future development of the World Wide Web. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Fed Decision Pushes Stocks Higher  Stocks rose sharply after the Federal Reserve decided to leave interest rates unchanged. The Dow Jones industrial average climbed 140.15 points, or 1.5 percent, to 9,748.31 points. The Nasdaq composite index gained 49.35 points, or 2.6 percent, to 1,932.26, and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 15.66 points, to 1,046.79. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Growth Accelerates Near Wal-Mart  Bentonville, Ark., has been undergoing a construction boom fueled by the eagerness of Wal-Mart to have its suppliers close at hand and the presence of several other major corporations. Commercial Real Estate. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
