<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cold Winter Freezes Much of Great Lakes and May Delay Shipping Season</title>
    <meta content="Y10LAK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/10/national/10LAKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1471261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Superior</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Huron</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Erie</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Lakes</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Ice Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Michigan</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DE163EF933A25750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cold Winter Freezes Much of Great Lakes and May Delay Shipping Season</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cold Winter May Delay Shipping Season in Great Lakes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, March 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cold weather in Midwest brings about rare nearly complete freeze-over of Lakes Superior, Huron and Erie; ice-up is major departure from what National Ice Center predicted month ago, and may delay shipping season; Lake Superior, largest and deepest of lakes, is almost 98 percent covered with ice; complete freeze-over would be first since 1979; lakes are not frozen over like skating rink, but they are largely covered with ice, in some spots few inches thick and in other places several feet; United States Coast Guard maintains fleet of six thick-hulled icebreakers on Great Lakes that plow through ice sheets that can be several feet thick; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unusually cold late winter has left 90 percent of Lakes Superior, Huron and Erie -- an area larger than the state of New York -- covered with ice, a condition that officials say could threaten the start of the shipping season.</p>
        <p>Lake Superior, the largest and deepest of the lakes, was almost 98 percent covered with ice on Thursday, the date of the most recent survey by the National Ice Center, a unit of the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration. A complete freeze-over would be the first since 1979, said Greg Rose, public affairs officer for the center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An unusually cold late winter has left 90 percent of Lakes Superior, Huron and Erie covered with ice, a condition that could threaten the start of the shipping season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An unusually cold late winter has left 90 percent of Lakes Superior, Huron and Erie -- an area larger than the state of New York -- covered with ice, a condition that officials say could threaten the start of the shipping season.</p>
        <p>Lake Superior, the largest and deepest of the lakes, was almost 98 percent covered with ice on Thursday, the date of the most recent survey by the National Ice Center, a unit of the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration. A complete freeze-over would be the first since 1979, said Greg Rose, public affairs officer for the center.</p>
        <p>''It has its own unique beauty,'' said Davis Helberg, executive director of the Duluth Seaway Port Authority, whose office looks out on Lake Superior. ''I've been in this business for 45 years and I've seen ice like this maybe three times.''</p>
        <p>Northern and coastal sections of Lakes Michigan and Ontario also have significant ice cover, though large sections are free of ice, Mr. Rose said.</p>
        <p>The lakes are not frozen over like a pond or skating rink, but they are largely covered with ice, in some spots a few inches thick, in other places several feet.</p>
        <p>The icy conditions have already pushed back the opening of the St. Lawrence Seaway, which connects the Great Lakes to the Atlantic Ocean. The seaway is now scheduled to open to ship traffic on March 31, instead of March 25. Opening of the Soo Locks at Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., the link between Superior and the other lakes, is still set for March 25, though that date could be threatened if conditions do not improve, Mr. Helberg said.</p>
        <p>Most of the shipping traffic in the Great Lakes carries raw materials like iron ore and coal from Duluth, Minn., and other ports on Lake Superior to ports near Chicago, Detroit and Cleveland on the lower lakes. Water levels on the Great Lakes have been low for several years and are not expected to be higher this year, Mr. Helberg said. Because ships must carry lighter loads when lake levels are down, carriers try to make as many trips as possible in the shipping season. So a delay in the start of the season this year could be especially costly, Mr. Helberg said.</p>
        <p>The United States Coast Guard maintains a fleet of six thick-hulled icebreakers on the Great Lakes that plow through ice sheets that can be several feet thick. The boats also shoot jets of water under the ice to break up the floes.</p>
        <p>Petty Officer Paul Roszkowski of the Coast Guard was in Chicago today on the 140-foot icebreaker Mobile Bay, which was breaking up ice around Calumet Harbor and Burns Harbor, south of the city.</p>
        <p>''The ice we are seeing is way out of the ordinary for a typical winter around here,'' Petty Officer Roszkowski said. ''It's rare for us to see such thick ice.''</p>
        <p>This winter, the area has had less snow than normal, and December and January were unusually warm. But in February the temperature averaged 5 degrees below normal. Today's low in Duluth was 13 below zero, compared with the normal 14 above.</p>
        <p>Mr. Helberg, who began working on the Great Lakes as a deckhand in 1959, says that when he looks out over Lake Superior on his morning drive to work, he sees a nearly uninterrupted field of ice, grayish because it is largely bare of snow. The same powerful waters that claimed the 729-foot-long freighter Edmund Fitzgerald in 1975 are now locked under a vast stillness, stretching the 360-mile length of the lake.</p>
        <p>''We have to have weather like this every once in a while to remind us how puny we are,'' Mr. Helberg said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
