<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Lifts Off With an Israeli Astronaut</title>
    <meta content="Y17SHU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/17/science/space/17SHUT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1457245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D61F31F934A25752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Lifts Off With an Israeli Astronaut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shuttle Lifts Off With an Israeli Astronaut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Jan. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Space shuttle Columbia takes off on 16-day research mission amid high security with crew that includes Ilan Ramon, first astronaut from Israel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space shuttle Columbia roared off into a picture-perfect sky today to begin a 16-day research mission with a crew that includes the first astronaut from Israel.</p>
        <p>The shuttle, with a crew of five men and two women, lifted off on time without incident at 10:39 a.m. and quickly climbed on a column of smoke through a bright sky punctuated by puffs of white clouds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 300 dignitaries and guests from Israel watched as Col. Ilan Ramon of the Israel Air Force became the first Israeli in space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space shuttle Columbia roared off into a picture-perfect sky today to begin a 16-day research mission with a crew that includes the first astronaut from Israel.</p>
        <p>The shuttle, with a crew of five men and two women, lifted off on time without incident at 10:39 a.m. and quickly climbed on a column of smoke through a bright sky punctuated by puffs of white clouds.</p>
        <p>More than 300 dignitaries and guests from Israel watched as Col. Ilan Ramon of the Israel Air Force became the first Israeli in space.</p>
        <p>''It was so moving,'' said Danny Ayalon, the Israeli ambassador to the United States. ''The skies were colored blue and white; these are our national colors. We are privileged to join this very prestigious club of nations who have had astronauts in space.''</p>
        <p>The presence of an Israeli on the flight heightened concerns in the National Aeronautics and Space Administration that the highly visible shuttle program might become a target for terrorists. The agency intensified the already increased security measures it put into place last year, but no problems were reported.</p>
        <p>For the first time since NASA has launched shuttles under added security, there were no air or sea incursions into restricted zones around the Kennedy Space Center, security officers from the Air Force said. They attributed the lack of wandering small planes and boats to the publicity about security for this mission.</p>
        <p>About two hours after the Columbia entered orbit 160 miles above Earth, the astronauts opened the shuttle's payload bay doors and began normal operations. The crew began setting up the more than 90 experiments that will be conducted on the scientific mission, the first in three years not devoted to the construction and maintenance of the International Space Station or the Hubble Space Telescope.</p>
        <p>The crew, divided into two teams, will work in shifts around the clock to conduct the maximum science possible during the flight, which is to end with a landing at the Kennedy center on Feb. 1, NASA said.</p>
        <p>The Columbia's research flight, originally scheduled to go up almost two years ago, had been repeatedly delayed by higher-priority missions and groundings of the space shuttle fleet for mechanical problems.</p>
        <p>''If there was ever a time to use the phrase 'All good things come to people who wait,' this is the one time,'' Michael Leinbach, the Kennedy launching director, told the astronauts just before liftoff.</p>
        <p>The crew, three veteran space fliers and four rookies, have an ambitious and versatile scientific agenda. The experiments include testing the biological effects of weightlessness, studying the nature of fire and examining new ways to monitor Earth's ozone layer. Most experiments will take place in a pressurized laboratory in the payload bay.</p>
        <p>The astronauts themselves will also be subjects of many experiments on the effects of space flight on sleep, perception and various organs and tissues.</p>
        <p>Also aboard the shuttle are animal test subjects, including ants, spiders, silkworms, fish embryos and rats. Many are involved in experiments involving high school students from countries around the world.</p>
        <p>Colonel Ramon's principal focus will be operating a twin-camera instrument from the Israeli Space Agency and Tel Aviv University that is to study dust storms and the effects of the particles they generate on climate. Readings from the payload bay instrument, operated by remote control, will follow dust or particles from North African storms as they spread over the Atlantic Ocean and the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>The flight is under the command of Col. Rick D. Husband of the Air Force, assisted by the mission pilot, Cmdr. William C. McCool of the Navy. Lt. Col. Michael P. Anderson of the Air Force is the payload commander in charge of the science equipment. The other members are Dr. Kalpana Chawla, an aerospace engineer, and two Navy doctors, Capt. David M. Brown and Cmdr. Laurel Salton Clark.</p>
        <p>More than 300 friends and dignitaries from Israel attended the launching, including Colonel Ramon's father, 79, and his older brother. His 75-year-old mother, an Auschwitz survivor, is too ill to travel.</p>
        <p>One personal item Colonel Ramon took into space is a piece of Holocaust-era art, a small black and white drawing called ''Moon Landscape'' that was borrowed from the Yad Vashem Art Museum in Israel. The drawing was created by Peter Ginz, a 14-year-old Jewish boy killed at Auschwitz in 1944.</p>
        <p>At the concentration camp, Peter dreamed of faraway places and drew a picture of what Earth would look like when viewed from mountains on the moon.</p>
        <p>''I feel that my journey fulfills the dream of Peter Ginz 58 years on,'' Colonel Ramon said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
