<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up in the Sky! A Yellow Orb? Don't Panic!</title>
    <meta content="24NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/24/nyregion/24NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1499373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Weather Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7D8153BF937A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up in the Sky! A Yellow Orb? Don't Panic!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Look, Up in the Sky! A Yellow Orb. Don't Panic!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman humorous NYC column on how rarely New Yorkers have seen sun during long rainy spell; describes phone call with National Weather Service in which he asked about sighting of 'yellow orb' in sky; warns that rain is sure to return (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WOKE up yesterday to a strange phenomenon in the morning sky. It was too early to phone the planetarium, so a concerned call went to the National Weather Service, which left its perch in Rockefeller Center several years ago for the splendors of Brookhaven, on Lawn Guyland.</p>
        <p>A most helpful meteorologist named Adrienne Leptich answered. She had a theory about what the phenomenon might be, but being a proper scientist, she first wanted empirical evidence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rains of this June are impossible to ignore. It is all that many New Yorkers want to talk about. And they are not one bit happy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WOKE up yesterday to a strange phenomenon in the morning sky. It was too early to phone the planetarium, so a concerned call went to the National Weather Service, which left its perch in Rockefeller Center several years ago for the splendors of Brookhaven, on Lawn Guyland.</p>
        <p>A most helpful meteorologist named Adrienne Leptich answered. She had a theory about what the phenomenon might be, but being a proper scientist, she first wanted empirical evidence.</p>
        <p>''Was it bright?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>Very, she was told.</p>
        <p>That was enough for Ms. Leptich to go out on a limb.</p>
        <p>''I think that's called the sun,'' she said. ''I think that's what I recall.''</p>
        <p>By Jove, the sun! Of course. What else could it be? It had been so long since it was last seen that everyone in the family simply forgot what it looked like.</p>
        <p>Don't feel too bad, Ms. Leptich said reassuringly. Plenty of New Yorkers have fallen victim to the same amnesia.</p>
        <p>The weather is normally not this column's bread and butter. The feeling here is that we have weather most days, and it speaks for itself. Leave it to the television people to get bent out of shape over how in summer it gets really hot and in winter awfully cold.</p>
        <p>But the rains of this June are impossible to ignore. It is all that many New Yorkers want to talk about. And they are not one bit happy. You stand a better chance of stumbling upon an Iraqi weapon of mass destruction than finding someone with a good word about the damp.</p>
        <p>You hear a great deal about ruined outings and trips to the ballpark, about twisted umbrellas and shoes ruined in puddles of unsuspected depth. No question, these are the times that try men's soles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Leptich says she has even received calls about our terrible weather from The Los Angeles Times and from several Japanese newspapers. ''It's like the world went wild,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles's interest is easy to understand. People there love it when New Yorkers are miserable. The same goes for many Floridians, especially those who used to live here. On a mild February night, nothing thrills them more in Boca Raton than to hear that 16 inches of snow fell on Corona.</p>
        <p>Why the Japanese should care is another matter. This is their rainy season. You would think they'd worry about their own problems.</p>
        <p>Frankly, it is disheartening to see how irritable so many New Yorkers have been about the rain. As you may have heard, we just broke a century-old record for June, with more than 10 inches of rain thus far and still a week to go. You'd think this might be a cause for celebration, something to push New Yorkers' well-worn ''We're No. 1'' buttons.</p>
        <p>Just as old-timers once talked about the Blizzard of '88 -- that's 1888, kid -- we now have something to leave our grandchildren bored silly. We can tell them for the umpteenth time what it was like to be a muggy Muggle back during the Torrents of '03.</p>
        <p>WHAT do we have instead? Endless grousing and much maligning of the rain.</p>
        <p>Think bright thoughts. Thanks to the damp, it has been pleasantly cool. This is splendid news for those who lose sleep over global warming.</p>
        <p>We can cheer ourselves by fancying we are in Paris, which has this kind of crummy weather all the time but always remains beautiful, regardless of the geopolitics of the moment.</p>
        <p>If rain is so terrible, how come lawyers describe the members of their tribe who bring in the big bucks as rainmakers?</p>
        <p>Now, without passing Go, we have zoomed from benign coolness to irritating heat. Temperatures all of a sudden are supposed to be hanging in the 90's.</p>
        <p>You know what this means. It means another summer of subway platforms that put furnaces to shame. It also means all too many New Yorkers parading around in what looks suspiciously like their underwear. The aesthetic assault can be overpowering.</p>
        <p>Let's be honest. How many times have you sat across from some ridiculously underdressed person on a train or bus, someone who does not exactly bring to mind the dimensions of J. Lo or her boyfriend B. Aff, and said to yourself, ''Lady/Mister, you're making a big mistake''?</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the sunny days can't last. So here's an unsolicited tip. Pick a spot of your choosing that puts the Empire State Building in your line of vision. If you can't see its very top, odds are good that it is raining. If you can see the top, it means it is going to rain.</p>
        <p>Count on it, sooner or later.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
