<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1453396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DA103FF931A35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>South Korea Becomes Policy Irritant for U.S.  South Korea, which for half a century has been among the United States' most dependable allies in Asia, has now become one of the Bush administration's biggest foreign policy problems. Years of resentment are boiling over in the form of demonstrations against the U.S. in Seoul and pronouncements challenging American policies on dealing with North Korea's nuclear ambitions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Afghanistan's Urban Poor  The urban poor made homeless by war and rising costs in Afghanistan have fallen through the aid net and face the freezing winter with completely inadequate shelter.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>South Korea Becomes Policy Irritant for U.S.  South Korea, which for half a century has been among the United States' most dependable allies in Asia, has now become one of the Bush administration's biggest foreign policy problems. Years of resentment are boiling over in the form of demonstrations against the U.S. in Seoul and pronouncements challenging American policies on dealing with North Korea's nuclear ambitions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Afghanistan's Urban Poor  The urban poor made homeless by war and rising costs in Afghanistan have fallen through the aid net and face the freezing winter with completely inadequate shelter.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Photo Questioned  A Pakistani jeweler said that his picture is among those of five men who the F.B.I. says may have entered the United States on doctored passports, but that he has never visited the United States.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Better U.S.-Syria Relations  Syria and the U.S. are still in dispute over a number of issues, but Syria's recent help against terrorists has brought an important thaw, the first since a brief warming of relations in 1990, when Damascus offered a largely symbolic force to the coalition against Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Brazilian President Inaugurated  Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, leader of the left-wing Workers Party and a former lathe operator and labor union leader, was inaugurated as president of Brazil, promising ''a new style of government'' and a crusade against hunger, injustice and corruption.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Chinese Charge Demonstrators  The police in China have charged two leaders of worker demonstrations in Liaoyang with subversion -- a crime that carries the death penalty -- after they organized protests to focus attention on workers' interests.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Cyclone Devastates Island  A small Pacific island, Tikopia, has been hit by 40-foot waves generated by a cyclone that seems to have swept away entire villages and completely destroyed the lagoon around the island.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Oil Tanker Strikes Sunken Ship  A tanker carrying 70,000 metric tons of highly flammable gas oil struck the sunken hull of a Norwegian transport ship in the English Channel. The tanker was the second vessel in recent weeks to strike the sunken ship, and was briefly stuck before refloating. There was no evidence of damage or leaking.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>New Day for Paper in Paris  The International Herald Tribune, descendant of an American paper first published in Paris in 1887, is appearing for the first time under the sole ownership and management of The New York Times Company.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>China Plans Manned Spacecraft  China plans to launch its first manned spacecraft in the second half of this year, a government news agency announced, citing a senior aerospace official.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-15</p>
        <p>Foes of Abortion Prepare Big Push in New Congress  Galvanized by the Republican takeover of the Senate, opponents of abortion are preparing a major push for new abortion restrictions in the next Congress, beginning with a ban on the type of medical procedure they call ''partial birth abortion.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Professors vs. Computers  As universities rush toward a wireless future, installing networks that let students and the faculty surf the Internet from laptop computers in the classroom, the library or any where on campus, professors say the technology poses a growing challenge for them: retaining their students' attention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>DNA Dragnet for Serial Killer  Investigators in Louisiana, searching for a serial killer whose DNA has been recovered from all four of his victims, have taken DNA samples from 800 men for testing. Many of those 800 own or have access to white pickup trucks similar to the one that several eyewitnesses placed at the scene of two of the crimes.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Missed Deadline Costs Nevada  Citing failed negotiations, officials in Southern California prepared for cuts in water deliveries from the Colorado River. Neighboring Nevada was poised to lose 11 percent of its share of the river, even though the state's water agencies did nothing wrong.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>West Virginia Insurance Fight  Almost all surgeries were canceled at four hospitals in West Virginia's Northern Panhandle after more than two dozen surgeons took leaves of absence to protest the high cost of malpractice insurance.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Inquiry on Missile Defense  The Massachusetts Institute of Technology is looking into charges that its premier laboratory lied to cover up serious problems with the technology at the heart of the Bush administration's proposed antimissile defense system.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Rehnquist Urges Higher Pay  In his 17th year-end report on the federal judiciary, Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist called for higher judicial pay, more judgeships and speedier filling of existing vacancies, familiar themes that he said ''seem to never go away.''</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>More Time for Abuse Lawsuits  A new California law that lifts the statute of limitations on sexual abuse lawsuits involving Roman Catholic priests has gone into effect, allowing more time for the filing of lawsuits, but Southern California dioceses have won a reprieve in more than 100 potential cases.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Global Warming Alters Habitats  Researchers say global warming is forcing species around the world, from California sea anemones to Alpine herbs, to move into new ranges or alter habits in ways that could disrupt ecosystems.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Pataki Is Inaugurated, Seeks Unity in Fiscal Crisis  George Elmer Pataki was sworn in for his third term as New York's governor and challenged New Yorkers to confront the state's dire fiscal problems with the same courage and unity they displayed during the terrorist attacks 15 months ago.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Problems in Nassau County  Thomas R. Suozzi says that it has taken him the past year, his first as county executive of Nassau County, to learn the depth and the maddening details of the county's problems. ''It was far worse than I ever imagined,'' Mr. Suozzi said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>2 Killed by Police in Brooklyn  Police officers traded shots with gunmen in three incidents just blocks from one another in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn, killing two men who had fired at them, according to police officials.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>New Jersey's Green Guerrilla  Governor James E. McGreevey of New Jersey is emerging as something of a green guerrilla, at least in the eyes of Trenton's building and business lobbies, who say he is favoring environmental protection over economic development.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-8</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Parcells Will Coach Cowboys  Bill Parcells will be named the Dallas Cowboys' head coach, according to a team official, who said that Parcells agreed to a four-year contract worth $17 million to $18 million.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Joe Foss  A Medal of Honor winner as a fighter pilot in World War II who was a two-term governor of South Dakota, commissioner of the American Football League and head of the National Rifle Association, he was 87.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>U.S. TV Shows Fading Overseas  From Sicily to Singapore, American dramas and sitcoms increasingly occupy fringe time slots on foreign networks, while a growing number of homegrown shows -- produced by local broadcasters -- are on the air at the best times.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Some Optimism on Stocks  While investors still worry about high oil prices and a possible war with Iraq, there are signs within the market, including widespread bearishness and a spike in volatility, that a turning point was reached when stocks bottomed on Oct. 9.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Big-Name Mergers Expected  The days of industries being transformed by megamergers are past, but dozens of deals are now being mapped out for 2003 and big-name companies like Bristol-Myers Squibb, H. J. Heinz and AT&amp;T Wireless Services are likely to be involved.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bond Outlook: Not So Good  The good news may be over for bond investors in 2003. In 2002, the fixed-income market outperformed stocks for the third consecutive year. But an expected increase in interest rates is likely to reduce yields on fixed-income securities.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Oil Could Go On Wild Ride  This year could be the worst in a decade for oil prices. Potential threats to price stability include war in the Mideast, political turmoil in Venezuela and labor unrest in Nigeria.</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Modest hopes for 2003; the exercise of American power; assessing Mayor Bloomberg.</p>
        <p>Column: William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E5  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E16  Crossword</p>
        <p>E15  Weather</p>
        <p>B9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
