<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tide of Humanity Alters Long Island Sound</title>
    <meta content="Y25SOU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/25/nyregion/25SOUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="HUMAN NATURE: The Eelgrass Returns" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1491734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DA1531F936A15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="4035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tide of Humanity Alters Long Island Sound</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tide of Humanity Alters Long Island Sound</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>GROTON, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First of summerlong series of articles on evolving nature of Long Island Sound; there has been growing realization that Long Island Sound, ancient estuary extending 110 miles northeast from New York City to Rhode Island through densest population corridor in nation, has in a very real way become a human creation, where impact of civilization is complete; people have come to realize that sound would have to be managed for its own sake, and for region's; in economics, politics, culture and science, people took action, and nature responded; tiny sea plant called eelgrass, and group of families in Groton who unitentionally triggered its resurgence, play a part in story; management of nature, called environmental stewardship, is being applied in many places around world; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forty years ago in the summer of 1963, a writer for The New Yorker named Morton M. Hunt spent two weeks circumnavigating Long Island Sound in a little sailboat.</p>
        <p>When he sat down to write, he mourned. A way of life was disappearing. The old culture of the Sound -- a still wild mix of scruffy boatyards, Gold Coast snobs and fishermen, all set against the vast mirror of nature -- would surely be homogenized and pushed to the brink by the pell-mell rush of suburbanization and the mass market, Mr. Hunt wrote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long Island Sound has been a breadbasket and a dump, a playground for the wealthy and a symbol of environmental despair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forty years ago in the summer of 1963, a writer for The New Yorker named Morton M. Hunt spent two weeks circumnavigating Long Island Sound in a little sailboat.</p>
        <p>When he sat down to write, he mourned. A way of life was disappearing. The old culture of the Sound -- a still wild mix of scruffy boatyards, Gold Coast snobs and fishermen, all set against the vast mirror of nature -- would surely be homogenized and pushed to the brink by the pell-mell rush of suburbanization and the mass market, Mr. Hunt wrote.</p>
        <p>But then there was a plot twist that he could not have foreseen. In the years that followed Mr. Hunt's trip, people gradually began to realize that the Sound -- by the power of history and population and the environmental damage inflicted upon it -- had in a very real way become a human creation. The impact of civilization was complete, the idea of a return to wild nature only a fantasy.</p>
        <p>The ancient estuary, extending 110 miles northeast from New York City to Rhode Island through the densest population corridor in the nation -- loved and loathed as a breadbasket, playground and dump -- would have to be managed for its own sake, and for the region's.</p>
        <p>And that realization produced another voyage -- of discovery and confounding mystery, triumph and setback -- as people came to understand the complexity of what they had undertaken to do.</p>
        <p>In economics, politics, culture and science, people took action, and nature responded. A tiny sea plant called eelgrass, and a group of families here in Groton who unintentionally triggered its resurgence, play a part in that story.</p>
        <p>''We're learning for the first time where the Sound's heartbeat is, where the pulse is,'' said Robert B. Whitlatch, a professor of marine sciences at the University of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The management of nature, loosely called environmental stewardship, is being applied in many places around the world. In the North Sea, marine managers have compiled an exhaustive database about the aquatic food chain -- a kind of who eats whom of the fish world.</p>
        <p>In the United States, managers are remaking the bottom of Tampa Bay with the sea grasses of its past.</p>
        <p>But on the Sound there is much more going on than mere ecology. How people connect with the Sound, for instance, or how they don't -- and thus how much political clout the Sound's advocates can wield in Albany or Hartford or Washington -- is part of the new management equation as well, as politicians and environmentalists try to increase access to the water with new parks and beaches.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Adirondacks or the Hudson River, the Sound never stole the region's heart. It was always too close to New York City, too taken for granted, too practical in its uses -- as a fishery, a transportation artery or a trash can. There was no wolf baying at the moon to shiver the spine, no sense of a lost wilderness to touch the soul.</p>
        <p>What the Sound had, first and foremost, was people -- a bustling, grasping, dreaming, teeming population. It was America's first urban sea, a kitchen sink for the industrial revolution, and an ecological witness to the rise of the suburbs after World War II. Now, in the age of management, scientists and politicians say, the huge force and clout of that population -- one in 10 Americans within an hour's drive -- has once again made the Sound a kind of vanguard and sentinel. Where the nation's other great tidal estuaries might go, as demographic patterns and economies change around Chesapeake Bay or Puget Sound or San Francisco Bay, the Sound has already arrived.</p>
        <p>''It's the first 21st-century estuary,'' said Glenn R. Lopez, a professor of marine sciences at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, on Long Island. ''Its issues are all about human habitation.''</p>
        <p>Profound philosophical questions have emerged from this. If the Sound cannot be restored to what it was in the pre-European past -- and no one thinks that is remotely possible -- then what should it be? What is the optimum natural state in a system that has been overwhelmingly and permanently transformed by human presence? Should the Sound be managed for the sake of nature and biological diversity, or for the human pocketbook, to maximize the species people want to extract and attract the most tourists?</p>
        <p>But perhaps the biggest question is whether people are smart enough to chart the course at all. Nature, for every push that people impose, has pushed right back.</p>
        <p>Local and state governments have committed billions of dollars, for example, to reduce nitrogen from sewage treatment plants. But even as that process goes forward, evidence has mounted that climate change and warmer water temperatures may be altering the ecosystem as fast as humans can fix it.</p>
        <p>Efforts to restore lobster populations have been undercut, some scientists believe, by programs to bring back other species like striped bass, which have soared in number in recent years under wildlife management. Stripers adore finger-sized larval lobsters and eat them with great gulps whenever they can.</p>
        <p>Or consider the air itself. Wind moves differently over the built-up expanses of New York City and its suburbs than it did in centuries past, climate researchers say, and different winds make for different rates of mixing in the Sound's water column. Different mixing rates, in turn, can compound the problem of low oxygen that kills the animals that local governments are working to save through nitrogen reduction.</p>
        <p>And on and on it goes. The ecosystem has been put in motion and no one knows where it will stop.</p>
        <p>At a recent daylong conference on the Sound, Arthur Glowka voiced those anxieties. Mr. Glowka, a fisherman and retired pilot who had the lean and windblown look of a life lived on the water, thundered that the Sound's new managers were messing with things beyond the human ability to control, and that the piper would have to be paid.</p>
        <p>''We're playing God,'' Mr. Glowka said. ''And when you start to play God, you don't know what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>When he finished, the director of the Environmental Protection Agency's Long Island Sound office, Mark A. Tedesco, rose to respond.</p>
        <p>''I would submit that we've been playing God on the Sound for the last 300 years,'' Mr. Tedesco said. ''Now we're just trying to do it responsibly.''</p>
        <p>The Human Hand  Politics and Lawyers Help the Grass Grow</p>
        <p>A willowy, jade-green sea plant called eelgrass grows on the bottom of Mumford Cove, and for marine biologists and fishermen -- not to mention baby scallops, which hide from predators amid its waving fronds -- this qualifies as very big news. Eelgrass is disappearing all over the East Coast and across most of the rest of Long Island Sound, but here in an obscure little inlet on Groton's east end, it has been growing for the last decade in resplendent and thickening abundance.</p>
        <p>The tale of Mumford's eelgrass is only partly about nature, however. And that is why it says so much about the new rhythms of the Sound. It is also about the mysteries of the human heart, and small-town politics and shrewd lawyers.</p>
        <p>A Mumford Cove Christmas party figures prominently into the story. And so does Herman E. Sheets, a widower and retired engineer who met and fell in love with a New York civil prosecutor, then named Paulann M. Caplovitz, and brought her to live with him on the cove in 1983.</p>
        <p>But perhaps the most important thing to know is that nothing to do with eelgrass was ever remotely intended by anybody. People, acting on their own messy and complicated agendas, changed the cove's waters, and nature, literally out of the deep blue sea, responded.</p>
        <p>''Mumford Cove is a poster child,'' said R. Scott Warren, a professor of botany at Connecticut College in New London. ''The hypothesis says that where you take action, nature can recover, and on Mumford Cove, you can actually test that.''</p>
        <p>What makes the cove such an ideal laboratory for the human-wild connection, Professor Warren and other experts say, is that the trajectory of its decline and rebirth was so stark and so well documented.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheets, who is now 94, remembers diving off the dock with his children almost every summer night in the 1950's and 1960's after coming home from work at the Electric Boat submarine yard a few miles away, where he designed boats for the Navy.</p>
        <p>But then, beginning in the mid-1970's, it all changed. The volume of wastewater from the local sewage treatment plant, which then drained into the cove from an upland creek, began increasing as more and more people moved to the shore.</p>
        <p>Giant mats of sea lettuce -- a thick and glutinous plant that thrives in nitrogen-rich waters -- began to take over. By 1980, the cove had stopped even hiring lifeguards because no one was swimming. And what was worse, residents were told again and again that nothing could be done. Lawyers said it would be impossible to prove in court that the sewage or the slimy lettuce were causing ''irreparable harm,'' which was the legal standard they said would be needed to force the town to move the pipe somewhere else.</p>
        <p>That is when the former Ms. Caplovitz, now Mrs. Sheets, strode into the picture. She had been an assistant attorney general in New York (where she had met her future husband when he testified as an expert witness in one of her cases) and she felt certain that there was another way to fight. So at her first Mumford Cove Christmas party, in 1983, she said she had an idea.</p>
        <p>''We'd given up until Paulann came,'' said Robert Boggs, who has lived on the cove since the 1960's and was at the party that night. ''She was the catalyst.''</p>
        <p>With the backing of Mumford residents, Mrs. Sheets arranged for a new law firm to look at the cove, and the lawyers there found exactly what she hoped they would. Years earlier, Groton had been instructed by the state to move the sewer pipe across town to drain into the Thames River, but the town never got around to it.</p>
        <p>For purposes of a lawsuit, the cove's pollution was secondary. All the residents needed to do was prove that the town had violated a state order.</p>
        <p>The resulting fight split Groton down the middle, sparking anger and passions that in some corners of town have still yet to cool, and it all revolved around a couple of nagging questions:</p>
        <p>If the cove's residents didn't want the sewer outflow, why should anybody else?</p>
        <p>Were Mumford residents better than the people who lived near the Thames, where the alternative pipe would drain?</p>
        <p>''There wasn't really a scientific or environmental argument,'' said Mark R. Oefinger, the Groton town manager, who butted heads with Mrs. Sheets many times during those years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oefinger added, ''It was all about, 'If this stuff is bad for you, why is it good for us?' ''</p>
        <p>But the Mumford argument, however narrow and technical it seemed to some, prevailed. In 1986, a Federal District Court judge ordered the town to comply with the old state order.</p>
        <p>The cove's days as a dump were over.</p>
        <p>And a great experiment had begun.</p>
        <p>Webs and Consequences  Warning: Beware Of the Mute Swans</p>
        <p>So the eelgrass bloomed, and the naturalists swooned. But people were not alone in noticing the change.</p>
        <p>Min Huang, the waterfowl coordinator for the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection, took a helicopter flight over southeastern Connecticut this spring and saw three pairs of mute swans nesting in Mumford Cove -- the first time any had been observed there in the state's annual bird surveys.</p>
        <p>The arrival of swans, Mr. Huang and other experts say, suggests that another cycle of human-influenced nature may be under way here. Mute swans, a non-native species that escaped from a private preserve on Long Island around World War I, are notoriously destructive and voracious feeders who love, perhaps more than anything else -- you guessed it -- eelgrass.</p>
        <p>An adult mute swan weighing 30 pounds can eat 8 pounds of grass a day, and destroy 12 more pounds in rooting around for the choice morsels it wants. And to make the twisted cycle of nature complete, swans -- who can live 20 years or more and tend to stay permanently in their nesting areas once they've moved in -- are also officially protected by the full power of state law. The Connecticut General Assembly granted the birds protected status in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Like a nursery rhyme turned on its head, the logical links tumble like dominoes: It's a crime to harm the mute swans that eat the eelgrass that shelter the scallops that the Sound's managers would love to restore if they could. A formal study of the bird's impact on sea grass, focused in part on Mumford Cove, will begin later this year.</p>
        <p>''We do know that our decline of eelgrass has to do with water quality in many areas, but are mute swans inhibiting the recovery as well? That's what we'll be looking at,'' Mr. Huang said. ''One hypothesis is that the places we have eelgrass are the places the birds haven't discovered yet.''</p>
        <p>And so the ripple of implications from the Mumford Cove sewer pipe fight continues to expand. Are mute swans, searching for the foods they like, a natural phenomenon, or a perverse consequence?</p>
        <p>What, in the end, is natural at all in a place like the Sound? That's a question that James N. Kremer wrestles with all the time.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kremer, a professor of marine sciences at the University of Connecticut, has been studying Mumford Cove for nearly a decade, since he moved into the neighborhood just a few blocks from the beach in the mid-1990's. And on a recent foggy morning, he was doing what has by now become a monthly ritual -- testing the water, checking the growth of the eelgrass, and trying, most of all, to put the pieces of the puzzle together.</p>
        <p>Leaning over the rail of his school's research boat about 50 yards offshore, he pushed a metal pole with a cage down into the cove's mud. Up came a green clutch of eelgrass -- short, perhaps a bit stunted from the cold winter -- but alive and well.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kremer's goal goes far beyond merely understanding the botany. He is trying to construct what might be called a social-biological history of the cove -- a kind of management manual that mayors and wetlands commissioners all over the Sound, and perhaps the world, might be able to use in managing their local waters. The model will be stocked with all the variables about water quality and clarity -- a key factor for eelgrass photosynthesis -- along with as much of the human story that he can gather about what people did to alter that chemistry.</p>
        <p>''We want to make it useful to town planners and managers who deal with these issues every day, so they can see where they are on the spectrum and be able to say, well, if I do something different in the future, how will it look?'' he said.</p>
        <p>This is increasingly how science works on the Sound, especially now as grant money has become tighter. In writing proposals, practical applications have become a hook, Dr. Kremer and others say. And so in a kind of feedback loop of its own, research reinforces the management systems that in turn pay for the science that justifies more management.</p>
        <p>Relationships Revealed  A Feeling of Being In Your Backyard</p>
        <p>Peter J. Bartinik Sr., a lawyer in Groton, remembers being dispatched as a boy to Mumford Cove by his grandmother in the 1950's to collect clams and blue crabs for dinner. He would jump in the family's boat -- not much more than a rowboat, he said, with a little outboard motor -- and gather crabs by the bucketful, jacklighting them with a flashlight beam that would stun the crustaceans in their tracks, ready for the plucking.</p>
        <p>No one lived on the cove then. There was no beach (that was created much later by a real estate developer, using sand dredged from the cove's bottom). People would just camp out in places like Mumford, pull up in their boats, throw out a tent and spend the night, or the summer.</p>
        <p>''We'll never get back to that feeling that the Sound is your backyard,'' said Mr. Bartinik, 60, who lives on the cove. ''But in a way, that's good -- thinking of it as your backyard means you can do with it as you please.''</p>
        <p>That old casual relationship with nature, fading even in Mr. Bartinik's youth, is over now. Rules, regulations, protections and licenses -- for human and environmental protection -- are part of the new net. But in other ways, places like Mumford signal the beginning of a new relationship -- a new voyage to a place that is both deeply familiar, and yet also strangely undiscovered.</p>
        <p>Some people fear that management will make the Sound into a kind of park -- pleasant and safe to be in, but no more than an extension of the built environment. Other people say the very opposite has been revealed by the management efforts so far -- how truly wild, or at least unpredictable, the Sound still is. Opportunistic species -- whether eelgrass or swans or stripers -- aggressively expand to fill the niches that arise. In such a place and time, hope and loss are intertwined.</p>
        <p>''Long Island Sound shrugs,'' said James O'Donnell, a professor of marine sciences at the University of Connecticut. ''These systems are more robust than anybody imagined.''</p>
        <p>And yet for all the vast machinery and energy of management that has been unleashed, perhaps the ultimate lesson of Mumford Cove is that a handful of people, thinking in new ways about the old backyard, made a difference.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sheets, 62, who still practices law part time -- mostly environmental cases -- said it was really a simple thing that happened. ''I had two young children,'' she said. ''I had to do something. Herman's children had swum and boated in the cove, but now it was unswimmable. I couldn't live on the shore of such a beautiful place that was so degraded.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheets nodded. A simple thing indeed, he said, in an interview in his living room with its a sweeping view of the cove. When he brought his new wife home here, a little more than a decade after the death of his first wife, Norma, healing began.</p>
        <p>''After I married Paulann, everything changed,'' he said. ''Mumford Cove started to live again.''</p>
        <p>Human Nature</p>
        <p>Over many years of settlement, Long Island Sound has been a breadbasket and a dumping ground, a private playground for the wealthy and a symbol of environmental despair.</p>
        <p>But when people reached for a new definition -- a repaired, restored, managed Sound -- nature did not respond according to the rulebook.</p>
        <p>For every push to achieve a certain end, the whorls of the ecosystem have pushed right back, often in unexpected ways.</p>
        <p>This is the first of a summer-long series of articles on the evolving nature of Long Island Sound. The second article will look at the fading world of the boatyards. Many are sinking fast as the old ways of the Sound ebb, while others hang on -- the last of the old salt survivors.</p>
        <p>Additional materials, including a preview of the remainder of the series, can be found on the Web at nytimes.com/lisound.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
