<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Heavenly Host, But a Grudging Guest</title>
    <meta content="08RITU$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/08/travel/escapes/08RITU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1510353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="RITUALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island/Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamptons (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4D81731F93BA3575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Heavenly Host, But a Grudging Guest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Heavenly Host, but a Grudging Guest</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Kaufman Rituals column explains why she cherishes her time at her weekend home in Connecticut and would rather be host than guest in someone else's place; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FRIENDS have just invited us to their beach house in the Hamptons. They have a tennis court, a swimming pool and a Jacuzzi. They are lovely, charming, wonderful people. The following weekend, we've been asked to visit friends whose enchanting weekend home is the former gatehouse of an estate in the mountains. They are fabulous. So are the views.</p>
        <p>Don't make me go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>However taxing it is to be a host, I find it infinitely less taxing than being a guest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FRIENDS have just invited us to their beach house in the Hamptons. They have a tennis court, a swimming pool and a Jacuzzi. They are lovely, charming, wonderful people. The following weekend, we've been asked to visit friends whose enchanting weekend home is the former gatehouse of an estate in the mountains. They are fabulous. So are the views.</p>
        <p>Don't make me go.</p>
        <p>There are those, I know, whose Samsonites are always loaded and ready, who happily depend on the kindness of friends thoughtful enough to hold deeds to mountain retreats and seaside cottages. Here's what I say: Give them the room you intended for me. I don't want to be your guest. Please understand it's nothing personal. I don't want to be anyone's guest.</p>
        <p>Since my husband, Michael, and I bought a weekend home in Connecticut a decade ago, I have fought hard for home court advantage. Cunningly, I have cultivated a reputation as -- literally and figuratively -- an accommodating host. Our establishment, which we call the Easton Westin (not to be confused with the Wilton Hilton, operated by our friends Tom and Rhonda), has a guest room in perpetual readiness (cable hookup, DVD player, a mint on the pillow, the whole deal). We have guacamole, salsa and fat-free black bean dip, chicken if you don't eat red meat, pasta if you eat neither. You want the pool heated to 81 degrees? Done, and here's your towel and sunblock. Friends marvel at the effort and the pesto I put forth. But if I'm a heavenly host, it's only because I want to avoid someone else's hospitality.</p>
        <p>Therapists -- and my husband -- might say I'm a control freak, pure and simple, and I'm not fool enough to argue the point. I do like sleeping in my bed, under my quilt with my two mushy pillows. I want the freedom to get up in the middle of the night and raid the refrigerator, to decide whether there will be onion in the hamburgers (there will) or avocado in the salad (there won't).</p>
        <p>But there's more to it than control. Summer is my favorite time in Easton. The pool is 50 feet away, the garden even closer. And because we're only there on weekends -- and because this year, at least, the first several of those summer Saturdays and Sundays were lost to rain -- I zealously guard my time in the chlorine and the clematis. Why deal with traffic, sand in my swimsuit and who knows what other guests when I'm right where I want to be? And I do think most people will agree that just when they figure out how to work the shower and the remote control, and where the host hides the good scotch, it's time to mosey on back home.</p>
        <p>I know that it is only fair to let people reciprocate, that if I keep refusing to go to friends' homes they are going to start refusing to come to mine, even with chocolate-chip brownies hanging in the balance. But I divide the world into two groups, hosts and guests. I think I'm pretty good at the former -- and I don't necessarily think that everyone has that skill set anymore than I think that everyone has the right stuff to be a guest (more about that in a minute). I have been to more homes than I care to count where those in charge labored under the impression that chicken is best eaten rare, that dinner is best served before 5 (I call that lunch) or after 10 p.m. (I call that either careless or breakfast), or who saw being a host as a way to tap into their inner cruise director. Thus, golf at 7:30 a.m., antiquing at 10, the garden conservancy tour at noon, croquet at 3, etc., etc.</p>
        <p>However taxing it is to be a host -- the shopping, the organizing, the cooking, the cleaning and the cleaning up -- I find it infinitely less taxing than being a guest. As a visitor, you must be as neat and tidy as a Trappist, and I'm not just talking about the way you leave the guest room and the bathroom. (Indeed, a highly meticulous, conscientious woman of my acquaintance insists on cleaning her hostess's kitchen floor after dinner.) Your relationship with your spouse has to be tidy, too. Snarky asides, while perfectly acceptable and understandable when directed by an overstressed hostess to her mate, come across as something straight out of ''Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?'' when you're the guest.</p>
        <p>Guests, I think, also have an obligation to play nicely with their fellow visitors (however odious the world view of such other folk) and to sing -- or zing -- for their supper, coming to the table with a working knowledge of geopolitics, campaign 2004, the greenhouse effect and Jen and Ben. But as the hostess, I don't have to spend Thursday night turning on C-Span, Charlie Rose and ''Entertainment Tonight'' to get up to speed. All I have to turn on is the Cuisinart.</p>
        <p>RITUALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
