<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Manhattan Freezes Over</title>
    <meta content="23REVK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/23/movies/23REVK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1583707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Emmerich, Roland</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strieber, Whitley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Art</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Day After Tomorrow, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Coming Global Superstorm, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Emmerich, Roland</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5DB123FF930A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="2179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Manhattan Freezes Over</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Manhattan Freezes Over</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew C Revkin article on scientific theory behind film The Day After Tomorrow, directed by Roland Emmerich, who is known for highly successful movies depicting catastrophic events; says film is based on 'pop-apocalyptic' book The Coming Global Superstorm by Whitley Strieber and Art Bell, which forecasts global freeze, rather than slow warming predicted by many scientists; Emmerich and Strieber comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEMISPHERE-SPANNING tempests rage. Hailstones the size of bowling balls bash Tokyo. Twisters tear up Hollywood. Snowstorms smother India. A flood tide swamps Manhattan, followed by a downburst of ultra-cold air that flash-freezes pedestrians in a New York second.</p>
        <p>At a pace far faster than any scientist had predicted, global warming caused by pollution disrupts vital ocean currents, and Earth is plunged within days into a big chill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"The Day After Tomorrow" is the biggest, brashest effort yet by a filmmaker to take the industrialized world to the woodshed for messing things up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEMISPHERE-SPANNING tempests rage. Hailstones the size of bowling balls bash Tokyo. Twisters tear up Hollywood. Snowstorms smother India. A flood tide swamps Manhattan, followed by a downburst of ultra-cold air that flash-freezes pedestrians in a New York second.</p>
        <p>At a pace far faster than any scientist had predicted, global warming caused by pollution disrupts vital ocean currents, and Earth is plunged within days into a big chill.</p>
        <p>Two survivors of the epic upheaval leave their bonfire of burning books inside the New York Public Library to scavenge medicine -- from the Russian ship that has run aground on Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>As if all that were not enough, the survivors have even more to contend with. ''Very quiet, everyone, the wolves are on the set,'' comes the stage whisper from an assistant director. ''And -- action.''</p>
        <p>Hunched beside his cinematographer on a Montreal soundstage in March of last year, Roland Emmerich, the director of the blockbuster ''Independence Day'' and the ''Godzilla'' remake, chuckled as he brushed faux snow from his sweater and prepared to assault civilization with his latest monster, an instant ice age spawned by humanity's disregard for the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Emmerich, 48, has made a profitable habit out of trying to humble Earth's dominant species. In his earlier movies, people united and defeated the aliens and the mutated reptile; in ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' we may have met our match. There have been other films depicting environmental debacles. But this is the biggest, brashest effort yet by a filmmaker to take the industrialized world to the woodshed for messing things up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Emmerich, who was born in Germany, has made no secret of his environmentalist streak or his dislike of President Bush, saying in a spate of recent European interviews that he hopes Mr. Bush is defeated in November. But he has been just as clear about his thirst to make money, and lots of it, with catastrophist cinema. With ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' which will be released worldwide on Friday, he claims to be uniting his political and financial motivations.</p>
        <p>The film is based on ''The Coming Global Superstorm,'' a pop-apocalyptic book forecasting an icy Armageddon -- written by proponents of extraterrestrials and the paranormal, not climate scientists. Mr. Emmerich said he bought the book as a diversion while shooting ''The Patriot'' in Charleston, S.C., in 1999.</p>
        <p>Most experts on climate change say a switch from slow warming to an instant hemispheric deep freeze like the one posited in the book is impossible. All the same, they say, regional disruptions in climate -- like a sharp wintertime cooling in Europe -- could take place in a warming world. Mr. Emmerich and his team acknowledge they have ramped things up over nature's real worst-case scenario perhaps a thousandfold. Otherwise, Mr. Emmerich said, they would have had to find another way to make events that stretch over decades or centuries scary enough for a movie.</p>
        <p>The book, Mr. Emmerich said, painted a vivid, jolting picture of the very worst worst-case scenario. Its chief author, Whitley Strieber, has had a strange, albeit successful, multipronged career as a catastrophist, horror writer and self-described alien abductee. (His novels include ''The Wolfen,'' ''The Hunger'' and, coming full circle, the novelization of ''The Day After Tomorrow.'') In an interview, Mr. Strieber said that ''Global Superstorm'' simply took the basic notion of warming as the trigger for cooling, and added imagined vignettes to illustrate the outcome. His co-author for the final volume was Art Bell, a longtime radio talk-show host who has focused on the paranormal.</p>
        <p>One scene, recreated in the film, has hundreds of thousands of Americans fleeing across the Mexican border ahead of the cold and ice. ''What a great symbol of a reversal of fortune,'' Mr. Emmerich said. ''I didn't read the book for three or four months, but as soon as I did, I immediately knew it was a movie.''</p>
        <p>The final script, written by Mr. Emmerich and Jeffrey Nachmanoff, uses the book mainly as a launching pad. Mr. Nachmanoff visited federal and academic researchers to gather ideas and maintain at least a threadlike attachment to reality. And many climate experts who have seen the script or screenings of the film say that, apart from the Hollywood exaggerations -- the speed with which the film's freeze-up occurs is impossible -- the underlying notions driving the film are legitimate.</p>
        <p>''To portray the dramatic effects of a major climatic disaster within a short time span, they simply took known weather extremes -- tornados, storm surges, cyclones, hail storms and blizzards -- and amplified those,'' said Dr. Stefan Rahmstorf, a prominent expert on oceans and climate from the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research in Germany. ''Given the rules and constraints of the genre, it is remarkable to what extent the filmmakers have tried to present some realistic background.''</p>
        <p>For all their exaggerations, the book and movie are based on the established theory that the higher global temperatures resulting from rising levels of heat-trapping smokestack and tailpipe discharges could set off abrupt cooling by disrupting the complicated array of currents in the North Atlantic. Scientists have found evidence that runoff from melting glacial ice around the Arctic has in millenniums long past occasionally shut down the ocean's natural conveyer belt for heat -- even part of the famous Gulf Stream, which carries tropical warmth to high latitudes.</p>
        <p>As Richard B. Alley, a climate expert at Pennsylvania State University, has put it, these currents explain why roses can grow in Norway even though elsewhere its latitude is home to polar bears. Evidence supporting the idea that such warmth is fragile accumulated a decade ago, when Dr. Alley and other scientists studying cylinders of ancient layered ice extracted from Greenland glaciers found patterns showing extraordinarily fast plunges in temperatures at least twice since the end of the last ice age. North Atlantic currents and patterns of saltiness have shown recent changes that are in line with those thought to have triggered the past climate disruptions.</p>
        <p>But many experts say it will take another decade of data collection to determine whether the ocean-climate system is switching to a new colder state or just fluctuating unpredictably, as it always does. And, scientists say, even if the currents do slow or stop, there's no evidence that conditions could shift in the way depicted in the movie. They believe that Northern Europe might see winters 10 degrees colder than now, but that summers would remain warm because of the building emissions and widespread warming.</p>
        <p>Still, climatologists are reluctant to rule anything out, given the list of surprising recent discoveries that indicate that the last 8,000 years or so represent a rare period of relatively stable climate amid epochs of upheaval. And the worst-case risks have prompted growing discussions in widening policy circles. The National Academy of Sciences issued a report in 2002 calling climate surprises ''inevitable.'' That led the Pentagon's longterm planners to hire corporate futurists to draw up a worst-case assessment. Their conclusion was that abrupt climate change was ''plausible'' and ''would challenge United States national security in ways that should be considered immediately.'' Their scenario had wars, rioting, floods, storms. In other words, it was a slightly paler version of the movie.</p>
        <p>Once again, life was imitating art, Mr. Emmerich said, recalling how, after he'd been sent an article on the Pentagon study earlier this year, he said: ''Someone's playing a joke on me. This can't be true.''</p>
        <p>''The Day After Tomorrow'' follows the Ulysses-like efforts of Jack Hall, an obsessive paleoclimatologist played by Dennis Quaid, to head north from Washington toward ice-crusted Manhattan -- against a flood tide of refugees -- to rescue his teenage son, Sam, played by Jake Gyllenhaal.</p>
        <p>On the set, Mr. Gyllenhaal, swathed in coats and gloves theoretically gleaned from the New York Public Library's lost and found, said he had initially been hesitant to sign on for a big-budget movie that builds global warming into such a caricature.</p>
        <p>''Your first fear with a movie like this is that it's so spectacular it would nullify the idea,'' he said, as technicians from Snow Business, the company supplying about 10 truckloads of fake flakes, refilled the blowers with ''medium snow'' for the next blizzard shot. ''People might just get back in their S.U.V.'s at the end.'' But as he learned more about the human role in climate change, Mr. Gyllenhaal said, he became more committed both to making the film and to trying to curb the emissions associated with his own lifestyle. ''Hopefully we're getting the message out there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Critics of the movie, including Steven J. Milloy, a commentator for foxnews.com and the libertarian, industry-supported Cato Institute, have jumped on statements of this sort. Mr. Milloy recently wrote that the whole project smacks of ''nauseating elitism.''</p>
        <p>The messages, however, will inevitably take a back seat to the action, even if it is mainly propelled by Earth's unbuckled atmosphere and oceans rather than careening cars and gravity-defying superheros. The filmmakers saved on salaries, avoiding superstars, so they could invest more money in special effects -- everything from the breakup of an Antarctic ice sheet the size of Rhode Island to the near-total swamping of the Statue of Liberty by a tidal wave.</p>
        <p>As preparations for filming accelerated through 2002, unusual weather patterns added a sense of urgency to the project.</p>
        <p>''With the floods in Europe and the breaking of that ice shelf in Antarctica, I realized we had to hurry up or otherwise we're making a documentary,'' Mr. Emmerich said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Emmerich -- whose aliens in ''Independence Day'' (1996) blew up the White House -- made his movie timely in other ways as well. The movie highlights the unilateralism of a fictional administration that is unmistakably similar to the current one and features a vice president (played by an actor who could be a stand-in for Dick Cheney) scoffing at climate warnings even as chaos spreads.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists have expressed surprise that the film, with a budget topping $125 million, is coming from 20th Century Fox, a division of the News Corporation. That conservative media empire, run by Rupert Murdoch, regularly produces commentaries, like Mr. Milloy's, attacking global warming as an eco-alarmist fantasy. Mr. Milloy has called Mr. Emmerich a big-budget eco-extremist. ''The movie's unmistakable purpose,'' he wrote recently, ''is to scare us into submitting to the Greens' agenda: domination of society through control of energy resources.''</p>
        <p>But there is every indication that the movie's potential to make lots of money has trumped any major concerns News Corporation executives may have about its politics. The company is spending about $50 million to promote the movie and has gained only tiny concessions from Mr. Emmerich in trying to soften the film's punches.</p>
        <p>There was some nervousness about creating the first big-budget movie to devastate New York since the attacks on the World Trade Center. Indeed, in one aerial view, one of the first places struck by a giant tidal surge is that now-vacant part of the city. But the filmmakers and studio agreed, Mr. Nachmanoff said, that the film depicts New Yorkers as enduring and indomitable. ''The positive aspect of this story is that humans will be able to endure and adapt,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Such optimism aside, Mr. Emmerich expressed a certain glee at having concocted what he called ''a popcorn movie that's actually a little subversive.''</p>
        <p>In the global marketplace for big-budget action movies, this could be to its benefit, particularly in Europe, where anger about American foreign and environmental policy has rarely been as intense, people involved in making the movie said. Prints have been prepared with dubbing or subtitles in 70 languages.</p>
        <p>Still, environmental groups were split until recently on whether to embrace the movie for raising the climate issue or avoid it because of its distortions. Most have decided it's too much free publicity to ignore. Volunteers from various groups plan to see the movie on its opening weekend and then hand out leaflets about the real risks of global warming.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace has chosen a more pointed tactic. The movie's official Web site, thedayaftertomorrow.com, uses the slogan ''Where will you be?'' Greenpeace's nearly identical site, thedayaftertomorrow.org, displays actual photographs depicting climate change and says: ''The day is today. What will you do?'' In its mock listing of cast and crew, the director is Exxon Mobil and the producer is George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
