<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq and Middle East at Center of Economic Summit</title>
    <meta content="08SUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/08/international/middleeast/08summ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1587824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Group of Eight</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yawar, Ghazi Al- (Sheik)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE1F31F93BA35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq and Middle East at Center of Economic Summit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraq and Middle East at Center of Economic Summit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON and DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>SAVANNAH, Ga., June 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush, secluded on heavily secured resort on Sea Island, Georgia, prepares for Group of 8 summit meeting at which he will discuss plans for encouraging Mideast democracy and keeping nuclear weapons out of terrorist hands; leading guest will be Iraq's new interim Pres Sheik Ghazi Ajil al-Yawar; security adviser Condoleezza Rice says UN Security Council talks on new Iraq resolution may be completed in time for meeting; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secluded on a heavily secured island off the Georgia coast, President Bush prepared Monday for a three-day international summit meeting that the White House said would showcase its plans for encouraging democracy throughout the Middle East and keeping nuclear weapons out of the hands of terrorists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush went fishing, held briefings with aides and readied himself for the arrival of leaders from seven other nations -- Britain, France, Italy, Canada, Germany, Japan and Russia -- who were making their way to the Group of 8 meeting of advanced industrial nations on Sea Island, Ga. The meeting is taking place as the United Nations Security Council moves toward a resolution for returning self-governance to Iraq while authorizing the continued presence of American and other foreign troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Group of 8 summit meeting will showcase the White House's plans for encouraging democracy throughout the Middle East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secluded on a heavily secured island off the Georgia coast, President Bush prepared Monday for a three-day international summit meeting that the White House said would showcase its plans for encouraging democracy throughout the Middle East and keeping nuclear weapons out of the hands of terrorists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush went fishing, held briefings with aides and readied himself for the arrival of leaders from seven other nations -- Britain, France, Italy, Canada, Germany, Japan and Russia -- who were making their way to the Group of 8 meeting of advanced industrial nations on Sea Island, Ga. The meeting is taking place as the United Nations Security Council moves toward a resolution for returning self-governance to Iraq while authorizing the continued presence of American and other foreign troops.</p>
        <p>In an exclusive beach resort setting chosen to protect against a terrorist attack and far away from the antiwar and antiglobalization protesters expected to assemble near here, the leaders are to consider a variety of issues including global warming, trade and the ways to help Africa deal with AIDS and poverty.</p>
        <p>But their agenda will be dominated by Iraq, the Middle East and the threat from terrorism, topics that in the administration's view are closely interlinked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will meet with, among others, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. But the guest likely to be lavished with the most attention is Iraq's new interim president, Sheik Ghazi Ajil al-Yawar, who will meet with Mr. Bush on Wednesday and take part in a broader meeting between the Group of 8 leaders and those from Middle Eastern nations.</p>
        <p>Condoleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's national security adviser, said negotiations on the Security Council resolution were ''going in a very positive direction'' and could be completed during the meeting. If so, Mr. Bush would be able to claim a major diplomatic victory surrounded by world leaders, even if he has to bend to some degree to international pressure to win United Nations backing.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they were also hopeful that the Arab world would be more receptive to the message that the way to address the forces that breed terrorism and conflict in the Middle East is to nurture moves toward democracy and economic development.</p>
        <p>The White House's efforts to sell that message so far have run into opposition from some Arab governments and a lack of enthusiasm from others. Some leaders said they did not want to receive a lecture from the United States and the other Group of 8 countries, some of which have also been uneasy about Mr. Bush's plan.</p>
        <p>To win support from Arab countries, the administration has rewritten parts of the statement the Group of 8 will issue on the topic, and added language calling for a new effort to solve the Arab-Israeli conflict.</p>
        <p>King Abdullah II of Jordan, Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan of Turkey, President Hamid Karzai of Afghanistan and President Ali Abdallah Salih of Yemen were among the leaders who were to attend the Group of 8 session on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Administration officials suggested that they were walking a fine line between responding to the concerns of Arab and Middle Eastern governments and pushing as hard as possible to send a signal of encouragement and support to people pushing for more democracy in the region.</p>
        <p>''There had been a desire on the part of some governments in the region that the G-8 work with and mention only governments,'' said a senior administration official, who the White House insisted not be identified. ''But of course, in some cases governments are the engine of reform and in other cases governments are attempting to hold reform back.''</p>
        <p>The official said the White House was ''cognizant of the fact that sometimes foreign support for reform and reformers can be helpful, and sometimes it won't be.'' The administration understands, the official said, ''that reform must be indigenous and that each country will be different, and that reform will look different in each country.''</p>
        <p>For the first time in four months, Mr. Bush is also expected to press anew for a broad effort to cut off the production of new nuclear materials that can be converted to fuel for nuclear weapons -- a step intended to cut off supplies to nations like Iran and North Korea.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush made the proposal in February, in the wake of the public disclosures of how the former head of a Pakistani nuclear laboratory, Abdul Qadeer Khan, sold uranium technology to both those countries and Libya, which has now dismantled its nuclear program.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's proposal -- and one issued last week by his presumptive Democratic opponent, Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts -- stops short of a full-scale cutoff of the production of new fissile materials. Instead, it would allow continued production and sales by nations that already enrich uranium or reprocess spent nuclear reactor fuel to produce plutonium. Several of those countries are represented here -- among them, Britain, France, Japan and Russia -- and none appear eager to give up their production capability.</p>
        <p>In a briefing, Ms. Rice said the president had ''a number of agenda items'' about his proposal, and other officials said they expected he would specifically mention Iran's nuclear program, which the International Atomic Energy Agency indicated last week was still engaged in nuclear development activities that it seemed unable or unwilling to explain.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice said the president would address how to deal with countries that ''pursue what are supposedly civilian uses of nuclear power, but, in fact, use that as a cover to producing or for pursuing military uses and perhaps nuclear weapons development.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Bush seems unwilling to reopen the central bargain of the three-decade-old Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty, which requires the nuclear-armed nations to provide technical help to nonnuclear states to develop those commercial programs. Nor has the Bush administration supported, so far, a broader proposal for a treaty to end all production of fissile material. The Pentagon fears this would stop it from producing new ''bunker-busting'' nuclear weapons, and the other nuclear powers say it would make it difficult for them to maintain their existing nuclear weapons stockpiles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
