<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alarms for Detecting Carbon Monoxide</title>
    <meta content="24HOME$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/24/realestate/24HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041031T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1621588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DA113AF937A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alarms for Detecting Carbon Monoxide</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Alarms for Detecting Carbon Monoxide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advice on new New York City law requiring installation of carbon monoxide detectors in homes and apartments; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Nov. 1, Local Law 7 of 2004 takes effect in New York City. If everyone does what the law requires, there will be at least 2.8 million carbon monoxide detectors installed in homes and apartments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael M. Marin, medical director of emergency services at Lenox Hill Hospital, said the law would almost certainly save lives. Indeed, three people in Staten Island died of carbon monoxide poisoning in their home on Oct. 19.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This November Local Law 7 takes effect in New York City, which means there will be at least 2.8 million carbon monoxide detectors installed in homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Nov. 1, Local Law 7 of 2004 takes effect in New York City. If everyone does what the law requires, there will be at least 2.8 million carbon monoxide detectors installed in homes and apartments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael M. Marin, medical director of emergency services at Lenox Hill Hospital, said the law would almost certainly save lives. Indeed, three people in Staten Island died of carbon monoxide poisoning in their home on Oct. 19.</p>
        <p>''Carbon monoxide is an odorless, tasteless, colorless gas that is a byproduct of the burning of almost every form of fuel,'' he said. ''When it enters the body, it decreases the body's ability to transport oxygen. It poisons you. It can kill you.''</p>
        <p>Ilyse Fink, a spokeswoman for the New York City Department of Buildings, said that Local Law 7 requires owners to install carbon monoxide detectors in residential buildings that use fossil fuels -- coal, kerosene, oil, wood, gas and other petroleum products -- in a furnace, boiler, water heater or fireplace. ''The law requires the installation of a detector within 15 feet of the primary entrance to any room used for sleeping purposes,'' Ms. Fink said. A home or apartment with bedroom entrances more than 30 feet apart -- as well as those with bedrooms on different floors -- will require more than one carbon monoxide detector.</p>
        <p>The law applies to one- and two-family homes, apartment houses (three-family homes and above), hotels, motels, lodging houses, rooming houses, dormitories, rectories, convents and group homes.</p>
        <p>Carol Abrams, a spokeswoman for the New York City Department of Housing Preservation and Development, said that when a landlord installs a detector in a rental apartment the law requires the tenant to reimburse the owner $25 within one year. Tenants are responsible for maintaining detectors, but landlords must replace missing or defective units. When a landlord has to replace a detector that was damaged by a tenant, lost or stolen, he is entitled to reimbursement.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide poisoning can take two forms: acute and chronic. Firefighters who run into a burning building can get significant exposure in a short time. ''Then there is low-level, chronic exposure you can get by being exposed to relatively small amounts of carbon monoxide over an extended period,'' Dr. Marin said.</p>
        <p>The symptoms associated with carbon monoxide poisoning include headache, fatigue and nausea. ''The problem is, these symptoms are associated with so many other illnesses, you may never realize that carbon monoxide is the cause,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mark Devine, vice president for product development and quality at First Alert, an alarm manufacturer in Aurora, Ill., said that carbon monoxide detectors cost from $20 to $40. ''With the $20 model you're getting basic protection,'' he said, explaining that such units sound a loud alarm when carbon monoxide levels are at 70 parts per million for 180 minutes, 400 parts per million for 15 minutes, and various levels in between. More costly models, in addition to the alarm, provide digital readouts and ''peak reading'' information, which stores in memory the highest level detected.</p>
        <p>Through the Fire Department, the city will distribute 60,000 detectors donated by First Alert over the next three years to residents who cannot afford them.</p>
        <p>If an alarm sounds, open a window, check on family members, vacate the area and call 911.</p>
        <p>The alarms do not have to be mounted on the ceiling but can be installed on the wall at any height. (Combination units, which serve as both smoke and carbon monoxide alarms, must be put on the ceiling.)</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 31, 2004, Sunday  The Your Home column last Sunday, about the installation of carbon monoxide detectors, misstated the positioning requirement in New York City for combination units, which sense both smoke and carbon monoxide. The alarms may be installed on or near the ceiling -- not necessarily on the ceiling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 31, 2004, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Your Home column last Sunday, about the installation of carbon monoxide detectors, misstated the positioning requirement in New York City for combination units, which sense both smoke and carbon monoxide. The alarms may be installed on or near the ceiling -- not necessarily on the ceiling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
