<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parenting a Common Loon</title>
    <meta content="05SUN3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/05/opinion/05sun3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1609250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Notebook"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Loons (Birds)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Adirondack Mountains</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randolph, Eleanor</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Editorial Notebook (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Eleanor</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DC1131F936A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parenting a Common Loon</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Parenting a Common Loon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR RANDOLPH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Randolph, Eleanor</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleanor Randolph, in Editorial Notebook column, expresses concern for loon chick on Adirondacks lake and whether it will have time to mature and fly south before lake freezes (M)9</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pair of exquisite common loons returned this year to the lake in the Adirondacks where the birds and I both feel serenely at home. Sometime in late July, these loons produced a chick, a small, brown thing that could barely be spotted riding the lake on its mother's back.</p>
        <p>This new addition was cause for a great deal of celebratory clucking among the humans who registered its birth at a respectful distance. We greeted this year's loon chick as an assuring sign that despite the world's ecological perils -- the acid rain, the mercury poisoning, the warming globe -- there is a little good news in our environment. The next generation of this splendid species had arrived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nervously watching our godchick and hoping for flight before the freeze.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A pair of exquisite common loons returned this year to the lake in the Adirondacks where the birds and I both feel serenely at home. Sometime in late July, these loons produced a chick, a small, brown thing that could barely be spotted riding the lake on its mother's back.</p>
        <p>This new addition was cause for a great deal of celebratory clucking among the humans who registered its birth at a respectful distance. We greeted this year's loon chick as an assuring sign that despite the world's ecological perils -- the acid rain, the mercury poisoning, the warming globe -- there is a little good news in our environment. The next generation of this splendid species had arrived.</p>
        <p>Yet our celebrations were quickly tempered by concern about the odds for this fragile ball of down. There are dangers from the motorboats, from curious humans, from birds of prey circling overhead. With each passing week, we also began to worry about a larger question: Will our little loon have time to mature and fly south before the lake freezes?</p>
        <p>Nina Schoch, who runs the Adirondack Cooperative Loon Program, sent word to our anxious flock of surrogate parents that only after a loon chick survives four or five weeks can you really start hoping that it will survive at all. Ours has now passed that threshold, but it needs another six or seven to get airborne. This is cutting it close.</p>
        <p>In much of the Adirondacks, July is summer. August is when the leaves turn. September and October can get too cold for things without fur, and November can be the absolute deadline: it's liftoff or nature's freezer. If this year's weather makes enough time for our bird, this family threesome will head for Long Island or possibly even farther south to New Jersey.</p>
        <p>As the nights signal oncoming winter, Gary Lee, a retired New York State forest ranger for our area, has added our baby loon to his own very long watch list. Mr. Lee is a busy man, caring for the north country's loons. Some of these large birds, which can live over 30 years, barely ruffle a feather when his canoe slides close to their nest. They know him as the creature who untangles the fishing line from around their beaks or who helps band them for naturalists assessing the loon population in the park. Some pairs trust him to hold their newborns in his hand. ''I talk to all my birds,'' Mr. Lee says fondly, ''They know me.''</p>
        <p>Our loon couple is not so trusting, he says, so our chick is viewed by even Mr. Lee at a distance. He gives it a chance, a maybe. The rest of us will not stay long enough into the winter to actually watch what happens to our little one. Maybe that is just as well. We do know how it will be treated if it ever tries to return to momma's alluring summer nest. In noises that do not sound anything like the tapes of loon tremolos and yodels that they sell in Adirondack souvenir shops, our splendidly feathered mom will tell it to buzz off. Meanwhile, if all goes well, she and the humans around her will already be cooing over the next summer's newborn loon.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR RANDOLPH</p>
        <p>Editorial Notebook</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
