<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Geometric Forms, Bending Nature at Will</title>
    <meta content="15WEART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1604051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, D Dominick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottsleben, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DA173FF936A2575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Geometric Forms, Bending Nature at Will</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. DOMINICK LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, D Dominick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D Dominick Lombardi reviews three art shows in Westchester County: sculpture by Tom Gottsleben at Fields Sculpture Park at Art Omni International Arts Center in Ghent, photographs at Center for Photography at Woodstock, and another show at Elena Zang Gallery, Shady; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Gottsleben: Living Stone  The Fields Sculpture Park at Art Omi International Arts Center, 59 Letter S Road, Ghent. (212)206-6060. Through Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>Art Omi International Arts Center, known for its residency programs in visual art, writing and music, is also home to one of the more substantive sculpture parks. The work of the outdoor sculptor Tom Gottsleben is featured in a one-person exhibition in the Fields Sculpture Park on the Art Omi campus.</p>
        <p>His art can best be described as somewhere between the natural and the spiritual, a combination that easily overlaps. Mr. Gottsleben's primary medium is bluestone, an abundant material in his hometown of Saugerties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Gottsleben: Living Stone  The Fields Sculpture Park at Art Omi International Arts Center, 59 Letter S Road, Ghent. (212)206-6060. Through Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>Art Omi International Arts Center, known for its residency programs in visual art, writing and music, is also home to one of the more substantive sculpture parks. The work of the outdoor sculptor Tom Gottsleben is featured in a one-person exhibition in the Fields Sculpture Park on the Art Omi campus.</p>
        <p>His art can best be described as somewhere between the natural and the spiritual, a combination that easily overlaps. Mr. Gottsleben's primary medium is bluestone, an abundant material in his hometown of Saugerties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gottsleben's subject matter comes mostly from forms and patterns in nature, from the simplest symmetrical branch shape to the spiral, the most important symbol in his iconography.</p>
        <p>Although works like ''Life Seed'' (2002), ''Earth Seed'' (1993), even ''Gyropod'' (2003) have a distinct geometry, they look and feel quite natural. When combined with the materials used, the fluidity of the form, I suspect, sets up this soothing rhythmic call to nature.</p>
        <p>The less geometrically formed works like ''Scapes'' (2002), sinuous garlic scapes replicated in stone, and ''Branch'' (1995), a Y-shaped arc of stone, speak more specifically to natural occurrences, while ''Cloud Mountain'' (2003) creates an incredible volume through three-dimensional line.</p>
        <p>While there, a visit to the rest of the grounds is worthwhile. The grounds feature more than 80 other works of art, some of which have been recently installed like Margaret Evangeline's ''Gunshot Landscape'' (2004): a suspended, bullet-riddled, rectangular sheet of highly reflective metal that, in these woods, made me think of some future, alternative world, where this pristine land would forever be changed by suburban sprawl and chaos.</p>
        <p>Frame: Analysis Of Movement  Center for Photography at Woodstock, 59 Tinker Street, Woodstock, (845)679-9957. Through Aug. 22.</p>
        <p>The exhibition ''Frame: Analysis of Movement'' makes a case for Eadweard Muybridge's continued influence on Contemporary Art. Muybridge (1830-1904) is most famous for his sequential photograph of the locomotive movements of a horse. The work was a result of a request made by Leland Stanford, president of Central Pacific Railroad, who asked Muybridge if he could prove photographically, that a running horse's hooves leave the ground at some point. Of course, Muybridge did.</p>
        <p>The work in this well-thought-out, wonderfully executed exhibition, curated by Ariel Shanberg, director of the Woodstock center, further emphasizes a general fascination with the complexities of human and animal movement begun by Muybridge.</p>
        <p>Jojo Whilden's curiously funny ''Jumping for Joy'' (2000) is a looping 2-minute-and-15-second DVD that shows a naked young woman jumping up and down on a bed until she is exhausted. The black-and-white footage is a little grainy, and at one point breaks into multiple panels in rows like a Muybridge print.</p>
        <p>Ray Rapp's alluring and fun miniature digital video displays animated, silhouetted forms flashing positive and negative. Jennifer and Kevin McCoy's unforgettable video projection, ''Horror Chase,'' (2002) shows a frightened man running for his life in an ever-changing, endless loop through what looks to be a television or movie set of a home.</p>
        <p>Giving motion a more timeless and ethereal effect, Justyna Badach takes still frames from western films like ''Unforgiven'' and ''Young Guns.'' Kenseth Armstead's digital video stills taken from footage he shot in Ghana become nonrepresentational and other-dimensional.</p>
        <p>Karina Aguilera Skvirsky took digital still photographs inside the Woolworth Building in New York, producing a dreamy, even ghostly view of the interior space. Jona Franks's ''Filmstrip Series'' (2003) shows what might be capturing Muybridge's attention, if he were alive today -- the movements of a skateboarder.</p>
        <p>If you go, also take a peek at Noelle Tan's show, ''Tracing the Invisible'' in the project room. Romantic and dreamy, her works call to mind the edges of consciousness.</p>
        <p>Inside/Out  Elena Zang Gallery, 3671 Route 212, Shady, (845)679-5432. Through Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>Elena Zang Gallery's current exhibition is as much fun to look at, as it is intellectually stimulating. The indoor component of the exhibition features Mary Frank's ''Chimera'' (1990) a powerful charcoal and pastel work on paper that represents, for the artist, the cycle of life. Peter Reginato's ''Tiffany Splat'' (2002) is a fun, biomorphic abstraction. Michael Mazur's ''Cascade Variant'' (2004), which features flowers that look as if they are battling the onslaught of acid rain, and Jonah Meyer's two assemblages ''Early American'' (2004) and ''Sunday'' (2004) are exceptionally appealing visually. I also found Doug Trump's 1950's-looking abstraction ''Expose'' (2002), Joy Brown's delightfully playful ''Two Together'' (2002) and Judy Pfaff's beautifully composed and executed ''Gooseberry Pie'' (2004) to be important works in the show.</p>
        <p>The outdoor component of the exhibition is dominated by two stellar works, ''Dragon Path'' (2004) and ''Strange Attractor'' (2004) by Tom Gottsleben. Working with colored crystal glass made in China, Mr. Gottsleben continues his ascent as one of today's most important, spiritually minded outdoor sculptors. I also enjoyed Paul Chaleff's ''Fountain'' (2004), a roughly 5-foot-5 pentagonal form made of wood-fired stoneware that forms its own pensive, yet private water environment.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
