<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lions in Front, and Ice Out Back?; Plan Would Put a Skating Rink in Library's Backyard</title>
    <meta content="10BRYA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/10/nyregion/10bryant.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rockefeller Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bryant Park (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bryant Park Restoration Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Public Library</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biederman, Daniel A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Library</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Biederman, Daniel A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDE1131F933A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lions in Front, and Ice Out Back?; Plan Would Put a Skating Rink in Library's Backyard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lions in Front, and Ice Out Back?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel A Biederman, executive director of Bryant Park Restoration Corp, proposes placing Olympic-size portable ice skating rink in Bryant Park that would be free to anyone with skates; says rink would not endanger extension of New York Public Library's stacks under park because it would not weigh as much as trucks assembled there for Fashion Week and lawn already has drainage to protect stacks in case of leak; rink would close for season at end of January 2006 to make way for Fashion Week; most other rink operators in city welcome proposal, but Rockefeller Center rink could be hurt by competition; city is looking for corporate sponsor for rink, which would cost estimated $400,000; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hey, meet you at the Bryant Park Skating Rink.</p>
        <p>Doesn't exist, you say? Well, brace yourself for triple-lutz double toe loops, double axels and the occasional salchow next November, if the executive director of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, Daniel A. Biederman, has his way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The executive director of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation plans to open a portable rink next November, free to everyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hey, meet you at the Bryant Park Skating Rink.</p>
        <p>Doesn't exist, you say? Well, brace yourself for triple-lutz double toe loops, double axels and the occasional salchow next November, if the executive director of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, Daniel A. Biederman, has his way.</p>
        <p>The overseer of the six-acre park, on city-owned land, Mr. Biederman plans to set up an Olympic-sized portable rink, Zambonis and all, on the park's lawn next November, free to everyone (or at least those who bring their own skates). The facility would be closed for the season at the end of January 2006 to make way for Fashion Week, the park's mid-February shmatte extravaganza.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biederman is rhapsodic when he envisions the vista enveloping skaters ''in the enclosure of surrounding skyscrapers and the library to the east.''</p>
        <p>Excavation and construction for any permanent rink would be fraught, since underneath the park lawn is a climate-controlled cocoon for book storage that is an extension of the stacks of the New York Public Library.</p>
        <p>Enter the portable rink. According to Mr. Biederman, engineering surveys have determined that the weight of the trucks and tents on the grass during Fashion Week far exceeds that of a rink full of skaters. And since the lawn already has rain-and-snow-runoff drainage, Mr. Biederman said, a leak from a future ice rink would do no harm to the library stacks.</p>
        <p>''We are looking forward to seeing the plan,'' said Caroline Oyama, a spokeswoman for the library.</p>
        <p>The planned skating rink is but the flashiest pirouette of a grand new initiative to increase the use of Bryant Park in the cold. ''We'd like to winterize the park, make it a park for all seasons,'' Mr. Biederman said.</p>
        <p>He added that a new Bryant Park rink would not cannibalize attendance at other skating facilities ''because they are really in different neighborhoods.'' The option of skating in Bryant Park ''would create a whole new group of patrons,'' he predicted, referring to the 40,000 office workers adjacent to the park and the 100,000 within two blocks.</p>
        <p>Bryant Park's landlord, the city's parks commissioner, Adrian Benepe, said, ''We are intrigued by the idea.'' Would a new rink lower attendance at his department's Wollman Skating Rink or Lasker Skating Rink? ''I don't think competition is a worry because Central Park is a destination location, attracting many loyal, well-established skating groups,'' the commissioner said. ''A new rink could, in fact, be helpful in relieving overcrowding.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Competition might be more likely with Rockefeller Center.'' A Midtown cynosure since it first opened on Christmas day in 1936, the Rink at Rockefeller Center is seven blocks north, and charges adults $14 on weekdays and $17 on weekends, exclusive of skate rentals.</p>
        <p>Admission at Wollman rink, on the east side of Central Park between 63rd and 64th Streets, is $8.50 for adults on weekdays and $11 on weekends. Lasker rink, in the park at 107th Street, charges $4.50 for adults. Sky Rink at Chelsea Piers, at 23rd Street and the Hudson River, charges $13.50 for adults. The Riverbank Skating Rink at 145th Street on the river charges $4.50 for adults.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Bryant Park users were enthusiastic about the prospect of ice skating.</p>
        <p>''Here, with all the trees, you'd feel you were skating on a pond,'' said Andrew Personette, 27, who designs clothes and furniture.</p>
        <p>''Rockefeller Center is too busy -- it's crazy there, so I'd rather use the rink here,'' said his girlfriend, Amelia Dombrowski, a 28-year-old costume designer who works less than a block from the park. (Rockefeller Center, through Steven Rubenstein, its spokesman, declined to comment on the potential competition.)</p>
        <p>Irene Williamson, a tourist from Norfolk, England, said, ''I like ice-skating, but only as long as they have enough places to sit and watch.''</p>
        <p>Last week, as part of the park's ''winterization'' strategy, Bryant Park furnished a jaunty, heated, green-and-white-striped tent for chess and checkers players and another for the outdoor Reading Room, the complement to the public library on the 42nd Street side of the park. Since the opening of the heated reading-room tent, it has attracted an average of 40 to 50 people per day, and 80 on sunny, mild days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biederman said that free admission was contingent on finding a corporate sponsor for the skating rink. In addition to a skate-rental operation, he hopes to furnish a proximate refreshment stand offering hot chocolate, the frost-fighting elixir.</p>
        <p>In addition, Bryant Park hopes to put up a tent for those watching the merry-go-round. A hit since it opened in 2002, the carousel has been operated sporadically in winter, but will now be open weekends ''and, we hope, other warm winter days,'' Mr. Biederman said. To attract weekday patrons, Bryant Park offers a sign-up sheet for carousel riders so that park administrators can send out e-mail reminders to hundreds of potential customers on sunny days.</p>
        <p>Another tent has increased winter patronage: Bryant Park Grill's enclosed, heated terrace, offering park views through vinyl, added 180 seats to the 200 in the restaurant.</p>
        <p>Cold-weather traffic has also been generated by the growing number of vendors at the park's Christmas market -- officially designated Fêtes de Noël: The Holiday Shops at Bryant Park -- which is ''a greenmarket concept expanded to crafts,'' as Mr. Benepe put it, based on the popularity of Christmas marketplaces in Europe. It has grown to 120 stores this year from 80 in 2002, and its inventory has expanded beyond crafts to offer commercial merchandise from vendors like The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biederman said he was in discussion with the operator of the Christmas market, ID&amp;A, to sponsor the rink. The installation of an Olympic-sized ice surface for a three-month season could cost nearly $400,000 according to a Texas-based installer and operator of seasonal facilities, IceRinkEvents.com.</p>
        <p>The Bryant Park corporation's $4.5 million budget derives from nonpublic sources, including $1 million from concessions, $2 million from events, $750,000 from real-estate and other sponsors of the business-improvement district, and $750,000 from other sponsors and donors.</p>
        <p>All these winter audience-builders seem to be necessary. ''Attendance definitely declines in the cold weather,'' said Daniel Z. Gordon, 41, a groundskeeper who has had the task of ''enumerating humans,'' as he put it, for nearly three years. Every weekday at 1:15 p.m., he works his way north from West 40th Street, tallying park visitors in imaginary squares that stretch from tree to tree; then he uses his practiced eye to estimate traffic on the walkways. He said peak attendance on nonevent days is about 6,200 in summer; the lowest turnout has been less than 100 on stormy winter days.</p>
        <p>Many hardy cold-weather park visitors are attracted to Bryant Park by free WiFi Internet access, available since 2002, when it attracted 5,188 separate log-ons. So far this year, there have been 39,000 log-ons</p>
        <p>Bryant Park's efforts coincide with a new winter-avidity phenomenon in the city. ''Anecdotally, I think there are many more people out in the parks in winter than before,'' Mr. Benepe said. He thinks the workout culture has contributed to a cold-weather renaissance. ''And I think another explanation,'' Mr. Benepe added, ''is that people feel safe.''</p>
        <p>And despite all the attention given to global warming, Mr. Benepe promised ''our biggest winter festival ever, two days instead of one,'' he said, referring to the celebration on Jan. 8 and 9 in the East Meadow, where the entrance is at 99th Street and Fifth Avenue. Ski-resort operators will provide artificial snow, and visitors will be encouraged to try free snowshoeing, snow-tubing and even snow-sculpting.</p>
        <p>What else is next? The indefatigable Mr. Biederman has summoned up 100 new green chairs from France fitted with writing surfaces and cupholders; 1,000 more are on order.</p>
        <p>Why not just relax and run the park as is? ''You must have new ideas to keep people coming,'' Mr. Biederman said. ''We reclaimed this park, and we must continue to make it an exciting place.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
