<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Gas Empire vs. Governor on a Mesa Out West</title>
    <meta content="16YATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/16/business/16yates.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1574587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Otero Mesa (NM)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yates Petroleum Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican National Committee</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFDF123BF935A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Gas Empire vs. Governor on a Mesa Out West</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Family Gas Empire vs. Governor on a Mesa Out West</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <dateline>ARTESIA, N.M., April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yates Petroleum's plan to drill for natural gas in desert grasslands of Otero Mesa in New Mexico, pristine area of grasslands and cattle ranches, is being challenged by Gov Bill Richardson; Richardson, energy secretary in Clinton administration and potential candidate for vice president on Democratic ticket, says opposition to Yates's drilling projects forms cornerstone of energy proposals he is promoting as alternative to what he describes as Bush administration's 'drill at all costs' policy; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever since the wildcatting days of the 1920's, the Yates family has left its mark on the oil patch of southeastern New Mexico. The headquarters of Yates Petroleum, a futuristic building with a glittering skyway that juts out in the otherwise hardscrabble town of Artesia, stands as a gleaming symbol of its might.</p>
        <p>Yet while the family is one of New Mexico's wealthiest, and the state's largest contributor to state and federal political campaigns, that has not stopped Gov. Bill Richardson from clashing with it over plans to drill for natural gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of New Mexico's wealthiest families is clashing with the state over plans to drill for natural gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever since the wildcatting days of the 1920's, the Yates family has left its mark on the oil patch of southeastern New Mexico. The headquarters of Yates Petroleum, a futuristic building with a glittering skyway that juts out in the otherwise hardscrabble town of Artesia, stands as a gleaming symbol of its might.</p>
        <p>Yet while the family is one of New Mexico's wealthiest, and the state's largest contributor to state and federal political campaigns, that has not stopped Gov. Bill Richardson from clashing with it over plans to drill for natural gas.</p>
        <p>Their fight involves a pristine area of desert grasslands and cattle ranches known as Otero Mesa, which stretches northeast from the Hueco Mountains in Texas to the Guadalupe Mountains in southern New Mexico.</p>
        <p>The quarrel that has unfolded in recent weeks is drawing attention throughout the West at a time of rising tension that pits energy companies seeking to cash in on elevated natural gas prices against environmentalists, ranchers and hunters who oppose their drilling plans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson, an energy secretary in the Clinton administration and now often mentioned as a potential nominee for vice president on the Democratic ticket, readily acknowledged in an interview at his Santa Fe office that opposition to the Yates's drilling projects formed a cornerstone of the energy proposals he was promoting as an alternative to what he described as the Bush administration's ''drill at all costs'' policy.</p>
        <p>''I'm a strong supporter of oil and gas drilling, but I elected to go full force against this project,'' Mr. Richardson said, citing concerns he had about the potential environmental impact. ''It just did not smell right.''</p>
        <p>[Hoping to draw the interest of other governors to his ideas, Mr. Richardson, in his role as chairman of the Western Governors' Association, is playing host to a three-day energy conference in Albuquerque. Delegates to the meeting, which concludes Friday, include envoys from nearby states in Mexico and also from Canada.</p>
        <p>[Among his proposals is a recommendation, which he conceived together with Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger of California, that Western states develop at least 30,000 megawatts of clean or renewable energy by 2015 through wind, solar and biomass projects -- an undertaking they say would help increase energy efficiency 20 percent in the United States by 2020.</p>
        <p>[At the outset of the meeting, Mr. Richardson also proposed state tax incentives for companies that develop technology for renewable energy projects, a measure he said would help put New Mexico on the path toward becoming the ''Saudi Arabia of clean energy.'' Such moves have done little to calm nerves within the Yates family.]</p>
        <p>''The irony is that New Mexico has developed the highest country risk of any place I do business,'' said George Yates, president of the Harvey E. Yates Company, or Heyco, which is seeking to drill gas wells in Otero Mesa and has other exploration ventures in Morocco, Britain and the Basque region of Spain.</p>
        <p>To the annoyance of Mr. Yates, 57, described as the ''patrón'' of the family by Robert A. Jones, an Otero Mesa cattle rancher, the Yateses' differences with the governor have shed light on a network of energy enterprises that have operated in relative obscurity for decades in New Mexico and elsewhere in the West. Mr. Yates said that if he was the patrón of anything, it was of just one branch of the family's interests.</p>
        <p>Because no Yates companies are publicly traded, they can avoid the scrutiny of institutional investors, and most are based in southeastern New Mexico towns like Artesia and Roswell, far from the prying eyes of energy-industry centers like Houston and Denver. The family got its start in New Mexico in the 1920's, when the flatlands around Artesia were on the margins of the oil boom in the Permian Basin in nearby West Texas.</p>
        <p>In contrast to other family-owned energy conglomerates, the 20 or so Yates companies sometimes compete with one another for promising gas fields or deals, pitting brother against brother, cousin against cousin. The family's wealth, estimated at more than $300 million, explains in part its extensive involvement in state and national politics.</p>
        <p>Yates family members and companies have contributed more than $250,000 to national candidates and organizations since 2000, according to the Campaign to Protect America's Lands, a nonprofit, nonpartisan organization based in Washington. In this election cycle, employees at Yates Petroleum and Heyco, the family's two leading companies, are New Mexico's largest political donors, with $40,700 in contributions.</p>
        <p>Nearly all the Yates money goes to Republican candidates or organizations, including $134,466 to the Republican National Committee since 2000. Mr. Yates said in an interview at an office he maintains in Dallas that such contributions were in line with his own conservative politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yates is a former chairman of the Mountain States Legal Foundation, a group based in Denver that promotes conservative legal causes, and a former president of the New Mexican Landmen's Association, which supports oil and gas exploration in the state. He was also president of the Independent Petroleum Association of America in the late 1990's, when Mr. Richardson, a Democrat, was energy secretary.</p>
        <p>Both men said they got along fine until recently, often working together on energy issues. But that was before they diverged on Otero Mesa this year. Mr. Yates's company drilled a successful exploratory well in Otero Mesa in 1997, signaling its intent to look for additional gas, but it was not until January that the federal Bureau of Land Management reversed earlier rulings, effectively allowing Heyco to move forward.</p>
        <p>The Campaign to Protect America's Lands has sought to connect the family's close ties to J. Steven Griles, deputy interior secretary, with its efforts to drill in Otero Mesa. Mr. Griles worked as a lobbyist for Yates Petroleum in 2001, and his former company, National Environmental Strategies, had Yates Petroleum as a client from 2001 to 2003.</p>
        <p>Tina Kreisher, a spokeswoman for the Interior Department, said the decision to allow drilling in Otero Mesa was not related to Mr. Griles's past ties to the family. Mr. Griles declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Watson, assistant secretary for land and minerals management at the Interior Department, said in a separate interview that the department had reached a balance between environmental and energy-company concerns at a time of tight gas supplies in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yates said it was ''absurd'' to suggest that the Interior Department had acted in his favor since he was not altogether pleased with limits it had placed on drilling in Otero Mesa, and, in any case, he said he had no role in the ownership or management of Yates Petroleum, which is run by his cousin Peyton.</p>
        <p>He also said it was wrong to look at the family's political contributions as a concerted effort to direct policy. ''We in the family have respect for each other but we often compete,'' Mr. Yates said, describing the critiques of his contributions by environmental groups as ''guerrilla tactics.''</p>
        <p>It is ultimately up to the Bureau of Land Management -- part of the Interior Department -- to decide whether Mr. Yates can proceed with drilling, but Mr. Richardson is making it as difficult as possible. One of his first decisions was to prevent the state water department from granting Heyco the water it might need to drill in the area, increasing the potential cost.</p>
        <p>In an unusual move, Mr. Richardson has also allied himself with a group of conservative ranchers in Otero Mesa who also oppose Mr. Yates's project out of concern that drilling might damage public land used to raise cattle. The ranchers, many of whom belong to the Paragon Foundation, an ultraconservative organization in Alamogordo, N.M., that is critical of many environmental causes, have also been working with environmental groups to combat drilling in Otero Mesa.</p>
        <p>''We've been surprised that Richardson came down on our side on this since we never thought of him as a great friend,'' Don Lee, owner of the Hat Ranch in Otero Mesa, said in an interview. Mr. Jones, a neighbor and another Otero Mesa rancher, was more blunt: ''I think the oil companies are the coldest-blooded bunch there ever was. We don't want them to have carte blanche.''</p>
        <p>Despite the unusual coalition that has taken shape against the Yates interests, Mr. Richardson's opposition to drilling in Otero Mesa has not extended to other areas of New Mexico, like the San Juan Basin in the northwest, where nearly every large gas company has drilling operations. The state, after all, is the nation's second-largest natural gas producer, after Texas, and depends on royalties from energy exploration for more than a quarter of its budget.</p>
        <p>''Richardson went beyond traditional strategy to get the right divided on Otero Mesa and the ranchers and environmentalists together in one swoop,'' said Brian Sanderoff, president of Research and Polling Inc., a political analysis company in Albuquerque. ''It was an astute political decision, but one that was made knowing it would alienate some of the most powerful interests in the state.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
