<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feel Free</title>
    <meta content="12SCHMEMA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/12/books/review/12SCHMEMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ash, Timothy Garton</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Free World (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Ash, Timothy Garton</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Free World: America, Europe, and the Surprising Future of the West (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DC1F3EF931A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feel Free</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Free World': Things Do Not Fall Apart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Serge Schmemann</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serge Schmemann reviews book Free World: America, Europe, and the Surprising Future of the West by Timothy Garton Ash (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FREE WORLD</p>
        <p>America, Europe, and</p>
        <p>the Surprising Future of the West.</p>
        <p>By Timothy Garton Ash.</p>
        <p>286 pp. Random House. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Timothy Garton Ash has written a manifesto for uniting the West and spreading democracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FREE WORLD</p>
        <p>America, Europe, and</p>
        <p>the Surprising Future of the West.</p>
        <p>By Timothy Garton Ash.</p>
        <p>286 pp. Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>TIMOTHY GARTON ASH is that rare creature in the world of political commentary, a prominent scholar who does not believe everything is falling apart. Perhaps this comes from his formative years as a journalist covering the collapse of Communism in Eastern Europe. I was there too, and we all emerged transformed by the extraordinary beauty and power of popular longings for freedom. Garton Ash's books -- especially ''The Magic Lantern,'' his personal account of the revolutions of 1989 in Warsaw, Budapest, Berlin and Prague -- are among the best chronicles of that stirring era. Now he seeks to extend this spirit to the current state of the West. More than another analysis of the crisis in trans-Atlantic relations, ''Free World'' is a manifesto, a call on the reader (and the West) to join the author in nothing less than a movement for a truly free world. To underscore that this is not simply a polemical challenge, Garton Ash steers recruits to a special Web site, FreeWorldWeb.net.</p>
        <p>From a lesser source, this would sound a bit quixotic. But despite his Oxonian diffidence (''it may be helpful to say briefly what I, as an English European, would like America to do''), Garton Ash is eminently qualified in his self-appointed calling as a ''historian of the present.'' He is one of Britain's foremost political writers, the director of the European Studies Center at St. Antony's College, Oxford, and a senior fellow at the Hoover Institution at Stanford. Moreover, as ''Free World'' amply confirms, he is a wonderful writer, with a bottomless bag of anecdotes, quotes, historical precedents and pithy judgments (''America is, in aid policy, the world's leading miser, but Europe is, in trade, the world's leading hypocrite''). Unlike so much of the current rash of books seeking to make sense of the post-Communist world (''a jagged landscape -- with a question mark on every peak,'' in Garton Ash's image), ''Free World'' is totally engaging.</p>
        <p>The book's fundamental proposition is that Europe and America are not monolithic blocs drifting inexorably apart, not Venus and Mars, but rather two pillars of a common West. The argument is meticulously built on a close reading of American and European history since World War II -- so meticulously, in fact, that a discussion of what we mean by ''West'' is preceded by a Clintonesque question: ''When you say 'we,' who do you mean?'' In the process, Garton Ash demolishes many of the popular myths on which the polemics of trans-Atlantic crisis draw, like the popular view of Winston Churchill as a die-hard Atlanticist. Churchill, Garton Ash recalls, ''never forgot Europe, and especially France,'' and devoted much of his time in his last years to the cause of a united Europe.</p>
        <p>The problem facing the British is the starting point in ''Free World.'' Garton Ash calls his country ''Janus Britain,'' after the Roman god who had two opposing faces -- except that Garton Ash's Britain has two pairs of opposing faces, one set gazing separately at Europe and the United States, the other at its insular self and the world. The point is that all these faces are an inextricable part of Britain, and even if the British favor one over another, their separate links to America and Europe are ''so thick and vital'' that they can only remain forever Janus Britain. Variations on that question also govern the behavior of the United States and the rest of Europe, as Garton Ash illustrates with a neat anecdote about two Polish noblemen who stand in a pouring rain outside a restaurant while each insists that the other enter first. Finally one goes indoors, and the other says, ''Shameful -- he argues with me for half an hour and then he goes first anyway!''</p>
        <p>The guided tour through the intricate interplay of histories, identities, myths and interests that unite and divide the Europeans and Americans will be of great use to anyone seeking to make sense of what is going on today. And the further I read, the more keenly I looked forward to the destination Garton Ash promised from the outset -- the manifesto. Alas, it proved disappointing. His prescriptions sounded a bit like those of op-ed writers who solemnly but ineffectually proclaim that it's high time the world community did something about this or that. ''The first freedom toward which we should now work, if we want a free world, is Roosevelt's 'freedom from want,' '' Garton Ash declares. ''The first step is to practice what we preach: free trade.'' And so on for American foreign policy, greenhouse gases, consumerism, all building to a final clash of cymbals: ''It's up to us.''</p>
        <p>It is up to us, of course. But the People Power template of 1989 does not really fit today; even back then, to be honest, it was not people, and not even the free world, but the gross inefficiency of the system that really finished Communism. Garton Ash argues at one point that there's no point offering prescriptions that are ''trimmed already to all the existing constraints,'' and that there's no point writing another Sermon on the Mount.</p>
        <p>I would add that there's also little point in wishful thinking. The trans-Atlantic rift is not some regrettable spat among pol-iticians that will be resolved if only the People are heard. Islamic terrorism, to take the most vital challenge before the West, is a very real enemy, which raises very concrete questions about who can use lethal force, how much and when. That, in turn, is related to a plethora of other issues: America's support for Israel; Russian behavior in Chechnya; the European Union's reluctance to fund credible armies. None of these would be resolved, or even helped, by a simultaneous protest march across the free world ''against terrorism of all kinds,'' as Garton Ash proposes.</p>
        <p>On balance, it is heartening, no doubt, that a political writer who can give us such a tour d'horizon of the West remains so optimstic about the capacity of people to set things aright. One can only hope he's correct.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
