<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Troubled Film Buff Lives Again On Screen</title>
    <meta content="29CHAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/29/movies/29chan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041220T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1630773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Z Channel (Pay-Movie Cable Station)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harvey, Jerry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cassavetes, Xan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aurthur, Kate</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Z Channel: A Magnificent Obsession (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6D7133EF93AA15752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Troubled Film Buff Lives Again On Screen</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Troubled Film Buff Lives Again on Screen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE AURTHUR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Aurthur, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jerry Harvey, programmer for Los Angeles pay-movie cable station Z Channel, who murdered his wife and killed himself in 1988 and who is subject of Xan Cassavetes documentary movie Z Channel: A Magnificent Obsession; movie is being screened at Museum of Modern Art as part of its Premiere Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a 1985 radio interview, Jerry Harvey, the programmer for a pay-movie cable station in Los Angeles called the Z Channel, was asked if he had any kind of life or interests outside of film. ''What do you mean?'' Harvey replied with a self-conscious laugh. He had worked since 1980 at the Z Channel, which had acquired a fanatical following among the 100,000 subscribers who loved Harvey's eclectic scheduling -- ''Fanny and Alexander'' might precede ''Beverly Hills Cop.'' Three years after that interview, Harvey murdered his wife and then killed himself. They were both 39. Z went under a year later.</p>
        <p>The entwined stories of Harvey and his movie channel are the subject of ''Z Channel: A Magnificent Obsession,'' a new documentary by Xan Cassavetes to be screened for members of the Museum of Modern Art tonight at the museum as part of its 10-week ''Premieres Series.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An eclectic programmer for a once-popular Los Angeles' cable station is the subject of a new documentary to be screened at the Museum of Modern Art on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a 1985 radio interview, Jerry Harvey, the programmer for a pay-movie cable station in Los Angeles called the Z Channel, was asked if he had any kind of life or interests outside of film. ''What do you mean?'' Harvey replied with a self-conscious laugh. He had worked since 1980 at the Z Channel, which had acquired a fanatical following among the 100,000 subscribers who loved Harvey's eclectic scheduling -- ''Fanny and Alexander'' might precede ''Beverly Hills Cop.'' Three years after that interview, Harvey murdered his wife and then killed himself. They were both 39. Z went under a year later.</p>
        <p>The entwined stories of Harvey and his movie channel are the subject of ''Z Channel: A Magnificent Obsession,'' a new documentary by Xan Cassavetes to be screened for members of the Museum of Modern Art tonight at the museum as part of its 10-week ''Premieres Series.''</p>
        <p>Because of the Z Channel's Los Angeles audience, including prominent people in the movie industry, Harvey's programming choices have been credited with reviving the careers of actors and directors, saving directors' cuts of films and influencing young filmmakers. The film includes interviews with the directors Robert Altman, Quentin Tarantino and Alexander Payne as testimony to Z's role in 1980's Hollywood.The documentary also weaves in other interviews -- with exes, friends and colleagues -- that fill out Harvey's biography, delving into his obsession with film and his violent side. The Z Channel's history and its programmer's life are unexplored terrain. ''Nobody under 35 really knows about it,'' Ms. Cassavetes said in an interview from Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cassavetes, the 39-year-old daughter of the late director John Cassavetes and the actress Gena Rowlands, said she grew up loving the Z Channel. ''My dad was the biggest fan of it,'' she said. ''Especially when he was sick, he watched all these great films that he loved. It was invaluable, it was beautiful.''</p>
        <p>In the summer of 2003 Ms. Cassavetes was ready to direct her first feature when the financing fell through two weeks before the start of shooting. At a friend's suggestion, she began researching the story of Z as a possible documentary subject.</p>
        <p>It was not easy. ''It was sort of slipping into some kind of oblivion, which was outrageous to me,'' she said. ''Because of the murder-suicide, a lot of the people who would have kept its memory didn't want to think about it because it was a painful thing.''</p>
        <p>That was true for F.X. Feeney, a movie critic and screenwriter who was a close friend of Harvey's and who has co-produced ''Z Channel.'' When Ms. Cassavetes first approached him, he didn't respond, but later, Mr. Feeney said, he became convinced she was not interested in exploiting Harvey's death.</p>
        <p>''Because of the way he died, it created kind of an acid rain layer over everything,'' Mr. Feeney said in a telephone interview from Los Angeles. ''I knew Xan would be able to dispel that without minimizing the tragedy.''</p>
        <p>The Independent Film Channel, which financed ''Z Channel'' and is to broadcast it in May of next year, was also concerned about the movie's potential pitfalls. ''We didn't want to glorify Jerry Harvey,'' said Ed Carroll, the channel's vice president and general manager. But, ''Xan convinced us that her documentary would say this is who he is, this is what he did, without making a martyr out of him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Z Channel'' made its debut at Cannes last May -- a rarity for a made-for-television movie -- where it earned positive word-of-mouth and became a festival hit from Toronto to Edinburgh. It had a limited theatrical release in Los Angeles last month.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's Jerry Harvey programmed movies for the Beverly Canon, a repertory theater in Los Angeles, and made a name for himself when he booked the uncut version of ''The Wild Bunch'' and its director, Sam Peckinpah, delivered the print in person. Z had been started in 1974 by a cable franchise as one of the country's first pay-movie channels. In 1980 Harvey wrote to Z's new owner, Select TV, complaining that their programming was terrible. He was hired.</p>
        <p>Under Harvey the Z Channel became a 24-hour mix of films by auteur directors like François Truffaut and Akira Kurosawa, little-known European movies, popular fare like ''Silver Streak'' and ''The Empire Strikes Back'' and, late at night, soft-core offerings. Harvey soon found another niche for the channel to fill. After ''Heaven's Gate'' was re-edited and shortened in a failed attempt to reverse its course as the biggest flop in movie history, he decided to play Michael Cimino's four-hour original version. The reassembled movie received admiring reviews, and the Z Channel was regarded as a new kind of salvager.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea of a director's cut being something you could actually market came out of his rescue of 'Heaven's Gate,' '' Mr. Feeney said. ''It's an important measure, because home video, home viewing via pay TV, these things have really revolutionized how we perceive movies.''</p>
        <p>Harvey went on to do the same kinds of unusual broadcasts with Wolfgang Petersen 's six-hour ''Das Boot,'' originally a mini-series in Germany; Rainer Werner Fassbinder's 14-hour ''Berlin Alexanderplatz''; and the five-and-a-half-hour version of Bernardo Bertolucci's ''1900.'' (In ''Z Channel,'' Mr. Payne brags that he still has the ''1900'' he recorded on VHS at the time.) Harvey played the cut and uncut versions of Sergio Leone 's ''Once Upon a Time in America'' as a double feature to show the difference in quality.</p>
        <p>''Z Channel'' chronicles these efforts alongside Harvey's changing moods. Brought up in Bakersfield, Calif., he was the son of a judge and a nurse. According to the film, he told friends that his father had been a sadistic alcoholic. Harvey's two sisters also killed themselves. He once fired an employee, interviewed in the film, by telling her: ''I don't like the air that you breathe. I don't like the ground that you walk on.'' Most chillingly, he held a gun given to him by Peckinpah against the head of his first wife, Vera Anderson, who is interviewed in ''Z Channel.''</p>
        <p>Also plaguing Harvey were the battles he was fighting for Z's future. Its ownership changed six times. In September 1987, Rock Associates, a small Seattle company, bought Z and wanted to take it national to compete with HBO and Showtime. A month later, Rock Associates was wiped out in the stock market crash of Oct. 19. In an attempt to save Z Channel, Harvey agreed to merge the company with American Spectacor, a cable firm that had bought the rights to broadcast Dodgers and Angels baseball games. Under the agreement, Z would broadcast live sports and continue to show movies. But the combination did not work for the channel's fans or its programmer.</p>
        <p>''That's a very short amount of time to go from thinking your dream is coming true entirely to your dream is over,'' Ms. Cassavetes said.</p>
        <p>But in ''Z Channel,'' Ms. Cassavetes avoids blaming the murder-suicide on Harvey's work problems. ''I've been criticized for not explaining to the audience exactly why Jerry had his mental illness and connecting the dots of what led to the murder,'' she said. ''But I don't know. Nobody in this movie knows.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Feeney, who by the time Harvey died was working full time at Z Channel as a consultant, agreed. ''To know somebody so well, and not see that coming,'' he said. ''I have been conscious for years of having been close to Jerry in such a way that I felt like I understood how Nick Carraway felt about Jay Gatsby.''</p>
        <p>The movie ends on a hopeful note with a montage of clips from Harvey's favorite films, as Irving Berlin's poignant song ''What'll I Do?,'' from the 1974 movie version of ''The Great Gatsby'' plays. ''It was important for me not to have the focus of the story be about the tragedy of Jerry Harvey as much as the triumph of Z Channel,'' Ms. Cassavetes said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 20, 2004, Monday  An article in The Arts on Nov. 29 about Jerry Harvey, programmer for the Z Channel, a movie station on cable in Los Angeles, misstated the name of another cable channel, where he formerly worked. It is SelecTV, not Select TV. The article also referred erroneously to a letter he once wrote that resulted in a job. It was a complaint to SelecTV, where he was hired in 1979; the complaint was about SelecTV's programming, not the Z Channel's. His hiring by the Z Channel in 1980 was not related to the letter. The article also misidentified the owner of the Z Channel at the time. It was Theta Cable, not SelecTV.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 20, 2004, Monday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts on Nov. 29 about Jerry Harvey, programmer for the Z Channel, a movie station on cable in Los Angeles, misstated the name of another cable channel, where he formerly worked. It is SelecTV, not Select TV. The article also referred erroneously to a letter he once wrote that resulted in a job. It was a complaint to SelecTV, where he was hired in 1979; the complaint was about SelecTV's programming, not the Z Channel's. His hiring by the Z Channel in 1980 was not related to the letter. The article also misidentified the owner of the Z Channel at the time. It was Theta Cable, not SelecTV.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
