<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forget Star Chemistry. How About the Film's?</title>
    <meta content="30CRIT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/30/movies/30crit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1615259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chemical and Engineering News</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilman, Victoria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hileman, Bette</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Day After Tomorrow, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DE1538F933A0575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forget Star Chemistry. How About the Film's?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Forget Star Chemistry. How About the Film's?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on movie reviews now appearing on Chemical and Engineering News' Web site, which emphsize the accuracy of the science; Bette Hileman, senior editor, comments on her review of movie The Day After Tomorrow; weekly's assistant editor Victoria Gilman says goal is to closely examine a movie's science without shirking duty of traditional movie review; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When an online news publication is the kind that runs articles with headlines like ''Disilyne at Last: Synthesis of a Silicon-Silicon Triple Bond Is Called a Milestone for Multiple-Bond Chemistry,'' you generally do not expect to find great concern in its pages for the finer points of moviemaking.</p>
        <p>And in a conversation with an editor of such a publication, you do not expect to hear her say that she really enjoyed ''Terminator 2: Judgment Day,'' partly because of its examination of scientific ethics but also because ''I just love when the bad guy goes all squishy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The magazine Chemical and Engineering News has started publishing movie reviews that focus on the accuracy of the science in the latest Hollywood releases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When an online news publication is the kind that runs articles with headlines like ''Disilyne at Last: Synthesis of a Silicon-Silicon Triple Bond Is Called a Milestone for Multiple-Bond Chemistry,'' you generally do not expect to find great concern in its pages for the finer points of moviemaking.</p>
        <p>And in a conversation with an editor of such a publication, you do not expect to hear her say that she really enjoyed ''Terminator 2: Judgment Day,'' partly because of its examination of scientific ethics but also because ''I just love when the bad guy goes all squishy.''</p>
        <p>But then maybe you have not spent enough time recently with Chemical and Engineering News, the weekly magazine of the American Chemical Society, which in addition to informing its readers about the latest developments in protein engineering and atomic-scale manipulation has now ventured into territory where the Heisenberg uncertainty principle really prevails: Hollywood.</p>
        <p>This summer, the Web site version of the weekly (pubs.acs.org/cen) started publishing movie reviews that focus (although not exclusively) on the accuracy of the science, especially the chemistry, in the latest releases. In a movie-obsessed world, it joins a growing number of Web sites that parse movies in ever more precise ways, from their Christian content to their physics to whether they have continuity problems. Other emergent critics are simply strange: One online reviewer, the Filthy Critic, seems to concentrate on putting as many curse words as possible into his reviews; instead of stars, he awards fingers. (One finger -- guess which -- is the lowest rating.)</p>
        <p>Chemical and Engineering News did not begin its new critical mission meekly. It recently awarded four stars to the environmental disaster epic ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' which was savaged by most established critics. In Cleveland Clint O'Connor of The Plain Dealer, for one, called it ''the ultimate water slide for Weather Channel nerds.''</p>
        <p>But Bette Hileman, a senior editor at Chemical and Engineering News, begged to differ.</p>
        <p>''Rather than disliking the movie because much of it is physically and thermodynamically impossible -- even under the most extreme of plausible climate scenarios,'' she wrote, ''I found myself intrigued, recalling what has happened recently and imagining what could happen in the future.''</p>
        <p>She did concede that the movie was marred by ''less than sterling dialogue, and stereotypical human drama,'' but said that it compensated for these shortcomings. ''It reminded me of historical precedents for rapid climate change,'' Ms. Hileman wrote admiringly. She added that the intense, bearded scientist played by Ian Holm reminded her of the intense, bearded scientists she used to see at global-warming conferences.</p>
        <p>In an interview, she explained that the review was the first she had ever written. She also said that if she hadn't taken the assignment to review ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' she wasn't sure that she would have gone to the theater to see it.</p>
        <p>''I might have waited for it to come to video,'' acknowledged Ms. Hileman, a former high school science teacher.</p>
        <p>She added that she was an odd choice for a critic, because she is really not much of a movie lover. ''In fact, I used to see almost no movies, but my fiancé really likes to go, so we see one about once a week,'' she said. And something in Ms. Hileman's voice suggested that this pace was a bit much for her taste.</p>
        <p>Victoria Gilman, an assistant editor at the weekly, said she came up with the idea of adding movie reviews to the Web site after coming across another science-related review site called Insultingly Stupid Movie Physics (intuitor.com/moviephysics), which for the last seven years has gone to sometimes absurd lengths to point out how many movies disregard the laws of physics and to praise the few that adhere to them.</p>
        <p>For example, the site, maintained by Tom Rogers, a South Carolina high school teacher, once devoted 4,500 words to the director Jon Amiel's 2003 film ''The Core,'' about a journey to the center of the earth, calling it ''the worst physics movie ever'' -- even though a physicist from the California Institute of Technology served as a consultant to the filmmakers. (A sampling from the review: ''Although the oxygen in the movie was at elevated temperature, the pressure would have been so high it would have had liquidlike density and hence an incredibly high concentration, leading to an explosive reaction rate.'') She was also inspired by Mark Griep, an associate professor of chemistry at the University of Nebraska, Lincoln, who has lectured about the portrayal of chemists -- are there too many evil ones? -- in movie history.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilman said her goal was reviews that would closely examine a movie's science without shirking the duty of a traditional movie review.</p>
        <p>''We want to do not just the science, but how well does it entertain,'' she said. ''I mean, it's not really getting the message across about the science if people are falling asleep in the theater.''</p>
        <p>So the cloning science in the director Nick Hamm's recent ''Godsend'' might be passable, but how is the acting, the script, the story arc? Does it, as they say in Hollywood, have legs? Aalok Mehta, who reviewed the movie for Chemical and Engineering News, obviously did not think so, awarding it only one star.</p>
        <p>''Genetic engineering has already created a monstrosity,'' he wrote. ''And it's playing in a theater near you.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Mehta said his turn as a critic ''was a lot more fun than some of the other stuff we get to write about.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Ms. Gilman said that when she began telling writers at the magazine that she was thinking about running movie reviews, she ''got flooded with people who wanted to do it.'' The writers had widely divergent backgrounds and areas of expertise, but she said they were generally united on one opinion: their disdain for ''CSI,'' the hit CBS show about crime-scene investigators.</p>
        <p>''It's just too easy for the scientists on screen,'' Ms. Gilman said. ''It's completely unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>She also knew she was on the right track when one of the magazine's writers mentioned noticing that the scientist portrayed by Sean Connery in the 1992 movie ''Medicine Man'' was using the wrong kind of chromatography equipment while searching in the Amazon jungle for a cure for cancer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gilman, who counts ''Terminator 2'' and ''Brazil'' among her favorite movies, has tried on the reviewer's hat herself, giving three and a half stars to this year's movie ''The Blue Butterfly.'' (It's ''an unusual human drama,'' she wrote, that introduces ''viewers -- young and old -- to the vast array of wildlife that inhabits a South American rainforest.'' Next, she plans to turn her critical eye on ''Sky Captain and the World of Tomorrow,'' the Jude Law-Gwyneth Paltrow vehicle that could probably use a nice blurb from her now.</p>
        <p>The magazine's decision to expand into film criticism has already proved quite popular with readers, Ms. Gilman said, though chemists are about as easy to please as movie critics.</p>
        <p>''One wrote in to say that he wanted even more scientific detail in the reviews,'' she said. ''So we're working on that. People really are interested in these things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
