<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$50 Billion Question: World, Where to Begin?</title>
    <meta content="05LOMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/05/arts/05LOMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hunger</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lomborg, Bjorn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poole, Gary Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lomborg, Bjorn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5D81331F936A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$50 Billion Question: World, Where to Begin?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">$50 Billion Question: World, Where to Begin?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARY ANDREW POOLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Poole, Gary Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN, May 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Statistician and environmental iconoclast Bjorn Lomborg convenes conference of eight economists in Copenhagen to discuss best way to spend $50 billion to benefit humankind; team decides best ways would be to spend $27 billion to control spread of AIDS, followed by $12 billion for malnutrition and $13 billion to combat malaria; concludes spending money on global warming or government corruption would be bad investment; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What would you do with $50 billion? (Assuming that the goal was the benefit of humankind as opposed to owning a personal Lear jet or a tropical island.)</p>
        <p>To answer that question, Bjorn Lomborg, a statistician and environmental iconoclast, brought eight economists, including three Nobel Prize winners, to this harbor city last week to rank the world's 10 worst problems. Forget politics, they were told, just look at how to get the most bang for the buck. After studying all the contenders and running the numbers, the economic ''dream team'' decided that the best of the worst was controlling the spread of AIDS (worth $27 billion), followed by $12 billion for malnutrition and $13 billion to combat malaria. Spending money on other scourges, like global warming or government corruption, by contrast, would be a bad investment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a conference in Denmark, the controversial statistician Bjorn Lomborg asked eight economists: Which of the world's problems is the best investment?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What would you do with $50 billion? (Assuming that the goal was the benefit of humankind as opposed to owning a personal Lear jet or a tropical island.)</p>
        <p>To answer that question, Bjorn Lomborg, a statistician and environmental iconoclast, brought eight economists, including three Nobel Prize winners, to this harbor city last week to rank the world's 10 worst problems. Forget politics, they were told, just look at how to get the most bang for the buck. After studying all the contenders and running the numbers, the economic ''dream team'' decided that the best of the worst was controlling the spread of AIDS (worth $27 billion), followed by $12 billion for malnutrition and $13 billion to combat malaria. Spending money on other scourges, like global warming or government corruption, by contrast, would be a bad investment.</p>
        <p>The conference, or what some would label a stunt, is characteristic of Mr. Lomborg, who has infuriated environmentalists and captivated the media with his claims that environmental threats are overblown.</p>
        <p>During the nearly weeklong ''Copenhagen Consensus'' conference, Mr. Lomborg was on television news every night. Danish newspapers gave him almost as much coverage as the recent royal wedding. A ''counter conference'' was held in a room in the Parliament building, while the country's prime minister and foreign minister gave speeches supporting him.</p>
        <p>The fixation on the man, prompted Bruno S. Frey, a Swiss economist who attended the conference, to say he was insulted that the news media kept implying that Mr. Lomborg had manipulated the panel toward an anti-environmental agenda. ''Perhaps Bjorn is a central person in Denmark,'' Mr. Frey told a reporter, ''but internationally there are other important people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lomborg's critics, and perhaps even the man himself, do not necessarily adopt that view. ''When I am criticized, I don't back down,'' said Mr. Lomborg, 39, who likes to dash around Copenhagen on his bike wearing a bright yellow coat, smiling and waving to passers-by. ''Saying something clearly is considered provocative here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lomborg, who is the director of the government-supported Environmental Assessment Institute, was actually a Greenpeace activist at one time. He said he set out to refute the claims of skeptics, but ended up being convinced by their arguments. The outcome was a screed against the Chicken Little-view of environmental dangers, ''The Skeptical Environmentalist,'' which was published in 1998 and continues to provoke fierce controversy. (The English version was first published in 2001.)</p>
        <p>The Observer of London reported that a ''secret White House memo'' cited Mr. Lomborg's book to help Republicans deflect criticism about their environmental policies. But Mr. Lomberg said: ''If George Bush has read my book, he has read it badly. There are a lot of people who want to misrepresent me.''</p>
        <p>Last year a scientific ethics panel accused Mr. Lomborg of ''scientific dishonesty,'' though withdrew its charge after the Danish Ministry of Science rebuked the panel for failing to present sufficient evidence. More recently, his public profile outside of Denmark was raised after Time magazine listed him as one of the world's 100 most influential people in April.</p>
        <p>Vernon L. Smith, a Nobel Prize winner on the panel, is one of Mr. Lomborg's admirers. Like all the attendees, he was paid $30,000 to attend the conference, which was sponsored by the institute and The Economist magazine. Mr. Smith, whose long gray hair and silver rings give him a striking resemblance to Willie Nelson, said that ranking the world's problems according to cost-benefit analysis seemed like a good first step in making better decisions for the poor.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that such analyses have limitations. For instance, the group wanted to see immigration barriers reduced, he said, but they could not figure out how to spend money effectively. ''The barriers are within the countries, and it is mostly a political problem,'' Mr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>For example, he said, in the United States many people oppose immigration because they think it is a burden on the welfare system, even though the numbers ''do not bear it out.'' Likewise, he said, investing in climate change over putting money into fighting hunger and disease is misguided.: ''As energy becomes more scarce, it becomes expensive, and people look at alternatives.''</p>
        <p>Thomas C. Schelling, a professor at the University of Maryland who also attended, agreed. ''The worst result of climate change will be the spread of tropical diseases, and we felt money is better spent eliminating the diseases.''</p>
        <p>But critics remain suspicious, arguing that the entire gathering was a setup to further Mr. Lomborg's anti-environmentalist agenda. Christian Ege, chairman of the Danish Ecological Council and leader of the counter conference, said: ''Lomborg presents himself as an impartial scholar, drawing conclusions on a well-founded basis. But it is a basis rejected by most of those with knowledge of environmental studies.'' Other critics worry that the conference will turn aid into a simplistic either-or proposition: if it pays to improve the sewage system, children will go without education.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lomborg defended the underlying premise of the conference:''Abrupt change is needed to help the developing world. If you spend a lot of time and effort on one area, that means there is another area you did not spend money on.''</p>
        <p>Douglass C. North, a member of the panel and a Nobel Prize winner, said he had thought ''long and hard'' about coming because of the controversy surrounding Mr. Lomborg. But he attended, he said, because economists are so focused on minutiae that they do not always look at the bigger problems in the world. He said he hoped that a new body of research would result that could be used to help developing nations.</p>
        <p>Experts from around the world wrote papers on their particular specialty, presenting the information to the economists in closed-door meetings. ''It was not always easy to keep them on point because there were some big egos in the room,'' said Mr. Lomborg, who moderated the sessions. A final round-table discussion among the economists was shown on Danish television.</p>
        <p>Frank Rijsberman, director general of the International Water Management Institute in Colombo, Sri Lanka, presented a paper about water needs. ''Half of the population in the developing world does not have access to clean water or sanitation,'' he said. ''But it is not that we need more money, but we need to spend it better.''</p>
        <p>As for reducing emissions of carbon to halt climate change, the panel looked at three proposals, including the Kyoto Protocol. Global warming is a serious problem, the group concluded, but regarded every proposal as having costs that were likely to exceed the benefits.</p>
        <p>''Climate is important but not as urgent of a problem as malnutrition and disease,'' said Robert W. Fogel, another Nobel winner there. There were 798 million undernourished people in the developing world in 2001, according to the United Nations. ''If we twiddle our thumbs, not spending money wisely, millions of people will die.''</p>
        <p>A Global Wish List</p>
        <p>Economists at the Copenhagen Consensus discussed 38 solutions to the world's problems and ranked 17 of them. (They decided there was insufficient information to rank the others)</p>
        <p>Very Good Projects</p>
        <p>Diseases: Control of H.I.V./AIDS</p>
        <p>Malnutrition: Providing micronutrients</p>
        <p>Subsidies and trade: Trade liberalization</p>
        <p>Diseases: Control of malaria</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>Malnutrition: Development of new agricultural technologies</p>
        <p>Water and sanitation: Small-scale water technology for livelihoods</p>
        <p>Water and sanitation: Community-managed water supply and sanitation</p>
        <p>Water and sanitation: Research on water productivity in food production</p>
        <p>Governance and corruption: Lowering the cost of starting a new business</p>
        <p>Fair</p>
        <p>Migration: Lowering barriers to migration for skilled workers</p>
        <p>Malnutrition: Improving infant and child nutrition</p>
        <p>Malnutrition: Reducing the prevalence of low birth weight</p>
        <p>Diseases: Scaled-up basic health services</p>
        <p>Bad</p>
        <p>Migration: Guest-worker programs for the unskilled</p>
        <p>Climate: Optimal carbon tax</p>
        <p>Climate: The Kyoto Protocol</p>
        <p>Climate: Value-at-risk carbon tax</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
