<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Moving To New Ban For Mad Cow, Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="10COW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/10/politics/10cow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1595543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feed</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blakeslee, Sandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dietary Supplements and Herbal Remedies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mad Cow Disease (Bovine Spongiform Encephalopathy)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Agriculture Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDC103BF933A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Moving To New Ban For Mad Cow, Officials Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Moving to New Ban for Mad Cow, Officials Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blakeslee, Sandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Food and Drug Administration says that in effort to eradicate mad cow disease, it is moving toward policy, based on advice of international experts, to ban feeding of farm animal parts to other farm animals; also announces closing of loophole that could have let disease spread to people who use certain food supplements and cosmetics; tells makers of supplements and cosmetics that they have to set up record keeping to prove they are complying with rule that bans risky cattle tissue in supplements and cosmetics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal health officials said yesterday that in an effort to eradicate mad cow disease, they were moving toward a policy, based on the advice of international experts, to ban the feeding of any farm animal parts to other farm animals.</p>
        <p>Current practice allows cattle to be fed chickens, pigs and other species that had been fed rendered cattle whose tissue could theoretically be infected. Such practices are widely said to have caused the epidemic of mad cow disease in Britain 20 years ago and its spread to other countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal health officials said that in an effort to eradicate mad cow disease they were moving toward a policy to ban the feeding of any farm animal parts to other farm animals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal health officials said yesterday that in an effort to eradicate mad cow disease, they were moving toward a policy, based on the advice of international experts, to ban the feeding of any farm animal parts to other farm animals.</p>
        <p>Current practice allows cattle to be fed chickens, pigs and other species that had been fed rendered cattle whose tissue could theoretically be infected. Such practices are widely said to have caused the epidemic of mad cow disease in Britain 20 years ago and its spread to other countries.</p>
        <p>The officials also announced the closing of a loophole that could in theory have let the disease spread to people who use certain food supplements and cosmetics.</p>
        <p>Consumer groups expressed outrage that the Food and Drug Administration, which is responsible for regulating animal feed, did not close another loophole, feeding cattle large amounts of cattle blood, chicken waste and other materials that might spread the disease.</p>
        <p>''On the most important issue facing it, F.D.A. has essentially put off issuing needed regulations to protect the public until after the November election,'' said Prof. Thomas O. McGarity, president of the Center for Progressive Regulation and an expert on food safety laws at the University of Texas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephen F. Sundlof, director of the Center for Veterinary Medicine at the food and drug agency, said in a telephone interview that the proposal to stop feeding cattle products to other animals and back to cattle went much further than previously announced proposals and would automatically remove remaining loopholes in animal feed safety.</p>
        <p>At least 30 million American cattle are slaughtered each year. Under the new plan, all their intestines, which can now be fed to other animals, would have to be disposed of. The brains, tonsils and other risky tissues from older animals would also have to find resting places. Today, the wastes go into chicken and hog feed and pet food.</p>
        <p>In Britain, such wastes are burned with fossil fuels to make Portland cement, Dr. Sundlof said.</p>
        <p>''We decided to focus our efforts on the one measure that will have the greatest effect,'' he said. ''We want to have a rule in place that the next time, if we find another animal, we can say, ''Look, we've done everything we can that is reasonable.'''</p>
        <p>The rules, if adopted, would require the cattle industry, food manufacturers, renderers and many other industries to revamp their practices completely, Dr. Sundlof said.</p>
        <p>The agency invited public comment on its proposal. Dr. Sundlof said it would take some time to gather information.</p>
        <p>''My guess,'' he added, ''is there would not be anything final before the end of this year.''</p>
        <p>The proposal stems from the finding in December of the first case of mad cow disease in the nation, in Mabton, Wash. The disease, technically bovine spongiform encephalopathy, can be transmitted to cattle and humans when infectious particles called prions find their way into food and other ingested products.</p>
        <p>In January, the Agriculture Department announced aggressive steps to prevent the disease from spreading. Among other steps, the department placed an immediate ban on sickly cattle, called downers, from entering the human food supply as hamburger or other cheap cuts.</p>
        <p>Later in January, the food and drug agency proposed two additional rules and invited public comment. The first rule bans the use of risky cattle tissue in dietary supplements and cosmetics. A number of supplements contain brain and adrenal glands. Some skin conditioners, emollients and hair products contain potentially dangerous cattle tissue that could enter the human body through cuts or the eye.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the agency said that the final rule would start on Wednesday. It also told makers of supplements and cosmetics that they had to set up record keeping to prove they were complying with the rule.</p>
        <p>The second proposal in January removed exemptions from cattle feeding practices. Since 1997, cattle have not been allowed to eat tissue from other ruminants, but they do consume vast quantities of cattle blood and feathers and excrement from industrial poultry operations. Consumer groups argue that because chickens are fed rendered beef pellets that might have prions, cattle could be cross-contaminated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sundlof said that such concerns were valid but that ''more radical, innovative solutions'' were needed. Although no Americans have been reported infected from eating domestic beef, the industry has suffered enormous losses in trade and consumer confidence.</p>
        <p>Changing practices is a huge undertaking, Dr. Sundlof said. The feathers and droppings of 8.5 billion chickens would have to be disposed in another way like being used as fertilizer, he said. But cows might pick up prions from grass.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
