<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23ART.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/23/arts/design/23ART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1576187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E6DD143AF930A15757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="8450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Berlin's Nationalgalerie has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. One of the show's great ''Metropolis'' paintings is Kirchner's large ''Potsdamer Platz'' (1914); in the ''Arcadia'' mode is Modersohn-Becker's ''Kneeling Mother With Child'' (1907). Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Berlin's Nationalgalerie has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. One of the show's great ''Metropolis'' paintings is Kirchner's large ''Potsdamer Platz'' (1914); in the ''Arcadia'' mode is Modersohn-Becker's ''Kneeling Mother With Child'' (1907). Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''BYZANTIUM: FAITH AND POWER (1261-1557),'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through July 4. This vast and humblingly beautiful show about the waning centuries of the Byzantine empire reminds us that political decay does does not necessarily mean artistic decline. Full of amazing exotica -- manuscripts, miniature mosaics, textiles, drawings, paintings -- the exhibition ends with a room of great Northern Renaissance art indebted to icons that proves Byzantium's continued reach. People who are not Eastern Orthodox believers can enjoy the earthly pleasures of aesthetic spectacle linked with historical enlightenment. Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $7 (Michael  Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>''CHRISTO AND JEANNE-CLAUDE: THE GATES, CENTRAL PARK, NEW YORK,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through July 25. At last ''The Gates,'' the long-plotted Christo-fest in Central Park, is about to be realized: in February 7,500 saffron-colored fabric panels, each suspended from a free-standing 16-foot-high framework, will be installed for 16 days on 23 miles of park walkways. The project, 25 years in the making, is saluted in this preview installation of Christo's drawings, collages, photographs, maps, diagrams and samplings of the actual ingredients, like poles, panels, bolts, supports and self-locking nuts. Like everything else the collaborative team of Christo and his wife, Jeanne-Claude, does, this documentation is as yawningly thoroughgoing as a space exploration log, sparing the viewer no detail. But for anyone who wants a pre-game fill-in, this show is indispensable. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''ECHOING IMAGES: COUPLES IN AFRICAN SCULPTURE,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through Sept. 5. In this wonderful little valentine of an exhibition, a couple means many things: man and woman, woman and woman, man and man, parent and child, human and divine, human and animal. And you would have to have a heart of stone not to fall in love with all of them: a Dogon carving of a ''primordial couple'' who sit alert and a little shy as the man's arm loops up around the woman's shoulders; a pair of men from Mali kneeling side by side, their arms intertwined; a set of gorgeous brass Yoruba sculptures made for a society of male and female elders among whom gender distinctions are ignored. Every piece is a superb example of a humane and stimulating art in which restraint and equanimity are governing ideals. Hours and admission: See above (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''GUSTAV KLUTSIS AND VALENTINA KULAGINA: PHOTOGRAPHY AND MONTAGE AFTER CONSTRUCTIVISM'' AND ''WAR IN IRAQ: THE COORDINATES OF CONFLICT, PHOTOGRAPHS BY VII,'' International Center of Photography, 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, through May 30. Provocatively buttressed by two smaller shows, these imposing exhibitions dovetail into a chillingly informative examination of the roles of photography in art, history and science. The political, the personal and the formal alternate energetically in the first exhibition in this country devoted to Klutsis and Kulagina, who were married, and is primarily the tale of an artist whose striking photomontage posters helped establish the graphic look of the young Soviet Union, until Stalin had him assassinated. ''War in Iraq'' makes manifest the kinds of events that swirled around but rarely registered within the work of Klutsis or Kulagina. Starting with the ruins at ground zero, 53 images by nine intrepid photojournalists associated with the agency VII record the havoc that war, violence, dictatorial regimes and fanatical faith have wrought in our own time. Whether riveting, shocking, seductive or merely banal, few can resolve the question raised by even the most seemingly straightforward photograph: does it bring us closer to reality or does it distance us from a reality that is already constructed largely of photographs? Hours and admission: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; students and 62+, $7 (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''MOMA AT EL MUSEO: LATIN AMERICAN AND CARIBBEAN ART FROM THE COLLECTION OF THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART,'' El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, through July 25. The first broad-scale exposure of the Modern's extensive holdings from Mexico, the Caribbean and Central and South America, the 150 or so objects here are a small selection from the more than 2,000 it owns. But they form an arresting show, from the powerful Surrealist-  influenced ''Jungle'' (1943) by the Cuban artist Wifredo Lam to an untitled 1995 sculpture by the Colombian Doris Salcedo that invokes the political violence in her country. The sardonic humor of Marisol (Venezuela) and Fernando Botero (Colombia); the geometric tweakings of Jesús Rafael Soto and Gertrude Goldschmidt (Venezuela); the Conceptual hatchings of Felix González-Torres (Cuba) and Cildo Meireles (Brazil), among others, remind us of the artistic richness south of the border. This show joins the strength of the Modern's resources with the growing importance of El Museo as a showcase of Latino culture. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., Thursdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $7; students and 65+, $5 (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''OPEN HOUSE: WORKING IN BROOKLYN,'' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, through Aug. 15. This all-Brooklyn show of new art has been timed to coincide with the inauguration of the museum's new front entrance pavilion and public plaza. With 300 pieces installed in the fourth- and fifth-floor galleries, and spilling over into the permanent collection galleries, it's a very crowded affair. It's also all over the place in terms of media, styles and themes, not to mention quality; the good, the bad and the iffy mingle. Still, there's plenty of good work by artists you know and by some you don't, drawn from across a borough that has many different art worlds. Also on view, though not part of the show, is Alexis Rockman's mural-size painting of Brooklyn 3,000 years in the future, submerged under water as a result of global warming. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 11 p.m. the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $6; $3 for students and 62+ (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''PARADISE NOW? CONTEMPORARY ART FROM THE PACIFIC,'' Asia Society, 725 Park Avenue, at 70th Street, (212) 288-6400, through May 9. Surveying 15 artists from the Pacific -- including Hawaii, Fiji and Samoa but mostly from New Zealand -- this exhibition reflects the new consciousness of Pacific or Polynesian cultures in the art and life of the region. Sometimes local motifs and themes are merely affixed to well-worn contemporary art strategies. But there is plenty to look at and think about, especially in an impressive video installation by Lisa Reihana, who uses the power dynamics of a 19th-century photographer's studio as the jumping-off point for a piercing meditation on colonialism and its aftermath. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., Fridays until 9 p.m. Admission: $7; students and 65+, $5 (Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''ROTH TIME: A DIETER ROTH RETROSPECTIVE,'' Museum of Modern Art, Queens, 45-20 33rd Street, at Queens Boulevard, Long Island City, (212) 708-9400, and P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084, through June 7. This exhaustive, exhausting but ultimately astounding exhibition offers total immersion in the art of the German-born, Swiss-based multimedia dynamo Dieter Roth (1930-1998), who not only erased the line between art and life, but also fused them into a single insoluble entity. With nearly 400 works of painting, drawing, prints, sculpture, assemblage, collage, music, poetry, film, photography, video and sound, and using every imaginable kind of found object or material -- foodstuffs included -- the exhibition moves through 50 years of incessant, obsessive art-making with remarkable clarity. It culminates in a presentation of five enormous installation pieces at the Modern's little-sister institution, P.S. 1, that reveal a seemingly boundless universe of artistic activity and a radically new picture of an artist at work. MoMA Queens hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays to 7:45 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $8.50. P.S. 1 hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $2 (Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''SINGULAR FORMS (SOMETIMES REPEATED): ART FROM 1951 TO THE PRESENT,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, through May 19. A lavish, mostly in-house display of Minimal art and its progeny. Along with the requisite examples by standard-bearers (Donald Judd, Dan Flavin, Robert Ryman) and a few by predecessors (Robert Rauschenberg, Ad Reinhardt), it features post-1960's works by a range of artists including Gerhard Richter, Charles Ray, Robert Gober, Liam Gillick, Sherrie Levine, Rachel Whiteread and Damien Hirst. Ultimately, Minimalism doesn't describe everything here. The show is a hodgepodge. But it's a stimulating hodgepodge, and it looks great in Wright's building. Hours: Saturdays through Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m., Fridays until 8 p.m. Admission: $15; students and 65+, $10 (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''TOOLS OF HER MINISTRY: THE ART OF SISTER GERTRUDE MORGAN,'' American Folk Art Museum, 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, through Sept. 26. If you wonder what it really means to say that art is a calling, see this ethereal show. A self-appointed prophet and street preacher, Sister Morgan was called by God to paint in the 1950's. Untutored but full of an uncanny grace, her vivid, high-key works have a plain-spoken ecstasy and inborn eloquence, both formal and literary, that can lift the soul. The mix of text and image relates to many modern artists and poets, none of whom she ever heard of or cared about. Her pictures are talismans of mystical devotion derived from inner necessity, conceived as teaching tools for lost souls. In heaven works like these would be eternally before our eyes. The world not being heaven, this is your opportunity to see them. The day has come, as Sister Morgan might say. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m., Fridays until 7:30 p.m. Admission: $9; $7, students and 62+ (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* WHITNEY BIENNIAL, Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, through May 30. Easily the best biennial in a long time. The spirit is upbeat and ingratiating -- almost polite -- on the surface at least, with a utopian streak and a youth-heavy emphasis on gloss and craft. There's plenty of painting and drawing, ratifying the much-hyped trend, and multigenerational work, stressing ecstatic engagement and meticulousness. But the real story is the stress on the handmade in general, on materiality in whatever medium -- a change from the politics-heavy, slacker installations of recent years. The cross-generational dialogue is an interesting subtext. Among the younger set utopia does not mean 1960's-style radicalism; it implies something unattainable, except perhaps in a hand-me-down form, and therefore smaller and inherently poignant. Look for a few standout works from artists both younger and older, including Yayoi Kusama, Alec Soth, Catherine Opie, Julie Mehretu, Jim Hodges, Eve Sussman, Raymond Pettibon, Slater Bradley, Robert Mangold and Stan Brakhage, who died last year. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 62+, $9.50 (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>RALSTON CRAWFORD, Salander-O'Reilly, 20 East 79th Street, (212) 879-6606, through May 1. Crawford, an American Modernist, painted in a stylistic range bounded by George Ault's reductivist Precisionism and Stuart Davis's jaunty, planar Cubism. This selection of paintings and photographs dating from the late 1930's to the late 70's reveals how he drew on the abstraction in his photographs of urban and industrial subjects for the composition of his hard-edged, nonrepresentational paintings (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>''THE DEVONSHIRE INHERITANCE: FIVE CENTURIES OF COLLECTING AT CHATSWORTH,'' Bard Graduate Center, 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000, through June 20. The stately English country home Chatsworth has been occupied since its construction in 1552 by the Cavendish family, headed by a long succession of dukes and duchesses of Devonshire. They have enriched it with notable collections of fine and decorative arts, an awesome library of books and manuscripts, scientific instruments, silver, furniture and needlework. A glimpse of these treasures is provided by this show, which has works by Rembrandt, Raphael, Titian, Dürer and Lucian Freud; books and drawings by Andrea Palladio; a spectacular jewelry ensemble worn at the coronation of Czar Alexander II and much else to light up the eyes of the most jaded connoisseur. The next step is a visit to Chatsworth itself, still a private home for the Cavendishes but very much open to the public (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>''ANIMALS AND US,'' Galerie St.-Étienne, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 245-6734, through May 22. This menagerie of an exhibition offers many different species of animals viewed through many stylistic lenses. It includes Sue Coe's expressionistic anticruelty cartoons; William Wegman's comic photographic dog portraits; Frank Noelker's photographs of live animals in zoos; Hiroshi Sugimoto's eerie photographs of simulated animals in museum dioramas; and Rona Pondick's surrealist stainless steel dog, which has a human head and hands cast from life with a smooth and shiny canine body (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JIM DINE, PaceWildenstein (through May 1) and Pace/MacGill (through May 8), 32 East 57th Street, (212) 421-3292. New works by Mr. Dine include a series of medium-large paintings, each of which has a valentine heart image imbedded in an all-over field of Abstract Expressionist brushwork; a freestanding folding screen with tools, Venus de Milo reproductions and molten metal puddles attached to a steel framework, randomly spray-painted in saturated colors; and a series of big, grainy photographic views of the artist's messy studio, which make it seem like a place of scary mystery (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* LES KRIMS, ''Fact or Fiction,'' Laurence Miller, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 397-3930, through May 15. In the 1970's, feminists hated Mr. Krims's staged pictures of naked women in absurd and humiliating situations. Today, these small prints from the late 1960's and early 70's are striking for their psychological urgency and mold-breaking inventiveness. His famous picture of a screaming legless man on a small table in a windowed alcove remains an image of frightening intensity. His mother seated naked in her dimly lighted living room is an image of heartbreaking vulnerability (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>CHRISTA DONNER, Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238, through May 8. This young Chicago artist makes surreal narrative paintings on paper, cutting out and pasting together generic comic-book style images of women in colors alternately muted and acidic. Why they are connected to one another by arteries or intestinal tubing, and why the prevailing mood is one of agitated, gothic melodrama with hints of a baleful supernaturalism, remain unexplained. But something promising is brewing in Ms. Donner's world (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''PAPER CHASE,'' Axel Raben, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 647-9064, through May 8. This entertaining show of things made of paper, organized by Renée Riccardo, includes Jon Rosenbaum's miniature, intricately detailed fantasy constructions; Charlene Liu's delicately visionary landscapes of cut paper and watercolor; Molly Smith's wryly simplified sculptures of a waterfall and a big blue drip leaking from a hole in the wall; Doug Morris's intensely patterned symmetrical reliefs; and Koji Shimizu's toylike, papier-mâché sculptures of industrial vehicles (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ANDRÉ PRETORIUS, ''A Year in the Life,'' ZieherSmith, 531 West 25th Street, (212) 229-1088, through May 8. Mr. Pretorius's comical, vividly illustrative paintings depict allegorically suggestive scenes. ''Active, Passive, Neuter'' shows three pajama-clad children in a bright modern living room -- a boy with his pants down, another with a raised switch and an amused girl watching. In ''Fear of a Second Child,'' a perplexed woman contemplates a farmer in the company of a child-size extraterrestrial and a metrosexual with a diapered chimpanzee (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* WILLIAM SCOTT, Denise Bibro, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 647-7030, through June 5. Pots, dishes, fruits, vases and other domestic shapes form the basis for much of this Scottish-born painter's imagery, magically reduced to lyrical, luminous ghosts of themselves. Scott, a figure of some importance in post-World War II British art, was well-known in New York, too. This small but engrossing show progresses from 1954 to 1977, and in his spare, sensual paintings shape, space and color play beautifully together (Glueck).</p>
        <p>CY TWOMBLY AND JEAN-MICHEL BASQUIAT, Briggs Robinson, 527 West 29th Street, (212) 560-9075, through May 1. Showing these works on paper together is a natural idea given Mr. Twombly's influence on Basquiat, and the differences are as interesting as the similarities. With a mix of irony and nostalgia, Mr. Twombly's scribbly improvisations romance the cults of antique humanism and modern primitivism. Basquiat's blocky diagrammatic organizations of found words and phrases and pictographic images suggest the comic pseudo-rationalism of an inspired but mentally unbalanced street poet (Johnson).</p>
        <p>KARIN WAISMAN, ''The Garden of Eden,'' Haim Chanin, 210 11th Avenue, near 24th Street, (646) 230-7200, through May 1. The setpiece of this Argentine-born artist's show is a room-size pink cube made of Styrofoam panels. There's no entrance, but you can peer through various peepholes to catch a glimpse of walls fetishistically embellished with intricate carvings of geometric and vegetal forms. But the show's chef d'oeuvre may well be a flat work, ''Evanescence III,'' a beautiful, almost transparent wall drawing. Ms. Waisman's work is a little late for the Pattern and Decoration movement of the 1970's, but she is a worthy successor (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Downtown</p>
        <p>GIDEON BOK, Plane Space, 102 Charles Street, Greenwich Village, (917) 606-1268, through May 9. In heavily worked paintings of his studio and living space, Mr. Bok captures temporal as well as visual experience. When objects or people move, he adds their new positions to the developing picture; the parts that stay still are finished, the things that move have a ghostly transparency. Combining scratchy lines, resinous glazes and troweled-on impasto, he produces a flickering, cluttered vision of bohemian transience (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''FIVE BILLION YEARS,'' Swiss Institute, 495 Broadway, near Spring Street, SoHo, (212) 925-2035, through May 1. This cohesive and affecting show comes across as a rueful meditation on human isolation. It includes Tony Matelli's realistic life-size ''Sleepwalker;'' a mysterious blinking light sculpture by Philippe Decrauzat; Ceal Floyer's projector going continually in and out of focus; lonesome seascape photographs by Hiroshi Sugimoto; Jonathan Monk's wall text designating a meeting time and place in the future; and François Curlet's white cube with a built-in antenna that periodically rises as though desperately seeking signs of intelligent life (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* CHRISTIAN JANKOWSKI, ''Now Playing,'' Maccarone, 45 Canal Street, near Orchard Street, Lower East Side, (212) 431-4977, through May 2. Spread throughout a small building, in contrasting viewing situations, the three film and video pieces in this inspired show include a Felliniesque film of people encountered on a street in Rome; a series of mysterious exit interviews with New York moviegoers; and outtakes from another director's film into which Mr. Jankowski has inserted his own script. The artist himself doesn't seem to do much of anything, but he has created something memorable: a cerebral, transparent, emotionally touching experience of the ways films flow out of and back into life (Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''OCEAN FLOWERS: IMPRESSIONS FROM NATURE,'' Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166, through May 22. Dense with ethereal images and silhouettes of seaweed, this unusual exhibition shows how the needs of Victorian botanists, book publishers and inspired amateurs pushed traditional drawing and printmaking into the realm of photography without so much as touching a lens. The driving force was the need to get the wonders of nature down on paper, one way or another. Those ways run riot here and provide a startlingly revised view of the mongrel hands-on origins of the age of mechanical reproduction (Smith).</p>
        <p>NOT VITAL, Sperone Westwater, 415 West 13th Street, West Village, (212) 999-7337, through May 1. A marble beam with 3,000 teardrops carved into it, a wall bristling with knife blades, and a tall plywood pedestal bearing a stack of silver boxes that looks like a high-rise office building: these resonant sculptures might read together as a post-9/11 elegy. When you learn what's inside the silver boxes, as well as in a set of 16 silver spheres, a broader meditation on faith, truth and reality emerges (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* GEORGE AULT, Zabriskie, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 752-1223, through tomorrow. Fans of this American Precisionist will be gratified by this quietly stirring show of paintings and drawings from Ault's middle years, the 1920's and 30's. It includes an especially beautiful painting of an orange farmhouse on a green lawn, under a blue sky and wispy clouds, which is almost medieval in its pristine distillation. With its impenetrably dark windows and raking shadows, it also exudes a Hopperesque lonesomeness and a dreamy, de Chiricoesque mystery (Johnson).</p>
        <p>MATTIA BONETTI, Luhring Augustine, 531 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-9100, through tomorrow. This gallery's entertaining first foray into furniture display presents a variety of functional cabinets, tables, dressers and lamps by a well-known Paris designer. Each piece is a campy, glossy play on one or another familiar aesthetic. The Modernist grid is invoked by a cabinet made of overlapping squares of polished stainless steel. A Surrealist bench has burlap cast in bronze draped over a rectilinear gold frame. And a big jewelry-box of a dresser is in the form of a giant egg leafed in white gold (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ROBERT COTTINGHAM, Forum, 745 Fifth Avenue, at 58th Street, (212) 355-4545, through tomorrow. The Photo Realist known for his paintings of neon signs presents impressive big pictures of old typewriters at Forum. The subject matter may not sound promising, but Mr. Cottingham's greatly enlarged overhead views, painted with a lovingly precise touch, yield a fine combination of vivid, slightly simplified illusionism and intricately rhythmic abstraction. Dieu Donné, 433 Broome Street, SoHo, (212) 226-0573, is showing large, shadowy paper-pulp pictures, each a monumentalizing close-up of a small, blocky machine part, through May 8 (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''GLASS AND GLAMOUR: STEUBEN'S MODERN MOMENT, 1930-1960,'' Museum of the City of New York, 1220 Fifth Avenue, at 103rd Street, (212) 534-1672, through Sunday. Saluting the 100th anniversary of Steuben Glass, this show represents an era when the company went all out for Modernism in its high-end products, turning out elegantly contemporary and flawlessly executed ornamental, table and bar ware. Clean design, the use of biomorphic and abstract shapes, a revolutionary formula said to produce the world's purest lead crystal: these are hallmarks of the nearly 200 Steuben objects here. The best pieces are the unfussy, classically elegant Steuben designs that make their point as vessels without unnecessary embellishment. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ALLAN McCOLLUM AND MATT MULLICAN, ''Your Fate,'' Christine Burgin, 243 West 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 462-2668, through tomorrow. A conceptual artwork in the form of a surprisingly engaging fortune-telling game. Throw the two dozen dice imprinted with Mr. Mullican's archetypal symbols and a hair-raisingly oracular configuration of signs turns up. As art, the project can be read as a commentary on the frequent convergence of spiritualism and consumerism in modern society. But you can also imagine the game being successfully mass-marketed. Its inventors could make a fortune (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''PLAYING WITH FIRE: EUROPEAN TERRA-COTTA MODELS, 1740-1840,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through Sunday. Long used for architecture and decoration, terra cotta became the chosen modeling medium in Italy during the 16th century for neo-Classical artists devoted to reviving the Greek and Roman past. They used it extensively for making bozzetti, or sculptors' rough drafts for larger works in stone and bronze. As the practice spread through Europe, collectors were not far behind. Some 135 treasures from the 18th and 19th centuries by star talents like Antonio Canova, Joseph Chinard, Claude Michel (called Clodion), Augustin Pajou and John Flaxman are here. They range from quick, rough sketches to finished, elegant work. Monuments, funerary sculptures, images from myth and fable, religious tableaus and genre pieces make the show a rich and lively mix of the subtle power of terra cotta. Hours and admission: See above (Glueck).</p>
        <p>ALEXIS SMITH, ''Lust/Rust/Dust,'' Artemis, Greenberg Van Doren, 730 Fifth Avenue, at 57th Street, (212) 445-0444, through tomorrow. Using all kinds of found patriotic kitsch -- flag stickers, old historic illustrations, paint-by-numbers canvases, a red, white and blue sock -- this invaluable Los Angeles collage maker has produced fiercely ironic antiwar and anti-Republican propaganda. A wall painting has the words lust, rust and dust formatted to mimic the typography of Robert Indiana's famous ''Love'' painting; it is a timely, elegiac echo of the Vietnam era (Johnson).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
