<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Executive Preaches: Sweat the Smallest Details</title>
    <meta content="05LUTZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/05/automobiles/05lutz.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1548361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pontiac Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lutz, Robert A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lutz, Robert A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D81531F936A35752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Executive Preaches: Sweat the Smallest Details</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.M. Executive Preaches: Sweat the Smallest Details</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>WARREN, Mich.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert A Lutz, General Motors vice chairman for product development, discusses cars he is developing, interview; cites his stress on eliminating minor defects that detract from image of American cars, interview; his efforts to make Pontiac more like BMW noted; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert A. Lutz is trying to persuade the world's largest automaker, General Motors, to obsess about the smallest details, from the way a stereo knob feels when you turn it to eliminating the cheap-looking shine from plastics used in interiors.</p>
        <p>''People say, 'I don't know what it is, but when I rent an American car at the airport and look at all these minor imperfections, the message it sends is that you guys don't care,' and that message is very powerful,'' said Mr. Lutz, General Motors' vice chairman for product development. ''It's a turnoff.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year, rekindling Americas desire for American passenger cars is the principal goal of the Detroit-based automakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert A. Lutz is trying to persuade the world's largest automaker, General Motors, to obsess about the smallest details, from the way a stereo knob feels when you turn it to eliminating the cheap-looking shine from plastics used in interiors.</p>
        <p>''People say, 'I don't know what it is, but when I rent an American car at the airport and look at all these minor imperfections, the message it sends is that you guys don't care,' and that message is very powerful,'' said Mr. Lutz, General Motors' vice chairman for product development. ''It's a turnoff.''</p>
        <p>This year, rekindling America's desire for American passenger cars is the principal goal of the Detroit-based automakers, who have grown overly reliant on sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks for their modest profits.</p>
        <p>During the news media preview of the North American International Auto Show, which started Sunday,  the Big Three -- G.M., the Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler division of DaimlerChrysler -- are showcasing new cars aimed at winning back customers who have grown to like Toyotas or Volkswagens or Hondas since giving up on American cars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutz, who at 71 is old enough to remember when Detroit ruled the industry, brings a youthful zeal to the project. He is the Motor City's Errol Flynn, a stogie-wielding, roguish former marine, the son of a Swiss banker who grew up in Europe and the United States and has been an executive at each of the Big Three, as well as at BMW.</p>
        <p>He commutes to work by helicopter and is known in Detroit for walking away from his Czech-built fighter jet after landing it without first putting down the wheels, a mental slip he now uses for a punch line. As a Ford executive and Chrysler's president in the 1990's, he was an important figure in popularizing the sport utility vehicle and refers to talk of global warming as environmental propaganda.</p>
        <p>He also loves cars.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, he derided many of Detroit's automobile designs as ''angry kitchen appliances'' that lacked the emotional appeal of classic American cars. Since returning to G.M. in 2001 as the company's products czar, after a three-decade hiatus, he has sought to bring a sense of intuition and taste to a corporation best known for its reliance on focus groups.</p>
        <p>''This company is rightly very much obsessed with measuring results,'' he said, in a recent interview at G.M.'s design center in this Detroit suburb. ''It works really well in manufacturing and all of those things. It works much less well when you get into abstract concepts like beauty.</p>
        <p>''I'm Mr. Nonquantifiable personified,'' he added. ''I believe very deeply in the automobile as an art form.''</p>
        <p>Because it can take years for a new design to go into production, it is early to measure his results. But this year, some of his most visible fingerprints will be seen at Pontiac, whose ''boy racer'' image he hopes to make more like BMW.</p>
        <p>Young Pontiac buyers, he said, ''would really like a BMW'' but can not afford one. ''You try to imbue the car with some of the same characteristics, in terms of the driving experience,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Wes Brown, a partner at Iceology, an automotive consulting firm in Southern California, discounted the idea of Pontiac selling itself as an affordable BMW. ''Let's be honest, that's a grandiose dream,'' Mr. Brown said. ''The average consumer looks at that brand, and, for lack of a better word, sees it as kind of cheesy.''</p>
        <p>To get someone who wants a BMW to settle for a Pontiac, he added, would take ''a decade of incredibly strong product and a massive turnaround at the retail level that is going to make the kind of person that is image conscious suddenly make that shift.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutz agrees that shock and awe are needed, not baby steps, to have a realistic shot at luring back import buyers. The immediate goal is to revive the brand's flagging sales, down 9 percent through November 2003, and make it profitable.</p>
        <p>''If we could get the average incentive from $4,000, which it is now, to something like $2,000, we would be making a lot of money on domestic cars,'' he said. ''That's the plan. You just have to get vehicles more to the point where people want them.''</p>
        <p>Detroit's current heavy discounting has left many customers with an attitude akin to ''what'll you pay me if I take this thing off your hands?'' he said. ''That's not a good place to be.''</p>
        <p>The Pontiac makeover started with a half step last year, when he took a car from G.M.'s Australian subsidiary, Holden, and turned it into a new version of the Pontiac GTO, a classic 1960's muscle car. Critics have praised its performance but complained about an exterior some see as drab.</p>
        <p>More important will be the G6 sedan, a replacement for the Grand Am that goes on sale this fall and is intended to be Pontiac's best-selling vehicle. Coupe and convertible versions are due in 2005.</p>
        <p>G.M. will also begin selling a two-seat sports car, the Solstice, in 2005; it is one of Mr. Lutz's first projects, and has been praised for its glossy looks. The field of such vehicles is crowded, but few sell for as little as the Solstice, which is expected to start under $20,000. Much of Mr. Lutz's time has been spent in what one Pontiac executive called flyspecking sessions where he and Gary Cowger, G.M.'s president for North American operations, pore over minute interior and exterior details.</p>
        <p>''In another couple of years, Gary and I won't have to do this anymore because it will be imbued into the culture,'' Mr. Lutz said, picking over the fit of a plastic ring around a door lock on G6 prototype. ''But right now, it's necessary.''</p>
        <p>One particular pet peeve that Mr. Lutz has attacked is the size of the gaps where the corners of car hoods meet the headlights.</p>
        <p>''These gaps on older G.M. cars always looked like the Mississippi River delta,'' he said, because they were so wide. Customers are not likely to specifically focus on such details, he added, but when many such imperfections are taken together, they have an enormous subliminal impact.</p>
        <p>''It's like walking into a hotel room that isn't clean,'' he said. ''You don't know what it is but somehow the overall impression just isn't quite right.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Perkins, the G6's designer, said it was very unusual to have a vice chairman criticizing such minutiae.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago, or even less, you wouldn't have people at that level looking at these details,'' he said, adding that ''the corporation has really realized the value of design.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutz sees progress in the design studio, but is worried about what comes off the production line.</p>
        <p>''We are really fighting a national cultural heritage,'' he said recently.</p>
        <p>Assembly line workers and parts makers were not prepared for the higher standards he has set, Mr. Lutz  said. But everyone is getting into line, he added, for two very good reasons.</p>
        <p>''Moral suasion,'' he said, a grin creeping over his face, ''and an explanation of the potential consequences.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
