<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York's Watery New Grave</title>
    <meta content="11YABL$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/11/arts/design/11YABL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040411T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1573162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockman, Alexis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yablonsky, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn Museum of Art</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rockman, Alexis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lehman, Arnold L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEEDA1638F932A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="2061" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York's Watery New Grave</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New York's Watery New Grave</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA YABLONSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yablonsky, Linda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Linda Yablonsky article on Alexis Rockman's painting Manifest Destiny, futuristic view of Brooklyn waterfront circa 5004; traces work from initial idea, to use of photographic views, to computer projections provided by architect Diane Lewis; completed 24-foot-long work will be unveiled at Brooklyn Museum; Rockman comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT a dinner party in January 2000, Alexis Rockman used his napkin to outline a painting for Arnold L. Lehman, director of the Brooklyn Museum. Part naturalist, part dreamer, Mr. Rockman wanted to alert the world to the dangers of global warming, which he attributes to ''the history of human activity.'' The image, he said, would be ''Angkor Wat meets Brooklyn Bridge.''</p>
        <p>An admirer of what he calls the ''historical-fantastical aspect'' of Mr. Rockman's work, Mr. Lehman was intrigued. His museum was already looking into the future, having undertaken a $63 million expansion that includes the new glass entrance pavilion opening to the public on Saturday. At the same time, the museum will unveil the postapocalyptic painting that grew out of that dinner party conversation in a mezzanine gallery overlooking the refurbished Grand Lobby. Mr. Rockman's oil-on-wood panorama, now titled ''Manifest Destiny,'' measures 8 by 24 feet. Even so, it can barely contain its subject: the Brooklyn waterfront, circa 5004. By then, he believes, the effects of global warming will have left New York City soaking in 82 feet of water the color of orange pekoe tea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This weekend, the Brooklyn Museum unveils a postapocalyptic painting by Alexis Rockman that imagines the Brooklyn waterfront in 3,000 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT a dinner party in January 2000, Alexis Rockman used his napkin to outline a painting for Arnold L. Lehman, director of the Brooklyn Museum. Part naturalist, part dreamer, Mr. Rockman wanted to alert the world to the dangers of global warming, which he attributes to ''the history of human activity.'' The image, he said, would be ''Angkor Wat meets Brooklyn Bridge.''</p>
        <p>An admirer of what he calls the ''historical-fantastical aspect'' of Mr. Rockman's work, Mr. Lehman was intrigued. His museum was already looking into the future, having undertaken a $63 million expansion that includes the new glass entrance pavilion opening to the public on Saturday. At the same time, the museum will unveil the postapocalyptic painting that grew out of that dinner party conversation in a mezzanine gallery overlooking the refurbished Grand Lobby. Mr. Rockman's oil-on-wood panorama, now titled ''Manifest Destiny,'' measures 8 by 24 feet. Even so, it can barely contain its subject: the Brooklyn waterfront, circa 5004. By then, he believes, the effects of global warming will have left New York City soaking in 82 feet of water the color of orange pekoe tea.</p>
        <p>Now 41, Mr. Rockman dates the actual start of the painting to early 2002, when Mr. Lehman officially commissioned it. First, Mr. Rockman walked to the East River from his basement studio in TriBeCa and photographed the opposite shore -- the area between the Manhattan and Brooklyn bridges known as Dumbo. ''I felt that I needed something iconic, like the Statue of Liberty in 'Planet of the Apes,' '' Mr. Rockman said. ''And I decided that the Brooklyn Bridge was it.'' All he had to do now was find a way to represent the site as it might appear 3,000 years from now.</p>
        <p>In a sense, that was the easy part for Mr. Rockman, who has been making, as he put it, ''history paintings about the future'' since his first exhibition, in the East Village, in 1985. ''Evolution,'' for example, a 1992 image that detailed species development around a swamp, had the same dimensions as ''Manifest Destiny.'' But, in nearly two decades of creating antediluvian jungles where prehistoric creatures mingled with modern-day Tarzans, he had never attempted a cityscape.</p>
        <p>''I didn't feel I could pull it off,'' he said. ''I didn't know how to deal with the geometry of the manmade structures, the multiple vanishing points.'' After a long search, he hired Diane Lewis, an architect widely known for her ability to fold the historic into the contemporary, to create a multilayered architectural plan for the waterfront's projected future.</p>
        <p>The possibility of a new painting commission from the NASA art program then cropped up in an unexpected call from Helen Matsos, editor of Astrobiology magazine, an Internet daily (www.astrobio.net) covering the space agency's search for the origins of life in the universe. But when Ms. Matsos heard about ''Manifest Destiny,'' she put Mr. Rockman together with scientists at the Goddard Institute for Space Science at Columbia University, which studies global climate change. ''Of course, scientists don't have climate models to predict more than 100 years in the future,'' she said. ''But Alexis extrapolated from that.''</p>
        <p>In March 2003, Mr. Rockman bolted together four 8-by-6-foot wood panels and started painting. By July, he had blocked in the sun and the sky and added geologic strata to the bottom front of the picture plane. He also covered the space under the water line -- roughly three-quarters of the painting -- with Mars Orange, a pigment recommended by Dr. Peter Ward, a paleontologist at the University of Washington in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rockman had been Dr. Ward's illustrator for ''Future Evolution'' (2001), a science book he treated as a ''field guide'' to his new painting. ''He would call to ask what does granite look like underwater,'' Dr. Ward said, ''what wildlife might be present, what the water would be like. It's a very technically informed piece.''</p>
        <p>Why go to such lengths for a scene that would ultimately be a work of imagination? Although he borrows elements from science-fiction films, Mr. Rockman explained, he did not want the painting to be dismissed as a fantasy. ''I see this as a very traditional history painting,'' he said. ''And as far as I can tell, it is also the most credible version of our history.''</p>
        <p>By mid-September, he had traced Ms. Lewis's computer projections onto the prepared surface of the painting and decided how the sunlight would ricochet off surfaces above and below the water. Setting his painting on the floor, he created each building with bits of masking tape, making them stand out against the orange ground like modular cast-offs from a minimalist's workshop.</p>
        <p>At this point, he asked another architect, Chris Morris, to redesign both the broken sea wall beneath the pylons of his Brooklyn Bridge and the remains of what Mr. Rockman imagines future New Yorkers will use to replace the Manhattan Bridge, along with a subterranean, eight-lane tunnel.</p>
        <p>On an adjacent wall of his studio, Mr. Rockman was simultaneously working on ''Wonderful World,'' five paintings showing the effects of biotechnology on agriculture, tourism, sex, sports and pets. They go on view at the Camden Arts Center in London a week after the Brooklyn opening. Last October, however, ''Manifest Destiny'' captured Mr. Rockman's full attention when he noticed a wide gap between the buildings and the Brooklyn Bridge. A basketball enthusiast, he added a an imaginary sports complex. (This was before the announcement of an actual plan for a stadium in downtown Brooklyn.)</p>
        <p>Diana Wall, a professor of anthropology at the City College of New York, became a frequent consultant on the project, partly because she is also Mr. Rockman's mother. ''What got me was that I always knew where to reach him,'' she said, sounding more maternal than anthropological. ''He was always there, and how often can you say that about anyone?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rockman admits to both an obsessive personality and Mrs. Wall's enormous influence on the course of his art. (His father, who died 10 years ago, was an Australian-born jazz musician). When Mr. Rockman was a child, his mother was Margaret Mead's assistant at the American Museum of Natural History, which was his favorite playground. The artists and illustrators who made the dioramas he studied so carefully there were inspired, he said, by the same painters whose work has been guiding him: Thomas Cole, Frederic Church and Albert Bierstadt.</p>
        <p>''I've been very deliberate about using the Hudson River School language,'' Mr. Rockman said in November. ''The Industrial Revolution and the Hudson River School were really tied in to the idea of using natural resources. Global warming, unimaginable in the 19th century, is obviously its dark side. That's why the title is 'Manifest Destiny.' ''</p>
        <p>Another influence, he said, was Chesley Bonestell, a legendary figure in science-fiction and fantasy art illustration. ''He did a series of unbelievably convincing paintings that imagine different cities after atomic bombings,'' Mr. Rockman recalled. ''They've been really important, too.''</p>
        <p>By Thanksgiving, Mr. Rockman's Brooklyn Bridge was well on its way to ruin and a submarine had appeared front and center, bent over the newly angled undersea wall of geologic rock like the village drunk. Mr. Rockman made botanical studies for jungly vegetation intended for the decaying arches of the bridge that remained above the water line.</p>
        <p>At first glance the scene looks like the aftermath of a bombing -- sticky subject matter for a museum in post-9/11 New York. For Mr. Rockman, however, the violence in the painting ''is not coming from anything other than our own behavior toward the environment'' and has nothing to do with war or terrorism. And Mr. Lehman, who will not see the painting until its unveiling, is confident that it will read as a credible warning of environmental disaster, and not the consequence of a specific event. In addition, he said, ''I've always believed that museums are, and should be, safe places for unsafe ideas.''</p>
        <p>By Dec. 12, all the architectural elements were in place, including the truncated roadway of the replacement Manhattan Bridge, now little more than a cantilevered perch for a cormorant that would appear later. An oil drum -- symbolic of fossil fuels -- floated on the water's eerily calm surface, while two seals played above several evil-eyed fish. ''We tend to identify with mammals,'' Mr. Rockman noted. ''That's why the seals are there. They are the conscience of the image.''</p>
        <p>By mid-January, roseate spoonbills, herring seagulls and the cormorant were giving ''Manifest Destiny'' a new sprightliness, but the underwater structures seemed to have sprouted yellow fuzz, crabs, eelgrass or stalactites. The entire painting appeared to rest on a suppurating ooze. All the same, Mr. Rockman, who has gone snorkeling in the Amazon and hunted the Tasmanian tiger, now faced a complex spatial puzzle that he could not quite solve. ''How do you keep this epic space, with buildings in it, and also show something as small as a shrimp?'' he asked. ''That's very challenging.''</p>
        <p>On Jan. 18, during a snowstorm, the space heater in his studio broke down, forcing Mr. Rockman to wear heavy sweaters, long underwear and gloves indoors. But the chill didn't prevent more studio visits from ecologists, botanists and Tumelo Mosaka, the Brooklyn Museum's assistant curator for contemporary art. ''It was a learning curve for me to see how Alexis translated the scientific information into visual language,'' he said, after numerous trips to view the painting's progress.</p>
        <p>By Feb. 22, the light in the work had turned from a harsh glare to a sublime glow that actually seemed to give off heat, an illusion the shivering Mr. Rockman embraced. To complement the fish, vegetation and other organic matter in the increasingly murky riverbed, he added manmade objects like a sunken oil freighter, a stealth bomber and a Spanish galleon, all placed at varying depths to represent civilizations that had contributed to the city's continuing decay. Actual humans, however, were nowhere to be seen.</p>
        <p>In early March, diseases like SARS, the West Nile virus and mad cow entered the picture, where they float by shellfish that have grown reptilian bodies or too many claws. Other survivors included a rat and a cockroach. An enormous H.I.V.-infected cell resembling a truck tire intruded on the stratigraphy, under a jellyfish trailing noodley tentacles across nearly half the painting. A snakehead fish had become especially monstrous, but the radiant light made the whole vista more haunting than ever. Finally, on March 16, Mr. Rockman pronounced the painting under control. ''It's going to work!'' he said with a wide grin. ''I'm dying to know what scientists will think, but now I just need to finish.''</p>
        <p>When the museum finally called for the painting at the end of March, it was Robert Rosenblum, a professor of Fine Arts at New York University, who happened to be visiting the studio. ''It's a fantastic, truly political marriage of Frederic Church and Stephen Jay Gould,'' he said. ''This painting should scare everyone.''</p>
        <p>Not bad for an artist who didn't even train to be a painter. Until 1981, when he entered a psychiatric ward for several months to treat a serious depression, Mr. Rockman had studied animated film. ''I started painting when I got out,'' he said. ''You know,'' he added with a chuckle. ''Everyone needs a hobby.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Linda Yablonsky is a contributing editor for ArtNews and the author of ''The Story of Junk,'' a novel.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 11, 2004, Sunday  A picture caption on Page 28 of Arts &amp; Leisure today with an article about ''Manifest Destiny,'' the mural by Alexis Rockman that will be unveiled at the Brooklyn Museum on Saturday, refers incorrectly to the version shown, which also appears on the section's front page. It is an unfinished version, photographed in December 2003, not the finished painting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 11, 2004, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Page 28 of Arts &amp; Leisure today with an article about ''Manifest Destiny,'' the mural by Alexis Rockman that will be unveiled at the Brooklyn Museum on Saturday, refers incorrectly to the version shown, which also appears on the section's front page. It is an unfinished version, photographed in December 2003, not the finished painting.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Linda Yablonsky is a contributing editor for ArtNews and the author of ''The Story of Junk,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
