<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Into Prehistory In the Dordogne</title>
    <meta content="DORDOGNE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1608987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Les Eyzies-De-Tayac (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Museum of Prehistory (Les Eyzies-De-Tayac, France)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DD1731F936A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Into Prehistory In the Dordogne</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elaine Sciolino travel article on visit to new National Museum of Prehistory in Les Eyzies-de-Tayac, France; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRESENTING prehistory to the masses is a daunting task. The unknowns -- from what prehistoric men and women looked like to how to define prehistoric artistic expression -- are often too great to make the subject accessible to amateurs.</p>
        <p>So the opening in July of the National Museum of Prehistory, perched on a cliff in the tiny village of Les Eyzies-de-Tayac in the Dordogne, was a major event in the French cultural world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRESENTING prehistory to the masses is a daunting task. The unknowns -- from what prehistoric men and women looked like to how to define prehistoric artistic expression -- are often too great to make the subject accessible to amateurs.</p>
        <p>So the opening in July of the National Museum of Prehistory, perched on a cliff in the tiny village of Les Eyzies-de-Tayac in the Dordogne, was a major event in the French cultural world.</p>
        <p>The $30 million museum, designed by the Florence-born architect Jean-Pierre Buffi, has been two decades and eight ministers of culture in the making, delayed by the discovery of fissures and springs in the cliff, huge cost overruns and fierce arguments over the museum's contents.</p>
        <p>On one level, the building's spare, modern design seems a violation of the landscape. A replacement for the small, dark museum that was housed in the late 16th-century castle next door, the new museum, built with local stone, announces its presence by jutting obtrusively from its yellow limestone site above the village.</p>
        <p>But it is also an architectural tour de force whose soaring windows and high ceilings provide exquisite natural light and reveal the stark faces of the limestone caves.</p>
        <p>Certainly, the museum's display of 18,000 objects -- a small fraction of the five million in its possession -- is regarded as one of the two or three richest collections of European ice-age artifacts in the world. Among the most important are a small 14,000-to-15,000-year-old bison carved in bone, its head turned to lick its flank, and a skeleton of a child of two or three that is 50,000 years old. Here also is the largest collection of 30,000-year-old stone engravings, among the most ancient art objects on earth.</p>
        <p>For people who know little about prehistory, the museum can be daunting. There is no system of multilingual tours, no interactive computers, not even a catalog, although museum officials promise English audio guides and an English catalog in early 2005. Those who don't speak French will be frustrated by the French-only labeling.</p>
        <p>In an effort to cover the sweep of human evolution, the museum has installed resin composition fakes, even of 3.2-million-year-old Lucy, whose bones were returned to the National Museum of Ethiopia in Addis Ababa by the Cleveland Museum of Natural History in 1980, and of the first known examples of human footprints, dating from about 3.6 million years ago.</p>
        <p>The region is home to the valley of the Vézère River, occupied by herds of large herbivores during the ice age. One of the ''cave man'' blockbuster novels of Jean M. Auel is set here.</p>
        <p>That makes it a vast living archaeological museum that extends for miles and boasts hundreds of excavated prehistoric sites dating back tens of thousands of years, including caves decorated with paintings and engravings, open-air cliff shelters used as prehistoric dwellings and campsites. New sites are discovered from time to time.</p>
        <p>In 1994, for example, Jean-Marie Chauvet, an amateur archaeologist and spelunker, discovered a vast network of caves in the Ardèche Gorge in the Rhone Valley, with more than 400 wall paintings up to 32,000 years old. They stunned the archaeological community because some of them were as sophisticated as those painted in caves more than 10,000 years later. To protect them from daylight and pollution, the caves will never be open to the public.</p>
        <p>In 2000, another amateur archaeologist discovered a warren of caves with about 100 prehistoric engravings, including a drawing of a 12-foot-long bison and female silhouettes, on the property of a British couple in Cussac in the Dordogne. There is even a property for sale in St.-Cirq three miles from Les Eyzies that boasts its own prehistoric cave with paintings.</p>
        <p>Lascaux, about 15 miles northeast of Les Eyzies, is by far the most celebrated site of prehistoric painted caves in the region. Discovered by four teenagers in 1940, it was closed to the public in 1963 after visits by more than a million people produced enough carbon dioxide, pollen and bacteria to damage the paintings. In 2001, it was closed to all but its small team of restorers. But 200 yards away is Lascaux II, a painstakingly constructed replica of a portion of the estimated 1,700 paintings and engravings of the original cave. (Marja Goevaers, our English-speaking guide, insists it's 90 percent of all the paintings, but experts say it isn't so.)</p>
        <p>On a visit in July, my husband, our two teenagers and I needed to move beyond the concrete ceilings, rubberized floors and green-and-white emergency exit signs before we were able to marvel at the creativity of the original artists. Using crushed minerals and clay to create hues of red, yellow, brown and deepest black, they followed the natural contours of the walls and ceilings to lend a three-dimensional quality to the delicate and powerful renderings. The artists even left their handprints.</p>
        <p>Our guide used a flashlight to point out the animal forms, even creatures that were half-human. She called the 55-foot-long Great Hall of Bulls, with its immense black bulls, bison, deer and horses, ''the Sistine Chapel of its time.''</p>
        <p>Still, this wasn't real. For that we went to Font-de-Gaume and Combarelles, two of the only prehistoric caves in the region open to the public. Font-de-Gaume is a showpiece of engravings and two-toned paintings -- of bison, horses, mammoths, reindeer, wooly rhinoceros, a wolf and a lioness. We learned that the painters built scaffolding to allow them access to walls 16 feet high, that some paintings had faded where visitors had touched them, that the painters struggled with perspective. One tender scene shows a male reindeer licking his mate.</p>
        <p>Combarelles, less than two miles away, features hundreds of engravings. There we saw how artists superimposed images on the same wall. Most striking are the engravings of humans, including a stylized profile of a woman and a seated man. Not far away were engravings that are often interpreted as a penis and a vulva. ''Some people say it is erotic representation,'' said Monique Veyret, who has been the guide at Combarelles for 22 years. ''But perhaps it is the moment when the woman is more fertile and open to conception.''</p>
        <p>Both caves are about 12,000 to 14,000 years old, and all tours are limited to no more than a dozen people, which lends an intimacy to the visits.</p>
        <p>Privately owned caves in the region can be visited with advance planning and a bit of ingenuity. One way (for those with deep pockets and no French) is to hire an English-speaking guide such as Christine Desdemaine Hugon, for about $300 a day, plus entry fees, for a daylong tour of private and public sites.</p>
        <p>For an unusual, personal encounter with the prehistoric, we visited René Castanet, the 81-year-old owner of Castel-Merle, about 12 miles from Les Eyzies. It is also the site of an archaeological dig by Randall White, a New York University professor of anthropology who has worked in the valley for 25 years and was there the day we visited. He is the author of ''Prehistoric Art'' ($45), published by Harry N. Abrams, a welcome introduction to the subject with color photos.</p>
        <p>Mr. White said that his current excavation area is so rich that it includes thousands of archaeological objects, from beads to pierced shells, in just a few square feet. His project this summer is the extraction of the skeleton of a toddler who lived around 20,000 years ago, whose remains are covered in hundreds of ornamental seashells.</p>
        <p>Since 1980, Mr. Castanet's property has served as an untamed wilderness of a museum. His father, Marcel, excavated the site in the 1910's and 1920's. He collected some of the most extraordinary objects in prehistoric France at a time when the French government imposed few controls on excavation and collection. René Castanet lives less than a mile away from the site and has turned two tiny rooms of his home into a private museum open only by appointment. The phone number for contacting him hangs on the outer gate. It is the antithesis of the new National Museum of Prehistory on the hill nearby.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Castel-Merle, as Mr. Castanet's museum is called, smells of the mustiness and humidity of old Dordogne houses. The paper labels identifying the objects have been eaten away by mice. There's not a plastic mammoth's tooth in the place, just hundreds of tools, beads and ornaments and 34,000-year-old engraved stones with animal and human images.</p>
        <p>Access to the museum is free with a visit to the site, which should come first. The original stone engraving of a horse excavated on his property is now in the American Museum of Natural History in New York; numerous engravings are in the new museum in Les Eyzies.</p>
        <p>At the site itself, Mr. Castanet gives tours to individuals and groups. An accomplished flint knapper, he holds demonstrations on making flint tools, while local painters demonstrate how prehistoric humans used different techniques to paint. (They even mixed paint in their mouths and spat it directly onto the walls). Mr. Castanet's granddaughter Isabelle can be pressed into service to give tours in English.</p>
        <p>On the day we visited, Randall White took us around. We stood at the Abri des Merveilles (the Shelter of Wonders), a rock shelter inhabited between 25,000 and 100,000 years ago. It has never been properly excavated. ''You are standing on a Neanderthal site!'' Mr. White exclaimed. ''You have to imagine a living campsite with a fire. If you were to dig down a foot or so, you'd come upon intact Neanderthal deposits.''</p>
        <p>His improvised tour included a look at Abri Blanchard (the Blanchard Shelter), which he calls ''the most important Cro-Magnon site in all of Europe,'' dating back 35,000 years, as well as remnants of the Dark Ages, such as a ninth-century oven and guard towers used to detect Viking invaders.</p>
        <p>Along a wooded trail, he picked up a piece of a 15,000-year-old flint tool, throwing it down just where he found it, as he is legally required to do. The area, he said, has never been dug. ''Here,'' Mr. White said, ''you stand exactly where people lived 25,000 years ago.''</p>
        <p>ELAINE SCIOLINO is chief of the Paris bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ELAINE SCIOLINO is chief of the Paris bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
