<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaders Jostle to Shape Agenda for a New Term</title>
    <meta content="04GLOBAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="P" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/04/international/europe/04global.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1624543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 ELECTIONS: A LOOK AHEAD -- WORLD REACTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DB173CF937A35752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaders Jostle to Shape Agenda for a New Term</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Leaders Jostle to Shape Agenda for a New Term</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Nov. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's electoral victory is greeted internationally with mixture of praise, disappointment and pragmatic resignation as world leaders jostle to congratulate Bush while hoping to influence his foreign policy agenda; Prime Min Tony Blair calls for addressing root causes of terrorism by revitalizing Mideast peace effort; not clear is whether France and Germany can move beyond bruised personal relations, although Pres Jacques Chirac and Chancellor Gerhard Schroder offer cooperation in common fight against terrorism; Pres Vladimir Putin, on Russian television, welcomes re-election while warning that new dialogue with US will not be easy; anxiety is rampant particularly in Mideast and elsewhere in Europe; photo; Japanese hope to reap benefits of having backed winner (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's electoral victory was greeted internationally on Wednesday with a mixture of praise, disappointment and pragmatic resignation as world leaders jostled to congratulate the president while seeking to influence his foreign policy agenda for the second term.</p>
        <p>From street corners, parliament halls and palaces, politicians and sidewalk pundits offered Mr. Bush unsolicited advice on how to strengthen America's effectiveness overseas by improving working relations with its allies and fulfilling a longstanding pledge to push for a permanent peace settlement between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's victory was greeted internationally with a mixture of praise, disappointment and pragmatic resignation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's electoral victory was greeted internationally on Wednesday with a mixture of praise, disappointment and pragmatic resignation as world leaders jostled to congratulate the president while seeking to influence his foreign policy agenda for the second term.</p>
        <p>From street corners, parliament halls and palaces, politicians and sidewalk pundits offered Mr. Bush unsolicited advice on how to strengthen America's effectiveness overseas by improving working relations with its allies and fulfilling a longstanding pledge to push for a permanent peace settlement between Israelis and Palestinians.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday night Prime Minister Tony Blair, in a congratulatory statement carried by American and British television networks, called on Mr. Bush and the rest of the international community to address the root causes of terrorism by revitalizing the Middle East peace effort, which he called ''the single most pressing political challenge in our world today.'' He also emphasized reducing ''poverty and injustice'' in Africa.</p>
        <p>The statement from Mr. Blair, who faces his own re-election contest next spring, fulfills a pledge to his governing Labor Party, and to Britons more generally, that the British role in the Iraq military campaign would advance the peace effort.</p>
        <p>Beyond policy, there were thorny questions of whether European leaders could move past bruised personal relations from Mr. Bush's first term, not least in France and Germany, where it was an open question whether a fresh start was possible after many disagreements over the war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>In their formal statements of congratulation, the presidents of both countries offered their cooperation.</p>
        <p>President Jacques Chirac raised the prospect of a new beginning with the Bush administration, referring to ''our common fight against terrorism and the actions we are leading together to promote liberty and democracy.''</p>
        <p>''We can only find satisfactory solutions to the numerous challenges with which we are confronted today through a close trans-Atlantic partnership,'' Mr. Chirac said.</p>
        <p>The German chancellor, Gerhard Schröder, told Mr. Bush in a telegram that the world faced challenges from international terrorism, the danger of unconventional weapons and regional crises, ''but also poverty, climate change and epidemics, which threaten our security and our stability.''</p>
        <p>''These challenges can only be faced together,'' Mr. Schröder said, offering renewed cooperation.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, Prime Minister Paul Martin of Canada set a cabinet meeting for Thursday to discuss how relations might be improved in Mr. Bush's second term after a series of trade and health disputes over lumber, wheat and mad cow disease soured Ottawa's ties with Washington. Canada also opted out of sending troops to Iraq.</p>
        <p>In Moscow, President Vladimir V. Putin sought to demonstrate once again that he shared a strong personal bond with Mr. Bush despite differences over Iraq and over Russia's sale of nuclear power generating technology to Iran.</p>
        <p>Speaking on Russian television on Wednesday evening, Mr. Putin said, ''I can only be glad that the American people did not allow themselves to be frightened'' by ''international terrorists'' who ''set a goal to prevent Bush from being re-elected.'' Mr. Putin said a new dialogue with the United States ''won't be an easy one,'' but he praised Mr. Bush as a ''man with a strong character.''</p>
        <p>But anxiety was rampant in many countries, particularly in the Middle East, including Iraq, where a tenacious insurgency could undermine the national elections scheduled for January.</p>
        <p>President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt, one of America's staunchest Arab allies, issued a statement saying he hoped that Mr. Bush would dedicate himself to ''a just and comprehensive peace in the Middle East by establishing a Palestinian state alongside the state of Israel'' while also securing Iraq and ridding the region of nuclear weapons, a reference intended to draw attention to Israel's undeclared nuclear arsenal.</p>
        <p>Yasir Arafat, speaking through an aide, congratulated President Bush and urged him to become ''more engaged'' in fostering progress toward peace in the Middle East, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>Many foreign analysts wondered whether Mr. Bush would adjust his strategies now that he is unencumbered by re-election pressures.</p>
        <p>Giuliano Gerrara, a prominent conservative commentator and editor of the Italian daily Il Foglio, called it ''the logic of the second mandate,'' freeing Mr. Bush to take political risks and shape compromises.</p>
        <p>In Turkey, businessmen worried that Mr. Bush's victory would spread instability on their borders from Iraq to Iran; in China, some analysts focused on whether American policy might encourage the independence movement on Taiwan through arms sales; and Japanese and South Korean officials fretted how Mr. Bush would act in the coming confrontation over North Korea's nuclear weapons program.</p>
        <p>In Europe, analysts focused on whether there was any hope of bridging increasingly stark differences over the role of the United Nations, NATO and institutions like the International Criminal Court. There were signs of lingering bitterness and reflections of the divisions among Europeans about Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Charles Grant, the director of the Center for European Reform, a nonpartisan policy institute, said in an open letter to Mr. Bush that ''your best potential allies are the Europeans'' and that it was time for him to make up with them.</p>
        <p>Pat Cox, the Irish politician who stepped down as president of the European Parliament this fall, said, ''European leaders have to live in the real world.'' But he added that Mr. Bush's governing style had created ''fault lines'' in Europe that would persist through a second Bush term and perpetuate the ''underlying tension in the European dynamic.''</p>
        <p>Michael Müller, the deputy head of the Social Democratic delegation in the German Parliament, said Americans had returned a ''fundamentalist'' to the White House and ''that is neither good for the world nor for a democratic America.''</p>
        <p>Italy's conservative prime minister, Silvio Berlusconi, who was visiting Mr. Putin in Moscow, felt vindicated in his strong support for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''The continuation of Bush in American politics makes things easier for us,'' he said, adding that Italy was looking forward to an American leader who would ''continue with the policy that assigns the United States the role of defender and promoter of freedom and democracy.''</p>
        <p>Spain's new prime minister, José Rodríguez Zapatero, who pulled Spanish troops out of Iraq, told Mr. Bush in a message, ''During this period, I think rapprochement would be very helpful.''</p>
        <p>In Poland, whose government deployed troops in Iraq to support the United States, President Aleksander Kwasniewski said that Mr. Bush ''is a very decisive leader who is right, simply right'' in the campaign against terrorism. He said he regarded Mr. Bush's winning a second term as ''really good news.''</p>
        <p>In Japan, where Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi and the leaders of the governing Liberal Democratic Party declared their support for Mr. Bush before Tuesday's election, many Japanese said they felt that they would enjoy the benefits of backing the winner.</p>
        <p>THE 2004 ELECTIONS: A LOOK AHEAD -- WORLD REACTION</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 5, 2004, Friday  An article yesterday about foreign reactions to the re-election of President Bush misspelled the surname of the editor of the Italian daily Il Foglio, who was quoted as saying Mr. Bush could now take political risks unencumbered by re-election pressures. He is Giuliano Ferrara, not Gerrara.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 5, 2004, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about foreign reactions to the re-election of President Bush misspelled the surname of the editor of the Italian daily Il Foglio, who was quoted as saying Mr. Bush could now take political risks unencumbered by re-election pressures. He is Giuliano Ferrara, not Gerrara.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
