<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE NAMES</title>
    <meta content="26BOLD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/26/nyregion/26bold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface Names"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Day After Tomorrow, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Boldface Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Actors and Actresses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6DA153EF935A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Help Us, We're Melting. Melting!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joyce Wadler; With Jess Wisloski</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Wadler interviews cast at premiere of movie The Day After Tomorrow, moving abouty global warming disaster; reports on slide show and talk on global warming by Al Gore in New York City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Help Us, We're Melting. Melting!</p>
        <p>There was a big premiere for the global warming disaster movie, ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' the day before yesterday. The film shows LADY LIBERTY up to her neck in tidal waves, and New York City in the grip of an ice age so intense that the grid of Manhattan is turned into a giant ice cube tray. So, in keeping the mood alive, the film's promoters judiciously decided to bank the arrival line with piles of snow.</p>
        <p>The red carpet in front of the American Museum of Natural History was white and banked by piles of the stuff; green oak leaves had been painted white. All very lovely, of course, but tragically, this global warming thing is more advanced than even the filmmakers thought: The snow was melting, the Astroturf carpet drenched.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a big premiere for the global warming disaster movie, "The Day After Tomorrow,'' the day before yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Help Us, We're Melting. Melting!</p>
        <p>There was a big premiere for the global warming disaster movie, ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' the day before yesterday. The film shows LADY LIBERTY up to her neck in tidal waves, and New York City in the grip of an ice age so intense that the grid of Manhattan is turned into a giant ice cube tray. So, in keeping the mood alive, the film's promoters judiciously decided to bank the arrival line with piles of snow.</p>
        <p>The red carpet in front of the American Museum of Natural History was white and banked by piles of the stuff; green oak leaves had been painted white. All very lovely, of course, but tragically, this global warming thing is more advanced than even the filmmakers thought: The snow was melting, the Astroturf carpet drenched.</p>
        <p>''Who do we sue if we get electrocuted?'' asked the Reuters television reporter SAMIRA NANDA, who periodically stepped off the carpet to try to dry her feet.</p>
        <p>Then, just as the chilly, wet scene couldn't get much more uncomfortable, three black limos pulled up in front of the museum, the cue for the snowblowers to be turned on. A collective groan from the press corps, as cameramen rushed to their vehicles for lens caps and soapy, white wet blobs hit reporters' notebooks.</p>
        <p>Still It Was Better Than ...</p>
        <p>But frivolous us. Here we were about to natter in our usual fashion about movie stars when we should be telling you about ''A Town Hall Meeting on Global Warming'' with AL GORE, ROBERT F. KENNEDY JR. and AL FRANKEN. It had been planned to coincide with ''The Day After Tomorrow'' -- the film's director ROLAND EMMERICH attended -- and was presented by MoveOn.Org and Environmental Media Services on Monday afternoon at the Fourth Universalist Church on Central Park West. We saw Mr. Gore speak, accompanied by a slide show of charts and graphs.</p>
        <p>How exciting was it?</p>
        <p>Next to us, a man with an American flag on his lapel was dead asleep despite the Starbucks cup near his feet. Mr. Gore and a slide show -- not even a supershot of espresso is going to keep you awake. In the crowd, we saw KEVIN BACON and KYRA SEDGWICK.</p>
        <p>But what did Mr. Gore tell the crowd?</p>
        <p>''This is what happens to the soil moisture in the continental United States,'' Mr. Gore was saying, as a graph came up on a giant screen. ''Up to 30 to 35 percent loss of soil moisture! And if we go barreling right through a doubling of CO2? Most of the growing areas of the United States become parched. Parched. So where are the ethics for somebody who says this is not a problem?'' (Oh, excuse us a minute. Medic! We've got somebody who was reading the National edition who's collapsed face first in Apple River, Ill. Take old Route 20 out past Stockton on to Scout Camp Road.)</p>
        <p>Golly, if only we didn't have that dreary premiere to go to later.</p>
        <p>There's More Snow Here Than the Blizzard of '96</p>
        <p>SHPLOT! SLOSH! SHPLOT! Here we are at the premiere.</p>
        <p>First down the red carpet, 17-year-old EMMY ROSSUM, who is somebody or another's love interest in the film. ''I have snow on my chin,'' she chirps, as publicists pick little soap chunks from her hair and face.</p>
        <p>Think much about global warming before making this flick, Ms. Rossum?</p>
        <p>''No, and it's made me think a lot more about it now, and it's made me more conscious of how I treat the environment. It's actually affected me a lot and ...''</p>
        <p>Ciao, darling!</p>
        <p>Here comes Mr. Emmerich, the German director of the movie. He's got a DAVID LETTERMAN gap in the teeth, nice tan, gray hair, a very suave silver suit and a look of bemusement indicating he's our kind of guy -- or else the freezing water has put him into shock.</p>
        <p>What would you like New Yorkers to do to save the environment, Mr. Emmerich? ''Maybe turn the air-conditioner on a little bit warmer. Today I was all day in and out of building and it's freezing in buildings. I don't know what America's obsession with air-conditioners is.''</p>
        <p>(Simple: It gets us into the theater to watch dumb disaster movies in August.)</p>
        <p>Hey, here's DENNIS QUAID, who plays the scientist who will try to save the world.</p>
        <p>(And wouldn't it be refreshing if for once the scientist in this genre said, ''Oh, the heck with it. I'm just going to bag it and check into that hotel I could never afford in South Beach and ...'')</p>
        <p>How about this snow, Mr. Quaid?</p>
        <p>''This is, uh, something,'' he replies. He looks down at his soaked feet and lifts one foot. ''You can't get a cab in weather like this, either. It's just too bad.''</p>
        <p>You said it. Our new sandals are ruined.</p>
        <p>''Incoming!'' hollers JAKE GYLLENHAAL, who plays the scientist's son, as he lobs a snowball down the aisle.</p>
        <p>''What do you think about being a hunk?'' a reporter from US Weekly asks him.</p>
        <p>''The real question is, a hunk of what?'' Mr. Gyllenhaal says, as he reaches forward and gently touches her face.</p>
        <p>''You have a little soap on your chin,'' he says.</p>
        <p>With Jess Wisloski</p>
        <p>Boldface Names</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
