<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mosquito's Gift in Singapore: A Bad Case of Breakbone Fever</title>
    <meta content="07CASE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/07/health/07case.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1609582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dengue Fever</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dengue Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1D81E31F934A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mosquito's Gift in Singapore: A Bad Case of Breakbone Fever</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Mosquito's Gift in Singapore: A Bad Case of Breakbone Fever</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wayne Arnold Cases article describes his personal experience when he contracted dengue fever in Singapore; discusses history of illness, its symptoms and efforts to combat spread of disease; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It began with a slight headache across my temples, the sort of feeling you would expect after a long day of meetings. By the time I returned home, I had begun to feel flu-ish. The headache became a migraine, concentrated behind my eyes, as though a pair of imps were squatting under my frontal lobe, kicking at my sockets. I spent the night vomiting, delirious, with a fever that crept close to 104 degrees.</p>
        <p>That was only the beginning of a monthlong ordeal. I had contracted dengue (pronounced deng-AY), a mosquito-borne virus for which there is no specific treatment and no vaccine, despite the fact that it afflicts an estimated 50 million people every year. And I had caught it right here in prosperous, squeaky-clean Singapore. Unlike the mosquito that carries malaria, a parasitic disease of the world's tropical backwaters, dengue's courier is a striped urbanite called Aedes aegypti.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coping with dengue, a mosquito-borne virus for which there is no specific treatment and no vaccine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It began with a slight headache across my temples, the sort of feeling you would expect after a long day of meetings. By the time I returned home, I had begun to feel flu-ish. The headache became a migraine, concentrated behind my eyes, as though a pair of imps were squatting under my frontal lobe, kicking at my sockets. I spent the night vomiting, delirious, with a fever that crept close to 104 degrees.</p>
        <p>That was only the beginning of a monthlong ordeal. I had contracted dengue (pronounced deng-AY), a mosquito-borne virus for which there is no specific treatment and no vaccine, despite the fact that it afflicts an estimated 50 million people every year. And I had caught it right here in prosperous, squeaky-clean Singapore. Unlike the mosquito that carries malaria, a parasitic disease of the world's tropical backwaters, dengue's courier is a striped urbanite called Aedes aegypti.</p>
        <p>Aedes flourishes indoors and in gardens, the female feeding on the blood of its human hosts in daylight, then laying its eggs in the tiny pools of water that collect around the home: under flowerpots, overturned lids and rain gutters. If a female bites a person with dengue, it passes it on to the next person it bites.</p>
        <p>Carried by international trade and global warming, the mosquito has traveled beyond Asia, reaching as far as northern Australia and the southeastern United States.</p>
        <p>''It is a pest, like rats, that has learned to live in an urban environment with man,'' said Dr. Donald S. Burke, director of Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health's center for immunization research.</p>
        <p>Dengue belongs to the same family of viruses that cause West Nile, Japanese encephalitis and yellow fever, which the mosquito also carries. Yet 9 out of 10 people who get any of dengue's four strains don't even know it. They might feel a bit of flu, or nothing at all. But in about 1 percent, patients develop dengue hemorrhagic fever, when the capillaries leak and the circulatory system collapses.</p>
        <p>Some patients suffer gastrointestinal bleeding, a rare few, brain hemorrhages. The rest of us just feel like we're dying. Not for nothing is dengue also known as breakbone fever.</p>
        <p>I, for one, felt as though someone had tied a Brink's truck to my lower back. My skin was flushed, I could not eat, and I slept for 12 to 14 hours at a stretch. When I went to the doctor two days later, I could hardly walk or open my bloodshot eyes.</p>
        <p>The doctor had little choice but to send me home with the painkiller Panadol and some muscle relaxants: tests for dengue rely on the presence of antibodies, which can take up to a week to develop.</p>
        <p>Dengue was first identified more than 300 years ago. It was an isolated problem until World War II, when it island-hopped across Southeast Asia with warring troops.</p>
        <p>After the war, Asia's explosive population growth and rapid urbanization gave Aedes new room to roam and by 1975, dengue was a leading cause of hospitalization and death among children in the region.</p>
        <p>The mosquito hopped the trade routes to India, Africa and the eastern Mediterranean. When campaigns to stamp out yellow fever in Latin America were declared victorious in the 1970's, Aedes made a comeback to carry dengue across the continent and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>Now it has worked its way into Florida and the Deep South. Dengue has even emerged in Hawaii. Meanwhile, countries that have long coped with dengue are experiencing increasingly widespread and virulent epidemics of the disease, according to the World Health Organization. Singapore's own experience with dengue bodes ill for prevention efforts. In the late 1960's, Singapore adopted perhaps the world's most rigorous anti-dengue program, educating the population about the dangers of standing water. Government inspectors routinely scour homes for breeding sites, issuing fines to offenders.</p>
        <p>A week after my first feverish night, a doctor looked at the tiny pinpricks of blood that had formed under the skin on my shoulders and sent me for a blood test, which confirmed that I had dengue.</p>
        <p>My case and all the others reported are plotted with red dots on a computerized map at Singapore's National Environment Agency. Together with breeding sites and other clues of mosquito havens, the computer searches for potential outbreaks and for ''hot spots, '' where cases emerge within Aedes's 150-yard range. At signs of trouble, the agency sends contractors to fog the area with insecticide.</p>
        <p>While Singapore has managed to reduce its Aedes population, its incidence of dengue has risen. So far this year, Singapore has recorded 3,525 cases. Health officials here hypothesize that fewer people are being bitten, but that because fewer people are immune, a smaller number of mosquitoes can infect a greater number of people.</p>
        <p>My first blood test also revealed that my platelets -- the cells that allow blood to clot and prevent hemorrhaging -- had dropped to almost half what doctors consider the minimum normal level. They weren't low enough for me to be hospitalized for transfusions, fortunately, but they were low enough to earn me daily blood tests just to make sure.</p>
        <p>The virus had inflamed my liver, as well, sending liver enzymes leaking into my bloodstream, another mysterious symptom. For weeks after my fever subsided and my platelets had returned to normal, I was still laid out, lethargic and giddy. My appetite returned slightly, but food and even water tasted strangely unpleasant.</p>
        <p>The good news is that once you get dengue, you have lifelong immunity to that particular strain. The bad news is that, for reasons that remain unclear, those infected by a second strain have a greater chance of developing the more intense, hemorrhagic, version. Researchers say this appears to be because the body overreacts to the second infection, bombarding the virus with weapons designed to kill the first strain. The second strain, unfazed, simply hitches a ride back to camp and wreaks havoc.</p>
        <p>Some scientists believe that many patients who come down with acute dengue are in fact suffering from their second infection. This observation complicates the search for a vaccine. Any vaccine against one strain of dengue has to work against all four, researchers say. Otherwise, it is likely to inoculate patients against one form, only to leave them more vulnerable to a more severe infection by the other three.</p>
        <p>A month of afternoon naps later, I was completely recovered. But I still have to wonder: Was that my first case of dengue? Or could it have been my second?</p>
        <p>If it was my second, I'm in luck: Researchers say immunity to two strains seems to provide protection to the third and fourth. But if this was only my first encounter with dengue, I have to be on the lookout for the next Aedes that buzzes my way.</p>
        <p>CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
