<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russia's Lower House Approves Kyoto Treaty on Emissions</title>
    <meta content="23KYOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/23/international/europe/23kyoto.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1621306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Putin, Vladimir V</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0DC1F3AF930A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russia's Lower House Approves Kyoto Treaty on Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Russia's Lower House Approves Kyoto Treaty on Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russia's lower house of Parliament voted overwhelmingly on Friday to ratify the Kyoto Protocol, setting the stage for enactment early next year of the pioneering international treaty aimed at reducing emissions blamed for global warming.</p>
        <p>The Parliament's vote was widely expected after President Vladimir V. Putin's government endorsed the long-delayed treaty late last month, ending years of internal debate over its potential effects on Russia and its economy. Nevertheless, environmental groups hailed Russia's latest step as a landmark in environmental diplomacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The vote set the stage for enactment of the international treaty aimed at reducing emissions blamed for global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Russia's lower house of Parliament voted overwhelmingly on Friday to ratify the Kyoto Protocol, setting the stage for enactment early next year of the pioneering international treaty aimed at reducing emissions blamed for global warming.</p>
        <p>The Parliament's vote was widely expected after President Vladimir V. Putin's government endorsed the long-delayed treaty late last month, ending years of internal debate over its potential effects on Russia and its economy. Nevertheless, environmental groups hailed Russia's latest step as a landmark in environmental diplomacy.</p>
        <p>''The vote really does change the geopolitical landscape,'' Fred Krupp, the president of Environmental Defense,  said in a telephone interview, expressing hope that it would accelerate efforts by treaty nations to begin reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>Russia's upper house and Mr. Putin still must approve the treaty to make Russia's ratification final, but that is considered a formality at this point. Once the process here is completed and Russia delivers its signed papers to the United Nations, the treaty's provisions aimed at accounting for emissions of gases and reducing their levels are to go into effect within 90 days.</p>
        <p>After the United States, Australia and others rejected the treaty, Russia's ratification became essential. Although 126 nations have already ratified the treaty, it can take effect only if supported by enough nations to represent at least 55 percent of industrialized countries' emissions in 1990. Russia was the only country left that produced enough to clear the threshold.</p>
        <p>In 1990, Russia accounted for 17.4 percent of emissions; the United States accounted for 36.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Leading environmentalists in the United States applauded the Russian decision and used the opportunity to criticize the Bush administration for its refusal to sign the treaty.</p>
        <p>''The Russian government's decision to adopt the Kyoto Protocol leaves the United States alone as the largest and most important industrialized nation to not adopt the treaty,'' said Jeff Fiedler, a policy specialist at the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''Russian ratification means a new market and a new economy has been given the green light, but the U.S. is not following the signal.''</p>
        <p>Philip E. Clapp, president of the National Environmental Trust, said: ''Because of the president's rejection of the agreement, U.S. businesses won't be at the table having input into the details of the emissions reduction system -- and there are billions of dollars at stake here. Regardless of who wins the presidential election, there is going to be enormous new pressure for the U.S. to go back to the negotiating table.''</p>
        <p>Former Vice President Al Gore, who wrote a book on global warming, called the Russian action ''an important and historic victory for sanity, science and reason.''</p>
        <p>He predicted that it would ''unleash a chain reaction of adaptation'' that would eventually include the United States, adding: ''The world faces a climate crisis that will soon be apparent to every person on earth. There is literally no time to lose in taking steps to avoid the worst.''</p>
        <p>The lower house, or Duma, voted 334 to 73 in favor of the protocol after only an afternoon of debate. Although some officials in Russia have vigorously criticized the treaty's limitations, deputies cited the potential boon for Russia from one of its crucial provisions: the trading system that would allow countries that produce excess gases to buy credits from those beneath their quotas or to earn credits by investing in emission-reducing projects.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
