<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making the Mosquito The Victim of a Sting</title>
    <meta content="20HOME$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/20/realestate/20HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1590600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romano, Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD1639F933A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making the Mosquito The Victim of a Sting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making the Mosquito the Victim of a Sting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romano, Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advice on devices to attract and kill mosquitoes; drawing (M)4</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE family's name is Culicidae, and they're a belligerent and sometimes dangerous bunch. If you breathe, sweat or give off body heat, they're likely to be out for your blood. They are, of course, mosquitoes, and besides their annoying bite, they can transmit disease -- malaria, yellow fever, West Nile virus -- in many parts of the world.</p>
        <p>The elements that apparently attract mosquitoes are the basis for several devices designed to dupe and eliminate them. ''Mosquitoes have been around for millions of years,'' said Rick Belmont, vice president for products at Blue Rhino Global Sourcing, the Winston-Salem, N.C., manufacturer of the SkeeterVac, a mosquito eliminator. ''And they've gotten pretty good at finding warm-blooded animals like us.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The elements that apparently attract mosquitoes are the basis for several devices designed to dupe and eliminate them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE family's name is Culicidae, and they're a belligerent and sometimes dangerous bunch. If you breathe, sweat or give off body heat, they're likely to be out for your blood. They are, of course, mosquitoes, and besides their annoying bite, they can transmit disease -- malaria, yellow fever, West Nile virus -- in many parts of the world.</p>
        <p>The elements that apparently attract mosquitoes are the basis for several devices designed to dupe and eliminate them. ''Mosquitoes have been around for millions of years,'' said Rick Belmont, vice president for products at Blue Rhino Global Sourcing, the Winston-Salem, N.C., manufacturer of the SkeeterVac, a mosquito eliminator. ''And they've gotten pretty good at finding warm-blooded animals like us.''</p>
        <p>Female mosquitoes seek warm-blooded animals to get the blood their bodies need to lay eggs, Mr. Belmont said. (Males don't bite.) They find their prey primarily by following a scent trail of carbon dioxide, a byproduct of mammalian breathing. Mosquitoes are also attracted to heat, water vapor, perspiration and other smells.</p>
        <p>The idea was to devise a machine that appears -- to a mosquito, at least -- to be a breathing, sweating mammal. ''We take propane from a standard propane cylinder, run it through a catalytic process in a sealed combustion chamber, and produce a significant amount of carbon dioxide,'' he said. The process also produces heat and water vapor.</p>
        <p>The SkeeterVac also uses octenol, a gas produced by ruminating cows that has an odor mosquitoes like. Once a mosquito finds the SkeeterVac, Mr. Belmont said, the idea is to keep it there. Permanently. On lower-priced models, sticky paper is used. On higher-end models, sticky paper and a vacuum traps the insects. SkeeterVac prices range from $169, for a sticky-paper model that covers a half acre, to $369 for a vacuum unit that produces its own electricity and covers up to 1.2 acres. A 20-pound propane tank (about $20) lasts two to four weeks.</p>
        <p>Another propane-based mosquito elimination system is the the Mosquito Magnet. Raymond Ianetta, president of the American Biophysics Corporation of North Kingstown, R.I., its manufacturer, said the key to mosquito control is catching them after they realize they have been duped. Mr. Ianetta said that the Mosquito Magnet has a vacuum intake port that surrounds a tube through which carbon dioxide and another attractant are emitted. Mosquitoes follow the carbon dioxide trail to the machine and start looking for a meal. ''When a mosquito realizes it isn't going to get a blood meal, it pulls up and starts to fly away,'' he said. ''When the mosquito pulls up, it's flying right into the vacuum.''</p>
        <p>The Mosquito Magnet Defender (about $295) covers about half an acre but must be connected to an electrical outlet. The Liberty Plus ($695) generates its own electrical power and covers about an acre.</p>
        <p>But do the machines really work? ''They are not a silver bullet, but in certain instances, they can be spectacularly successful,'' said Joseph Conlon, technical adviser to the American Mosquito Control Association, a nonprofit educational group, in Eatontown, N.J.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conlon said that it is critical to position the machine according to the manufacturer's recommendations and that it takes at least 21 days to reduce a mosquito population significantly. Traditional approaches, including removing standing water and applying a repellent containing DEET, should also be used, he said.</p>
        <p>''These people are working with sound scientific principles,'' he said. ''This is not fly-by-night stuff.''</p>
        <p>YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
