<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Guilt Trip to Hot Wheels</title>
    <meta content="13CARS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/13/fashion/13CARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1589081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toyota Motor Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DF1230F930A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Guilt Trip to Hot Wheels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Guilt Trip to Hot Wheels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on hybrid Toyota Prius, which uses gasoline engine and battery-powered electric motor, and which has become latest automotive fashion statement; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PARKED side by side on Deb and Jason DeSalvo's driveway in Montclair, N.J., amid the trappings of suburban prosperity like a newly landscaped yard and a kitchen extension, are two virtuous little cars. Once, they were curiosities popular mainly with tree-huggers, but today they are the must-have, can't-get automotive fashion statement all over the country.</p>
        <p>The car on the right is a 2002 Toyota Prius, a hybrid vehicle that seamlessly makes the transition from a gasoline engine to a battery-powered electric motor and thus gets twice the gas mileage of a conventional car. The car on the left is also a Prius, model year 2004, with the same holier-than-thou, anti-S.U.V. philosophy. But the new model has enough sex appeal for Hollywood celebrities, enough trunk space for soccer moms and enough whiz-bang gadgets for somebody who defines success as having more toys than the next guy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2004 Prius could keep its must-have luster longer than usual and be the vehicle that makes hybrid technology mainstream.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PARKED side by side on Deb and Jason DeSalvo's driveway in Montclair, N.J., amid the trappings of suburban prosperity like a newly landscaped yard and a kitchen extension, are two virtuous little cars. Once, they were curiosities popular mainly with tree-huggers, but today they are the must-have, can't-get automotive fashion statement all over the country.</p>
        <p>The car on the right is a 2002 Toyota Prius, a hybrid vehicle that seamlessly makes the transition from a gasoline engine to a battery-powered electric motor and thus gets twice the gas mileage of a conventional car. The car on the left is also a Prius, model year 2004, with the same holier-than-thou, anti-S.U.V. philosophy. But the new model has enough sex appeal for Hollywood celebrities, enough trunk space for soccer moms and enough whiz-bang gadgets for somebody who defines success as having more toys than the next guy.</p>
        <p>''This is a car you have to be an environmentalist to tolerate,'' Mr. DeSalvo said, pointing to the pale aqua first-generation Prius.</p>
        <p>Then he turned to the slate blue 2004 model, recently snatched off eBay for $32,299, or $6,000 over the sticker price, after he had spent six months on a dealer's waiting list and still not received a car. Mr. DeSalvo evangelized over the new Prius, with a sound system that rocks, a hatchback big enough for a trip to the Home Depot and an eye-popping instrument panel that displays real-time gas mileage and shows when the car is running on gas or electricity, or recharging its battery. ''This is a quantum leap forward,'' Mr. DeSalvo said. ''This is a car anybody can love. It has all the benefits of the old one without compromises.''</p>
        <p>The timing could not be better for a hybrid car that asks affluent suburbanites to give up little in the way of creature comforts. In recent months, gas prices have topped $2 a gallon, the war in Iraq has grown ever more worrisome and the dangers of global warming have hit the big screen in ''The Day After Tomorrow.'' Meanwhile, Prius dealers from Westbury on Long Island to Westwood in Los Angeles report ghastly waiting lists. Some buyers complain that price-gouging by dealers has added thousands to the base price of about $21,000 to $26,000. Others happily take cars they've never test-driven, in colors they don't like and with options they don't need.</p>
        <p>The DeSalvos, pioneers when they bought their first Prius in 2001 after reading about it in a Sierra Club magazine, are no longer the geeky couple with the weird car. He has converted several business colleagues and she several friends. Mr. DeSalvo's brother has a Prius. So does Mrs. DeSalvo's father. Their contractor's son bought their original car. If the 2004 model they ordered from the dealer ever arrives, Mr. DeSalvo intends to sell it at a profit to one of the thousands of would-be Prius owners who post desperate messages in automotive chat rooms and at online car-buying sites.</p>
        <p>Hot cars, waiting lists as long as two years and price-gouging by dealers are nothing new for an industry bent on fanning consumer cravings. Commonly, analysts say, the buzz lasts about six months before production meets or exceeds demand. Then, as with the PT Cruiser, a car that has been impossible to buy without payment of a buyer's premium, becomes impossible to sell without dealer incentives.</p>
        <p>But dispassionate analysts suspect that the 2004 Prius could keep its must-have luster longer than usual and be the vehicle that takes hybrid technology mainstream. Brian Moody, the road test editor for Edmunds.com, a car buyers' Web site, is one of several experts to guess that thanks to the new Prius, within five years virtually every car model made will have a hybrid version.</p>
        <p>''This could be the car that makes it the norm, not so out-there,'' Mr. Moody said.</p>
        <p>Another family of early adapters, Nonie and Chris Reich of Purchase, N.Y., are finally seeing some interest among their social set. With Toyota reporting a backlog of 22,000 orders in the United States for Priuses, anyone driving one already possesses an instant status symbol -- one that satisfies Americans' thirst to be the first on the block with something new and their sometimes contradictory desire to do the right thing.</p>
        <p>Like the DeSalvos, the Reichs have a pair of Priuses, which they use to shuttle back and forth between their four-acre spread with a swimming pool (unheated) that is being renovated and a temporary rental apartment in nearby Greenwich, Conn. The Reichs also have put their names on a waiting list for a hybrid Lexus S.U.V., which, along with the hybrid Toyota Highlander, will make its debut next year. When the Reichs signed up in early February, they were No. 60 on the list.</p>
        <p>At the Wall Street investment bank where Mr. Reich works, his colleagues pay attention when he talks about getting 41 miles per gallon with the air-conditioning blasting, versus 17 in the lumbering Chrysler Town &amp; Country minivan the family last drove. In the carpool line at her children's private school, where the other mothers drive Hummers or Mercedes wagons, Mrs. Reich can now boast that her new Prius has enough room for furniture, a litter of eight Labrador puppies or her son's sports equipment.</p>
        <p>''This car makes it very easy to do the right thing,'' Mrs. Reich said. ''There's zero sacrifice.''</p>
        <p>Since the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, Mrs. Reich said, she has been thinking more deeply about the links between oil and foreign policy, and between consumerism and global warming. But she said she tries ''not to get on my high horse and instead use a sense of humor'' when lobbying friends and relatives. On the windshield of her car, for example, there is a laminated cartoon from The New Yorker: a hybrid driver explaining that ''it runs on its conventional gasoline-powered engine until it senses guilt, at which point it switches over to battery power.''</p>
        <p>You had to be a pretty staunch environmentalist to buy the early Prius, which had a cramped trunk and a ho-hum sound system. Its sales were modest: the 2002 model never sold more than 2,000 cars a month, barely 1 percent of the market for compact cars. By contrast, the spiffier 2004 model, seen on HBO's ''Curb Your Enthusiasm'' and outside Hollywood Oscar parties in February, burst from the gates last fall with monthly sales as high as 5,000 and a market share as high as 3 percent among comparable small sedans.</p>
        <p>''It's a real car,'' said Dr. G. Clotaire Rapaille, an anthropologist whose company, Archetype Discoveries Worldwide in Boca Raton, Fla., searches the souls of consumers to learn why they chose one product over another.</p>
        <p>The 2004 Prius, this year's Motor Trend Car of the Year, satisfies Americans' need to make a personal statement, Dr. Rapaille said -- in this case, ''I'm more intelligent than the next guy.'' It also satisfies the love of breakthrough technology and comfort. All that's missing, Dr. Rapaille said, is a distinctive shape recognizable from a mile away, like the PT Cruiser's or the Mini Cooper's.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rapaille doubts that hybrids will command a wide audience merely because of gas mileage, since people buy cars using primitive reasoning, with ''their reptilian brains, not their cerebral cortex.'' But even cerebral types would be hard-pressed to justify waiting months for a Prius, or paying $5,000 over its sticker price.</p>
        <p>A few facts: A Prius, on average, costs about $10,000 more than a nonhybrid Toyota Corolla and saves perhaps $200 a year in gas over the Corolla, according to Art Spinella, an auto industry analyst at CNW Marketing Research in Bandon, Ore.</p>
        <p>Overall, comparable nonhybrid sedans use $1,074 worth of gas a year, at $2 a gallon, versus $623 for the new Prius, according to Edmunds.com. In prosperous suburban communities, that $451 is hardly life-changing.</p>
        <p>But that does not stop Prius owners from wanting to know how much gas they are using every second. Jason DeSalvo, who cares more about smog and greenhouse emissions than about gas prices, still knows that when he drives to work with a tail wind he gets 64 miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>Barbara Dannenbring, who says ''cars are not my thing'' and has yet to read her owner's manual, laughs merrily as she drives the hilly terrain near her home in Dobbs Ferry, N.Y. As she coasts on a steep hill, the dashboard bar graph announces that she is getting 100 miles to the gallon. As the road levels, the graph inches to 67.6. ''Well, that didn't last long,'' Mrs. Dannenbring said. ''But it sure was fun while it did.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
