<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida's Luck Runs Out With 2 Hits in One Month</title>
    <meta content="05HURR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/05/national/05hurricane.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1609347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HURRICANE FRANCES: METEOROLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Andrew (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charley (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frances (Storm)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D61131F936A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida's Luck Runs Out With 2 Hits in One Month</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Climate, and Bad Luck, Favor Hurricanes in Florida</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses formation, naming, path and frequency of hurricanes and tropical storms; Florida was spared major hurricanes from 1968 to 2003, with notable exception of Andrew in 1992, but new active era for hurricanes began with natural oscillation in ocean temperatures in 1995; this year's double strike, with Hurricanes Charley and Frances coming within one month of each other, is unlucky, but within natural variation in trends of storms; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Battered on the west three weeks ago by Hurricane Charley and being battered this weekend on the east by Hurricane Frances, Florida is a victim of a climate currently favorable for hurricanes and of simple bad luck.</p>
        <p>In 1995, after three relatively unstormy decades, a naturally occurring oscillation in the Atlantic Ocean started a new active era for hurricanes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1995, after three relatively unstormy decades, a naturally occurring oscillation in the Atlantic Ocean started a new active era for hurricanes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Battered on the west three weeks ago by Hurricane Charley and being battered this weekend on the east by Hurricane Frances, Florida is a victim of a climate currently favorable for hurricanes and of simple bad luck.</p>
        <p>In 1995, after three relatively unstormy decades, a naturally occurring oscillation in the Atlantic Ocean started a new active era for hurricanes.</p>
        <p>''The number of major hurricanes went up by a factor of two and a half,'' said Stanley B. Goldenberg, a meteorologist with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's hurricane research division in Miami. ''You have a lot of arrows, and you have a lot of targets.''</p>
        <p>Some hurricane targets like the Caribbean have been hit several times since then. ''They've been pounded,'' Mr. Goldenberg said. ''They know we've had an increase.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldenberg and other hurricane experts said Florida and other parts of the United States were fortunate that more disastrous storms had not struck in recent years. Of the 35 major hurricanes -- Category 3 or stronger, with sustained winds of more than 111 miles per hour -- that have formed in the Atlantic since August 1995, only four, or less than one in eight, have hit the United States as major hurricanes. Historically, the odds have been one in three.</p>
        <p>That means most of Florida has been unscathed since the 1960's, when the last active era of hurricanes ended. In the 38 years from 1966 through 2003, only one major hurricane, Andrew in 1992, struck southern Florida. In the preceding active period, the 40 years from 1926 to 1965, the region was hit 14 times.</p>
        <p>''I view this year as very unlucky for Florida,'' said Dr. William Gray, a professor of atmospheric science at Colorado State University who forecasts the hurricane season, ''but this is within the natural variation of storms.''</p>
        <p>Each year, between August and November, about 60 low-pressure systems form off the western coast of Africa and waft westward. Warm waters and favorable winds turn some of them into tropical storms; others dissipate and disappear.</p>
        <p>Tropical storms acquire names when sustained winds exceed 39 miles per hour; hurricanes are Atlantic tropical storms with winds of at least 74 miles per hour. An average hurricane season has 9.6 named storms, of which 5.9 become hurricanes and 2.3 of them turn into major hurricanes.</p>
        <p>But this year, eight named storms formed during August alone -- a record. On Friday, he increased his forecast for this year's season to 16 named tropical storms (up from 13), 8 hurricanes (up from 7) and 5 major hurricanes (up from 3).</p>
        <p>He predicts that September will remain active, but that hurricane activity will tail off in October, because of warm water in the central tropical Pacific, possibly the beginnings of an El Niño climate pattern, which tends to suppress storms in the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray, Mr. Goldenberg and other scientists reported in 2001 that the severity of a hurricane season correlated strongly with a decades-long cycle of ocean temperatures in the Atlantic. When waters in the North Atlantic are cooler, wind shear, which tears storms apart, is stronger, suppressing hurricanes.</p>
        <p>Global warming is not a significant factor in this year's storminess, experts said. While some climate models predict that warming might eventually mean somewhat stronger hurricanes, that effect is expected to be very small compared to the natural hurricane cycle.</p>
        <p>Where a hurricane goes depends on the surrounding meteorological conditions. As they spin like tops across the Atlantic, some barrel straight west, into Central America or Mexico. Others, after passing a semipermanent high-pressure system that sits over Bermuda in the summer, take a sharp right to the north, missing land entirely. And some veer into the United States.</p>
        <p>Although the number of hurricanes has been up for years, most have either headed straight west, like Hurricane Mitch in 1998, which killed 10,000 people in Honduras and Nicaragua, or turned north, harmlessly.</p>
        <p>When Hurricane Charley formed in August, the high-altitude winds known as the jet stream, which usually blow near the American-Canadian border, had dipped much farther south. That created a low-pressure system over the western Gulf of Mexico, so Hurricane Charley, instead of continuing westward, was steered to the northeast, into Florida.</p>
        <p>This time, with Hurricane Frances, the Bermuda high has stretched westward for most of the past week almost to Tennessee. That prevented the storm from turning northward.</p>
        <p>Because the active hurricane pattern for the Atlantic will most likely continue for decades longer, Mr. Goldenberg said disaster planners need to prepare for years like 2004.</p>
        <p>''This is not just a spike,'' Mr. Goldenberg said. ''This is a taste of what we still have to come.''</p>
        <p>HURRICANE FRANCES: METEOROLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
