<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kerry Pitches Energy Plan in Missouri</title>
    <meta content="06KERR$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/06/politics/campaign/06kerry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040818T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1602023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE MASSACHUSETTS SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1D9123CF935A3575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kerry Pitches Energy Plan in Missouri</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kerry, Touring Missouri, Pitches 'Energy Independence' Plan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER and NEELA BANERJEE; David M. Halbfinger reported from Jefferson City for this article, and Neela Banerjee from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela; Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>JEFFERSON CITY, Mo., Aug. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry whistle-stops across Missouri by locomotive, unveiling plan for energy independence; promises to make nation's security 'depend on America's ingenuity and creativity,' rather than on foreign oil; outlines broad strategy for promoting alternative and renewable fuels; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day when oil prices reached a record high, Senator John Kerry issued a plan for energy independence on Thursday as he whistle-stopped across Missouri, promising to make the nation's security ''depend on America's ingenuity and creativity, not the Saudi royal family.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Kerry left his motorcade of some 20 cars in St. Louis and boarded a diesel-powered locomotive, his aides unveiled a plan that they said would lower energy bills for consumers and re-establish the nation's leadership in developing renewable energy sources.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day when oil prices reached a record high, John Kerry issued a new plan for energy independence as he whistle-stopped across Missouri on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day when oil prices reached a record high, Senator John Kerry issued a plan for energy independence on Thursday as he whistle-stopped across Missouri, promising to make the nation's security ''depend on America's ingenuity and creativity, not the Saudi royal family.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Kerry left his motorcade of some 20 cars in St. Louis and boarded a diesel-powered locomotive, his aides unveiled a plan that they said would lower energy bills for consumers and re-establish the nation's leadership in developing renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Among Mr. Kerry's new initiatives are a $5,000 consumer incentive to buy so-called clean-energy vehicles, incentives to manufacturers to retool their plants to use clean fuels, and a ''clean fuels partnership'' linking agriculture, industry and government with the goal of meeting 20 percent of the nation's demand for motor fuels with alternatives like ethanol, biodiesel and, eventually, hydrogen. He is also calling for national reliability standards and upgraded technologies, which he calls a ''smart grid,'' to prevent blackouts.</p>
        <p>''We are going to reach for alternative and renewable fuels,'' Mr. Kerry said to tremendous applause in St. Louis on Thursday. ''We are going to reach for energy independence. We are going to create the jobs of the future, because I want America's security to depend on America's ingenuity and creativity, not the Saudi royal family.''</p>
        <p>Crude oil prices closed at a record high of $44.41 a barrel on the New York Mercantile Exchange on Thursday. Gasoline prices have hovered around $2 a gallon in most of the country all summer, and last week the government reported that the economy had grown at a slower rate than expected in the second quarter, in part because of high energy prices.</p>
        <p>''The truth is, it's not just hurting consumers,'' said Sarah Bianchi, Mr. Kerry's national policy director, ''but investors and the economy over all.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry's railroad tour, which ends Monday in Kingman, Ariz., began after he detoured to Washington by airplane to address a national convention of minority journalists, where he was asked what would he have done had he been president on Sept. 11, 2001, if he was reading a story to a group of schoolchildren when an aide told him that the United States was under attack.</p>
        <p>''I would have told those kids, very politely and nicely,'' Mr. Kerry said, ''that the president of the United States had something that he needed to attend to.''</p>
        <p>This was no hypothetical, of course: one of the most searing scenes in Michael Moore's polemical film ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' shows President Bush continuing to read a story to a class of Florida youngsters for seven minutes after his chief of staff informed him of the attacks.</p>
        <p>Also at the journalists' conference, which Mr. Bush is to address on Friday, Mr. Kerry was asked if he thought the comedian Bill Cosby was right in saying recently that African-Americans should take responsibility for their own economic status, incarceration rate and educational shortcomings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry seemed slightly thrown by the question. After saying that ''all of us are responsible,'' he proceeded to suggest that Mr. Bush was more responsible than others, because public schools in black neighborhoods rely largely on property taxes, and because ''the great ethic of the politics of our nation'' is to cut taxes and spending, and ''because it's more important to get a tax cut to people earning more than $200,000 a year.''</p>
        <p>From Washington, Mr. Kerry flew to St. Louis to meet with his running mate, Senator John Edwards, and board a train for a whistle-stop tour through Missouri, Kansas and the Rockies that winds up in Arizona on Monday.</p>
        <p>In St. Louis, Mr. Kerry and Mr. Edwards addressed thousands under the railroad shed of the old Union Station. ''I want to talk to the Show-Me State,'' Mr. Kerry shouted, ''and I want to show you, as John has shown you, that we can make a better set of choices that lift this country up. The middle class of the United States of America is playing by the rules. People are working two jobs, three jobs, and they're still not getting ahead.</p>
        <p>''I'm running for president because the middle class deserves a champion, and the people struggling to get in deserve one,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry threw some red meat to the partisans in St. Louis, including Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the onetime vice-presidential prospect whose introduction was cut short when loudspeakers started blasting music heralding the approach of Mr. Kerry's bus.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing conservative about a certain attorney general from somewhere,'' Mr. Kerry said, referring to Missouri's own John Ashcroft, ''who silences the civil rights and civil liberties of Americans.''</p>
        <p>From St. Louis, Mr. Kerry's group boarded a special 15-car train -- including cars reserved for the Secret Service, an observation deck for journalists, and a Pullman coach built in 1914 that had been used by Presidents Bill Clinton, Jimmy Carter, Lyndon B. Johnson and Harry S. Truman.</p>
        <p>But in a sign of how closely fought the presidential race will be in Missouri, the sights and sounds along the route's first leg included plenty of chants of ''four more years'' and Bush-Cheney signs in and among the cries of ''three more months'' and ''hope is on the way'' placards.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Mo., after her husband had finished a shortened stump speech from the train's rear platform and giddily blown the train whistle four times, Teresa Heinz Kerry gave a taste of her alternately sharp and warm-and-fuzzy touch.</p>
        <p>''You cannot solve problems by throwing stones,'' she said. ''And you cannot solve problems by telling lies. And you cannot solve problems by wishing ill to other people. The only way you solve problems is by holding hands and talking about it. And that's what we want to do in this campaign.''</p>
        <p>Here in Jefferson City, about 5,000 people waited hours at the State Capitol for the Democrats to arrive. Luana Gifford said she had skipped her own birthday party, though she declined to say which one.</p>
        <p>''This will be so much more exciting than my party would ever be,'' she said. ''For my present this year I don't want diamonds, I want John Kerry to be president.''</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE MASSACHUSETTS SENATOR</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 18, 2004, Wednesday  An article on Aug. 7 about a speech by President Bush to a convention of minority journalists referred incorrectly to a scene in the movie ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' that Senator John Kerry cited when he spoke to the journalists and criticized the president's handling of the attacks on Sept. 11, 2001. The movie shows Mr. Bush, having learned of the attacks, continuing to listen to schoolchildren read a book with their teacher; it does not show the president reading to them. (The error also appeared in an article on Aug. 6 about a campaign appearance by Mr. Kerry in which he questioned the president's leadership on Sept. 11.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 18, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Aug. 7 about a speech by President Bush to a convention of minority journalists referred incorrectly to a scene in the movie ''Fahrenheit 9/11'' that Senator John Kerry cited when he spoke to the journalists and criticized the president's handling of the attacks on Sept. 11, 2001. The movie shows Mr. Bush, having learned of the attacks, continuing to listen to schoolchildren read a book with their teacher; it does not show the president reading to them. (The error also appeared in an article on Aug. 6 about a campaign appearance by Mr. Kerry in which he questioned the president's leadership on Sept. 11.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
