<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="01BIZD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1615547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D61238F932A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Justice Department Is Said To Start Fannie Mae Inquiry  The Justice Department has started a criminal investigation of Fannie Mae, the nation's largest mortgage buyer, in response to a federal report accusing executives at the company of sloppy accounting practices, said an official who has been briefed on the matter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Justice Department Is Said To Start Fannie Mae Inquiry  The Justice Department has started a criminal investigation of Fannie Mae, the nation's largest mortgage buyer, in response to a federal report accusing executives at the company of sloppy accounting practices, said an official who has been briefed on the matter.</p>
        <p>Because of the findings in the federal report, by the Office of Federal Housing Enterprise Oversight, the Justice Department decided to open the inquiry, the government official said. The latest inquiry follows one started earlier by the Securities and Exchange Commission. [Page C3.]</p>
        <p>Russia Endorses Emissions Treaty  The long-delayed Kyoto Protocol on global warming overcame its last critical hurdle to taking effect around the world when Russia's cabinet endorsed the treaty and sent it to Parliament. [A1.]</p>
        <p>No Agreement in Subsidy Dispute  Top trade officials for the United States and the European Union failed to resolve their dispute over government subsidies to aircraft manufacturers, especially Airbus and Boeing, inching closer to a clash before the World Trade Organization. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Ahold Says It Misused Documents  The Dutch food retailer Royal Ahold admitted that it had improperly used documents in the reporting of its results and agreed to pay $9.9 million to avoid criminal prosecution, even as its former chief executive dismissed charges he had done anything improper or illegal. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>California Drug Bill Is Vetoed  Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger vetoed several bills that would have made California the middleman in large-scale consumer purchases of prescription drugs from Canada. [A12.]</p>
        <p>Closing of Loan Loophole Urged  The secretary of education called on members of Congress to close a loophole that has allowed student loan companies to collect more than a billion dollars in excess federal subsidies, saying he lacked the authority to stop the escalating payments anytime soon. [A14.]</p>
        <p>Circuit City Tries New Advertising  Circuit City is trying an image makeover centered on the rock tune ''Just What I Needed.'' Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Dow Jones Average Declines  The Dow Jones industrial average fell 55.97 points, or 0.6 percent, to 10,080.27, weighed down by Merck &amp; Company. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index was down 0.22, or 0.02 percent, at 1,114.58, and the Nasdaq index gained 2.90, or 0.2 percent, to 1,896.84. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Spending Stalls as Income Rises  Consumer spending stalled and personal income rose in August, according to government reports. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft Asks Europe for Delay  Microsoft, seeking to stave off legal sanctions, warned a European appeals court that software developers and consumers would face dire consequences should the company be penalized. Speaking at the start of a hearing before the European Court of First Instance, Microsoft's general counsel, Brad Smith, asked the court to delay until the end of the appeals process moves aimed at forcing the company to change its practices. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Raymond James Financial Is Sued  Raymond James Financial Services Inc., its former president and a former branch manager have been sued by the Securities and Exchange Commission for failing to supervise a broker accused of defrauding investors, the agency announced. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
