<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kerry Criticizes U.S. Plan to Send Nuclear Waste to Nevada</title>
    <meta content="11KERR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/11/politics/campaign/11kerry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1603238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Las Vegas (Nev)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yucca Mountain (Nev)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada/Las Vegas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Nevada</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5DA1F3CF932A2575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kerry Criticizes U.S. Plan to Send Nuclear Waste to Nevada</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kerry Criticizes U.S. Plan to Send Nuclear Waste to Nevada</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS, Aug. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry, campaigning in Las Vegas, vows not to send nuclear waste to Yucca Mountain, Nev, and charges Pres Bush broke similar promise he made four years ago; Bush campaign, showing its awareness of issue's importance in state, circulates memos scouring Kerry's record to show votes that could be construed as supporting Yucca Mountain storage; Republicans note Sen John Edwards backed storage before joining ticket; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seizing on an issue that this state's Democratic senator calls ''the most important to the people of Nevada,'' Senator John Kerry vowed Tuesday not to send nuclear waste to Yucca Mountain and accused President Bush of breaking a similar promise he made four years ago.</p>
        <p>In a state that Mr. Bush won by four percentage points in 2000, Mr. Kerry, the Democratic presidential nominee, hammered at the administration's support for the nuclear waste repository at Yucca Mountain, 100 miles northwest of Las Vegas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry vowed Tuesday not to send nuclear waste to Yucca Mountain and accused President Bush of breaking a similar promise he made four years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seizing on an issue that this state's Democratic senator calls ''the most important to the people of Nevada,'' Senator John Kerry vowed Tuesday not to send nuclear waste to Yucca Mountain and accused President Bush of breaking a similar promise he made four years ago.</p>
        <p>In a state that Mr. Bush won by four percentage points in 2000, Mr. Kerry, the Democratic presidential nominee, hammered at the administration's support for the nuclear waste repository at Yucca Mountain, 100 miles northwest of Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>''Yucca Mountain to me is a symbol of the recklessness and arrogance with which they are willing to proceed with respect to the safety issues and concerns of the American people,'' Mr. Kerry said of the administration.</p>
        <p>''This is not just a Nevada issue; this is not just about Yucca Mountain,'' he told a small crowd of invited guests at a middle school here. ''This is about America. This is about a relationship between the people who lead and the people, you, the governed. It's about promises kept and promises broken.''</p>
        <p>In 2000, Mr. Bush followed his opponent, Vice President Al Gore, in promising to veto plans to store high-level nuclear waste at the mountain, saying in late September that he would not send waste to any site unless it was proved safe scientifically. Once in office, amid scientific debate over safety, Mr. Bush accepted an Energy Department recommendation to approve the storage site.</p>
        <p>Showing its own awareness of the issue's importance in the state, the Bush campaign circulated memorandums on Tuesday scouring Mr. Kerry's Senate record to show six instances over a decade in which he cast votes that could be construed as supporting storage at Yucca Mountain. Republicans also noted that Mr. Kerry's running mate, Senator John Edwards of North Carolina, backed storage at the Nevada site before joining the ticket.</p>
        <p>''The Kerry-Edwards ticket was for Yucca Mountain before they were against it, and Nevadans should not be fooled by election-year pandering,'' Nevada's Republican senator, John Ensign, said in a statement circulated by the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ensign himself, when pressed on a cable television program last week, said of Mr. Kerry that ''on this one issue he's been better than George Bush, but that's on one issue.'' And campaigning alongside Mr. Kerry on Tuesday was Mr. Ensign's Democratic counterpart, Senator Harry Reid, who dismissed the votes cited by the Republicans, saying, ''John Kerry has been with us every time we've needed him. ''</p>
        <p>The daylong focus on the storage plan, which is currently stalled in the courts, signals the power to frame the political fight of swing states like Nevada, whose swelling population has increased its value to five electoral votes, from four.</p>
        <p>At an evening rally that drew more than 10,000 people to the University of Nevada-Las Vegas basektball arena, Mr. Kerry declared firmly, "When I'm President of the United States, I'll tell you about Yucca Mountain: Not on my watch! No!" To loud cheers, he added with a flourish that if Congress tried to change environmental standards to overcome legal obstacles, "Veto pen, gone, out!"</p>
        <p>Several recent polls here have shown the race in the state to be in a virtual dead heat. In 2000, polls showed that Mr. Gore overtook Mr. Bush in Nevada after opposing Yucca Mountain and then lost the edge when Mr. Bush echoed the opposition.</p>
        <p>The debate over Yucca Mountain stretches back two decades, and has captured attention in part because some 100,000 shipments of waste would have to be trucked across 44 states to get to the facility, in some cases skirting homes and schools. Congress picked Yucca as a national repository for high-level waste in 1987, but a federal court this summer dealt the plan a major setback, saying it could not proceed because the government lacked standards to prevent leaks after 10,000 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry and Mr. Reid said that instead of storing waste at Yucca they would keep it at the nation's 100-plus nuclear reactors. Mr. Kerry also invoked the legacy of Roosevelt and Truman's leadership supporting the invention of the atomic bomb, saying, ''what we need now is the reverse of that: we need a Manhattan Project that learns how to tame the negative consequences of that power of the atom.''</p>
        <p>In a 45-minute give-and-take in which he uncharacteristically read from notes, fumbling somewhat with statistics and quotations from government studies, Mr. Kerry sought to broaden the seemingly parochial issue into a symbol of differences between himself and Mr. Bush on the environment and science, two mainstays of his campaign.</p>
        <p>''The United States of America deserves a president of the United States who believes in science,'' he said. ''It's not just the science of Yucca Mountain, it's the science of global warming. It's the science of stem cell research and the possibilities of the future; it's the science of clean air and clean water.''</p>
        <p>Steve Schmidt, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, said Tuesday that Mr. Bush had based his decision on Yucca mountain on ''sound science,'' as he had promised to do in 2000.</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Edwards's support for storage at Yucca Mountain, Mr. Reid said Mr. Edwards had called him after being tapped by Mr. Kerry and said he was now ''on the Yucca Mountain bandwagon.''</p>
        <p>Mark Kornblau, Mr. Edwards's spokesman said: ''John Kerry has very clearly stated that his administration will oppose the storage of dangerous nuclear waste at Yucca Mountain and John Edwards is very comfortable with that policy.''</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
