<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="18OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1582506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">European Southern Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stone Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beryllium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flounder (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Proteins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trout</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frogs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Nevadas (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California (Berkeley)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vrendenburg, Vance T (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Proteins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFD8143FF93BA25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>German and Austrian astronomers, along with European Southern Observatory, Chile, observe supersized protostar that is 250 times size of solar system; discovery, which is published in journal Nature, dispels theory that protostars cannot be larger than 10 solar masses; protostar is 5,000 light-years away and could measure 120 solar masses before it finishes growing; scientists from Israel, Switzerland and Italy study whether Stone Age man mined flint or collected it from surface; study, published in Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences, measures beryllium concentration in flint; researchers have found some evidence of Stone Age mining; Canadian researchers pinpoint second protein in winter flounder, fish found in cold waters, that works as antifreeze for blood; findings are published in journal Nature; Dr Vance T Vrendenburg of University of California, Berkeley, Museum of Vertebrate Zoology identifies reason for decline of frogs in Sierra Nevadas; study, published in Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences, finds that trout, stocked in regional lakes over last century, are eating tadpoles as soon as they hatch; there is worldwide decline in frogs; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists Spy a Hungry Star</p>
        <p>Like babies and parking meters, young stars need constant feeding. The protostar that forms from the collapse of a cold, dense clump of dust and gas has a voracious appetite. In its formative years, it spends all its time sucking up material from the disk of gas and dust around it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists Spy a Hungry Star</p>
        <p>Like babies and parking meters, young stars need constant feeding. The protostar that forms from the collapse of a cold, dense clump of dust and gas has a voracious appetite. In its formative years, it spends all its time sucking up material from the disk of gas and dust around it.</p>
        <p>But at some point this gas bag grows big enough, and hot enough, for nuclear fusion to begin. This creates outward radiation pressure (a solar wind) that effectively stops the accretion of more gas and dust.</p>
        <p>Scientists have calculated that in theory at least, radiation pressure should prevent the formation of stars bigger than about 10 solar masses, or 10 times the size of the sun. Any bigger star (and there are plenty) must be formed through the merging of smaller ones.</p>
        <p>That theory may now be out the window. Astronomers from Germany, Austria and the European Southern Observatory in Chile have spotted a protostar that is already on the order of 20 solar masses and is showing no signs of finishing its meal. Their research is reported in the current issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The object is in the Omega nebula, about 5,000 light-years away. The disk of gas and dust surrounding it is supersized, 250 times the size of the solar system and by far the largest such disk ever seen.</p>
        <p>The scientists estimate that the disk contains another 100 solar masses worth of gas, so the star has the potential to grow a lot more.</p>
        <p>Now, That's Good Flint</p>
        <p>To do good work, any carpenter will tell you, you need good tools. That is true in this era of laser measuring tapes and power miter saws, but it was also true in the Stone Age, when scrapers, knives and other tools were made from flint. The best flint comes from underground -- it is harder and more durable than surface-gathered rock.</p>
        <p>A team of scientists from Israel, Switzerland and Italy has now come up with a way to analyze Stone Age flint to see whether the early people who used it collected it from the surface, or had developed the ability to mine it. The key, they write in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, is measuring the concentration of a certain isotope of beryllium in the rock.</p>
        <p>The isotope is produced through the bombardment of Earth by cosmic rays. The effect is greater on the surface; flint extracted from a depth of three feet or more has a lower concentration of the isotope.</p>
        <p>The researchers studied flint artifacts from two sites in Israel, both dating from about 350,000 to 200,000 years ago. At one site, the flint had beryllium isotope concentrations indicating the stone was collected from the surface or, at best, shallow quarries. At the other, the concentrations were such that it seems certain the rock was mined. The researchers say their technique should be applicable to other rock types.</p>
        <p>An Answer in a Cold Case</p>
        <p>Fish that live in extremely cold conditions have proteins in the blood that function like antifreeze in a car: they lower the freezing point of the body below that of seawater (about 28.5 degrees Fahrenheit).</p>
        <p>But the winter flounder, a bottom-dwelling fish found as far north as the Arctic, has been a puzzling case. An antifreeze protein was identified several decades ago, but it offers only a certain amount of protection -- down to about 29.3 degrees.</p>
        <p>Now, Canadian researchers have identified another antifreeze protein in the fish that accounts for the extra protection. The protein, which they describe in Nature, is much more active than the first -- meaning that only very small amounts of it are needed -- and on a par with antifreeze proteins found in some insects (which have to survive even colder temperatures). The small amounts required are probably one reason the protein was never identified before, the researchers say.</p>
        <p>Frogs and Fish: Not the Best of Friends</p>
        <p>The worldwide decline in frogs and other amphibians has been well documented, though the reasons for it are less clear. Scientists have suggested many possible factors, including climate change, disease and increased exposure to ultraviolet radiation and pesticides.</p>
        <p>But for some species, a major reason could simply be that they are being eaten -- by predators introduced into their habitat. A researcher at the University of California at Berkeley has shown this to be the case for a frog in the Sierra Nevadas. The researcher, Dr. Vance T. Vredenburg of the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology at the university, demonstrated that rainbow and brook trout, introduced over the last century for sport fishing, are largely responsible for the decline of the mountain yellow-legged frog. He reported the finding in the current issue of The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Vredenburg wanted to show the effects of the fish without harming more frogs, which exist almost exclusively in declining populations in California mountains. ''I had two choices,'' he said. ''One was to actually introduce fish into a frog lake and watch what happens. But I couldn't do that in any conscionable manner.''</p>
        <p>Instead, Dr. Vredenburg studied what occurs when the trout are removed. Beginning in 1997, he laboriously removed the fish from five lakes in a remote region of Kings Canyon National Park in the central Sierra Nevada. In a year or two, Dr. Vredenburg found signs that frogs were returning.</p>
        <p>To determine exactly how the fish affect the frogs, he conducted another experiment, placing a few rainbow trout in small cages in the lake and introducing some frog eggs. The trout, he found, ate the tadpoles emerging from the eggs. ''The fish would sit there and pick them off one by one,'' he said. Taken together, Dr. Vredenburg said, the two findings provide strong direct evidence of the trout's role. ''The fish in this case obviously are a major player in the decline of this frog,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The solution is easy. If you want to restore the frog, just remove the fish, which the National Park Service has begun to do. ''The most exciting thing about this,'' Dr. Vredenburg said, ''is that this is one study of frog decline where we can actually do something about it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
