<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unlike Leopards, Jupiter Finds a Way to Change Its Spots</title>
    <meta content="27JUPI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/27/science/space/27JUPI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1577243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voyager Project</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Anticyclones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California (Berkeley)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marcus, Philip (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jupiter (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7D7103AF934A15757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unlike Leopards, Jupiter Finds a Way to Change Its Spots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unlike Leopards, Jupiter Finds a Way to Change Its Spots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH CHANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Kenneth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Philip Marcus, University of California, Berkeley, mechanical engineering professor, predicts that some of Jupiter's spots, widely regarded as anticyclones, will disappear over next few years due to climate change; NASA's Voyager spacecraft counted almost 100 anticyclones during 1979 mission; in 1998, White Ovals, three large anticyclones, merged first into two storms and then into one; simulations of anticyclones, jet stream factors and historic events support Marcus' theory that anticyclones will continue to merge, particularly in southern hemisphere of Jupiter; findings are published in journal Nature; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jupiter, it seems, is about to lose some of its characteristic spots. And the reason will be familiar to readers on Earth -- climate change.</p>
        <p>The spots, many of them easily seen from Earth-based telescopes, are caused by vast long-lived storms that roil the Jovian atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jupiter, it seems, is about to lose some of its characteristic spots. And the reason will be familiar to readers on Earth  climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jupiter, it seems, is about to lose some of its characteristic spots. And the reason will be familiar to readers on Earth -- climate change.</p>
        <p>The spots, many of them easily seen from Earth-based telescopes, are caused by vast long-lived storms that roil the Jovian atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Over the next few years, a scientist at the University of California at Berkeley predicted last week, those storms will shift. Then Jupiter's climate will spawn a new generation of storms.</p>
        <p>But the scientist, Dr. Philip S. Marcus, a professor of mechanical engineering, said the biggest storm, the Great Red Spot, would persist unaffected.</p>
        <p>Writing in the current issue of the journal Nature, Dr. Marcus said computer simulations indicated that storms grew, then merged and ebbed at the end of the current climate cycle of 60 to 70 years.</p>
        <p>Jupiter's atmosphere consists of about 12 jet streams alternately blowing east and west, producing its stripes. The visible storms like the Great Red Spot are high-pressure regions known as anticyclones, unlike hurricanes on Earth, which are pockets of low-pressure air.</p>
        <p>Anticyclones rotate clockwise in the northern hemisphere and counterclockwise in the southern hemisphere.</p>
        <p>What is puzzling is that a series of storms tends to exist along the same latitude -- ''They come in rows,'' Dr. Marcus said -- and that the storms last for decades.</p>
        <p>But not forever.</p>
        <p>In early 1998, three large anticyclones known as the White Ovals that were first spotted in 1939 suddenly became the two White Ovals. Two years later, the two became one.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcus said he had been trying to explain the long-lived anticyclones since NASA's Voyager 1 spacecraft counted about 100 of them as it flew by in 1979.</p>
        <p>''Every time I tried to simulate them, they failed miserably,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the simulations, when the storms approached one another, the ''vortices would quickly merge together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I had a problem with this,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The newest simulations provide an answer to that problem. For every two anticyclones, he said, there is a cyclone rotating in the opposite direction, wedged between them in the neighboring jet stream.</p>
        <p>''That's an incredibly stable configuration,'' Dr. Marcus said. ''If they approach, they repel each other just marvelously.''</p>
        <p>Astronomers have long debated whether such long-lived cyclones exist, because they are not clearly seen in the photographs. In anticyclones, Dr. Marcus said, air rises and cools at the center, making ice crystals that delineate the spiral structure. In cyclones, the center is warm air, producing wispy filamentary clouds.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter J. Gierasch, a professor of astronomy at Cornell, said that he found Dr. Marcus's simulations convincing for the existence of cyclones, but that he was reserving judgment on the forecast of merging storms.</p>
        <p>In Dr. Marcus's simulations, the cyclones weaken, eventually allowing the anticyclones to merge, as the White Ovals did. That, in turn, reduces the mixing of air in Jupiter's atmosphere, causing temperatures to increase at the equator by about 20 degrees Fahrenheit and cool at the poles by about the same amount. The increasing temperatures are destabilizing the jet streams, causing them to become more wavy and push together more of the anticyclones.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't be surprised if a third of them are gone in the southern hemisphere,'' Dr. Marcus said.</p>
        <p>Eventually, though, the jet streams will become so wavy that the tops of the waves will pinch off to form new storms and start a new climate cycle. All that should happen within the next decade or so, Dr. Marcus predicts.</p>
        <p>Even with all the changes, Jupiter will still be recognizable at first glance.</p>
        <p>''It's still going to look like a round striped planet,'' Dr. Marcus said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
