<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Boston Federal Building Is Going Green at Age 72</title>
    <meta content="08PROP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/08/business/08prop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">McCormack, John W, Post Office and Courthouse (Boston)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowen, Ted Smalley</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cram, Ralph Adams</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Services Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6D91231F93BA35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Boston Federal Building Is Going Green at Age 72</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Boston Federal Building Is Going Green at Age 72</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TED SMALLEY BOWEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowen, Ted Smalley</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Dec. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John W McCormack Post Office and Courthouse, monumental granite-clad 22-story Art Deco structure in Boston's financial district, is about to undergo $78 million renovation that has number of distinctive goals; among most ambitious renovations of federal building, the project is committed to applying environmentally friendly 'green' standards; modern systems must be installed without compromising historical integrity of landmark Depression-era building; 1932 building was designed by Ralph Adams Cram; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The John W. McCormack Post Office and Courthouse, a monumental granite-clad 22-story Art Deco structure in Boston's financial district, is about to undergo a $78 million renovation that has a number of distinctive goals. Among the most ambitious renovations of a federal building, the project is committed to applying environmentally friendly ''green'' standards; at the same time, modern systems must be installed without compromising the historical integrity of the landmark Depression-era building.</p>
        <p>The 1932 building was designed by Ralph Adams Cram, an architect known mainly for his university buildings and churches, notably the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine in Manhattan. The project is to refurbish courtrooms and a library, the entrance and elevator lobbies and coffered ceilings while saving energy, minimizing the building's negative impact on the environment and improving workplace conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The $78 million renovation of the John W. McCormack Post Office and Courthouse in Boston will use environmentally friendly "green" standards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The John W. McCormack Post Office and Courthouse, a monumental granite-clad 22-story Art Deco structure in Boston's financial district, is about to undergo a $78 million renovation that has a number of distinctive goals. Among the most ambitious renovations of a federal building, the project is committed to applying environmentally friendly ''green'' standards; at the same time, modern systems must be installed without compromising the historical integrity of the landmark Depression-era building.</p>
        <p>The 1932 building was designed by Ralph Adams Cram, an architect known mainly for his university buildings and churches, notably the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine in Manhattan. The project is to refurbish courtrooms and a library, the entrance and elevator lobbies and coffered ceilings while saving energy, minimizing the building's negative impact on the environment and improving workplace conditions.</p>
        <p>Achieving all this requires finesse and compromise, according to the Boston architectural firm Goody Clancy, the prime contracting architectural firm, and the building's manager, the General Services Administration. Other participants include government agency occupants like the Environmental Protection Agency, the building's largest tenant.</p>
        <p>While the challenges of renovating a structure in its eighth decade of existence may seem evident, buildings of this vintage actually have some inherently green features. ''The designs of earlier periods incorporated natural ventilation and light and used very sustainable materials,'' said John Buckley, the assistant project manager for the General Services Administration.</p>
        <p>At the same time, preservation requirements can complicate major updates of a building's heating, ventilation, air-conditioning, electrical and communications systems.</p>
        <p>Goody Clancy and the G.S.A. are hashing out construction papers; work is expected to begin next year and wrap up late in 2006 or in 2007.</p>
        <p>The G.S.A. is upgrading the original aluminum windows; adding vegetation to create a green roof, which reduces storm water runoff and the ''urban heat island effect'' created when dark roofs and paving absorb heat in the summer; knocking out office partitions to improve natural light and ventilation; installing compact fluorescent lights and energy-efficient controls; and using recycled and nontoxic materials, according to agency officials.</p>
        <p>With support from the Massachusetts Technology Collaborative's Renewable Energy Trust, a program financed by utility ratepayers, the G.S.A. is exploring the use of renewable energy sources like photovoltaic cells, which power solar electric systems. It is also examining fuel cells, wind turbines and other clean fuels to reduce demand on the electrical grid. The agency is also working with a local steam provider, TriGen-Boston, on the possibility of reusing steam condensate in a heating system cooling tower and toilet tanks and is considering a back-pressure steam turbine to generate electricity.</p>
        <p>Besides the E.P.A., the building's other tenants include the Department of Education and the Federal Bankruptcy Court. The post office moved across the street this summer, partly for security reasons.</p>
        <p>Although it might seem an unlikely advocate of sustainability and historic preservation, the General Services Administration owns and leases hundreds of millions of square feet of work space for federal employees and it counts hundreds of historic buildings among its holdings. In addition, the agency helped to draft energy use and environmental guidelines as part of the ''greening the government'' initiative begun in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The G.S.A. is a member of the United States Green Building Council, a nonprofit organization that includes designers, developers, institutions, builders, environmentalists and manufacturers. The group developed Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design, or LEED, specifications, which lay out measures that are intended to benefit the environment and reduce energy use. They include locating near public transportation and building on formerly contaminated property to recycling construction waste and adding onsite power generation.</p>
        <p>Qualifying projects are certified on a graduated scale. G.S.A. projects aim for LEED silver status, the third-highest level, behind platinum and gold. The agency also uses LEED criteria in pressing for better conditions in the spaces it leases.</p>
        <p>There are no federal or state green building tax incentives equivalent to the 20 percent federal tax break and various state tax breaks for historic preservation of properties listed on the National Register of Historic Places. But private developers can qualify for a variety of grants, offsets and preferences at the state and local level. And federal agencies, state and local governments and institutions are increasingly adopting the LEED system as a requirement for their own building and renovation projects.</p>
        <p>Renovations make up a considerable portion of commercial building projects -- more than 15 percent of United States construction spending in recent years, according to McGraw-Hill Construction, a research and publishing unit of the McGraw-Hill Companies. That figure is conservative, since it excludes smaller projects and those that did not involve architects, according to a McGraw-Hill economist, Jennifer Coskren.</p>
        <p>How many of those are historic preservation projects or exercises in sustainable design is difficult to determine, though interest in both categories is increasing.</p>
        <p>The National Park Service, which maintains the National Register of Historic Places, annually approves 1,200 to 1,300 preservation projects, with an investment value of $3 billion, for the 20 percent federal tax break, according to the chief of technical preservation services, Sharon Park. In the last three years, about 22 percent of that has been office space and 25 percent other commercial space, Ms. Park said. Most projects are in the Northeast and South, where the National Register properties are concentrated.</p>
        <p>Especially in cases where historic tax credits are not available, developers are likely to need incentives to pursue green preservation projects, according to Jean Carroon, Goody Clancy's principal for preservation.</p>
        <p>''The tax credits for historic preservation were key to urban redevelopment, and we need the same kind of thing for sustainable design,'' she said. ''We need more documentation that shows that people really want to work in healthy environments and are willing to pay more to work in a healthy environment because there is a payback to the business owner in fewer sick days and a better work environment. That documentation is starting to happen but it is vague, so that makes it very challenging.''</p>
        <p>The G.S.A. and other institutional owner-managers, through their projects and follow-up studies, are generating data that advocates say may help to make the case that green preservation projects are worth the effort.</p>
        <p>Historic preservation and sustainability are not incompatible, of course -- reuse is a central tenet of environmentally sensitive design. But the goals can conflict, as in the treatment of windows, changes in floor plans or the use of insulation. The relatively small group of designers and advocates who specialize in green preservation are gearing up to bring both priorities into alignment.</p>
        <p>Some preservationists caution that LEED's emphasis on direct energy savings may predispose developers to replace historic windows and other original building elements, even though LEED does not proscribe operable windows and natural ventilation.</p>
        <p>''Often we're ripping out windows that are 100 and some years old in order to have a lower energy bill from the thermostat, but when we start looking at more of the holistic picture about how windows are made, about the trucking to move windows, we see the environmental cost,'' said Ms. Carroon of Goody Clancy. ''And the embodied energy of glass is very high.'' Embodied energy is a measure of the energy required to manufacture, transport, use and recycle or dispose of a given product or material.</p>
        <p>In the case of the McCormack Building, the original windows seem to be beyond repair, according to the G.S.A. project manager, Ivan Lopez. ''You can see through the metal in some places, and they're single-pane, sealed with caulking containing asbestos.''</p>
        <p>The decision on the windows is still pending and the design team is looking at the feasibility of bolstering the existing windows and of commissioning replicas. State and city historic preservation authorities will have to sign off on the plan.</p>
        <p>COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
