<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Gasoline Hits Record Price, Bush, Kerry and Democrats Spar Over Policy and Next Move</title>
    <meta content="Y24GAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1568780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strategic Petroleum Reserve</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D61730F937A15750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Gasoline Hits Record Price, Bush, Kerry and Democrats Spar Over Policy and Next Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD and JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John; Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Record-high price of gasoline becomes one of most contentious issues in Washington, with presidential candidates and members of Congress rushing to assign blame and propose ways to lower voters' costs at gas pump; senators call on Bush administration to release oil from Strategic Petroleum Reserve to help curb prices; Sen John Kerry, presumptive Democratic presidential nominee, accuses Pres Bush of neglecting energy conservation and favoring oil companies; Bush re-election campaign blames Kerry for voting against oil drilling in Alaska last year and for his past advocacy of higher gasoline taxes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The record-high price of gasoline has suddenly become one of the most contentious issues here, with presidential candidates and members of Congress rushing to assign blame and propose ways to lower voters' costs at the gas pump.</p>
        <p>As senators called on the Bush administration on Tuesday to release oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve to help curb prices, Senator John Kerry, the presumptive Democratic presidential nominee, accused President Bush of neglecting energy conservation and favoring oil companies. The Bush re-election campaign blamed Mr. Kerry for voting against oil drilling in Alaska last year and for his past advocacy of higher gasoline taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The record-high price of gasoline has suddenly become one of the most contentious issues here, with presidential candidates and members of Congress rushing to assign blame and propose ways to lower voters' costs at the gas pump.</p>
        <p>As senators called on the Bush administration on Tuesday to release oil from the Strategic Petroleum Reserve to help curb prices, Senator John Kerry, the presumptive Democratic presidential nominee, accused President Bush of neglecting energy conservation and favoring oil companies. The Bush re-election campaign blamed Mr. Kerry for voting against oil drilling in Alaska last year and for his past advocacy of higher gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>''It's clear we need a new energy policy,'' Mr. Kerry said. He cited a survey released Tuesday by AAA, formerly the American Automobile Association, showing that the average price for a gallon of self-serve regular unleaded was $1.738. The group said the price was a record, not taking into account inflation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said, ''We need a balanced energy policy that protects consumers from high gas prices, invests in renewable energy and promotes responsible development here at home.''</p>
        <p>Steve Schmidt, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, replied, ''The John Kerry complaining about energy costs today must not have checked with the John Kerry who helped block the energy bill last year or the John Kerry who supported a 50-cent tax hike on a gallon of gas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also mentioned that 50-cent tax in a campaign appearance in Florida on Saturday, saying, ''He wanted you to pay all that money at the pump and wouldn't even throw in a free carwash.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry has said in the past that the 50-cent tax was merely an idea floated to reduce the federal deficit in 1992, that he never voted for it and that by the mid-1990's he had decided it was a bad idea.</p>
        <p>He said on Tuesday, in a statement from Sun Valley, Idaho, where he is vacationing, that consumers were paying a ''Bush gas tax'' because prices had increased 11.5 percent during his administration. ''The profits from gasoline sales go to overpaid oil company executives and other countries,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Instead of trying to ''drill our way to independence,'' Mr. Kerry said, the United States should focus on conservation and domestic sources of renewable energy.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, on Capitol Hill, Democrats faulted the administration as not responding to ease the price increase. Three Democratic senators, Charles E. Schumer of New York, Barbara Boxer of California and Harry Reid of Nevada, called on the Energy Department to offer petroleum from the reserve to oil companies now, in exchange for repayment in a few months of the original plus interest, paid in oil. The department has used the technique before, and it is attractive at times like this, when prices for delivery in future months are lower than spot prices now.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer, citing a prediction that prices would rise about 7 cents a month from now until late summer, said the average family with two cars would soon pay more in extra gasoline costs than it received with the tax credit of $400 per child that was issued in July 2003.</p>
        <p>''What Uncle Sam has given with one hand, he's allowed OPEC to take away with the other,'' Mr. Schumer said at a briefing for reporters, referring to the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries.</p>
        <p>Ceasing to fill the reserve, as the members of the House requested on Monday and as the Senate voted March 12 to do, would divert about a million barrels a week to refineries and would presumably push down prices.</p>
        <p>But oil economists say there would be only a tiny effect on prices because the oil in question is only about 0.15 percent of the world market.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham, testifying at a Senate hearing on Tuesday, said that as a matter of national security the administration would continue to fill the reserve. The reserve now holds nearly 650 million barrels, a record, but the level of imports has risen even faster than the reserve has grown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abraham is far from alone in opposing the release of oil from the reserve. Lawrence J. Goldstein, president of the Petroleum Industry Research Foundation, a nonprofit group in New York, said in a telephone interview that the government should not be interfering with prices in a free market.</p>
        <p>''This is not tinkering; this is tampering,'' Mr. Goldstein said.</p>
        <p>The reserve should be saved for occasions when its oil is needed to protect the economy, he added, but right now the economy is growing.</p>
        <p>Ms. Boxer, appearing with Mr. Schumer on Tuesday, said: ''Mr. Goldstein would be right if we were dealing with a free market in oil. We're not. OPEC itself constructs supply, manipulates supply and demand to set a price level.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
