<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Brookhaven Lab, Less Glass to Blow</title>
    <meta content="07LIJOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1625307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Glassblowers Society</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookhaven National Laboratory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Popular Science (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lafler, Barry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Svoboda, Karel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DF173CF934A35752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Brookhaven Lab, Less Glass to Blow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal: Barry Lafler, honored in 2003 by American Glassblowers Society, works at Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton and is last scientific glassblower on island; Lafler, citing economics and outsourcing, says scientific glassblowers are dying breed; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory neurobiologist Karel Svoboda, leader of team undertaking groundbreaking research on how brain works in mice, is selected by Popular Science magazine as part of its third annual 'Brilliant 10' group (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BARRY LAFLER handcrafts the specialized glassware needed for research at Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton: not the customary beakers, flasks and test tubes but funky, complicated gizmos and doodads that researchers use to perform experiments.</p>
        <p>Working in the chemistry department, Mr. Lafler, 56, of Ridge, molds long glass rods into scientific apparatus and transforms mass-produced glassware into labyrinths of cylinders and bubbles. He has made plasma tubes for lasers, furnace tubes for physics experiments and a 72-liter flask for a distillation operation. To create a safer alternative to toxic mercury diffusion pumps, Mr. Lafler concocted a glass oil pump.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BARRY LAFLER handcrafts the specialized glassware needed for research at Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton: not the customary beakers, flasks and test tubes but funky, complicated gizmos and doodads that researchers use to perform experiments.</p>
        <p>Working in the chemistry department, Mr. Lafler, 56, of Ridge, molds long glass rods into scientific apparatus and transforms mass-produced glassware into labyrinths of cylinders and bubbles. He has made plasma tubes for lasers, furnace tubes for physics experiments and a 72-liter flask for a distillation operation. To create a safer alternative to toxic mercury diffusion pumps, Mr. Lafler concocted a glass oil pump.</p>
        <p>But like other scientific glassblowers, Mr. Lafler has been working himself out of a job.</p>
        <p>''Over the years the glass houses have put all the items that we developed into their catalogs,'' Mr. Lafler said, his voice tinged with despair. ''We develop it and they take it and run with it.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year Mr. Lafler was honored for his contributions by the American Glassblowers Society, a professional, nonprofit organization with 700 members, down from 2,000 in the 1960's. But the need for masters of molten glass has gone the way of the abacus. Mr. Lafler is the last scientific glassblower on the Island.</p>
        <p>''I am semibusy,'' Mr. Lafler said recently, his workbench clear of projects, dozens of glass rods stacked in a container. ''There doesn't seem to be a lot of work here. I have work to do. I wish I had more.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafler said it takes 10 to 12 years to become a topnotch scientific glassblower, able to design specialized glass apparatus on the fly.</p>
        <p>''We are just an extension of the scientists' ideas,'' Mr. Lafler said.</p>
        <p>Years ago Brookhaven, like most research institutions and universities, had a cadre of scientific glassblowers.</p>
        <p>Now there are no apprentices in the pipeline. The four other benches in the glass workshop have been empty since Mr. Lafler started a dozen years ago.</p>
        <p>Scientific glassblowers are a dying breed, he said, because of economics and outsourcing. ''There isn't as much money flowing into research as there has been in the past,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafler starts each project with glass rods of varying thicknesses. He uses a torch to heat borosilicate glass and some quartz glass up to 1,500 degrees Centigrade, peering into the flame through dark safety glasses to mold and blow glass.</p>
        <p>Jack Preses, a chemist, often needs to combine gases for experiments. He recently asked Mr. Lafler to design a glass apparatus that would hasten the process. After negotiating ideas, Mr. Lafler created a glass bulb with a glass fan that could be turned with a magnetic stirrer.</p>
        <p>''Having an expert glassblower is not a luxury but a necessity,'' Dr. Preses said.</p>
        <p>While Dr. Preses admitted that scientists used less glass than they used to, what they do use is custom made. ''We don't use beakers and flasks anymore,'' he said. ''We use glass as vacuum systems and vacuum vessels.''</p>
        <p>George Meinken, a chemist research associate, produces radioactive isotopes for medical purposes. When extractions or distillations have do be done and dexterity is limited, specially designed glassware is required. That's when Mr. Lafler is called in.</p>
        <p>''I don't see how the lab could do without a glassblower,'' Mr. Meinken said. ''Most of the time we can't use what comes in a catalog.''</p>
        <p>Michael Souza, a former president of the American Scientific Glassblowers Society, attributed the decline in the number of scientific glassblowers to advances in technology.</p>
        <p>''You used to have to make a lot of wet chemistry to do an analysis on a compound,'' Mr. Souza said. ''Now you have nuclear magnetic resonance'' that enables an analysis to quickly be made based on a couple of drops of a compound.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it,'' Mr. Souza said. ''Part of research is to put yourself out of business.''</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Lafler, glass has been a lifelong passion. Growing up in Horseheads, N.Y., he frequently watched the workers at Corning blow glass. One day one of the glassblowers asked him if he wanted to blow a bubble. ''It was a real trip for me,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Lafler got out of the Navy in the late 1960's, he went to his local employment office. A glass job with a small company making generator tubes for night-vision scopes used in the Vietnam War was available.</p>
        <p>''As I soon as I saw the work they were doing, I said, 'This is it for me,''' he recalled. ''I took my coat off and I never looked back.''</p>
        <p>A year later he started a three-year apprenticeship program at Eastman Kodak and continued for 22 years. He joined Brookhaven in 1991.</p>
        <p>For the lab's 50th anniversary in 1997, Mr. Lafler created five-gallon, moisture-resistant glass time capsules, which were filled with memorabilia. They were buried on the federal property, to be opened in 2047.</p>
        <p>Beyond the lab, Mr. Lafler concentrates on creating Art Deco and Art Nouveau objects out of blown glass.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of thinking out of the box,'' he said. ''It is more creative.''</p>
        <p>Later this month, Mr. Lafler plans to open a shop, Island Glass Studio, in Patchogue, where he will hold glassblowing classes and sell the goblets, pedestal dishes and teapots he makes in his home workshop.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafler's blown-glass pieces have been exhibited at Gallery North in Setauket and in the gift shop at the Heckscher Museum of Art in Huntington. He also teaches at the Art League of Long Island and gives glassblowing demonstrations at craft fairs.</p>
        <p>''I am a glass junkie,'' Mr. Lafler said. ''I can't get enough of it.''</p>
        <p>Pursuing Brain Mysteries</p>
        <p>To unravel how the brain works and how memories are stored, Karel Svoboda, a neurobiologist at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, built a powerful laser-scanning microscope.</p>
        <p>''The brain can only be understood in its entirety,'' Dr. Svoboda said. ''It has to be studied intact.'' Noninvasive technologies, like MRI and PET scans, didn't show what was going on at the cellular level. What could be garnered from studying brain cells in a dish under a microscope was limited, he said.</p>
        <p>But few good tools were available to explore the electrical and biochemical dynamics of the intact brain. Dr. Svoboda, 38, of Huntington, decided to build his own, developing microscopes and imaging methods to do groundbreaking research using live mice.</p>
        <p>''Our interest is to figure out what happens at the level of neurons, which are cells in the brain, and synapses, which are the connections between the cells in the brains,'' said Dr. Svoboda, who heads a lab with 10 postdoctoral students, 4 graduate students plus a handful of technicians. To have a window into a mouse's brain, Dr. Svoboda devised a way to replace a tiny piece of skull with custom-made glass.</p>
        <p>In October, Dr. Svoboda was selected by Popular Science magazine as part of its third annual ''Brilliant 10,'' a group of the brightest and most promising scientists in their respective fields, yet little known to the public. Others on the scientific innovators' list include an evolutionary ecologist investigating how deforestation could affect global carbon dioxide levels and a computer scientist who developed the animation method used to create lifelike characters.</p>
        <p>Emily Laber-Warren, the executive editor for features at Popular Science, said Dr. Svoboda was chosen from a pool of about 10 neuroscientists.</p>
        <p>''He is kind of a maverick,'' Ms. Laber-Warren said. ''He did something he had to invent the actual tools to do. He was so intent on his quest that he did that.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Svoboda unexpectedly discovered that new synapses are formed in the adult brain.</p>
        <p>''It was previously thought to only occur in the developing brain,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He contrasted the wiring in the brain, which can change, to a digital computer where the wiring is fixed when the microprocessor is made.</p>
        <p>''We suspect that the components, the transistors, the switches can, in fact, change their properties also in the brain,'' Dr. Svoboda said.</p>
        <p>Initially trained as a physicist at Cornell University, Dr. Svoboda delved into molecular physics as a graduate student at Harvard. Looking for problems to work on, he realized there was a lot to do in brain research. But he had to build his own mammoth lasers. Synapses are one billionth the size of a grain of rice. The microscope needed resolution that is 1,000 times that of an MRI.</p>
        <p>Dr. Svoboda's said his research, done by trimming the rodent's sensory whiskers and then studying their brains as they search harder for food, could help lay the groundwork for treatments for Alzheimer's and Fragile X syndrome, a form of mental retardation.</p>
        <p>''We develop tools and technologies that other people use for more applied means,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laber-Warren said his research would someday impact lives.</p>
        <p>''We are looking to put our finger on who will be the next Nobel prize winner,'' she said.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
