<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australians Re-elect Howard As Economy Trumps the War</title>
    <meta content="10AUST$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/10/international/asia/10australia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041013T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1618282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonner, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howard, John (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Howard, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DA133BF933A25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australians Re-elect Howard As Economy Trumps the War</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Australians Re-electHoward as Prime Minister</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND BONNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bonner, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sunday, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Australian Prime Min John Howard of Liberal Party is decisively elected to fourth term; preliminary results show Liberals winning 71 of 150 seats in House of Representatives and coalition partner National Party taking 12 seats; Australia's participation in Iraq war is widely unpopular, but booming economy was key issue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister John Howard of Australia, who went into the country's election with a good-luck message from President Bush, was decisively re-elected Saturday, according to official returns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howard's Liberals, a center-right party, defeated the center-left Labor Party, led by Mark Latham. Mr. Howard, first elected prime minister in 1996, becomes only the third prime minister in Australia's history to be elected to a fourth term.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister John Howard, who went into the election with a good-luck message from President Bush, was decisively re-elected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister John Howard of Australia, who went into the country's election with a good-luck message from President Bush, was decisively re-elected Saturday, according to official returns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howard's Liberals, a center-right party, defeated the center-left Labor Party, led by Mark Latham. Mr. Howard, first elected prime minister in 1996, becomes only the third prime minister in Australia's history to be elected to a fourth term.</p>
        <p>Iraq loomed in the background during the campaign, but Australian political analysts cautioned that the voting was not a referendum on the war. The main issue was the economy, and that is booming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howard sent some of Australia's best combat forces at the beginning of the Iraq war, adopting the arguments of the Bush administration that Saddam Hussein possessed unconventional weapons. Even as evidence has emerged to the contrary, Mr. Howard has steadfastly insisted that he had no regrets about the decision. Mr. Latham had harshly criticized the war.</p>
        <p>At this point, Australia's contribution to the war is of more symbolic importance to the Bush administration than it is militarily. Fewer than 200 Australian troops are in Iraq now, and none are engaged in combat. Most are security forces at the Australian Embassy, and some are trainers.</p>
        <p>Labor had faced a formidable challenge in trying to unseat Mr. Howard. The economy has been growing steadily for more than a decade; unemployment is near historic lows, as are interest rates.</p>
        <p>''This country is too wealthy'' to vote for Labor, said Antonino D'Albora, a 60-year old taxi driver, capturing the political ambience here. He was voting at a school in Bondi, in the heart of one of the wealthiest districts in Australia, within sound and sight of the famed beach.</p>
        <p>Voting is mandatory in Australia, and George Harris, 44, wearing only his bathing suit and tennis shoes, walked into the Bondi surf club to cast his ballot for the Liberals.</p>
        <p>''It's purely a matter of economic management,'' he said. A former senior executive with an international company, he now manages his own investments, from stocks to property to cattle and sheep.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris said whatever people thought about Australia's going to war -- the vast majority were against it at the time -- there was no choice now but to stay until the war was won.</p>
        <p>On the other side of Sydney, in a middle-class suburb, Richard Lo, a 32-year-old computer programmer who immigrated from Hong Kong a decade ago, expressed similar sentiments.</p>
        <p>''The economy here, that is the major thing,'' he said. ''I don't like the policy in Iraq. But it is not enough to vote against him.'' He cast his vote for the Liberals.</p>
        <p>Aware of the strong opposition to the war, Mr. Howard has handled it with political deftness, even his Labor opponents concede. Australia's tough special forces played an important role in the early stages of the war, much of it still secret. But as soon as the main fighting was over, in May 2003, Mr. Howard pulled them out. No Australian soldier has been killed in combat.</p>
        <p>The primary differences between Liberals and Labor are on social and environmental issues. ''I voted for Labor,'' Julie Luc, who emigrated from Vietnam in 1978, said in a tone that said, how could anyone think she wouldn't. ''I'm a worker. I'm poor. I'm not rich.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Howard has declined to sign the Kyoto treaty on global warming (again putting him in sync with Mr. Bush), while Mr. Latham said he would sign it. But the real environmental battle is in Tasmania, the island state where environmentalists and loggers are in a heated conflict over the island's old-growth forests. Mr. Latham said he would protect 600,000 acres. Mr. Howard's program would protect only 42,000 acres. ''Howard backs jobs over trees,'' read the headline in The Australian, one of Australia's largest dailies, which endorsed Mr. Howard.</p>
        <p>Labor had held five seats in Tasmania. It lost one, almost certainly because Mr. Latham's forestry policy was seen as hurting loggers.</p>
        <p>With 77 percent of the vote counted, the Liberals won 71 seats in the 150-seat House of Representatives, it was reported Sunday, and its coalition partners, The Nationals, a conservative rural party, won 12, for a coalition total of 83.</p>
        <p>In his last major appearance before the voting, Prime Minister Howard said the ''good luck'' message from Mr. Bush had been delivered by the American ambassador here, Tom Schieffer, who had been a partner with Mr. Bush when he owned the Texas Rangers baseball team.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 13, 2004, Wednesday  An article on Sunday about the re-election of Prime Minister John Howard of Australia misstated the number of parliamentary seats lost by the opposition Labor Party in the southern state of Tasmania, where the party's promise to protect large areas of old-growth forests had angered loggers. Labor lost two of its five seats, not one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 13, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Sunday about the re-election of Prime Minister John Howard of Australia misstated the number of parliamentary seats lost by the opposition Labor Party in the southern state of Tasmania, where the party's promise to protect large areas of old-growth forests had angered loggers. Labor lost two of its five seats, not one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
