<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Not A Park?</title>
    <meta content="16GROUNDZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="55" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/16/magazine/16GROUNDZERO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1581917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">West 8 Landscape Architects</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DIRT Studio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corner, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EEDA133CF935A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Not A Park?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Why Not a Park?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on possibility of turning World Trade Center site into grand urban park for downtown Manhattan; landscape-architecture firms Ken Smith Landscape, James Corner, West 8 Landscape, DIRT Studio offer proposals; renderings; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that Larry Silverstein, the World Trade Center leaseholder, has lost his bid to double his insurance payout, it is not clear where the money to fulfill the master plan for ground zero will come from. The 1,776-foot-high Freedom Tower, which promises to become the tallest building in the world, is slated to begin construction this summer. But many of the other large office towers planned for the site may need to be scaled back; it is possible that they will not be built at all. The future of one of America's most significant public spaces has become unsettled.</p>
        <p>So why not a park -- a grand urban park for downtown Manhattan? Earlier this spring, The New York Times Magazine asked several leading landscape-architecture firms to consider the question, and the proposals that are illustrated on the following pages offer a provocative variety of responses. References to the trade-center towers themselves are abstract or absent; in only one plan do the towers' ''footprints'' appear, and even then only as openings in a heavily planted roof above a sunken memorial plaza. Two of the firms involved suggest using either ground zero or the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island as tree nurseries; these sites would generate greenery that would, in turn, be distributed to neighborhoods around the New York City area. While not every firm proposed an actual park on the site, all four provide ample proof of the power of landscape to transform a scarred and haunted place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four landscape-architecture firms reimagine ground zero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that Larry Silverstein, the World Trade Center leaseholder, has lost his bid to double his insurance payout, it is not clear where the money to fulfill the master plan for ground zero will come from. The 1,776-foot-high Freedom Tower, which promises to become the tallest building in the world, is slated to begin construction this summer. But many of the other large office towers planned for the site may need to be scaled back; it is possible that they will not be built at all. The future of one of America's most significant public spaces has become unsettled.</p>
        <p>So why not a park -- a grand urban park for downtown Manhattan? Earlier this spring, The New York Times Magazine asked several leading landscape-architecture firms to consider the question, and the proposals that are illustrated on the following pages offer a provocative variety of responses. References to the trade-center towers themselves are abstract or absent; in only one plan do the towers' ''footprints'' appear, and even then only as openings in a heavily planted roof above a sunken memorial plaza. Two of the firms involved suggest using either ground zero or the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island as tree nurseries; these sites would generate greenery that would, in turn, be distributed to neighborhoods around the New York City area. While not every firm proposed an actual park on the site, all four provide ample proof of the power of landscape to transform a scarred and haunted place.</p>
        <p>WORKSHOP: KEN SMITH LANDSCAPE ARCHITECT, NEW YORK  A large pleasure park would provide a ''Respite,'' as we call our project, from the density of the financial district and the trauma of its recent history. This new park should be a tranquil place of detachment from the hubbub and concerns of everyday life. Historically, much of the World Trade Center site was under water, and today's Greenwich Street was the original shoreline of the Hudson River. This part of the park would be returned to water in the form of a large urban lake with two acres of scattered islands, planted with willow trees and grass. The island fragments are equivalent in area to the footprints of the twin towers and serve as silent memorials. Small boats, piloted by gondoliers, would carry people to the islands to sit, picnic, look at the sky and let their minds drift. In winter, there would be ice skating.</p>
        <p>A broad public promenade would align with Greenwich Street, and there would be a substantial grove of pines and flowering trees with a long canal along Church Street. Within this grove would be spaces devoted to small pleasures: a carousel for children, gardens devoted to various phenomena of light, reflection, sound and smell and a beautiful pavilion by Santiago Calatrava for people arriving from New Jersey. Materials would be simple: trees of various types, gravel, stone and grass.</p>
        <p>Design team: Elizabeth Asawa, Alex Felson, David Hamerman, Thomas Oles, Ken Smith, Annie Weinmayr, Yuka Yoshida.</p>
        <p>JAMES CORNER: FIELD OPERATIONS, NEW YORK  How might landscape go beyond its traditional role as a passive, benevolent respite from the dense, commercial and sometimes brutal aspects of the city and become something that might carry us into a future that we have yet to imagine?</p>
        <p>Our proposal, ''Life Forms: Growing a New Urban Landscape,'' offers a long-range program that imagines the entire fabric of Lower Manhattan as a synthetic, productive landscape -- an alternative to the traditional model of clearly defined parks. The best tribute to the tragic history of the World Trade Center site is life -- evolution, profusion and creativity. This transformation would be effected over decades, beginning next year:  2005: Propagation. The ''bathtub'' of the World Trade Center site would be turned into a tree nursery as part of a regenerative landscape of tree farms, growing new life. Vertical garden aviaries and a temporary memorial ''forest'' of trade-center building remnants would be arrayed along the western half of the site. New tree-lined public promenades along Vesey and Liberty Streets would connect to the Hudson River.  2020: Reforestation. The trees grown in the bathtub nursery would be used in an extensive reforestation of public spaces and streets. The tree farm will become a memorial arboretum -- a large sunken garden of extraordinary tree specimens, flowers and wildlife from all over the world.  2050: Landscape Urbanism. A built fabric emerges, synthesizing natural materials, air, light, water and energy into radically new amalgams of nature and urban life. Building skins that respond to air and temperature changes, ecological roof gardens, gardens that recycle water and air, geothermal heating and cooling systems, solar and wind energy producers, biochemical super-decomposers of waste and other ecotechnologies create a sustainable environment in which landscape functions less as a backdrop and more as a productive, living machine. The sunken arboretum memorial grows into a synthetic water garden, a petri dish of diverse and exotic life forms.  2200: Bio-Urbia. With rising sea levels and changes in global climate, Lower Manhattan may one day become an island with extraordinary beaches. The World Trade Center site would link the new island to Manhattan, serving as a metropolitan transit hub, exotic water garden, perimeter promenade and nucleus of a global Earth.</p>
        <p>WEST 8 LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTS, ROTTERDAM, HOLLAND  The ground-zero debate has been entirely preoccupied by architectural solutions. Changing the perspective to landscape allows new identities to emerge. We suggest turning the site into a pasture, an image that will overwhelm and impress because it is such a common scene in such an unexpected setting. Rather than colonize ground zero, we propose to define the site as an icon of itself. Creating a green surface with a strong outline captures the imprint of the tragedy of 9/11. We envision ground zero as a contemplative oasis enclosed by West, Vesey, Church and Liberty Streets. The existing West Street would be a building site for commercial real estate, with traffic diverted through a new underground tunnel. Not only will these new buildings satisfy demand for commercial space; they will also help define ground zero as a sublime void.</p>
        <p>The park, which would cover almost 20 acres, consists of a memorial plaza, paved with granite, that provides an urban space for conversation as well as contemplation. The roof over the plaza is an undulating shell that will be planted with a pasture of grass and 1,000 New York State apple trees. This pasture extends beyond the roof to solid ground at the east end of the site and is linked visually to the green space around Trinity Church to the northeast, a small spot that should be considered as potential public space and part of the memory of both the disaster and its mourning. A public gallery overlooks the plaza, and two squares excised in the roof frame views of the sky above and allow sunlight to trace the shape of the twin towers' footprints below. In the winter, snow falling through these openings will create two perfect white squares on the floor of the plaza. Other openings in the roof will allow monumental beams of light into the plaza, in the manner of the sky windows in Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>Design team: Adriaan Geuze, Edzo Bindels, Juan Antonio Sanchez MuÑoz, Karsten Buchholz, Javier Muñoz Galán, Anna Holder, Daphne Schuit, Carlos Peña Ponte, Masayuki Tajima.</p>
        <p>D.I.R.T. STUDIO CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA.  We believe that places emerges through process. At the World Trade Center site, the process of rebuilding and the process of remembering converge, and require additional time and space beyond the site itself. Therefore, our proposal inaugurates a citywide regenerative cycle. Soil would be produced and trees cultivted by turning a portion of the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island into a farm. The local rivers would become a connective tissue; loads of good soil and young trees would be carried by barge from Fresh Kills - along nearly the same routes once traveled by daily commuters from the World Trade Center on their way home - to neighborhood streets and parks.</p>
        <p>Design team: D.I.R.T. studio (Julie Bargmann, Heidi Baker, Stacey Farinholt) and Nicholas De Monchaux.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
