<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="27BIZD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1562204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC113CF934A15751C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shareholder Displeasure Over Disney Chief Grows  A growing number of state pension funds, mutual fund companies and other investors have expressed displeasure over the management of Michael D. Eisner, the chairman and chief executive of the Walt Disney Company.</p>
        <p>Up to one-third of Disney's shareholders are expected to withhold votes for the besieged Mr. Eisner in the company's annual board election next week, well above the 10 percent many governance experts had predicted just two weeks ago. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shareholder Displeasure Over Disney Chief Grows  A growing number of state pension funds, mutual fund companies and other investors have expressed displeasure over the management of Michael D. Eisner, the chairman and chief executive of the Walt Disney Company.</p>
        <p>Up to one-third of Disney's shareholders are expected to withhold votes for the besieged Mr. Eisner in the company's annual board election next week, well above the 10 percent many governance experts had predicted just two weeks ago. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Stewart Fraud Charge Said to Stay  The federal judge overseeing the trial of Martha Stewart did not drop one of the most serious charges against her, securities fraud, from the proposed instructions to the jury that she shared with lawyers, according to a person briefed on the draft document. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers for Tyco International's former chief financial officer rested their case yesterday. Prosecutors said they would mount a rebuttal case. [C3.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Faces European Sanctions  The European Union's trade commissioner, Pascal Lamy, said the United States would face $4 billion in sanctions starting Monday because Congress has failed to eliminate overseas tax shelters for American exporters that were declared illegal by the World Trade Organization. Even though the sanctions are the largest ever authorized by the W.T.O., they have not elicited the same sense of outrage among Americans as a similar threat last year over steel tariffs. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Jury Decision Supports I.B.M.  A jury ruled in favor of I.B.M. in a case brought by two former employees who claimed they contracted cancer while working around dangerous chemicals. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Rambus Case Reverberates  A judge's decision last week dismissing an antitrust case against Rambus, a designer of computer memory chips, is proving to be bad news for memory chip makers. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Resistance to Mad Cow Proposal  A beef producer in Kansas has proposed testing all its cattle for mad cow disease so it can resume exports to Japan, but it is encountering resistance from the agriculture department and other beef producers. [A18.]</p>
        <p>Stock Movement Is Restrained  Technology shares rose slightly while blue chips were close to unchanged The Dow Jones industrial average closed down 21.48 points, or 0.20 percent, at 10,580.14. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index ended up 1.24 points, or 0.11 percent, at 1,144.91. The Nasdaq composite index was up 9.59 points, or 0.47 percent, at 2,032.57. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Orders Drop for Durable Goods  Factory orders for big-ticket goods dropped 1.8 percent in January, the Commerce Department reported. But much of that reflected huge declines in bookings for commercial and military airplanes. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Nestlé Profit Declines 18%  Nestlé, the world's largest food conglomerate, said high cocoa prices, a weak dollar and the effects of SARS on Asian business cut its 2003 profit by almost 18 percent. Nestlé's chief executive said that the company had performed well despite the odds. The company said that it was ahead in a cost-cutting drive that began in 1997, saving 45 percent more than it expected. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Promoting Protein With Humor  Solae, a maker of soy additives, is taking its pro-protein message to the public with a humorous new ad campaign. Advertising. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Global Warming Reports Are Urged  A group of pension fund managers said they had filed shareholder resolutions calling on 10 oil companies to report on their plans to deal with the potential impact of global warming and related climate change. [C3.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
