<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four Scary Days With a Newborn Grandson</title>
    <meta content="21BROD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/21/health/21brod.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1636320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDF1330F932A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four Scary Days With a Newborn Grandson</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Newborn Grandson Turns 'Very, Very Sick'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thanksgiving Day was fraught with fear and anxiety for my family and me. The morning before, my fourth grandson, ''Baby T,'' aka Tennyson, entered the world at a robust 8 pounds 14 ounces. His Apgar score five minutes after birth was 9 of a possible 10, indicating good color, good muscle tone, good health. But two hours later, his life hung in a precarious balance.</p>
        <p>An observant nurse noted that his color was ''not right'' -- pink above the chest but grayish below. Minutes later, the neonatologist told my daughter-in-law that her baby, who initially seemed perfectly healthy, was now ''very, very, very sick and could go either way.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Persistent pulmonary hypertension in newborns is considered rare, but it is surprisingly common, afflicting an estimated 1 baby in 700.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thanksgiving Day was fraught with fear and anxiety for my family and me. The morning before, my fourth grandson, ''Baby T,'' aka Tennyson, entered the world at a robust 8 pounds 14 ounces. His Apgar score five minutes after birth was 9 of a possible 10, indicating good color, good muscle tone, good health. But two hours later, his life hung in a precarious balance.</p>
        <p>An observant nurse noted that his color was ''not right'' -- pink above the chest but grayish below. Minutes later, the neonatologist told my daughter-in-law that her baby, who initially seemed perfectly healthy, was now ''very, very, very sick and could go either way.''</p>
        <p>Shaking with terror, she quickly signed permissions for a host of tests and interventions.</p>
        <p>Baby T's body was being deprived of oxygen, and whenever he was handled in any way, the oxygen level in his blood dropped even further. A chest X-ray revealed pneumonia. An echocardiogram found no heart defect but rather a failure of his circulatory system to convert from the womb to the outside world.</p>
        <p>Breathing, for Nothing</p>
        <p>Baby T was breathing, all right, but the oxygen was not getting into his blood because the pulmonary artery was bypassing the lungs.</p>
        <p>This life-threatening condition is called persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn, or P.P.H.N. Experts call it rare, but to me it is surprisingly common, afflicting an estimated 1 baby in 700, most of them, like Baby T, born full-term or post-term.</p>
        <p>My experience with this otherwise perfect birth and baby reaffirmed my belief that all babies should be born in well-equipped hospitals, with neonatologists at the ready and a neonatal intensive care unit down the hall. If Baby T had been delivered at a birthing center distant from a hospital or, worse, at home, he probably would have died or, had he survived, suffered irreversible organ failure and brain damage.</p>
        <p>Normally after birth, the pulmonary artery carries ''used'' oxygen-poor blood from the heart to the lungs, where it can pick up a fresh supply of oxygen and release carbon dioxide. This oxygenated blood is then returned to the heart, which pumps it to the rest of the body.</p>
        <p>While in the womb, a fetus gets oxygen from the mother's placenta through the umbilical cord, so the lungs are not used and need just a minimal blood supply. During fetal life, high blood pressure in the lungs shunts the blood in the pulmonary artery to a fetal blood vessel, the ductus arteriosus, which carries it back to the heart, bypassing the lungs.</p>
        <p>Most of the time, when a newborn baby takes its first breaths, the pressure in the lungs drops and blood can flow more freely into them, allowing an adequate exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide to maintain all the body's organs. Within a day or two after birth, the ductus arteriosus shuts down permanently.</p>
        <p>But in persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn, pressure in the lungs remains high for hours, days, even weeks after birth, depriving the baby of an adequate supply of oxygen-rich blood to maintain life. The condition is called persistent fetal circulation and soon results in severe respiratory distress.</p>
        <p>Administering oxygen, which is the first step tried when a baby is in respiratory distress, does no good because the lungs cannot do their job. Even though babies with the hypertension disorder are breathing, the oxygen they inhale cannot reach the bloodstream. So, as is the case for babies with this condition, Baby T had to be placed on a ventilator that did the work his lungs could not do.</p>
        <p>Baby T was also given medication that raised his overall blood pressure to help even out the pressure between his lungs and the rest of his body, enabling blood to better flow into his lungs. A feeding tube was inserted and an intravenous line was established. Two potent antibiotics were given through the IV to treat what was believed to be congenital bacterial pneumonia. Other lines measured blood gases, blood pressure and respiration and heart rate round the clock. Baby T was more tubes than baby.</p>
        <p>In addition, Baby T had to be sedated, both to keep him from pulling out the tubes and to minimize the stresses that caused his oxygen level to plummet.</p>
        <p>Looking for Good Signs</p>
        <p>The first four days of his life were considered critical. If his condition stabilized or improved, it was considered a good sign. We were painfully aware of a horrifying statistic: nearly one baby in five with persistent pulmonary hypertension dies. But Baby T rallied, his lungs doing more and more of the work. After five days, he was able to get off the ventilator and begin taking tiny amounts of breast milk by mouth. He handled that well, and was soon ready to nurse directly from the breast.</p>
        <p>We celebrated Thanksgiving on Sunday, when we had good reason to believe Baby T was all right. He came home a week later only two ounces below his birth weight and nursing eagerly.</p>
        <p>Though no one can say for sure what causes this disorder, various stresses that occur in pregnancy, as well as certain diseases or congenital conditions that affect a baby's lungs, have been linked to it. In the mother, precipitating stresses may include diabetes, high blood pressure, anemia or delivery after 40 weeks of pregnancy. In the baby, aspiration of meconium, anemia, severe pneumonia, low blood sugar and birth asphyxia have been associated with the disorder.</p>
        <p>A baby with it is likely to breathe rapidly and have a fast heart rate. Signs of respiratory distress include flaring nostrils, grunting and a bluish tinge to the skin.</p>
        <p>As in Baby T's case, when oxygen is in short supply, the brain is preferentially spared, which is why his face remained pink even when his abdomen and legs looked grayish. Had oxygen-rich blood not been circulated throughout his body fast enough, his kidneys, liver and heart and ultimately his brain would have been damaged or destroyed.</p>
        <p>This is why proximity to a well-equipped neonatal intensive care unit, a neonatologist and a well-trained nursing team is so critical. Even in a seemingly ideal pregnancy and birth, you just never know when something will go wrong.</p>
        <p>Had Baby T not responded adequately on his own, other measures would have been necessary that required transferring him to another hospital. Studies have shown that supplying inhaled nitric oxide to newborns with persistent pulmonary hypertension often has a relaxing effect on pulmonary blood vessels, enabling them to fill with blood sent from the heart.</p>
        <p>And if that doesn't work, a last resort is to place the baby for several days on an extracorporeal membrane oxygenator -- essentially a heart-lung machine -- which involves major surgery and expert monitoring. This treatment, which gives the baby's lungs a chance to kick in, is reserved for the sickest babies because serious side effects can set in.</p>
        <p>Even the minimal treatment Baby T received could have lasting consequences, including speech development and hearing problems. He will be periodically evaluated for them.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, we are all immeasurably grateful for medical progress. Not even 20 years ago nearly half those with persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn died; that number is now less than 20 percent, with only one-fifth of survivors experiencing long-term complications.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
