<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Movies, at Least, Good Vanquishes Evil</title>
    <meta content="10BOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/10/movies/10BOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040511T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1580627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waxman, Sharon</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Van Helsing (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Troy (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">King Arthur (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D8153CF933A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Movies, at Least, Good Vanquishes Evil</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At the Movies, at Least, Good Vanquishes Evil</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON WAXMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waxman, Sharon</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on summer movies that focus on violent, heroic fantasy battles in which good guys tend to win, including Van Helsing, Troy and King Arthur; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the vampire slayer Van Helsing made his debut in American movie theaters this weekend, there was no question who was going to win the contest against the evildoers.</p>
        <p>''Evil has one name to fear,'' a tag line for the movie declares. ''Van Helsing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This summer brings a host of violent battles that mirror the violence on the nightly news. Except that on screen, reassuringly, the good guys tend to win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the vampire slayer Van Helsing made his debut in American movie theaters this weekend, there was no question who was going to win the contest against the evildoers.</p>
        <p>''Evil has one name to fear,'' a tag line for the movie declares. ''Van Helsing.''</p>
        <p>Vanquishing evil, battling for freedom and dying for honor will be Hollywood's preoccupations this summer, as big movies gestated in the insecure post-Sept. 11 world finally make their way onto screens.</p>
        <p>While there will be plenty to divert audiences from the concerns of wartime in ''Shrek 2,'' ''Catwoman'' and the latest installment of Harry Potter, few in Hollywood have the stomach to blow up the White House on screen today, as in ''Independence Day,'' the summer blockbuster of 1996.</p>
        <p>Instead, this summer brings a host of violent, heroic battles that mirror, through Hollywood's fantasy lens, the violence on the nightly news. Except that on screen, reassuringly, the good guys tend to win.</p>
        <p>After ''Van Helsing'' comes a enormous $200 million battle epic from Warner Brothers, ''Troy,'' about the ancient clash between Sparta and Troy, directed by Wolfgang Petersen, known for straight-ahead action thrillers like ''The Perfect Storm'' and ''Air Force One.''</p>
        <p>July brings ''King Arthur,'' a Jerry Bruckheimer production that is a bloody retelling of the story of the knights of the Round Table. In this rendition they are fighting for the freedom to return to their homes abroad.</p>
        <p>''The knights,'' said Mr. Bruckheimer, one of the most successful producers in Hollywood, ''are like Special Forces, wherever they are now, fighting for another country. It's heroism, camaraderie, brotherhood. They are fighting for what they believe in, for the moral high ground -- all the kinds of themes I love.''</p>
        <p>Hollywood is expert at tacking with the zeitgeist, or at least gearing its marketing campaigns to the sentiment of the moment. Fast-changing events in Iraq -- rising American casualties and the latest prison abuse scandal -- may rattle the movie industry's working assumptions about how its summer movies will be received.</p>
        <p>But while America's enemies remain elusive and foreign engagements are morally murky, studio executives are betting that audiences will want to see pictures with identifiable villains and clear, resounding victories, set in distant times or fictional places.</p>
        <p>Traditional disaster pictures, or even contemporary war movies, they say, are too close to the real thing. ''Right now people don't want to see us lose,'' Stacey Snider, chairwoman of Universal Pictures, said.</p>
        <p>''As a consumer -- and it affects me as an executive -- when it's too real, when the danger is in our time, our world, I resist it. I have no room for fake fear or fake titillation when there is so much to be frightened of for real,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That was partly why Ms. Snider bought the pitch last year for ''Van Helsing'' from the writer and director Stephen Sommers, who had made the hit movies ''The Mummy'' and ''The Mummy Returns'' for Universal. She was struck by the word ''vanquish,'' which was in the script, and used it in the marketing the film.</p>
        <p>''It just feels so strong, like it's going to eradicate bad things,'' Ms. Snider said. ''It suggests to me that it's a personal mission. It's not a campaign of many people. It's a personal mission: 'I will take it upon myself to make you safe.' ''</p>
        <p>The film certainly lives up to that promise. Van Helsing, played by Hugh Jackman, spends almost all 125 minutes of the film relentlessly pounding monsters, from Dr. Jekyll to the Wolfman to Dracula, all nightmarish creatures who emerge from secret places and refuse to die.</p>
        <p>The movie made more than $100 million worldwide on its opening weekend, with $54 million in the United States and a total of $53 million in 41 other countries.</p>
        <p>Some film and social historians read these types of movies as thinly veiled wish-fulfillment fantasies in a complicated world, or even as a coping mechanism after a societywide trauma.</p>
        <p>''It is our way of dealing with a very complex thing for most of us,'' said Linda Voorhees, a screenwriter and visiting assistant professor at the School of Theater, Film and Television at the University of California, Los Angeles. ''This is our way of dealing with 9/11 and how we feel about those foreigners, and those terrorists, whom we are trying very hard to define.</p>
        <p>''In our nondefinition, we have a need to vilify, and these big pictures help the audience identify a villain,'' she said. ''The morality of these types of movies tend to be very black and white, very good good guy, very bad bad guy. That serves our purpose of 'we are good and they are bad.' These movies are very much that way.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Voorhees and others observed that societies needed time to assimilate trauma and to express it through popular culture. Movies take longer than most media, because of the time it takes to write scripts and produce and release the films, she noted.</p>
        <p>Still, the violence in a new age of terrorism has been evident in Hollywood for some months. In December movie screens were filled with bloody battlefields and epic conflict, from ''The Last Samurai'' to ''Cold Mountain'' to ''Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King.''</p>
        <p>This spring has brought a series of revenge pictures, from Quentin Tarantino's ''Kill Bill: Vol. 2'' to ''Man on Fire,'' with Denzel Washington as avenging angel, to ''The Punisher,'' whose very title bespeaks retribution.</p>
        <p>As the season of popcorn movies approaches, the theme is reflected not just in $200 million blockbusters, but in smaller-budget films like ''The Chronicles of Riddick,'' starring Vin Diesel as a renegade soldier battling aliens who impose their religion and culture on other planets, and Miramax's ''Blind Swordsman: Zatoichi,'' a Japanese cult hit about a sightless ''killing machine'' set in 19th-century samurai society.</p>
        <p>Not all the summer blockbusters fit this bill. ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' from 20th Century Fox, is more traditional, a disaster film about global warming by Roland Emmerich, the director who blew up the White House in ''Independence Day.''</p>
        <p>Some Hollywood films spend years in development before making it to theaters, but ''Troy,'' like ''Van Helsing,'' was conceived after 9/11. Warner Brothers bought the pitch of the screenwriter David Benioff (who got some help from Homer) in fall 2002, and approved production in February 2003.</p>
        <p>Studio executives said they were not specifically looking for a blockbuster war movie. But that seemed to be what leading writers and directors were offering.</p>
        <p>''It's a weird gestalt,'' Jeff Robinov, president of production at Warner Brothers, said. ''I don't say, 'I want a big, epic war movie this year.' We had already made 'The Last Samurai,' so the idea of another war, romance movie'' made him hesitate, he said. ''But we really liked the script.''</p>
        <p>''Troy'' turned out to be one of three period war films that the studio set in motion in a short period of time. After ''The Last Samurai'' came ''Troy,'' then Oliver Stone's ''Alexander,'' about Alexander the Great, scheduled for release this fall.</p>
        <p>''Troy'' is a glossy production starring Brad Pitt as Achilles, an unstoppable warrior with nary a battle scratch on his gleaming, muscled body, and with hundreds of computer-generated battleships plowing across the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>The image of two traditional armies facing each other on a vast battlefield, abiding by the codes of warfare and evoking -- as Achilles does -- respect even for one's enemy, seems a stark contrast to the messy war the United States faces in Iraq and against Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>''King Arthur,'' to be released by the Walt Disney Company, is a much grittier tale, about a Roman-born King Arthur who chooses to stay in England to defend the local ''freedom fighters'' against the invading Saxons.</p>
        <p>David Franzoni, who also wrote ''Gladiator,'' sold the idea for ''King Arthur'' in a pitch to Mr. Bruckheimer and wrote it in the summer of 2000. Mr. Franzoni called it more an allegory for the Vietnam War, which he opposed, than for Iraq.</p>
        <p>And he sees no connection in his work, or in the culture, to the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. ''I think 9/11 -- we've forgotten about it,'' he lamented. ''It's Busby Berkeley time. I think it's over with. We saw two towers knocked down. The trauma was maybe for 10 minutes.''</p>
        <p>He confessed to being deeply affected by the attack personally, but for him ''King Arthur'' was about individualism. ''Each of us is essentially a floating island,'' he said. ''We shouldn't be anchored to a point of view, a religion, a culture. We as individuals have to be strong enough to cast that aside and decide what's best for the universe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruckheimer, whose politics differ from Mr. Franzoni's, sees it differently. The movies are all about where society is as a whole, he said. ''We all want heroes now,'' he said. ''We'll never forget 9/11. It had such an emotional impact. Our world will never be the same because of it.''</p>
        <p>He mentioned Pat Tillman, the N.F.L. player who joined the Army Rangers after 9/11 and died in Iraq in April. ''We look for those kinds of lions, those heroes. They're hard to find,'' Mr. Bruckheimer said. ''It's hard to seek out the Tillmans, the Arthurs, the Achilles of the world. We have to pick up a history book.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 11, 2004, Tuesday  An article in The Arts yesterday about new and forthcoming Hollywood movies -- and their preoccupation with honor and heroism -- misidentified the country where the former National Football League player Pat Tillman was killed last month while serving as an Army Ranger. It was Afghanistan, not Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 11, 2004, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts yesterday about new and forthcoming Hollywood movies -- and their preoccupation with honor and heroism -- misidentified the country where the former National Football League player Pat Tillman was killed last month while serving as an Army Ranger. It was Afghanistan, not Iraq.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
