<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, We Have No Bananas, Yet</title>
    <meta content="01GARD$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/01/garden/01GARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1570738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="GARDEN NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Glen Cove (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Druse, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Robert (Glen Cove, NY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Garden Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0DE1439F932A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, We Have No Bananas, Yet</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yes, We Have No Bananas, Yet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN DRUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Druse, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Wong grows tropical plants in his small garden in Glen Cove, NY, well north of their natural growing zone; does not try to keep all his plants alive through winter; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a huge saucer magnolia on my property in New Jersey. In eight years I have seen it bloom perfectly only once. I call it the brown tissue tree, because each year, around April 22, a hard frost turns the budding pink flowers to mush.</p>
        <p>I did not plant this tree, and if it were not a century old, I might cut it down. (I might anyway.) Global warming aside, it is the wrong plant in the wrong place. But it shows that, even a century ago, gardeners were succumbing to what must be called ''zone denial.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Wong has turned his Glen Cove, N.Y., property into a tropical fantasy. But what happens to those tropical plants in winter?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a huge saucer magnolia on my property in New Jersey. In eight years I have seen it bloom perfectly only once. I call it the brown tissue tree, because each year, around April 22, a hard frost turns the budding pink flowers to mush.</p>
        <p>I did not plant this tree, and if it were not a century old, I might cut it down. (I might anyway.) Global warming aside, it is the wrong plant in the wrong place. But it shows that, even a century ago, gardeners were succumbing to what must be called ''zone denial.''</p>
        <p>Zone denial can fell gardeners in small ways, like growing a butterfly bush where it may or may not survive a bitter January like this year's. More and more gardeners are falling for tropicals and planting them as annuals. But few people have gone as far in zone denial -- or more precisely zone disregard -- as Robert Wong. He has turned his Glen Cove, N.Y., property into a tropical fantasy, with hibiscus, banana trees, taro and ginger. That is easy so long as the plants enjoy a hot and humid summer, familiar to most Americans. After that, he must decide whether to let them die, take cuttings or try to keep them alive in the basement for another year.</p>
        <p>Some tender perennials, like impatiens and begonias, grow all year long in the tropics. Luckily for Northern gardeners most of them are inexpensive and easy to replace. Mr. Wong's garden, on less than a fifth of an acre, will have lots of Blue Angel impatiens this year, covered with lavender flowers on two-foot tall plants with purplish-green leaves. His begonia, species unknown, topped out last year at five feet with leaves as large as dessert plates. He cut back the behemoth, lifted it and put it in a pot to carry over in a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>When one realizes the possibilities tropical plants offer, the candy store opens with a selection of weird and extraordinary items. With ample moisture, tender perennials grow fast, and they grow big. In Mr. Wong's Lilliputian garden, entering its fifth year, plants are often Brobdingnagian. Just consider the variety of rice paper plant called Tetrapanax papyrifera Steroidal Giant. And his Abyssinian banana plant, which reaches the second story of the foursquare bungalow that Mr. Wong, a professional gardener, and Colin Storrie, the grounds manager for an estate, bought in 1999. That banana is planted each year in late May, when neighboring gardeners are putting in their flats of impatiens.</p>
        <p>And the banana is hardly an extravagance. A two-foot-tall banana plant costs about $15. It used to be that anyone hoping to grow the tropical banana would have to order one from a specialty mail-order nursery. Not anymore.</p>
        <p>The interest in growing tender perennials far outside their tropical zones began a dozen years ago in a few wholesale nurseries that sold to professionals doing containers. Then local nurseries began offering them to everyone.</p>
        <p>Now, one can find golden sweet potato vine at nearly any nursery in the country. Every now and then, a banana plant will turn up at the Home Depot or Lowe's. Mr. Wong knows how to get plants from catalogs, wholesale suppliers and colleagues, but he still keeps an eye out for oddities that might show up at the big box stores or even the supermarket. The big-leaf taro, for example, can be bought at a grocer that specializes in selling Caribbean vegetables, and then grown in the garden.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Wong and Mr. Storrie first saw their house, built in 1929, it had suffered numerous misguided remodelings. Few people would have seen the potential. The garden was not much to look at, either. The driveway had a view of junked cars. An old grapevine and several wisteria plants needed serious renovation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wong trained the grape to grow over a trellis designed and built by Mr. Storrie, who has a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree from Purchase College of the State University of New York. ''Robert does most of the garden,'' said Mr. Storrie, an amateur chef who built his own kitchen. ''I do the carpentry.''</p>
        <p>The taro Mr. Wong grows is not destined for Mr. Storrie's kitchen, however. It is an ornamental variety of elephant ears with near-black leaves. The plants are available at nurseries specializing in water gardens and by mail order for $10 to $20. The black taro's leaves are a dramatic background for a nearby flowering maple with shell pink flowers. The variegated Angels' Trumpets get their name from their flaring, tubular flowers. Angels' Trumpets are considered poisonous or at least psychotropic, so like most plants not known to be edible, they are best left in the garden.</p>
        <p>The six-foot-tall Angels' Trumpets, which are related to datura or locoweed, dangles its white 10-inch-long blossoms in Mr. Wong's garden, filling the air at dusk with the scent of vanilla.</p>
        <p>But what happens to those tropical plants in winter? He does not try to keep them all alive. ''I tried with that banana, but it turned to mush,'' he said. And besides, he is happy to plunk down cash for a new one, because he knows a two-foot tree can grow 10 feet in just one summer. (And some people are proud of their tomato plants!)</p>
        <p>He keeps some of his favorites, like the Angels' Trumpets, in his basement, where winter temperatures may dip to 40 degrees. Two windows supply enough light to keep the plants alive, but for all intents and purposes, the plants are dormant, kept dry and cool in suspended animation. On a warm weekend, like last weekend, the plants are taken up to the garden shed staging area (read garage) in preparation for outdoor planting after all danger of frost has passed, around the first of May.</p>
        <p>I</p>
        <p>STORE many of my tender perennials,'' Mr. Wong said. Cannas and dahlias are left in the garden until the first frost blackens their foliage. Then the rhizomes and tubers can be dug up, wrapped in newspaper and stored in boxes. The tubers and rhizomes should be kept barely moist, so they do not dry completely, but not too wet, or they will rot. The dormant roots are kept in a cool area of the basement where the temperature remains reliably above freezing.</p>
        <p>But some plants, like begonias and coleus, do not go dormant. Thus Mr. Wong roots cuttings or digs up small plants for next year's garden.</p>
        <p>''I usually take just a few,'' he said. He has the advantage of a benevolent friend with a little extra room in his greenhouse.</p>
        <p>The seasonal fireworks of Mr. Wong's garden provide a boon to the neighborhood. Oglers stroll by in the evening to gawk at his unconventional plantings, craning their necks as if expecting to spot Dorothy Lamour hiding behind a huge leaf.</p>
        <p>Come summer, the glory bush, or Tibouchina heteromalla, will have square stems and round leaves covered in silver hairs and will sprout an 18-inch-tall panicle with vivid lilac-purple flowers. (It may be hard to find, but goes for $6.50 for a small plant at Kartuz Greenhouses, in Vista, Calif., www.kartuzs .com.)</p>
        <p>And not all of Mr. Wong's tropicals are giants. His exquisite little Aristolochia fimbriata, or ''eyelash'' Dutchman's pipe, has a teaspoon-size flower. (It can be ordered from from Plant Delights Nursery in Raleigh, N.C. for $18; www.plantdelights.com.)</p>
        <p>Every spring Mr. Wong has some surprises, for example, the cannas that actually survived a mild winter. But he does not expect many happy results from this last challenging winter, especially since he had no snow cover until January. There are plenty of new things on his wish list, however, like a ground-covering taro, Colocasia fallax, and an upright fuchsia with tubular pink flowers, called Trautchen.</p>
        <p>With the plants dug up, moved or deceased this winter, and two months to go before he can begin moving them outdoors, Mr. Wong has had to enjoy the view of his empty pots. ''I love Vietnamese pots,'' he said, indicating some lapis blue and turquoise ones. They are high-fired for their glazes. ''I was thrilled that they didn't crack in the winter, and I love the Day-Glo colors.''</p>
        <p>As for myself, and my own zone denial, I covet one plant Mr. Wong has, a marginally hardy evergreen tree, Magnolia grandiflora, a prehistoric relic of a time when much of North America was hot and humid year-round. It is a variety called D. D. Blanchard and is sometimes available from the more esoteric nurseries. But I had never seen it in the flesh before spotting it at Mr. Wong's, and I did not realize it grew as a slender column.</p>
        <p>''Oh, it doesn't,'' Mr. Wong said. ''We had an ice storm two years ago, and it had to be pruned.''</p>
        <p>It seems one can challenge the gods only up to a point, even in Mr. Wong's virtual tropical paradise.</p>
        <p>0 to 6 Feet in a Summer</p>
        <p>Caladiums are familiar, cheerful plants that rarely grow taller than two or three feet. Their cousins, the taro or elephant ear or Colocasia, may grow to six feet in a single summer. Leafless taro tubers can be found at garden centers now to pot up and grow indoors until May, and you can find some of the more esoteric plants with variegated foliage, red stems or pure black leaves from specialty plants suppliers like the ones below. On the North Fork of Long Island, there is S. Scherer &amp; Sons in Northport; (631) 261-7432 or, in New Jersey, Waterford Gardens in Saddle River (201) 327-0721.</p>
        <p>An Imperial taro, a black-leaf elephant ear with green veins, is $18, and a hazy purple Burgundy Stem elephant ear is $22 at Plant Delights Nursery in Raleigh, N.C.; www.plantdelights.com; (919) 772-4794. The nursery has 13 varieties of taro.</p>
        <p>Singing Springs Nursery in Cedar Grove, N.C., has exotics like Ruffles, Chicago Harlequin and Nancy's Revenge, which looks like a mammoth hosta, $16 each; www.singingspringsnursery.com or (919) 732-9403.</p>
        <p>Taros are also sold at the Crownsville Nursery of Strasburg, Va.; www.crownsvillenursery.com or (540) 631-9411.</p>
        <p>KEN DRUSE</p>
        <p>GARDEN NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
