<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Prankster Invasion In the Elephant House</title>
    <meta content="04YES$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/04/movies/MoviesFeatures/04yes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1608825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yes Men (Performance Artists)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bichlbaum, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bonanno, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Yes Men (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Republican National Convention</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D91031F937A3575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Prankster Invasion In the Elephant House</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Prankster Invasion in the Elephant House</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andy Bichlbaum and Mike Bonanno, pair of politically charged performance artists known as Yes Men, pulled stunts on Republicans visiting New York City during Republican National Convention; crashed Madison Square Garden posing as fans of Bush administration's global warming policies and organized team to distribute fake Bush campaign fliers along with stickers advertising Yes Men movie, set to open on September 24; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yes Men, a pair of politically charged performance artists whose anticorporate mockery at World Trade Organization meetings is chronicled in a new documentary film, were taking aim this week at President Bush and the party faithful at the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>Andy Bichlbaum and Mike Bonanno, who impersonate World Trade Organization officials with wild costumes and even wackier ideas, pulled similar stunts on the Republicans to promote their political ideas and, not incidentally, the independent film, which United Artists will open in New York and Los Angeles on Sept. 24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yes Men, a pair of politically charged performance artists chronicled in a new documentary, took aim this week at the Republican convention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yes Men, a pair of politically charged performance artists whose anticorporate mockery at World Trade Organization meetings is chronicled in a new documentary film, were taking aim this week at President Bush and the party faithful at the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>Andy Bichlbaum and Mike Bonanno, who impersonate World Trade Organization officials with wild costumes and even wackier ideas, pulled similar stunts on the Republicans to promote their political ideas and, not incidentally, the independent film, which United Artists will open in New York and Los Angeles on Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>The two crashed Madison Square Garden posing as fans of the administration's global warming policies. Inside, they sought out and heaped insincere praise on Energy Secretary Spencer Abraham and Newt Gingrich, the former speaker of the House. At the protests outside the convention hall, they organized a street team to distribute thousands of fake Bush campaign fliers along with stickers advertising the ''Yes Men'' movie. One pamphlet, mocking the Patriot Act, encouraged individuals to ''take the USA Patriot Pledge'' and volunteer to have a ''permanent nuclear waste storage facility'' in their communities; another brochure parodied a ''Let's Go'' budget travel guide with tips on how to dress like a Republican and ''where to get born again, again'' on a ''God-themed'' Big Apple tour. They even said that they outfitted a fake Bush-Cheney campaign bus with a miniature oil rig on the roof, but it broke down on its way to New York.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to do the same thing now with Bush that we did with the W.T.O.,'' Mr. Bichl said. The Yes Men, who call their impersonations ''identity corrections,'' hoped these routines would expose administration hypocrisy and generate publicity, as their activities did five years ago when their scathing Internet parody of Mr. Bush provoked him to file a complaint with the Federal Election Commission.</p>
        <p>While they try to deliver serious messages with their pranks, they also hope to draw attention to their film amid a crowded slate of political documentaries this campaign season. Piggybacking on presidential politics takes a page out of the Michael Moore marketing strategy for ''Fahrenheit 9/11,'' but executives at United Artists say that unorthodox promotional methods may be the best way to reach a niche audience of sophisticated young people. ''Ultimately, the way you get people to see this movie is through word of mouth,'' said Danny Rosett, the president of United Artists.</p>
        <p>In its marketing efforts, the studio has steered away from national television advertising for a targeted campaign in alternative papers like the satirical Onion. Over the next few weeks, the studio will sponsor a ''Yes Men'' movie Web site featuring a campaign blog. (The two men maintain a separate faux campaign Web site that parodies the Bush-Cheney ticket's.) The studio has offered college professors in New York City and Los Angeles free copies of the ''Yes Men'' book, based on the film, to spark student interest.</p>
        <p>And though United Artists is quick to distance itself from endorsing the pair's political antics, it has conveniently scheduled screenings and media events along the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>''We are in the business of supporting movies, not supporting candidates,'' Mr. Rosett said. The Yes Men, he added, plan and pay for their own stunts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bichlbaum said that this week, posing as a Danish radio team, the Yes Men obtained what he claimed was a copy of a 210-page convention script. ''Every single word was scripted, even the votes,'' he said. He thumbed through a document to find the Tuesday night section with the governor of California's speech, full of three-word teleprompter phrases. ''Arnold reads in haiku,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
