<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opposition Surfaces To Gas Plant Proposal</title>
    <meta content="19WEGAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1635829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liquefied Natural Gas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iroquois Natural Gas Pipeline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Broadwater Energy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E2DB1430F93AA25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opposition Surfaces To Gas Plant Proposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental groups on Long Island and in Connecticut rally opposition to proposal by Broadwater Energy Corp to build floating liquefied natural gas plant in center of Long Island Sound and 25-mile-long pipeline that would feed gas into Iroquois pipeline in Sound; say project would decrease incentives to develop renewable energy resources, lead to continued dependence on foreign sources of fossil fuel and set precedent for industrializing and privatizing Sound; proponents of plan stress need for energy; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the first sign of slowly stirring opposition to a proposal for a $700 million floating gas plant the size of the Queen Mary 2 that would be permanently moored in Long Island Sound, one Long Island group has voted to oppose the project as an environmental and safety risk.</p>
        <p>''We thought it was important that we make a statement loud and clear and early about this project,'' said Sid Bail, the president of the group, the Wading River Civic Association. ''It sounds to us like the industrialization of the Sound.'' Nine directors in the association voted to oppose the plant, and one was undecided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the first sign of slowly stirring opposition to a proposal for a $700 million floating gas plant the size of the Queen Mary 2 that would be permanently moored in Long Island Sound, one Long Island group has voted to oppose the project as an environmental and safety risk.</p>
        <p>''We thought it was important that we make a statement loud and clear and early about this project,'' said Sid Bail, the president of the group, the Wading River Civic Association. ''It sounds to us like the industrialization of the Sound.'' Nine directors in the association voted to oppose the plant, and one was undecided.</p>
        <p>The Broadwater Energy Corporation of Houston, a partnership formed by the TransCanada Corporation of Calgary, Alberta, and Shell U.S. Gas and Power of Houston, an affiliate of the Royal Dutch/Shell Group, proposed the plant last month after two years of searching for a site.</p>
        <p>If the project gets federal and state approval, the plant could be operating by 2010 in New York waters 11 miles south of the Connecticut coast and 9 miles north of Wading River and its neighbor, Shoreham. A floating plant would be safer and less environmentally intrusive than a plant on land, Broadwater says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bail said he had no illusions that the opposition of his 200-member group would change the outcome unless other civic and environmental groups, including many that were part of the years of struggle to stop the Shoreham nuclear power plant from opening, joined in the new fight.</p>
        <p>''To say that we are tiny is very kind,'' Mr. Bail said. ''I see us as a flea on the buttocks of Shell Oil. And unless there is sustained support from civic, environmental and political leaders, our opposition will be a hollow gesture.''</p>
        <p>Some support has already arrived. The directors of the Rocky Point Civic Association have voted unanimously to oppose the project. On Tuesday, the directors of the Affiliated Brookhaven Civic Organization voted 8 to 0 to oppose the project. The group, known as ABCO, represents 40 civic groups in the Town of Brookhaven.</p>
        <p>Thalia Bouklas, ABCO's president, said the project would decrease incentives to develop renewable energy resources, would lead to continued dependence on foreign sources of fossil fuel and would set a precedent for industrializing and privatizing Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>Richard Johannesen, a lawyer from Rocky Point who represents ABCO, said opposition was spreading along the North Shore.</p>
        <p>''We just found out about this project two weeks ago, and so Broadwater got a two-year head start,'' he said. ''They may not know yet that they have stumbled into a hornet's nest, but they will very soon.''</p>
        <p>Federal, state and local officials have so far taken no position on the project and say they want to hear more from the public and from experts before making judgments.</p>
        <p>Broadwater has hired Robert J. Gaffney, the former Suffolk county executive, and John Gallagher, a former Suffolk police commissioner, as consultants. It has also hired Giuliani Partners, whose principal is former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, to handle security for the project.</p>
        <p>Broadwater, which has opened an office in Riverhead, immediately expressed regret over the Wading River group's position.</p>
        <p>In a news release dated Dec. 13, Broadwater said it was disappointed that the group had ''taken a decision on the project in this early stage of a multiyear process to identify impacts, benefits and potential ways to achieve a balance that addressed long-term energy needs of the region.''</p>
        <p>John Hritcko, the regional project director for Broadwater, rejected Mr. Bail's argument that the plant would industrialize the Sound. ''We don't agree that it is industrialization, nor is there any indication that having this facility will lead to having other such facilities in this region,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the Citizens Campaign for the Environment in Farmingdale said the project was massive and inappropriate.</p>
        <p>''It represents a taking of Long Island Sound by the oil industry, and the public has to say no,'' said Adrienne Esposito, the executive director.</p>
        <p>Broadwater says the project will provide needed natural gas to Long Island and the New York metropolitan area. Tankers would deliver liquefied natural gas to the plant, which would store it and then convert to a gaseous state.</p>
        <p>Up to one billion cubic feet of natural gas a day would flow from the plant to the Iroquois pipeline through a 25-mile-long connecting pipeline in the Sound seabed. While more than 30 liquefied natural gas plants are currently proposed around the country, the Long Island Sound project would be the first floating plant in the country. It would store the equivalent of eight billion cubic feet of natural gas, or more than twice Broadwater's estimate of the average daily use -- 3.8 billion cubic feet -- for New York and Connecticut combined.</p>
        <p>The tankers serving the proposed plant would be capable of carrying the equivalent of 2.5 billion cubic feet of gas. It would be cooled to minus-260 degrees to liquefy it for more compact and less volatile shipment. Even so, its explosive power would be immense, and opponents say such an explosion would be cataclysmic.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
