<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Science Adviser's Rejoinder</title>
    <meta content="10SAT1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/10/opinion/10SAT1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1573002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Union of Concerned Scientists</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marburger, John H III (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Union of Concerned Scientists</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marburger, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D71338F933A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Science Adviser's Rejoinder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Science Adviser's Rejoinder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that report by White House science adviser John Marburger III was meant to rebut accusations that Bush administration systematically distorted or suppressed scientific information that would conflict with its policy preferences; holds that unpersuasive document was little more than attempt to put positive spin on some 'flagrant examples' of tailoring science to fit politics</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president's science adviser issued a report last week meant to rebut accusations that the Bush administration has systematically distorted or suppressed scientific information that would conflict with its policy preferences. On several issues of real import, this detailed but ultimately unpersuasive document was little more than an attempt to put a positive spin on some flagrant examples of tailoring science to fit politics.</p>
        <p>The long-simmering issue was brought to a boil in February when the Union of Concerned Scientists, a liberal advocacy group, issued a highly critical report of the administration's handling of science and a passel of prominent scientists, including 20 Nobel laureates, endorsed the concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Marburger's report, intended to rebut accusations of tailoring science to fit politics, is more evasion than evaluation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president's science adviser issued a report last week meant to rebut accusations that the Bush administration has systematically distorted or suppressed scientific information that would conflict with its policy preferences. On several issues of real import, this detailed but ultimately unpersuasive document was little more than an attempt to put a positive spin on some flagrant examples of tailoring science to fit politics.</p>
        <p>The long-simmering issue was brought to a boil in February when the Union of Concerned Scientists, a liberal advocacy group, issued a highly critical report of the administration's handling of science and a passel of prominent scientists, including 20 Nobel laureates, endorsed the concerns.</p>
        <p>On some points, we are inclined to agree with the point-by-point rebuttal issued by John Marburger III, the White House science adviser. Although the critics complained that a former Congressional staffer without professional training had been made Dr. Marburger's deputy, surely Dr. Marburger has the right to appoint a deputy he deems well qualified to improve coordination with Congress and other agencies.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marburger has also found some other errors or overstatements in the critics' attack. But on many substantive issues, his defense sounds more like bureaucratic evasion than a candid evaluation. The critics complained, for example, that the administration diluted criteria that would be used to evaluate the performance of abstinence-only education programs so as to obscure their lack of efficacy. Instead of measuring such real outcomes as the proportion of students who engage in sexual intercourse despite taking the programs or the rate of births to female participants, the measures were revised to focus on attitudes and intentions, such as a commitment to abstain from sexual activity until marriage. Dr. Marburger offers the lame excuse that the program was never designed to produce useful scientific data and that other long-range evaluation efforts are under way to assess the effectiveness of abstinence-only education.</p>
        <p>That same ploy -- taking refuge in the need for further research -- was trotted out on the important issue of global warming. Dr. Marburger justified elimination of material that linked climate change to human activities from an Environmental Protection Agency report last year by asserting that the E.P.A. had not adequately addressed the complexities and that a far more expansive exposition was soon to be published as part of the administration's climate change plan. That pat explanation glided past the fact that the E.P.A. document was apt to attract attention, whereas the administration's plan calls for a lot more research in lieu of prompt action.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marburger claimed that the National Academy of Sciences had given a ''highly favorable review'' of the administration's climate research plan but failed to mention that the academy expressed doubt that it would be adequately financed and worried about ''a real or perceived political influence that could discredit the program.''</p>
        <p>None of the critics are attacking Dr. Marburger personally. He is a respected physicist and lifelong Democrat who would not seem an automatic apologist for this administration. The question yet to be answered is whether he is speaking from conviction when he claims that the critics are off base or is serving as a frontman for an administration whose activities in this area are sometimes hard to defend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
