<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="28ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/28/arts/design/28ART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DF123EF93BA15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="8417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Nationalgalerie Berlin has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Nationalgalerie Berlin has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''THE ART DECO BOOKBINDINGS OF PIERRE LEGRAIN AND ROSE ADLER,'' New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089, through June 12. The achievement of two French bookbinders is showcased in this sumptuous exhibition of 45 hand-bound rare editions and manuscripts of major French writers from Stendhal to Breton, commissioned by the couturier, collector and philanthropist Jacques Doucet. Only a few have been exhibited before. Their extraordinary exteriors are usually treated as a single flat surface and decorated with bold geometric designs, accented with crocodile, lizard, snakeskin, metal and gemstone. Legrain and Adler are credited with modernizing bookbinding and the show leaves little doubt that they did. Hours: Tuesdays and Wednesdays, 11 a.m. to 7:30 p.m.; Thursdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Free (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''BYZANTIUM: FAITH AND POWER (1261-1557),'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through July 4. This vast and humblingly beautiful show about the waning centuries of the Byzantine empire reminds us that political decay does does not necessarily mean artistic decline. Full of amazing exotica -- manuscripts, miniature mosaics, textiles, drawings, paintings -- the exhibition ends with a room of great Northern Renaissance art indebted to icons that proves Byzantium's continued reach. People who are not Eastern Orthodox believers can enjoy the earthly pleasures of aesthetic spectacle linked with historical enlightenment. Hours: Sundays, this Monday only (Memorial Day) and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $7 (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''CORPORAL IDENTITY -- BODY LANGUAGE,'' Museum of Arts and Design, 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535, through June 4. Skin, hair, orifices, veins, organs, face, feet, sex, birth, disease, plastic surgery, mind-body connections, human cloning and so on come under the relentless scrutiny of the 200-odd German and American participants in this anthology of attitudes toward the body. The show's premise is that given today's view of the body as a repairable, nearly replaceable, longer-than-life object, artists and artisans are exploring all kinds of ways of expressing new views about it. The old craft standbys like ceramics, wood, glass, metal, fiber and fabric play important roles, but so do advanced new techniques and media, some derived from medical and computer technology. Leave the children at home. Hours: Daily, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $8; students and 65+, $5 (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''FROM THE CLASSROOM TO THE WORLD: HINE, ULMANN, STRAND, ARBUS AND THE ETHICAL CULTURE FIELDSTON SCHOOL,'' New-York Historical Society, 2 West 77th Street, (212) 873-3400, through July 18. A persuasive pitch for the influence of the high-minded, progressive Ethical Culture Fieldston School on four famous photographers: Lewis W. Hine, Doris Ulmann, Paul Strand and Diane Arbus. As a young teacher there, Hine (1874-1940) discovered his own photographic talent and went on to become one of the great documentary photographers of the poor and oppressed in the United States. Ulmann's tenure at the school strengthened her budding social consciousness; Strand was directly mentored by Hine; and Arbus, who received all her formal education there, developed her own vision of the outsider side of everyday life. Along with rather dull photographs of the school, examples of their work are displayed. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; $3 for students and 65+ (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''OPEN HOUSE: WORKING IN BROOKLYN,'' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, through Aug. 15. This all-Brooklyn show of new art has been timed to coincide with the inauguration of the museum's new front entrance pavilion and public plaza. With 300 pieces installed in the fourth- and fifth-floor galleries, and spilling over into the permanent collection galleries, it's a very crowded affair. It's also all over the place in terms of media, styles and themes, not to mention quality; the good, the bad and the iffy mingle. Still there's plenty of good work by artists you know and by some you don't, drawn from across a borough that has many different art worlds. Also on view, though not part of the show, is Alexis Rockman's mural-size painting of Brooklyn 3,000 years in the future, submerged under water as a result of global warming. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 11 p.m. the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $6; $3 for students and 62+ (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>''THE PIERRE AND MARIA-GAETANA MATISSE COLLECTION,'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710), through June 26, 2005, in three installments. This heterogeneous array of paintings, sculptures and works on paper was once owned by the Manhattan-based art dealer Pierre Matisse (1900-1989) and his wife, Maria-Gaetana (1943-2001). Most of the material came to the Met after Mrs. Matisse's death. It includes sexy paintings by Balthus, Magritte and Wifredo Lam, batty ones by Jean Dubuffet, and a feminist icon in a self-portrait by Leonora Carrington. A selection of the rich, calm, pleasurable art of Henri Matisse, Pierre's father, takes pride of place. Hours and admission: See above (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''ROTH TIME: A DIETER ROTH RETROSPECTIVE,'' Museum of Modern Art, Queens, 45-20 33rd Street, at Queens Boulevard, Long Island City, (212) 708-9400, and P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084, through June 7. This exhaustive, exhausting but ultimately astounding exhibition offers total immersion in the art of the German-born, Swiss-based multimedia dynamo Dieter Roth (1930-1998), who not only erased the line between art and life, but also fused them into a single insoluble entity. With nearly 400 works of painting, drawing, prints, sculpture, assemblage, collage, music, poetry, film, photography, video and sound, and using every imaginable kind of found object or material -- foodstuffs included -- the exhibition moves through 50 years of incessant, obsessive art-making with remarkable clarity. It culminates in a presentation of five enormous installation pieces at the Modern's little-sister institution, P.S. 1, that reveal a seemingly boundless universe of artistic activity and a radically new picture of an artist at work. MoMA Queens hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays to 7:45 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $8.50. P.S. 1 hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $2 (Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''FRED WILSON, OBJECTS AND INSTALLATIONS: 1979-2000,'' Studio Museum in Harlem, 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, through July 4. Mr. Wilson, who represented the United States at the 2003 Venice Biennale, made his reputation with conceptually pointed, technically polished and visually engaging installations and objects that focused on excavating American racial history and illustrating the exclusionary power of cultural institutions shaped by social, economic and ideological domination. Elements of his subversive museum projects appear in this traveling show, along with sculptures and a fine, short new film. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $3; children under 12, $1 (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* ''GARDEN IN DELFT: WILLEM DE KOONING LANDSCAPES 1928-1988,'' Mitchell-Innes &amp; Nash, 1018 Madison Avenue, near 78th Street, (212) 744-7400, through June 26. For the centennial of Willem de Kooning's birth, this exhibition of 14 canvases represents a jubilant skip through his long career, with emphasis on his relationship to landscape. Never mind that the suggestion of abstracted still lifes sometimes seems equally strong, especially in two unfamiliar canvases from the late 1930's. A third painting, titled ''Still Life'' and dated circa 1929, may well be the earliest de Kooning painting most of us have ever seen. Its crisp shapes and deep primary colors suggest the influence of Joseph Stella and look forward to David Hockney. A second de Kooning tribute, at the Richard Gray Gallery upstairs through tomorrow, features four paintings from the 1940's and 50's that lean toward, or land in, the realm of figuration (Smith).</p>
        <p>* JEFF KOONS, ''Highlights of 25 Years,'' C&amp;M Arts, 45 East 78th Street, (212) 861-0020, through June 5. This excellent 27-piece survey touches on all phases of Mr. Koons's career, including greatest hits like the basketballs mysteriously hovering in aquarium tanks; the Mylar ''Rabbit'' balloon cast in shiny stainless steel; and the sexy blonde embracing the Pink Panther in glazed ceramic. The climax of the show is the 10-foot-tall ''Balloon Dog.'' Made of stainless steel and coated in coppery translucent orange, it is a breathtaking symbol of the inflationary euphoria and anxiety of our times (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>JORGE PARDO, Lever House Lobby Gallery, 400 Park Avenue, between 53rd and 54th Streets, there is no phone through July 31. If Ikea sold sculptures, they might look like the ones Mr. Pardo installed in the lobby of this famous Modernist high-rise: squat wooden constructions resembling the skeletons of biomorphic chairs, with attractive colored glass lights nested like eggs in the depressions where you sit. Curiously, the plywood elements that touch the floor have been cut into the silhouettes of animal feet: hooves, bear paws or tentacles (Johnson).</p>
        <p>FRANK STELLA, ''Exotic Birds,'' Gagosian Gallery, 980 Madison Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 744-2313, through June 5. Looking at Mr. Stella's three big, splashily painted reliefs from a 1976 series, it is easy to forget how shockingly flamboyant they seemed in their day. Now, with their curvy, tilting forms cut from honeycomb-core aluminum panels, and neatly puzzled together within wide slanting frames, they seem prettily demure compared to what has happened since in painting as well as in sculpture (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''WEEGEE'S STORY,'' Ubu, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444, through July 23. Wielding his 4-by-5 Speed Graphic with a master's touch, the New York tabloid photographer Weegee probably shot more murders and fires during his heyday, the 1930's and 40's, than anyone in the business. But his passion for the city also drew him to its many other photo opportunities: the strivers and the homeless, festivities and freaks, politicians and celebrities, posh avenues and mean streets. This show of 220 Weegee vintage photographs, culled from a collection assembled over a 30-year period by the Berlin dealer Hendrik Berinson, reveals his remarkable range (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>ANDREA CHAMPLIN/RACHEL URKOWITZ, Michael Steinberg, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 924-5770, through June 18. The two artists appear in separate rooms, but they share a devotion to energetically animated abstraction. Ms. Champlin's big, explosive paintings of pixilated, balloonlike volumes and other bulbous forms are based on digitally scrambled self-portrait photographs. Ms. Urkowitz makes lively collages on large, irregularly shaped sheets of paper, combining passages of Cubist crystallization, biomorphic Surrealism and trippy doodlelike forms. She also presents a series of goofy, free-standing sculptures: oversize cartoon daisies neatly laser-cut from sheets of colored plastic (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* WILLEM DE KOONING, ''A Centennial Celebration,'' Gagosian, 555 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 941-1111, through June 19. This beautifully installed 40-work survey begins with several previously unexhibited late ''ribbon'' paintings with their wafting, tangling strands of color that intimate both landscapes and still lifes but are, above all, abstract. The presentation seems to argue that de Kooning, like his younger colleague Philip Guston, would still have ample art historical stature had he made no other paintings than these, produced during the decade before he descended into Alzheimer's disease. But the show then backtracks through most of the artist's development, making the counter argument by demonstrating the many divergent and crisscrossing paths he took to reach his final distillation (Smith).</p>
        <p>EDGAR JERINS, Tatistcheff, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 627-4547, through June 12. The dramatically lighted realist images that Mr. Jerins draws, in charcoal on sheets of paper measuring about 5 by 8 feet, look like scenes from novels by Russell Banks. There's an air of grim desperation in his self-portrait with his two daughters and his pregnant, exhausted-looking wife, posed in a cramped bedroom and subtitled, ''We Need to Move.'' The portrait of a hunter with a shotgun in his tidy living room -- with a little girl and two women, one pregnant -- projects an unsettling hint of possible violence (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DOUG OHLSON, Andre Zarre, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 255-0202, through June 19. Pure formalism with an emphasis on color is not the most fashionable approach to painting these days, which makes Mr. Ohlson's pulsating stripe paintings all the more gratifying to behold. On horizontal canvases, the artist, who is 78, paints vertical bands, some hard-edged, some brushy, in hues that range from glowing sherbets to deep, near-black blues. He orchestrates a rich wedding of Puritanism and hedonism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* CLAES OLDENBURG AND COOSJE VAN BRUGGEN, ''Images à la Carte,'' Paula Cooper, 534 West 21st Street, (212) 255-1105, through July 2. Made mostly on blue-lined notebook pages the size of index cards, using pencil, ink and watercolor, these wonderfully lively and keenly observed drawings depict shrimp cocktails, crabcakes, salads, sandwiches, a banana split, tarts, cheesecakes and other elaborate restaurant fare, interspersed with simpler items like a lemon slice, an apple core and a piece of cornbread. Mr. Oldenburg drew them; his longtime partner, Ms. van Bruggen, contributed ideas (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''SYMMETRIES,'' Senior &amp; Shopmaker, 21 East 26th Street, (212) 213-6767, through June 30. The four sculptors in this fine exhibition are like cousins with shared as well as divergent interests. The show features a vibrant and whirling new wall painting by Sol LeWitt; an elegant arrangement of three-dimensional geometrical elements by Barry LeVa; a surprising early Cubist assemblage of unfinished boards by Richard Artschwager; and a conflation of vernacular architecture and Constructivist sculpture by Siah Armajani (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''TERRORVISION,'' Exit Art, 475 10th Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 966-7745, through July 31. Terror comes in all sizes, shapes and degrees, and this show runs the gamut, with exhibits by some 50-odd artists facing up to their most ''extreme fears'' -- from the general threats posed by Al Quaeda and its franchises to the traumas of personal catastrophe like toothache, breast cancer and heart operations. The gallery's multidisciplinary emphasis is manifest in film, video, audio and computer-generated creations, along with media as simple as prints and photographs. It's a mix of successful efforts and some that don't quite make it, the lightweight with the more substantial. But it's alive and kicking (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>''DOGS + CATS,'' American Primitive, 594 Broadway, near Houston Street, (212) 966-1530, through June 12. This lively exhibition includes more than 60 feline or canine representations in two or three dimensions. Some are by self-taught artists. A big colorful painting by Jean Metcalf has cats and dogs in it but features a formal parade of rats carrying wounded birds on stretchers. Many are by unknown craftsmen, like the smoothly carved wooden head of a boxer with brown glass eyes and the functional dog-shaped bench in the form of a wooden slab with branches that have been turned into legs (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* TONY FEHER, ''The Wart on the Bosom of Mother Nature,'' D'Amelio Terras, 525 West 22nd Street, (212) 352-9460, through July 2. Mr. Feher makes wryly poetic and visually enchanting sculptures out of the least promising of materials: plastic and glass bottles and bottle caps, foam packing material, bent wire, soda stacking crates, marbles, colored string, crushed aluminum foil and stones. A pyramid of green plastic strawberry baskets has a luminous, dematerialized look. A collection of brown bottles stopped by red and blue marbles is captivatingly sensuous and obliquely political (Johnson).</p>
        <p>ANISH KAPOOR, Barbara Gladstone, 515 West 24th Street, (212) 206-9300, through June 25. Mr. Kapoor is the master of a certain sculptural paradox. He makes abstract sculptures that are powerfully and often luxuriously physical, but which have an apparently immaterial dimension. The four concave sides of ''Whiteout'' bend inward to what seems an impossible extent. ''Vortex,'' a shiny black circle built into the wall, recedes inward like a whirlpool toward a deep, dark and apparently limitless space. The effect is hair-raising (Johnson).</p>
        <p>LAMAR PETERSON, ''Milk and Cookies,'' Deitch Projects, 26 Wooster Street, (212) 343-7300, through June 5. The basic ingredients of Mr. Peterson's paintings seem friendly enough: tropical vacation spots, cute pets, quality family time. So does the tasty, candy-colored cartoon-realist style he has couched them in. But something -- maybe everything -- is wrong in this inorganically Disneyesque world, populated exclusively by African-Americans and robots. The racial dimension stands out at first, but the stereotypes he deals with are those of middle-class culture at large, one glutted on fantasies of perfection and excess (Cotter).</p>
        <p>HOWARDENA PINDELL, ''Works on Paper 1968-2004,'' Sragow, 73 Spring Street, (212) 219-1793, through June 5. Ms. Pindell belongs to an understudied generation of African-American artists who were working with abstract painting and sculpture in the 1960's and 70's. The earliest drawings in this jewel-like show are composed of sequences of words and numbers arranged in patterns on graph paper and suggest roots in postminimalism. Later she made collages of small circles, hand-punched from sheets of blank or printed paper. In her recent three-dimensional prints, the dots are suspended in clusters on grids made of threads, and the early words and numbers become the names and coordinates of constellations (Cotter).</p>
        <p>GERHARD RICHTER, ''Two Sculptures for a Room by Palermo,'' Peter Freeman, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 966-5154, through June 26. Here is one of the very few sculptures made by Mr. Richter, the immensely influential German painter, during his career. It consists of two plaster heads cast from life, slathered in gray paint and mounted on pedestals. One head is Mr. Richter's; the other, his fellow German painter Blinky Palermo. Facing each other with closed eyes, in a gallery that is empty but for a small study version in a shadow box on the wall, the faux classical sculptures create an ambience of dry existential ennui (Johnson).</p>
        <p>T. L. SOLIEN, ''Hollow,'' Luise Ross, 568 Broadway, at Prince Street, (212) 343-2161, through June 5. If you were around in the early 80's you may remember Mr. Solien's intriguingly quirky paintings from the 1983 Whitney Biennial. His last show in New York was 14 years ago, so it is good to see that he is still making beguiling paintings while living in Wisconsin. Mixing abstraction, appropriated cartoons, and illustrations and images of homey, old-time interiors, the paintings create a haunting narrative blend of the domestic and the hallucinatory (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''THE DEVONSHIRE INHERITANCE: FIVE CENTURIES OF COLLECTING AT CHATSWORTH,'' Bard Graduate Center, 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000, through June 20. The stately English country home Chatsworth has been occupied since its construction in 1552 by the Cavendish family, headed by a long succession of dukes and duchesses of Devonshire. They have enriched it with notable collections of fine and decorative arts, an awesome library of books and manuscripts, scientific instruments, silver, furniture and needlework. A glimpse of these treasures is provided by this show, which has works by Rembrandt, Raphael, Titian, Dürer and Lucian Freud; books and drawings by Andrea Palladio; a spectacular jewelry ensemble worn at the coronation of Czar Alexander II and much else to light up the eyes of the most jaded connoisseur. The next step is a visit to Chatsworth itself, still a private home for the Cavendishes but very much open to the public (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''WORLDSCAPES: THE ART OF ERRO,'' Grey Art Gallery, New York University, 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village, (212) 998-6780, through July 17. The career of Erro, a prodigiously productive Pop-style painter said to be Iceland's most acclaimed artist, is featured in a nearly 50-year retrospective at the Grey Art Gallery. It will not persuade you that he is a great painter, but you may be taken by his manic graphic activity, antic humor and promiscuous sampling from popular culture. If so, you may also want to see ''Femmes Fatales'' at the Goethe-Institut, 1014 Fifth Avenue, at 83rd Street, (212) 439-8700, through July 17, which offers 10 colorful paintings from an Erro series devoted to female comic book superheroes (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>ROBERT INDIANA, ''Peace Paintings,'' Paul Kasmin, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474, through tomorrow. Mr. Indiana's colorful new paintings are about peace, or rather the absence of peace. Each diamond-shaped canvas features a circle, like a life-saver, bearing block-lettered sentences about the loss of peace: ''Peace falls in terror,'' ''Peace dives in oblivion,'' ''Peace plunges in despair.'' Within each circle is the familiar forked peace sign. With their rich colors, punchy compositions and resonant echoes of the Vietnam era, these pictures should be disseminated as posters (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''GUSTAV KLUTSIS AND VALENTINA KULAGINA: PHOTOGRAPHY AND MONTAGE AFTER CONSTRUCTIVISM'' AND ''WAR IN IRAQ: THE COORDINATES OF CONFLICT, PHOTOGRAPHS BY VII,'' International Center of Photography, 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000, through Sunday. Provocatively buttressed by two smaller shows, these imposing exhibitions dovetail into a chillingly informative examination of the roles of photography in art, history and science. The political, the personal and the formal alternate energetically in the first exhibition in this country devoted to Klutsis and Kulagina, who were married, and is primarily the tale of an artist whose striking photomontage posters helped establish the graphic look of the young Soviet Union, until Stalin had him killed. ''War in Iraq'' makes manifest the kinds of events that swirled around but rarely registered within the work of Klutsis or Kulagina. Starting with the ruins at ground zero, 53 images by nine intrepid photojournalists associated with the agency VII record the havoc that war, violence, dictatorial regimes and fanatical faith have wrought in our own time. Hours and admission: Tuesdays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; students and 62+, $7 (Smith).</p>
        <p>LEONARD KOSCIANSKI, OK Harris, 383 West Broadway, near Spring Street, SoHo, (212) 431-3600, through tomorrow. For two decades Mr. Koscianski has been painting dreamy, slightly cartoonish, Magic Realist pictures of dogs, boars, hawks and other wild animals in violent Darwinian action. This show finds him in top form. It also includes glowing images of butterflies and tropical flowers that radiate a lush erotic heat (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''STAGING THE ORIENT: VISIONS OF THE EAST AT LA SCALA AND THE METROPOLITAN OPERA,'' Dahesh Museum of Art, 580 Madison Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 759-0606, through Sunday. For centuries opera was one of Europe's more popular theatrical forms. And while music was certainly a big part of its appeal, for many fans the real attraction lay in spectacular stage sets. These were often designed by leading academic painters and the results, set deep in the past and in places remote from Europe, were examples of how one culture -- Western in this case -- invents exotic, often demeaning visions of others. The Dahesh show considers such matters with the help of prints and drawings and some spectacular costumes worn by famous singers, past and present. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $9, students and 62+, $4. (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* WHITNEY BIENNIAL, Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, through Sunday. Easily the best biennial in a long time. The spirit is upbeat and ingratiating -- almost polite -- on the surface at least, with a utopian streak and a youth-heavy emphasis on gloss and craft. There's plenty of painting and drawing, ratifying the much-hyped trend, and multigenerational work, stressing ecstatic engagement and meticulousness. But the real story is the stress on the handmade in general, on materiality in whatever medium -- a change from the politics-heavy, slacker installations of recent years. The cross-generational dialogue is an interesting subtext. Among the younger set utopia does not mean 1960's-style radicalism; it implies something unattainable, except perhaps in a hand-me-down form, and therefore smaller and inherently poignant. Look for a few standout works from artists both younger and older, including Yayoi Kusama, Alec Soth, Catherine Opie, Julie Mehretu, Jim Hodges, Eve Sussman, Raymond Pettibon, Slater Bradley, Robert Mangold and Stan Brakhage, who died last year. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 62+, $9.50 (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* DAISY YOUNGBLOOD, McKee, 745 Fifth Avenue, at 57th Street, (212) 688-5951, through today. Ms. Youngblood, who is in her late 50's and lives in Costa Rica, won a MacArthur award last year for her exquisitely sensitive, usually small ceramic sculptures of animals and human spiritual gurus. Here are 18 works dating from 1975 to 2003 in which the interest is mainly in the magical tension between the raw clay and the lifelike, psychologically evocative forms and gestures of animal and human bodies (Johnson).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
