<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dutch Town Under a Vermeer Sky</title>
    <meta content="DELFT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/14/travel/14delft.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041128T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1626966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Delft (Netherlands)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yarnall, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/Delft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Netherlands</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D6133CF937A25752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="2094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dutch Town Under a Vermeer Sky</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Dutch Town Under a Vermeer Sky</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH YARNALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yarnall, Judith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judith Yarnall travel article on two-day visit to Delft, Netherlands; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Dutch love their skies. They brag about their infinite variety, so different from vistas of flat, green, water-ditched polders. The most celebrated Dutch sky of all occupies nearly two-thirds of Johannes Vermeer's canvas in his ''View of Delft,'' now in the collection of the Mauritshuis in The Hague and a 20-minute tram ride from the artist's hometown, which inspired it.</p>
        <p>In Vermeer's painting, cumulus clouds billow through astonishing blueness and light, but the dark underside of one dominates the upper foreground. The weather in the ''View'' is both eternal and mercurial; clearly anything can happen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeing Delft on canvas and along its canals is not so different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Dutch love their skies. They brag about their infinite variety, so different from vistas of flat, green, water-ditched polders. The most celebrated Dutch sky of all occupies nearly two-thirds of Johannes Vermeer's canvas in his ''View of Delft,'' now in the collection of the Mauritshuis in The Hague and a 20-minute tram ride from the artist's hometown, which inspired it.</p>
        <p>In Vermeer's painting, cumulus clouds billow through astonishing blueness and light, but the dark underside of one dominates the upper foreground. The weather in the ''View'' is both eternal and mercurial; clearly anything can happen.</p>
        <p>As a longtime traveler to the Netherlands, I should have remembered this likelihood when packing for a two-day expedition to Delft in late August. Shortly after my husband, Victor, and I arrived by train from Amsterdam and rented bikes at a shop at the station, the skies opened. We ducked into a store off the town's huge market square to buy umbrellas.</p>
        <p>Once shielded, and with both 17th-century and modern maps in hand, we comfortably walked along the town's lime-tree-bordered canals. When the sun suddenly illumined the lilies and blue hydrangeas in the Thursday flower market set up along the Hippolytusbuurt, the whole town took on a sheen.</p>
        <p>We shared Delft's wet streets with mainly Dutch tourists, drawn by the intimacy and beauty of its old center and probably also by monuments associated with William of Orange, the George Washington of the Netherlands who led an insurrection against the Spanish Hapsburgs in the 16th century. His tomb in the Nieuwe Kerk was a tourist sight even in Vermeer's day.</p>
        <p>Now Delft is known also for the excellence of its technical university, where hydraulic engineers much in demand in an era of global warming get their training. But in the 17th-century Delft was a magnet for artists, who found wealthy patrons among its brewers and pottery factory owners and government officials. Pieter de Hooch and Emanuel de Witte, known respectively for their interiors of homes and churches, lived here, as well as the painter of tavern life, Jan Steen.</p>
        <p>So did Carel Fabritius -- an artist of great promise still in his early 30's when he was killed by the Thunderclap of 1654, an arsenal explosion that destroyed the northeastern section of the town. Fabritius, who apprenticed in Rembrandt's studio before he moved to Delft and who painted works known to be owned by Vermeer, provides a link between Holland's two greatest artists. His small but esteemed oeuvre is now being celebrated by an exhibition at the Mauritshuis running to Jan. 9. Its poster features his recently restored ''Goldfinch,'' so comely and pert that your eye almost misses the delicate chain that binds it.</p>
        <p>The Mauritshuis was our prep for Delft. Housed in an elegant 1640 mansion built by another member of the House of Orange, the Mauritshuis's collection is among the most distinguished in Europe. It contains three Vermeers, including the ''View'' and ''Girl With a Pearl Earring''; at least five Rembrandts, including ''Homer'' and a self-portrait done in 1669, the year of Vermeer's death; a host of Golden Age landscapes, interiors and genre scenes; and Rogier van der Weyden's ''Lamentation'' -- a painting so direct and precise in its delineation of sorrow that it stopped the 5-year old accompanying us in his tracks.</p>
        <p>In four visits to the Mauritshuis I've never entered a crowded room. The museum affords its visitors the great luxury of viewing its paintings as their creators did: unimpeded, and from alternating distances. Up close, you can notice that the famous ''Girl'' has eyes of hazel, not honey-brown; that the shadowing on her blue scarf is done with surprisingly bold, almost reckless, strokes; that a minuscule clock on a building in the center of ''View of Delft'' says 7:12 -- a.m. or p.m.? And that Vermeer stippled centuries before Seurat, for tiny sparks of yellow-white on the gunnel and flank of a boat in Delft's harbor resolve themselves into an intense play of sunlight when seen from a distance.</p>
        <p>Over dinner at the Bistro Patachou, on the Oude Delft canal, we conceived the literalist scheme of standing at Vermeer's vantage point by the harbor at exactly 7:12 the next morning. (By then we knew from collating our maps with the painting's angle of light that it was a.m.) The restaurant was tiny, with service even slower than Holland's leisurely norm, but the prix fixe menu -- a first course of tuna carpaccio with capers and lemon, followed by either grilled lamb chops or gurnard baked in a savory basil, tomato, and red wine sauce, and with fresh strawberry tarts as dessert -- was entirely to our liking.</p>
        <p>Thunder trumped our 6:30 a.m. alarm. So much for exactitude. Despite the wet streets, we decided to bike down to the Hooikade, at the southern tip of the old city, directly beneath the spot where Vermeer must have set up his easel by a second-story window across from the boat basin. What did time or the fall of light matter on a gray day?</p>
        <p>No sooner were we stationed than it poured, driving us into a nearby cafe. We scrapped a plan for a cycling exploration of the nearby countryside and determined instead to concentrate on Delft interiors, building on our acquaintance of the previous afternoon, when we had visited the town's three best-known landmarks: the Oude Kerk, the Nieuwe Kerk and William's last residence, the Prinsenhof.</p>
        <p>At the Oude Kerk, built in the 13th and 14th centuries, the bones of Vermeer and his family rest, as well as those of his friend and around-the-corner neighbor, the microscope's inventor, Antony van Leeuwenhoek. A relief portrait above Leeuwenhoek's grave shows him to have been long-chinned and prominently nosed, with a cascade of curly hair: corroboration for the hunch of those who suspect he was Vermeer's model for ''The Astronomer'' and ''The Geographer.''</p>
        <p>The details at the Prinsenhof are more chilling: two bullet holes left by William's assassin in a staircase wall. Upstairs in the Prinsenhof's gallery I had noticed a portrait of the archvillain of Dutch history, the Spanish Duke of Alba, who no doubt would have approved of the dastardly deed. With his ascetic face and long, forked beard he looks appropriately Inquisitorial. Much more of a surprise had been five other version of the ''View of Delft,'' all done by contemporaries of Vermeer. An overlooked mini-genre? Daniel Vosmaer-- a fantasist if there ever was one -- apparently whisked his Delft off to Tuscany, where it basks beyond a loggia and beneath a sapphire sky.</p>
        <p>Now, with unexpected time in town, we took a tram to the Delftse Pauw, one of the town's three remaining factories producing traditional Delftware. A brief, informative tour ended in the showroom, where quality is fully matched by price. Delftware, our guide pointed out, has always been earthenware, produced when the industry began around 1640 from local reddish clay covered by a white glaze as background for its blue, Chinese-inspired designs. But for centuries now, a stronger white clay imported from England and Germany has been the base of choice. I'll stick with red, I thought when I heard this. My eye had already been caught by thick old tiles, some with homely designs of animals or children at play, in the windows of antique shops near the Nieuwe Kerk.</p>
        <p>IT'S hard to think of a more pleasant way of getting to know Delft than just wandering in and out of these shops, talking to their owners, listening to the huge old Bourdon bell in the Oudekerk mark the hour and half hour. My last stop in this destinationless meander was Antiekhandel de Drie Klaveren, Peter Arkensteijn's shop on Vrouwenregt 2. Peter had not only a generous selection of 17th-century tiles -- some, he said, with coded iconography, like crosses hidden among geometric flowers -- but also an archaeologist's and historian's knowledge of his town. The restoration of his shop and house, one of the few buildings to survive the fire of 1536, was financed by his discovery and sale of a cache of old Protestant texts hidden above a beam, probably there since the Inquisition. On my desk now there's a tile bought from him for a song -- cracked, glued, pitted and beautiful.</p>
        <p>From the shop it was a short journey through a garden and two passageways to the place Victor and I had agreed to meet, the Café Vlaanderen on the Beestenmarkt. Though it's only a short distance from the very public market square, the Beestenmarkt seems hidden. It's as lovely a square as I've seen in the Netherlands, shaded by sycamores and graced by a fanciful monument, a blue cow atop a Holstein-spotted pedestal that sports with its history as the place where, for several centuries, cattle and hogs changed owners.</p>
        <p>The Vlaanderen has many tables in the Beestenmarkt's public space, as well as a cozy interior and a back garden where you can choose from a menu that features cosmopolitan approaches to local seafood.</p>
        <p>When we took the train back to Amsterdam, I regretted not having spent another night. No matter what the weather -- short of Jove's fury -- Delft had been a calm but invigorating place to be. How does it manage waters so still without algae? Around every bend there had been a pleasant surprise: water lilies, a white bridge, a passing swan or the Venetian lap of water directly against the buildings of the Voldersgracht, one of Delft's oldest canals. No wonder Vermeer never left.</p>
        <p>Delft, oud and nieuw</p>
        <p>Lodging and Dining</p>
        <p>Hotel Leeuwenbrug, Koornmarkt 16, (31-15) 214 77 41, fax (31-15) 215 97 59, www.leeuwenbrug.nl, has 36 rooms as well as an inviting lounge, in a mansion by a canal. Rates for doubles, including breakfast, $120 to $163 (prices at $1.30 to the euro).</p>
        <p>Hotel de Ark, Koornmarkt 65, (31-15) 215 79 99, fax (31-15) 214 49 97, www.deark.nl, is in three restored 17th-century houses; many of its 28 rooms have fine architectural details and canal or garden views. Doubles $162 , including breakfast; nine apartments also available.</p>
        <p>Herberg de Emauspoort, (31-15) 219 02 19, fax (31-15) 214 82 51, www.emauspoort.nl, at Vrouwenregt 9 in the historic center, has 12 pleasantly furnished rooms, at $114 for a double, as well as two gypsy caravans in the courtyard at $107. A bakery at the hotel makes the included breakfast special.</p>
        <p>Bistro Pitachou, Oude Delft, (31-15) 92, 215 98 37, features a prix fixe menu at $29. Dinner for two with wine, and tip about $85.</p>
        <p>Café Vlaanderen, Beestenmarkt 16, (31-15) 213 33 11, offers both cafe fare and a varied dinner menu. The three-course prix fixe dinner is $47.</p>
        <p>Sights</p>
        <p>The Mauritshuis, Korte Vijverberg 8 in The Hague, is about a 10 minutes' walk from Central Station; (31-70) 302 34 56, www.mauritshuis.nl. It can also be reached by several trams from the station. Closed Monday; the fee for general admission is $12 during the Fabrititius exhibition.</p>
        <p>The Prinsenhof, Sint Agathaplein 1, (31-15) 260 23 58, is closed Monday. Admission is $6.50 or $11 for a combination ticket also good for the nearby Museum Lambert van Meerten, where tiles from the 16th to 19th centuries are on display.</p>
        <p>Admission to the Nieuwe Kerk, on the market square, and the Oude Kerk, Heilige Geestkerhof 25, is $3.25 for a combined ticket. For an extra $2.60 you can climb the 356 steps of the Nieuwe Kerk tower.</p>
        <p>De Delftse Pauw, just outside the old center at Delftweg 133, is open every day for free factory tours; www.delftsepauw.com or (31-15) 212 49 20. Get off at the Vrijenbanselaan stop on Tram No. 1.</p>
        <p>Getting Around</p>
        <p>Trains in the Netherlands are frequent, prompt and cheap. An Amsterdam-Delft round trip costs about $23. The Netherlands railway site, www.ns.nl, posts schedules complete with station platform numbers.</p>
        <p>Excellent bikes can be rented at the shops adjacent to stations all over the country for about $7.25 a day. Photo ID is necessary.</p>
        <p>JUDITH YARNALL travels to the Netherlands frequently.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 28, 2004, Sunday  Because of an editing error, an article on Nov. 14 about the town of Delft, in the Netherlands, misidentified the artist who died in 1669, the year of a self-portrait on display there. He was Rembrandt, not Vermeer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 28, 2004, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article on Nov. 14 about the town of Delft, in the Netherlands, misidentified the artist who died in 1669, the year of a self-portrait on display there. He was Rembrandt, not Vermeer.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JUDITH YARNALL travels to the Netherlands frequently.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
