<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Be Afraid. Be Very Afraid.</title>
    <meta content="30KLINKEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/30/books/review/30KLINKEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1585379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="CHRONICLE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lynas, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Speth, James Gustave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meadows, Donella</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randers, Jorgen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meadows, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gelbspan, Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehrlich, Paul R (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehrlich, Anne H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">High Tide: The Truth About Our Climate Crisis (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Red Sky at Morning (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Limits to Growth (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Boiling Point (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">One With Nineveh (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Speth, James Gustave</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gelbspan, Ross</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ehrlich, Paul R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ehrlich, Anne H</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Red Sky at Morning: America and the Crisis of the Global Environment (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D8103FF933A05756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Be Afraid. Be Very Afraid.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Be Afraid. Be Very Afraid.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Verlyn Klinkenborg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg Chronicle column reviews some new books on the environment: High Tide: The Truth About Our Climate Crisis by Mark Lynas; Red Sky at Morning: America and the Crisis of the Global Environment by James Gustave Speth; Limits to Growth by Donella Meadows, Jorgen Randers and Dennis Meadows; Boiling Point by Ross Gelbspan; and One With Nineveh: Politics, Consumption, and the Human Future by Paul R Ehrlich and Anne H Ehrlich; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At least for the moment, ''The Day After Tomorrow'' -- 20th Century Fox's new movie about catastrophic climate change -- has reawakened public anxiety over global warming and broken through the thick crust of American denial. Unfortunately, the movie does for climatology only what ''Independence Day,'' also directed by Roland Emmerich, did for cosmology. It delivers summer blockbuster thrills and the kind of hyperbole -- a tidal wave pounding through Manhattan -- that makes the whole problem easy for skeptics to dismiss. All across the country, ''The Day After Tomorrow'' has started debates the movie itself cannot resolve -- debates, all too often, between the prejudiced and the ill informed.</p>
        <p>As it happens, several significant new books on the environment are also about to appear, or will be published later this summer, and they could settle the debate right now -- if people take the trouble to read them. They range from anecdotal, first-person accounts of vanishing Peruvian glaciers and Pacific islands slipping beneath a rising ocean, like Mark Lynas's High Tide: The Truth About Our Climate Crisis (Picador, paper, $14), to profoundly sobering studies, like James Gustave Speth's Red Sky at Morning: America and the Crisis of the Global Environment (Yale University, $24). For the most part, these books don't advance new arguments, because the arguments essentially haven't changed. As Speth writes, ''Our use of fossil fuels -- coal, oil and natural gas -- together with deforestation have increased the concentration of atmospheric carbon dioxide, a heat-trapping 'greenhouse' gas . . . and thus begun the process of man-made climate change.'' This is not news. According to Donella Meadows, Jorgen Randers and Dennis Meadows, the authors of the updated Limits to Growth (Chelsea Green, cloth, $35; paper, $22.50), the ecological burden of humanity had already outstripped the carrying capacity of the earth two decades ago -- as the first edition of this book, originally published in 1972, warned it would.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several significant new books could settle the debate about climate change right now  if people take the trouble to read them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At least for the moment, ''The Day After Tomorrow'' -- 20th Century Fox's new movie about catastrophic climate change -- has reawakened public anxiety over global warming and broken through the thick crust of American denial. Unfortunately, the movie does for climatology only what ''Independence Day,'' also directed by Roland Emmerich, did for cosmology. It delivers summer blockbuster thrills and the kind of hyperbole -- a tidal wave pounding through Manhattan -- that makes the whole problem easy for skeptics to dismiss. All across the country, ''The Day After Tomorrow'' has started debates the movie itself cannot resolve -- debates, all too often, between the prejudiced and the ill informed.</p>
        <p>As it happens, several significant new books on the environment are also about to appear, or will be published later this summer, and they could settle the debate right now -- if people take the trouble to read them. They range from anecdotal, first-person accounts of vanishing Peruvian glaciers and Pacific islands slipping beneath a rising ocean, like Mark Lynas's High Tide: The Truth About Our Climate Crisis (Picador, paper, $14), to profoundly sobering studies, like James Gustave Speth's Red Sky at Morning: America and the Crisis of the Global Environment (Yale University, $24). For the most part, these books don't advance new arguments, because the arguments essentially haven't changed. As Speth writes, ''Our use of fossil fuels -- coal, oil and natural gas -- together with deforestation have increased the concentration of atmospheric carbon dioxide, a heat-trapping 'greenhouse' gas . . . and thus begun the process of man-made climate change.'' This is not news. According to Donella Meadows, Jorgen Randers and Dennis Meadows, the authors of the updated Limits to Growth (Chelsea Green, cloth, $35; paper, $22.50), the ecological burden of humanity had already outstripped the carrying capacity of the earth two decades ago -- as the first edition of this book, originally published in 1972, warned it would.</p>
        <p>What is news is the nature of the evidence. There are signs that global warming and environmental degradation are accelerating much more quickly than anyone expected even 10 years ago, and thus our ability to reduce the scale of climate change is swiftly diminishing. As Speth argues, ''Our first attempt at global environmental governance'' -- the international efforts leading up to the Kyoto Protocol -- yielded very little, thanks largely to opposition from the United States. ''Our second attempt,'' he writes, ''may be our last chance to get it right.''</p>
        <p>The question that haunts Speth's book -- all of these books, really -- is, why? Why have Americans refused to face up to the evidence of global warming? The answers are both political and economic. But Ross Gelbspan, a former Boston Globe reporter and editor, makes the case that the news media are also guilty. In Boiling Point (Basic Books, $22, to be published in August), he argues that on matters of scientific fact, journalists employ an essentially unfair idea of ''balance'' -- treating global warming as though it were still a matter of open conjecture, with equal weight on both sides. As a result, the story of global warming as reported in the American press largely reflects the political manipulation of the story, not the science. Accurate coverage, Gelbspan writes, ''would have reflected the position of mainstream scientists in 95 percent of the story -- with the skeptics getting a paragraph at the end.''</p>
        <p>To most scientists, global warming is a truly successful hypothesis. The evidence overwhelmingly shows, as predicted, that human behavior is altering the climate, with potentially catastrophic results. And yet it seems strangely difficult to scare or reason or argue Americans, the critical audience to reach, into recognizing the truth and acting on it. The world's population is trapped in a malign paradox. Instead of taking the lead, the United States -- the country with the highest emissions and the most excessive consumption, as well as enormous potential to produce innovative energy technologies -- knows and seems to care the least about global warming. Short-term self-interest is a powerful buffer against reality. So is the lobbying of the fossil fuel industries and the complacency of an administration that lives in thrall to them.</p>
        <p>As the object of our collective fears, the environmental fate of the earth isn't nearly as rousing, or as pinpoint precise, as our old fear of the Bomb. The Bomb was hard to beat. We'd already seen what it could do at Alamogordo, Hiroshima, Nagasaki, Bikini. We'd watched Peter Watkins's ''War Game'' and read Jonathan Schell's ''Fate of the Earth.'' Only a few people had the Bomb, and none of them were you or the next-door neighbors. Your personal decision not to drop the Bomb had no effect on the problem. In time, the people who did have the Bomb came to understand that having it meant they couldn't use it. Using it would have meant a sudden break with history, a cataclysmic rending of reality as we knew it. Fear of the Bomb was also easily aroused. It was a fear of death, charring, radiation sickness and of something much larger too: the evisceration of society and global environmental destruction, all of it spiraling outward from that first incendiary flash. Once the powers-that-be found the will to step away from the nuclear precipice, the threat diminished abruptly -- though it will linger as long as the Bomb exists.</p>
        <p>Man-made climate change isn't as percussive as nuclear war. It lacks the immediacy of a mushroom cloud over the Nevada desert. Yet without international action -- a new Manhattan Project to develop low-impact energy technologies and a revolutionary commitment to global equity -- it too promises social and economic collapse. Climate change is a slow Bomb, and it has already been detonated. You and I and the next-door neighbors are all part of the problem. And even if we all shifted course immediately and began sharply reducing the causes of global warming, it would take many years before those actions began to register significantly. All the more reason, of course, to begin now -- to have begun 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>We are well past the threshold of inevitable change and on the cusp of climate destabilization. As Paul R. Ehrlich and Anne H. Ehrlich note in One With Nineveh: Politics, Consumption, and the Human Future (Island Press/Shearwater, $27), ''Extreme weather events, such as heat waves and fierce storms, have become more common and are appearing in places where they have never been seen before.'' Concerted international action could help mitigate the worst effects, and many nations are well ahead of the United States in facing the issue. But the hardest part is assuming responsibility for the future. James Speth has served as an environmental adviser to Presidents Carter and Clinton. He writes that our absorption in the present -- our selfishness -- is in conflict with one of the ''central principles of environmental ethics -- the proposition that we have duties to future generations.''</p>
        <p>The prospects for controlling our impact on nature are not good. What it will take isn't just a change in habits of consumption, yours and mine, or an international protocol, or smaller cars and better mileage. It will take an enormous reduction in carbon dioxide emissions over the next few decades -- a far cry from the minor cuts proposed in the Kyoto Protocol, which President Bush has rejected anyway. What stands in the way is custom, ignorance, sloth, greed and fear.</p>
        <p>In a way, the true puzzle of global warming isn't the mechanics of man-made climate change -- the feedback loops, the damage to the ozone layer, the shift in oceanic oscillations, the melting of the ice-caps, the desertification of formerly productive agricultural lands. Those can be studied and understood. The true puzzle is human nature. In every one of these accounts of climate change and environmental degradation, the authors note the inertia of the global system, whether they're talking about economic or climatic models of the future. But there's another kind of inertia built into the system too, and I know no better account of it than a passage from Isaac Asimov's ''Foundation,'' the opening novel in his classic series about a science called ''psychohistory,'' which combines psychology and statistics. ''The psychohistoric trend of a planet-full of people contains a huge inertia,'' says Hari Seldon, the ancestral hero of the foundation. ''To be changed it must be met with something possessing a similar inertia.''</p>
        <p>This is a way of saying we live as we have always lived. Sometimes -- like now -- nearly everyone is aware of dramatic changes in the world. Yet we continue to live in the assumption that we can ride out the changes without changing ourselves, coasting, as we have always coasted, on the historic wave of human development. What it will take to wake us up is a wave of equal size traveling in the opposite direction. That wave is already on its way.</p>
        <p>CHRONICLE ENVIRONMENT Verlyn Klinkenborg writes editorials for The Times. He is the author, most recently, of ''The Rural Life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Verlyn Klinkenborg writes editorials for The Times. He is the author, most recently, of ''The Rural Life.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
