<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA Spots New Youngest Planet, Just a Million Years Old</title>
    <meta content="28PLAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1585089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spitzer Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDB103EF93BA15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA Spots New Youngest Planet, Just a Million Years Old</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newest NASA space telescope, with ability to see past obscuring clouds of cosmic dust, spots what astronomers believe is evidence of youngest planet observed so far, gaseous body that could be less than million years old; this is first major finding of Spitzer Space Telescope (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The newest NASA space telescope, with its ability to see past obscuring clouds of cosmic dust, has spotted what astronomers believe is evidence of the youngest planet observed so far, a gaseous body that could be less than a million years old.</p>
        <p>Announcing the first major findings of the Spitzer Space Telescope on Thursday, scientists said the observations could indicate that planet formation around stars is more common and more rapid than previously suspected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The newest NASA space telescope, with its ability to see past obscuring clouds of cosmic dust, has spotted what astronomers believe is evidence of the youngest planet observed so far, a gaseous body that could be less than a million years old.</p>
        <p>Announcing the first major findings of the Spitzer Space Telescope on Thursday, scientists said the observations could indicate that planet formation around stars is more common and more rapid than previously suspected.</p>
        <p>The telescope, launched in August into a singular orbit around the Sun that keeps it trailing the Earth by 5.4 million miles, uses supercold instruments to detect the faint infrared warmth of distant objects. That method lets it study objects too cold or distant to be otherwise seen through dust and gas clouds.</p>
        <p>''By seeing what's behind the dust, Spitzer has shown us star and planet formation is a very active process in our galaxy,'' said Dr. Edward N. Churchwell of the University of Wisconsin, a principal investigator who is using the observatory.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a NASA news briefing in Washington, Dr. Churchwell said the early findings ''knocked our socks off.''</p>
        <p>''Spitzer is likely to change our perception of star formation in our galaxy,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The infrared observatory looked at a dusty star nursery region called RCW 49 and uncovered 300 newborn stars in one image. A close look at two stars showed that they had faint planet-forming discs of dust and gas around them. Dr. Churchwell said preliminary information suggested that all 300 might harbor such discs. RCW 49 is 13,700 light-years from Earth, in the constellation Centaurus.</p>
        <p>Spitzer also surveyed young stars in the constellation Taurus, 420 light-years from Earth, and returned surprising findings about infant stars less than a million years old and slightly older toddlers. Looking at the star CoKu Tau 4, which is one million years old, Spitzer found a highly defined clear area in the dust from which it formed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dan M. Watson of the University of Rochester said the clear area was probably swept away by a young gaseous planet that was forming around the star that cleaned up the debris. Although other events were possible like heat and light from the star blowing away the dust or asteroids forming in the area, scientists said the clean inner edge of the void suggested a planet.</p>
        <p>''The hole is real, the hole is really clear, really sharp,'' Dr. Watson said at the briefing.</p>
        <p>A third finding was made in surveying five very young stars in Taurus. Dr. Watson and a colleague at Rochester, Dr. William J. Forrest, found significant quantities of icy organic materials in the planet-forming discs that circled infant stars. Those stars, a few hundreds of thousands of years old, were swimming in dust particles coated in ice made of water, methanol and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The presence of the organic materials throughout the discs could explain the origin of icy bodies like comets, which some scientists believe could have supplied Earth, and other planets, with some water and organic materials that could have enabled life to form.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
