<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Judge Rejects Rules On Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="05POLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/05/nyregion/05pollute.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stein, Leslie (Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFDB1031F936A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Judge Rejects Rules On Acid Rain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Judge Tosses Rules to Curb Acid Rain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Justice Leslie Stein throws out state's tough new acid rain regulations on technicality, providing reprieve to owners of 10 old coal-fired power plants and derailing, at least temporarily, measures that were to have been high point of Gov George E Pataki's environmental record; rules that new regulations were adopted improperly after state missed deadline for publication of notice to inform public of proposed changes in rules; but rejects energy companies' claim that Dept of Environmental Conservation does not have authority to adopt such stringent rules (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New York judge threw out the state's tough new acid rain regulations yesterday on a technicality, providing a reprieve to owners of 10 old coal-fired power plants and derailing, at least temporarily, measures that were to have been a high point of Gov. George E. Pataki's environmental record.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said the unexpected ruling would keep harmful chemicals in the state's air and prolong the exposure of New York forests, lakes and streams to the harmful effects of acid rain, which has already damaged sensitive areas like the Adirondacks. The energy companies that challenged the new rules, which were to take effect in October, will be able to delay making costly improvements to the coal-fired plants still operating in the state. Some are half a century old and are considered major sources of air pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A New York judge threw out the state's tough new acid rain regulations Friday on a technicality, providing a reprieve to owners of 10 old coal-fired power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A New York judge threw out the state's tough new acid rain regulations yesterday on a technicality, providing a reprieve to owners of 10 old coal-fired power plants and derailing, at least temporarily, measures that were to have been a high point of Gov. George E. Pataki's environmental record.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said the unexpected ruling would keep harmful chemicals in the state's air and prolong the exposure of New York forests, lakes and streams to the harmful effects of acid rain, which has already damaged sensitive areas like the Adirondacks. The energy companies that challenged the new rules, which were to take effect in October, will be able to delay making costly improvements to the coal-fired plants still operating in the state. Some are half a century old and are considered major sources of air pollution.</p>
        <p>Although New York officials insisted that their efforts to reduce air pollution were continuing to move forward, the ruling yesterday was a setback for Governor Pataki, who promised in 1999 that New York would have the country's strictest acid rain regulations.</p>
        <p>The new rules, which have already been delayed for several years, would reduce smokestack emissions of nitrogen by 75 percent and sulfur by 50 percent, far below levels set by the federal government.</p>
        <p>Several energy companies jointly filed a lawsuit challenging the regulations. They said the new rules would lead to higher consumer electricity rates without reducing pollution.</p>
        <p>But Peter M. Iwanowicz, the director of environmental health for the American Lung Association of New York State, said that a delay of even a few months in adopting the rules would have a serious effect on the health of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''It will mean that more people will die, more people will get sick and more children will have asthma attacks because the air will be dirtier for longer,'' Mr. Iwanowicz said.</p>
        <p>In striking down the regulations, Justice Leslie Stein of State Supreme Court in Albany ruled that they had been adopted improperly after the state missed a deadline for publication of a notice to inform the public of proposed changes in the rules.</p>
        <p>But Justice Stein rejected the energy companies' claim that the Department of Environmental Conservation did not have sufficient authority to adopt such stringent and far-reaching rules.</p>
        <p>Lesa A. Bader, a spokeswoman for NRG Energy, one of the electric generating companies that brought the suit, said that despite the issues raised in the court case, the company ''remains committed to working with New York and the governor to achieve reductions in emissions.''</p>
        <p>NRG, a Minneapolis company, operates several coal-fired plants in New York, including the 749-megawatt C.R. Huntley plant in Erie County, near Buffalo, which was built in 1942.</p>
        <p>Most of New York's coal-fired plants are in the central and western parts of the state. All of them must continue to meet federal standards.</p>
        <p>Jason K. Babbie, an analyst with the New York Public Interest Research Group, said the power companies were attempting to obstruct the state's efforts to clean the air.</p>
        <p>''It seems like a last-ditch effort to hold on to the oldest and dirtiest technology available instead of taking a step into the 21st century,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki and state environmental officials have not yet decided whether to appeal the decision or immediately restart the process of drafting the new regulations.</p>
        <p>''The state remains fully committed to achieving the objectives of the original regulations,'' said Michael J. Fraser, a spokesman for the Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>John F. Sheehan, a spokesman for the Adirondack Council, an environmental advocacy group, said that even a short delay in adopting the new rules would hurt because power companies would forgo complying with them months in advance, which often occurs with a new regulatory arrangement.</p>
        <p>In another development yesterday relating to the regulation of coal-fired plants, the attorneys general of New York and five other states in the Northeast and one in the Midwest asked President Bush to force the government-run Tennessee Valley Authority to meet stricter air pollution standards at its 11 coal-burning power plants in the South.</p>
        <p>''T.V.A.'s illegal pollution from its coal-fired power plants is seriously harming the health and environment of Americans,'' the attorneys general stated in a letter sent to President Bush.</p>
        <p>Scott Segal, executive director of the Electric Reliability Coordinating Council, a group representing the power industry, said the action by the seven states was misguided because harmful emissions from the T.V.A.'s power plants have been steadily declining for 20 years.</p>
        <p>Carbon, sulfur, nitrogen and mercury released by coal-fired electric generating plants in states west of New York are carried eastward and across state lines by prevailing winds.</p>
        <p>New York and other Northeastern states have campaigned for several years to get the oldest and dirtiest of the T.V.A. plants cleaned up or closed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
