<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SUMMER MOVIES</title>
    <meta content="09MAY.$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/09/movies/moviesspecial/09MAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1580170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D9113DF93AA35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="6281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SUMMER MOVIES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Summer Releases: May</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES; Compiled with the assistance of Suzanne O'Connor.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief descriptions of films scheduled to open in May; photos M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>May  All dates subject to change.</p>
        <p>Open</p>
        <p>GODZILLA -- It's the 50th anniversary of Japan's most famous monster movie, and if you're American, you've probably never seen the real thing. This time Ishiro Honda's 1954 ''Gojira'' is uncut (with an impressive 40 minutes of restored footage) and uncensored, the anti-nuke messages have been revived, there are new English subtitles and Raymond Burr is nowhere to be seen (his part was added for American moviegoers). Takashi Shimura stars as a famous paleontologist faced with -- well, you know this part -- a 150-foot-tall reptile with radioactive breath who seems determined to destroy Tokyo. And by the way, this version, shown in Japan, has long been on the country's lists of best films.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>May.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>May  All dates subject to change.</p>
        <p>Open</p>
        <p>GODZILLA -- It's the 50th anniversary of Japan's most famous monster movie, and if you're American, you've probably never seen the real thing. This time Ishiro Honda's 1954 ''Gojira'' is uncut (with an impressive 40 minutes of restored footage) and uncensored, the anti-nuke messages have been revived, there are new English subtitles and Raymond Burr is nowhere to be seen (his part was added for American moviegoers). Takashi Shimura stars as a famous paleontologist faced with -- well, you know this part -- a 150-foot-tall reptile with radioactive breath who seems determined to destroy Tokyo. And by the way, this version, shown in Japan, has long been on the country's lists of best films.</p>
        <p>THE MUDGE BOY -- Emile Hirsch stars as a 14-year-old farm boy dealing, in less than traditional ways, with his mother's death. For one thing, he often talks in her voice (although he's not going the way of Norman Bates in ''Psycho''). For another, he sometimes sleeps in her fur coat. His schoolmates call him Chicken Boy because he seems to have taken a hen as a pet. He is also gay and possibly in love. Our young hero is getting no help from his dismayed father (Richard Jenkins). Michael Burke wrote and directed.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK MINUTE -- The allegedly adorable Olsen twins (they're 17 now) hit the big city. Ashley plays the overachiever, who comes to New York to deliver a speech that should help her win a college scholarship. Mary-Kate plays her punk-rocker sister, who plans to sneak into a music video shoot. But this is an ''action comedy,'' so there are mishaps, involving, fortunately, a stellar supporting cast that includes Andy Richter, Eugene Levy and Andrea Martin. Dennie Gordon, (''What a Girl Wants'') directed.</p>
        <p>OASIS -- A romantic drama from Korea that won four prizes at the 2002 Venice Film Festival. Sol Kyung-gu stars as Hong Jong-du, a young man just out of jail for a hit-and-run accident that his brother actually committed. Despite that, Jong-du sets out to make peace with the victim's family and, as a result, meets a young woman (Moon So-ri) with cerebral palsy. The two misfits (at least that's the way their families see them) fall in love. Lee Chang-dong, who is also Korea's minister of culture, wrote and directed.</p>
        <p>SEEING OTHER PEOPLE -- Ed (Jay Mohr) and Alice (Julianne Nicholson) are getting married in two months, and Alice is having second thoughts about lifelong monogamy. Maybe she hasn't had enough casual sex, she thinks. Maybe now would be the time. She and Ed agree to have an ''open engagement,'' but the experiment gets out of control. Lauren Graham is Alice's disapproving sister, and Bryan Cranston is the sister's lascivious husband. Josh Charles and Andy Richter are Ed's best friends. Wally Wolodarsky directed this sex-driven romantic comedy.</p>
        <p>A SKIN TOO FEW: THE DAYS OF NICK DRAKE -- Drake, whose song ''Know'' included the lyrics ''Know that I love you/ Know I don't care,'' was 26 when he died of an antidepressant overdose in 1974. He was becoming sort of the Emily Dickinson of his era: it is said that he found interacting with other people torture, and after he finished school he rarely left his parents' home. But he did manage to record three albums: ''Five Leaves Left,''  ''Bryter Layter'' and ''Pink Moon.'' Jeroen Berkvens directed this documentary.</p>
        <p>SUPER SIZE ME -- Some fast-food lovers might say they'd love to exist on a diet of Big Macs, Egg McMuffins, fries and preprocessed apple pies, but one man had the courage to do it. Morgan Spurlock, a healthy man of 33 at the time, existed on an all-McDonald's diet for 30 days. As a result, he gained almost 25 pounds, sank into depression and almost destroyed his liver. Mr. Spurlock won the documentary directing award at this year's Sundance Film Festival.</p>
        <p>SUPERSTAR IN A HOUSEDRESS -- When Jackie Curtis died, he was buried with photos, an assortment of mementos, packs of Kool cigarettes and a cocktail shaker of martinis, with a liberal sprinkling of glitter on his body and face. Craig B. Highberger's documentary is a portrait of Curtis: poet, playwright, screenwriter, director, Warhol star and noted transvestite. With scenes from the films ''Women in Revolt'' and ''Flesh'' and from Curtis's plays, including ''Femme Fatale'' and ''Vain Victory: The Vicissitudes of the Damned.'' Harvey Fierstein, Lily Tomlin, Holly Woodlawn, Joe Dallesandro, Sylvia Miles and Michael Musto are among those who talk about Curtis, born John Holder Jr., who died of a heroin overdose in 1985 at the age of 38.</p>
        <p>VALENTIN -- From Argentina, a comedy about an 8-year-old boy who brings all manner of joy and assistance to grown-ups. Rodrigo Noya stars as Valentin, who lives with his grandmother in 1960's Buenos Aires, makes friends with some adults and ends up a confidant, philosopher and matchmaker. Although all he really wants to be is an astronaut. The cast includes Carmen Maura and Alejandro Agresti, who directed, as Valentin's father.</p>
        <p>VAN HELSING -- Stephen Sommers's movie is teeming with monsters, but Hugh Jackman, in the title role, is the real attraction. As the 19th-century monster hunter and general force-for-good from ''Dracula,'' Mr. Jackman gets his name above the title. In 19th-century London, Rome, Paris and Transylvania, he goes up against not only Dracula (Richard Roxburgh) but also Frankenstein's Monster (Shuler Hensley), the Wolf Man (Will Kemp) and Dracula's three brides, who want children, even though that could be a problem for the undead. Kate Beckinsale is Van Helsing's sidekick, with a family curse she'd like to dispel. A ''Van Helsing'' sequel and a television series, ''Transylvania,'' could be in our future.</p>
        <p>Thursday</p>
        <p>SLAVES OF THE SWORD: ARIEL SHARON and THE JUNCTION -- Documentaries about the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. The first, directed by Paul Jenkins, covers 50 years of the career of Ariel Sharon, the Israeli prime minister who has been compared to Napoleon, for better or worse. The second, directed by Ilan Ziv, looks at the effects of the deaths of two young men at an intersection in the Gaza Strip. One was an Israeli soldier; the other lived in a Palestinian refugee camp.</p>
        <p>Friday</p>
        <p>BREAKIN' ALL THE RULES -- Jamie Foxx in a comedy of errors about a man who is dumped by his fiancée and turns the experience into a best-selling how-to book. Too bad his advice to his male friends doesn't work out so well. With Morris Chestnut and Gabrielle Union. Daniel Taplitz wrote and directed.</p>
        <p>CARANDIRU -- It could have been Brazil's version of ''Oz,'' but clearly Drauzio Varella's experience was less gruesome than what viewers saw in HBO's prison series. Dr. Varella worked as a volunteer at Casa de Detençao, a notorious São Paulo prison, for 10 years. These are his reminiscences about crime, revenge, love and friendship. Hector Babenco wrote and directed.</p>
        <p>COFFEE AND CIGARETTES -- From Jim Jarmusch, a lot of famous people sitting around, sipping and smoking and telling stories (about Elvis, Paris in the 20's, English tea and the inventions of Nikola Tesla). Speakers include Cate Blanchett, Bill Murray, Steven Wright, Roberto Benigni, Steve Buscemi, Alfred Molina and Iggy Pop. This is Mr. Jarmusch's fourth film called ''Coffee and Cigarettes,'' but the first three were shorts.</p>
        <p>OFF THE LIP -- Lucky Kat Shutte (Marguerite Moreau) has a brand-new journalism degree and a great new job in Hawaii: working for a surfing publication. But she soon feels that her life is falling apart. She can't find the elusive, reclusive, maybe nonexistent surfer she's looking for; she's constantly fighting with her filmmaker boyfriend (Mackenzie Astin); her boss (Adam Scott) is falling in love with her; and she's basically decided men are hopeless. As she writes in her journal, ''I'm too young to be this bitter.'' Robert Mickelson directed.</p>
        <p>A SLIPPING DOWN LIFE -- Just knowing this love story is based on an Anne Tyler novel tells us a lot. Lili Taylor stars as Evie Decker, a lonely small-town Southern woman who becomes obsessed with a sexy musician, Drumstrings Casey (Guy Pearce). So obsessed that she carves his last name into her forehead. Casey's people, rather than being appalled by the act, decide to use it as a marketing gimmick. And unexpectedly, Casey develops real feelings for Evie. The actress Toni Kalem (''The Sopranos'') wrote and directed. The film did the festival circuit in 1999 but is only now being released after legal wrangles.</p>
        <p>SPRINGTIME IN A SMALL TOWN -- This Chinese drama is Tian Zhuangzhuang's first film since ''The Blue Kite,'' which ran afoul of state censors. That may be why this film, based on a classic 1940's melodrama, is decidedly apolitical. Set at the end of World War II, it's the story of a respected but gloomy family that receives an unexpected visitor and finds its staid household turned upside down. The visitor is a handsome doctor from Shanghai. He's a dear childhood friend of the man of the house and a former lover of his wife's. (This is not something the man of the house knows.) Hidden emotions are revealed when everybody drinks too much at a party.</p>
        <p>STRAYED -- (''Les Égarés'') The exquisite Emmanuelle Béart stars in André Téchiné's latest, a drama set in Nazi-occupied France. Ms. Béart plays a young widow fleeing Paris with her two children. They run into a 17-year-old delinquent (Gaspard Ulliel), who breaks into an abandoned house, where they make themselves at home and imagine themselves a family. Related article, Page 15.</p>
        <p>TROY -- The return of Brad Pitt, resplendent in mini-leather as the Greek hero Achilles. In Wolfgang Petersen's new version of Homer's epic about the Trojan War, a relative unknown, Diane Kruger, plays Helen of Troy. Orlando Bloom is Paris, who steals Helen away from the king of Sparta and begins the decade-long war. Related article, Page 1.</p>
        <p>THE 24TH DAY -- What is the first thing you'd do if you learned you had AIDS? Most of us, no matter how devastated, wouldn't follow the example of the protagonist in this thriller, written and directed by Tony Piccirillo. Two young hunks play the leads. Scott Speedman is Tom, a married man who receives the horrific medical news. James Marsden is Dan, the only man he ever slept with. Tom kidnaps Dan and threatens to kill him, but Dan knew he was H.I.V. positive at the time, so who, if anyone, is in the moral right?</p>
        <p>WITH ALL DELIBERATE SPEED -- Fifty years ago next week (May 17, 1954), the Supreme Court ruled on Brown v. Board of Education, striking down racial segregation in American schools. Peter Gilbert, the cinematographer of ''Hoop Dreams,'' directs this documentary, focusing on that landmark decision and featuring both archival footage and new interviews. One subject is Barbara Johns, who led a student strike in Farmville, Va., where the county board of education actually shut down schools for five years rather than integrate them.</p>
        <p>May 19</p>
        <p>S21: THE KHMER ROUGE KILLING MACHINE -- Some two million people were tortured and murdered at S21, a Cambodian prison in a suburb of Phnom Penh. Rithy Panh's parents and sisters were among them. Mr. Panh directed this documentary horror movie, which includes re-enactments as well as interviews with survivors and guards.</p>
        <p>May 21</p>
        <p>CONTROL ROOM -- Behind the scenes at Al-Jazeera. Setting out to explore the concept of journalistic objectivity, Jehane Noujaim takes her cameras to the studios of what is now the most popular source of information in the Arab world and talks to reporters and editors there. Ms. Noujaim, an Egyptian-American born in Cairo, worked with D. A. Pennebaker on American music documentaries.</p>
        <p>LOVE ME IF YOU DARE -- (''Jeux d'Enfants'') This French romantic comedy-drama begins when 8-year-old Sophie is teased by classmates on the school bus and Julien befriends her. He's feeling like an outsider because his mother is dying, and they shut out the world by inventing a game of outrageous dares. The strange part is that they keep up the game until they've grown into love-starved adults (Guillaume Canet and Marion Cotillard) and unaware that it prevents them from realizing they're meant for each other. Yann Samuell, the first-time director, has set the story in an allegorical universe that sometimes feels like a fairy tale and sometimes feels more serious.</p>
        <p>MY MOTHER LIKES WOMEN -- (''A Mi Madre Le Gustan las Mujeres'') It happens. A woman gets married, brings up children, builds a career, lives her life and then, one day, realizes she's a lesbian. And when it happens to Sofia (Rosa María Sardà), a famous pianist, in this comedy from Spain, her three grown daughters all react differently. Elvira (Leonor Watling), the true neurotic among them, decides to split up her mother and her new lover (Eliska Sirová) by seducing the other woman. Inés París and Daniela Fejerman directed.</p>
        <p>SHREK 2 -- The celebrity voices of Mike Myers, Cameron Diaz and Eddie Murphy are back for this sequel to the story of two extremely unattractive ogres who meet and fall in love. When Fiona (Ms. Diaz) and Shrek (Mr. Myers) pay a visit to her royal parents (the voices of John Cleese and Julie Andrews), Mom and Dad are not thrilled that their little girl's husband is green and lumpy. And so is she! Soon, Dad is doing everything to encourage a romance between Fiona and Prince Charming (the voice of Rupert Everett) instead. Meanwhile, Donkey (Mr. Murphy) has had a taste of the happily-ever-after potion and turned into a handsome stallion. Other new voices include Antonio Banderas as Puss-in-Boots and Larry King as the Ugly Stepsister.</p>
        <p>STATESIDE -- This love story begins like a sort of dark-side ''Private Benjamin'' for boys. Mark Deloach (''The Texas Chain saw Massacre''), a rich kid from Connecticut, joins the Marine Corps at a judge's urging after a sports-car-related prank. Luckily he gets an impressive drill instructor (Val Kilmer), so maybe Mark has found his home. But on leave, he falls in love with a young pop star (Rachael Leigh Cook). Now he's torn between helping her (she's also a mental patient) and returning to his unit. The cast also includes Carrie Fisher, Joe Mantegna, Ed Begley Jr., Penny Marshall and Diana Venora. Written and directed by Reverge Anselmo.</p>
        <p>TWIST -- Dickens's ''Oliver Twist'' set among male hustlers in present-day Montreal. Joshua Close is Oliver, who is a sort of supporting player here. Gary Farmer is Fagin. And Nick Stahl plays Dodge, formerly known as the Artful Dodger. Jacob Tierney directed.</p>
        <p>UNION SQUARE -- A documentary about seven young homeless heroin addicts in New York and the lengths to which they go, regularly, for their next fix. Directed by Stephen J. Szklarski.</p>
        <p>May 26</p>
        <p>THE FIVE OBSTRUCTIONS -- Lars von Trier loves his mentor, Jorgen Leth, so much that he challenged him to remake his 1967 short ''The Perfect Human'' (a mockumentary about models of the ideal modern Dane) with some new, rather limiting conditions. Like ''Film in the most miserable place on earth.'' For some reason, Mr. Leth agreed.</p>
        <p>May 28</p>
        <p>ADORED: DIARY OF A MALE PORN STAR -- It's an Italian family drama and a gay man's fun-filled story. Marco Filiberti wrote, directed and stars in the story of Riki Kandansky, a rich, happy bachelor living in Rome. When his father dies, his brother comes to visit and learns just how Riki finances his glamorous life: as a successful gay porn star. Then an orphaned boy enters the picture, and Riki decides he'd like to be a father. The next question is who is allowed to create a family and who gets to decide that.</p>
        <p>BAADASSSSS! -- Mario Van Peebles writes and directs a portrait of a film pioneer (whom he also plays): his father, Melvin. The elder Mr. Van Peebles had to make his first full-length film, ''The Story of a Three-Day Pass'' (a 1968 romantic comedy about racism and the United States Army), in France, but Hollywood was ready (sort of) for his next, ''Watermelon Man,'' and his third, ''Sweet Sweetback's Baad Asssss Song'' (1971), was an indie hit. David Alan Grier, Ossie Davis, Bill Cosby, Joy Bryant, Nia Long, Adam West and Sally Struthers make appearances.</p>
        <p>THE DAY AFTER TOMORROW -- One day it's boiling hot. The next it's subzero. Sounds like two months ago in New York, but it's also the situation in this disaster picture about global warming. Dennis Quaid, Jake Gyllenhaal, Emmy Rossum, Ian Holm and Sela Ward are among the earthlings facing the cataclysm, created by Roland Emmerich, who gave us ''Independence Day.''</p>
        <p>THE MOTHER -- In ''Notting Hill,'' Roger Michell made us believe that a shy London bookstore owner could find love with a glamorous Hollywood movie star. Here he proposes that a suburban grandmother (the British television actress Anne Reid), whose husband inconveniently dies during a family visit to London, can find love with a much younger man who is renovating her son's house and sleeping with her daughter. The lover is played by Daniel Craig (Ted Hughes in ''Sylvia''). Moral: Very often, when you think your life is over, it isn't. The screenplay is by Hanif Kureishi. Related article, Page 15.</p>
        <p>RAISING HELEN -- Kate Hudson (of whom we're not quite tired) and John Corbett (of whom, post-''Sex and the City,'' we cannot get enough) in a romantic comedy directed by Garry Marshall, who loves fairy tales (''The Princess Diaries,'' ''Runaway Bride''). Ms. Hudson plays the cool New York aunt, with a glamorous modeling-agency career and a late-night party life, who suddenly finds herself responsible for her sister's three children (ages 5, 10 and 15). Mr. Corbett is the doubly wholesome (he's the principal and the minister) potential love interest in her new world. Could the outcome be any more predictable?</p>
        <p>SAVED! -- When Mary's boyfriend tells her he may be gay, she asks herself what Jesus would want her to do. After all, she's a respected born-again Baptist at American Christian High School. So she helps the boyfriend explore his sexuality, finds herself pregnant and is soon a school outcast. Mary (Jena Malone) then turns to some other losers (Macaulay Culkin, Patrick Fugit and Eva Amurri among them) and creates a new inner circle. Their novel idea: open-mindedness. Mandy Moore and Heather Matarazzo play her former friends in this satiric drama. Martin Donovan is Pastor Skip. Brian Dannelly directed.</p>
        <p>SOUL PLANE -- Some people who had a bad experience on a plane, sued and came away with a fabulous cash settlement might buy a 12-room apartment with park views, a house in the Hamptons and a couple of Bentleys. When that happens to Nashawn Wade (Kevin Hart), he founds Nashawn Wade Airlines, on which you'll find sexy flight attendants, funky music, a person in the bathroom who hands you towels and an on-board dance club. The maiden voyage is quite a party. This ensemble comedy also stars Tom Arnold, D. L. Hughley, Method Man, Mo'Nique and Snoop Dogg. Jessy Terrero (''The Clinic'') directed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
