<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="29OBSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1593011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Caffeine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hibernation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lemurs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philippines</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madagascar</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Sydney</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phillips University (Marburg, Germany)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heldmaier, Gerhard (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hibernation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1D91438F93AA15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Sydney researchers find that bees have internal thermostats that tell them when to fan hive to cool it down; study, published in journal Science, suggests that more genetically diverse hives maintain optimum temperature more easily than hives containing bees from same parents; team of researchers from Philippines, China and United States study how temperatures affect rice yields; findings, published in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, show that warmer night temperatures recorded during dry season over period from 1979 to 2003 have reduced yield; hold that 1.8 degree increase reduces mass yield by 10 percent; Brazilian scientists discover naturally decaffeinated arabicas coffee plant; discovery is reported in journal Nature; Gerhard Heldmaier, Phillips University in Marburg, Germany, animal sociology professor, leads team of researchers studying hibernation habits of Madagascar's fat-tailed dwarf lemur, which is first primate shown to hibernate; study, published in journal Nature, suggests that body temperature is key reason for periods of arousal during hibernation; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Running Hot and Cold</p>
        <p>Diversity in the workplace can be a good thing, particularly if that workplace is a beehive. Not a beehive of human activity, Australian scientists report, but a real beehive.</p>
        <p>In a study to be published by the journal Science, researchers at the University of Sydney show that genetic diversity among worker bees helps make a hive more stable, by better regulating temperature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Running Hot and Cold</p>
        <p>Diversity in the workplace can be a good thing, particularly if that workplace is a beehive. Not a beehive of human activity, Australian scientists report, but a real beehive.</p>
        <p>In a study to be published by the journal Science, researchers at the University of Sydney show that genetic diversity among worker bees helps make a hive more stable, by better regulating temperature.</p>
        <p>For proper brood development, a hive needs to stay 90 to 97 degrees Fahrenheit and, optimally, about 95. The heating and cooling to maintain temperature is provided by the workers. If the hive is too hot, the bees fan hot air out. If it is too cold, they cluster together to generate warmth.</p>
        <p>That is the overall response. But individually, each bee has its own thermostat -- a ''task threshold,'' in the researchers' words -- that tells it when to start fanning. If all the bees were genetically similar, the progeny of the queen and a single male, then they all might be expected to start fanning at the same temperature. The hive might reach the proper temperature, but the uniform response would make it swing between too hot and too cold.</p>
        <p>But if the workers were genetically diverse, the offspring of several males, then response temperatures would be more varied, heating and cooling would be more gradual, and the bees would be better able to maintain the optimum temperature.</p>
        <p>This is exactly what the researchers found. While genetically diverse and uniform hives reached the optimum temperature, the temperature of the diverse hive varied one-third as much as that of the uniform hive.</p>
        <p>The researchers suggest that other elements of life in bee colonies may be affected by variation in task thresholds among the individuals.</p>
        <p>Rice and Warm Weather</p>
        <p>Humans, of course, have not been doing too well in regulating the temperature of their own beehive. And now an international team of researchers has shown one more negative effect of global warming -- it can reduce crop yields.</p>
        <p>The team, from the Philippines, China and the United States, studied temperature trends and yields at a farm run by the International Rice Research Institute, a research group in Los Baños, near Manila.</p>
        <p>From 1979 to 2003, mean daily maximum (daytime) temperatures at the site increased by 0.6 degrees, and minimum (nighttime) temperatures increased 2 degrees. Globally, nighttime temperatures have increased faster than daytime ones, as greenhouse gases tend to trap more heat radiating from the ground, reducing the cooling.</p>
        <p>The researchers, whose work was published in the current issue of The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, found a correlation between night temperatures in the dry season from January to April and rice yields.</p>
        <p>For each increase in temperature of 1.8 degrees, they say, the total biomass yield (all the above-ground portion of the plant) is reduced by 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Most studies of the effects of global warming on crops have used computer simulations. This is one of the first to try to measure the effects directly. Because so much of the world depends on rice, it could be severe.</p>
        <p>Hope for Decaf Lovers</p>
        <p>For coffee drinkers, the news is slightly better. Scientists in Brazil have discovered a naturally decaffeinated coffee plant.</p>
        <p>Coffee is decaffeinated by industrial processes, with a loss of some flavor. While some low-caffeine but poor-quality species of coffee shrub have been discovered, scientists have been unable to blend them genetically with arabica plants, the preferred variety worldwide.</p>
        <p>The Brazilian plants, however, are arabica variants and contain about one-sixteenth as much caffeine as typical arabicas. The researchers, reporting on their discovery in Nature, say it should be relatively easy to transfer the low-caffeine trait to commercial arabica varieties.</p>
        <p>Sitting Out the Summer</p>
        <p>Thanks to modern refrigeration, you can ice skate in July and ski in August. Now it seems that hibernation is not a cold-weather activity, either.</p>
        <p>Scientists in Germany have discovered that the fat-tailed dwarf lemur of Madagascar hibernates in holes in trees for about seven months of the year. It is the first primate that has been definitely shown to hibernate, the scientists say.</p>
        <p>Madagascar is hardly a winter wonderland. Temperatures can be in the 70's that time of year.</p>
        <p>''Usually, everybody thinks hibernation has to do with cold,'' said Dr. Gerhard Heldmaier, a professor of animal sociology at Phillips University in Marburg and an author of a paper on the lemur that is in the current issue of the journal Nature. ''These data show that's not necessary.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Heldmaier said the fruit-eating lemurs hibernated to avoid food shortages in the dry season. Like other hibernators, to prepare, they pack on the pounds -- in the tail. ''It looks like a real fat sausage,'' he said.</p>
        <p>All hibernators have periods of arousal, usually every 7 to 10 days, when they raise body temperatures. Scientists do not know why this happens, but the lemur research offers an important clue, Dr. Heldmaier said.</p>
        <p>He and a doctoral student, Kathrin Dausmann, along with other researchers, obtained detailed body temperature data for about two dozen lemurs, thanks to sensors implanted in the abdomen or on collars. Some animals hibernated in holes that had thick walls and were thus well insulated. Air temperature in those holes did not vary much, and neither did body temperature, except in arousal periods, when it climbed to 95 from about 75.</p>
        <p>Other lemurs hibernated in holes that were less well insulated. In these cases, body temperatures fluctuated widely each day, from 60 to 90 degrees, closely following fluctuations in the air temperature in the hole.</p>
        <p>These lemurs, Dr. Heldmaier said, did not have wakeful periods, presumably because the air had warmed them up enough. ''There seems to be a threshold temperature that has to be passed so that arousals are not necessary,'' he said.</p>
        <p>This further suggests why periodic arousal is common for hibernators. ''They cannot tolerate a permanent state at a low body temperature,'' Dr. Heldmaier said. ''They have to raise it after a while.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
