<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D81630F93AA35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Unanimous Vote at U.N. For Iraq Resolution  The Security Council voted in favor of an American and British resolution to end the formal occupation of Iraq on June 30 and transfer ''full sovereignty'' to an interim Iraqi government. The resolution authorized an American-led multinational force to be part of a ''security partnership'' with Iraqi forces.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Bush, in Georgia for a three-day meeting of the Group of 8 leaders, welcomed the adoption of the resolution.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Unanimous Vote at U.N. For Iraq Resolution  The Security Council voted in favor of an American and British resolution to end the formal occupation of Iraq on June 30 and transfer ''full sovereignty'' to an interim Iraqi government. The resolution authorized an American-led multinational force to be part of a ''security partnership'' with Iraqi forces.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Bush, in Georgia for a three-day meeting of the Group of 8 leaders, welcomed the adoption of the resolution.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A crisis for the new Iraqi government loomed as Kurdish leaders threatened to withdraw from the Iraqi state unless they received guarantees against Shiite plans to limit Kurdish self-rule.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The leaders of the Senate intelligence committee are pressing the C.I.A. to agree to a declassification and release of the panel's report, which is critical of the agency's prewar performance on Iraq.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Car bombings in two cities killed at least 11 Iraqis, and an American soldier and six soldiers from three other countries were killed while trying to defuse mines, officials said.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>A power plant south of Baghdad was shut down last weekend by coordinated attacks on fuel and transmission lines, American and Iraqi government officials said.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>American Killed in Saudi Capital  An employee of an American military contractor was shot dead in Riyadh, the latest in a series of killings aimed against foreigners.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Two Terror Arrests in Italy  The Italian police said they had arrested two men suspected of being terrorists, including an Egyptian who reportedly helped plan the train bombings in Madrid on March 11.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>New Setback for Sharon  Two senior members of a far-right party quit Prime Minister Ariel Sharon's government following a cabinet vote approving in principle a Gaza Strip withdrawal plan.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-21</p>
        <p>Crowds Come Out in Force To Pay Tribute to Reagan  As many as 100,000 visitors sought to file past the coffin of former president Ronald Reagan at the rotunda of his library in California, forcing officials to extend the planned viewing hours to 10 p.m. from 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>On the way to pay his respects to Mr. Reagan, Senator John Kerry criticized President Bush for marginalizing Democrats and recalled his own role in Mr. Reagan's history.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan's death has set off debates among Republicans about honoring him on the nation's currency or coins. The Ronald Reagan Legacy Project has focused on the $10 bill because Alexander Hamilton, who now occupies it, was not a president.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Boston Bracing for Convention  The transit authority of Boston said it would begin random inspections of the bags of passengers on subway and commuter trains as the Democratic Convention nears.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Felons' Voting Rights Debated  Some county elections supervisors in Florida worry that a new list of suspected felons might be flawed, and that a new state law makes it too easy to disqualify valid voters.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Kin of Bomb Victims Testify  Two people who lost relatives in the Oklahoma City bombing testified on behalf of Terry Nichols, as closing arguments ended in the penalty phase of his state murder trial.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Venus Aligns With Earth and Sun  Millions of people across the world watched as the orbits of Earth, Venus and the Sun were aligned along the same plane for the first time in more than a century.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>New Evidence of Water on Mars  The Mars rover Spirit dug up more evidence of water on the planet, NASA scientists said.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Impeachment Hearings Begin in Connecticut  The legislative committee investigating whether to recommend the impeachment of Gov. John G. Rowland began taking testimony in public hearings, the first such proceeding involving a sitting United States governor in 16 years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rally for Higher Wages  Thousands of teachers, police officers and firefighters packed several blocks of Broadway near City Hall Park in a demonstration of their demands for raises and new labor contracts.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Robber Flees Red-Handed  A man robbed a Manhattan bank, escaped with an undisclosed amount of cash and then ran into a busy subway station, where a dye pack in his bag of money exploded, sending out a cloud of red smoke and stinging the eyes of morning commuters, the police said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>New Script for Emergency Drill  An emergency drill conducted at the Indian Point nuclear power plant involved a simulated terror attack and the participation of the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>SPORTSWEDNESDAY</p>
        <p>D1-6</p>
        <p>Lakers Tie Series, 1-1  Los Angeles beat the Detroit Pistons, 99-91, in overtime in Game 2 of the N.B.A. championship finals.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Plan Would Cut Car Emissions  An initial draft of a California global warming regulation would require automakers to cut emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases linked to climate change by as much as 30 percent over the next decade.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Warning on Interest Rates  Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve, signaled the financial markets to prepare for a sharper rise in interest rates in future months if inflation turns out to be a more serious problem.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Clear Channel to Pay Fines  Clear Channel Communications agreed to pay the F.C.C. more than $1.7 million in penalties to settle a series of indecency complaints made against its stations.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Pressure on Bank Regulators  The State Department is pressing federal bank regulators to address the inability of some foreign embassies to find banking services in the United States.</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The roots of Abu Ghraib; shushing the big city; sneaky moves on tobacco; Serge Schmemann on a Russian émigré who finally gets his Russian passport.</p>
        <p>Columns: Nicholas D. Kristof, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E2  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
