<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Exploring After Martian Winter, Rovers Send Back More Signs of Water</title>
    <meta content="08MARS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/08/science/08mars.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1617374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spirit (Mars Rover)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opportunity (Mars Rover)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD153BF93BA35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Exploring After Martian Winter, Rovers Send Back More Signs of Water</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Still Exploring After Martian Winter, Rovers Send Back More Signs of Water</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mission officials say roving vehicles Spirit and Opportunity continue to amass evidence of past liquid water shaping now arid surface of Mars, NASA teleconference; search for water is major objective because it could indicate presence of life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aging but still on the go, climbing in and around craters, tapping into the mysteries of strangely cracked rocks, the two roving vehicles Spirit and Opportunity have explored Mars about three times as long as originally scheduled and keep finding evidence of past liquid water shaping the now arid surface.</p>
        <p>Mission officials reported yesterday that the rovers, which landed on Mars in January, have emerged from the planet's winter and resumed full operations. Even Spirit, suffering steering troubles with two of its six wheels, was able to climb higher into the hills inside a vast crater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two roving vehicles Spirit and Opportunity have explored Mars about three times as long as originally scheduled and keep finding evidence of past liquid water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aging but still on the go, climbing in and around craters, tapping into the mysteries of strangely cracked rocks, the two roving vehicles Spirit and Opportunity have explored Mars about three times as long as originally scheduled and keep finding evidence of past liquid water shaping the now arid surface.</p>
        <p>Mission officials reported yesterday that the rovers, which landed on Mars in January, have emerged from the planet's winter and resumed full operations. Even Spirit, suffering steering troubles with two of its six wheels, was able to climb higher into the hills inside a vast crater.</p>
        <p>In a NASA teleconference with reporters, scientists said that in addition to evidence of water-altered bedrock the rover Opportunity had come across numerous flat rocks covered in cracks that form patterns of interconnected polygons. Or to be more down-to-earth, the rocks appeared to be fractured like dried mud.</p>
        <p>The scientists showed pictures of the fractured rocks and suggested that they were possible evidence of watery episodes even after the main contours of the surface were formed, events that are also thought to have been associated with the presence of liquid water.</p>
        <p>''When we saw these polygonal crack patterns, right away we thought of a secondary water event significantly later than the episode that created the rocks,'' said Dr. John Grotzinger, a geologist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who is on the rover science team.</p>
        <p>At some point, Dr. Grotzinger explained, the rocks may have been soaked in water, perhaps from frost melting during an interval of climate change. Another possibility is that the release of underground water left a shallow lake within the crater. In that case, the saturated rocks would have contracted as they dried, leaving stress fractures.</p>
        <p>The episode presumably occurred after the rocks formed, the scientists said, because the polygon patterns appear to crosscut the underlying layers within the rock. Like many of the other rocks examined by the rovers, these held chemical clues of alterations caused by liquid water.</p>
        <p>But geologists conceded that they could not be sure the cracks developed after the crater was formed. Another explanation, they said, is that the force of the crater-causing impact could have left the polygonal fractures. Opportunity's next target for study, a lumpy boulder, could narrow the range of speculation.</p>
        <p>The search for water on Mars is a major objective of scientists because it could provide evidence that life evolved there.</p>
        <p>New investigations by the two rovers have continued to turn up evidence of liquid water scrambling the chemistry of surface rocks.</p>
        <p>''Every single rock has shown significant signs of alteration by liquid water,'' said Dr. Steven W. Squyres, a Cornell planetary scientist who is the principal investigator for the rover mission. ''We're having a wonderful time trying to work out exactly what happened here.''</p>
        <p>Mission officials also made public the rovers' close-up pictures of the rocks as well as spectacular mosaics of dunes spreading over a crater floor and a 360-degree view of the hills and valleys of Gusev Crater. A part of Spirit itself is seen in the foreground, looking out on the vista where scientists say they can just make out the rover's tracks back toward its landing site nearly two miles away. Photographs are available at jpl.nasa.gov.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
