<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What O. J. Passed To the Gipper</title>
    <meta content="20RICH$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/20/arts/20RICH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1591010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Frank Rich"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Simpson Murder Case</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, O J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, Nicole Brown (1959-94)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldman, Ronald Lyle (1968-94)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Simpson, O J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DD1E30F933A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What O. J. Passed To the Gipper</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What O. J. Passed to the Gipper</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Rich column questions reasons for exhaustive, week-long media coverage of Ronald Reagan's interment; sees excess shaped more by cultural forces than by partisanship; cites transformation of American television news into 24/7 'news' reality by coverage 10 years ago of O J Simpson murder case; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOT a single jelly bean remained unturned in the weeklong interment of Ronald Reagan, but a week later there's one question that still hasn't been laid to rest: what in heaven's name was going on?</p>
        <p>Was this runaway marathon of mourning prompted by actual grief? A vast right-wing conspiracy? A vast reservoir of displaced sorrow about the war in Iraq? Global warming? Whatever it was about, it was not always about Ronald Reagan. His average approval rating in office was lower than that of many modern presidents, including each George Bush. His death at 93, after a full life and a long terminal illness, was neither tragic nor shocking. And in 2004, his presidency was far from the center of American consciousness. The cold war that he ''won'' (with no help from the Poles, the Czechs, Mikhail Gorbachev, the first President Bush or anyone else, mind you) had dropped into the great American memory hole in our age of terrorism, along with his administration's support of incipient bin Laden-style Islamic militants in Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like every other big story in the post-O. J. era, Ronald Reagan's farewell was automatically supersized to satisfy our bottomless appetite for the mediathon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOT a single jelly bean remained unturned in the weeklong interment of Ronald Reagan, but a week later there's one question that still hasn't been laid to rest: what in heaven's name was going on?</p>
        <p>Was this runaway marathon of mourning prompted by actual grief? A vast right-wing conspiracy? A vast reservoir of displaced sorrow about the war in Iraq? Global warming? Whatever it was about, it was not always about Ronald Reagan. His average approval rating in office was lower than that of many modern presidents, including each George Bush. His death at 93, after a full life and a long terminal illness, was neither tragic nor shocking. And in 2004, his presidency was far from the center of American consciousness. The cold war that he ''won'' (with no help from the Poles, the Czechs, Mikhail Gorbachev, the first President Bush or anyone else, mind you) had dropped into the great American memory hole in our age of terrorism, along with his administration's support of incipient bin Laden-style Islamic militants in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Of course, Reagan's funeral was must-see TV. But then there was all the rest of it. You knew things had gotten out of hand when CNN's Anderson Cooper invited an expert from the ''Grief Recovery Institute'' to instruct the nation: ''Today I'm saying we need to feel sad.'' Or when C-Span broadcast uninterrupted late-night video of Americans trooping past Reagan's coffin in the Capitol's rotunda. (Though those mourners were often touted as representative of the entire nation, you could nod off counting the white visitors before a black person appeared.) Even those voting at the Web site of The Wall Street Journal's editorial page, that permanent shrine to all things Reagan, decided by a slightly larger than the Gore-Bush margin by the week's end that the coverage was ''too much'' (36 percent to 34, when I checked).</p>
        <p>To liberals, the circus was a political plot to cover up Reagan's failures and obscure fresh headlines about the paper trail linking the Bush administration to the practice of torture. To conservatives, anyone who opted for even modest restraint in Reagan coverage (like The New York Times, with its three-column headline announcing his death) was guilty of insufficient sentimentality; anyone who criticized the man was a traitor. ''Thoughtless, mean, hateful'' were just some of the epithets heaped by Fox's Sean Hannity on a rare Reagan dissenter who showed his face on TV, the political cartoonist Ted Rall.</p>
        <p>By the time the final rites reached their finale, however, you could see that other, more powerful cultural forces had shaped the week's excess, not mere partisanship. The crucial influence may have been an apolitical event whose 10th anniversary all too aptly coincided with Reagan's farewell -- the murders of Nicole Simpson and Ron Goldman. That crime sped the profound transformation of American television in the ensuing decade, when news was remade into a 24/7 ''news'' reality show. (Which in turn begat the equally fictionalized genre of reality television, the bastard child of the original bastard.) The impact of O. J. Simpson on America's infotainment media culture was as pronounced in its way as the Gipper's touchdown for conservatism in American politics.</p>
        <p>During the Reagan show the Simpson impact was sometimes literally acted out: the gratuitously attenuated aerial shots of the hearse streaking on California freeways to Simi Valley carried an eerie visual echo of the Bronco chase. But the greater symmetry was in the overall dramatic format of the seven-day extravaganza. Like every other story in the post-O. J. era involving some admixture of death, scandal or celebrities, from presidents to punks, Reagan's farewell was automatically supersized to satisfy our bottomless appetite for the mediathon, an epic form of TV news that has become as rigid and familiar as a game show or a sitcom.</p>
        <p>There has been blanket coverage of news events since TV's infancy -- this spring marks the 50th anniversary of the first story to receive it, the Army-McCarthy hearings -- and of presidential funerals since the Kennedy assassination. But it was not until the O. J. trial, all 251 days of it, that the powerful and relatively new tool of the all-news TV channel collided with a news story of big emotions and little actual news to become an addictive brand of marathon diversion. Though Reagan, the first true TV president, was a master of showbiz manipulation, he would hardly recognize the bizarre brew of fact and fiction that so thoroughly redefined televised reality in the decade since his withdrawal from the public stage. (His letter announcing the diagnosis of his Alzheimer's followed O. J.'s arraignment by some four months.) It was during the O. J. soap opera that we first learned we could spend not just hours and days but weeks watching a drama even when it was unfolding in slo-mo (under Lance Ito's Warholesque direction) and even when nothing was happening beyond the idle, frequently erroneous speculation of camera-hogging ''experts'' (most of them looking for fame or book deals).</p>
        <p>So went the seven days of Reagan. As we now know, the former president's aides and family had devised some of the settings years in advance through a secret plan they code-named Operation Serenade: the camera angles and sunset timing of the California service, the distribution of 50,000 small American flags to extras organized along the route. Such Old Hollywood cinematic touches no doubt seemed clever when the Reaganauts first hatched them, but by the time of Reagan's death they were as dated as ''Bedtime for Bonzo.'' The post-O. J. arsenal of media weapons all but upstaged the prissy soundstage pageantry. Unchanging, lachrymose platitudes were repeated histrionically again and again day after day, padded out with faux controversies (will Reagan wipe Andrew Jackson off the $20 bill, Alexander Hamilton off the $10 bill, or J.F.K. off the half-dollar?) and the musings of third-tier experts like Gahl Burt, ''former Reagan social secretary.'' When all else failed, non-celebrated victims of Alzheimer's were rolled on to CNN to supply some collateral tragedy. Network anchors interviewed former colleagues like Cokie and Sam, who were happy to airbrush the history of the presidency they covered as payoff for reliving their own salad days as TV stars.</p>
        <p>But there was one encouraging sign in the flood of blather about optimism. America's infatuation with these exercises in overkill shows signs of waning. More viewers realize that the excessive length and grave tone of a mediathon are not necessarily an indication of either the importance of the events getting the air time or of the accuracy of the flowery storytelling. Experts kept saying how ''surprised'' everyone was about ''the outpouring'' for Reagan, but saying didn't make it so. The dirty little secret of the week: the outpouring didn't live up to its hype. ''There was this kind of extraordinary outpouring not by the public but by reporters who should know better,'' as Morley Safer told Larry King after it was over.</p>
        <p>A total of some 200,000 Americans passed by the coffin in California and Washington. The crowds watching the funeral procession in Washington numbered in the ''tens of thousands,'' reported The Washington Post. By comparison, three million Americans greeted the cross-country journey of Warren Harding's funeral train from San Francisco to Washington when he died in office in the steamy August of 1923, according to Mark Sullivan's history, ''Our Times.'' It took 3,500 soldiers to direct the crowd in his hometown of Marion, Ohio, alone. The grief for Harding was so pronounced in New York, a city that hardly knew him, that The Times reported how theaters canceled their shows to hold impromptu memorial gatherings for those citizens unable to jam into the packed services held in Trinity Church at Wall Street and Temple Emanu-El uptown and most houses of worship in between. Next to that, the Reagan outpouring, much of it carried out by bubbly TV-camera-seeking citizens in halter tops and shorts, was grief lite.</p>
        <p>Harding's huge turnout didn't alter his hapless historical fate, but at least it was a genuine event. When every tragic news story, from Columbine to the Columbia shuttle to JonBenet Ramsey and Chandra Levy, is supersized in our national theater of TV, all of them are downsized. Incessant hyperbole becomes as numbing as Muzak. No matter how many TV recyclings, the close-ups of Nancy Reagan's three trips to her husband's coffin may never trump the single long shot of John John saluting his father. No matter how many pundits proclaim Reagan a great president, a realistic assessment remains on hold -- especially since, as The Los Angeles Times reported, 90 percent of the 55 million pages of his papers is still off-limits to scholars at the presidential library where he was entombed. (A 2001 George W. Bush executive order could restrict access to every modern president's historical record indefinitely.)</p>
        <p>When that entombment finally arrived, national mourning was giving way to national boredom. Except at Fox News Channel, ratings did not spike on either network or cable. ''It was not a massively watched event,'' one CNN producer said to The Times's Bill Carter. ''It was a largely watched event.'' Translation: Is it too late to grab a piece of the new J. Lo nuptials? Eventually, even Fox was elbowing Reagan into the wings for its O. J. retrospectives. On the Friday morning of Reagan's National Cathedral funeral, Matt Lauer tried to hold the ''Today'' show audience by promising a medley of mediathon standards: ''A lot of news coming out of Washington, Katie, but there's other news to talk about as well, including major developments in the Kobe Bryant, Martha Stewart and Scott Peterson cases.''</p>
        <p>Only three days later, Bill Clinton, the star of the longest-running news miniseries of them all, ''Impeachment of the President,'' was back in the White House, as a preview of coming attractions for the televised book tour he kicks off tonight on ''60 Minutes.'' Even President Bush was glad to see him. Once people line up to buy the book, there will be no shortage of talking heads remarking on ''the surprise outpouring'' for the man they declared dead just a few years ago. At least Ronald Reagan, who understood nothing if not the cruel and fickle vagaries of show business, might find it funny. You can almost hear him saying, ''There you go again.''</p>
        <p>Frank Rich</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
