<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ART GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="14ART.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/14/arts/design/14ART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1581455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2DD113CF937A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="8295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ART GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Listings</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Berlin's Nationalgalerie has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. One of the show's great ''Metropolis'' paintings is Kirchner's large ''Potsdamer Platz'' (1914); in the ''Arcadia'' mode is Modersohn-Becker's ''Kneeling Mother With Child'' (1907). Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy art, design and photography exhibitions at New York museums and art galleries this weekend. At many museums, children under 12 and members are admitted free. Addresses, unless otherwise noted, are in Manhattan. Most galleries are closed on Sundays and Mondays, but hours vary and should be checked by telephone. Gallery admission is free unless noted. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>''ARCADIA AND METROPOLIS: MASTERWORKS OF GERMAN EXPRESSIONISM FROM THE NATIONALGALERIE BERLIN,'' Neue Galerie, 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, through June 7. In 1937 the Nazis seized a large collection of Expressionist works from the Kronprinzen Palace in Berlin, Germany's first museum of contemporary art. But this branch of Berlin's Nationalgalerie has made great strides in restoring what was the heart of its collection. This show of 40 works by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Emil Nolde, Max Beckmann, George Grosz, Otto Dix, Hannah Hoch, Paula Modersohn-Becker and others touches on the history of German modern art -- Expressionism, Dadaism, Neue Sachlichkeit -- from around 1910 through the post-World War I period. Its title is drawn from the early preference of the Expressionists for rural places versus their later attraction to the city. One of the show's great ''Metropolis'' paintings is Kirchner's large ''Potsdamer Platz'' (1914); in the ''Arcadia'' mode is Modersohn-Becker's ''Kneeling Mother With Child'' (1907). Satirical thrusts at the failures of the Weimar Republic by Hoch, Dix and Grosz are also standouts. Hours: Fridays, 11 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and Mondays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $10; $7 for students and 65+ (Grace Glueck).</p>
        <p>* ''BYZANTIUM: FAITH AND POWER (1261-1557),'' Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street, (212) 535-7710, through July 4. This vast and humblingly beautiful show about the waning centuries of the Byzantine empire reminds us that political decay does does not necessarily mean artistic decline. Full of amazing exotica -- manuscripts, miniature mosaics, textiles, drawings, paintings -- the exhibition ends with a room of great Northern Renaissance art indebted to icons that proves Byzantium's continued reach. People who are not Eastern Orthodox believers can enjoy the earthly pleasures of aesthetic spectacle linked with historical enlightenment. Hours: Sundays and Tuesdays through Thursdays, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $7 (Michael Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''AN ENDURING VISION: 17th- TO 20TH-CENTURY JAPANESE PAINTING FROM THE GITTER-YELEN COLLECTION,'' Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, (212) 832-1155, through June 20. Six schools of Japanese art that flourished during the Edo period (1615-1868) and on into the 20th century -- Nanga, Zenga, Rinpa, Maruyama-Shijo, Ukiyo-e and the Eccentrics -- are celebrated with about 75 examples from an outstanding private collection. With screens, hanging scrolls, albums and fans depicting flora and fauna, the forces of nature, abstract mountainscapes, genre scenes and calligraphy, done by some of the era's best artists, the show provides a rich acquaintance with four centuries of Japanese art. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 65+, $3 (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* ''FASHIONING FICTION IN PHOTOGRAPHY SINCE 1990,'' Museum of Modern Art, Queens, 33rd Road and Queens Boulevard, Long Island City, (212) 708-9600, through June 28. With its first exhibition of fashion photography, the Modern dips a toe into a very large body of water, and dithers. The works by 13 artists and fashion photographers, including Cindy Sherman, Nan Goldin, Phillip-Lorca diCorcia and Cedric Buchet, focuses on the recent uses of narrative in both magazine features and advertising. How recent this development is could be debated, but mainly the Modern seems determined to make everything look like appropriation art. This seems unnecessary in a museum known for showing all kinds of everyday design objects. The show sticks too closely to the mainstream fashion press, which keeps it too superficial, too polite and in some ways misleading. Largely missing are the field's raunchy underbelly and cheap thrills: the intimations of heroin chic, grunge, homoeroticism and teenage sex that can make perusing a fashion magazine feel like a vaguely subversive act. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays to 7:45 p.m. Admission: $12; $8.50 for students and 65+ (Roberta Smith).</p>
        <p>* ''MOMA AT EL MUSEO: LATIN AMERICAN AND CARIBBEAN ART FROM THE COLLECTION OF THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART,'' El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212) 831-7272, through July 25. The first broad-scale exposure of the Modern's extensive holdings from Mexico, the Caribbean and Central and South America, the 150 or so objects here are a small selection from the more than 2,000 it owns. But they form an arresting show, from the powerful Surrealist-  influenced ''Jungle'' (1943) by the Cuban artist Wifredo Lam to an untitled 1995 sculpture by the Colombian Doris Salcedo that invokes the political violence in her country. The sardonic humor of Marisol (Venezuela) and Fernando Botero (Colombia); the geometric tweakings of Jesús Rafael Soto and Gertrude Goldschmidt (Venezuela); the Conceptual hatchings of Felix González-Torres (Cuba) and Cildo Meireles (Brazil), among others, remind us of the artistic richness south of the border. This show joins the strength of the Modern's resources with the growing importance of El Museo as a showcase of Latino culture. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., Thursdays until 9 p.m. Admission: $7; students and 65+, $5 (Glueck).</p>
        <p>''NEXUS: TAIWAN IN QUEENS,'' Queens Museum of Art, Flushing Meadows Corona Park, Queens, (718) 592-9700, through July 4. Twenty artists, all Taiwanese, are assembled for an exhibition about immigration, assimilation, isolation, cultural identity and related issues. Many works are straightforward illustrations of the theme: Lu Hsian Fu's installation of red paper Chinese lanterns threaded with strings of Christmas lights, for example, is about the immigrant's bicultural experience. Some works, like C. J. Yeh's cybernetic translations of Mondrian paintings, resonate more broadly. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission, $5 (Ken Johnson).</p>
        <p>''OPEN HOUSE: WORKING IN BROOKLYN,'' Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000, through Aug. 15. This all-Brooklyn show of new art has been timed to coincide with the inauguration of the museum's new front entrance pavilion and public plaza. With 300 pieces installed in the fourth- and fifth-floor galleries, and spilling over into the permanent collection galleries, it's a very crowded affair. It's also all over the place in terms of media, styles and themes, not to mention quality; the good, the bad and the iffy mingle. Still, there's plenty of good work by artists you know and by some you don't, drawn from across a borough that has many different art worlds. Also on view, though not part of the show, is Alexis Rockman's mural-size painting of Brooklyn 3,000 years in the future, submerged under water as a result of global warming. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (until 11 p.m. the first Saturday of each month). Admission: $6; $3 for students and 62+ (Holland Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''ROTH TIME: A DIETER ROTH RETROSPECTIVE,'' Museum of Modern Art, Queens, 45-20 33rd Street, at Queens Boulevard, Long Island City, (212) 708-9400, and P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084, through June 7. This exhaustive, exhausting but ultimately astounding exhibition offers total immersion in the art of the German-born, Swiss-based multimedia dynamo Dieter Roth (1930-1998), who not only erased the line between art and life, but also fused them into a single insoluble entity. With nearly 400 works of painting, drawing, prints, sculpture, assemblage, collage, music, poetry, film, photography, video and sound, and using every imaginable kind of found object or material -- foodstuffs included -- the exhibition moves through 50 years of incessant, obsessive art-making with remarkable clarity. It culminates in a presentation of five enormous installation pieces at the Modern's little-sister institution, P.S. 1, that reveal a seemingly boundless universe of artistic activity and a radically new picture of an artist at work. MoMA Queens hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Fridays to 7:45 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 65+, $8.50. P.S. 1 hours: Thursdays through Mondays, noon to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $2 (Smith).</p>
        <p>''STAGING THE ORIENT: VISIONS OF THE EAST AT LA SCALA AND THE METROPOLITAN OPERA,'' Dahesh Museum of Art, 580 Madison Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 759-0606, through May 30. For centuries opera was one of Europe's more popular theatrical forms. And while music was certainly a big part of its appeal, for many fans the real attraction lay in spectacular stage sets. These were often designed by leading academic painters and the results, set deep in the past and in places remote from Europe, were examples of how one culture -- Western in this case -- invents exotic, often demeaning visions of others. The Dahesh show considers such matters with the help of prints and drawings and some spectacular costumes worn by famous singers, past and present. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $9, students and 62+, $4. (Cotter).</p>
        <p>* ''WHERE GODS AND MORTALS MEET: CONTINUITY AND RENEWAL IN URHOBO ART,'' Museum for African Art, 36-01 43rd Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-7700, through Aug. 16. This engrossing show documents aspects of a so-called traditional African art as it existed in the recent past, and as it survives in a 21st-century world. Africa in this case means a society called the Urhobo of the Niger Delta, and the art ranges from spectacular larger than life-size figures of ancestor spirits to carvings of grotesque beasts with gaping, saber-toothed mouths, images meant to both encourage and control male aggression. Although some sculptures are now rarely produced in their original forms, they are in the paintings and prints of Bruce Onobrakpeya, a contemporary Delta-born artist of international stature, in whose art Urhobo traditions live on. Hours: Mondays, Thursdays and Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 to 5 p.m. Admission: $6; students and 65+, $3 (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* WHITNEY BIENNIAL, Whitney Museum of American Art, 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676, through May 30. Easily the best biennial in a long time. The spirit is upbeat and ingratiating -- almost polite -- on the surface at least, with a utopian streak and a youth-heavy emphasis on gloss and craft. There's plenty of painting and drawing, ratifying the much-hyped trend, and multigenerational work, stressing ecstatic engagement and meticulousness. But the real story is the stress on the handmade in general, on materiality in whatever medium -- a change from the politics-heavy, slacker installations of recent years. The cross-generational dialogue is an interesting subtext. Among the younger set utopia does not mean 1960's-style radicalism; it implies something unattainable, except perhaps in a hand-me-down form, and therefore smaller and inherently poignant. Look for a few standout works from artists both younger and older, including Yayoi Kusama, Alec Soth, Catherine Opie, Julie Mehretu, Jim Hodges, Eve Sussman, Raymond Pettibon, Slater Bradley, Robert Mangold and Stan Brakhage, who died last year. Hours: Wednesdays, Thursdays, Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Fridays, 1 to 9 p.m. Admission: $12; students and 62+, $9.50 (Kimmelman).</p>
        <p>* ''FRED WILSON, OBJECTS AND INSTALLATIONS: 1979-2000,'' Studio Museum in Harlem, 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, through July 4. Mr. Wilson, who represented the United States at the 2003 Venice Biennale, made his reputation with conceptually pointed, technically polished and visually engaging installations and objects that focused on excavating American racial history and illustrating the exclusionary power of cultural institutions shaped by social, economic and ideological domination. Elements of his subversive museum projects appear in this traveling show, along with sculptures and a fine, short new film. Hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, and Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $5; students and 62+, $3; children under 12, $1 (Cotter).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>BRICE BROWN AND DON JOINT, ''A Marriage in Paint,'' Naumann, 22 East 80th Street, (212) 472-6800, through May 22. Painters who share a life as well as a studio, Mr. Brown and Mr. Joint nevertheless have distinctly disparate abstract styles. Mr. Joint's is one of exuberant high-key color laid down in hard-edge geometric and biomorphic shapes; Mr. Brown's looser brushwork and softer palette relate more to Abstract Expressionism. But subtle similarities might be discerned and the two have painted a collaborative canvas that comes off. Soft shapes and hard ones form a pleasant melding; wayward linear trackings play off precisely formed edges. The colors get along. But each is a persuasive painter in his own right (Glueck).</p>
        <p>* JEFF KOONS, ''Highlights of 25 Years,'' C&amp;M Arts, 45 East 78th Street, (212) 861-0020, through June 5. This excellent 27-piece survey touches on all phases of Mr. Koons's career, including greatest hits like the basketballs mysteriously hovering in aquarium tanks; the Mylar ''Rabbit'' balloon cast in shiny stainless steel; and the sexy blonde embracing the Pink Panther in glazed ceramic. The climax of the show is the 10-foot-tall ''Balloon Dog.'' Made of stainless steel and coated in coppery translucent orange, it is a breathtaking symbol of the inflationary euphoria and anxiety of our times (Johnson).</p>
        <p>MARKUS LÜPERTZ, ''About the Three Graces,'' Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623, through May 29. Mr. Lupertz, usually mentioned along with Georg Baselitz, Sigmar Polke and Anselm Kiefer as a German Neo-Expressionist star of the 1980's, here presents a quartet of massive heads cast in bronze. Tinted in primary colors, these boulderlike representations of the Three Graces, Hera, Venus and Athene, plus one of Paris, look as if they were gouged out of the earth and pummeled into shape by an impatient giant (Johnson)</p>
        <p>JORGE PARDO, Lever House Lobby Gallery, 400 Park Avenue, between 53rd and 54th Streets, , through July 31. If Ikea sold sculptures, they might look like the ones Mr. Pardo installed in the lobby of this famous Modernist high-rise: squat wooden constructions resembling the skeletons of biomorphic chairs, with attractive colored glass lights nested like eggs in the depressions where you would sit. Curiously, the plywood elements that touch the floor have been cut into the silhouettes of animal feet: hooves, bear paws or tentacles (Johnson).</p>
        <p>FRANK STELLA, ''Exotic Birds,'' Gagosian Gallery, 980 Madison Avenue, at 76th Street, (212) 744-2313, through June 5. Looking at Mr. Stella's three big, splashily painted reliefs from a 1976 series, it is easy to forget how shockingly flamboyant they seemed in their day. Now, with their curvy, tilting forms cut from honeycomb-core aluminum panels, and neatly puzzled together within wide slanting frames, they seem prettily demure compared to what has happened since in painting as well as in sculpture (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>''ANIMALS AND US,'' Galerie St. Étienne, 24 West 57th Street, (212) 245-6734, through May 22. This menagerie of an exhibition offers many different species of animals viewed through many stylistic lenses. It includes Sue Coe's expressionistic anticruelty cartoons; William Wegman's comic photographic dog portraits; Frank Noelker's photographs of live animals in zoos; Hiroshi Sugimoto's eerie photographs of simulated animals in museum dioramas; and Rona Pondick's surrealist stainless steel dog, which has a human head and hands cast from life with a smooth and shiny canine body (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* DAISY YOUNGBLOOD, McKee, 745 Fifth Avenue, (212) 688-5951, through May 29. Ms. Youngblood, who is in her late 50's and lives in Costa Rica, last year won a MacArthur award for her exquisitely sensitive, usually small ceramic sculptures of animals and human spiritual gurus. Here are 18 works dating from 1975 to 2003 in which the interest is mainly in the magical tension between the raw clay and the lifelike, psychologically evocative forms and gestures of animal and human bodies (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>LOUISE BELCOURT, ''Wriggling Philosophical Life,'' Jeff Bailey, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 989-0156, through May 29. Ms. Belcourt paints lovable, extremely simplified, sharply contoured pictures of what look like sunlit monumentalized sofa cushions under powder blue skies. Actually they are images of garden hedges in a small northern Quebec town where she grew up. With their attractively glossy, brush-textured surfaces they adroitly juggle the influences of Color Field painting, Pop and Surrealism (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DELIA R. GONZALEZ AND GAVIN R. RUSSOM, ''Evolution Is Extinct,'' Daniel Reich, 537-A West 23rd Street, (917) 408-9097, through May 22. Suburban modernism meets Neo-Gothic grunge in this young team's crowded installation of bookcases, end tables and speaker cabinets, all painted black. Some elements have metal control panels for fine tuning the weird electronic sound effects that reverberate through the gallery. There are also sand sculptures shaped like office buildings; little totemic, sequin-covered coneheads with cowrie shells for eyes and mouths; and a short, low-budget semi-abstract horror movie (Johnson).</p>
        <p>DONALD JUDD, ''Single Stacks 1964-69,'' Van de Weghe, 521 West 23rd Street, (212) 929-6633, through May 28. The wall-mounted boxes featured here look like units from Judd's vertical ladderlike works. Different ones are made of shiny copper, stainless steel or galvanized steel; some have Plexiglas panels casting colored light on the walls below. The installation is elegant and funereal: the sculptures are like containers for the ashes of Modernism. Or they might be Pandora's boxes, from which the demonic energies of pluralism would soon emerge (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JOHN MONTI, ''Fancy,'' Elizabeth Harris, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 463-9666, through May 27. Mr. Monti's sumptuously colored, intricately designed rubber reliefs in the form of stylized daisies riff on a kind of cheap, stick-on decoration that you may vaguely associate with the 1970's. Sculptural fusions of Pop and Minimalism that resemble giant clown lips -- the big orange one is called ''Tangerine Smile'' -- could be from a logo for a toy store or an ice cream vending chain (Johnson).</p>
        <p>''ONE TO ONE,'' Chambers, 210 11th Avenue, near 24th Street, (212) 414-1169, through May 29. Eight Chinese artists who toy with formal and narrative conventions of photography, including gridded photographic diaries by Guan Shi and Lin Jingjing; animal silhouettes composed of hundreds of thumbtack-size portraits, by Bai Yiluo; Chi Peng's fantasies of naked young men pursued by red bird-size airplanes; and Yi Deer's images of himself in a gold costume emerging from a cornfield and a manhole (Johnson),</p>
        <p>* PUSHPAMALA N., Bose Pacia Modern, 508 West 26th Street, (212) 989-7074, through May 15. Photography and moving pictures arrived in India immediately after their invention in Europe, which is one reason South Asia has long produced some of the most sophisticated work in both media. Pushpamala N., a contemporary artist working in Bangalore, takes account of that history and makes it her own in a New York solo debut that both sends up and pays homage to cinematic conventions. The show includes four photographic series in which the artist herself appears in various roles, playing them with a confounding mix of self-consciousness and conviction (Cotter).</p>
        <p>ERIK SCHMIDT/NEAL ROCK, Henry Urbach, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 627-0974, through May 22. Mr. Schmidt, a Berlin painter, depicts corporate sterility in high-contrast, photo-derived images of spectral businessmen and office buildings. Crusty painterly surfaces call to mind stale cake frosting. The London-based Mr. Rock created ''Work From the Polari Range,'' an installation of sculptural reliefs, by squeezing colored silicone out of pastry bags. Suggesting reeflike accumulations of tropical submarine creatures, they are grotesque, seductive and comical (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* WILLIAM SCOTT, Denise Bibro, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 647-7030, through June 5. Pots, dishes, fruits, vases and other domestic shapes form the basis for much of this Scottish-born painter's imagery, magically reduced to lyrical, luminous ghosts of themselves. Scott, a figure of some importance in postwar British art, was well known in New York, too. This small but engrossing show progresses from 1954 to 1977, and in his spare, sensual paintings shape, space and color play beautifully together (Glueck).</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>''DOGS + CATS,'' American Primitive, 594 Broadway, near Houston Street, (212) 966-1530, through June 12. This lively exhibition includes more than 60 feline or canine representations in two or three dimensions. Some are by self-taught artists. A big colorful painting by Jean Metcalf has cats and dogs in it but features a formal parade of rats carrying wounded birds on stretchers. Many are by unknown craftsmen, like the smoothly carved wooden head of a boxer with brown glass eyes and the functional dog-shaped bench in the form of a wooden slab with branches that have been turned into legs (Johnson).</p>
        <p>JOHN KESSLER, ''Global Village Idiot,'' Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, (212) 343-7300, through June 5. Mr. Kessler's Rube Goldberg-style contraptions incorporating computers, video equipment, photographs, electric lights and motors reflect on terrorism, airplane safety, fashion, pornography and media saturation. Their ingenious workings are absorbing to study, but unlike the beautifully made mechanized sculptures for which he became known in the 1980's and 90's, these have a raw, unfinished look, as if they had been built in the secret basement workshop of an angry and paranoid electrical engineer (Johnson).</p>
        <p>VINCENT LAMOUROUX, Spencer Brownstone, 39 Wooster Street, (212) 334-3455, through May 22. For his first New York solo exhibition, this young French artist has filled the gallery with a sloping undulating plywood floor. Negotiating its creaking dips and mounds is like walking on an uneven hillside outdoors or traversing an amusement park funhouse. It updates Carl Andre's Minimalist carpets, and it might be a metaphor about the instability of modern experience (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''OCEAN FLOWERS: IMPRESSIONS FROM NATURE,'' Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 219-2166, through May 22. Dense with ethereal images and silhouettes of seaweed, this unusual exhibition shows how the needs of Victorian botanists, book publishers and inspired amateurs pushed traditional drawing and printmaking into the realm of photography without so much as touching a lens. (Smith).</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>''THE DEVONSHIRE INHERITANCE: FIVE CENTURIES OF COLLECTING AT CHATSWORTH,'' Bard Graduate Center, 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000, through June 20. The stately English country home Chatsworth has been occupied since its construction in 1552 by the Cavendish family, headed by a long succession of dukes and duchesses of Devonshire. They have enriched it with notable collections of fine and decorative arts, an awesome library of books and manuscripts, scientific instruments, silver, furniture and needlework. A glimpse of these treasures is provided by this show, which has works by Rembrandt, Raphael, Titian, Dürer and Lucian Freud; books and drawings by Andrea Palladio; a spectacular jewelry ensemble worn at the coronation of Czar Alexander II and much else to light up the eyes of the most jaded connoisseur. The next step is a visit to Chatsworth itself, still a private home for the Cavendishes but very much open to the public (Glueck).</p>
        <p>MIN KIM, ATM Gallery, 170 Avenue B, near 10th Street, East Village, (212) 375-0349, through May 23. Ms. Kim's finely made paint-and-ink work amounts to a a kind of child's vision of Eden. A nude, doe-eyed prepubescent girl meets a boy, almost her twin, in a garden dominated by a glitter-producing tree; their story of Paradise Found comes to an ambiguous conclusion in a Chinese-style landscape overhung with tangle of snaking black lines. Ms. Kim's application of cartoon-style sweetness to an adult-style morality tale is common in new art and can easily be arch or sappy. She makes it work by presenting innocence more or less straight: threatened from without, unblemished from within (Cotter).</p>
        <p>''TACTICAL ACTION,'' Gigantic Artspace, 59 Franklin Street, TriBeCa, (212) 226-6762, through June 10. This lively but crowded and unfocused exhibition is designed to promote leftish dissidence. Highlights include scenes of the war in Iraq, drawn on location by Steve Mumford; clever anticorporate lenticular photographs by David Byrne and Danielle Spencer; David Krippendorff's noirish video about the eroticism of hate; Michele Pred's American flag sculpture, made from pen knives confiscated at airports; and a mock prison visitors' booth, with a soundtrack about teenage gang violence, by Dread Scott (Johnson).</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* ''DRAWING OUT THE VOID,'' Vestry Arts, 15 Gramercy Park South, (212) 995-1774, through tomorrow. This excellent show of drawings in a beautiful new gallery brings together two famous Surrealists, now dead, and two living contemporary Neo-Surrealists. Hans Bellmer's Freudian amalgamations of body parts drawn in elegantly spidery lines, Pavel Tchelitchew's glowing pictures of a giant eye and heads seemingly made of neon tubing, Steve DiBenedetto's colored-pencil visions of octopuses, Ferris wheels and helicopters, and Peter Schoolwerth's diagrammatic Pop-Surrealist narratives prove that drawing is still an excellent way to explore the weirdness of modern experience (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* LES KRIMS, ''Fact or Fiction,'' Laurence Miller, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 397-3930, through tomorrow. In the 1970's feminists hated Mr. Krims's staged pictures of naked women in absurd and humiliating situations. Today, these small prints from the late 1960's and early 70's are striking for their psychological urgency and mold-breaking inventiveness. His famous picture of a screaming legless man on a small table in a windowed alcove remains an image of frightening intensity. His mother seated naked in her dimly lighted living room is an image of heartbreaking vulnerability (Johnson).</p>
        <p>* ''SINGULAR FORMS (SOMETIMES REPEATED): ART FROM 1951 TO THE PRESENT,'' Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500, through Wednesday. A lavish, mostly in-house display of Minimal art and its progeny. Along with the requisite examples by standard-bearers (Donald Judd, Dan Flavin, Robert Ryman) and a few by predecessors (Robert Rauschenberg, Ad Reinhardt), it features post-1960's works by a range of artists including Gerhard Richter, Charles Ray, Robert Gober, Liam Gillick, Sherrie Levine, Rachel Whiteread and Damien Hirst. Ultimately, Minimalism doesn't describe everything here. The show is a hodgepodge. But it's a stimulating hodgepodge, and it looks great in Wright's building. Hours: Saturdays through Wednesdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m., Fridays until 8 p.m. Admission: $15; students and 65+, $10 (Kimmelman).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
