<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York and 3 Other States Join Against Air Pollution</title>
    <meta content="21CLEA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/21/nyregion/21clean.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1583402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allegheny Energy Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0D6113FF932A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York and 3 Other States Join Against Air Pollution</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">4 Northeast States Join Against Pollution</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York, New Jersey, Connecticut and Pennslyvania sue Allegheny Energy Inc, claiming that company's coal-fired electric generating plants in Pennsylvania emit pollution that drifts across state lines, worsens smog, produces acid rain and causes respiratory problems for people in metropolitan region; want company to install antipollution equipment; company says it is not in violation of pollution laws (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York and three adjoining states began legal action yesterday against a Pennsylvania power company, accusing it of emitting air pollution that drifts across state lines and worsens smog, produces acid rain and causes respiratory problems for people in the metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>The litigation seeks to force the company to install antipollution equipment in five coal-fired electric generating plants that federal environmental officials were investigating until the Bush administration changed its enforcement policy for the Clean Air Act last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York and three adjoining states began legal action yesterday against a Pennsylvania power company, accusing it of emitting air pollution that drifts across state lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York and three adjoining states began legal action yesterday against a Pennsylvania power company, accusing it of emitting air pollution that drifts across state lines and worsens smog, produces acid rain and causes respiratory problems for people in the metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>The litigation seeks to force the company to install antipollution equipment in five coal-fired electric generating plants that federal environmental officials were investigating until the Bush administration changed its enforcement policy for the Clean Air Act last year.</p>
        <p>After the federal government announced plans to drop 50 investigations of possible pollution violations in November, Eliot Spitzer, the New York attorney general, obtained the government's comprehensive files and said he and the attorneys general of Connecticut and New Jersey would carry on the enforcement effort through litigation.</p>
        <p>This is the first of the cases to be brought by the attorneys general, who were joined by the Pennsylvania secretary of environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the four states sent the required letter of intent to sue to the corporate officers of Allegheny Energy Inc., based in Greensburg, Pa. The company provides power to about four million people in Pennsylvania and four other mid-Atlantic states.</p>
        <p>The company said its plants were not violating pollution laws.</p>
        <p>''We have been and continue to be in compliance with all existing state and federal environmental laws,'' the company's president, Paul J. Evanson, said in a statement. ''We welcome the opportunity to meet with these states to amicably resolve these matters.''</p>
        <p>The company has 60 days to negotiate a settlement. If one is not reached, the case will proceed.</p>
        <p>The action represents the latest volley in the continuing struggle between Northeast states and utility companies concerning high levels of pollution that drift eastward. It also underscores the rising frustration among some Northeast officials who believe that the Bush administration is hampering environmental enforcement.</p>
        <p>''From Day 1, the Bush administration has tried to eviscerate and undercut the Clean Air Act,'' Mr. Spitzer said in a telephone interview. ''We at the state level will fulfill the critical policy mission of ensuring that the air we breathe is clean.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer was joined in the case by Attorney General Richard Blumenthal of Connecticut, Attorney General Peter C. Harvey of New Jersey and Kathleen A. McGinty, the Pennsylvania environmental protection secretary.</p>
        <p>All three attorneys general are Democrats. Ms. McGinty was chairwoman of the Council on Environmental Quality in the Clinton White House.</p>
        <p>An industry representative said that if the officials won their case, it would only raise electricity rates in poor areas of West Virginia, where the coal plants are located, and do nothing to decrease pollution.</p>
        <p>''If you want a better emissions profile at a power plant, bringing a lawsuit is not the way to achieve it,'' said Scott H. Segal, director of the Electric Reliability Coordinating Council. ''Adopting a robust maintenance program is the best way to increase pollution controls.''</p>
        <p>The officials' case focuses on the definition of maintenance. Longstanding federal rules require new or substantially modified coal-burning power plants to use the most advanced, and most expensive, pollution-control devices available.</p>
        <p>The officials maintain that Allegheny made major modifications to the five plants but classified the work as routine maintenance to avoid installing the pollution controls required by the regulations.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, those coal-fired plants -- which range in size from 243 megawatts to 1,961 megawatts -- emitted more than 175,000 tons of sulfur dioxide a year and more than 60,000 tons of nitrous oxide a year, the state officials said.</p>
        <p>Each side believes its chance of winning the case is good, and each cites a different recent federal ruling in cases in which utilities were accused violating the antipollution rules.</p>
        <p>In August, a federal judge ruled that Ohio Edison, a unit of FirstEnergy, had mislabeled extensive renovations on several coal plants as ''routine maintenance'' and unlawfully avoided installing upgraded pollution controls. The ruling buttressed the states' position.</p>
        <p>But in the same month last year, a federal judge in North Carolina offered a different interpretation of maintenance that seemed to favor the companies' position. In that case, involving Duke Energy, the judge interpreted ''routine maintenance'' broadly enough to have included what federal regulators had considered major modifications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
