<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slow Learner on Energy-Efficiency Front; While U.S. Backslides, France Offers Lessons in Cutting Oil Use</title>
    <meta content="05CONS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/05/business/05conserve.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1616664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mouawad, Jad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EEDD1F38F936A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slow Learner on Energy-Efficiency Front; While U.S. Backslides, France Offers Lessons in Cutting Oil Use</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Slow Learner on Energy-Efficiency Front</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAD MOUAWAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mouawad, Jad</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of France's successful state-led effort to curb its reliance on imported oil in response to 1970's oil shock, which contrasts with US effort that was gradually abandoned; oil use in France is still 10 percent lower now than in 1973, while United States consumption rose 16 percent from 1973 to 2003 in response to lower oil prices; some experts say outlook for substantially higher energy prices in next decade than in 1990's should force government and industry to rethink basic policies; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States, land of gas-guzzling S.U.V.'s and air-conditioned McMansions, might do well to turn to the country some Americans love to hate for lessons on how to curb its reliance on imported oil: France.</p>
        <p>Now that oil has reached roughly $50 a barrel and the world is coming to expect relatively high oil prices to last a long time, experts say that a rethinking of America's wasteful ways is once again an urgent undertaking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States might do well to turn to the country some Americans love to hate for lessons on how to curb its reliance on imported oil: France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States, land of gas-guzzling S.U.V.'s and air-conditioned McMansions, might do well to turn to the country some Americans love to hate for lessons on how to curb its reliance on imported oil: France.</p>
        <p>Now that oil has reached roughly $50 a barrel and the world is coming to expect relatively high oil prices to last a long time, experts say that a rethinking of America's wasteful ways is once again an urgent undertaking.</p>
        <p>And like it or not, France -- whose perceived diplomatic obstructionism in the run-up to the Iraq war provoked a boycott of French products by some Americans -- has displayed a quality ripe for export: an impressive tenacity in waging what the French call the war on gaspi, short for gaspillage, or waste. It has also done so in a way that the United States has not been able to: over the long term.</p>
        <p>Spurred by the oil shocks of the 1970's, France embarked on a vast state-led drive to flush out as much oil from its economy as possible. With the national slogan at the time, ''We don't have oil, but we have ideas,'' it accelerated the shift of electricity production from oil-fired power plants to nuclear reactors, increased taxes on gasoline to the equivalent of $3.75 a gallon, encouraged the sale of diesel-powered cars and gave tax breaks to energy-hungry industries like aluminum, cement and paper to shift from oil to other fuels.</p>
        <p>It worked. In contrast to the United States, where oil consumption initially fell but then ended up rising by a total of 16 percent from 1973 to 2003, in France, despite some increase in recent years, oil use is still 10 percent lower today than it was three decades ago, according to the United States Energy Information Administration. (Germany also matched France's record.)</p>
        <p>''Americans have completely abandoned their efforts at energy conservation over the past decade and have been incredibly care-free about oil consumption because they believed they would get access to cheap energy -- through force if necessary,'' said Pierre Terzian, an energy specialist who runs the Paris-based consulting firm PetroStrategies.</p>
        <p>The contrast between French resolve and American abandon in recent years is sharp. The United States, too, took the high road in the 1970's and early 80's, when the combined impact of the 1973 oil embargo, the growing power of OPEC and the Iranian revolution of 1979 created long gas lines and raised the prospect of an oil producers' stranglehold over the American economy.</p>
        <p>The price of Arabian light crude rose from $1.85 a barrel in 1972 to $40 in 1981, or $80 in today's dollars.</p>
        <p>Americans responded with a nationwide speed limit of 55 miles an hour, a home-insulating boom and a blossoming of energy-technology start-ups to help businesses cut their energy bills. Vast improvements came in home appliances: refrigerators, for example, now consume a third of the energy needed 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>But slowly, the nation resumed old habits. By the late 1980's, with the economy booming and oil prices below $20 a barrel, gas guzzlers were back, cars raced along highways at 75 m.p.h. with impunity and new vehicles' average mileage per gallon, which had almost doubled to 27.5 in 1987 from 14 in 1972, slipped back to 24, compared with Europe's 36.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, the United States, which represents roughly 24 percent of world economic output and an even lower share of industrial production, nonetheless accounted for a third of the growth in demand for global oil.</p>
        <p>A big reason for the policy divide, said Amy Jaffe, the associate director of Rice University's energy program, is a cultural contrast of two sharply opposed ways of looking at the world.</p>
        <p>''In the United States, we try to control things over which we have no control, like Russia or Saudi Arabia, instead of looking at what we could do inside,'' Mrs. Jaffe said. ''We're like drug addicts. We're looking around for another dealer instead of going to detox.''</p>
        <p>For now, the presidential candidates are preaching familiar themes in their campaigning, with President Bush calling for more exploration and increased domestic production and Senator John Kerry promoting alternative energies.</p>
        <p>But with oil now at $50 a barrel, double what it was two years ago, and with many analysts expecting substantially higher energy prices in the next decade than during the 1990's, some experts are saying that both government and industry are going to need to do some fundamental rethinking of some basic policies.</p>
        <p>''The lack of emphasis on demand in the past 20 years in the United States has a lot to do with the predicament we're in now,'' said Ashok Gupta, an economist with the National Resources Defense Council. ''We need to look at what it will take to get manufacturers to offer technologies that people want.''</p>
        <p>One obvious step, which politicians are loath to even mention, would be to increase taxes on gasoline. Here again, the divergence between the United States and Europe is instructive. To encourage the use of mass-transit systems, and finance their development, European governments impose generally high taxes on gasoline. French drivers pay over $5 a gallon for gasoline, $3.75 of that in taxes, compared with $1.90 a gallon on average in the United States, with only 41 cents of that going to taxes.</p>
        <p>Proposing a tenfold increase in taxes to match the European level would, of course, be political suicide in the United States. There have been several attempts to increase federal taxes on gasoline over the years, but ''they've all met with disaster,'' said Kateri Callahan, the president of the Alliance to Save Energy, a business-supported group that promotes energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>''Mobility is seen as a national right here in the United States,'' Mrs. Callahan said. ''To impose a higher tax when gasoline prices are already perceived to be high is simply not good politics.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, environmentalists face pressure to accept some trade-offs.</p>
        <p>Most European countries, for example, have encouraged drivers to buy cars with diesel engines, which burn 30 percent less fuel than regular engines. Two-thirds of cars registered in France are diesel-fueled, according to the European Automobile Manufacturers' Association. That compares with diesel sales of less than half of 1 percent in the United States.</p>
        <p>One hurdle to diesel sales in the United States is that compared with conventional gasoline-powered cars, diesels emit more smog-forming pollutants, though they offer lower emissions of the kind that contribute to global warming. Still, with better technology, some carmakers like Chrysler plan to offer new diesel models later this year.</p>
        <p>While diesels have made little headway, fuel-efficient hybrid cars -- with electric motors that take over for the gas engines at low speeds and stops -- are gaining in popularity. But so far, only a few carmakers offer them, and there is a waiting list for some of the more popular models, like the Toyota Prius.</p>
        <p>An additional disparity between the United States and France is the approach to nuclear energy. With domestic production of oil a tiny 3 percent of the two million barrels it consumes each day, France has turned to nuclear power as its economic savior; 80 percent of its electricity now comes from the country's 19 nuclear plants, compared with 40 percent in Sweden, 30 percent in Japan and Germany and 20 percent in the United States.</p>
        <p>''Because it didn't draw a lucky geological hand, France has always looked for energy independence,'' said Dominique Maillard, the country's top official in charge of energy policy as the director of energy at the Ministry of Industry. ''We used nuclear power as a path to offset our dependency on imports.''</p>
        <p>The United States, in contrast, has turned up its nose at nuclear energy, in part because of the risk of a meltdown (much reduced in recent years, experts say), and in part because of the controversy over the disposal of nuclear waste. The biggest factor, though, was the soaring cost of building nuclear plants to satisfy more rigorous standards.</p>
        <p>Since the accident at the Three Mile Island nuclear reactor in Pennsylvania in March 1979, no new reactors have been built. With oil prices rising and concern about global warming spreading, nuclear power advocates argue that a new generation of power plants can overcome the problems with nuclear energy at an acceptable cost.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the depiction of the United States as the world's energy wastrel and of France as a model of virtue can be overdrawn. All developed countries have significantly improved their energy efficiencies in manufacturing and construction since 1973. Moreover, oil's slice of global energy demand has fallen to 35 percent today from 45 percent 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>Still, oil will remain the main source of energy for decades to come, and official projections still show oil consumption in the United States rising by 43 percent by 2025.</p>
        <p>But rising prices could go a long way to damp demand.</p>
        <p>''The question is, How much do prices have to increase for attitudes to change?'' Mr. Gupta of the National Resources Defense Council said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
