<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going to Glacier? You Should Hurry</title>
    <meta content="07GLAC$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/07/travel/escapes/07GLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1579728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="JOURNEYS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Glaciers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Glacier National Park (Mont)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selingo, Jeffrey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana/Glacier National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glaciers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Montana</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Glacier National Park</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DC163CF934A35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going to Glacier? You Should Hurry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going to Glacier? You Should Hurry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY SELINGO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Selingo, Jeffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on visit to Glacier National Park in northwestern Montana, whose glaciers are rapidly disappearing; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the white-knuckle drive up and over the Continental Divide on Going-to-the-Sun Road in Glacier National Park, each new view -- emerald-colored lakes, knife-edge peaks and vast open valleys -- outdoes the last. The narrow two-lane road hugs the cliffs, rising in a series of switchbacks as it climbs to Logan Pass at 6,646 feet. No wonder this park, in the remote northwestern corner of Montana, claims the nickname Crown of the Continent. Its eye-popping grandeur drew 1.9 million visitors last year to camp, hike, kayak and gawk.</p>
        <p>But one thing that's hard to see from anywhere along the road is a glacier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The glaciers in Glacier National Park, Mont., are melting, and sneaking a good peek at those that remain is a challenge to relish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the white-knuckle drive up and over the Continental Divide on Going-to-the-Sun Road in Glacier National Park, each new view -- emerald-colored lakes, knife-edge peaks and vast open valleys -- outdoes the last. The narrow two-lane road hugs the cliffs, rising in a series of switchbacks as it climbs to Logan Pass at 6,646 feet. No wonder this park, in the remote northwestern corner of Montana, claims the nickname Crown of the Continent. Its eye-popping grandeur drew 1.9 million visitors last year to camp, hike, kayak and gawk.</p>
        <p>But one thing that's hard to see from anywhere along the road is a glacier.</p>
        <p>The glaciers in Glacier National Park are melting, and not at a glacial pace, but so quickly that scientists from the United States Geological Survey predict that there won't be any left by 2030. Sneaking a good peek at those that remain is a challenge to relish for its sheer difficulty and the bragging rights that go with it.</p>
        <p>At one time, this was the place to see glaciers in North America. In the late 1800's, 150 glaciers, relics of the last great ice age, graced the towering cliffs. There were bigger, more spectacular glaciers in Alaska and western Canada, but they were impossibly far away from anywhere most travelers might hope to reach. The completion of the Great Northern Railway in 1892 made the area a tourist stop, and in 1910 it became a national park.</p>
        <p>Today just 27 glaciers remain, covering about 12 square miles, many of them so small they are tough to distinguish from surrounding snowfields. Glacial beauty is still to be seen if you're determined, but what is probably more compelling is the simple chance to witness the last vestiges of these rivers of ice, survivors dating back 10,000 years.</p>
        <p>The park itself has adapted to its changing circumstances, repositioning itself as a northern wilderness for hiking and observing wildlife. One day last season, as hikers headed off to Red Rock Falls, they chatted about bears and backpacking but not about the glaciers that, far in the past, formed these falls, along with St. Mary Falls, Avalanche Lake and other popular spots.</p>
        <p>And when Dave Benson, a National Park Service naturalist, led a hike to Grinnell Lake, he was asked about West Nile virus, beargrass and huckleberries, but not the park's glaciers. The exceptions come when he leads hikes up to Grinnell Glacier itself. ''The people on those hikes tend to know more about global warming,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The best views of the glaciers from park roads require a map, good binoculars and some knowledge of what to look for -- deep crevasses or the moraine, the rocks and other debris that glaciers deposit as they move. (Many tourists who think they have seen glaciers on the park's mountaintops have been looking only at ordinary snowpack. By definition, glaciers are moving chunks of ice that carve and shape the landscape as they go.) You can glimpse the largest, Blackfoot Glacier, and its offshoot, Jackson Glacier, which was split from it by melting about 60 years ago, from an overlook on Going-to-the-Sun Road. But most of the glaciers are hidden in small valleys.</p>
        <p>For a closer view, the easiest approach is from the air. In summer, helicopters loaded with sightseers swoop over a dozen active glaciers, including Ahern, Old Sun and Ipasha, making the circuit high over peaks and low over lakes like Iceberg Lake, where icebergs do indeed float.</p>
        <p>But for the most immediate sense of the shrinking glaciers, you have to hike up and meet them in person.</p>
        <p>The two most accessible are Sperry and Grinnell, named for Lyman Sperry, a mountain climber, and George Bird Grinnell, who lobbied to have this area named a national park. The rugged trails to them are clear of snow in July, August and September.</p>
        <p>The trip to Grinnell, the easier of the two, starts with a boat ride across Lake Josephine to the start of the steep 3.8-mile trail. (If you skip the boat trip, it's a 5.5-mile hike.) As you climb 1,600 feet from the base of the trail to the glacier, you look down on milky-green Grinnell Lake. Its color is the result of sunlight reflecting off sediment that floats in the water from the melting glaciers. Even dying, they provide beauty.</p>
        <p>The end of the trail opens to iceberg-filled upper Grinnell Lake, which was created in 1927, when Grinnell Glacier split apart to form Salamander Glacier. Since then, the gray-green lake has grown from a few acres to 30-plus acres. Grinnell Glacier, which is itself 300 feet thinner than it was only two decades ago, is just off to the left.</p>
        <p>Walking on Grinnell Glacier first involves a hair-raising scramble across a rushing stream. By the end of summer, steppingstones placed there by previous hikers are submerged by water that rises as the ice melts. But for those who venture across, the walk on the glacier is often the highlight of the trip. It's not much to look at -- it's filled with rocks that have been picked up along the way -- but those who get to stand on it know that in a few decades, only the rocks will be left. There's a sense of witnessing history.</p>
        <p>The trail to Sperry Glacier starts near the Lake McDonald Lodge and goes 10 miles up, rising 4,500 feet. Most visitors make it an overnight trip, stopping six miles in at the Sperry Chalet. Built in 1913 and now a national historic landmark, the chalet has 17 rooms but no electricity or running water. Since the rooms tend to fill up fast, the park service operates a camping area nearby.</p>
        <p>The handful of hikers who make it each year to the more remote glaciers, like Blackfoot, have an even more grueling trip, but they are richly rewarded. Here, at last, is something like the kind of glacier that park visitors could expect to experience half a century or more ago -- ''big and dramatic'' is the way it is described by Dan Fagre, an ecologist with the geological survey who is tracking climate changes in the park. Large crevasses split Blackfoot, and there are ice falls, which look like waterfalls in suspended animation, and ''beautiful blue ice cliffs where the glaciers are pushing over rock formations,'' Mr. Fagre said.</p>
        <p>Although global warming remains politically sensitive and highly debated, park officials tell the public that the rise in temperatures since the Industrial Revolution, which vastly increased the amount of carbon dioxide and other gases that hold heat close to the earth, is melting the glaciers. At the park's Apgar Visitor Center in West Glacier, a town on the southwestern edge of the park, are photographs of Grinnell Glacier through the decades, showing climate change in terms anyone can understand.</p>
        <p>More than 12,000 photos, some dating to the 1800's, are in the park's archives, and a geological survey team is taking new ones of the same locations for comparison. Of the 56 glaciers that have been rephotographed, only four small ones, in the park's shady, north-facing valleys, have shown no significant shrinkage, Mr. Fagre said.</p>
        <p>To some, the anomaly may be the fact that glaciers were ever this far south at all. But there are glaciers at high elevations in many parts of the world well south of the Arctic, including Mount Rainier National Park in Washington. There are even tropical glaciers -- on Mount Kilimanjaro, for example, and in the Andes -- though they, too, are rapidly shrinking. Glaciers survived so long at Glacier National Park because they are so high and because the snow that accumulated on them outstripped the summer snowmelt. But now that is changing: more snow is melting than accumulating.</p>
        <p>So will Glacier National Park keep its name after the glaciers go away? Officials say they have no plans to change it, pointing out that the glaciers formed the park's stunning geological features, whether they themselves remain or not.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey S. Kargel, a scientist with the geological survey who studies glaciers worldwide, calls the handful remaining in the park only ''technically glaciers'' because ''they are so minuscule.''</p>
        <p>Even so, they have a significance. The changes occurring here are a road map for what will come in Alaska and elsewhere decades from now. ''In 100 years or so,'' Dr. Kargel said, ''it's going to be much more difficult to see a glacier anywhere.''</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO  See the Ice While It's Still Cold</p>
        <p>THE closest airport, Glacier Park International, is in Kalispell, Mont., about 25 miles from West Glacier. America West, Big Sky, Delta, Horizon and Northwest serve the airport. Great Falls International Airport, about 200 miles southeast, is served by Northwest, Sky West, Horizon and Big Sky.</p>
        <p>Take Highway 2 if you're driving from the east or west. From the south, use Interstate 15 north to Shelby, Mont., and take Highway 2 west to the park.</p>
        <p>Glacier Park Inc. is the National Park Service's concessionaire, and its Web site, www.glacierparkinc.com, lists recommended activities and lodging. The phone number for reservations is (406) 892-2525.</p>
        <p>Places to stay include the 208-room Many Glacier Hotel ($111 to $225), the 100-room Lake McDonald Lodge ($96 to $145) and, just over the border in Canada, the 86-room Prince of Wales Hotel ($190 to $580 in United States currency).</p>
        <p>JOURNEYS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
