<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going Fast: The Fresh Fish of Venice</title>
    <meta content="03VENI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/03/dining/03VENI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040310T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1563344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D8143FF930A35750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="2473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going Fast: The Fresh Fish of Venice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going Fast: The Fresh Fish of Venice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple Jr reports on where to eat seafood in Venice; says at their best, city's fish and shellfish are sublime; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''LOOK at this,'' said Cesare Benelli, brandishing a plastic bag with a slab of fish the color of raspberry Jell-O inside. ''Mummified tuna. Nothing to do with our native fish. It's caught in Indonesia, treated with sulfites, then vacuum packed and shipped to Italy. It has no taste at all, but people buy it, because it's cheaper.''</p>
        <p>A silver-haired, Hollywood-handsome chef who owns Al Covo, one of the city's best restaurants, Mr. Benelli champions authentic regional ingredients, especially fish and shellfish from the Venetian lagoon and the inshore waters of the Adriatic. A few years ago, with like-minded restaurateurs, he organized an alliance dedicated to the preservation of local culinary traditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite increasing scarcity and cost and threats from pollution, fish and shellfish from the Venetian lagoon is sublime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''LOOK at this,'' said Cesare Benelli, brandishing a plastic bag with a slab of fish the color of raspberry Jell-O inside. ''Mummified tuna. Nothing to do with our native fish. It's caught in Indonesia, treated with sulfites, then vacuum packed and shipped to Italy. It has no taste at all, but people buy it, because it's cheaper.''</p>
        <p>A silver-haired, Hollywood-handsome chef who owns Al Covo, one of the city's best restaurants, Mr. Benelli champions authentic regional ingredients, especially fish and shellfish from the Venetian lagoon and the inshore waters of the Adriatic. A few years ago, with like-minded restaurateurs, he organized an alliance dedicated to the preservation of local culinary traditions.</p>
        <p>He had asked me to meet him underneath the 19th-century neo-Gothic arches of the Pescheria, the open-air fish market near the Rialto Bridge, to see for myself what he and his friends -- the proprietors of holes-in-the-wall like Alle Testiere as well as famous establishments like Da Fiore -- are up against. And what visitors to this jewel-like city face as well if they wander heedlessly into one of the Serenissima's countless tourist-trap restaurants.</p>
        <p>Tourists have been feasting on seafood here for generations, going all the way back to the participants in the 18th-century Grand Tour, and unscrupulous restaurateurs have been fleecing customers for just as long.</p>
        <p>Yet at their best, the city's fish and shellfish are sublime -- small, delicately textured and incomparably sweet, especially those from the outer lagoon's shallow, brackish waters, which are rich in plankton, fish eggs and other foods, and regularly scrubbed by salt-water tides.</p>
        <p>The best is now increasingly scarce and costly, frighteningly so. Inevitably, inferior substitutes abound -- farmed fish, foreign fish, frozen fish. I saw a farmed Dutch turbot on sale for $29.50, and a wild local turbot, of the succulent variety the Venetians call ''chiodato'' or ''nailed,'' because of its bony, nailhead-like protrusions, priced at $59.50.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benelli also pointed out defrosted octopus, farmed bay scallops from Scotland and worst of all, a shell game played with clams.</p>
        <p>Vongole veraci (caparossoli in Venetian dialect) are cute little characters with two valves, indispensable to a proper dish of pasta with clams.</p>
        <p>But the local population has been hard hit by pollution, much of it from factories and ocean-going ships, so Manila clams, seeded in the lagoon some years ago, are rapidly supplanting them. Coarser in texture, less subtle in flavor, with rounder shells, they cost a third as much and reproduce three times as quickly. It takes a discerning eye to tell one from the other in the market.</p>
        <p>Pollution is only part of the problem. Overfishing has taken a toll as well, although large sections of the region's fisheries are closed at different times for a month or two each summer, to allow stocks to regenerate. This is known as the fermo pesca. Fish farming and improved transportation have created fresh competition.</p>
        <p>Now a new threat looms. Always precariously poised between land and sea -- Ruskin famously warned that it had as much chance of surviving as ''a lump of sugar in hot tea'' -- Venice is increasingly plagued by spells of acqua alta, the extra-high tides that flood the city's streets and squares.</p>
        <p>The sea level around Venice has risen by about four inches in the last century, which many Italian scientists attribute to global warming and the gradual melting of the polar icecap. The city has settled about five inches in the same period, partly because of the increased use of underground fresh water in the nearby industrial port of Marghera.</p>
        <p>Scientists expect further rises in the sea level. So after decades of study, the government has begun to build a multibillion-dollar system of 79 movable barriers to seal off the lagoon at times when surge tides threaten the city. This will be necessary only occasionally, engineers who planned the defenses insist, and the periods of closure at the three lagoon inlets will be brief.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists disagree, convinced the closures will be longer, and they worry that the fragile ecology of the lagoon will be changed forever.</p>
        <p>For their part, chefs and fishmongers fret that the project will disrupt the prime fishing grounds for the boats based at Chioggia and Caorle. Those are located around the inlets where the salty water of the Adriatic meets the less saline water of the lagoon, precisely where the barriers are supposed to be built.</p>
        <p>''It's a war, finding fresh, local fish,'' Mr. Benelli said. ''Only 53,000 of us are left here, and I worry that we're losing our identity as Venetians. Much more than our fish -- our collective memories, our dialect, our culture, our flavors and our tastes.''</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, hand-lettered signs saying ''nostrano'' or ''ours,'' meaning local, guided customers to the choicest fish. Now such signs may appear on boxes of crabs from Spain or John Dory from Morocco -- but not, of course, at the stalls of respected dealers like Luca D'Este and Marco Bergamasco.</p>
        <p>Their fish tend to be more expensive, but they are carefully labeled with the Latin name, the exact sea zone they came from, as defined by the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organization, and the name of the fishing boat.</p>
        <p>OR the Venetians, water is the giver of life. Long ago, initially out of sheer necessity, they became a species of sea creature themselves.</p>
        <p>The Pescheria is small, but the range of fish is absolutely spellbinding. What most Americans might call shrimp go by many names in Venice, including minuscule creatures called schie, still wriggling in their boxes at the market, which turn from gray to brown when cooked, and larger, fatter, standard-issue pink gamberi.</p>
        <p>Scampi are not shrimp at all, no matter what Italian-American restaurants may insist, nor are the bigger, brinier mazzancolle; both are saltwater crayfish, with claws. Weird-looking crustaceans with squinty eyes on their tails, called canoce or mantis shrimp or (incorrectly) cigale, are caught at night when they emerge from their muddy burrows; they have a nutty, lobstery taste.</p>
        <p>Gourmands that they are, Venetians differentiate between two types of triglie (red mullet), one from waters with sandy bottoms, the other from waters with more rocks. They prefer seppioline, or baby cuttlefish, born in the lagoon, not in the open sea. Among crabs, they have one word for males, another for females. We poor Anglophones have to make do with ''she-crabs.''</p>
        <p>At Al Covo, Mr. Benelli and his peppy, throaty wife, Diane, who grew up in Lubbock, Tex., serve a lot of their fish raw -- the famous local sea bass, branzino, seasoned with coarse salt and spider-crab roe; jumbo sea scallops in their shells; and small scampi, unbelievably creamy and ethereally sweet. The raw langoustines that Joël Robuchon serves in Paris and David Pasternack's raw fluke at Esca in Manhattan are perhaps better seasoned, at least to my taste, but there is no doubt that Al Covo's raw materials take first prize.</p>
        <p>''When fish is this fresh and this good,'' Mr. Benelli told us during dinner, ''it becomes the protagonist. The less the chef does to it, the better it will be.''</p>
        <p>With that philosophy in mind, he serves crab meat cool, mixed with its coral and parsley, on a bed of microscopic leaves -- ''24-hour lettuces,'' as he calls them -- allowing the captivating, low-key notes of the spider crab's flavor to be appreciated to the full, without distraction from the drums and trumpets of strident sauces.</p>
        <p>Razor clams, no bigger than a pinkie, are flipped, flipped and flipped again on a flat grill, to keep them moist. And rosy gamberetti are combined with white polenta and fruity, exceptionally peppery olive oil to produce an elegantly restrained version of Charleston's creamy shrimp and grits.</p>
        <p>The day after our most recent visit to the Benellis, my wife, Betsey, and I managed to squeeze three small meals into a single day, and each of those also exemplified, in its way, the Venetian gift for inspired simplicity.</p>
        <p>At lunch at the sumptuous Hotel Cipriani, I asked whether I could have turbot, my favorite fish, but without all the elaborate furbelows proposed by the menu. But of course, sir; out came several fish scaloppine, sautéed no more than a moment or two, their lusciousness nicely cut by the bitterness of grilled radicchio.</p>
        <p>At Alle Testiere that evening, we had time only for a few cicheti, or snacks, with our preprandial slurps of white wine. There are only 10 tables, mostly for two, jammed into its single tiny room, and we had to make way for serious diners to follow, but Luca Da Vita, one of the partners, ferried plates to our table so speedily that we managed to taste several delicious tidbits, including gnocchi with tenderissimo baby squid, octopus salad enlivened with apple, and clams with ginger (a throwback to the days when Venice traded with the Orient, like the more familiar sweet-and-sour pesce en saor).</p>
        <p>Mascaron, a bare-bones, cash-only osteria with paper napkins, thronged even in low season, served us a raft of vegetable antipasti and well-grilled sole and orata (the gold-spotted bream that was sacred to Aphrodite). But the highlights were the Rabelaisian humor of Gigi Vianello, one of the proprietors, and the steaming, copious plates of spaghetti with clams. No sauce, no garlic, just tiny vongole veraci, oil and gobs of parsley atop perfectly chewy pasta. Four ingredients that produce pure bliss.</p>
        <p>Neighbors still gather at the bar of Da Fiore, which is surely Venice's best restaurant, for a glass of prosecco or tocai; it began life as a bacaro, or tavern. Now, its dining room is a study in sophistication, with silk wallcoverings and high-backed wicker chairs.</p>
        <p>The urbane Maurizio Martin, whose wife, Mara, does the cooking, brought us a parade of dishes of such bright, transparent flavor that our usual lunchtime badinage subsided into a series of happy monosyllables, mainly ''mmm.'' We started with baccalà mantecato, a rich, milky, whipped fish purée made not with salt cod, as elsewhere in Italy, but with the dried cod preferred by Venetians.</p>
        <p>Nothing flashy, perfectly executed, a classic. I could say nothing less about the scampi risotto that followed, with shellfish and carnaroli rice both hitting the magic mark of tenderness shy of mushiness. ''Devastatingly good,'' said Betsey, a devastating critic of second-rate risotto, mine and most of Manhattan's included.</p>
        <p>For some reason I had never ordered eel (locally known as bisato) on any of my 15 or 20 visits to Venice, even though it is a local favorite, eaten by tradition on Christmas Eve. So I hastened to do so at Da Fiore, and it was so sensationally unctuous that I neglected to ask how it was cooked; I suspect that it was skinned, boned, butterflied and baked or grilled over bay leaves, which is the textbook preparation.</p>
        <p>We had more classics at Graspo de Ua, brought back to life after a long slumber by Lucio Zanon, once a Harry's Bar stalwart -- fried fresh sardines, one of the ''blue'' or oily fish the Venetians love, and a risotto made with cuttlefish and their ''ink,'' appropriately robust and slightly chalky. And at Fiaschetteria Toscana (confusingly, neither Tuscan nor a wine bar) we gorged on moeche, deep-fried soft-shell male crabs no bigger than a half-dollar.</p>
        <p>AFTER all of this, we should have been sated. But for two years I had carried around a ragged piece of paper on which my pal Burton Anderson, nonpareil wine writer and ferreter-out of undiscovered but excellent restaurants, had jotted two mysterious words: ''Laguna'' and ''Cavallino.''</p>
        <p>A few inquiries and a ride on a crowded ferry took us to Punta Sabbioni, a hamlet on a sand spit just northeast of the Lido, part of a chain that separates the lagoon from the Adriatic. A car was waiting to shuttle us to the Trattoria Laguna in nearby Cavallino, sent by Olindo Balarin, its proprietor.</p>
        <p>An unassuming place facing the lagoon near a trailer park frequented by German sun-seekers, ignored by the Michelin guide, the Laguna has a real country atmosphere, with wood fires on crisp days, copper pots hanging from the ceiling and baskets of chestnuts still in their prickly husks.</p>
        <p>The loquacious Mr. Balarin educated us about the special virtues of fish from the valle, a kind of underwater trench between two small streams that flow into the lagoon.</p>
        <p>We passed the time until the food started arriving with squash chips and doughy home-baked rolls rather like savory hot cross buns. Before we finished three hours later, we sampled (just for starters) ice-cold raw shellfish; orata smoked over laurel wood, sliced and sprinkled with 40-year-old balsamic vinegar; a dazzling duo of scallops the size of pencil erasers, called canestrelli; and reddish little razor clams from the Adriatic. These were grilled and served on an arugula salad dressed with seafood juices and oil from Puglia.</p>
        <p>It was all exquisite, and so were the telline, microscopic mollusks with purple-tipped white shells, new to me, that looked like angels' wings when open. When he was a child, Mr. Balarin said, he found them by the thousands on the beach; now rare, they are delectable with a squirt of lemon.</p>
        <p>There was more, much too much more, including bites of two seafood pastas. Happily, we paced ourselves, because the pièce de résistance was Trattoria Laguna's star turn -- a whole orata, slow-roasted in the oven in a salt crust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Balarin broke the crust (with a hatchet!) and deftly boned the fish, depositing neat fillets, soft, sweet and shimmering with moisture, on our plates. This time, he chose a milder Ligurian olive oil as the flavoring agent.</p>
        <p>''It is natural for fish,'' our teacher said, ''to be in salt.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 10, 2004, Wednesday  An article last Wednesday about the increasing scarcity of local fish and shellfish in Venice misstated the name of the United Nations agency that monitors fisheries there. It is the Food and Agriculture Organization, not Agricultural.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 10, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article last Wednesday about the increasing scarcity of local fish and shellfish in Venice misstated the name of the United Nations agency that monitors fisheries there. It is the Food and Agriculture Organization, not Agricultural.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
