<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where They Stand, What They've Done</title>
    <meta content="TEXT.TXT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Voter Guide 2004" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1622290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE ISSUES"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1DB143DF935A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where They Stand, What They've Done</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President George W. Bush</p>
        <p>ABORTION  *Opposes abortion, except in cases of rape or incest or when a woman's life is endangered, but has said neither the country nor Congress is ready for a ban. Opposes federal funding for abortion. Signed legislation to outlaw a type of second- and third-trimester abortion procedure.</p>
        <p>*Says he would not impose an abortion ''litmus test'' on judicial appointments, but cited justices who oppose abortion rights as model appointments and says he favors ''strict constructionists.''</p>
        <p>*Criticized F.D.A.'s approval of morning-after pill.</p>
        <p>DEATH PENALTY  *Supports the death penalty.</p>
        <p>ECONOMY  *Signed tax cuts in each of the past four years, including a $1.35 trillion cut over 10 years in 2001, which he wants to make permanent. Says the cuts have helped the nation overcome recession and are responsible for a surge in economic growth. The cuts have contributed to deficits expected to surpass $400 billion this year. Pledges to cut the deficit in half after five years, in part by urging Congress to limit discretionary spending except for defense and homeland security.</p>
        <p>*Would cut the corporate rate to 32 percent from 35 percent.</p>
        <p>*Wants $3,000 re-employment accounts to help with jobsearch costs.</p>
        <p>*Supports Nafta and World Trade Organization agreements. Supports liberalized trade.</p>
        <p>*Opposes an increase in the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION  *Supports taxpayer-financed vouchers for tuition at parochial and other private schools. Signed the 2002 No Child Left Behind Act, calling for increased annual testing in third through eighth grades by 2005-2006 and tying federal funding to results of tests.</p>
        <p>*Opposes making preschool available to all 4-year-olds.</p>
        <p>*Opposes making federally backed bonds available for school repair and construction.</p>
        <p>*Signed a law providing some tax breaks for college tuition that the administration says saved students and their parents an estimated $9 billion.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT  *Rejected Kyoto Protocol on limiting global-warming gases on the ground it would hurt the nation's economy. Reversed a pledge to regulate carbon dioxide and proposed easing requirement that older factories and refineries to add pollution controls if they expand.</p>
        <p>*Reduced plans for drilling off the Florida coast because of local opposition. Proposed opening the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN POLICY  *After the Sept. 11 attacks, instituted a policy of preemptive strikes, unilaterally if necessary, against suspected threats to the nation's security. Swift military victory in Iraq has been followed by a violent insurgency against the new government. Despite later findings that Iraq had no weapons of mass destruction and had only tenuous ties to Al Qaeda, Mr. Bush said that Saddam Hussein had the will and potential to develop such weapons and help terrorists and that ousting him has made the world safer and will encourage democracy in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>*Waged a successful war against Taliban in Afghanistan, where elections were held this month.</p>
        <p>*Won Congressional approval of $87 billion for continued military operations and aid in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>*Calls for a Palestinian state as part of the peace plan known as the road map.</p>
        <p>GAY RIGHTS  *Opposes gay marriage. Supports a constitutional amendment defining marriage as the union between a man and a woman, but says states should decide whether to allow civil unions for gay couples.</p>
        <p>*Has continued Clinton policy allowing gays to serve in the military if they are not open about their sexuality.</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL  *Favors granting gun makers immunity from civil lawsuits arising from wrongful use of weapons.</p>
        <p>*Supports renewing the ban on assault-type weapons and requiring background checks at gun shows, but let the 10-year-old ban on assault-type weapons expire.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE  *Signed a law giving the elderly limited prescription drug coverage under Medicare for the first time, at an estimated cost of $534 billion over the next 10 years. It subsidizes costs for low-income patients and encourages private insurance companies to offer coverage for the elderly who drop traditional Medicare.</p>
        <p>*Generally opposes importation of lower-cost drugs on grounds that the government cannot guarantee their safety.</p>
        <p>*Supports expansion of tax-free medical savings accounts.</p>
        <p>*The president's election-year budget proposes a $1,000 tax credit to help four million uninsured Americans buy health insurance.</p>
        <p>*Argued against patients' right to sue federally regulated health plans and proposes capping medical malpractice awards.</p>
        <p>HOMELAND SECURITY AND DEFENSE  *After resisting Congressional demands, created a new cabinet-level position to coordinate antiterrorism efforts; tripled spending on security.</p>
        <p>*Argues that even illegal immigrants without known links to terrorist groups can be detained indefinitely.</p>
        <p>*Reconfigured the F.B.I. to focus on preventing attacks.</p>
        <p>*Signed the Patriot Act, which gave law enforcement agents expanded powers to apprehend suspects.</p>
        <p>*Hopes to deploy a shield against ballistic missiles.</p>
        <p>*Has increased defense spending by $100 billion, the most in real terms since the Korean War.</p>
        <p>*Began redeployment of troops from South Korea and Europe. Pledges he will not reinstate the draft.</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY  *Favors giving younger workers choice of placing some of their Social Security payroll tax into personal retirement accounts, with potential of a higher return in exchange for smaller Social Security benefits.</p>
        <p>*Has not ruled out raising retirement age.</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry</p>
        <p>ABORTION  *Supports abortion rights and federal funding for abortion and abortion counseling. Voted against the ban on a second- and third-trimester abortion procedure because it does not allow for abortion when the life of the woman is endangered.</p>
        <p>*Says he will appoint only judges who support abortion rights to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>*Says health plans should assure women coverage for contraceptives.</p>
        <p>DEATH PENALTY  *Opposes the death penalty, except for terrorists.</p>
        <p>ECONOMY  *Would repeal Mr. Bush's tax cuts for taxpayers with incomes above $200,000 and promises not to raise taxes for people earning less. Favors $18 billion a year in health care tax credits for low- and moderate-income workers, including a 75 percent credit for those earning up to 300 percent of the poverty level.</p>
        <p>*Criticizes Mr. Bush because during his presidency, the country has lost at least 585,000 jobs. Calls for $50 billion over an unspecified period for job-creation and economic-stimulus programs and tax credits to discourage outsourcing abroad.</p>
        <p>*Would cut the corporate tax rate by 5 percent.</p>
        <p>*Vows to cut deficit in half by end of first term, letting federal spending rise no more than the inflation rate except for defense, domestic security and education.</p>
        <p>*Supported North American and world trade agreements and elevated trade status with China. Would review trade agreements to assess local labor and environmental standards.</p>
        <p>*Favors an increase in the minimum wage to $7 from $5.15 by 2007 and then indexing it to inflation.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION  *Opposes private-school vouchers as a drain on public school resources. Supports the 2002 legislation but says the funding has been insufficient and proposes $27 billion fully fund the act and creation of a $200 billion education trust fund.</p>
        <p>*Supports a $3.2 billion community service plan for high school students that would qualify them for the equivalent of their state's four-year public college tuition they perform two years of national service.</p>
        <p>*Favors a tax credit for college tuition costs.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT  *Would not sign Kyoto Protocol to cut emissions but would invest in development of hydrogen, ethanol and other cleaner renewable fuels.</p>
        <p>*Would steer $20 billion from oil and gas royalties to development of cleaner energy.</p>
        <p>*Opposes drilling in Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. Wants 20 percent of electricity from renewable or alternative sources by 2020.</p>
        <p>*Supported tougher fuel-efficiency standards for vehicles.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN POLICY  *Supported a Congressional resolution letting Mr. Bush go to war in Iraq but now says he did so based on faulty intelligence and assuming the president would build a broad coalition and invade as a last resort.</p>
        <p>*Voted against an $87 billion package for Iraq and Afghanistan (after voting for an earlier version that would have been paid for by repealing tax cuts for people who earn more than $200,000). Says he would begin troop withdrawal within six months and complete it within four years by enlisting more support from NATO allies.</p>
        <p>*Voted to enlarge NATO to include Eastern Europe</p>
        <p>*Sees the Bush administration's Middle East road map as an acceptable approach for reinvigorating peace efforts, but says there must be verifiable security benchmarks that the Palestinian Authority can reasonably achieve.</p>
        <p>GAY RIGHTS  *Does not favor gay marriage, but opposes a constitutional amendment banning it and says individual states should decide. Supports right to civil unions for same-sex couples. Would ban job discrimination against homosexuals and extend hate-crime protections to gays.</p>
        <p>*Would let gays serve openly in the military.</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL  *Opposes granting gun makers immunity from suits.</p>
        <p>*Supports renewing the ban on assault-type weapons.</p>
        <p>*Would require the same background checks at gun shows that are mandatory for other gun sales. Supports mandatory child safety locks.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE  *Proposes expanding health insurance coverage so that all children and 95 percent of adults are covered, at a cost to the government of $895 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>*Favors lowering costs of prescription drugs by allowing bulk purchasing by Medicare and easier importation of drugs from Canada.</p>
        <p>*Criticized law signed by Mr. Bush giving the elderly prescription drug coverage under Medicare as insufficient, saying it fails to directly involve the government in lowering costs.</p>
        <p>*Wants to expand the insurance system now available for federal employees to private citizens through tax credits and subsidies.</p>
        <p>*Favors a 75 percent tax credit to help pay for insurance.</p>
        <p>*Would give patients an independent review process to appeal coverage decisions.</p>
        <p>*Would bar medical malpractice suits unless a specialist ruled the claim reasonable.</p>
        <p>*Favors federal support to expand access to stateadministered health insurance for children.</p>
        <p>HOMELAND SECURITY AND DEFENSE  *Voted for the Patriot Act, which gave the federal government broad new law enforcement powers; says he supports most of it, but believes it can be improved to enhance its effectiveness and prevent abuses.</p>
        <p>*Opposes a national missile defense shield.</p>
        <p>*Proposes to increase active-duty forces by 40,000 and double Army Special Forces. Would place National Guard under Homeland Security. Opposes a draft and says that reserve call-ups and orders that involuntarily extend tours of duty amount to a "backdoor draft."</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY  *Opposes personal accounts under Social Security.</p>
        <p>*Opposes raising retirement age or reducing payments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President George W. Bush</p>
        <p>ABORTION  *Opposes abortion, except in cases of rape or incest or when a woman's life is endangered, but has said neither the country nor Congress is ready for a ban. Opposes federal funding for abortion. Signed legislation to outlaw a type of second- and third-trimester abortion procedure.</p>
        <p>*Says he would not impose an abortion ''litmus test'' on judicial appointments, but cited justices who oppose abortion rights as model appointments and says he favors ''strict constructionists.''</p>
        <p>*Criticized F.D.A.'s approval of morning-after pill.</p>
        <p>DEATH PENALTY  *Supports the death penalty.</p>
        <p>ECONOMY  *Signed tax cuts in each of the past four years, including a $1.35 trillion cut over 10 years in 2001, which he wants to make permanent. Says the cuts have helped the nation overcome recession and are responsible for a surge in economic growth. The cuts have contributed to deficits expected to surpass $400 billion this year. Pledges to cut the deficit in half after five years, in part by urging Congress to limit discretionary spending except for defense and homeland security.</p>
        <p>*Would cut the corporate rate to 32 percent from 35 percent.</p>
        <p>*Wants $3,000 re-employment accounts to help with jobsearch costs.</p>
        <p>*Supports Nafta and World Trade Organization agreements. Supports liberalized trade.</p>
        <p>*Opposes an increase in the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION  *Supports taxpayer-financed vouchers for tuition at parochial and other private schools. Signed the 2002 No Child Left Behind Act, calling for increased annual testing in third through eighth grades by 2005-2006 and tying federal funding to results of tests.</p>
        <p>*Opposes making preschool available to all 4-year-olds.</p>
        <p>*Opposes making federally backed bonds available for school repair and construction.</p>
        <p>*Signed a law providing some tax breaks for college tuition that the administration says saved students and their parents an estimated $9 billion.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT  *Rejected Kyoto Protocol on limiting global-warming gases on the ground it would hurt the nation's economy. Reversed a pledge to regulate carbon dioxide and proposed easing requirement that older factories and refineries to add pollution controls if they expand.</p>
        <p>*Reduced plans for drilling off the Florida coast because of local opposition. Proposed opening the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN POLICY  *After the Sept. 11 attacks, instituted a policy of preemptive strikes, unilaterally if necessary, against suspected threats to the nation's security. Swift military victory in Iraq has been followed by a violent insurgency against the new government. Despite later findings that Iraq had no weapons of mass destruction and had only tenuous ties to Al Qaeda, Mr. Bush said that Saddam Hussein had the will and potential to develop such weapons and help terrorists and that ousting him has made the world safer and will encourage democracy in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>*Waged a successful war against Taliban in Afghanistan, where elections were held this month.</p>
        <p>*Won Congressional approval of $87 billion for continued military operations and aid in Iraq and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>*Calls for a Palestinian state as part of the peace plan known as the road map.</p>
        <p>GAY RIGHTS  *Opposes gay marriage. Supports a constitutional amendment defining marriage as the union between a man and a woman, but says states should decide whether to allow civil unions for gay couples.</p>
        <p>*Has continued Clinton policy allowing gays to serve in the military if they are not open about their sexuality.</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL  *Favors granting gun makers immunity from civil lawsuits arising from wrongful use of weapons.</p>
        <p>*Supports renewing the ban on assault-type weapons and requiring background checks at gun shows, but let the 10-year-old ban on assault-type weapons expire.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE  *Signed a law giving the elderly limited prescription drug coverage under Medicare for the first time, at an estimated cost of $534 billion over the next 10 years. It subsidizes costs for low-income patients and encourages private insurance companies to offer coverage for the elderly who drop traditional Medicare.</p>
        <p>*Generally opposes importation of lower-cost drugs on grounds that the government cannot guarantee their safety.</p>
        <p>*Supports expansion of tax-free medical savings accounts.</p>
        <p>*The president's election-year budget proposes a $1,000 tax credit to help four million uninsured Americans buy health insurance.</p>
        <p>*Argued against patients' right to sue federally regulated health plans and proposes capping medical malpractice awards.</p>
        <p>HOMELAND SECURITY AND DEFENSE  *After resisting Congressional demands, created a new cabinet-level position to coordinate antiterrorism efforts; tripled spending on security.</p>
        <p>*Argues that even illegal immigrants without known links to terrorist groups can be detained indefinitely.</p>
        <p>*Reconfigured the F.B.I. to focus on preventing attacks.</p>
        <p>*Signed the Patriot Act, which gave law enforcement agents expanded powers to apprehend suspects.</p>
        <p>*Hopes to deploy a shield against ballistic missiles.</p>
        <p>*Has increased defense spending by $100 billion, the most in real terms since the Korean War.</p>
        <p>*Began redeployment of troops from South Korea and Europe. Pledges he will not reinstate the draft.</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY  *Favors giving younger workers choice of placing some of their Social Security payroll tax into personal retirement accounts, with potential of a higher return in exchange for smaller Social Security benefits.</p>
        <p>*Has not ruled out raising retirement age.</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry</p>
        <p>ABORTION  *Supports abortion rights and federal funding for abortion and abortion counseling. Voted against the ban on a second- and third-trimester abortion procedure because it does not allow for abortion when the life of the woman is endangered.</p>
        <p>*Says he will appoint only judges who support abortion rights to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>*Says health plans should assure women coverage for contraceptives.</p>
        <p>DEATH PENALTY  *Opposes the death penalty, except for terrorists.</p>
        <p>ECONOMY  *Would repeal Mr. Bush's tax cuts for taxpayers with incomes above $200,000 and promises not to raise taxes for people earning less. Favors $18 billion a year in health care tax credits for low- and moderate-income workers, including a 75 percent credit for those earning up to 300 percent of the poverty level.</p>
        <p>*Criticizes Mr. Bush because during his presidency, the country has lost at least 585,000 jobs. Calls for $50 billion over an unspecified period for job-creation and economic-stimulus programs and tax credits to discourage outsourcing abroad.</p>
        <p>*Would cut the corporate tax rate by 5 percent.</p>
        <p>*Vows to cut deficit in half by end of first term, letting federal spending rise no more than the inflation rate except for defense, domestic security and education.</p>
        <p>*Supported North American and world trade agreements and elevated trade status with China. Would review trade agreements to assess local labor and environmental standards.</p>
        <p>*Favors an increase in the minimum wage to $7 from $5.15 by 2007 and then indexing it to inflation.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION  *Opposes private-school vouchers as a drain on public school resources. Supports the 2002 legislation but says the funding has been insufficient and proposes $27 billion fully fund the act and creation of a $200 billion education trust fund.</p>
        <p>*Supports a $3.2 billion community service plan for high school students that would qualify them for the equivalent of their state's four-year public college tuition they perform two years of national service.</p>
        <p>*Favors a tax credit for college tuition costs.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT  *Would not sign Kyoto Protocol to cut emissions but would invest in development of hydrogen, ethanol and other cleaner renewable fuels.</p>
        <p>*Would steer $20 billion from oil and gas royalties to development of cleaner energy.</p>
        <p>*Opposes drilling in Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. Wants 20 percent of electricity from renewable or alternative sources by 2020.</p>
        <p>*Supported tougher fuel-efficiency standards for vehicles.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN POLICY  *Supported a Congressional resolution letting Mr. Bush go to war in Iraq but now says he did so based on faulty intelligence and assuming the president would build a broad coalition and invade as a last resort.</p>
        <p>*Voted against an $87 billion package for Iraq and Afghanistan (after voting for an earlier version that would have been paid for by repealing tax cuts for people who earn more than $200,000). Says he would begin troop withdrawal within six months and complete it within four years by enlisting more support from NATO allies.</p>
        <p>*Voted to enlarge NATO to include Eastern Europe</p>
        <p>*Sees the Bush administration's Middle East road map as an acceptable approach for reinvigorating peace efforts, but says there must be verifiable security benchmarks that the Palestinian Authority can reasonably achieve.</p>
        <p>GAY RIGHTS  *Does not favor gay marriage, but opposes a constitutional amendment banning it and says individual states should decide. Supports right to civil unions for same-sex couples. Would ban job discrimination against homosexuals and extend hate-crime protections to gays.</p>
        <p>*Would let gays serve openly in the military.</p>
        <p>GUN CONTROL  *Opposes granting gun makers immunity from suits.</p>
        <p>*Supports renewing the ban on assault-type weapons.</p>
        <p>*Would require the same background checks at gun shows that are mandatory for other gun sales. Supports mandatory child safety locks.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE  *Proposes expanding health insurance coverage so that all children and 95 percent of adults are covered, at a cost to the government of $895 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>*Favors lowering costs of prescription drugs by allowing bulk purchasing by Medicare and easier importation of drugs from Canada.</p>
        <p>*Criticized law signed by Mr. Bush giving the elderly prescription drug coverage under Medicare as insufficient, saying it fails to directly involve the government in lowering costs.</p>
        <p>*Wants to expand the insurance system now available for federal employees to private citizens through tax credits and subsidies.</p>
        <p>*Favors a 75 percent tax credit to help pay for insurance.</p>
        <p>*Would give patients an independent review process to appeal coverage decisions.</p>
        <p>*Would bar medical malpractice suits unless a specialist ruled the claim reasonable.</p>
        <p>*Favors federal support to expand access to stateadministered health insurance for children.</p>
        <p>HOMELAND SECURITY AND DEFENSE  *Voted for the Patriot Act, which gave the federal government broad new law enforcement powers; says he supports most of it, but believes it can be improved to enhance its effectiveness and prevent abuses.</p>
        <p>*Opposes a national missile defense shield.</p>
        <p>*Proposes to increase active-duty forces by 40,000 and double Army Special Forces. Would place National Guard under Homeland Security. Opposes a draft and says that reserve call-ups and orders that involuntarily extend tours of duty amount to a "backdoor draft."</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY  *Opposes personal accounts under Social Security.</p>
        <p>*Opposes raising retirement age or reducing payments.</p>
        <p>THE ISSUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
