<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Commerce Secretary's Other Job</title>
    <meta content="11SAT2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/11/opinion/11sat2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Oceanic &amp; Atmospheric Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kellogg Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gutierrez, Carlos</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0D61131F932A25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Commerce Secretary's Other Job</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Commerce Secretary's Other Job</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial notes that 60 percent of Commerce Dept's budget is allocated not to economic development but to National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration; holds that it would be surprising if Carlos Gutierrez, Pres Bush's nominee to be secretary of commerce, thought much about ocean policy when he was running Kellogg Co; asserts that Senate committee in charge of approving his nomination should make sure that he gets up to speed in a hurry</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretaries of commerce tend to be plucked from the business world, and for good reason. As commonly understood by the public and the presidents who appoint them, the secretary's role is to be a cheerleader for American business, to promote enterprise and trade and -- to the extent he cares to listen -- to advise the president on economic policy. That was certainly President Bush's understanding when he described his nominee, Carlos Gutierrez, chief executive of the Kellogg Company, as a man who ''knows exactly what it takes to help American businesses grow and to create jobs.''</p>
        <p>But that is only the half of it -- in budgetary terms, less than half. Fully 60 percent of the Commerce Department's budget is allocated not to economic development but to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, called NOAA. That agency not only monitors developments in Earth's atmosphere (global warming among them), but also has the primary responsibility for understanding, managing and protecting America's ocean waters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the secretary of commerce, Carlos Gutierrez will oversee the monitoring of America's ocean waters, an issue that is coming to a boil in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretaries of commerce tend to be plucked from the business world, and for good reason. As commonly understood by the public and the presidents who appoint them, the secretary's role is to be a cheerleader for American business, to promote enterprise and trade and -- to the extent he cares to listen -- to advise the president on economic policy. That was certainly President Bush's understanding when he described his nominee, Carlos Gutierrez, chief executive of the Kellogg Company, as a man who ''knows exactly what it takes to help American businesses grow and to create jobs.''</p>
        <p>But that is only the half of it -- in budgetary terms, less than half. Fully 60 percent of the Commerce Department's budget is allocated not to economic development but to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, called NOAA. That agency not only monitors developments in Earth's atmosphere (global warming among them), but also has the primary responsibility for understanding, managing and protecting America's ocean waters.</p>
        <p>By all rights, these executive responsibilities alone should entitle Mr. Gutierrez to play an important role in setting the government's broad environmental policy. None of his predecessors have chosen to do so. But Mr. Gutierrez will have to be more engaged than they were, especially on oceans policy. President Bush is obliged to respond to a report by the United States Commission on Ocean Policy by Dec. 20. The report is one of two exhaustive studies in the last year -- the other was produced privately by the Pew Oceans Commission -- that found America's ocean waters to be increasingly at risk from coastal pollution, rampant overfishing and confusion among the agencies responsible for ocean health.</p>
        <p>It will be Mr. Gutierrez's job to follow up on Mr. Bush's proposals and deal with a Congress that is increasingly impatient for action. There are a half-dozen bills circulating on Capitol Hill that would impose new discipline on an essentially self-regulating fishing industry, toughen laws on coastal development and reorganize the way oceans policy is made. One bill that should be of particular interest to Mr. Gutierrez would strip NOAA from his department and set it up as an independent agency with control over scores of ocean-related programs now scattered throughout the bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>It would be surprising if Mr. Gutierrez gave any of these issues much thought while he was running a big cereal company. But the Senate committee in charge of approving his nomination should make sure that he gets up to speed in a hurry.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
