<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Patchogue Inventor, a Costly Uphill Battle</title>
    <meta content="26LIBIZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="L.I.@WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vasile, Carmine F</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Renewability Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strugatch, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EED71330F935A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Patchogue Inventor, a Costly Uphill Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN STRUGATCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strugatch, Warren</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carmine F Vasile invents heat exchange process that he claims was duplicated by Renewability Inc of Canada; Renewability denies that it is same product Vasile patented; US patents are not protected under Canadian patent system, and small inventors cannot afford to have inventions patented in all markets where they may sell or be manufactured; Vasile believed his product, gravity film exchange, or GFX, was protected under Economic Espionage Act of 1996; goverment is investigating; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the heart of American enterprise is the ''build a better mousetrap'' axiom: create a fine product, and the market will reward you handsomely.</p>
        <p>Try telling that to Carmine F. Vasile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the heart of American enterprise is the ''build a better mousetrap'' axiom: create a fine product, and the market will reward you handsomely.</p>
        <p>Try telling that to Carmine F. Vasile.</p>
        <p>This last year has been a long and trying one for Dr. Vasile, an electrophysicist who lives in Patchogue, a basement inventor and, of late, a lapsed believer in free-market economics. Dr. Vasile (pronounced vah-SILL-ee) believes that he invented the proverbial better mousetrap but that bigger companies and their lawyers have stolen his ideas. ''A great invention doesn't do you any good unless you can afford to protect it all over the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nineteen years ago, during a period of self-employment between stints at Motorola and the Hazeltine Corporation, an electronics manufacturer in Greenlawn, Dr. Vasile developed a heat-exchange process that had considerable commercial potential, he thought. The process uses a copper coil inserted in a drain to absorb heat from wastewater and transfer it to incoming cold water. The process makes it cheaper to heat cold water.</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile, who said that during his career he had received about 35 patents on behalf of various employers, including Motorola, Rockwell, Hazeltine and Grumman, holds Patent No. 4,619,311 himself. He assigned the patent to a company called Hydrofilm, a limited partnership he and his wife, Cheryl, operate from their home.</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile calls his invention a gravity film heat exchanger -- GFX for short. In 1994 Dr. Vasile retired early to focus his entrepreneurial energies on bringing the GFX to market. At the time, Dr. Vasile said, he thought the GFX would finance a comfortable retirement for himself and his wife.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, Dr. Vasile found a partner, Doucette Industries of York, Pa., which manufactured and marketed the device and mailed him monthly royalty checks ranging from $2,000 to $4,000.</p>
        <p>In March, the checks stopped. Doucette announced it was ceasing distribution of the GFX in favor of another product called the Power-Pipe, manufactured by a company called Renewability Inc. in Aurora, Ontario.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, Dr. Vasile was furious, and the Power-Pipe, in his view, is just the GFX under another name.</p>
        <p>''This is fraud,'' he said. ''I have pictures of the product. Power-Pipe is the same thing as GFX.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile wrote letters, many letters, to everyone involved. He complained to Underwriters Laboratories in Melville, which certified the safety of the GFX; to the Canadian Embassy in Washington; to a trade association of building contractors; and to the Federal bankruptcy court in Central Islip.</p>
        <p>''They tell you to watch out for countries like Thailand,'' he said, describing warnings he received about product counterfeiting. ''Nobody tells you about Canada.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile acknowledges that his design is not protected under the Canadian patent system, and he knows that most companies routinely patent their inventions in all markets where they expect to sell or where the product might be manufactured.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't afford to do that,'' he said. He said he relied on the belief that the GFX design qualified as a trade secret and was thus protected under the Economic Espionage Act of 1996.</p>
        <p>''I protected trade secrets for 20 years for companies like Hazeltine,'' Dr. Vasile said. ''When I talk about trade secrets, I know what I'm talking about.''</p>
        <p>Charlie Boeckmann, an aide to Representative Tim Bishop, said that he had written letters on Dr. Vasile's behalf to appropriate F.B.I. officials, asking them to review his claims under the espionage act, and that the F.B.I. told him earlier this month that the claims were being investigated.</p>
        <p>''If in fact his allegations are correct, we have a serious issue on the federal level.'' Mr. Boeckmann said.</p>
        <p>John Lebo, the president of Doucette Industries, refused to comment on Dr. Vasile's contentions. ''There really is nothing to discuss with you,'' he said. ''We will comment at the proper venue, and this is not it.''</p>
        <p>Denis Van Decker, a vice president of Renewability Energy, denied that the Power-Pipe was the same product as the GFX.</p>
        <p>Of Dr. Vasile, he said: ''The man has no credibility. He throws mud at people. The products aren't the same, and our customers know the difference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Decker said that arbitrators had ruled against Dr. Vasile in 12 instances, but Dr. Vasile denied that. He said that there had been only three rulings against him and that the arbitration process was incomplete, because he could not afford to pay the costs assessed by the arbitrators. Mr. Van Decker said the issue would be resolved in court.</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile has ''done the lion's share of what would be expected of him'' to get his idea successfully commercialized, said an official of the federal Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, which administered a grant of nearly $100,000 given to Dr. Vasile to help him develop and market his invention.</p>
        <p>Inventors often confront the problem of defending their patents in other countries, said the official, who spoke on the condition that his name not be used because he was afraid of how his supervisors would react to his comments.</p>
        <p>''All these guys are disadvantaged trying to get their technology to the market,'' the official said, describing independent inventors. ''They're like the guy in the Greek myth who pushes the boulder up the mountain,'' only to have it roll down again.</p>
        <p>The official said that there was little the government could do for them, aside from sympathizing with them. His own approach, he said, is to recite motivational speeches made by Vince Lombardi, the Green Bay Packers' coach. ''I told Carmine, 'Don't give up,''' the official said. ''I regularly tell inventors, 'Don't give up.'''</p>
        <p>Dr. Vasile said that he had not given up but that because of financial problems brought on by the GFX, he could not afford to hire a patent lawyer and is presenting a claim in bankruptcy court.</p>
        <p>Ronald Weiss, a Huntington lawyer who represented Dr. Vasile at his bankruptcy hearing in Central Islip last month, called the case ''particularly complex with several overlapping issues.''</p>
        <p>''This is a David and Goliath situation, and Carmine is taking on six Goliaths,'' Mr. Weiss said.</p>
        <p>So, instead of financing a comfortable retirement for him and his wife, Dr. Vasile said his efforts to market his GFX invention had depleted ''our lifetime earnings.''</p>
        <p>''It's been a nightmare,'' he added. ''I blew through my retirement money and my wife's. What I've learned is that people can steal technology at will. Unless you've got money to defend your patent, it's worthless.''</p>
        <p>The GFX patent comes up for renewal next June, but Dr. Vasile is not giving up. ''I'll renew it,'' he said. ''With improvements.'' And things are, in fact, looking up. In July he found a new manufacturer for the GFX, Fuel Cell Components Integrators of Hauppauge, and sales have just gotten under way.</p>
        <p>L.I.@WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
