<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D6123EF934A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Questioning of Detainees Produced Little of Value  The questioning of hundreds of Iraqi prisoners last fall in the interrogation center at Abu Ghraib prison yielded very little valuable intelligence. Most of the prisoners apparently were not linked to the insurgency and had been questioned already by the troops who captured them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Three of the seven soldiers now charged with abuse at the Abu Ghraib prison repeatedly committed infractions and disobeyed orders in the six months leading up to the investigation, but received only the mildest of punishments.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Questioning of Detainees Produced Little of Value  The questioning of hundreds of Iraqi prisoners last fall in the interrogation center at Abu Ghraib prison yielded very little valuable intelligence. Most of the prisoners apparently were not linked to the insurgency and had been questioned already by the troops who captured them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Three of the seven soldiers now charged with abuse at the Abu Ghraib prison repeatedly committed infractions and disobeyed orders in the six months leading up to the investigation, but received only the mildest of punishments.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>An Iraqi nuclear scientist touted as the likely interim leader of Iraq withdrew his name from consideration, while the American military captured a close aide of the radical Shiite cleric, Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Linked Car Bombs in Pakistan  One police officer was killed and at least 26 people were wounded in Pakistan when two car bombs went off within 25 minutes and a dozen feet of each other in Karachi. The timing and location seemed to indicate that the militants were making a statement about Pakistan's aligning with America to fight terrorism.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Putin Claims Interference  President Vladimir V. Putin said that foreign pressure was being used in an attempt to weaken Russia's chances of competing globally. Mr. Putin singled out private groups that he said claimed to support the welfare of the people but were in fact serving other foreign and domestic masters for pay.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Possible Terror Link in Japan  Five foreigners who had been in contact with a Frenchman with possible ties to Al Qaeda were arrested in Japan. Four of the men were charged with violating immigration laws, while the fifth was charged with falsifying a document. The Japanese authorities hope to discover what the men were doing in the country.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-26</p>
        <p>Court Sides With Oregon On Assisted Suicide Policy  A federal appeals court rejected an effort by the Justice Department to block the only law in the nation authorizing doctors to help their patients commit suicide, upholding Oregon's Death With Dignity Act.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Democrats Plot Kerry Course  President Bush's political difficulties have prompted a debate among Democrats and aides to John Kerry about how cautious his campaign should be on a host of issues, from choosing a vice president to responding to the turmoil in Iraq.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Senator John Kerry said he would accept the Democratic nomination at his party's convention in July, abandoning the idea of a strategic delay to narrow President Bush's substantial financial advantage.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Gore Criticizes Bush Cabinet  Former Vice President Al Gore called for the resignations of six high-ranking officials of the Bush administration, declaring that they had ''shamed America'' with their policy on Iraq.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Kissinger Tapes Released  The National Archives released 20,000 pages of recorded conversations of Henry A. Kissinger during his time as the national security adviser under President Nixon.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Guilty of 161 Murders  Nine years after a homemade bomb ripped through a federal office building in Oklahoma City, Terry L. Nichols was convicted of 161 counts of first degree murder in the blast, and a state jury now must decide whether he should be executed.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Prostate Test May Mislead  Significant numbers of men whose results are normal on a popular screening test for prostate cancer still may have cancer, a new study finds.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>Juilliard Drama Student Strangled, Autopsy Shows  A woman whose badly decomposed body was found laying naked in a heavily wooded section of Inwood Hill Park was identified as a missing drama student at the Juilliard School. An autopsy found that the woman had been strangled.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Animal Advocates Arrested  Seven animal rights activists were arrested on charges of trying to disrupt the work of a pharmaceutical testing company based in New Jersey and threatening its employees and those of six companies doing business with it, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Designer for Olympic Village  Morphosis, a firm based in Santa Monica, Calif., has been chosen to design the 2012 Olympic Village.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>SPORTSTHURSDAY</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Fire Guts Saatchi Collection  A fire in East London destroyed millions of dollars worth of work by leading contemporary British artists, dozens of them from the vast collection of Charles Saatchi, the warehouse's owner and Mr. Saatchi said.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B9-10</p>
        <p>Roger W. Straus Jr.  The book publisher who presided for nearly six decades over the company that bore his name, he was 87.</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>David Dellinger  The activist who became a leading defendant in the raucous political conspiracy trial of the Chicago Seven, he was 88.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Premium Increases May Slow  Health insurance premiums are expected to rise up to 10 percent this year, well below the annual increases of 14 to 18 percent in the past few years but still more than double the overall inflation rate.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Controlling Energy Costs  The nation's industrial companies are reinvigorating efforts to use a variety of energy-efficient measures in response to the surge in oil prices.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New Rules for Mutual Funds  The Securities and Exchange Commission unanimously approved new rules to require mutual funds to adopt new ethics codes.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: Judicial ethics under review; culture in Lower Manhattan; Robert B. Semple Jr. on a film that could warm up the debate on global warming.</p>
        <p>Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>B11  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
