<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="11MOVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E4D91430F932A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="5362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy movies playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film. Ratings and running times are in parentheses.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''BUKOWSKI: BORN INTO THIS.'' Directed by John Dullaghan. (Not rated, 113 minutes). This definitive, deeply engrossing film biography of the famously scrappy, hard-drinking poet Charles Bukowski, who died in 1984, combines interviews, many done for European television, with the reminiscences of former drinking buddies, fellow writers and his second wife, Linda, the keeper of his flame. The portrait that emerges is of a cantankerous misanthrope zestfully living out his legend as a profane realist and professional lowlife, whose lean, brutal literary style allowed no sentimentality. He wryly credits his abusive childhood in which his father regularly beat him for no reason as having helped form his style. Without straining, the film makes a strong case for Bukowski as a major American poet whose work was a slashing rebuke to polite academic formalism (Stephen Holden).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times: New or noteworthy movies playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film. Ratings and running times are in parentheses.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''BUKOWSKI: BORN INTO THIS.'' Directed by John Dullaghan. (Not rated, 113 minutes). This definitive, deeply engrossing film biography of the famously scrappy, hard-drinking poet Charles Bukowski, who died in 1984, combines interviews, many done for European television, with the reminiscences of former drinking buddies, fellow writers and his second wife, Linda, the keeper of his flame. The portrait that emerges is of a cantankerous misanthrope zestfully living out his legend as a profane realist and professional lowlife, whose lean, brutal literary style allowed no sentimentality. He wryly credits his abusive childhood in which his father regularly beat him for no reason as having helped form his style. Without straining, the film makes a strong case for Bukowski as a major American poet whose work was a slashing rebuke to polite academic formalism (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>''CARLOS CASTANEDA: ENIGMA OF A SORCERER.'' Directed by Ralph Torjan. (Not rated, 91 minutes). Was Carlos Castaneda, the U.C.L.A. anthropologist whose 1968 book ''The Teachings of Don Juan: A Yaqui Way of Knowledge'' became one of the founding texts of the New Age movement, a great spiritual leader or a cynical con man? Directed by Ralph Torjan, once a member of Castaneda's inner circle of students, this digital video documentary piles up plenty of evidence that Don Juan, the Yaqui shaman who supposedly trained Castaneda in the ancient Indian ways to alternative realities, was a complete invention on Castaneda's part. But at the same time Mr. Torjan is reluctant to abandon the teachings of his former mentor, and the film bogs down in ambivalence and ambiguity (Dave Kehr).</p>
        <p>* ''CARANDIRU,'' starring Luiz Carlos Vasconcelos. Directed by Hector Babenco. (R, 146 minutes; in Portuguese, with English subtitles). The human life teeming through this sprawling portrait of Brazil's criminal class crowded within a notorious penitentiary exudes a throbbing flesh-and-blood intensity so compelling that it's impossible to avert your eyes. Watching this messy epic is a little like being jammed into an un-air-conditioned subway car on a steamy summer night as it rattles through an urban wasteland: at any second, things could explode. And eventually they do. It is the 1980's, and the setting is São Paulo's real-life house of detention, which was torn down in 2002, a decade after a riot led to the massacre of 111 inmates by the police. The film is a splashy return to form by the celebrated director of ''Pixote'' and ''Kiss of the Spider Woman.'' In examining social ills, it interweaves multiple stories of the prisoners' lives as viewed by a doctor volunteering his services. Below its documentarylike sprawl, ''Carandiru'' is a hands-on movie passionately engaged in its characters' personal dramas. Just when it threatens to go soft, it erupts in what may be the most horrific prison riot ever filmed (Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''COFFEE AND CIGARETTES,'' starring Cate Blanchett, Alfred Molina, Bill Murray, Meg White, Jack White and Steve Coogan. Written and directed by Jim Jarmusch (R, 96 minutes). Over 17 years, in the midst of other, more ambitious projects, Mr. Jarmusch assembled this anthology of minor-key vignettes in celebration of caffeine, nicotine and the indolent pleasure of sitting around and consuming them. Not that the people in the film are always having such a good time: they seem, rather, to get on one another's nerves with some regularity. Some of the chapters are almost vanishingly slight -- hipster anecdotes that float away like smoke rings. Others -- notably a hotel bar encounter in which Ms. Blanchett plays herself and a resentful cousin, and a game of celebrity one-upmanship between Mr. Molina and Mr. Coogan -- have the compact perfection of good one-act plays. The whole thing is like an old LP; some tracks are more memorable than others, but the cumulative effect is ragged, serendipitous magic (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>''THE DAY AFTER TOMORROW,'' starring Dennis Quaid and Jake Gyllenhaal. Directed by Roland Emmerich (PG-13, 117 minutes). Tornadoes in Los Angeles. Hail in Tokyo. The entire Northern Hemisphere encased in a sheet of ice, with uncountable casualties, including life as we know it. All of which adds up, in the hands of Mr. Emmerich, to a sprawling, oddly lighthearted action picture. The computer-generated special effects are awesome, though not in the traditional sense of the word. As you watch cities obliterated by wind, water and ice, you don't think, ''My God, how horrible''; you think, ''Cool!'' The only one who seems genuinely worried is Mr. Quaid, playing a scientist whose apocalyptic warnings are ignored until it's too late. He sets out to find his son (Mr. Gyllenhaal), who is stranded at the New York Public Library and who seems, all in all, pretty relaxed. Like most disaster films, this one is ultimately more soothing than alarming, which may undermine its supposed ambition to raise awareness about the perils of climate change (Scott).</p>
        <p>''HARRY POTTER AND THE PRISONER OF AZKABAN.'' Starring Daniel Radcliffe, Rupert Grint and Emma Watson. Directed by Alfonso Cuarón (PG, 136 minutes). Taking over the franchise from Christopher Columbus, Mr. Cuarón injects this third Potter picture with a shadowy, sensual mood. The look is grainier and grimier, and the themes are a bit darker and more unsettling than those in ''Sorcerer's Stone'' or ''Chamber of Secrets.'' There is less Quidditch and more Snape, which is all to the good, as are the efforts of new cast members like Michael Gambon (taking over for Richard Harris as Albus Dumbledore), Emma Thompson (as a batty divination teacher), David Thewlis (as the latest defense-against-the-dark-arts master) and Gary Oldman, who brings his adaptable villainy to the title role. The film's major weakness, sad to say, is Harry himself. Approaching adolescence, Mr. Radcliffe may also be reaching the limit of his range as an actor; he seems unable to summon the complex, volatile emotions that the story demands, with its notes of grief and rage amid the usual boarding-school intrigue. Still, Mr. Cuarón breathes some new life -- and a new sense of mystery -- into a series whose charms are in danger of declining due to overfamiliarity (Scott).</p>
        <p>''MEAN GIRLS,'' starring Lindsay Lohan and Rachel McAdams. Directed by Mark Waters (PG-13, 97 minutes). This tart and often charming new comedy is a version of the heart-of-darkness teenage social comedy ''Heathers'' for the tweener audience; it has the ambitious and cartoony dark side of a Disney Channel sitcom, with a lively and talented young cast. The ''Saturday Night Live'' writer and performer Tina Fey wrote the script and gives the material a stylized vitality. But the film adds a be-yourself finale that this picture doesn't quite seem to buy. It's the kind of bored manipulation you come to expect from the Plastics, the pack of hallway-shrewd and glamorous teenage queens who use subtle terror to rule the high school that Cady (Ms. Lohan) attends. It's her first brush with socialization, since she was home schooled by her zoologist parents in Africa. Though narrative cohesion isn't the strength of ''Girls,'' the intelligence shines through in its understanding of contradictions (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''RAISING HELEN,'' starring Kate Hudson, John Corbett and John Cusack. Directed by Garry Marshall (PG-13, 119 minutes). This softhearted, squishy-minded prototype for a network sitcom is mildly ingratiating but never laugh-out-loud funny. Ms. Hudson is the scuffling gal Friday and Little Ms. Fixit to the queenly chief of a New York fashion agency. On the fast track to A-list Manhattan insufferability, she lives out a dreamy, sanitized version of the ''Sex and the City'' lifestyle, partying all night, then skipping into the office all a-bubble with nifty little notions that anticipate her boss's every whim. Her life of fun, fun, fun comes to a screeching halt when her older sister and her husband are killed in a car crash, and their will gives Helen custody of three orphaned children. The rest of the movie tells the warm and fuzzy story of Helen's bumbling surrogate parenthood to the brood she inherits, and her discovery of family values and true romance in an outer borough. The movie pretends to address the practical issues of single parenthood in New York but is far too skittish to do more than bring up a problem or two, then solve it with a magical sitcom-ready wave of its wand (Holden).</p>
        <p>''SAVED!'' Starring Jena Malone, Patrick Fugit, Mandy Moore and Macaulay Culkin. Directed by Brian Dannelly (PG-13, 92 minutes). This teenage satire set in a Christian high school is an admirable attempt to acknowledge the powerful influence of religion in contemporary American youth culture. Mr. Dannelly resists easy, smug caricature, but the picture ultimately fails both as comedy and as sentimental melodrama, veering from not-very-funny jokes to canned speeches about tolerance and human fallibility. This is a shame, since the bright young cast (especially Ms. Moore, relishing the chance to play a villainous, self-righteous teenage queen bee) performs with conviction and high spirits. Ms. Malone plays Mary, who becomes pregnant while trying to cure her gay boyfriend and whose crisis separates the pious hypocrites from the decent folk. In the end, ''Saved!'' is an exercise in liberal humanist piety, a peace offering in the culture wars that is sadly unable to realize its good intentions, or to make you laugh (Scott).</p>
        <p>''SHREK 2,'' with the voices of Mike Myers, Eddie Murphy, Cameron Diaz, Antonio Banderas and Jennifer Saunders. Directed by Andrew Adamson, Kelly Asbury and Conrad Vernon (PG, 93 minutes). This sequel revives the raucous high spirits of its predecessor, with some new characters, jokes and satiric targets to compensate for the loss of novelty. Shrek (Mr. Myers) and Fiona (Ms. Diaz), now married, travel with Donkey (Mr. Murphy) to meet Shrek's in-laws, the king and queen of Far Far Away, which is to Hollywood what Duloc was to Disney in the first ''Shrek.'' There they contend with a scheming fairy godmother (Ms. Saunders) and a swashbuckling, scene-stealing Puss in Boots (Mr. Banderas). The animation has improved, and the cross-generational appeal -- slapstick and moralizing for the kids, cheekiness and pop music for the grownups -- is precisely calibrated and jauntily executed. Still, the cynicism of the enterprise leaves a bit of a sour taste. The movie is too timid to risk genuine ugliness, and too crude to try for real beauty (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''SINCE OTAR LEFT,'' starring Esther Gorintin, Nino Khomassouridze and Dinara Droukarova. Directed by Julie Bertuccelli (not rated, 102 minutes; in French with English subtitles). Although the title character is seen only fleetingly in blurry snapshots, his presence haunts the imaginations of the three women at the center of this beautifully written and acted drama. Otar, a medical student from the former Soviet republic of Georgia, has fled the bleak, crumbling city of Tblisi, where he grew up, to live in Paris, where he is struggling to make his way without a visa. Left behind are his doting mother (Ms. Gorintin), his sister (Ms. Khomassouridze) and his sister's daughter (Dinara Droukarova). Like Chekhov's ''Three Sisters,'' ''Since Otar Left'' is about yearning as a life force. The mother, a painfully stooped, hobbling old woman, lives for her son's occasional phone calls and letters. When word comes that Otar has died in a construction accident, the sister and granddaughter, afraid to break the news, put on a charade, writing bogus letters that spur the mother to journey to Paris to see her son. The film sustains a fine balance of pathos, humor and a clear-headed realism (Holden).</p>
        <p>''THE STORY OF THE WEEPING CAMEL.'' Directed by Byambasuren Davaa and Luigi Falorni. (PG, 87 minutes.) This lovely, uncomplicated though limited movie is a shaggy dog story -- well, actually, a shaggy animal story. The title isn't a metaphor (though the story itself is). The filmmakers have actually made a film about a pale and needy newborn camel whose mother ignores it. After a difficult birth, the mother abandons her calf, refusing to nurse it. In the wrong hands -- probably any other hands -- ''Camel'' would drip with stickiness, and it verges on being an old-school live-action Disney feature. Yet Ms. Davaa and Mr. Falorni deny us the easiness of narration that spells out what their cameras are ably, and simply, filming. They have said they were inspired by the pioneering documentarian Robert Flaherty. This movie follows Flaherty's mission to capture traditions of cultures far from his own. Though similar in motivation, it is modest and leisurely, rather than epic and obsessive like Flaherty's films. The filmmakers' patience and the quality of the images they obtain give a mellow contentment to the project, a thoughtful and honest serenity that is passed on to viewers (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>* ''STRAYED,'' starring Emmanuelle Béart and Gaspard Ulleil. Directed by André Téchiné (not rated, 95 minutes; in French, with English subtitles). This taut, swift wartime drama, set in the early days of the German occupation of France, begins with a montage of devastating black-and-white news clips interwoven with flashes of the flight south of a terrified young widow (Ms. Béart) and her two children, a 13-year-old boy (Grégoire Leprince-Ringuet) and 7-year-old girl (Clémence Meyer). When a German air strike leaves the family car a burned-out shell, a boyish young stranger (Mr. Ulleil) guides them into the woods where they find refuge in a grand abandoned house. The movie plays multiple variations on the theme of initiation as the foursome improvises a structured family life and delicately lays out fundamental conflicts: between survivalist and bourgeois perspectives; between wartime and peacetime expectations; between habitually clinging to family values and fending for yourself. Until their precarious idyll is finally interrupted, each of the four is forced to stretch and grow up in uncomfortable ways (Holden).</p>
        <p>''SUPER SIZE ME,'' directed by Morgan Spurlock (not rated, 96 minutes). For 30 days, Mr. Spurlock consumed nothing but food from McDonald's, an experiment in bad living that frames a jaunty critique of junk gastronomy and corporate power. Like a thinner, less aggressive Michael Moore, the director talks to consumers, experts and food-industry flacks, weaving alarming statistics about rampant obesity with visits to the doctor and double-quarter-pounder-with-cheese combo meals. The film is an entertaining statement of the obvious, though its big questions -- Do corporations serve our need or enslave our bodies and souls? Are public health problems caused by capitalist rapacity or personal choice? -- are not as simple as Mr. Spurlock would have us believe (Scott).</p>
        <p>''TROY,'' starring Brad Pitt, Eric Bana and Orlando Bloom. Directed by Wolfgang Petersen (R, 140 minutes). All the talk of glory and immortality is a clear signal that this big, expensive, intermittently campy example of Hollywood Homerism is desperate to be regarded as a classic. It isn't, but it's not so bad either. Yes, the score is dreadful and the dialogue sometimes painfully obvious, but Mr. Petersen and the screenwriter David Benioff take the ancient world and its notions of war seriously. Despite an odd pseudo-English accent (perhaps adopted in deference to the mostly British and Australian cast), Mr. Pitt plays Achilles with wit and charisma, turning the character into a kind of existentialist warrior rock star. Mr. Bana, as Achilles's Trojan counterpart and nemesis, Hector, has a brooding sensitivity that contrasts with Mr. Pitt's brashness. Some of the battle scenes have a vigorous old-time grandeur, and though it takes some inevitable liberties with the source material, the film is more astute about the political and moral complexities of war than most recent combat pictures (Scott).</p>
        <p>''VAN HELSING,'' starring Hugh Jackman and Kate Beckinsale. Written and directed by Stephen Sommers (PG-13, 125 minutes). A whole lot of monsters -- werewolves, a Frankenstein creation and, above all, Dracula, his three wives and several thousand potential bat-children -- roar and squirm in this long, grinding special-effects migraine. Mr. Sommers, who wrought similar havoc in ''The Mummy'' and ''The Mummy Returns,'' seems to be aiming for a kind of insouciant pop grandeur, something that will mix spookiness and spoofiness in spectacular fashion. But whatever visual and narrative wit there is (and there is a little) is crushed by the lumbering rhythms of the plot and the hectic, murky action sequences. Ms. Beckinsale is Dracula's ancestral nemesis, while Mr. Jackman, with none of the wired gravitas that was so effective in the ''X-Men'' movies, plays the title character, a centuries-old monster fighter with bad amnesia. Lucky him (Scott).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
