<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vacation Reading</title>
    <meta content="06LISTL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/06/books/review/06LISTL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1587053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DC133EF935A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="18273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vacation Reading</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vacation Reading</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of books recommended for vacation reading; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FICTION &amp; POETRY  ABSOLUTE FRIENDS. By John le Carré. (Little, Brown, $26.95.) Le Carré's novel returns to the cold-war stomping grounds of Germany and Eastern Europe, but with the fall of the Berlin Wall his espionage counterparts, an English expatriate and a German radical who found their ''natural art form'' in spying, are trying to redefine their idealism and reignite their passions over the invasion of Iraq.</p>
        <p>ALOFT. By Chang-rae Lee. (Riverhead, $24.95.) The newer developments of Long Island, and the optimistic (if also ambivalent and cautionary) tale of self-made American rising, provide the conditions for Lee's third novel, whose affable, ingratiating hero, Jerry Battle (descended from Battaglias), approaches his 60th birthday with a gift for affable contentment that is also his deepest flaw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This list of notable books has been selected from reviews since the Holiday Books issue of December 2003. Book titles are linked to their original reviews.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FICTION &amp; POETRY  ABSOLUTE FRIENDS. By John le Carré. (Little, Brown, $26.95.) Le Carré's novel returns to the cold-war stomping grounds of Germany and Eastern Europe, but with the fall of the Berlin Wall his espionage counterparts, an English expatriate and a German radical who found their ''natural art form'' in spying, are trying to redefine their idealism and reignite their passions over the invasion of Iraq.</p>
        <p>ALOFT. By Chang-rae Lee. (Riverhead, $24.95.) The newer developments of Long Island, and the optimistic (if also ambivalent and cautionary) tale of self-made American rising, provide the conditions for Lee's third novel, whose affable, ingratiating hero, Jerry Battle (descended from Battaglias), approaches his 60th birthday with a gift for affable contentment that is also his deepest flaw.</p>
        <p>THE AMATEUR MARRIAGE. By Anne Tyler. (Knopf, $24.95.) An ambitious exploration of domestic dislocation, ranging over 60 years of American experience, beginning with the marriage of Tyler's two ''amateurs,'' thrown together after the attack on Pearl Harbor.</p>
        <p>APPRENTICE TO THE FLOWER POET Z. By Debra Weinstein. (Random House, $23.95.) A deliciously nasty first novel featuring a great fraud of a poet (Z.) who seeks perfection of the life, leaving her work to be done by the book's real heroine, Annabelle Goldsmith, Z.'s apprentice and dogsbody, who eventually researches and even writes Z.'s poems.</p>
        <p>BANDBOX. By Thomas Mallon. (Pantheon, $24.95.) At the center of this novel, set in a Hecht-and-MacArthur universe of curmudgeonly editors, swell dames and shimmering watering holes, two glossy magazines wage a circulation war in the twilight of the pre-Depression era.</p>
        <p>THE BIRTH OF VENUS. By Sarah Dunant. (Random House, $21.95.) A witty, ingenious historical novel whose heroine avoids taking guff from Florentine male chauvinists of the late quattrocento by falling in love with art, artists and gossip; she companionably marries a nice old guy who really goes in for fellows, while she eventually hides as a Dominican nun.</p>
        <p>BLUE HORSE DREAMING. By Melanie Wallace. (MacAdam/Cage, $23.) A first novel that turns on Indian captivity (as other novels have done, notably works by Fenimore Cooper and Thomas Berger, so well the subject fits ''modern'' themes of isolation and identity loss). Its heroine, Abigail Buwell, is ''redeemed'' from a life she infinitely prefers to 19th-century Western civ.</p>
        <p>THE BODY OF JONAH BOYD. By David Leavitt. (Bloomsbury, $23.95.) A charmingly acerbic novel about a psychology professor's family, their secretary and their vortex of a house that attracts inexplicable affection and mystery, including the disappearance of a precious manuscript on Thanksgiving of 1969.</p>
        <p>BY SORROW'S RIVER: The Berrybender Narratives, Book 3. By Larry McMurtry. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $26.) FOLLY AND GLORY: The Berrybender Narratives, Book 4. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) This disjointed family of English aristocrats finish their trek across the American West in these novels, at the center of which stands Tasmin Berrybender, a sharp lass with impulsive appetites.</p>
        <p>CITY BOY. By Jean Thompson. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.) A rising young couple (he a writer, she a beautiful but troubled banker) move into a Chicago apartment to discover their neighbor upstairs is a stoner kid with an almighty loud reggae blaster and other bad habits; before long, his hippie antinomianism begins to corrupt the lives below him.</p>
        <p>CODEX. By Lev Grossman. (Harcourt, $24.) This entertaining novel (the author's second) concerns a young investment banker who (improbably) agrees to catalog a duke's library and ferret out a lost 14th-century book. Along the way, he -- and we -- learn a lot about bibliographic entries and entities, as well as how to derive plots from computer games.</p>
        <p>THE CONFESSIONS OF MAX TIVOLI. By Andrew Sean Greer. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $23.) Dorian Gray would have understood: Max Tivoli's misfortune in this fantastic novel is to be born with the appearance of a 70-year-old man, and to regress methodically through his life to physiological babyhood. This is a hard fate, but it does enable Max to woo the same woman three times, at suitable intervals, without being recognized as the same man.</p>
        <p>THE CONFUSION: Volume 2 of the Baroque Cycle. By Neal Stephenson. (Morrow, $27.95.) Part 2 of Stephenson's projected historical epic novel is as rollicking and overstuffed as its predecessor, ''Quicksilver,'' featuring the return of Jack Shaftoe, the world-renowned ''King of the Vagabonds,'' and the beautiful Eliza, now a French duchess and spymistress at the court of Louis XIV.</p>
        <p>THE DEW BREAKER. By Edwidge Danticat. (Knopf, $22.) Short stories by a Haitian-American writer who has pungently portrayed the distress and torment of the Haitian people both in this country and in their homeland. The title story of this collection describes an agent of the 1960's dictator François Duvalier waiting for a political victim, arresting him, torturing him, then murdering him at last.</p>
        <p>DOT IN THE UNIVERSE. By Lucy Ellmann. (Bloomsbury, paper, $13.95.) A cheerfully subversive novel whose heroine, Dot, an inconspicuous wifey in an English seaside town, acquires a taste for blood in an accident and takes to wiping folk out, including herself; after a spell in hell, she is reborn to an American family, but retains, for social observation and comment, all her British powers of snideness.</p>
        <p>DOUBLE VISION. By Pat Barker. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $23.) Barker's latest novel describes a single English winter in the lives of a handful of interconnected characters, starting with Kate, a newly widowed sculptor, and the sinister young man who becomes her assistant after she is disabled in a car crash. He in turn is a former lover of a 19-year-old girl who is now involved with a foreign correspondent who was working with Kate's husband when he died.</p>
        <p>EMMA BROWN: A Novel From the Unfinished Manuscript by Charlotte Brontë. By Clare Boylan. (Viking, $25.95.) A novelist steeped in Brontëana shrewdly develops the characters and ideas of two original chapters into a story of a passionate, reform-minded woman cramped by hypocrisy and convention.</p>
        <p>EVERYTHING WILL BE ALL RIGHT. By Tessa Hadley. (Holt, $24.) Hadley is a British novelist mesmerized by the perpetual turbulence of domestic arrangements; here, the correspondences and frictions of about 50 years emerge over three generations of daughters as they feel their way toward adulthood, each one mimicking and refracting the experiences of those who went before.</p>
        <p>EVERY TIME I TALK TO LISTON. By Brian DeVido. (Bloomsbury, $22.95.) A novel set deep in the world of professional boxing, by a sportswriter and former Golden Gloves fighter; in it, a heavyweight sparring partner, Amos (Scrap Iron) Fletcher, is betrayed in Las Vegas, crosses the continent to recuperate and returns, musing throughout on Sonny Liston, a fighter some fans consider a supremely gifted all-time great who has never received due recognition.</p>
        <p>THE FOUNTAIN AT THE CENTER OF THE WORLD. By Robert Newman. (Soft Skull, paper, $14.95.) This frisky political novel by a British comedian concerns resistance to international capitalism's world empire and stars two brothers who have never met; one is a corporate shark who manipulates consciousness, the other an inept eco-terrorist.</p>
        <p>GHOSTFIRES. By Keith Dixon. (St. Martin's, $23.95.) Dixon's first novel is a fierce and intimate snapshot of a wealthy family's self-destruction, aided by addictions (drugs, booze, status) perfect for corrupting physically and spiritually.</p>
        <p>GRACELAND. By Chris Abani. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $24.) Abani's protagonist, Elvis Oke, lives in a slum near Lagos, Nigeria, where the poor pick on the extremely poor, violence is ubiquitous and justice rare. The author was arrested in 1985, when he was 18, in connection with a politically dangerous novel he had written two years earlier.</p>
        <p>THE GRANDMOTHERS: Four Short Novels. By Doris Lessing. (HarperCollins, $23.95.) A collection of novellas that reflects the panoply of subjects, styles and literary modes that Lessing has commanded for more than 50 years, including a political allegory and a London social drama of class and race.</p>
        <p>THE HAMILTON CASE. By Michelle de Kretser. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) A beguiling, multilayered novel that spans much of the 20th century, shifting its point of view several times; its primary action bears on the murder of a white man in Ceylon (now Sri Lanka) and the history, both family and personal, of Sam Obeysekere, an upper-class Sinhalese lawyer whose analysis of the crime is crucial but does nothing to advance his prospects.</p>
        <p>HARD REVOLUTION. By George Pelecanos. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) Derek Strange, African-American cop turned private investigator, is the hard-boiled hero through whom Pelecanos has filtered his knowledge of the unfortunate victims and nearly as unlucky perpetrators of crime in Washington. This volume, a kind of prequel, flashes back to Derek at 12, then yields to a family tragedy in 1968, amplified by the fury of the Martin Luther King riots.</p>
        <p>THE HAVANA ROOM. By Colin Harrison. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $24.) Bill Wyeth, hero of this thriller-cum-social-satire novel, is a rising young New York lawyer and master of the universe when an accident ruins his prospects; disgraced and out of work, he becomes involved in a peculiar real estate deal and (eventually) in a subterranean private bar, the Havana Room, where strange goings-on go on.</p>
        <p>HOTTENTOT VENUS. By Barbara Chase-Riboud. (Doubleday, $24.) A powerful, earnest historical novel that humanizes the indignities endured by Sarah Baartman, a young woman from South Africa's Eastern Cape who was lured to Europe in 1810 and displayed as a scientific oddity and a sideshow curiosity -- even after her death in 1816.</p>
        <p>ICELAND'S BELL. By Halldor Laxness. (Vintage International, paper, $15.) Originally published in Icelandic in the 1940's, this novel by Iceland's sole Nobel laureate is a fabulistic tale of two heroes: Jon Hreggvidsson, a scoundrel, scapegrace and candidate for hanging, and Arni Arnaeus, who devotes his life and resources to the discovery and preservation of Iceland's medieval manuscripts.</p>
        <p>IRA FOXGLOVE. By Thomas McMahon. (Brook Street, $21.95.) A darkly genial novella, discovered among McMahon's papers a year or so after his death in 1999; set around an amateur inventor whose projects include a device to assist a failing heart -- and who happens to suffer from a bum ticker himself -- this work, early as it may be, has the same loopy charm as McMahon's other published fiction.</p>
        <p>THE JANE AUSTEN BOOK CLUB. By Karen Joy Fowler. (Marian Wood/Putnam, $23.95.) An ambitious comic novel that is more about how to read than about book groups or Jane Austen; all the members have different, private Austens, and their proprietary attitudes speak to the improbability that any two readers, or any two Janes, are alike.</p>
        <p>A KIND OF FLYING: Selected Stories. By Ron Carlson. (Norton, paper, $15.95.) Each of these 33 stories can take the reader off guard between Carlson's skills and his imagination; ''Plan B for the Middle Class,'' for instance, on the surface a story about a married couple's first vacation without their children, grows to become the recollection of the narrator's romantic coming-of-age.</p>
        <p>THE LIBERATED BRIDE. By A. B. Yehoshua. (Harcourt, $27.) A dark and comic novel that presents the two worlds of Israel's two nations, the Jews and the Arabs, and the travels in both of them by an Israeli professor whose magnificent obsession, for five years so far, is with trying to find out why his son's marriage to a rich young woman failed to endure.</p>
        <p>LINKS. By Nuruddin Farah. (Riverhead, $24.95.) Farah, a Somali novelist living in South Africa, explores his homeland's disintegration by sending his protagonist, Jeebleh, back to Somaliland, where he tries to find his mother's grave and rescue a kidnapped girl; menace succeeds menace so densely Jeebleh is soon possessed by a spirit of violent vengeance.</p>
        <p>LITTLE BLACK BOOK OF STORIES. By A. S. Byatt. (Knopf, $21.) Five scary Gothic tales that are also meditations on art and its place in a world where the mere appearance of a horrible creature can make one woman grow up a child psychologist, another a storyteller; or where a woman is literally transformed into stone in a gritty manner that out-Ovids Ovid.</p>
        <p>LITTLE CHILDREN. By Tom Perrotta. (St. Martin's, $24.95.) This novel of adultery and child-raising in a generic suburb is an outstanding contribution to the literature of Bad Mommy and Bad Daddy; its families are hothouses of boredom and everyone dreams of escape, if only to a new environment that is much the same as its predecessor.</p>
        <p>LOVE AND HYDROGEN: New and Selected Stories. By Jim Shepard. (Vintage Contemporaries, paper, $13.) PROJECT X. By Jim Shepard. (Knopf, $20.) A story collection and a novel by an author who applies a lapidary style to outlandish subjects; the stories often dwell on characters near collapse, like German fighter pilots flying deathtraps or a collector whose bubble gum cards become hallucinations. ''Project X'' considers the half-demented, perpetually embarrassed world of early adolescence in a sensitive examination of the Columbine phenomenon.</p>
        <p>LOVING CHE. By Ana Menéndez. (Atlantic Monthly, $22.) A deft first novel that captures, in an unnamed narrator's journeys to Cuba in search of the mother she never knew, the shifting sense of identity in the now mythic early days of Cuba's revolution and the desperate reality that has since set in.</p>
        <p>THE LUCKY ONES. By Rachel Cusk. (Fourth Estate/HarperCollins, $24.95.) Five loosely linked narratives purporting to be a novel, by an English writer; the first story is a brutal account of a convict in the last stages of pregnancy, and the long concluding pair devastate the reader with characters nobody could love and marriages nobody should have entered into.</p>
        <p>THE MADONNA OF EXCELSIOR. By Zakes Mda. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $23.) The author, a South African playwright as well as novelist, conducts his story, which concerns forbidden sexual relations and their consequences, in a voice that is humorous, wry and generous, never softening the brutality visited on blacks but never denying the humanity of the oppressors as well as of the oppressed.</p>
        <p>MY FATHER'S FIGHTER. By Ronald K. Fried. (Permanent Press, $24.) This boxing novel explores character rather than fistology through a private-school English teacher, Vincent Rosen, a twerp who inherits the management of a hypochondriacal light heavyweight. Eventually, proximity to menace proves good for Rosen's mental health, though the novel is surprisingly pitiless beneath a therapeutic gloss.</p>
        <p>NO MATTER HOW MUCH YOU PROMISE TO COOK OR PAY THE RENT YOU BLEW IT CAUZE BILL BAILEY AIN'T NEVER COMING HOME AGAIN. By Edgardo Vega Yunqué. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) A roomy novel full of colorful characters soaked in the ethnic stew of New York; families and cultures are linked in the precocious Vidamía Farrell and her search for her father, a pianist who lost two fingers in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>NOTHING LOST. By John Gregory Dunne. (Knopf, $24.95.) This final novel by a writer who could do anything well (usually in a belligerent mode) concerns a black drifter in a Plains state, two men who killed him, a supermodel and several lawyers, all of whom seem to have secrets; few of them are still standing at the end of the day.</p>
        <p>OUR KIND. By Kate Walbert. (Scribner, $23.) A novel in stories, collectively narrated by women who came of age before 1960, the last educated generation to miss out on feminism; to know that the natural order made career and family incompatible; to choose, almost exclusively, motherhood. Now they are about to die off in a novel that zealously and successfully grapples with the passage of time.</p>
        <p>POMPEII. By Robert Harris. (Random House, $24.95.) The hero of Harris's latest imaginative -- and prodigiously researched -- reconstruction of the past doesn't have time for sentimental musings about the meaning of civilization; a hydraulic engineer, he's too busy investigating the systemic failure of the water system in the days leading up to the cataclysmic eruption of Mount Vesuvius.</p>
        <p>PORT MUNGO. By Patrick McGrath. (Knopf, $24.) This immensely clever, tautly composed novel concerns a Gauguinistic artist who flees the suffocating confines of London for New York, then Havana, then Port Mungo, at the end of world and mind, where his genius flourishes. Unless it doesn't, since we learn that the narrator of all this is quite unreliable and full of hidden purpose.</p>
        <p>A QUESTION OF BLOOD. By Ian Rankin. (Little, Brown, $22.95.) Rankin's 14th novel (the first was published in 1987) about Inspector John Rebus adheres fairly closely to the procedural formula, though its author sometimes cites the perceptions of the Rolling Stones. This time around, Rebus himself is in trouble for being seen drinking with a man who turns up the following day as a murder victim.</p>
        <p>REMEMBER ME. By Trezza Azzopardi. (Grove, $23.) A suitably memorable British novel whose focus is Lillian, a vagrant old woman upstairs in an empty room. Nearly all she ever had has been taken from her, starting before World War II, and as her story is slowly unearthed from the bogs of East Anglia, loss itself becomes the subject of meditation.</p>
        <p>THE RULES OF ENGAGEMENT. By Anita Brookner. (Random House, $23.95.) Brookner's 22nd novel arrives, regular as clockwork and twice as delicate. Steeped in the moral codes of just yesteryear, two Englishwomen (one called Elizabeth, the other Betsy), childhood friends born in 1948, putter in their rooms and in their lives until, surprisingly, each of them has an affair with the same married man. It does not turn out well.</p>
        <p>SEPHARAD. By Antonio Muñoz Molina. (Harcourt, $27.) An alarming novel whose elusive narrator seems to tell a large but arbitrary selection of all Spain's dislocation stories, from the expulsion of the Jews onward; the author acknowledges his intention to memorialize all the ''lives that deserve to be told'' lest they ''fade from memory as if they had never existed.''</p>
        <p>SHOOTING THE SUN. By Max Byrd. (Bantam, $23.95.) Science fiction meets the Wild West in this ingenious novel about an expedition in 1840, organized by a beautiful young Francophile American astronomer, to photograph an eclipse of the sun, predicted by an early computing machine of the English savant Charles Babbage.</p>
        <p>THE SINGING. By C. K. Williams. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $20.) Williams's ninth collection of poems (a National Book Award winner last year) exhibits the exacting ethical scrutiny he has long applied to the world before him and the world within; he is able to ask whether poetry is worth writing and to conclude that it is, provided what it speaks is the truth.</p>
        <p>THE SLEEPING FATHER. By Matthew Sharpe. (Soft Skull, paper, $14.) Sharpe's second novel rotates the point of view among the members of the Schwartz family of suburban Connecticut; of these, our primary guide is Chris, a bitterly intelligent boy rolling bored through high school. He contains the family's emotion by simple commentary: ''Anyone who didn't embrace irony was a fool, because whether you embrace irony or not, sooner or later irony embraces you.''</p>
        <p>SOME HOPE: A Trilogy. By Edward St. Aubyn. (Open City, paper, $14.95.) Part comedy of manners, part chamber of horrors, these linked autobiographical novellas, set in the loftiest echelons of the British upper class, demonstrate that deep chemical dissolution and crisp Savile Row tailoring need not be conflicting imperatives.</p>
        <p>A SPECTACLE OF CORRUPTION. By David Liss. (Random House, $24.95.) Benjamin Weaver, the ruffian for hire introduced in ''A Conspiracy of Paper,'' is back, caught in the roil of 18th-century English politics and accused of murder to boot: he wants you to know he's been framed.</p>
        <p>THE STORIES OF RICHARD BAUSCH. (HarperCollins, $29.95.) The stirrings of the male heart and soul are the matter of Bausch's stories. In ''Valor,'' for example, a man acts heroically when a school bus crashes, then goes home to his wife, who has decided to leave. But his noble deed retains its nobility and enables him to reach over and touch her shoulder. It's not much, but it isn't nothing.</p>
        <p>THE STRANGE HOURS TRAVELERS KEEP. By August Kleinzahler. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.) Complex, cognitive poetry by a writer who might be called a postmodern metaphysical poet when his poems spring from a conceit deftly played out; in this collection we accompany him en route as he writes loving, reflective odes and epistles from modern life.</p>
        <p>THE STRANGER AT THE PALAZZO D'ORO: And Other Stories. By Paul Theroux. (Houghton Mifflin, $25.) Sexual awakening (not necessarily at the right time or for the right object) is a constant in this rather clinical collection of a novella (which centers on an aging countess whose vanity demands the perpetual service of a young lover) and three short stories about older men ruined by inopportune attacks of desire.</p>
        <p>THERE ARE JEWS IN MY HOUSE. By Lara Vapnyar. (Pantheon, $17.95.) This first collection of stories, by a woman who immigrated from the Soviet Union in 1994, chiefly concerns the perceptions of children trying to figure out what adults are up to. They half know and half understand the grown-up world but prefer their own consciousness of exploration and wonder.</p>
        <p>TRANSMISSION. By Hari Kunzru. (Dutton, $24.95.) A fast-paced up-to-date British novel whose protagonist, a shy young computer programmer in India, moves to America, where he finds the demand for his services far less than he had supposed; thwarted at work (and in love also), he launches a killer computer virus in the hope of becoming a hero by ultimately stopping it. Rotten idea.</p>
        <p>TRIOMF. By Marlene van Niekerk. (Overlook, $25.95.) Published 10 years ago in South Africa, ''Triomf'' is a comic triumph, featuring a burned-out family of Afrikaner Snopeses in flight from democratic changes; their easygoing brutality and prejudice are often mingled with startling tenderness and love, much as happens in real life.</p>
        <p>TROUBLE IN MIND: Poems. By Lucie Brock-Broido. (Knopf, $23.) The inner landscape of a poet who has seemed to allegorize her own life has become northern, bleak, full of negation; the book appears to circle obsessively about its griefs as the poet's incantations are directed toward death and the diminished self; elegy and epitaph abound.</p>
        <p>TRUE NORTH. By Jim Harrison. (Grove, $24.) David Burkett -- scion of a wealthy logging dynasty, narrator of this novel and son of a crooked, nympholeptic father -- inhabits a morass of guilt and self-loathing, all wrapped up in a grim comic struggle between his better self and an Oedipal fancy of killing his father.</p>
        <p>THE WINEMAKER'S DAUGHTER. By Timothy Egan. (Knopf, $24.95.) This first novel by Egan, a Pulitzer Prize-winning correspondent for The Times, revolves around a beautiful, feisty woman charged with saving her aging father's Pacific Northwest vineyard, set against a backdrop of beautifully captured settings and equally serious issues (river ecology, Indian land rights, water rights).</p>
        <p>WOLVES OF THE CALLA: The Dark Tower V. By Stephen King. Illustrated by Bernie Wrightson. (Donald M. Grant/Scribner, $35.) The epic Mid-World fantasy that King began in 1970 resumes its everything-but-the-kitchen-sink storytelling enthusiasm, as the trekking ''ka-tet'' (roughly, those joined by destiny) defends Calla Bryn Sturgis, a village teeming with twins.</p>
        <p>YOU HAVE TO BE CAREFUL IN THE LAND OF THE FREE. By James Kelman. (Harcourt, $25.) Jeremiah Brown, Kelman's hero in this novel, is a down-and-outer, authority hater and epic drinkist. Brought up Glaswegian, he has lived in the United States for 12 years and acquired the analytical powers that make this paranoid performance, set mainly in bars, a brilliant gloss on the political and social reverberations of 9/11 in this country.</p>
        <p>NONFICTION  THE ACCIDENTAL CONNOISSEUR: An Irreverent Journey Through the Wine World. By Lawrence Osborne. (North Point/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $24.) A journalist who is knowledgeable about wine feigns ignorance to patrol the grounds of the makers and promoters of wine, inviting them to say pretentious things and quibble about nonexistent distinctions; he uses his encounters to tell us how the righteous stuff is really made.</p>
        <p>ACQUAINTED WITH THE NIGHT: A Parent's Quest to Understand Depression and Bipolar Disorder in His Children. By Paul Raeburn. (Broadway, $24.95.) In this harrowing memoir, forged out of the disintegration of Raeburn's family and encounters with an obtuse mental health system, the author seems in the end as much a victim as anyone, caught up in the same anxiety-producing system as his children.</p>
        <p>AFTER SUCH KNOWLEDGE: Memory, History, and the Legacy of the Holocaust. By Eva Hoffman. (PublicAffairs, $25.) Hoffman, born to Holocaust survivors in Poland in 1945, renders the catastrophe as it is revealed to members of a generation drastically affected by events they cannot themselves remember, filtered through the memories of their elders and their vastly diverse experiences since the end of the war.</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF SHAKESPEARE. By Frank Kermode. (Modern Library, $21.95.) A characteristically lucid study by a critic and scholar whose overview of Tudor politics and English Christianity serves as background to the breathtaking development of English drama from nothing much to the heights of Shakespeare in less than a generation.</p>
        <p>ALEXANDER HAMILTON. By Ron Chernow. (Penguin Press, $35.) Everyone knows how Hamilton died, but who can truly recall his pre-Weehawken years? (If you can't, you are encouraged to blame Jefferson and Adams, who energetically swept their rival into the dustbin of history.) Hamilton wrote a treatise on the proper bathing of children, for one thing; he created American capitalism for another.</p>
        <p>ALFRED KAZIN'S AMERICA: Critical and Personal Writings. Edited by Ted Solotaroff. (HarperCollins, $29.95.) A large (540 pages) collection from more than 50 years of work by a polymathic critic, comfortable in his outsider status, who developed at length the theory that American literature was a long-term search for an ever-receding God.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MAFIA: A History of Its Rise to Power. By Thomas Reppetto. (John Macrae/ Holt, $26.) A smart, reasoned study, by the president of the Citizens Crime Commission of New York, of the ascendancy of Italian-American organized crime, from a few bad-guy Italian immigrants in the late 19th century to the Kefauver Committee hearings in the early 1950's.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN SUCKER. By David Denby. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) The midlife crisis that led to an even greater financial one for Denby, an amateur investor and film critic for The New Yorker, is presented as a cautionary tale, a mix of lacerating confessions about his love life and meditations on capitalism, conspicuous consumption and the psychological roots of greed.</p>
        <p>THE ANATOMY OF HOPE: How People Prevail in the Face of Illness. By Jerome Groopman. (Random House, $24.95.) Groopman, a physician and a writer for The New Yorker, derives from the surprising, often troubling stories of his patients the proposition that hope itself is a kind of vital organ that needs mindful handling in negotiations between doctor and patient.</p>
        <p>BETTER THAN SANE: Tales From a Dangling Girl. By Alison Rose. (Knopf, $23.) In a memoir of loopy, priceless observations, Rose trips lightly through a succession of ex-boyfriends and brief careers, including her arrival at The New Yorker in the 1980's, where she was transformed from receptionist (and resident femme fatale) to full-fledged writer.</p>
        <p>BIRTH OF THE CHESS QUEEN: A History. By Marilyn Yalom. (HarperCollins, $24.95.) A wide-ranging exploration of the origins of chess and of its most powerful piece, the queen. Chess was once queenless, and Yalom attributes the queen's arrival and empowerment to the rising status in medieval Europe of women like Toda of Navarre, Blanche of Castile and Eleanor of Aquitaine.</p>
        <p>BLUE BLOOD. By Edward Conlon. (Riverhead, $26.95.) A sprawling, wry, improbable memoir by a New York City police officer with a Catholic education followed by a Harvard one; his family tree is full of cops, but he chose his career to avoid suits and commutes. What he got was a life full of incident and time to meditate on his observations.</p>
        <p>THE BOOKSELLER OF KABUL. By Asne Seierstad. (Little, Brown, $19.95.) A detailed account of a four-month stay in 2002 by Seierstad, a Norwegian journalist, with an Afghan bookstore owner and his family. The picture of the bookseller that emerges is one of a public liberal intellectual and a private tyrant.</p>
        <p>THE BRASS WALL: The Betrayal of Undercover Detective #4126. By David Kocieniewski. (Holt, $25.) A harrowing story, by a Times reporter, of an undercover detective who infiltrates the mob in the Bronx neighborhood of Throgs Neck, only to have his cover blown -- and his life jeopardized -- by a fellow detective.</p>
        <p>THE BRONTË MYTH. By Lucasta Miller. (Knopf, $26.95.) In a book about biography as much as about the Brontës, Miller surveys the mythification of the three brilliant bad-luck sisters on the blasted heath of Yorkshire as a growth industry, a process of romantic adoption and transformation that started while Charlotte, the last to die, was still on the scene.</p>
        <p>A CONTINENT FOR THE TAKING: The Tragedy and Hope of Africa. By Howard W. French. (Knopf, $25.) There is far more tragedy than hope in this memoir, by a reporter for The Times who covered West and Central Africa during the genocidal 1990's; there are also many villains here, not least among them, he argues, the United States.</p>
        <p>COOK: The Extraordinary Voyages of Captain James Cook. By Nicholas Thomas. (Walker, $28.) This life of Cook, by a professor of anthropology, concentrates less on Cook's feats of navigation and cartography, which were marvelous, than on the ambassador from Europe who probably produced more ''first contacts'' with exotic peoples than anyone else ever.</p>
        <p>THE CREATION OF THE MEDIA: Political Origins of Modern Communications. By Paul Starr. (Basic Books, $27.50.) A scholar's cautious, detailed, convincing account of the deliberate framing of information carriers, from cheap postage to privatized electronics (telegraph, telephone, radio) to saturation by movies, networks and magazines.</p>
        <p>DANCING WITH CUBA: A Memoir of the Revolution. By Alma Guillermoprieto. (Pantheon, $25.) In 1969 the author, then a 20-year-old Merce Cunningham dance student, took a teaching job in Castro's Cuba. She and Cuba did not get on; though she did her best, she found homosexual artists more appealing than Fidelista officials. She grew up to become not a dancer but a splendid reporter, and this book is a sagaciously observed view of her memories.</p>
        <p>DESIGN FOR LIVING. Alfred Lunt and Lynn Fontanne: A Biography. By Margot Peters. (Knopf, $30.) A concise, candid biography of the legendary acting team, their performances and their complex 55-year marriage that was all but indistinguishable from their stage shows.</p>
        <p>THE DEVIL'S PLAYGROUND: A Century of Pleasure and Profit in Times Square. By James Traub. (Random House, $25.95.) A history of the rising and falling and rising again of a corner of New York, perhaps the nation's most self-revising city, explaining why Bat Masterson doesn't drink there anymore but the Durst Organization does.</p>
        <p>THE DOCTORS' PLAGUE: Germs, Childbed Fever, and the Strange Story of Ignac Semmelweis. By Sherwin B. Nuland. (Norton, $21.95.) The setting: a 19th-century Viennese hospital. The conundrum: why were so many new mothers dying? The hero: a physician, now long forgotten, who in fingering the culprit (the unwashed hands of doctors scurrying from morgue to maternity ward) almost invented the germ theory of disease.</p>
        <p>EATS, SHOOTS &amp; LEAVES: The Zero Tolerance Approach to Punctuation. By Lynne Truss. (Gotham, $17.50.) A punctuation primer (the title derives from a joke about a sloppily edited natural history of the panda) by a British journalist more than a little irritated by lazy writers and superfluous apostrophes but still a fan of the ''dangerously habit-forming'' semicolon.</p>
        <p>EVIL: An Investigation. By Lance Morrow. (Basic Books, $24.) Morrow's thoughtful consideration of an age-old concept is organized around the events of Sept. 11, 2001, recognizing the need to understand those acts as evil, but ultimately insisting that the word belongs to a new ''metaphysics'' that affects not just individual fanatics but great nations, too.</p>
        <p>THE FABRIC OF THE COSMOS: Space, Time, and the Texture of Reality. By Brian Greene. (Knopf, $28.95.) The irreconcilable differences between the cornerstones of theoretical physics -- the general theory of relativity and quantum mechanics -- aren't easily visualized, but Greene ably presents the latest astronomical data to help us make sense of them.</p>
        <p>THE FAILURES OF INTEGRATION: How Race and Class Are Undermining the American Dream. By Sheryll Cashin. (PublicAffairs, $26.) Though she is an ''ambivalent integrationist'' suffering ''integration exhaustion,'' Cashin, a law professor at Georgetown, still sees merit in some existing public schools, and denounces the damage done to education by opponents of ''acting white.''</p>
        <p>FATHER JOE: The Man Who Saved My Soul. By Tony Hendra. (Random House, $24.95.) Hendra, a multifaceted satirical presence in America since the 1970's, shows another side in this account of an English Benedictine monk whose remarkable personal warmth and wisdom sustained his skill at passing God's love along to those who couldn't find it alone.</p>
        <p>FOR LOVE OF INSECTS. By Thomas Eisner. (Belknap/Harvard University, $29.95.) An absorbing story of Eisner's career as a professor of chemical ecology (a discipline he helped found), interwoven with a passionate celebration of his subject -- the lowly insect -- and countless did-you-know's from the world of entomology.</p>
        <p>FREEDOM JUST AROUND THE CORNER: A New American History, 1585-1828. By Walter A. McDougall. (HarperCollins, $29.95.) In the first of what will be a three-volume work, a Pulitzer Prize-winning historian discerns a special American talent for making it, supplied by living where constraints on conduct were few.</p>
        <p>HER HUSBAND: Hughes and Plath -- A Marriage. By Diane Middlebrook. (Viking, $25.95.) Middlebrook's interpretation of the irresistible Ted Hughes-Sylvia Plath story focuses on their union as a remarkable creative partnership, with each as the other's best critic, deeply connected from the moment they met at a party at Cambridge.</p>
        <p>HIDING THE ELEPHANT: How Magicians Invented the Impossible and Learned to Disappear. By Jim Steinmeyer. (Carroll &amp; Graf, $26.) A celebration of the genius, glamour and gargantuan egos of stage magic from the mid-1800's to the 1920's, by one of the creative minds behind many of the great illusionists of the last quarter-century.</p>
        <p>HIS BROTHER'S KEEPER: A Story From the Edge of Medicine. By Jonathan Weiner. (Ecco/HarperCollins, $26.95.) A cautionary tale about the promise and peril of biomedical research, in which a family of remarkable bold achievers attempts to create or discover a cure for one of their number who is faced with death from amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (Lou Gehrig's disease).</p>
        <p>IN THE COMPANY OF SOLDIERS: A Chronicle of Combat. By Rick Atkinson. (Holt, $25.) A vivid account of the major combat operations in Iraq that President Bush declared at an end on May 1, 2003; by a Pulitzer Prize-winning reporter embedded with the Army's 101st Airborne Division.</p>
        <p>THE ISLAND AT THE CENTER OF THE WORLD: The Epic Story of Dutch Manhattan and the Forgotten Colony That Shaped America. By Russell Shorto. (Doubleday, $27.50.) A history of the first multiethnic upwardly mobile society in America, tolerant (for 17th-century Dutch political reasons) toward religious dissenters, embryo capitalists and hard drinkers; from it arose the fantastic metropolis that drove Boston into the second rank of cities.</p>
        <p>JOHN CLARE: A Biography. By Jonathan Bate. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $40.) The author lays out a good amount of what's known about the strange and often wonderful life of an agricultural laborer turned Romantic poet who, while outliving his contemporaries (Byron, Shelley and Keats) spent better than a third of his life in an asylum.</p>
        <p>JUNG: A Biography. By Deirdre Bair. (Little, Brown, $35.) A comprehensive biography of the Swiss psychiatrist Carl Jung, all the more impressive because of the Jung family's iron grip on his archives; scrupulously fair to her subject, Bair, the author of biographies of Samuel Beckett, Anaïs Nin and Simone de Beauvoir, shows less interest in the content of Jung's ideas than in his life.</p>
        <p>LIFE ON THE OUTSIDE: The Prison Odyssey of Elaine Bartlett. By Jennifer Gonnerman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $24.) The hard life and times of a young mother of four who drew 20 to life for her first offense -- selling cocaine to an undercover police officer -- against New York's drug laws. She saw her children, who were 10, 6, 3 and 1, in prison visiting rooms for the next 16 years until she was pardoned; the author is a staff writer for The Village Voice.</p>
        <p>LUCIA JOYCE: To Dance in the Wake. By Carol Loeb Shloss. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) A fervent biography of James Joyce's talented but difficult daughter, vivid in its description of the experimental dance groups in 1920's Europe and of Lucia's encounters with modernism and surrealism.</p>
        <p>A MAN AFTER HIS OWN HEART: A True Story. By Charles Siebert. (Crown, $23.95.) In a popular-science inquiry that is driven by personal history -- his father's heart suffered from defective ''fly-wing muscle fibers'' -- a poet and essayist performs a deeply researched and reported tour of the human heart, including his own hypochondriacal relationship with his pump.</p>
        <p>THE MAN WHO WOULD BE KING: The First American in Afghanistan. By Ben Macintyre. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) A British journalist pursues, over several continents, the story of Josiah Harlan (1799-1871), Pennsylvania Quaker, soldier of fortune, autodidact surgeon, counterfeiter, dope smoker, Civil War cavalry officer (for the Union side), Central Asian suzerain and inspiration for the tale by Kipling, who had the unenviable job of making his subject's life appear humanly possible.</p>
        <p>MIND WIDE OPEN: Your Brain and the Neuroscience of Everyday Life. By Steven Johnson. (Scribner, $25.) A technologically oriented journalist surveys the work of scientists who study the contents of the skull, which are far more accessible than ever before, and have revealed that more things go on in the mind than even Freud supposed.</p>
        <p>MISSING MEN: A Memoir. By Joyce Johnson. (Viking, $24.95.) Johnson meditates on her lifelong engagement with a missing man, her maternal grandfather, who killed himself at 37. She shows herself repeatedly seeking out partners who, like her mother, grew up without fathers, starting in her own case with Jack Kerouac; and she makes this second-generation reaction sound psychologically plausible.</p>
        <p>NAME ALL THE ANIMALS: A Memoir. By Alison Smith. (Scribner, $24.) A painful memoir that portrays a family's grief at the accidental death of the author's teenage brother and the unhinging of the author's faith as she entertains the thought that some unknown sin of her own had provoked God to do this thing (she was 15 at the time).</p>
        <p>NATALIE WOOD: A Life. By Gavin Lambert. (Knopf, $25.95.) A wistful, humane, readable account, by a friend of the actress, that means to capture her as an intelligent, industrious performer and as a vulnerable woman, prone to depression and a superstitious fear of ''dark waters.''</p>
        <p>NEGRO LEAGUE BASEBALL: The Rise and Ruin of a Black Institution. By Neil Lanctot. (University of Pennsylvania, $34.95.) Lanctot, a University of Delaware historian, provides a prodigiously researched account of organized black baseball from 1933 through the early 60's, when social pressures forced the major-league owners to integrate.</p>
        <p>1912: Wilson, Roosevelt, Taft &amp; Debs -- the Election That Changed the Country. By James Chace. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.95.) A lively, engrossing history that sees the presidential election of 1912 -- all four of its principals versus one another -- as setting up the conflict between progressive idealism and conservative values that has played itself out ever since Roosevelt, who had crowned Taft, rose in rebellion against his own party.</p>
        <p>NO WOMAN NO CRY: My Life With Bob Marley. By Rita Marley with Hettie Jones. (Hyperion, $22.95.) In a moving if occasionally abstract memoir -- some tales are more summarized than told -- Rita Marley reports on how she survived life with the reggae hero Bob Marley, whom she married in 1966 and ceased to speak to in 1972, after his sexual arrangements and her Rastafarianism became hard for either to bear.</p>
        <p>ON PARADISE DRIVE: How We Live Now (and Always Have) in the Future Tense. By David Brooks. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) Brooks, an Op-Ed columnist for The New York Times, examines and classifies the American population with the tools of social anthropology, instant dichotomy and heroic generalization, using techniques he perfected in his previous book, ''Bobos in Paradise.''</p>
        <p>OUR FATHERS: The Secret Life of the Catholic Church in an Age of Scandal. By David France. (Broadway, $26.95.) France, who covered the pedophilia scandal for Newsweek, demands that both the priests and their victims be seen as people with faces, no two alike and no amorphous masses of perps and victims; this makes for a long book and sometimes an overwhelming one.</p>
        <p>OUR MOTHERS' WAR: American Women at Home and at the Front During World War II. By Emily Yellin. (Free Press, $26.) While the Greatest Generation was fighting in 1941-45, about 350,000 women served in American military units, and millions went to work in war industries. Yellin studies these women in primary sources and finds their competence and independence provoking much male resentment and persecution.</p>
        <p>THE OUTLAW SEA: A World of Freedom, Chaos, and Crime. By William Langewiesche. (North Point, $23.) An Atlantic Monthly writer reports from the empty three-fourths of the globe, where 40,000 merchant ships operate with virtually no oversight and hundreds of pirate attacks occur every year. His centerpiece is the Baltic ferry Estonia, which sank in minutes in 1994, killing 852.</p>
        <p>OVER THE EDGE OF THE WORLD: Magellan's Terrifying Circumnavigation of the Globe. By Laurence Bergreen. (Morrow, $27.95.) A superb real-life thriller about the voyagers who sailed west from Spain in 1519 and returned in 1522, having lost their captain, Magellan (whom no one liked anyhow), about 200 of their total crew of 260 and all but one of their five ships; with them they brought spices and the first true report on the size of the Pacific.</p>
        <p>PATHS OF DESIRE: The Passions of a Suburban Gardener. By Dominique Browning. (Scribner, $24.) Browning, the editor in chief of House &amp; Garden, struggles to impose her will over the effects of time and neglect on her suburban garden and her broken heart.</p>
        <p>PERFECTLY LEGAL: The Covert Campaign to Rig Our Tax System to Benefit the Super Rich -- and Cheat Everybody Else. By David Cay Johnston. (Portfolio, $25.95.) Johnston, a Pulitzer Prize-winning business and financial reporter for The Times, presents an eye-popping list of promising tax developments for some 13,400 households, or the richest hundredth of 1 percent; but the real scandal, Johnston shows, isn't what the rich don't pay, but what the rest of us now have to.</p>
        <p>THE PERFECT PRINCE: The Mystery of Perkin Warbeck and His Quest for the Throne of England. By Ann Wroe. (Random House, $35.) So how could anyone prove in 1491 that Perkin Warbeck was not the lawful king of England, one of the princes thought killed in the Tower of London by Richard III in 1483? This exciting, colorful book is packed with recreated cultural clues and the anxiety that went with belonging to the ruling classes in an age of dynastic shakeout.</p>
        <p>PLAN OF ATTACK. By Bob Woodward. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $28.) An unparalleled behind-the-scenes look at a most secretive administration's decision to invade Iraq and its struggle to contain a war that has found neither its promised justification nor an exit strategy.</p>
        <p>THE POLITICS OF TRUTH. Inside the Lies That Led to War and Betrayed My Wife's CIA Identity: A Diplomat's Memoir. By Joseph Wilson. (Carroll &amp; Graf, $26.) An engaging account of a foreign service career; Wilson, the top American diplomat in Baghdad before the first gulf war, condemns the latest war with Iraq and the politics of intimidation and personal destruction inside the Beltway.</p>
        <p>THE PRICE OF LOYALTY: George W. Bush, the White House, and the Education of Paul O'Neill. By Ron Suskind. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $26.) A persuasively detailed account of the forces driving the Bush White House, as described by former Treasury Secretary Paul O'Neill, from Saddam Hussein to tax-cut battles. Suskind, a Pulitzer Prize-winning journalist, says that in this administration, evidence and argument are routinely pushed aside when they get in the way of previously decided political outcomes.</p>
        <p>PULL ME UP: A Memoir. By Dan Barry. (Norton, $24.95.) Barry, who writes the About New York column for The Times, presents himself as an ordinary guy who just does prose. That's true in a way -- he grew up in ordinary Long Island in the 60's, with lots of Irish and 60's inhibitions, and it took him a long time to get a decent job -- but his voice is so natural its honesty seems beyond question.</p>
        <p>THE PYTHONS: Autobiography by the Pythons. By Graham Chapman, John Cleese, Terry Gilliam, Eric Idle, Terry Jones and Michael Palin with Bob McCabe. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $60.) A big, heavy, much illustrated oral biography of the dear mostly British lads who in the 1970's exerted the heaviest culture-changing clout since Mad Comics.</p>
        <p>QUEEN OF SCOTS: The True Life of Mary Stuart. By John Guy. (Houghton Mifflin, $28.) A biography, by a Cambridge historian, of a woman whose privileged existence (queen of Scots in infancy, wife of the French dauphin at 15, notably good-looking) went all agley through a series of unwise decisions and later marriages until her head was cut off to fortify the title of Elizabeth I of England.</p>
        <p>QUEER STREET. Rise and Fall of an American Culture, 1947-1985: Excursions in the Mind of the Life. By James McCourt. (Norton, $29.95.) A heroically imaginative account of gay metropolitan culture, an elegy and an apologia for a generation, steeped in opera, ballet, theater, all kinds of haute stuff, that is now sometimes held in contempt by the latest arrivals as a pathetic, self-hating, closeted crew.</p>
        <p>RATS: Observations on the History and Habitat of the City's Most Unwanted Inhabitants. By Robert Sullivan. (Bloomsbury, $23.95.) An urban Thoreau spends his nights in a Manhattan streetlet, gathering the lore of Rattus norvegicus and studying its ways, which if not showy are very successful.</p>
        <p>THE REAL THING: Truth and Power at the Coca-Cola Company. By Constance L. Hays. (Random House, $25.95.) A history of the company, by a business reporter for The Times, that pivots around a recurring image: that of a Coca-Cola boss obsessed with expanding the beverage's global reach.</p>
        <p>RED SKY AT MORNING: America and the Crisis of the Global Environment. By James Gustave Speth. (Yale University, $24.) A profoundly sobering study, by an environmental adviser to Presidents Carter and Clinton, of the nation's failure to address the probability of global warming both in the past, when there might have been time, and now, when there may not.</p>
        <p>REDS: McCarthyism in Twentieth-Century America. By Ted Morgan. (Random House, $35.) The demagogic career of a senator from Wisconsin is just part of Morgan's sweeping account of anti-Communist purges and Communist espionage that begins with America's involvement in the Russian Revolution and gallops through the birth of the New Left, Vietnam, Watergate and beyond.</p>
        <p>THE SECRET EPIDEMIC: The Story of AIDS and Black America. By Jacob Levenson. (Pantheon, $25.) In the fall of 2000, Levenson went to the South to see why black Americans were acquiring H.I.V. at seven times the white rate; he was stopped short by a tangled web of poverty, misinformation, crack use and the insufficiency of language to convey what its users really hope to say.</p>
        <p>SIDNEY POITIER: Man, Actor, Icon. By Aram Goudsouzian. (University of North Carolina, $29.95.) A grudging but well-researched biography of the groundbreaking performer who was forced to tread a fine line between black aspirations and white anxieties.</p>
        <p>SIR JOHN GIELGUD: A Life in Letters. Edited by Richard Mangan. (Arcade, $30.) What could they be but delightful, these 900-odd letters, dated 1912 to 1999, by an actor celebrated for his candor who took his art seriously indeed without letting it inhibit observation, gossip, generosity, snobbery or affection.</p>
        <p>SIR WALTER RALEIGH. By Raleigh Trevelyan. (John Macrae/Holt, $35.) A brisk yet careful biography of the notorious courtier to Queen Elizabeth and prototypical Renaissance man, with whom Trevelyan acknowledges a ''tenuous family connection,'' based on archival records not only in England but also in Spain and the United States.</p>
        <p>SOMETHING FROM THE OVEN: Reinventing Dinner in 1950s America. By Laura Shapiro. (Viking, $24.95.) A deliciously readable account of a dark decade in domestic gastronomy; Shapiro is at her best when profiling the writers -- Julia Child and Betty Friedan, among others -- whose instructive authority eventually improved home cooking.</p>
        <p>SONTAG &amp; KAEL: Opposites Attract Me. By Craig Seligman. (Counterpoint, $23.) An eager, confiding book, by an experienced writer and editor, about two widely discussed and influential critical icons who arose at the same historical moment (mid-1960's). They come to represent a quarrel, never explicit, between attitudes that Kael might call solemnity and that Sontag might call frivolity.</p>
        <p>A SPORTSWRITER'S LIFE: From the Desk of a New York Times Reporter. By Gerald Eskenazi. (University of Missouri, $29.95.) Thoughtful reflection upon Eskenazi's 41-year career at the newspaper, the sports luminaries he covered and the changing nature of sports journalism.</p>
        <p>STALIN: The Court of the Red Tsar. By Simon Sebag Montefiore. (Knopf, $30.) A British novelist and journalist, with access to previously secret private documents, presents a newly intimate portrait of the Soviet dictator who, despite the oceans of blood on his hands, was capable of tender, humane moments with family and friends.</p>
        <p>STRANGERS: Homosexual Love in the Nineteenth Century. By Graham Robb. (Norton, $26.95.) A brilliant work of social archaeology by a writer who comes to gay history by way of writing the lives of Rimbaud and Balzac; he has discovered that there were plenty of gay people way back when, that everybody knew this and that attitudes were not radically different from what they are now, though the criminal penalties could be a lot more severe.</p>
        <p>SWIMMING TO ANTARCTICA: Tales of a Long-Distance Swimmer. By Lynne Cox. (Knopf, $24.95.) An account of her own performances by a woman whose remarkable physiology (plus plenty of training) allows her to survive (though painfully) in water that would kill an ordinary person in minutes.</p>
        <p>TOUR OF DUTY: John Kerry and the Vietnam War. By Douglas Brinkley. (Morrow, $25.95.) A full-scale account of Kerry's perilous stint in Vietnam, his journey from war to peace and the risk-taking nature and sense of destiny that characterized his life before and after his military career.</p>
        <p>TRUTH &amp; BEAUTY: A Friendship. By Ann Patchett. (HarperCollins, $23.95.) A memoir of Patchett's 17-year friendship with Lucy Grealy, whose ''Autobiography of a Face'' explored her life-defining struggle with a disfiguring facial cancer. Using Grealy's vivid letters and her own spare prose, Patchett describes a complicated relationship of temperamental opposites.</p>
        <p>WATERFRONT: A Journey Around Manhattan. By Phillip Lopate. (Crown, $25.95.) A noted essayist is here a walker in the city -- or, more precisely, along its outer edges -- ruminating as he goes on the history, architecture and inhabitants of a water-ringed metropolis that until very lately was a bustling port.</p>
        <p>WORK AND OTHER SINS: Life in New York City and Thereabouts. By Charlie LeDuff. (Penguin Press, $24.95.) A blunt and touching collection of LeDuff's street vignettes, written for The Times, many of them spiked with the sadness and wit found only at the bar rails of New York's most notorious watering holes.</p>
        <p>THE WORKING POOR: Invisible in America. By David K. Shipler. (Knopf, $25.) A daring journalist's approach to one of the most intractable of all social subjects, the millions of Americans who work steadily but fail to escape upward into the middle class; he follows some of them with meticulous empathy for nearly seven years, while recognizing that extracting the poor from their poverty is far easier to desire than to accomplish.</p>
        <p>CRIME  THE BREATHTAKER. By Alice Blanchard. (Warner, $24.95.) Set in a region of rural Oklahoma known as Tornado Alley, this gale-force thriller charts the warped progress of a serial murderer who strikes only during tornadoes, rattling the chief of police and lending a macabre kick to the daredevil local custom of driving into the eye of a killer storm.</p>
        <p>DON'T LOOK BACK. By Karin Fossum. (Harcourt, $23.) The first of this Norwegian author's police procedurals to be published in the United States, this subtly horrifying crime story discreetly mourns the loss of innocence in a picturesque village at the edge of the sea when the naked body of a well-liked high school athlete is discovered on a mountain by a local child.</p>
        <p>DOUBLE PLAY. By Robert B. Parker. (Putnam, $24.95.) In a deeply felt and intimately told memory tale, Parker defends the ideals of a young Dodgers fan from Boston by sending out a hero named Joseph Burke to save Jackie Robinson from being killed by mobsters during the historic 1947 season, when he integrated major-league baseball.</p>
        <p>MEDUSA. By Michael Dibdin. (Pantheon, $23.) On a par with his superb Venetian mystery, ''Dead Lagoon,'' Dibdin's latest Aurelio Zen investigation takes the Italian cop into the mountainous district of the northern Dolomites, where the recovery of a soldier's desiccated corpse stirs up old political animosities.</p>
        <p>MR. PARADISE. By Elmore Leonard. (Morrow, $25.95.) Tone is the key to divining deception from reality in this novel, Leonard's 40th book, as the homicide detective Frank Delsa sorts out the murders of an ogre of a lawyer named Anthony Paradiso and a former prostitute caught in the middle of a contract hit on ''Mr. Paradise.''</p>
        <p>THE MURDER ROOM. By P. D. James. (Knopf, $25.95.) James's 12th Commander Dalgliesh mystery preserves the element of old-fashioned, hair-raising suspense as the dour poet-detective investigates the bizarre death of a museum trustee and pursues (but more cautiously) a new romantic relationship.</p>
        <p>THE NARROWS. By Michael Connelly. (Little, Brown, $25.95.) Harry Bosch's homicidal nemesis, the Poet, resurfaces in this murder marathon to give the retired California homicide cop an opportunity to work another case with the maverick F.B.I. agent Rachel Walling and to settle scores with characters from such past novels as ''Blood Work'' and ''The Poet.''</p>
        <p>SCIENCE FICTION  BROKEN ANGELS. By Richard K. Morgan. (Del Rey/ Ballantine, paper, $14.95.) Takeshi Kovacs, the all-but-indestructible galactic mercenary whom Morgan so memorably introduced in ''Altered Carbon,'' is back, this time on an archaeological dig that triggers a scam of truly cosmic proportions. Once again, Morgan breathes energy and authority into a post-human killing machine who suffers from an irrepressibly working conscience.</p>
        <p>FOR US, THE LIVING: A Comedy of Customs. By Robert A. Heinlein. (Scribner, $25.) Written and rejected in the late 1930's, this manuscript of Heinlein's first extended piece of writing went missing for over 60 years until its recent unearthing. More utopian tract than flesh-and-blood fiction, its most effective passages show Heinlein's uncanny knack for making the future feel like the present.</p>
        <p>KALPA IMPERIAL: The Greatest Empire That Never Was. By Angélica Gorodischer. (Small Beer Press, paper, $16.) These tales of an imaginary empire burst from the mouth of a storyteller whose meditations on power -- its acquisition, possession and loss -- elude easy paraphrase. Ursula K. Le Guin's translation of a work by a prominent Argentine writer elegantly articulates the shifting tones of the larger narrative, whose theme seems to be the endless imperfectibility of human society.</p>
        <p>THE SKINNER. By Neal Asher. (Tor/Tom Doherty, $26.95.) If every age gets the science fiction it deserves, what does Asher's frighteningly effective exercise in existential horror say about ours? Set on a planet whose evolutionary arena makes the jungles of Earth look like playgrounds, the story tracks a dead man who is bent on righteous revenge. Asher imagines an unrelentingly brutal future with such conviction that it carries the force of prophecy.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS  CHASING VERMEER. By Blue Balliett. Illustrated by Brett Helquist. (Scholastic, $16.95.) (Ages 10 and up) This imaginative mystery in the classic children's book tradition -- complete with codes and clues hidden in illustrations -- about the theft of a painting by Vermeer is set at the University of Chicago's Laboratory Schools.</p>
        <p>JACK AND THE SEVEN DEADLY GIANTS. By Sam Swope. Illustrated by Carll Cneut. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $16.) (Ages 7 to 10) A slapstick fairy tale in which Jack encounters seven giants who threaten the kingdom where he lives and embody the seven deadly sins; stylishly told and illustrated.</p>
        <p>MESSENGER. By Lois Lowry. (Walter Lorraine/Houghton Mifflin, $16.) (Ages 12 and up) Another short, spare novel of a utopia gone awry, by the author of ''The Giver,'' in which three young people from three coexisting dystopias must use their special powers and come together to save the world.</p>
        <p>MISS BRIDIE CHOSE A SHOVEL. By Leslie Connor. Illustrated by Mary Azarian. (Houghton Mifflin, $16.) (Ages 4 to 8) The story of an Irish immigrant who brought a shovel to America and used it in many ways throughout her long and productive life; well told and thoughtfully illustrated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
