<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA's New Eye on Sky To Watch Earth's Ozone</title>
    <meta content="06AURA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/06/science/earth/06aura.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1594662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aura (Satellite)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Observing System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vandenberg Air Force Base (Calif)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DA163BF935A35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA's New Eye on Sky To Watch Earth's Ozone</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">NASA's New Eye on Sky to Watch Earth's Ozone</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aura, last in series of major satellites that make up National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Earth Observing System, is awaiting launch from Vandenberg Air Force Base, California; is designed to monitor earth's ozone for next six years; craft will measure trace gases and pollutants and observe heat emission from earth and earth's atmosphere to help better understand global climate changes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NASA is about to launch a large satellite that will monitor the health of Earth's atmosphere in unprecedented detail, keeping daily track of everything from the upper ozone layer, which guards against solar radiation, to the air near the ground that people breathe.</p>
        <p>The $785 million mission is to be launched Saturday from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California. A Boeing Delta II rocket will send the 6,542-pound spacecraft into a 438-mile-high polar orbit. It is to scan the atmosphere for at least six years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NASA is about to launch a large satellite, named Aura, that will monitor the health of Earth's atmosphere in unprecedented detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NASA is about to launch a large satellite that will monitor the health of Earth's atmosphere in unprecedented detail, keeping daily track of everything from the upper ozone layer, which guards against solar radiation, to the air near the ground that people breathe.</p>
        <p>The $785 million mission is to be launched Saturday from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California. A Boeing Delta II rocket will send the 6,542-pound spacecraft into a 438-mile-high polar orbit. It is to scan the atmosphere for at least six years.</p>
        <p>The craft, named Aura, is the third and final addition to a series of major satellites making up NASA's Earth Observing System, an initial set of spacecraft designed to study all of the processes that affect the Earth's climate and weather. Terra, which monitors land-based processes, was launched in 1999; Aqua, which observes the oceans and water cycle of Earth, went up in 2002.</p>
        <p>These flagship spacecraft, joined by more than a dozen other satellites launched by the United States and several other nations, allow long-term studies of the factors that influence climate change, using many different instruments.</p>
        <p>The launching, said Dr. Ghassem R. Asrar, NASA's Earth Science director, ''is fundamentally a mission to understand and protect the very air we breathe.''</p>
        <p>In conjunction with the other climate observatories, Aura should make a major contribution to determining the causes, extent and consequences of global change, he said.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft carries four instruments that will survey the atmosphere from top to bottom, including monitoring ozone in its good and bad forms. In the upper atmosphere, ozone in the stratosphere provides a protective barrier to harmful ultraviolet radiation from the Sun. In the troposphere, the atmospheric layer that goes from the ground up to about six miles, ozone produced by combustion is a major pollutant in smog.</p>
        <p>Aura will monitor the upper ozone layer, including seasonal ''holes'' that open over arctic areas, to see if the layer is recovering after a worldwide ban on ozone-depleting chemicals like chlorofluorocarbons. Studies indicate that between 1980 and 2000, stratospheric ozone decreased 3 percent globally. The craft will detect levels of ozone-eating chemicals and such byproducts as chlorine and bromine, and also help distinguish between natural and human-caused sources of destructive gases.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft's ozone monitoring instrument, which also measures trace gases and pollutants important to air quality, will help scientists determine if there is any mixing between the ''good'' ozone in the stratosphere and the pollution variety nearer the ground. In addition, readings from Aura will examine the mechanisms in the atmosphere that clean pollution.</p>
        <p>Aura's other major job will be to track atmospheric chemicals and aerosol particles, including pollutants, to see how they mix and how they are transported from one area of the world to other regions. Aerosols from human and natural sources absorb or reflect solar energy based on their size, shape, color and chemical composition, and their effect on climate is largely unknown, experts said.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft will also track greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide and water vapor, which trap heat and contribute to global warming. In addition, it will observe heat emission from Earth's surface and atmosphere, day and night.</p>
        <p>Aura is to take on a new role later in its mission, when it becomes part of a planned fleet of Earth-observing satellites flying in a formation. Under the scheme, nicknamed the A Train because Aqua will lead the formation and Aura will bring up the rear, four other American and French satellites will fill the gap between the large spacecraft.</p>
        <p>Although on independent missions, the satellites will be positioned to pass over a region one after another, building a database of observations that should create a global picture of Earth's changing climate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
