<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Virginia man hopes his birdbath will create less buzz than other inventions. It kills mosquito eggs.</title>
    <meta content="05PATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/05/technology/05patent.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1594523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Patents"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riordan, Teresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Donald R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E4D61F38F936A35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Virginia man hopes his birdbath will create less buzz than other inventions. It kills mosquito eggs.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Way to Kill Mosquitoes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Teresa Riordan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riordan, Teresa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Donald R Hall patents several approaches he</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the threat of West Nile virus and the invasion of fierce Asian tiger mosquitoes in his neighborhood in Arlington, Va., Donald R. Hall was beginning to worry about his young granddaughter playing outside.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Hall, 60, who retired as an electromechanical engineer in the military and intelligence sectors to spend his days dreaming up inventions in his backyard skunk works, went on the offensive several years ago in the war against the mosquito.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A retired electromechanical engineer recently received a patent for a way to kill mosquito eggs rather than the mosquitoes themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the threat of West Nile virus and the invasion of fierce Asian tiger mosquitoes in his neighborhood in Arlington, Va., Donald R. Hall was beginning to worry about his young granddaughter playing outside.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Hall, 60, who retired as an electromechanical engineer in the military and intelligence sectors to spend his days dreaming up inventions in his backyard skunk works, went on the offensive several years ago in the war against the mosquito.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall recently received United States patent 6,708,443, a wide-ranging patent covering several approaches that he contends might help control mosquito populations across wide areas such as wetlands or regions in Africa where mosquito-borne illnesses like malaria are rampant. Most of Mr. Hall's approaches rely on the same principal: killing the mosquito eggs rather than the mosquitoes themselves.</p>
        <p>''They will breed in a bottle cap,'' Mr. Hall said. ''The idea is to interrupt the life cycle.''</p>
        <p>His first weapon: a birdbath. According to Mr. Hall, the birdbath, which can run on batteries, solar power or electricity, provides an attractive place for mosquito mothers to lay their eggs. (Under a microscope, the eggs resemble little clusters of beach balls floating on a raft.)</p>
        <p>Every few days a tiny computer chip embedded in the birdbath instructs a pump to flush the water out, pushing it through a fine-mesh filter. As the mosquito eggs go through the filter, they are crushed. Of course, some early bloomers may already have developed into larvae or nymphs. But since they are too young to fly and they don't really know how to swim, Mr. Hall said, they drown as they take the mosquito's equivalent of a whitewater rafting trip without a life vest.</p>
        <p>Another device Mr. Hall has invented is a shallow tray powered by what is known as a bimetal coil. As rainwater stagnates in the tray, which has a fine mesh at the bottom, it becomes an attractive spot for mosquitoes to deposit their eggs.</p>
        <p>The coil -- made of two different metals strapped together, each with different expansion and contraction rates -- expands as it warms during the day, pushing the mesh above the water line. The mesh captures the eggs, which bake in the sun during the day. In the evening, the coil cools and contracts, pulling the mesh back under the water, waiting for more unsuspecting mosquitoes to lay their eggs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall said such devices would require little or no maintenance and would be cheap to build, making them appealing for the developing world or for places where they would need to be distributed widely, such as wetlands.</p>
        <p>''You could give them away,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall is not the only inventor preoccupied with mosquitoes. In April, for example, Mary Robison, who lives in Missouri, patented a sticky mosquito trap whose main attraction is lactic acid, which humans secrete when they sweat.</p>
        <p>One invention already on the market is the Mosquito Magnet, a propane-powered device that mimics mammals by exhaling carbon dioxide. Then it sucks in mosquitoes which think they have just found a warm meal. But that product is relatively expensive, Mr. Hall points out, with models ranging from $195 to more than $1,200. And the propane tank must be changed every three weeks, at a cost of about $20. The Mosquito Magnet has garnered mixed reviews from customers on Internet sites that sell the device, like Amazon.com and Target.com.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Hall has not licensed any of his mosquito ideas. But he is busy at work on other projects, including a utopian-sounding plan for linking neighborhoods to communal hard drives on telephone poles, for which he received patent 6,402,031 two years ago. Which is not to say that the rest of the insect world is safe from his inventive zeal: percolating in his mind at the moment, he said, is a scheme involving cat food and bug zappers as a way to do in that other flying pest, the common housefly.</p>
        <p>Patents</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
