<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="15QNA.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/15/garden/15QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1596745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Garden Q&amp;A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1D7163AF936A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Troubleshooting Columbines</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Troubleshooting Columbines</p>
        <p>Q.  My columbines bloomed beautifully for weeks, but then their centers began to look stepped on, their long stems turned brown and their leaves yellowed. Some new leaves grew, but they soon yellowed, too. What can I do?</p>
        <p>A.  Becoming leggy, then dying back, is almost as common with these spring bloomers as the lacelike squiggles in the leaves caused by columbine leaf miners. Gardeners whose aging columbines will be hidden by other plants usually just ignore these developments. Others cut off the old growth and wait for good-looking new leaves, which usually stay healthy for quite a while.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>My columbines bloomed beautifully for weeks, but then their centers began to look stepped on, their long stems turned brown and their leaves yellowed. What can I do?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Troubleshooting Columbines</p>
        <p>Q.  My columbines bloomed beautifully for weeks, but then their centers began to look stepped on, their long stems turned brown and their leaves yellowed. Some new leaves grew, but they soon yellowed, too. What can I do?</p>
        <p>A.  Becoming leggy, then dying back, is almost as common with these spring bloomers as the lacelike squiggles in the leaves caused by columbine leaf miners. Gardeners whose aging columbines will be hidden by other plants usually just ignore these developments. Others cut off the old growth and wait for good-looking new leaves, which usually stay healthy for quite a while.</p>
        <p>But columbines are short-lived, and yours may simply be quitting. If plants are young and soil is poor, yellow leaves may mean hunger. Try a dose of liquid organic fertilizer. Wet soil and poor air circulation often lead to wilts and rots that can cause yellow leaves. Fungicides are not much help, but giving the plants breathing room, especially at ground level, may be enough to save them.</p>
        <p>Worst case is a virus disease like asters yellows or beet mosaic. These have no cure and spread easily, so it is important to destroy the plants, start new ones elsewhere and consider some different species. Big, bright hybrids like McKanna's Giant are the most widely offered. But there are dozens of others in a dazzling variety of colors and flower shapes. You can learn about them and get seeds by joining the North American Rock Garden Society, www.nargs .org. Unusual columbines are also sold by Joy Creek Nursery, (503) 543-7474 or www.joycreek.com.</p>
        <p>Winter's Deadly Return</p>
        <p>Q.  The hydrangeas that came with my house bloomed reliably for years but not this spring. What happened and what can I do?</p>
        <p>A.  Chances are your spring-blooming hydrangeas have the same problem as other readers' redbuds, roses, smoke bushes, daphnes, lavenders, roses, lambs ears, roses, creeping thymes, roses, oriental poppies, chrysanthemums and roses. Its name is winter kill, and you can be glad you didn't lose more.</p>
        <p>For several years, Northeastern winters were warmer than average in many places. Established trees and shrubs made lots of vulnerable new growth. Gardeners in Zones 4 and 5 had great success with plants that are better off in Zone 6.</p>
        <p>But last winter was average, and many places suffered a dearth of insulating snow. Nature does this occasionally in order to keep gardeners humble, and it is also a useful reminder that when scientists say ''global climate change,'' they mean a great deal more than a cozy promotion to the next hardiness zone.</p>
        <p>Too Much, Too Soon</p>
        <p>Q.  I have heard that you should put houseplants outside in summer, so last month I moved my prized waterlily begonias to the terrace. But their gorgeous green leaves immediately turned pale and blotchy. Now what?</p>
        <p>A.  Now you move them to a shadier spot and wait for new growth. Just as people whose winter garb approached total coverage should not bask in the first broiling sun clad only in bikinis, even light-loving indoor plants need time to get adjusted. And begonias are not light-loving. All they want is the dating relationship provided by dappled shade.</p>
        <p>Garden Q&amp;A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
