<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let the Design Sprint Begin</title>
    <meta content="11NOTE$22" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/11/garden/11NOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040312T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1565412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2012)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D7153EF932A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let the Design Sprint Begin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Let the Design Sprint Begin</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp Critic's Notebook appraises five proposals for Olympic Village used to bolster New York's bid for 2012 Olympics; photos; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE are five scenes from the buffed-up city yet to come. Perhaps never to come, alas. Five architecture teams have prepared designs for an Olympic Village, to be in Long Island City, Queens, to help New York win its bid to be host to the summer games in 2012. The designs were unveiled yesterday and will be on view for the next two weeks at Vanderbilt Hall in Grand Central Terminal. A winning design will be chosen in May. After that, who knows?</p>
        <p>Built by private developers, the Olympic Village would house 1,600 athletes during the games. Afterward, the complex would become middle-income housing. The site would occupy the southern portion of Queens West, the state-sponsored residential development across the East River from the United Nations headquarters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five architecture teams have prepared designs for an Olympic Village in Queens. Aesthetically, at least, the process is off to a good start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE are five scenes from the buffed-up city yet to come. Perhaps never to come, alas. Five architecture teams have prepared designs for an Olympic Village, to be in Long Island City, Queens, to help New York win its bid to be host to the summer games in 2012. The designs were unveiled yesterday and will be on view for the next two weeks at Vanderbilt Hall in Grand Central Terminal. A winning design will be chosen in May. After that, who knows?</p>
        <p>Built by private developers, the Olympic Village would house 1,600 athletes during the games. Afterward, the complex would become middle-income housing. The site would occupy the southern portion of Queens West, the state-sponsored residential development across the East River from the United Nations headquarters.</p>
        <p>The creative ambition of the teams is pitched at a high level, overall, and it must be said at the outset that this is an impressive achievement in itself. Whether New York is chosen over London, Paris and the six other contending cities, it says a good deal that a city agency has embraced architects of the caliber of Zaha Hadid, Thom Mayne, and the Dutch firm MVRDV. In this case, the agency is NYC2012, the outfit established for planning the Olympics bid.</p>
        <p>Selected from 130 entries from 20 countries, the finalists also include Henning Larsens Tegnestue of Copenhagen and Smith-Miller &amp; Hawkinson Architects of New York.</p>
        <p>The public deserves much of the credit for the quality of the Olympics proposals. In July 2002, New Yorkers rejected the initial round of plans for the World Trade Center site. Alexander Garvin, a city planning commissioner who presided over the design of ground zero, is performing the same function for the Olympics bid. Aesthetically, at least, the design process is starting off on a sounder footing this time around.</p>
        <p>The audience for civic works, we are again reminded, does not consist exclusively of neighborhood groups. It also includes an audience as broad and international as that for Olympic sports. At the Grand Central show, there are ideas of which any city can be proud.</p>
        <p>The Olympic Village is part of a brilliant master plan for the games devised by Mr. Garvin in 2002. Entitled the Olympic X Plan, the scheme uses the city's transportation system to link new and existing sports venues arranged in giant intersecting axes draped across all five boroughs and the New Jersey Meadowlands. The Olympic Village sits at the center of the crossing, facing the Manhattan skyline. The view could make even the losers feel like champions.</p>
        <p>In another sign of changing times, the architects were instructed to disregard the development's original master plan, by the New York firm Beyer Blinder Belle, architects of ill-fated ground zero plans.</p>
        <p>Instead, following the example of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation's ''innovative design study,'' the teams have been asked to submit ideas for planning as well as architectural design.</p>
        <p>This is not a design competition, although it has the general appearance of one. There is no formal jury (deliberations will be conducted by a loose group associated with NYC2012, including Mr. Garvin and Daniel L. Doctoroff, the deputy mayor for economic development). There is also no fixed set of criteria by which the designs will be judged. We don't yet know whether the winner will be an architect or a design.</p>
        <p>The schemes presented are proposals, not fully developed master plans or designs for actual buildings. This is a study of ideas or, to use a term now largely discredited by its abuse by politicians, an array of ''visions'' to support the city's bid. We've had our Libeskind vision, and now we will have our Hadid, Smith-Miller &amp; Hawkinson and MVRDV visions. Two projects, in particular, stand out: Mr. Mayne's and Ms. Hadid's. These designs are radically different in form, but they share a trait. Both attempt to revive urban concepts repudiated by city planners more than a generation ago.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Mayne, the concept is the megastructure, a sweeping, usually horizontal building much favored by progressive architects in the 1960's. A spinoff of the British Brutalist movement, the megastructure combined architecture and urbanism beneath a single roof. Typically, it housed a variety of functions, including schools, shops, offices and recreation as well as housing.</p>
        <p>An ambitious example for lower Manhattan was proposed by Paul Rudolph in 1970. But the most notorious, and possibly most outstanding, example of the genre is that symbol of Nixon's Washington, the Watergate complex.</p>
        <p>The highly articulated forms of Mr. Mayne's facades suggest that his design, too, contains a mixed program. It consists entirely of housing, however. This represents a partial reversion to the Unité d'Habitation in Marseille, the residential blocks designed by Le Corbusier in the late 1940's. The Unité, which included an interior arcade of shops and a rooftop park, was the original inspiration for the megastructure concept.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hadid has reached back even further in time but, again, to Le Corbusier. She proposes nothing less than our old friend and favorite postmodern enemy, the Towers in the Park. Entitled the Radiant City, the concept was presented by Le Corbusier in 1931. In the postwar years, it became the leading paradigm for urban renewal projects in the United States, where it became synonymous with the modern movement's ambition to engineer society.</p>
        <p>It does not require a long memory to recall why both Corbusian models eventually came under attack. With both, the architect asserted a uniform control that all but eliminated urban diversity. They eliminated conventional streets and with them continuity with the surrounding urban fabric. They also eliminated the ''eyes on the street,'' the neighborhood self-policing that results from active street life. These powerful objections, raised by Jane Jacobs in 1960, went far toward discrediting modern architecture in the United States.</p>
        <p>Times change. So do urban scale, the meaning of modernity and the relationship of cities to their past, including modernisms gone by. Not all towers-in-a-park designs were failures. A few, like Waterside on the East River and Silver Towers in Greenwich Village, contributed to the rich diversity of the cityscape.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mayne's and Ms. Hadid's projects do not stem solely from Le Corbusier. They also embody Oscar Niemeyer's concept of the poetic urban object and the sculptural tradition that has been carried forward in recent years by Frank Gehry. These designs are right-brain poetry, not the precisely calibrated gridscapes of modernism's cold, objective truth. The forms are sensuous, playful, sinewy, as if the buildings had incorporated nature into themselves instead of standing apart from it.</p>
        <p>The other three projects are skimpy on the wow factor. This doesn't disqualify them, of course. All five designs deserve more than a once-over. MVRDV's proposal at least has the advantage of simplicity. The Rotterdam office wants to build a big beach with some housing behind it, a not unnatural shift in emphasis for a time of global warming. The Dutch will have much to teach us as water levels rise. In the 1970's, Rem Koolhaas gave us ''Delirious New York.'' Now, MVRDV gives us ''Drowned New Amsterdam,'' a reprise of colonial times as our great city subsides beneath the waves.</p>
        <p>To judge from the proposal by the firm Henning Larsens Tegnestue, New York still looks delirious to the Danes. It divides the site into four zoning quadrants: a pleasing reminder of its placement in the X Plan, but an idea with unfortunate theme park connotations. This is Manhattan replayed on the scale of ''It's a Small World,'' with miniature versions of Times Square, Central Park and Co-op City.</p>
        <p>And it could work. At least, for people who want to raise their children in a theme park. Yet it is hard to shake the feeling that the design is intended as a parody of post-Cold War fortress America, with its intoxicating, commercialized freedoms gaily paraded beneath the scrutiny of video surveillance cameras and Men in Black. As Vincent Scully might put it, the Danes have got our number, and it hurts.</p>
        <p>The Smith-Miller &amp; Hawkinson submission is almost unaccountably dull. I say almost, because I suspect that the design's pedestrian quality may be calculated. This is one of those mysteries that can occur when you hold a competition while denying that it is a competition: nobody really knows the rules. You can tell architects to go all out for innovation and imagination, but when the time comes to pick a winner you throw all this rationale in the air about budget, feasibility, community preference and so on.</p>
        <p>It shouldn't work that way. It's somehow less than obedient to the Olympic spirit. If you want architects to compete on the level of architecture, that is the sole basis on which a winner should be chosen. Then, should New York be fortunate enough to be host to the games in 2012, there will be more than enough time to deal with the pragmatics. This is all just fantasy, right?</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK  Correction:  March 12, 2004, Friday  An article and a subheading in House &amp; Home yesterday about designs for an Olympic Village in Queens, part of New York's bid to be host of the 2012 Summer Games, misstated the number of people the complex would house. It is 16,000, not 1,600.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 12, 2004, Friday</p>
        <p>An article and a subheading in House &amp; Home yesterday about designs for an Olympic Village in Queens, part of New York's bid to be host of the 2012 Summer Games, misstated the number of people the complex would house. It is 16,000, not 1,600.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
