<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Companies Don't Use Half of Federal Land They Lease</title>
    <meta content="25DRIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/25/politics/25drill.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1606516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Working Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Interior Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Land Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Interior Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DB123EF936A1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Companies Don't Use Half of Federal Land They Lease</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Energy Companies Don't Use Half of Federal Land They Lease</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Working Group reports that oil and gas developers in Western states are using less than half of land they lease from Interior Department; also says volume of natural gas from areas in use has increased for all but one of last seven years; report was compiled from Bureau of Land Management records; chart compares acreage leased to acreage in use (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Western states where oil and gas resources are most plentiful, the oil and gas developers are using less than half of the acreage they have under lease from the Interior Department, according to a new report and online database compiled by the Environmental Working Group.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the report shows, the volume of natural gas from the productive areas has increased for all but one of the last seven years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Western states, the oil and gas developers currently leasing Interior Department land are using less than half of the acreage they have under lease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Western states where oil and gas resources are most plentiful, the oil and gas developers are using less than half of the acreage they have under lease from the Interior Department, according to a new report and online database compiled by the Environmental Working Group.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the report shows, the volume of natural gas from the productive areas has increased for all but one of the last seven years.</p>
        <p>The information was compiled by the environmental group from files obtained from the Bureau of Land Management, a unit of the Interior Department.</p>
        <p>Representatives of environmental groups say that the data is further evidence that energy companies have more land available than they can use and that the figures undermine early reports by the Bush administration that excessive restrictions have hampered oil and gas development in the Rocky Mountain West.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that a large amount of acreage that is currently under lease is not in production,'' David Alberswerth, a public lands expert for the Wilderness Society, said. ''So why is it the administration insists on continuing to lease some of the most sensitive unproductive land? Isn't it clear that there is a large inventory of leased but undeveloped land?''</p>
        <p>Rebecca Watson, assistant secretary of the Interior Department, countered: ''People are leasing where there's oil and gas. Not all federal lands have oil and gas underneath.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Watson said the new report and database failed to reflect that ''the number of acres that are leased right now -- 41 million acres -- are less in this administration than the Clinton administration.''</p>
        <p>The new database and report, which is based on tens of thousands of separate bits of information in Interior Department files, offers an unusually detailed picture of the oil and gas industry's fluctuating interest in using public lands in the 12 Western states that hold most of the nation's underground mineral resources.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, after technological advances in extracting natural gas that made methane in Rockies coal beds accessible, the interest in natural gas leases intensified.</p>
        <p>A continual rise in natural gas prices, which have more than doubled since the late 90's, also fed the new demand for access to reserves on federal land.</p>
        <p>That demand has led to battles with environmentalists over leasing in remote and scenic areas like the Powder River Basin in Wyoming and Otero Mesa in New Mexico.</p>
        <p>''Most critics of the administration's policies will concede that oil and gas development is a legitimate use of the public lands,'' Mr. Alberswerth said. ''But not everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Edward Porter, research manager for the American Petroleum Institute, an industry group, said the land under lease was ''being used.''</p>
        <p>''It's like a building under construction,'' Mr. Porter added. ''It's not occupied, but that doesn't mean it's not being used.''</p>
        <p>The new database showed that natural gas production on Bureau of Land Management lands increased, to 1.1 trillion cubic feet in 2003 from 832 billion cubic feet in 1993. In its analysis, the report suggests, based on separate information from the Department of Energy, this amount represents 18 days' supply at current use levels, a figure the report highlights to support its call for energy conservation and development of renewable energy resources.</p>
        <p>It also showed that leases on Interior lands declined to 8,604 this year from 9,131 in 1999.</p>
        <p>Dusty Horwitt, an analyst with the Environmental Working Group, said the report gave '' ''a reason to focus on other sources of energy and energy efficiency.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
