<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Night-Life Reporter And Other Characters</title>
    <meta content="09BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/09/nyregion/thecity/09book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1580343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK BOOKSHELF/NOVELS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dolby, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paddock, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Ellis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Westlake, Donald E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Trouble Boy, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Secret Word, A (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Road to Ruin, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Reckless Abandon (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Drop Dead, My Lovely (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DB173CF93AA35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Night-Life Reporter And Other Characters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Night-Life Reporter and Other Characters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from new novels set in New York City: The Trouble Boy by Tom Dolby, A Secret Word by Jennifer Paddock, The Road to Ruin by Donald E Westlake, Reckless Abandon by Stuart Woods and Drop Dead, My Lovely by Ellis Weiner; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE TROUBLE BOY  By Tom Dolby  Kensington Books  ($23, hardcover)</p>
        <p>Later that afternoon, I was treated to my first glimpse of Lola Copacabana, one of CityStyle's night-life reporters. I would be editing her column, ''Whatever Lola Wants.'' I knew Lola wrote for the site, but I didn't know that, unlike the site's other writers, she would be corning in once a week to compose her piece.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE TROUBLE BOY.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE TROUBLE BOY  By Tom Dolby  Kensington Books  ($23, hardcover)</p>
        <p>Later that afternoon, I was treated to my first glimpse of Lola Copacabana, one of CityStyle's night-life reporters. I would be editing her column, ''Whatever Lola Wants.'' I knew Lola wrote for the site, but I didn't know that, unlike the site's other writers, she would be corning in once a week to compose her piece.</p>
        <p>''Lola doesn't have a computer at home,'' Donovan explained, rolling his eyes.</p>
        <p>Lola was known around the city as a post-op transsexual nightclub performer who had come to New York from Miami 11 years ago. While in Miami, she had peddled an act in which she impersonated Marilyn Monroe, smearing herself with birthday cake during her ''Happy Birthday, Mr. President'' number and then shooting herself in the head with a squirt gun filled with pig's blood. A nightclub in New York had flown her up for the weekend to perform and she ended up staying in the city permanently.</p>
        <p>In order to offset her act's significant investment in dry cleaning, Lola quickly found work go-go dancing or performing nearly every night of the week.</p>
        <p>A SECRET WORD  By Jennifer Paddock  Touchstone  ($13, paperback)</p>
        <p>My father is the reason that I'm in New York and in law school, and his money will make it easier for me to stay. But it's hard to go to class. I make myself. I can sit through lectures fine. If I get called on, I say, ''I don't know.'' I spend afternoons wandering around Times Square, among tourists, everyone unsure of where to walk next.</p>
        <p>I walk to the Ambassador Theater where ''Bring in 'Da Noise, Bring in 'Da Funk'' is playing. It stars Savion Glover. I've seen him dance before, when I was 12 years old, on a trip here with my father.</p>
        <p>The musical is in previews, and I am able to buy a matinee ticket, a good one in the orchestra, maybe because I'm by myself. I wander back into Times Square and wait for the show to begin.</p>
        <p>The theater is old with an orchestra and mezzanine. The ceiling is a gray-blue, and a glass chandelier hangs down. The seats are violet. I'm on the fourth row. The curtain is deep red. The beginning isn't seen but heard. There are taps, and it is dark, and then there is light on the dancer's feet, more taps that grow faster, and then there are other sounds, other feet, other dancers. There are drummers. There is a singer.</p>
        <p>And being here so close to the dancer, Savion, I feel a charge, and a current runs through my heart, and I am happy, and I won't let myself look at anyone but him because I don't want my happiness to leave.</p>
        <p>THE ROAD TO RUIN  By Donald E. Westlake  Warner Books  ($25, hardcover)</p>
        <p>When Dortmunder walked into the O.J. Bar and Grill on Amsterdam Avenue at 11 that night, Rollo the bartender was nowhere to be seen. The regulars, clustered as usual at the left end of the bar, were continuing without him, like a conductorless orchestra.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the discussion concerned global warming. ''The reason for global warming,'' one of them said as Dortmunder leaned his front against the bar somewhere down to the right of them, ''is air conditioners.''</p>
        <p>Two or three of the regulars wished to object to this idea, but he with the most powerful voice won out, speaking, perhaps, for the group as a whole: ''Whadaya mean, air conditioners? Air conditioners make things cold.''</p>
        <p>''Indoors,'' the first regular said. ''What happens to all the heat used to be indoors? It's outdoors. It's what they call vent. All the cold air's inside, all the hot air's outside, there you go, global warming.''</p>
        <p>RECKLESS ABANDON  By Stuart Woods  Putnam  ($25.95, hardcover)</p>
        <p>''Drop your luggage, freshen up, and meet me at Elaine's -- Second Avenue, between Eighty-eighth and Eighty-ninth.''</p>
        <p>''Sounds great. We're at the tunnel now. How long should it take me?''</p>
        <p>''If you're quick, half an hour, but you're a woman.''</p>
        <p>''Half an hour it is, and don't ever put a 'but' in front of that statement.'' She hung up.</p>
        <p>Gianni put a Knob Creek on the rocks in front of him, and Stone took a sip. ''Better get him something, too,'' Stone said, pointing at Dino, his partner when he had been an NYPD detective. Dino spoke to a couple of people at the front tables, then came back and pulled up a chair. His drink had already arrived.</p>
        <p>''How you doing?'' Dino asked.</p>
        <p>''Not bad. You?''</p>
        <p>''The same. You're looking thoughtful.''</p>
        <p>''I was just truing to remember everything about my trip to Vero Beach, Florida, last year, when I was picking up my Malibu at the Piper factory.''</p>
        <p>''Why?''</p>
        <p>''I was in a bank in the next town, a place called Orchid Beach, getting a cashier's check to pay for the airplane, when a bunch of guys wearing masks walked in and stuck the place up.''</p>
        <p>DROP DEAD, MY LOVELY  By Ellis Weiner  New American Library  ($23.95, hardcover)</p>
        <p>I walked into a tall building on Lex in the 40's and read on the address board that the law firm occupied the third and fourth floors. I took the elevator to Reception on Four. When the doors opened I had to dodge and weave around an obstacle course of overturned desks on dollies and small citadels of cartons marked HRLJ -- FILES. The gal at the reception kiosk smiled with mechanical dependability.</p>
        <p>I held back. I hit the brakes. On-the-job jitters? Performance anxiety? Try due diligence and sensible professional caution. Litman might be missing, and his colleagues might have their own sheaf of reasons for wanting him found ... but they'd have a larger stake in maintaining a facade of normalcy, which is not really a word, but people use it instead of normality. So delicacy, or delicality, was called for.</p>
        <p>This office full of savvy pros would be well versed in the fine art of giving a mug like Ingalls the big stall and the endless runaround. Getting face time with a person who knew where Litman might be would prove as difficult as actually finding the man, a project requiring as much finesse as persistence. I steeled myself for some tricky maneuvering.</p>
        <p>The receptionist, a cute youngster in a big black blouse, a tiny gold hoop through her right ear, perked, ''Hi,'' as I eased up to her command post. I smiled in a restrained way.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking for a certain individual,'' I said.</p>
        <p>I pulled Celeste Vroman's photo of Litman out of my jacket pocket and showed it to her. I had the sudden sensation of standing at the base of a large mountain, preparing to embark on an arduous climb.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOOKSHELF/NOVELS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
