<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="09CTGUIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1580249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4D61F3DF93AA35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Understanding His Father</p>
        <p>The private life of Louis I. Kahn, an internationally revered architect, was consumed with maintaining three separate families, each knowing nothing about the others. He was memorialized in a film last year, written, directed and narrated by his son Nathaniel. The movie may be seen today at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., and Monday and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. at Cinestudio, Trinity College on 300 Summit Street in Hartford.</p>
        <p>Nathaniel was 11 years old in 1974 when his father, whose life began in Estonia, collapsed and died in Pennsylvania Station with outstanding debts of $500,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Understanding His Father</p>
        <p>The private life of Louis I. Kahn, an internationally revered architect, was consumed with maintaining three separate families, each knowing nothing about the others. He was memorialized in a film last year, written, directed and narrated by his son Nathaniel. The movie may be seen today at 2:30 and 7:30 p.m., and Monday and Tuesday at 7:30 p.m. at Cinestudio, Trinity College on 300 Summit Street in Hartford.</p>
        <p>Nathaniel was 11 years old in 1974 when his father, whose life began in Estonia, collapsed and died in Pennsylvania Station with outstanding debts of $500,000.</p>
        <p>The film, called ''My Architect: A Son's Journey,'' is a record of Nathaniel Kahn's effort to understand his father by traveling to see his masterpieces in California, Texas, Bangladesh and Connecticut, where Mr. Kahn was the architect for the Yale Center for British Art, hand-picked by the museum's founder, Paul Mellon.</p>
        <p>Among the architects who make brief appearances in the film are Philip Johnson, Vincent Scully, I.M. Pei and Frank Gehry.</p>
        <p>Admission is $6, students $5. Information: (860)297-2463.</p>
        <p>'Velveteen,' the Musical</p>
        <p>A new musical version of Margery Williams's classic story of ''The Velveteen Rabbit,'' staged by the Connecticut Children's Theater of Essex, will be presented for two performances this week at the University of Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>Adapted and composed by Patty Carver and Leo P. Carusone, the show was initially intended for groups of children from pre-kindergarten through third grade. But demand for individual tickets has made a limited supply available.</p>
        <p>Jerry Goehring, executive director of the award-winning National Theater of the Deaf, directed the production, which features a half-dozen professional actors from New York. Voiceovers by Bea Arthur of ''The Golden Girls'' as the Magic Fairy and by Marla Gibbs of ''The Jeffersons'' as the Wind Up Doll are part of the production.</p>
        <p>Performances at the university's Arnold Bernhard Arts Center on 84 Iranistan Avenue are on Thursday at 10 a.m. and 12:30 p.m., and Friday at 10 a.m. For tickets priced from $7 to $10 call (800)887-6639.</p>
        <p>Art at the Bruce</p>
        <p>About 65 works loosely identified as drawings from a reservoir of 20,000 such works in the J.P. Morgan Chase Collection started by David Rockefeller in 1959 are on loan to the Bruce Museum in Greenwich from Saturday through Sept. 12.</p>
        <p>The exhibition includes works by Saul Steinberg, Andy Warhol, Chuck Close, Jean Michel Basquiat, David Salle, Gerhard Richter and Carl Ostendarp. Sculpture, painting, mixed media, abstraction, futurist, representational and non-objective art are embraced within the overarching framework of drawings.</p>
        <p>The Bruce is downtown off Exit 3 of I-95 and is open Tuesday through Saturday from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., Sunday from 1 to 5 p.m. Admission is $4 or $5, depending on age, and free on Tuesdays. Free tours are conducted Fridays at 12:30 p.m. Information: (203)869-0376.</p>
        <p>Energy-Minded at Home</p>
        <p>How homeowners, homebuilders and businesses can save energy and money using new technologies will be demonstrated in a self-guided tour of four new solar homes selected for viewing by People's Action for Clean Energy Inc. The tour will take place Saturday from noon to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>The group has been sponsoring the tours for 30 years. This one is sponsored by SmartPower, a nonprofit organization dedicated, as is People's Action for Clean Energy to non-polluting renewable energy.</p>
        <p>Two houses to be visited are off-the-grid farmhouses in Ashford and North Windham. Also part of the tour is an all-electric home on a former mill site in Eastford where a dam powers the reconditioned mill turbine and a new, 1,500-square-foot stone and shingle house in Canterbury that relies on passive solar heating and a basement wood stove connection system. Tickets with maps are $15 and may be obtained by calling (860)693-0107.</p>
        <p>Rural New England</p>
        <p>Reverse-glass painting, an almost lost folk art, was taken up some 30 years ago by Milton Bond, a sailor, oysterman and then master of one of the last commercial sailing ships plying New York Harbor and the Connecticut coast.</p>
        <p>Over the years, working alone and without instruction, he mastered the technique of painting with the details in the foreground painted first, the background last and the finished oil painting protected by the glass.</p>
        <p>His style is semi-primitive, finely detailed, gaily colored and featuring rural New England scenes and villages. One in particular is of the National Building that still stands at the gateway to Westport, painted in 1873 on the Fourth of July.</p>
        <p>His work has won awards and has been acquired by the Smithsonian Institution, the Museum of American Folk Art in New York, the Grand Palais and the Henri Rousseau Museum in Paris.</p>
        <p>Sharing the exhibition space at the New Canaan Library's Curtis Gallery through May 17 is the work of Ted Jeremenko, another self-taught but contemporary artist who also left his day job as a computer software designer in the 1970's and began painting semi-primitive but finely detailed, gaily colored scenes of eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>As his work began to sell he turned to serigraphs -- 34 have been published. His work has been acquired for corporate and private collections across the country, and he has had notably successful exhibitions in Europe and Japan. The library is at 151 Main Street.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
