<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1583529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DB1F3FF931A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-11</p>
        <p>Intimidation Tactics in Iraq Approved by U.S. Officers  The use of dogs to intimidate prisoners during interrogation at Abu Ghraib prison in Iraq was approved by military intelligence officers there, and was one of several aggressive tactics they adopted even without approval from higher commanders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-11</p>
        <p>Intimidation Tactics in Iraq Approved by U.S. Officers  The use of dogs to intimidate prisoners during interrogation at Abu Ghraib prison in Iraq was approved by military intelligence officers there, and was one of several aggressive tactics they adopted even without approval from higher commanders.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Pentagon is preparing for an influx of compensation claims as evidence of abuse continues to surface. Since last June, the military has paid more than $2.5 million in compensation claims in Iraq, but most of those involved accidents or cases of negligence.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Hundreds of worshipers poured into two Shiite shrines in Karbala to hear clerics demand an end to continuing clashes between American forces and insurgents loyal to the rebel cleric Moktada al-Sadr.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff has written a new national military strategy that makes clear that greater attention must be paid to the complicated and dangerous transition between the end of major combat operations and the return of civil authority.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Arab Summit in North Africa  Arab leaders gathering for a summit meeting in the North African capital of Tunis are expected to issue a collective criticism of the United States for the abuse of Iraqi prisoners and for the anemic American effort toward ending the Arab-Israeli conflict.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Clashes in Afghanistan  Two Afghan policemen and three other Afghans died in clashes in Afghanistan that left four American soldiers wounded. In a separate incident, Pakistani officials protested what they said was the second incursion by American forces into Pakistani territory in a month.</p>
        <p>A2</p>
        <p>Israeli Troop Relocation  The Israeli Army announced that it was redeploying some of the forces it had sent to the Gaza Strip in a major operation intended to sever arms-smuggling routes in tunnels from Egypt. The incursion, the biggest in years, followed the killing of 13 Israeli soldiers in Gaza last week.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-14; 18</p>
        <p>Kerry Considers Delay In Accepting Nomination  Senator John Kerry is considering delaying his acceptance of the Democratic presidential nomination until five weeks after the party's July convention so he may continue spending the tens of millions of dollars he has raised for the primary season, his aides said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraq Blocks View of Economy  Despite a big rebound in hiring in the last several months, President Bush has been unable to translate the economic improvement into political benefit, leaving Republicans anxious that the White House might let slip away its best chance to counter the bad news from Iraq.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conservatives Ponder Split  As Presbyterians prepare to gather next month for their General Assembly in Richmond, Va., a band of conservatives is advancing a plan to split the church along liberal and orthodox lines.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Question in Lawyer's Case  Questions surround the strength of the evidence against a Portland, Ore., lawyer who was arrested two weeks ago in connection with the deadly Madrid bombings and then abruptly released.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>California's Credit Improving  A Wall Street rating agency upgraded California's dismal credit rating for the first time in nearly four years, reflecting a modest economic rebound and the prospect of an end to years of political stagnation in Sacramento.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Crackdown on Licenses  The attorney general of Massachusetts, Thomas F. Reilly, ordered officials in four communities to quit issuing marriage licenses to out-of-state same-sex couples.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Telephone Workers on Strike  Telephone company workers picketed in 13 states, and callers around the country were unable to get through to directory assistance as 102,000 employees of SBC Communications Inc. went on strike.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Police in New Jersey Send Bulletproof Vests to Iraq  State troopers and other police officers in New Jersey have donated about 1,000 old bulletproof vests to American troops stationed in Iraq, all in the spirit of making the thin-skinned, vulnerable Humvees safer for the soldiers and marines who ride them.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Different Account of 9/11  Lloyd Thompson, who was the deputy fire safety director in the World Trade Center's north tower, gave an account to the national commission investigating the Sept. 11 attacks that is at odds with the commission's leading theory on what went wrong.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>No Offense Intended  John J. Myers, the archbishop of Newark, said he was ''deeply disappointed'' that his recent criticism of Catholic elected officials who support abortion rights had been interpreted by some New Jerseyeans as a political slap at Gov. James E. McGreevey.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-15</p>
        <p>Libel Laws Under Scrutiny  Craig Unger's best-selling book, ''House of Bush, House of Saud: The Secret Relationship Between the World's Two Most Powerful Dynasties,'' is not for sale in Britain -- the latest caualty of the country's tough libel laws. Some worry the case may be another example of how wealthy Saudis are increasingly using British laws to intimidate critics.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B16</p>
        <p>Melvin J. Lasky  The editor of two major intellectual journals -- including Encounter, which was one of postwar Europe's leading literary and political journals -- and a man at the vortex of the debates and controversies thrown up by the cold war, he was 84.</p>
        <p>B16</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Stewart Witness Charged  The government charged Larry F. Stewart, the prosecutors' expert on ink in the Martha Stewart trial, with two counts of perjury for lying repeatedly during the trial. Lawyers said it was too early to tell whether Mr. Stewart's statements would result in a successful appeal.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Saudis to Increase Oil Output  Saudi Arabia offered to increase its oil output by at least 500,000 barrels, to 9 million barrels a day, starting June 1.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Europe Backs Russia for W.T.O.  Russia won support for membership in the World Trade Organization from the European Union and said it would support the environmental treaty on emissions known as the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTSSATURDAY</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>Lakers Win First of Series  The Los Angeles Lakers beat the Minnesota Timberwolves 97-88, in the first game of the best-of-seven Western Conference final series.</p>
        <p>B16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: An Abu Ghraib investigation; affordable housing in crisis; weakening the rules for judges.</p>
        <p>Columns: David Brooks, Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B12  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B15  Crossword</p>
        <p>B10  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
