<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fuel-Saving Proposal From Your Automaker: Tax the Gas</title>
    <meta content="18FUEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/18/business/yourmoney/18fuel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1575326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS AND ANALYSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Energy Information Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3DA1F3AF93BA25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fuel-Saving Proposal From Your Automaker: Tax the Gas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Fuel-Saving Proposal From Your Automaker: Tax the Gas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States auto industry backs higher taxes on gasoline, hot potato for politicians, to curb consumption as alternative to stricter fuel economy rules; Ford Motor chairman William Clay Ford Jr holds American consumers want bigger and faster vehicles, not more efficient ones; notes high fuel taxes have forced foreign consumers to get use to smaller, more efficient vehicles; graphs of gasoline prices and taxes and of oil consumption; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME people have wacky ideas, like taxing gasoline more so people drive less.''</p>
        <p>So said a recent television ad from the Bush presidential campaign, set to jaunty music from the silent-movie era, that linked Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, the likely Democratic presidential nominee, to a 50-cent-a-gallon increase in the gas tax. Actually, Mr. Kerry told a Boston Globe reporter a decade ago that he supported such a measure at the time to help cut the deficit, but he has never introduced it in legislation or voted for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one unlikely place, higher gas taxes are seen as the best way to cut oil consumption: Detroit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME people have wacky ideas, like taxing gasoline more so people drive less.''</p>
        <p>So said a recent television ad from the Bush presidential campaign, set to jaunty music from the silent-movie era, that linked Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, the likely Democratic presidential nominee, to a 50-cent-a-gallon increase in the gas tax. Actually, Mr. Kerry told a Boston Globe reporter a decade ago that he supported such a measure at the time to help cut the deficit, but he has never introduced it in legislation or voted for it.</p>
        <p>The Kerry campaign rebutted by pointing out that in Fortune magazine five years ago, N. Gregory Mankiw, a top economic adviser to the president, argued for a 50-cent increase in the gas tax. And Democrats also highlighted Vice President Dick Cheney's support for a 1980's proposal to tax imported oil, a plan that would have meant higher prices at the pump.</p>
        <p>All right, so both sides flirted with higher gas taxes in the past. Does either back them today?</p>
        <p>Are you kidding? Don't forget that the United States started with a tax rebellion. And with the presidential sweepstakes in full swing and with gas prices up almost 30 cents a gallon this year -- to well over $2 a gallon for regular in California -- a gas tax increase is not going to happen.</p>
        <p>But in one unlikely place, higher gas taxes are seen as the only nonwacky way to cut oil consumption. That's Detroit, the manufacturing center for the nation's largest oil-consuming product, the automobile.</p>
        <p>Auto industry executives are accustomed to dealing with much higher fuel prices abroad, and there is evidence that high gas taxes have helped Europeans curb their oil habit. Overall oil consumption has actually fallen in Germany and Britain since the 1970's, while it is up substantially in the United States -- to 20 million barrels a day, from 14.7 million barrels in 1970. (Light-duty cars and trucks drink more than 40 percent of that.)</p>
        <p>Many factors influence America's growing thirst for crude, including the proliferation of suburbs, whose sprawling landscape forces people to spend more time on the road. But there is also compelling evidence that higher fuel taxes have given Europeans a strong impetus to buy vehicles that are more efficient.</p>
        <p>In the first week of April, when prices for premium gasoline averaged $1.96 a gallon in the United States, the price of a similar grade in Germany was $5.19, and $5.34 in Britain, according to the federal Energy Information Administration.</p>
        <p>In interviews at the New York International Auto Show this month, top executives of General Motors and the Ford Motor Company, both of which make and sell a lot of cars in Europe, reiterated their support for high gasoline taxes -- as opposed to stricter fuel economy regulations.</p>
        <p>''Anything that can align the individual customer's purchase decisions with society's goals are the way to go,'' Ford's chairman and chief executive, William Clay Ford Jr., said, adding that his company has previously supported a 50-cent increase in gas taxes.</p>
        <p>(The current federal gas tax is 18.4 cents, and state taxes vary. All told, taxes account for about 24 percent of the cost of a gallon of gasoline.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said the current regulatory system, which compels automakers to make cars and trucks that meet minimum standards for fuel efficiency, ''puts the manufacturer in this tug of war that's unsustainable between what the customer wants and what society says it wants.''</p>
        <p>In other words, most customers want bigger and faster cars -- actually, light-duty trucks like sport utility vehicles -- not efficient ones.</p>
        <p>''Every place else we operate,'' Mr. Ford added, ''fuel prices are very high relative to here and customers get used to it, but they get used to it by having a smaller vehicle, a more efficient vehicle.''</p>
        <p>G. Richard Wagoner Jr., the chairman and chief executive of G.M., concurred.</p>
        <p>''If you want people to consume something less, the simplest thing to do is price it more dearly,'' Mr. Wagoner said. ''And there is just no track record of sustainable success in the U.S. of doing that, versus Germany, for example, which just regularly says, 'Oh, we have a budget deficit; we're going to raise the fuel taxes by 10 pfennigs, or euros, or whatever,' and do that. And I think that's the rub.''</p>
        <p>Robert A. Lutz, G.M.'s vice chairman, often likens fuel regulations to tackling the nation's problem with obesity by forcing clothing manufacturers to produce smaller sizes. His point is this: As long as gasoline is cheaper than bottled water, fuel economy will not matter to car buyers. G.M. also says fuel regulations unfairly burden domestic automakers because they sell more big trucks.</p>
        <p>Consumer groups roll their eyes at these arguments because they know that such tax increases are unlikely to win approval in the United States, as both Mr. Ford and Mr. Wagoner acknowledge. And the groups are skeptical that companies that depend on S.U.V.'s and pickups for profit -- and tend to lose money on passenger cars -- really want high gas taxes.</p>
        <p>''It's easy to argue for a politically unviable solution in place of actually making progress,'' said David Friedman, senior policy analyst at the Union of Concerned Scientists, an environmental research and advocacy group. ''There's probably room to do both, but at a minimum we have to talk about ways to save consumers money by raising fuel economy standards.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Becker, an expert on global warming for the Sierra Club, said: ''It's like Bush saying: 'Let's go to Mars. Let me offer you the impossible to divert you from the practical.'</p>
        <p>''We totally support a gas tax,'' Mr. Becker added, ''and we'd be happy to meet with the other people who support a gas tax -- at a phone booth in Grand Central station.''</p>
        <p>Higher fuel prices in Europe, and in nations like Japan, are less burdensome on the poor, because mass transportation is a viable alternative.</p>
        <p>''It has the potential to price some people at the lower end of the economic spectrum out of the ability to drive,'' Mr. Friedman said. ''And we don't have a lot of options besides cars.''</p>
        <p>Europe is not relying on taxes alone. The European Union is phasing in its own fuel economy regulations, in the form of requiring automakers to reduce the amount of global-warming emissions that their cars create.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the fuel-economy question has rarely been more pressing. For starters, the war in Iraq and strained relations with Saudi Arabia and other Middle Eastern oil producers have raised new doubt about the short-term flow of oil. And there is renewed debate among academics and geologists over when the longer-term supplies will peak.</p>
        <p>At home, gasoline prices have reached record highs this year, close to $1.80, on average, for a gallon of regular nationwide. (Prices, though, are still far below the peaks of the early 1980's, when gasoline sold for the equivalent of about $3 a gallon today, after adjusting for inflation.)</p>
        <p>STILL, Mr. Ford said his company was preparing for a future of higher gas prices by pushing technologies like hybrid vehicles. One reason is that demand for oil is expected to accelerate greatly as the economies of China and India become more developed.</p>
        <p>New vehicles in the United States, meanwhile, are becoming less fuel efficient, on average. In fact, in the 2002 model year, automotive fuel economy reached its lowest point in more than two decades -- a result of the industry's successful lobbying to keep fuel economy regulations largely stagnant as the market has tilted to bigger and faster vehicles, like S.U.V.'s and big pickups. And the largest and most inefficient vehicles, like the Hummer, are not even covered by fuel economy regulations -- paradoxically because they are so big.</p>
        <p>Senator Kerry has a plan to couple significantly higher fuel economy standards with incentives for consumers to buy efficient vehicles and for the domestic automakers to build them. By contrast, the Bush administration has suggested a variety of proposals aimed at overhauling fuel regulations but has said its plans might not improve overall fuel economy.</p>
        <p>And higher taxes?</p>
        <p>''If Kerry's gas-tax increase were law, the average family would pay $657 more a year,'' the Bush ad said.</p>
        <p>Not that Senator Kerry is proposing such a plan. At a rally in San Diego in late March, he said, ''I'm going to stand up for students and middle-class families and all those who need relief at the pump.''</p>
        <p>NEWS AND ANALYSIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
