<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garages for Chardonnays, Not Camrys</title>
    <meta content="29WINE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/29/travel/escapes/29WINE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1622970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HAVENS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Patricia Leigh</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Vermont</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wine Spectator</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFDB133DF93AA15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garages for Chardonnays, Not Camrys</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Garages for Chardonnays, Not Camrys</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LEIGH BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Patricia Leigh</byline>
      <dateline>PIEDMONT, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 'garagistes,' amateur home vintners in California who transform their garages and apartments into places to crush and ferment grapes; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE fever comes on suddenly for Tom Clark, a lawyer with the Port of Oakland, when he spies his office phone blinking with an urgent message. The news on the voice mail will haunt him, cost him sleep, draw him from his bed into the garage in the middle of the night, where, giddy and nervous with anticipation, he will wait in musty seclusion illuminated by a single light bulb until sweet deliverance arrives: 550 pounds of freshly picked wine grapes.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't go to bed,'' he would say the next evening as he punched down a Rubbermaid container of fermenting booty with a toilet-bowl plunger. ''I wanted to play with those sangioveses.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nondescript garages are being transformed into chateaus by "garagistes"  amateur home vintners who obsess about their wine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE fever comes on suddenly for Tom Clark, a lawyer with the Port of Oakland, when he spies his office phone blinking with an urgent message. The news on the voice mail will haunt him, cost him sleep, draw him from his bed into the garage in the middle of the night, where, giddy and nervous with anticipation, he will wait in musty seclusion illuminated by a single light bulb until sweet deliverance arrives: 550 pounds of freshly picked wine grapes.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't go to bed,'' he would say the next evening as he punched down a Rubbermaid container of fermenting booty with a toilet-bowl plunger. ''I wanted to play with those sangioveses.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the fever is rampant in northern California. At this time of year in neighborhoods like Mr. Clark's in Piedmont, a small bedroom community tucked into the Oakland hills, nondescript garages housing wet-vacs and lawn mowers are transformed into chateaus by ''garagistes'' -- amateur home vintners -- who obsess about malolactic fermentation and how to carpool 650 pounds of petit verdot grapes in the back seat during rush hour.</p>
        <p>''When the crush is in, there is nothing better,'' said Mr. Clark, whose two-car garage, along with the three-car garage of his neighbor Mike Masero, has been transformed into a grease-stained Napa. In this inelegant tableau, the two are producing their ambitious 2004 vintages -- about 2,000 bottles of 13 varieties -- that began with muscat canelli grapes crushed in August and continued to the sangioveses that Mr. Masero, an information technology specialist for a webcasting company, recently raced to pick up late after work.</p>
        <p>''Part about having a passion about something is, you're not in control,'' said Mr. Clark, a sophisticated winemaker who will drop everything for the right grapes. ''You're having to accommodate yourself to some other force. There is also a kinetic energy to it. I sit in front of the computer all day, and it's a real relief. We're physical beings. So it's 'Let's go out there, get our hands all mucky and crush some grapes.' ''</p>
        <p>Spurred by the grape glut of recent years, do-it-yourselfism and, perhaps, the indefatigable baby boom desire for perfection, the garagiste scene is expanding throughout California, the Pacific Northwest, the Finger Lakes region of New York and other hubs of winemaking. Thanks to the increasing availability of cultured wine yeasts and wine-quality concentrated grape juice, home vintners are also flourishing in less likely places like Vermont and especially Canada, where, largely for economic reasons, one quarter of the wine consumed is now made by hobbyists, according to Brad Ring, publisher of WineMaker, a magazine geared to home winemakers founded six years ago in Manchester, Vt.</p>
        <p>Across the country, there are an estimated 750,000 home winemakers and counting, Mr. Ring said, among them members of intensely serious wine clubs like Cellarmasters Home Wine Club in Los Angeles, the Sacramento Home Winemakers and the Contra Costa Wine Group outside San Francisco, who compete in amateur wine competitions at state and county fairs and at events like the International Amateur Wine Competition in Vermont. Unlike the landed gentry or old-time rural families, most garagistes do not have their own vineyards but buy grapes in bulk, sometimes doing the picking themselves. They produce wine for their own consumption and to share or trade with friends; the sale of wine is limited to bonded wineries.</p>
        <p>''You get close to your inner Dionysus,'' said Jerry Miller, 56, an energy utility analyst, who has been making wine since 1979 and whose garage, filled with neighbors and friends with chronically wine-purple hands during crush season, has the festive quality of an Amish barn-raising. ''I do it for the sensuality of it.''</p>
        <p>AROUND the San Francisco Bay area, arguably the hub of the garagiste movement, placid oak-lined streets are alive with the clicketyclack of hand-cranked wine presses, as home winemakers with a penchant for jazz and chèvre sit on milk crates in their driveways, buckets at the ready to catch the torrential ''free run'' of flowing juice -- the wine equivalent of nirvana. Cars banished to curbsides, they speak of ''brix'' (sugar content), ''hot'' wine (too much alcohol) and ''mog'' (material other than grapes, like spider webs and bees, that gets mixed in during picking).</p>
        <p>Vacations are out, as internal clocks are reset to the rhythm of grapes. Weekends and wee hours are consumed with crushing, de-stemming, pressing, and racing -- particularly if, like Mr. Clark, you have your heart set on a certain row of petit verdot hanging provocatively in a grove of eucalyptus near Lodi, 75 miles away, and learn it is to be picked that day.</p>
        <p>Many garagistes fantasize about going pro. ''Home wines are some of the best wines in California,'' said Kent M. Rosenblum, a veterinarian turned vintner whose respected winery, Rosenblum Cellars, got started in his basement. ''They're also some of the worst wines in California.''</p>
        <p>Since the repeal of Prohibition, government rules permit households to make up to 200 gallons -- 1,000 bottles -- of wine a year. At Bissie and Jerry Miller's, six couples get together each harvest season to purchase a ton of grapes, which yields between nine and 11 cases for each family. Each couple's $500-a-year investment works out to about $5 a bottle.</p>
        <p>Their wine, which is pumped through a siphon hose from the garage to the basement, is also liquid memory. Their Wedding Ring wine of 1991, a pinot noir, commemorated the year that Bevan Vinton, a high school social studies teacher, lost her wedding ring in the crush (it was retrieved during pressing a week later in the ''cake'' of smashed skins and seeds). The Fire zinfandel was named for the Oakland Hills fire, during which the Millers temporarily fled their home, leaving the grapes behind in the garage.</p>
        <p>The Bay area's extreme garagistes ''know they can buy Two Buck Chuck,'' said Lisa Van de Water, a technical wine consultant and founder of the Wine Lab in Napa, which does scientific analyses for home winemakers and sells yeast nutrients and related products. ''They're trying to make really good wine, something that's theirs.''</p>
        <p>It helps to be a geek. Bonneau Dickson, 60, who has christened his home elixirs Chateau Bonneau, for instance, is a sanitary engineer who lives in Berkeley. ''Wine is an anaerobic process, like sludge digestion,'' he said, an observation not likely to be repeated in The Wine Spectator.</p>
        <p>The ceiling of his 700-square-foot third-floor walk-up is dented from an errant stopper blown off a vigorously fermenting chardonnay. His kitchen is a welter of calibrated cylinders, acidity kits and pH meters. His décor consists of 65 wine-filled carboys, six-gallon glass containers, which have subsumed nearly every inch of his apartment. His preoccupation, however, does wonders for his social life. ''As soon as I started making wine, I noticed I had more friends,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Stephen and Susan Abbanat, who, like Mr. Dickson, are members of the Contra Costa Wine Group, spend their leisure time developing math-laden spreadsheets to monitor the parts-per-million of potassium metasulfite and the like, spurred by the yeasty smell of wine fermenting in their Oakland basement. ''You start to build a taste for your own wine, and that's what you prefer,'' Mr. Abbanat said.</p>
        <p>''There's a mystery to it, a random element,'' he said, turning philosophical as he drove home from a vineyard recently with 155 pounds of merlot grapes in his Lexus. ''Making things is a survival trait, part of our genetic code. It's a piece of ourselves we're trying to connect with.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, romance can fade with panic, spurred, say, by pernicious Brettanomyces, a spoilage yeast, or, in the Abbanats' case, ''Pepto-Bismol-colored bubbles coming off during fermentation that could have been a funky bacteria.'' Because he lives near wine country, Mr. Abbanat was able to drive a vial of the suspicious cabernet up to the Wine Lab in Napa, founded by Ms. Van de Water, who has earned the nickname ''the bad wine lady'' (everything was fine). Home winemakers, she noted, must function without microbiologists, state-of-the-art filtration systems and other resources available to commercial wineries. ''Their expectation that everything will turn out O.K. leads to a lot of ruined wine,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A big reason winemakers form groups, at least in California, is access to know-how and most important, good grapes. The grape glut, which peaked in 2000 with a staggering 90,000-plus tons of grapes, has opened up many once-exclusive vineyards to home winemakers, but many growers still regard them as the equivalent of telephone solicitors in the middle of dinner. ''It is difficult to convince a grower to sell 300 to 500 pounds of grapes,'' said Dave Lustig, 48, a Pasadena computer programmer and secretary of the Cellarmasters, who admits to having driven 23 hours nonstop from the Willamette Valley in Oregon with five tons of pinot noir in a rented Ryder truck. ''In a co-op you can buy a 1,000- or 2,000-pound quantity, so it's easier to be treated like a big boy than someone showing up with garbage pails and a cooler.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark and Mr. Masero said they have had great success obtaining grapes from stellar vineyards, first sampling commercial wines to decide on a growing region, then setting out on a field trip to meet growers. ''You say, 'Man, whatever you're doing to that mourvèdre is so fine,' '' Mr. Clark said. ''You have to establish a rapport. It's about friendships. It also helps to pay cold hard cash.''</p>
        <p>His face was pure ecstasy one night recently as he sat with Mr. Masero at a TV table set up in front of his garage, drinking a 2003 mourvèdre while a pink cascade of sangiovese emanated from the basket press. In Mr. Masero's ''annex,'' Big Bertha, a 110-gallon tank of petite sirah, was improving every day. ''It's pure gold,'' Mr. Clark said. ''You know they are going to give you pleasure for 15 years.''</p>
        <p>In Berkeley, Bonneau Dickson was euphoric, too, as he sat on his porch watching carbon dioxide bubbles percolate through the carboys' air locks. He keeps his windows open at night so he can hear them, the surround-sound of bubbles luring him to dreamland. ''They're nice at night,'' he said. ''They help me sleep. It's like a babbling brook.''</p>
        <p>HAVENS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
