<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Backs Regulating Utility Emissions</title>
    <meta content="14SMOG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/14/business/14smog.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1574011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources Defense Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Service Enterprise Group Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DC163BF937A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Backs Regulating Utility Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pollution Study Favors Regulation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies reports that review of enviromental record of nation's 100 largest electric power companies has found that regulation is more effective in reducing air pollution than voluntary programs are; data show progress in reducing emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide; unregulated carbon dioxide emissions rose substantially in 1990's (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regulation is more effective than relying on voluntary programs to reduce air pollution, according to the authors of a new review of the environmental record of the nation's 100 largest electric power companies.</p>
        <p>The report, to be released today, was sponsored by the Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies, which includes environmental, investor and business groups; the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group; and the Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent of New Jersey's largest utility. It focuses on data collected by the federal government from the utility industry covering 1991 to 2002.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regulation is more effective than relying on voluntary programs to reduce air pollution, according to the authors of a new study.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Regulation is more effective than relying on voluntary programs to reduce air pollution, according to the authors of a new review of the environmental record of the nation's 100 largest electric power companies.</p>
        <p>The report, to be released today, was sponsored by the Coalition for Environmentally Responsible Economies, which includes environmental, investor and business groups; the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group; and the Public Service Enterprise Group, the parent of New Jersey's largest utility. It focuses on data collected by the federal government from the utility industry covering 1991 to 2002.</p>
        <p>The data showed progress in reducing emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide, two federally regulated pollutants that contribute to smog and acid rain and are associated with increased risk of heart and lung disease.</p>
        <p>But unregulated carbon dioxide emissions, which most scientists say are raising the temperature of the atmosphere and contributing to more violent weather, rose substantially in the 1990's. Utilities generate roughly the same amount of carbon dioxide for each kilowatt of power produced that they did in 1991, according to the report.</p>
        <p>''Voluntary programs don't work at all in the utility sector,'' said David G. Hawkins, a former assistant administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency who now directs the climate center at the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins said that the 35 percent decline in sulfur dioxide emissions and the 28 percent decline in nitrogen compounds since 1990 were limited victories given the E.P.A.'s estimates that roughly 30,000 people are still dying prematurely each year from exposure to particulate forms of the two chemicals emitted by power plants.</p>
        <p>American Electric Power, the nation's largest utility and the owner of numerous coal-fired plants, was the largest producer of air pollutants, while Exelon, the fourth-largest utility and a major operator of nuclear power plants, had far lower emissions. For example, American Electric generated 70 percent more power in 2002 than Exelon and emitted 15 times more carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>American Electric, which has advocated relying on voluntary efforts to reduce carbon dioxide emissions, argued yesterday against drawing broad regulatory lessons from such different pollutants.</p>
        <p>Power plants generate almost 70 percent of the sulfur dioxide air pollution, and reasonably priced technology exists to cut such emissions, so imposing regulations like caps on the industry makes sense, said John M. McManus, vice president for environmental services at the company, based in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>But, he said, utilities represent a third of the carbon dioxide emissions; no technology exists to capture carbon dioxide from its smokestacks at a reasonable cost; and other air pollutants are far more potent contributors to global warming.</p>
        <p>Thus, Mr. McManus said, it was sound policy to not focus on power plants in considering what to do about greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The report, titled ''Benchmarking Air Emissions,'' is available at www.nrdc.org.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
