<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="07FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1602206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0DF103CF934A3575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Rebels Killed As Gun Battles Rage in Iraq  Gun battles raged for a second day between a militia force loyal to the radical Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, left, and American and Iraqi forces in Najaf, raising fresh fears of an extended battle that could undermine Iraq's new interim government. Incomplete figures were given for American casualties, but commanders said 300 rebels had been killed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The soldiers charged with mistreatment at Abu Graib prison have defended themselves by saying they were simply following orders, but there have been no witnesses and no evidence to back up that central assertion.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-7</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Rebels Killed As Gun Battles Rage in Iraq  Gun battles raged for a second day between a militia force loyal to the radical Shiite cleric Moktada al-Sadr, left, and American and Iraqi forces in Najaf, raising fresh fears of an extended battle that could undermine Iraq's new interim government. Incomplete figures were given for American casualties, but commanders said 300 rebels had been killed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The soldiers charged with mistreatment at Abu Graib prison have defended themselves by saying they were simply following orders, but there have been no witnesses and no evidence to back up that central assertion.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Israel Reopens Border Crossing  Israel opened a border crossing between the Gaza Strip and Egypt that had been closed for nearly three weeks, allowing most of the more than 2,000 stranded Palestinians to return home. The crossing was closed because Israel believed that Palestinians were planning to attack the site.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Britons Suspends Author  The British Council, which promotes culture and learning around the world, has suspended one of its senior press officers, Harry Cummins, after it emerged that he is suspected of being the author of a series of newspaper commentaries attacking Muslims and denouncing ''the black heart of Islam.''</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Updating U.S. Cold War Base  The United States, Denmark and Greenland signed agreements to upgrade the early warning radar system at Thule, Greenland, an important American air base during the cold war and now a crucial part of the Bush administration's plans for an antimissile defense system.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Chechen Rebel Granted Asylum  Russia accused the United States of undermining the fight against global terrorism by offering political asylum to a leader of Chechen rebels fighting Moscow's rule, Ilyas Akhmadov. Mr. Akhmadov was granted asylum this week after the Department of Homeland Security scrapped an appeal against an earlier decision to grant him asylum.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Divided Nation Deteriorating  Tensions are running high between Georgia and its two separatist regions, and coastal patrol boats are under presidential orders to sink any vessel that may try to make an illegal port visit in Abkhazia, the breakaway region on the northwestern coast.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Timor Convictions Overturned  An Indonesian appeals court has overturned the convictions of three army officers and one policeman for crimes against humanity during violence in 1999 over East Timor's independence that left some 1,500 people dead. The court has also reduced the prison sentence of Eurico Guterres, who led paramilitary gangs recruited by the Indonesian Army.</p>
        <p>A2</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-13, 16</p>
        <p>Terror Suspect Was Sent To U.S., Officials Say  American intelligence officials now believe that Issa al-Hindi, the Al Qaeda operative now in British custody, was dispatched to the United States in early 2001 by Khalid Sheik Mohammed at the direction of Osama bin Laden to case potential targets in New York City.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Papers Allege Detainee Abuse  A brief unsealed in a Seattle courtroom contains an account by a prisoner at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, alleging that he was mistreated in several ways that may have violated the Geneva Conventions.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Searches Unexplained  F.B.I. officials would not explain why the homes of a doctor who has consulted on bioterrorism preparedness were raided, saying only that the man being investigated was not arrested in connection with the 2001 anthrax attacks.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Kerry Energy Plan Criticized  The idea of a United States independent of Middle East oil is a touchstone of John Kerry's campaign and a huge crowd pleaser, but it has divided and exasperated many of his most experienced energy advisers.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>An advertisement by an independent group accusing Mr. Kerry of exaggerating his Vietnam War record came under fire by Democrats as new questions arose about the claims of one of the men calling Mr. Kerry a liar.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Bush Denounces a Perk  President Bush told a convention of 5,000 minority journalists that colleges should not give preferences for admission to the children of alumni, a position that put him at odds with his own history at Yale.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Upgrading Los Angeles Sewers  Los Angeles officials announced that they would comply with an environmental group's demands that they repair the city's dilapidated sewer system, the country's largest, after six years of legal wrangling and millions of dollars in legal fees.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>H.I.V.'s Racial Divide  AIDS is still a killer among African-Americans despite a dramatic decline in death rates from H.I.V./AIDS in the United States over the last eight years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Video to Combat Terror Worries Transit Workers  New Jersey Transit conductors are being rattled by a Federal Transit Administration DVD intended to heighten awareness of potential terrorist activities on their trains. The agency has issued the videos as the Republican National Convention nears and security measures widen.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Many New Yorkers, fearing everything from terrorism to Republicans to congestion, are planning to leave during the convention.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Title Swapping in Albany  The State Senate minority leader, who announced earlier this week that Senator Ada L. Smith of Queens had been removed from a leadership post because of less-than-professional behavior, did not disclose that Senator Smith was merely swapping titles with another senator and would keep her stipend and other privileges.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Beliefs</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>No Hazard Found  The United States Coast Guard stopped the CSAV Rio Puelo, a container ship, off the coast of New Jersey after being alerted of a dangerous substance on board. The Coast Guard found many lemons, but no hazardous substances.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-18</p>
        <p>SPORTSSATURDAY</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Rick James  The unabashedly bawdy funk-rock pioneer was 56.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Job Growth Stalled in July  Job growth ground nearly to a halt last month, the Labor Department reported. Employers added just 32,000 jobs in July, a small fraction of what forecasters had expected and far below the robust gains in employment earlier this year. The news reshaped the political debate over the economy's performance less than three months before election day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Dow dropped 147.70 points, to 9,815.33, 324.38 points below last week's close. The Nasdaq declined 44.74 points, to 1,776.89, 110.47 points lower than last week's close.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>California Air Rule Weaker  California gave some ground to the auto industry in its ambitious plan to regulate global warming emissions from tailpipes, but the state is unlikely to avert a legal challenge.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Adelphia to Accept Bids  Adelphia Communications, which has operated under bankruptcy protection for the last two years, said that it would start accepting bids after Labor Day to buy the company.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Show Goes On Without Martha  Martha Stewart's company is trying to build a following on public television -- without her -- while her show, Martha Stewart Living, is on hold.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials: Bad news on the job front; Kenya's imperiled reform; Verlyn Klinkenborg on victory gardens.</p>
        <p>Column: David Brooks.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B14  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B18  Crossword</p>
        <p>B16  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
