<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Beer Company Responds to the Low-Carb Crowd, Saying Its Product Isn't at Fault</title>
    <meta content="Y24BEE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/24/science/24BEER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1576418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DE123AF937A15757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Beer Company Responds to the Low-Carb Crowd, Saying Its Product Isn't at Fault</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Beer Company Responds to the Low-Carb Crowd</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As if dieting were not complicated enough -- picky eaters who just scraped through high school chemistry are expected to nod knowingly about net carbohydrates as a percentage of glycemic load -- a beer company has now loudly attacked the South Beach diet over a chemical that may or may not lurk in beer and may or may not make any difference if it does.</p>
        <p>That chemical is (cue swirl of violins, please, indicating entrance of villain) maltose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A beer company has loudly attacked the South Beach diet over a chemical that may or may not lurk in beer and may or may not make any difference if it does.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As if dieting were not complicated enough -- picky eaters who just scraped through high school chemistry are expected to nod knowingly about net carbohydrates as a percentage of glycemic load -- a beer company has now loudly attacked the South Beach diet over a chemical that may or may not lurk in beer and may or may not make any difference if it does.</p>
        <p>That chemical is (cue swirl of violins, please, indicating entrance of villain) maltose.</p>
        <p>Maltose is actually a dull workhorse of a sugar. It has been around for at least as long as grain and rain have, which is to say, for millions of years before Homo sapiens arrived and exploited it to invent beer. It is created when grain is wetted down and allowed to sprout -- or malt -- before being fermented into alcohol.</p>
        <p>To describe it with a bit more chem-lab panache, maltose is a disaccharide and divides in the intestine into two molecules of glucose. That's where the villainy comes in. Aficionados of the South Beach, Atkins and other low-carbohydrate diets say glucose is evil. Spikes in blood glucose, the prevailing theory goes, lead to overproduction of insulin, creating uncontrollable cravings for sweet food.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Anheuser-Busch took out full-page advertisements in 31 newspapers, including The New York Times.</p>
        <p>''The South Beach Diet book recommends against drinking beer, claiming that it's high in maltose,'' the advertisements read. ''Yet independent testing shows that beer does not contain maltose. So go ahead and enjoy a beer, even when you're watching your carbs.''</p>
        <p>In interviews and press material, the brewer cited chemists who back their contention that fermentation converts virtually all the maltose into alcohol and carbon dioxide. Beers do contain calories and carbohydrates, the company concedes. Light beers contain 7 grams of carbohydrates and 100 calories per 12-ounce serving. Regular beers contain 10 grams of carbs and 160 calories.</p>
        <p>But, Anheuser-Busch argued, dieters who drink responsibly should not feel overwhelmed by ''carb guilt.''</p>
        <p>''We're not saying drinking beer will make you lose weight,'' a spokesman, Francine Katz, said. ''We think beer has gotten a bad rap, and we'd like it corrected.''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview yesterday, Dr. Arthur Agatston, author of ''The South Beach Diet,'' conceded that Anheuser-Busch was generally right about maltose. In his book, Dr. Agatston said ''the king of all sugars, the one that increases blood sugar faster than any other, is maltose, which exists in beer.''</p>
        <p>Since Anheuser-Busch began complaining in February, he said, he hired a graduate student to look into the question.</p>
        <p>''There is maltose in beer, but most of it is fermented out,'' the doctor said. ''The amount varies, but it doesn't play a part in the beer belly.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Agatston called the issue ''a red herring.''</p>
        <p>''The fact is that beer is fattening,'' he said. ''And that's why they've come out with low-carb beer.''</p>
        <p>Two obesity experts agreed that arguing over maltose, or even beer, missed the point of a healthy diet.</p>
        <p>''This is making a mountain out of a molehill,'' said Dr. Thomas M. S. Wolever, acting chairman of the nutritional science department at the University of Toronto.</p>
        <p>A typical beer, Dr. Wolever said, has the same carbohydrate load as two teaspoons of sugar or two-thirds of a slice of bread. A sugary soda pop has about four times as much. But, he noted, the two drinks have about the same number of calories, because alcohol has more calories per gram than carbohydrates do. In a typical diet of 240 grams of carbohydrates a day, he said, a 10-gram beer ''is not a huge issue.''</p>
        <p>''But,'' Dr. Wolever added, ''if you're really trying to limit carbs, you should stick to a low-carb beer.''</p>
        <p>Dr. David S. Ludwig, a professor of pediatrics at the Harvard Medical School and the founder of obesity programs at Children's Hospital in Boston, agreed that ''light beer is the way to go'' for low-carbohydrate diets. Dr. Ludwig cautioned that with beer's relatively many calories from alcohol, ''this shouldn't be taken as a license to drink without limit and think you're not affecting your caloric balance.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
