<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Oil Prices Rise, a Sense of Alarm in Asia</title>
    <meta content="10ASEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/10/business/worldbusiness/10asean.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Investment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Association of Southeast Asian Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Association of Southeast Asian Nations</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Asean</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DA1730F933A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Oil Prices Rise, a Sense of Alarm in Asia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">As Oil Prices Rise, a Sense of Alarm in Asia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE, June 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Asian nations have sense of alarm about security of oil supplies in region that counts on Middle East for no less than half of its oil; recent terrorist attacks in Saudi Arabia have awakened region to possibility that attack on Middle East oil shipments could deprive region of oil at any price; energy ministers from Southeast Asia meet in Manila with counterparts from China, Japan and South Korea to discuss how they might cooperate to reduce that risk; Association of Southeast Asian Nations organized meeting; Asean ministers agree to improve climate for investment in oil exploration and infrastructure and to raise amount of power derived from renewable energy sources to 10 percent in next six years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thailand has imposed a curfew on its gasoline stations. Once free to stay open around the clock, gas stations will now be required to close from 10 p.m. to 5 a.m.</p>
        <p>The new rules, which the government introduced this week, are part of a broader effort to curb fuel consumption as record-high oil prices put the bite on Thailand's economy. In addition to putting its pumps to bed at night, Thailand plans to raise taxes on gas-guzzling automobiles and switch off billboard lights at midnight to conserve electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Asia, there are signs of the spreading sense of alarm about the security of oil supplies in the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thailand has imposed a curfew on its gasoline stations. Once free to stay open around the clock, gas stations will now be required to close from 10 p.m. to 5 a.m.</p>
        <p>The new rules, which the government introduced this week, are part of a broader effort to curb fuel consumption as record-high oil prices put the bite on Thailand's economy. In addition to putting its pumps to bed at night, Thailand plans to raise taxes on gas-guzzling automobiles and switch off billboard lights at midnight to conserve electricity.</p>
        <p>Small measures, perhaps, but signs of the spreading sense of alarm around Asia about the security of oil supplies in a region that counts on the Middle East for no less than half of its oil, according to Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>While the rapid rise in oil prices to their highest in two decades stands to dent regional economic growth -- particularly if they hurt global demand for Asian exports -- recent terrorist attacks in Saudi Arabia have awakened the region to the possibility that an attack on Middle Eastern oil shipments could deprive the region of oil at any price.</p>
        <p>''Just that one small event would really have quite a catastrophic effect,'' said Adrian Loh, an oil analyst at Merrill Lynch in Singapore.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday in Manila, energy ministers from Southeast Asia met with counterparts from China, Japan and South Korea to discuss how they might cooperate to reduce that risk. The Association of Southeast Asian Nations, or Asean, organized the meeting under its Asean plus 3 initiative with its three larger northern trading partners. Asean includes Brunei, Cambodia, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Myanmar, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam. In a joint statement, the ministers said they resolved to improve energy security by diversifying their sources of energy and promoting a freer market for trading oil products. Most significantly, the ministers said Asean was studying ways to create oil stockpiles that members could use in case of supply disruptions.</p>
        <p>Ministers of Asean agreed separately to improve the climate for investment in oil exploration and infrastructure and to raise the amount of power derived from renewable energy sources to 10 percent in the next six years.</p>
        <p>Southeast Asia's problem is that its reliance on Middle Eastern oil, high as it is, is getting worse. Its economies are growing at an average rate of 6 percent and the Asean Center for Energy in Jakarta estimates that Southeast Asia's total energy demand will more than double in 20 years. Despite efforts to promote the use of natural gas as an alternative to imported oil, the center projects that oil will continue to be the region's largest source of energy even as the region's own oil production declines.</p>
        <p>Southeast Asia also buys oil from West African nations like Nigeria and Angola, but the distances involved make it more expensive. So, too, with oil from the Americas.</p>
        <p>As a result, Southeast Asia shares with Japan and South Korea a dependence on Middle Eastern oil imports.</p>
        <p>Middle Eastern suppliers take advantage of the situation by charging Asian buyers up to $1.50 more a barrel than they do buyers in the United States and Europe, analysts say.</p>
        <p>''Business is business,'' said Kurtubi, who uses only one name and is the director of the Center for Petroleum and Energy Economics Studies in Jakarta. ''Asian buyers pay more.''</p>
        <p>That Southeast Asia is beholden to the Middle East for its oil may surprise students of history who remember that it was to secure Southeast Asia's oil, among other precious commodities, that helped drive imperial Japan to invade in the years leading up to World War II.</p>
        <p>But the region's rapid industrialization since has outstripped its ability to find and exploit new sources of oil. Southeast Asia now has fewer oil reserves than Europe. Only tiny Brunei and Malaysia produce more oil than they consume. Indonesia, Southeast Asia's largest oil producer and its only member in the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries, this year became a net oil importer for the first time as aging wells dry up and investment in new ones dwindles.</p>
        <p>Southeast Asia has a relative abundance of natural gas reserves, but more than half of these are tucked around the more than 17,000 islands that make up Indonesia, where political and regulatory uncertainty make recovery a risky undertaking. As a result, Southeast Asia has few ways to get its natural gas to the urban centers where it is needed or ways to use it once it gets there.</p>
        <p>''The problem with gas is that by its very nature it's a difficult commodity,'' said Mr. Loh at Merrill. ''Once you bring it out of the ground, you either have to liquefy it straight away or put it in a pipe. And you're not going to build a massive pipe without a contract that backs you up.''</p>
        <p>Indonesia is the world's largest exporter of liquefied natural gas, which, because contracts are priced relative to oil, means that Indonesia still benefits from higher oil prices despite the fact that it has to import more crude than it exports.</p>
        <p>Most Indonesian liquefied natural gas, however, goes not to Southeast Asia but to Japan and South Korea. Building more plants to liquefy natural gas is prohibitively expensive, as are terminals to receive the liquid natural gas and turn it back into gas. Both require first securing buyers willing to commit to contracts of up to 30 years.</p>
        <p>So do pipelines. Asean envisions someday having a network of gas pipelines crisscrossing Southeast Asia, enabling the region to have a spot market for natural gas like those already established in Europe and the United States.</p>
        <p>While pipelines have been built to get gas from Indonesia to Singapore and Malaysia, most pipeline construction has been held up by the same concerns preventing exploration or construction of liquefied natural gas plants: Indonesia is too volatile to interest buyers in 25-year commitments.</p>
        <p>Oil from the Middle East, therefore, remains Southeast Asia's most readily available source of energy -- until something interrupts the flow, that is.</p>
        <p>While some oil companies in Southeast Asia maintain reserve supplies of oil, the region has nothing similar to the strategic oil reserves maintained in the United States, Japan and South Korea. Now that China has announced its intention to begin stockpiling oil, Southeast Asia's ministers are getting help from Japan and South Korea on how to set up stockpiles.</p>
        <p>Efforts are also under way to derive more power from renewable energy sources. Singapore is experimenting with both natural-gas powered vehicles and vehicles using hydrogen fuel cells. Thailand this week signed a contract with BP to develop a $20 million solar power project to supply electricity to rural areas. It also has a program to promote the use of agricultural wastes, like rice husks, to produce biomass fuel.</p>
        <p>Thailand, in the meantime, is trying to alleviate the pressure of higher oil prices on its consumer-led economic boom. While Thailand is the only country in Southeast Asia that has managed to shift from oil to natural gas for most of its electricity, its heavy demand for gasoline and diesel fuel makes it the economy most vulnerable in the region to higher oil prices, analysts say.</p>
        <p>In January, after prices for gasoline started climbing, the government started subsidizing gas prices. It has spent at least 13 billion baht ($320 million) so far, according to the country's Energy Policy and Planning Office. This week, the government raised the price of gasoline to the equivalent of $1.70 a gallon, but analysts said it was unlikely to let pump prices rise too high with a general election due in less than a year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
