<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Amazon at Risk</title>
    <meta content="31TUE3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/31/opinion/31tue3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1676640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Amazon River Basin</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lula Da Silva, Luis Inacio (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Mendes, Chico</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DC1F39F932A05756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Amazon at Risk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Amazon at Risk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says destruction of world's largest tropical forest, the Amazon, is proceeding apace; calls in Pres Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva to persuade country's agricultural oligarchy that rain forest is not commodity to be exploited for private gain</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even the government of Brazil seemed shocked by the news that despite efforts to curb deforestation -- including a $140 million package of conservation measures announced last year -- the destruction of the world's largest tropical forest, the Amazon, proceeds apace. In the 12-month period ending last August, farming and logging, much if it illegal, destroyed 10,000 square miles of forest, an area almost the size of Massachusetts. This was the biggest one-year loss since 1995, when the Amazon shrank by about 11,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>Most of the Amazon lies in Brazil, but its destruction has been a matter of global concern ever since the 1980's, when satellite photographs documenting widespread burning of the forest first appeared. Like tropical forests everywhere, the Amazon is a storehouse of biodiversity, a source of medicines and an important antidote to global warming. Healthy forests absorb greenhouse gases. Blazing forests increase them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brazil's president must persuade himself and his country's agricultural oligarchy that the rain forest is not a commodity to be exploited for private gain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even the government of Brazil seemed shocked by the news that despite efforts to curb deforestation -- including a $140 million package of conservation measures announced last year -- the destruction of the world's largest tropical forest, the Amazon, proceeds apace. In the 12-month period ending last August, farming and logging, much if it illegal, destroyed 10,000 square miles of forest, an area almost the size of Massachusetts. This was the biggest one-year loss since 1995, when the Amazon shrank by about 11,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>Most of the Amazon lies in Brazil, but its destruction has been a matter of global concern ever since the 1980's, when satellite photographs documenting widespread burning of the forest first appeared. Like tropical forests everywhere, the Amazon is a storehouse of biodiversity, a source of medicines and an important antidote to global warming. Healthy forests absorb greenhouse gases. Blazing forests increase them.</p>
        <p>The struggle to save the Amazon has claimed many victims, notably Chico Mendes, an environmentalist shot to death by two ranchers in 1988, and Dorothy Stang, an American-born nun and advocate for the forest and for peasant farmers who was gunned down earlier this year. Brazilian authorities have been intermittently responsive, setting aside forest preserves, ending subsidies to cattle ranchers and passing laws requiring landowners to leave much of their forest land untouched.</p>
        <p>But the Amazon seems largely immune to law, especially in a country where there are not nearly enough police to enforce the rules, where economic growth seems to supersede everything and where powerful local politicians tend to have more influence than the national government.</p>
        <p>Right now, for instance, the biggest single threat to the Amazon is the explosive growth of soybean farming in the state of Mato Grosso on the forest's southern fringe, fueled mainly by soaring demand in China and Europe. As it happens, Mato Grosso's governor, Blairo Maggi, is also its soybean king -- o rei da soja -- who has been quoted as saying that a 40 percent increase in deforestation in Mato Grosso ''doesn't mean anything at all, and I don't feel the slightest guilt over what we are doing here.''</p>
        <p>There are people in the Brazilian government, in particular its environmental minister, Marina Silva, who believe there are better ways to assist Brazil's economy than by turning a valuable rain forest into cattle feed, which is essentially what Mr. Maggi is doing. But they need help -- from multilateral lending agencies and corporations, which should make sound environmental practices a condition of future investment, and from environmental organizations, which must keep up the public pressure.</p>
        <p>Most of all they need help from Brazil's charismatic president, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, who must persuade himself and his country's agricultural oligarchy that the rain forest is not a commodity to be exploited for private gain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
