<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lean Cuisine: Can I Put My Oven on a Diet?</title>
    <meta content="17cooks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/17/garden/17cooks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1718155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CLOSE TO HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Thanksgiving Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Thanksgiving Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDF113EF934A25752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lean Cuisine: Can I Put My Oven on a Diet?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lean Cuisine: Can I Put My Oven on a Diet?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH BALDWIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a hard-core New Englander, I was raised to view the local oil company as the enemy and heating as something one resorts to only after donning thermal underwear and a wool vest. It was so cold in our house it took an extra day to defrost the Thanksgiving turkey; one uncle used to show up for the big meal in his shirt sleeves and make an elaborate ritual of putting on his down vest before joining the table.</p>
        <p>Today, with the cost of natural gas having ticked up at warp speed, the game is taken to a new level. Now that I've cut the lard out of our heating by setting the thermostat at 62, I have no other choice: the gas range is going to have to take a hit, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If your guests are sincere about the energy crisis, they will be happy with cold cuts and broccoli spears.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a hard-core New Englander, I was raised to view the local oil company as the enemy and heating as something one resorts to only after donning thermal underwear and a wool vest. It was so cold in our house it took an extra day to defrost the Thanksgiving turkey; one uncle used to show up for the big meal in his shirt sleeves and make an elaborate ritual of putting on his down vest before joining the table.</p>
        <p>Today, with the cost of natural gas having ticked up at warp speed, the game is taken to a new level. Now that I've cut the lard out of our heating by setting the thermostat at 62, I have no other choice: the gas range is going to have to take a hit, too.</p>
        <p>In recent years my husband, Irwin, a k a the Indulgent Host, has become a sucker for those fashionable slow-cooked dishes that dally in the oven all day as if time weren't money. Pork belly braised until it oozes, short ribs simmered to the melting point in three quarts of wine, duck rendered tender by a leisurely bath in its own fat.  Does he think B.T.U.'s grow on trees?</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's Energy Star program has been wrestling with this very issue as part of its appliance labeling. When asked to help calculate the true costs of a Thanksgiving meal, a team there went to work. Two days later, Maria T. Vargas, a spokeswoman, called back with their crunched numbers: the stove alone will gobble up some 200,000 B.T.U.'s. In electricity, that's 35 kilowatt hours. Or in terms a ConEd consumer would understand, $10.14.</p>
        <p>That tidy figure does not include the real activity on a feast day -- incidentals like chilling the wine, microwaving the sweet potato casserole, whipping the cream, plugging in the coffeemaker and running the dishwasher the customary seven or eight times. Those activities will drain the grid of another 25 kilowatt hours.</p>
        <p>Even a cheapskate like me can handle $17.28 for fuel when feeding a crowd. But most evenings it's him and me and the latest recipe for slow-cooked whatever. A watt here, a watt there: after a while it adds up.</p>
        <p>Besides, there are those penguin habitats to worry about. Burning 200,000 B.T.U.'s generates 25 pounds of greenhouse gases, I learned, and 35 kilowatt hours twice that much. ''It's a big 'aha' for people that their homes are responsible for greenhouse gases -- twice as much as their car,'' Ms. Vargas said.</p>
        <p>Entertaining, which I used to think of as a satisfying alternative to being gouged by restaurants, has lost its allure. Forget Paula Wolfert's Seven-Hour Lamb. Think of it as Lamb With Seven Cubic Feet of Gas.</p>
        <p>Rummaging through old cookbooks, I found a Chinese recipe more in keeping with the times. It yields one poached chicken and was probably developed by peasants who had to do all their cooking over a lump of coal. You simply immerse your chicken in flavored broth, simmer it for 15 minutes, cover and -- this is my favorite part -- turn off the heat. It will finish cooking all by itself, eventually.</p>
        <p>Poached chicken, of course, doesn't really hold a candle to crowd pleasers like Chinese spareribs, which are best prepared in what I've come to think of as a kitchen triathlon. First Irwin blanches them over a flagrantly open flame, then roasts them forever. As if this weren't enough, he gives them a final crisping under the extravagant blue heat of an infrared broiler. They aren't spareribs; they're gas guzzlers.</p>
        <p>For those who want to dazzle guests with artisanal pizza, my advice is: Don't try this at home. Cook's Illustrated wants you to preheat your artisanal pizza stone for an hour at 500 degrees. It probably takes less fuel to fly to Rome.</p>
        <p>If your guests are sincere about the energy crisis, they will be happy with cold cuts and broccoli spears. Serve them with barely hot toddies and a nice, warm scarf.</p>
        <p>CLOSE TO HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
