<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenhouse Gas Pact Is in Disarray</title>
    <meta content="16emissions" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/16/nyregion/16emissions.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1725252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources Defense Council</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1D61F31F935A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenhouse Gas Pact Is in Disarray</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Greenhouse Gas Pact Is in Disarray</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials in New York, New Jersey and several other Northeastern states scrambled yesterday to hold together what was left of a landmark regional pact to control power plant emissions after the governors of Massachusetts and Rhode Island abruptly refused to sign on.</p>
        <p>The officials said they hoped to go ahead with the agreement without losing any of the seven remaining states in the regional agreement, which would limit carbon dioxide emissions linked to global climate change. The first agreement of its kind in the nation, the market-driven system of emissions limits and tradable pollution allowances was widely considered a symbolic rebuff to the Bush administration's hands-off position on global climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials in New York, New Jersey and several Northeastern states tried to salvage a regional pact to control power plant emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Officials in New York, New Jersey and several other Northeastern states scrambled yesterday to hold together what was left of a landmark regional pact to control power plant emissions after the governors of Massachusetts and Rhode Island abruptly refused to sign on.</p>
        <p>The officials said they hoped to go ahead with the agreement without losing any of the seven remaining states in the regional agreement, which would limit carbon dioxide emissions linked to global climate change. The first agreement of its kind in the nation, the market-driven system of emissions limits and tradable pollution allowances was widely considered a symbolic rebuff to the Bush administration's hands-off position on global climate change.</p>
        <p>But the abrupt departure of two of the states that have been linked in the agreement since it was announced by Gov. George E. Pataki more than two and a half years ago set off a round of political speculation.</p>
        <p>Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts, a Republican who is expected to run for his party's presidential nomination in 2008, pulled his state out of the agreement yesterday, hours before the deadline for reaching an agreement, and just before announcing that he would not run for a second term next year.</p>
        <p>He said in a telephone interview yesterday that Massachusetts corporate leaders had told him that the pact did not protect businesses and customers from increased energy costs that would result if emissions caps were imposed.</p>
        <p>By painting the regional initiative as hurting business, Mr. Romney seemed to seek to distance himself from other potential rivals for the Republican nomination, including Mr. Pataki and Senator John McCain, who have supported programs that control heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Romney said his decision was based on economic and not political concerns. ''These are matters that affect our environment and our economy,'' he said. ''They're too important to be considered in a political light.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists were stunned and angered by Governor Romney's decision. ''By taking the side of polluters to advance his own political ambitions, Governor Romney has sold out the citizens of Massachusetts and failed the country,'' Frances Beinecke, executive director of the Natural Resources Defense Council, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the power industry who oppose emission limits said the problems in the Northeast suggested how difficult it would be to establish a national program.</p>
        <p>Gov. Donald L. Carcieri of Rhode Island said through a spokesman that he had not signed the agreement at this time because he shared Governor Romney's concerns about its impact on energy prices.</p>
        <p>And contrary to earlier reports that Connecticut would also drop out of the pact, Gov. M. Jodi Rell of Connecticut announced that she would sign the agreement, calling it a ''historic milestone'' that addressed climate change while protecting customers from sharply increased energy costs.</p>
        <p>The other states involved are Delaware, Maine, New Hampshire and Vermont.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, the nine states would have modestly reduced carbon dioxide emissions from power plants in the region by 2020. Each state would have its own emissions cap, and limits would be set on the amount of carbon dioxide that operators could release. They could accumulate unused excess allowances by running their cleanest plants, and then sell or trade the allowances to other operators in an open market.</p>
        <p>Over the last several weeks, Mr. Romney had expressed reservations about the plan, insisting that it needed to limit how much power generators would have to pay if they exceeded their pollution allowances.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month Mr. Romney asked for negotiations to be prolonged past a Dec. 1 deadline. Massachusetts and the other states negotiated intensely and thought they had reached an agreement on a proposal to limit the cost of pollution allowances, thereby protecting customers.</p>
        <p>If prices exceeded $7 a ton of carbon dioxide emissions, generators would have had additional opportunities to offset emissions by supporting environmentally sound projects, like recovering methane gas from landfills, anywhere in the country.</p>
        <p>If allowance prices rose above $10 a ton, the offset projects the operators supported could have been anywhere in the world.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Romney rejected the plan on Wednesday, over the advice of his advisers, prompting officials in other states to wonder whether he had ever intended to accept them at all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney defended his actions. ''I've been in the deal business all my life,'' said Mr. Romney, a former businessman who headed the 2002 Salt Lake City Olympics. ''A deal is not a deal until everybody's agreed on it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney said Massachusetts had adopted its own state carbon restriction program that will take effect next year, and it will have the kind of limits he wanted to see in the regional agreement.</p>
        <p>For Governor Pataki, the loss of the two states is a setback, but a spokesman, David Catalfamo, said it did not weaken Mr. Pataki's political clout. ''I don't think this hurts him at all,'' Mr. Catalfamo said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki disagreed strongly with Mr. Romney's contention that the emissions pact would be bad for business. And New York business leaders said that the states still in the pact had a chance to create business opportunities through clean energy and compete with European companies.</p>
        <p>Bradley M. Campbell, commissioner of the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection, said the loss of two states was a temporary setback and would not undermine the states' message that they were willing to act on climate change even if the Bush administration was not.</p>
        <p>''By moving forward we will inevitably attract other states,'' Mr. Campbell said. He thought that whoever followed Mr. Romney in the Massachusetts Statehouse would most likely agree to join the regional pact.</p>
        <p>''They will see that we are developing a structure that can effectively reduce CO2 emissions,'' he said, ''and at the same time increase, not diminish, economic opportunities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
