<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vote Nearing, Clean Air Bill Prompts Rush Of Lobbying</title>
    <meta content="15ENVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/15/politics/15enviro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1650098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DF123AF936A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vote Nearing, Clean Air Bill Prompts Rush Of Lobbying</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vote Nearing, Clean Air Bill Prompts Rush of Lobbying</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heart-shaped boxes of Valentine's Day sweets sent by environmental groups reached Senate offices by Monday, but they came with distinctly sour words for the Clear Skies Act of 2005: ''Clearly a sweetheart deal for polluters.''</p>
        <p>A day earlier, union members fanned out across Illinois in support of Clear Skies, the Bush administration's preferred approach to pollution reduction. They distributed fliers intended to influence the state's freshman Democratic senator, Barack Obama, who is on the committee handling the measure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The burst of activity by forces for and against the Clear Skies Act of 2005 reflects the approaching showdown over it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heart-shaped boxes of Valentine's Day sweets sent by environmental groups reached Senate offices by Monday, but they came with distinctly sour words for the Clear Skies Act of 2005: ''Clearly a sweetheart deal for polluters.''</p>
        <p>A day earlier, union members fanned out across Illinois in support of Clear Skies, the Bush administration's preferred approach to pollution reduction. They distributed fliers intended to influence the state's freshman Democratic senator, Barack Obama, who is on the committee handling the measure.</p>
        <p>The burst of activity by forces for and against the bill reflects the approaching showdown over it.</p>
        <p>Senator James M. Inhofe, Republican of Oklahoma and chairman of the Committee on Environment and Public Works, has scheduled final consideration of the bill for Wednesday, followed by a vote. Committee members have been deadlocked 9 to 9, an impasse that will doom the measure unless the Republican leadership, through a special procedure, gives it floor time for debate.</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Inhofe is holding to his plan, expressing optimism that continuing discussions may lead one opponent to switch sides. The split largely follows party lines, with Senator Lincoln Chafee, a Rhode Island Republican who prefers an alternative approach, expected to join the committee's seven Democrats and the ranking member, Senator James M. Jeffords, an independent from Vermont, in opposing the measure.</p>
        <p>Most major health and environmental groups oppose the bill, arguing that the promised reductions of sulfur dioxide, nitrogen oxides and mercury could be achieved faster through other approaches, including a bill co-sponsored by Mr. Chafee and Senator Thomas R. Carper, Democrat of Delaware. Many of the groups also favor legislation that includes caps on carbon dioxide, a heat-trapping gas that scientists say contributes to global warming.</p>
        <p>Besides the Valentine's candy, environmental groups began running advertisements against the bill in publications widely read by lawmakers and others active on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>The large unions that are strongly supporting the bill say economic benefits and job stability would derive from a law that forces power plants to spend billions of dollars for technological upgrades to lower pollution. One of the unions, the Teamsters, is promoting the measure through a partnership with the Council of Republicans for Environmental Advocacy, a partisan group that supports a balanced approach to improving the environment.</p>
        <p>As part of the campaign, Teamsters began hanging tens of thousands of fliers on doorknobs in Illinois, aimed at persuading Mr. Obama to support the bill in committee.</p>
        <p>The fliers include a tear-off postcard to mail to Mr. Obama that reads: ''You made an admirable pledge to be the nonpartisan leader for all of Illinois. Thank you for your commitment.''</p>
        <p>''A vote for S.131,'' it continues, referring to the measure, ''is an opportunity to demonstrate that commitment. Unlike alternative proposals, S.131 is a vote for both clean air and jobs in Illinois and throughout America. Please vote yes for Clear Skies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Obama, the only Democrat among the five freshmen on the committee, has talked openly in committee hearings about intense competing interests in his state, where environmental passions are matched with constant worries about the loss of manufacturing jobs and rising fuel costs.</p>
        <p>While he has suggested that enforcing the Clean Air Act, as is, may produce more beneficial environmental effects than Clear Skies, he has expressed the need ''to have an honest debate.'' To some supporters of the bill, the comment represented an open-mindedness that they believe other Democrats lack.</p>
        <p>''He's a new senator who has not yet taken a position on Clear Skies,'' said Doug Wheeler, a consultant to the partnership between the Teamsters and the Republican group. ''He stated in his campaign that it's important to balance environmental quality with jobs, particularly in an industrial state where jobs are at risk.''</p>
        <p>Efforts to reach Mr. Obama for comment were unsuccessful. Phone messages left with his offices in Washington and Chicago were not returned.</p>
        <p>John M. Stanton, a lawyer with Clear the Air, an environmental group, said union support for Clear Skies under the promise of job stability was misguided.</p>
        <p>''If they supported the more stringent Clean Air Act regulations,'' Mr. Stanton said, ''there'd be even more work. Besides, why would unions support a measure that impacts union families adversely? Many of the blue-collar communities where union members live are located close to power plants. Logically, I don't think you would put those families in harm's way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
