<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Making of a Vegetarian: A Dinosaur Is Caught in the Act</title>
    <meta content="05DINO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/05/science/05dino.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1670058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Utah</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEEDD1730F936A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Making of a Vegetarian: A Dinosaur Is Caught in the Act</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Making of a Vegetarian: A Dinosaur Is Caught in the Act</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paleontologists in Utah announce discovery of new species of dinosaur in intermediate stage between carnivore and herbivore; speculate on reason for change but note that it occurred in time of global warming and arrival of flowering plants in profusion; fossil of species, named Falcarius utahensis, shows beginnings of features associated with plant-eating dinosaurs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Without government nutrition guidelines, a doctor's advice or some primeval diet fad, entire species of dinosaurs sometimes forsook their predatory, meat-eating lifestyle and evolved into grazing vegetarians. Scientists now think they have found rare evidence of a species undergoing just such a dietary transition 125 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Paleontologists in Utah announced yesterday that they had discovered a new species of dinosaurs in an intermediate stage between carnivore and herbivore, on the way to becoming a committed vegetarian. They could only speculate on the reasons for the change, but noted that it occurred in a time of global warming and the arrival of flowering plants in profusion, a tempting new food source.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists think they have found rare evidence of a dinosaur species undergoing a dietary transition into vegetarianism 125 million years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Without government nutrition guidelines, a doctor's advice or some primeval diet fad, entire species of dinosaurs sometimes forsook their predatory, meat-eating lifestyle and evolved into grazing vegetarians. Scientists now think they have found rare evidence of a species undergoing just such a dietary transition 125 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Paleontologists in Utah announced yesterday that they had discovered a new species of dinosaurs in an intermediate stage between carnivore and herbivore, on the way to becoming a committed vegetarian. They could only speculate on the reasons for the change, but noted that it occurred in a time of global warming and the arrival of flowering plants in profusion, a tempting new food source.</p>
        <p>Dr. James I. Kirkland, a paleontologist with the Utah Geological Survey, said the new species, named Falcarius utahensis, was uncovered two years ago at a remote dig site near the town of Green River. The animal, about 13 feet long and 4 1/2 feet tall, was a primitive member of the therizinosaur group of feathered dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>Under closer examination, Dr. Kirkland said, the Falcarius fossils showed ''the beginnings of features we associate with plant-eating dinosaurs.'' The teeth were not the sharp, bladelike serrated teeth of the typical predator, but smaller and adapted for shredding leaves. ''I doubt that this animal could have cut a steak,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Other characteristics of an animal in transition to herbivory included an expansion of the gut to digest the mass of fermenting plants, stouter legs for supporting a bulkier body instead of the slender legs of a fast-running predator, and a lengthening of the neck, perhaps to reach for leaves higher in the trees.</p>
        <p>Dr. Scott D. Sampson, chief curator of the Museum of Natural History at the University of Utah, said the new fossils were ''amazing documentation of a major dietary shift'' and promised to ''tell us how this shift happened.''</p>
        <p>The scientists described and interpreted the findings in interviews and a teleconference from Salt Lake City. A detailed report is being published today in the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mark A. Norell, a dinosaur specialist at the American Museum of Natural History who was not involved in the research, said the fossils were well preserved and the teeth appeared to be similar to those of plant-eating dinosaurs. But he questioned how much scientists would be able to learn from the specimen about the change from meat eating to plant eating.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sampson said, ''Falcarius represents evolution caught in the act, a primitive form that shares much in common with its carnivorous kin, while possessing a variety of features demonstrating that it had embarked on the path toward more advanced plant-eating forms.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Norell agreed that the new species ''is a very important and interesting animal,'' primarily because it is a rare early example of the therizinosaur group in North America. Falcarius is anatomically more primitive than the better-known therizinosaurs that were prevalent in China about 90 million years ago and had already evolved as plant eaters.</p>
        <p>Lindsay E. Zanno, a doctoral student in paleontology at Utah, said Falcarius was ''the most primitive known therizinosaur, demonstrating unequivocally that this large-bodied group of bizarre herbivorous dinosaurs'' came from predatory carnivores like the swift, fierce Velociraptor. Falcarius and Velociraptor had a common ancestor.</p>
        <p>Scientists say all the vegetarian dinosaurs evolved from ancestors that were carnivores. Some 230 million years ago, the first dinosaur was presumably a small-bodied, fleet-footed predator. Then two major groups of dinosaurs, the gigantic species and the smaller duck-billed grazers, evolved as plant eaters.</p>
        <p>As for Falcarius, scientists are not sure what it ate, meat or plants or both, and they suspect that the transition extended over several million years.</p>
        <p>But with Falcarius, Dr. Sampson said, ''we have actual fossil evidence of a major dietary shift, certainly the best example documented among dinosaurs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
