<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You Care About Palau, This Is a Good Place to Be</title>
    <meta content="11NATI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/11/international/asia/11nations.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1686500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="United Nations Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Palau</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Palau</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Palau</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D6153DF932A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You Care About Palau, This Is a Good Place to Be</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">If You Care About Palau, This Is a Good Place to Be</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, July 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Stuart J. Beck, a Manhattan television company executive, becoming an ambassador at the United Nations was not the problem it can be for Americans with diplomatic ambitions.</p>
        <p>He sailed through his legislative hearings without a single objection being raised and promptly took up his post last year alongside the other 190 ambassadors here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Stuart J. Beck becoming an ambassador was not the problem it can be for Americans with diplomatic ambitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Stuart J. Beck, a Manhattan television company executive, becoming an ambassador at the United Nations was not the problem it can be for Americans with diplomatic ambitions.</p>
        <p>He sailed through his legislative hearings without a single objection being raised and promptly took up his post last year alongside the other 190 ambassadors here.</p>
        <p>But where his experience was significantly different from the long confirmation struggles of recent American envoys like Richard C. Holbrooke and John D. Negroponte and the current nominee, John R. Bolton, so was the country he represents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck, 58, a Long Island-born graduate of Yale Law School who lives in Bronxville, N.Y., is the permanent representative of tiny Palau, in the Pacific.</p>
        <p>Palau is a nation of 300 islands, 20,000 people, 1,500 species of fish, 700 varieties of coral and no disputatious interest groups with competing stakes in who speaks for it at the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Only nine of Palau's islands are inhabited, and its chain of lush jungle-covered rock islands that appear to be sunbathing on the ocean's emerald surface are populated by birds, bats, monkeys, crocodiles and stingless jellyfish.</p>
        <p>The last country in the world to shed its colonial status officially, it became independent in 1994 and appointed Mr. Beck its first ambassador to the United Nations last year.</p>
        <p>He had been a legal adviser to Palau when it was still administered by the United States in the late 1970's, at the outset of its quest for independence, and in 1983 he married a Palauan woman, Tulik, now the mother of the couple's four children.</p>
        <p>Visiting the island with his family two years ago, he suggested that the best way to validate the country's new sovereignty would be to take up its seat at the United Nations.</p>
        <p>''I said to them, 'Look, you don't produce anything, you don't manufacture anything, nobody's after your labor pool, you don't have anything that anyone wants, the U.S. already has defense and basing rights, so the only thing of value you have is your U.N. vote,''' he said. ''So they said to me, 'Why don't you do it?'''</p>
        <p>Gregarious and brashly glad of hand, Mr. Beck goes about his United Nations rounds with almost childlike wonder. ''I grew up in New York,'' he said. ''The U.N.'s a big deal. For all the carping and all the criticism, this chance to be a member of the 191-nation club is a wonderful thing. I love the General Assembly with all its different people speaking different languages and dressed in different clothes and the fact that if you want to do business with Japan or Brazil, you just get up from your seat and walk 100 feet.''</p>
        <p>The Palau he first encountered in 1977 had a high commissioner, a flag, a golf course, lots of scuba diving and no phones.</p>
        <p>The country he represents today is busy turning itself into a tourist spot for vacationing Asians and replacing its shantytown capital city on its most populous island, Koror, with a new capital on its largest island, Babeldaob. The jungle site has yet to be cleared, but the completed government building, a spanking white, domed replica of the United States Capitol, already stands in its midst.</p>
        <p>''As China and the Asian middle class grows, Palau will be their Bermuda,'' Mr. Beck said. ''Taiwanese who want to get married on a tropical island already think of Palau as a hot destination.''</p>
        <p>He also cited its location as one of growing strategic importance for the United States. Palau is at once the westernmost projection of American naval capacity and a possible base for efforts to counter insurgencies in restive places like Indonesia and the Philippines.</p>
        <p>There are 100 Palauans in the United States military. One, a marine, was killed in Iraq in September.</p>
        <p>The filming of ''Survivor'' in Palau may have put the country on the map for some Americans, but it had little impact on the Palauans because it was not shown on the islands. ''Besides, it was a shallow and superficial depiction of a wonderful place; it could have been a beach anywhere,'' Mr. Beck said.</p>
        <p>The signs of Mr. Beck's two lives mingle in the 34th floor Manhattan office suite that he occupies as the president of the Granite Broadcasting Corporation.</p>
        <p>Carved wooden storyboards, Palau's primary handicraft, hang on the walls, and issues of the newspaper Palau Horizon stack a shelf, while the most prominent object on his desk is a ceramic pen and pencil holder shaped like the jersey of the New York Mets catcher Mike Piazza.</p>
        <p>Despite his long association with Palau, there are adjustments to be made now that he is actively involved in Palauan affairs.</p>
        <p>''For instance, if you have a run-in with a guy in New York, you're never going to see him again,'' he said. ''In Palau, you see him the next day, and besides, you're married to his cousin.''</p>
        <p>Another occupational hazard in schmoozing Palauans is their betel-nut-chewing habit. ''Any receptacle will do for Palauans, and when you go to parties, you have to make sure that the Coke can you choose isn't filled with disgusting red spittle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations, Mr. Beck tends to work the environment-minded committees and agencies because, as an island nation, Palau could disappear with a serious rise in sea levels. Last month, with the introductory flourish, ''Palau stands up and recommends,'' he proposed an immediate global moratorium on high seas bottom trawling.</p>
        <p>Palau's vote is one that the United States has been able to count on. In a number of resolutions in the General Assembly over the past year when the United States was isolated by overwhelming numbers, Palau was at its side, and sometimes the only one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck also champions Israel, which regularly loses lopsided votes in the General Assembly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck is leaving his television company this month and moving the Palau mission into new offices closer to the United Nations. Asked why he felt safe enough in his new job to do that, he answered with the moxie of his original island.</p>
        <p>''At a dollar a year,'' he said, ''it's a good deal for them.''</p>
        <p>United Nations Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
