<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Plants In Deal to Slash Coal Emissions</title>
    <meta content="12EMIS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/12/nyregion/12emissions.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1641462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Filters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Finger Lakes Region (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Adirondack Council</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Lung Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nrg Energy Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aes Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Niagara Mohawk Power Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Finger Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Filters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2D71638F931A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Plants In Deal to Slash Coal Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Power Plants Agree to Slash Coal Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Operators of six coal-burning power plants in upstate New York agree to significantly reduce emissions that cause smog and acid rain in what state officials call largest settlement ever for reducing air pollution; agreements, announced by Gov George Pataki and Atty Gen Eliot Spitzer, call for air pollution cuts equivalent to removing millions of vehicles from roads; plants are to install filters, switch to cleaner-burning coal and close some of oldest, least-efficient units; actions at six plants alone will more than halve amount of sulfur dioxide produced each year by all of power plants and factories in New York, and cut nitrogen oxide by more than one-fifth; Spitzer, who sued owners of plants in other states, says settlements show New York is serious about own polluters as well; American Lung Assn and environmental groups like Adirondack Council welcome accord; first agreement settles lawsuit against NRG and Niagara Mohawk over Huntley and Dunkirk plants; second covers four smaller AES plants in Finger Lakes and Southern Tier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The operators of six coal-burning power plants in upstate New York have agreed to significantly reduce emissions that cause smog and acid rain in what state officials called the state's largest settlement ever for reducing air pollution.</p>
        <p>The agreements with the plants -- which were announced here jointly on Tuesday by Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican, and Attorney General Eliot Spitzer, the Democrat who would like to replace him in two years -- call for them to cut the air pollution they produce to a level that officials said would be the equivalent of removing 2.5 million cars from the state's roads, as well as every diesel truck and bus in the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six coal-burning power plants in upstate New York agreed to significantly reduce emissions that cause smog and acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The operators of six coal-burning power plants in upstate New York have agreed to significantly reduce emissions that cause smog and acid rain in what state officials called the state's largest settlement ever for reducing air pollution.</p>
        <p>The agreements with the plants -- which were announced here jointly on Tuesday by Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican, and Attorney General Eliot Spitzer, the Democrat who would like to replace him in two years -- call for them to cut the air pollution they produce to a level that officials said would be the equivalent of removing 2.5 million cars from the state's roads, as well as every diesel truck and bus in the nation.</p>
        <p>The power plants, including the two biggest coal-fired plants in the state, which are in western New York, and four more in the Finger Lakes and Southern Tier regions, agreed to several measures to make them cleaner, including installing filters, switching to cleaner-burning coal, and shutting some of their oldest and least-efficient units.</p>
        <p>The actions at these six plants alone will cut by more than half the amount of sulfur dioxide, the main cause of acid rain, produced each year by all the power plants and factories in New York State, according to data from the attorney general's office. And they will cut by more than a fifth the amount of nitrogen oxide, which causes smog and contributes to acid rain, that is produced by the state's power plants and factories.</p>
        <p>The settlements come more than five years after Mr. Spitzer struck on the novel approach of suing the operators of coal-fired power plants in other states, arguing that winds brought the pollution they generated to New York State. Mr. Spitzer said Tuesday that the settlements showed that the state is concerned about its own polluters as well. ''We have been evenhanded in our enforcement, and we will continue to be evenhanded,'' Mr. Spitzer said.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki, whose administration recently imposed some of the strictest emissions rules in the nation, called the settlements historic. ''This is a historic afternoon, and it's not because I'm holding a press conference with Eliot Spitzer,'' he said. He said the agreements represent ''the largest single reduction of pollutants as a result of a settlement ever, in the history of New York State.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists praised the settlements, saying that the pollution spewed out by coal-fired plants kills and sickens thousands of people each year.</p>
        <p>An analysis by the American Lung Association of New York State estimated that the reduced emissions from these six plants alone could result in roughly 63 fewer premature deaths of elderly New Yorkers each year, as well as 460 fewer emergency room visits, 530 fewer cases of bronchitis in children, and 6,400 fewer asthma attacks.</p>
        <p>And they said the reductions would help protect the state from the ravages of acid rain. Brian L. Houseal, the executive director of the Adirondack Council, an environmental-advocacy group, said the reductions would also have ''a long-term beneficial impact on the survival rate of the Adirondack Park's lakes, forests and wildlife.''</p>
        <p>State officials said that while the settlements would require enormous capital expenditures -- some estimated that the cost could run into the hundreds of millions of dollars -- they do not expect electric rates to rise to pay for them.</p>
        <p>Meredith Moore, a spokeswoman for NRG Energy Inc., which owns the two largest plants, said the company would absorb the cost and not pass it on to customers.</p>
        <p>The companies did not provide estimates of the cost, and government officials said a precise estimate was difficult because the operators could choose from a range of options to meet the pollution standards.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer said the settlements built on the lawsuits his office filed in federal court in 1999 charging eight utility companies that operate 17 power plants across the Midwest with violating the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The act exempted older power plants from meeting the strict air pollution standards applied to new ones unless they make major modifications, under the theory that they would soon be replaced by newer, more environmentally friendly plants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer, who was joined by other states, charged that the plants had made major modifications without adding the necessary pollution controls. One company, the Dominion Virginia Power Company, agreed to reduce emissions in 2003. Cases are still pending against companies in Ohio, West Virginia and Indiana. And Mr. Spitzer has fought the Bush administration in court over its attempt to relax existing environmental regulations in ways that could allow aging plants to make upgrades without adding pollution controls.</p>
        <p>The agreements to reduce emissions from New York State plants were contained in two separate settlements.</p>
        <p>The first, which covers the two biggest coal-powered plans in the state, the Huntley and Dunkirk power plants in western New York, settled a lawsuit that the state brought against NRG and its former owner, Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation, charging that the plants had made major modifications without installing the pollution controls required by federal law.</p>
        <p>As part of the settlement, NRG agreed to reduce emissions causing acid rain by 87 percent and emissions causing smog by 81 percent.</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk agreed to pay a $3 million fine, to give 2,500 acres of land along the Salmon River in Oswego County to the state, and to spend another $3 million on environmental projects in the region.</p>
        <p>The second agreement, which was made without litigation, covers four smaller plants in the Finger Lakes and Southern Tier regions. Their current owner, AES, agreed to reduce smog-causing emissions by at least 70 percent and acid-rain-causing emissions by at least 90 percent.</p>
        <p>It will install new, cleaner technology at the Greenidge plant in Torrey, and it will either shut down or install pollution controls at the Hickling plant in Corning, the Westover plant in Johnson City, and the Jennison plant in Bainbridge. The Jennison and Hickling plants have been dormant for years, but would be able to reopen if they are able to comply with the standards set by the agreement.</p>
        <p>Their former owner, the New York State Electric and Gas Corporation, agreed to pay a $700,000 fine, and AES will provide $1 million toward environmentally friendly projects.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates said that the joint appearance by Mr. Pataki and Mr. Spitzer, who were once seen as trying to trump each other's environmental records, was heartening to them. Officials spoke of the cooperation between the state's Department of Environmental Conservation and the attorney general's office.</p>
        <p>''New York is really the only state that has taken any significant action against its own coal-burning power plants,'' said Katherine Kennedy, a senior lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''The symbolism of the joint announcement sends a great message that clean air and the environment is a bipartisan issue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
