<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Human Footprint Is Lightest</title>
    <meta content="marsh31" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1691630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3D81031F932A05754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Human Footprint Is Lightest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL MARSH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRISTINE lands, by the strictest definition, no longer exist. Atmospheric pollution has settled on every earthly surface; human-induced climate change is affecting ecosystems across the planet, scientists say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRISTINE lands, by the strictest definition, no longer exist. Atmospheric pollution has settled on every earthly surface; human-induced climate change is affecting ecosystems across the planet, scientists say.</p>
        <p>The wolf's-eye view of American wilderness is not quite so stark, but today's untrammeled landscapes are fragmented and shrinking. landscapes are fragmented and shrinking.</p>
        <p>Where is the last of the truly wild? The Wildlife Conservation Society, with the Center for International Earth Science Information Network at Columbia University, assembled satellite and land-use data to plot the extent of the global human footprint. On its colorful maps, the zones closest to pristine pop out as patches of leafy green.</p>
        <p>Worldwide, the society found that 17 percent of land is still virtually untouched -- mostly because it is inhospitable to humans. In areas capable of growing basic crops, and therefore most able to support people, untouched lands have diminished to just 2 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Alaska holds the vast majority of least-altered lands in the United States. In the more settlement-friendly lower 48, the wildest areas have become islands ringed by interstates, farms, towns and cities, making up only 0.9 percent of land.</p>
        <p>Disputes on managing these areas, and other nearly pristine lands, continue. In May, the Bush administration canceled the so-called roadless rule imposed by President Bill Clinton. The rule banned road-building in nearly 60 million acres of national forest, about the land mass of New York and Pennsylvania combined.</p>
        <p>Now state governors can recommend building in their roadless areas, perhaps for mining, logging or fire control; final decisions on road construction come from the Forest Service.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Representatives Jay Inslee, Democrat of Washington, and Sherwood Boehlert, Republican of New York, introduced a bill to restore the road ban.</p>
        <p>Here are four of the wildest areas, which are largely, but not entirely, off limits to commercial uses.</p>
        <p>BILL MARSH</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
