<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dauphin Island Shows How a Hurricane Shifts Natural Processes Into Fast-Forward</title>
    <meta content="20lida" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/20/science/earth/20lida.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1703583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alabama</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7DD1630F933A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dauphin Island Shows How a Hurricane Shifts Natural Processes Into Fast-Forward</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How a Hurricane Shifts Natural Processes Into Fast-Forward</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People think of the landscapes they inhabit as terra firma, solid ground. Usually they are right, in that natural processes like the flow of a river alter the land so slowly that their effects emerge only in thousands or even millions of years -- ''geological time,'' as scientists call it.</p>
        <p>But storms like hurricanes run these processes in a matter of hours, destroying beaches and punching inlets through barrier islands. Winds, waves and surges of water pick up sand and move it inland. This process can help islands survive the rising sea levels of global warming. Undeveloped islands ordinarily regain their shape and plant life within a few years, though they may have been shifted slightly inland, toward higher ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When storms strike barrier islands, like Dauphin Island off the coast of Alabama, they can dramatically reshape the landscape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People think of the landscapes they inhabit as terra firma, solid ground. Usually they are right, in that natural processes like the flow of a river alter the land so slowly that their effects emerge only in thousands or even millions of years -- ''geological time,'' as scientists call it.</p>
        <p>But storms like hurricanes run these processes in a matter of hours, destroying beaches and punching inlets through barrier islands. Winds, waves and surges of water pick up sand and move it inland. This process can help islands survive the rising sea levels of global warming. Undeveloped islands ordinarily regain their shape and plant life within a few years, though they may have been shifted slightly inland, toward higher ground.</p>
        <p>When islands are developed, though, the effects of this natural process can be extreme, as is visible in these images of Dauphin Island, Ala., made by scientists at the United States Geological Survey. The scientists used an airborne, radar-like system called lidar that measures topography in great detail.</p>
        <p>The image at top left is of a stretch of the island before Hurricane Ivan struck the Gulf Coast a year ago. The island's main road, Bienville Boulevard, runs down the center of the island, the Gulf of Mexico is on the left and there are several rows of houses in between. The center image shows the island after Hurricane Ivan passed. The storm has removed some sand from the Gulf beach and deposited on the road, covering it. After Hurricane Katrina, as the image at right shows, the storm has pushed sand over the island and into the sound behind it, a phenomenon geologists call rollover. In the image at the bottom, made by comparing pre- and post-Katrina lidar measurements, light pink areas show where sand has been swept away and light green shows where it has been deposited behind the island in formations geologists call overwash fans. (The dark pink spots are vanished houses and dark green spots are houses built after Ivan that survived or houses picked up and moved by the storm.)</p>
        <p>Scientists search images like these for clues to why some structures survived while others failed, in the hope that they will be able to predict a storm's damage potential as well as its speed and strength. Usually, they start making observations as quickly as they can after a storm passes, before waves and tides and winds start smoothing over the storm's tracks.</p>
        <p>They could not do that with Hurricane Katrina. The damage was too severe and the disruption was too widespread. But scientists say the storm's strength means its signatures will remain on the land for a while.</p>
        <p>The changes on Dauphin Island are especially striking given that Hurricane Katrina came ashore relatively far away, at Gulfport, Miss., said Abby Sallenger, a scientist who is leading the USGS imaging efforts. ''There's a lesson, I think, in the resulting destruction of homes,'' he said in an e-mail message. ''It's happened here before, during Hurricane Frederick in 1979, and again in Hurricane Elena in 1985. I hate to think that someday we'll be back, flying over the same kind of destruction yet again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
