<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking Green, Acting Dirty</title>
    <meta content="12WESULLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/12/opinion/nyregionopinions/12WEsullivan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1679518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributors"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Electric Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sullivan, Ned</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E3DE1138F931A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking Green, Acting Dirty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Talking Green, Acting Dirty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ned Sullivan and Rich Schiafo</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, Ned</byline>
      <dateline>Poughkeepsie</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE General Electric Company is trying to package itself as a company that cares about the environment. To those of us who have spent our careers protecting the environment, this would be a bad joke if there were not serious health consequences involved.</p>
        <p>Last month, General Electric announced its ''ecomagination'' initiative, presenting itself as a provider of environmental and energy technology. In rolling out this strategy, Jeffrey Immelt, General Electric's chief executive, called on the Bush administration to articulate a clear national policy on global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Electric Company is trying to package itself as a company that cares about the environment, but that's hard to believe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE General Electric Company is trying to package itself as a company that cares about the environment. To those of us who have spent our careers protecting the environment, this would be a bad joke if there were not serious health consequences involved.</p>
        <p>Last month, General Electric announced its ''ecomagination'' initiative, presenting itself as a provider of environmental and energy technology. In rolling out this strategy, Jeffrey Immelt, General Electric's chief executive, called on the Bush administration to articulate a clear national policy on global warming.</p>
        <p>While General Electric's increased emphasis on clean technology will probably result in improved products and benefit its bottom line, Mr. Immelt's credibility as a spokesman on national environmental policy is fatally flawed because of his company's intransigence in cleaning up its own toxic legacy.</p>
        <p>General Electric's announcement culminates a year of planning and packaging aimed at positioning the company as the dominant player in environmental technology, where it already holds a commanding position. The ecomagination initiative is expected to consume much of the company's $90 million corporate advertising budget, according to AdAge.com, and ramp up General Electric's investment in researching and developing greener technologies to $1.5 billion in 2010, up from $700 million in 2004. The company is making considerable contributions to new products, including wind turbines, energy-efficient engines for commercial jets and fuel cells, which can potentially benefit the environment.</p>
        <p>But General Electric under Mr. Immelt's leadership hasn't applied its penchant for innovation to the cleanup of the Hudson River, one of the largest federally designated hazardous waste sites.</p>
        <p>Since the 1940's, and up until 1977, General Electric factories used PCB's, which are persistent organic pollutants, that contaminated the Hudson River. Still today, residual PCB's from their factory sites continue to leak into the river. New York State identified high levels of the contaminants in the upper Hudson River in the early 1970's, and the pollutants have been linked to cancer and other health problems. They wiped out most of the Hudson's commercial fishing industry decades ago. State health officials continue to advise that children and women of child-bearing age not consume fish caught in the Hudson.</p>
        <p>In February 2002, the Environmental Protection Agency decided that General Electric's PCB's pose a public health and environmental threat and must be dredged up from 40 miles of the Hudson River. Yet three years later, General Electric is dragging its feet on this cleanup.</p>
        <p>For the past few years, the company has hidden behind a veil of cooperation, doing what regulators have asked while still disputing and trying to negotiate over the agency's decision. The start date for the cleanup has been postponed from 2005 to 2006, and additional delays seem likely. In federal court, General Electric continues to challenge the cleanup law, trying to strip the government of its authority to order companies to deal with hazardous waste.</p>
        <p>The same week that General Electric rolled out its eco-friendly campaign. Representative Charles Taylor, Republican of North Carolina, using research provided by General Electric, attached language to a House appropriations bill calling for further study of PCB dredging projects. If Congress approves that language, it can be used by General Electric to justify a further delay, if not a derailing, of the cleanup.</p>
        <p>According to General Electric, the stalling isn't about the cost of the cleanup. The company has consistently assured its stockholders that the cleanup will have no material impact on its financial condition. Indeed, its first-quarter earnings in 2005 exceeded earnings in the same period of 2004 by about $600 million, or $100 million more than the cleanup itself.</p>
        <p>In rolling out the ecomagination publicity campaign, Mr. Immelt was quoted as saying, ''It's no longer a zero-sum game -- things that are good for the environment are also good for business.'' Only after G.E. uses its ecomagination to rid the nation's waterways of its contamination will these words ring true. Until then, its green campaign is nothing more than an eco smoke screen.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributors Ned Sullivan is the president and Rich Schiafo is a project manager of Scenic Hudson, an environmental group and land trust.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ned Sullivan is the president and Rich Schiafo is a project manager of Scenic Hudson, an environmental group and land trust.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
