<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="11obse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/11/science/11obse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1708840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDD163FF932A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Taking Inspiration From Sperm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Fountain</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Titan's Bright Spot</p>
        <p>The Cassini spacecraft may have studied it intensely, and the Huygens probe may have landed on its surface, but there is still a lot about Saturn's moon Titan that is unknown.</p>
        <p>The latest mystery involves a bright spot in the moon's southern hemisphere. The feature, which measures about 275 miles east to west and 250 miles north to south, is bright at all wavelengths, but particularly so in the infrared portion of the spectrum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Designing micromachines with sperms cells in mind, a bright spot on Saturn's moon and more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Titan's Bright Spot</p>
        <p>The Cassini spacecraft may have studied it intensely, and the Huygens probe may have landed on its surface, but there is still a lot about Saturn's moon Titan that is unknown.</p>
        <p>The latest mystery involves a bright spot in the moon's southern hemisphere. The feature, which measures about 275 miles east to west and 250 miles north to south, is bright at all wavelengths, but particularly so in the infrared portion of the spectrum.</p>
        <p>Since Titan has an opaque, smoggy atmosphere (caused by the breakdown of methane and other hydrocarbons), figuring out what's behind the bright spot involves a fair amount of informed guesswork, aided by the process of elimination.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the Lunar and Planetary Laboratory at the University of Arizona have done the guessing, along with colleagues from the NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory and many other institutions. Their conclusion, reported in Science, is that the spot probably results from differences in surface composition.</p>
        <p>The spot was visible in images taken by Cassini's instruments during several flybys since mid-2004, and was also seen in images from ground-based telescopes from 2003. That means it could not be a large cloud, since clouds tend to come and go over days or even hours.</p>
        <p>Cassini's radar showed that it was not appreciably hotter or colder than other areas. Scientists had thought that a hotter temperature might indicate a region of ''ice volcanoes,'' structures that spew ice and methane into the atmosphere. A colder temperature, on the other hand, might have indicated a massive mountain or other high topographic feature.</p>
        <p>That leaves the strong possibility that the surface in the area of the hot spot is covered in some material that reflects sunlight differently from the surrounding surface. A possibility, the researchers say, is that the area is covered in frozen carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>A Shark's Journey</p>
        <p>For all that is known about marine life, sometimes it seems that Earth's oceans are as opaque as Titan's atmosphere. Take great white sharks, for instance. Biologists understand little about their migratory behavior and whether there is any link between populations that are scattered from coastal California to South Africa and Australia.</p>
        <p>Previously, only male great whites were known to make long journeys; females were considered to be stay-at-home types. But research by scientists from the Wildlife Conservation Society and other institutions has upended those ideas.</p>
        <p>The researchers, who tagged great whites off South Africa's Western Cape with tracking devices, report in Science that a female shark made a 12,000-mile round trip to Western Australia over nine months. It's the first time a great white has been known to travel between the South African and Australian populations.</p>
        <p>The outbound journey, which was logged by the device, took 99 days, at a minimum speed of slightly less than three miles an hour, the fastest known long-distance swim by a shark. Five and a half months later, the shark was identified back in the area where it had been tagged.</p>
        <p>It may have been on an extended foraging trip or may have traveled all that way to find a mate. If it was looking for love (and finding it), there may be more of a link between populations than previously thought.</p>
        <p>Bottom-Feeding Plesiosaurs</p>
        <p>Not all marine mysteries are modern; there are ancient ones as well. The prehistoric marine reptiles known as plesiosaurs, for instance, have long puzzled researchers.</p>
        <p>The plesiosaurs, which had long necks and small heads and lived during the era of the dinosaurs (and died out at the same time), had been thought to have a diet of fish and cephalopods like squid. But two new fossils, unearthed in Australia, are different. Based on an analysis of their stomach contents, described in Science, they were bottom feeders.</p>
        <p>The two plesiosaurs, each 15 to 20 feet long and weighing about a ton, had large quantities of sea snails and bivalves in their stomachs. To help grind those shells, the reptiles also had gastroliths, or gizzard stones, like birds, crocodiles and seals.</p>
        <p>Taking Inspiration From Sperm</p>
        <p>In all the talk about a future in which microscopic machines will course through our bodies, delivering drugs, say, to specific cancer cells, one thing often gets overlooked: just how those micromachines will do their coursing.</p>
        <p>Researchers in Paris have a suggestion. How about if they swim by wiggling a tail? After all, it works for sperm cells.</p>
        <p>The researchers, Rémi Dreyfus, Jean Baudry and Jérôme Bibette, all from a division of the National Center for Scientific Research, along with colleagues from other institutions, connected tiny colloidal particles with fragments of DNA, creating strands of beads on the order of 20 microns long, or 0.00098 inch.</p>
        <p>''The idea was to make this assembly and see what we could do with it,'' Dr. Bibette said. ''Then Rémi discovered that you could make them swim.''</p>
        <p>The colloidal particles contain tiny bits of iron oxide that become aligned when exposed to a magnetic field, making the particles magnetic.</p>
        <p>The researchers found that if they attached one of the strands to a cell, making a tail, then exposed the cell to a varying magnetic field, the tail could be made to wiggle as the now-magnetic beads interacted with the field. The cell would take off.</p>
        <p>''You get a real swimming effect,'' Dr. Dreyfus said. ''And you can change the speed and direction by changing the frequency and amplitude of the field.''</p>
        <p>Red blood cells were used in the experiments, which were described in the journal Nature, but in theory, at least, the strands could be attached to microscopic devices.</p>
        <p>The use of an external magnetic field overcomes another potential pitfall of using futuristic micromachines: a method to power them.''There's no way to have a battery or gas tank,'' Dr. Bibette said. ''Here we transfer energy with magnetic force.''</p>
        <p>''We can move one cell to a very precise location,'' he added. ''The ability to control position and motion and velocity is enormous.'' The technique may also be used to create artificial cilia, the tiny hairs that line certain tissues and control the movement of fluids around them.</p>
        <p>The researchers have developed a method to make a carpetlike surface by embedding many of these strands on a backing sheet. ''If you have a carpet of these filaments and activate them, it will make the fluid around the filaments flow,'' Dr. Bibette said.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
