<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cristina Iglesias</title>
    <meta content="23gall-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1704395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DF1430F930A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cristina Iglesias</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRACE GLUECK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marian Goodman Gallery  24 West 57th Street, Manhattan  Through Oct. 1</p>
        <p>In the darkened front room here, Cristina Iglesias has installed two big lanailike structures, formed of overlapping screens hung from the ceiling. Though of braided wire, the screens have been fashioned to look like woven raffia, and they are topped by similar screens suspended flat above them. The two structures, colored a mellow brown, are arranged as a walk-in ''double pavilion.'' The latticing of the screens actually forms words -- albeit indecipherable -- from the classic ''Rendezvous With Rama'' (1973) by the British science fiction writer Arthur C. Clarke; it has to do with, well, human attempts to explore the vast mysteries of space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marian Goodman Gallery  24 West 57th Street, Manhattan  Through Oct. 1</p>
        <p>In the darkened front room here, Cristina Iglesias has installed two big lanailike structures, formed of overlapping screens hung from the ceiling. Though of braided wire, the screens have been fashioned to look like woven raffia, and they are topped by similar screens suspended flat above them. The two structures, colored a mellow brown, are arranged as a walk-in ''double pavilion.'' The latticing of the screens actually forms words -- albeit indecipherable -- from the classic ''Rendezvous With Rama'' (1973) by the British science fiction writer Arthur C. Clarke; it has to do with, well, human attempts to explore the vast mysteries of space.</p>
        <p>The connection here is obscure, but the structures, which cast intriguing shadows on the walls and floor of the room, exert a kind of haunting presence, intensified as you stroll through them.</p>
        <p>Echoes of the suspended structures can be seen in another room, where eight large copper diptychs, each silk-screened with elements of the suspended pavilions, are on view. Working with sculpture, photo-collage and drawings, the artist, who represented Spain at the 1993 Venice Biennale, has managed to create on the shiny, flat surfaces of the diptychs the contradictory effect of deep space, affording fractured glimpses of the pavilions as if seen in a dream.</p>
        <p>In a third space, Ms. Iglesias has set up what she calls a vegetable passage, a claustrophobic fiberglass cul-de-sac of high, curving walls, whose richly tactile surfaces are carved all over with proliferating, and decaying, vines, branches, exotic leaves and other matter. It has the feel of a teeming tropical rain forest, but its dead patina makes an ominous suggestion that it may be dying off. Global warming? What's lacking here is a jungle soundtrack to enliven it.</p>
        <p>GRACE GLUECK</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
