<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deconstructing Harry</title>
    <meta content="08KALMANL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/08/books/review/08KALMANL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1670644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Becoming Justice Blackmun: Harry Blackmun's Supreme Court Journey (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DA1031F93BA35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deconstructing Harry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Becoming Justice Blackmun': Deconstructing Harry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laura Kalman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BECOMING JUSTICE BLACKMUN</p>
        <p>Harry Blackmun's Supreme Court Journey.</p>
        <p>By Linda Greenhouse.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 268 pp.</p>
        <p>Times Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Linda Greenhouse tells a judicial Horatio Alger story and a tale of a remarkable transformation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BECOMING JUSTICE BLACKMUN</p>
        <p>Harry Blackmun's Supreme Court Journey.</p>
        <p>By Linda Greenhouse.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 268 pp.</p>
        <p>Times Books/Henry Holt &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>IF there is a special place in heaven for those considerate of the claims of history, Justice Harry Blackmun deserves a spot. Some justices destroy their papers. They believe the less the public knows about the Supreme Court, the more easily the illusion is preserved that our system is based on rule of law, rather than men and women.</p>
        <p>But Blackmun, who sat on the court for 24 years, kept everything from hotel receipts to private exchanges between justices in many of the 3,875 cases in which he participated; and he sat for 38 hours of videotaped interviews with his former clerk Harold Hongju Koh, now the dean of Yale Law School. This pack rat then donated his entire collection to the Library of Congress, providing that it be opened five years after his death.</p>
        <p>As the requisite waiting period drew to a close in 2004, hordes of journalists, scholars and the curious were expected on ''opening day.'' After all, Blackmun wrote the majority opinion in the 1973 decision Roe v. Wade. His daughters shrewdly decided to give Linda Greenhouse, the Pulitzer Prize-winning Supreme Court reporter for The New York Times, a two-month head start.</p>
        <p>Just a year later comes this fascinating book. In clear and forceful prose, ''Becoming Justice Blackmun'' tells a judicial Horatio Alger story and a tale of a remarkable transformation.</p>
        <p>Born in 1908, Harry Blackmun grew up in a working-class section of St. Paul, won a scholarship to Harvard and worked his way through Harvard Law School. After clerking for Judge John Sanborn on the United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, Blackmun rose from cub to partner in a distinguished Minneapolis law firm, then became first resident counsel of the Mayo Clinic. Judge Sanborn and Warren Burger, Blackmun's best friend since kindergarten and, at that time, a federal appeals judge, engineered Blackmun's appointment to the Eighth Circuit. Later, Burger intervened again when the Nixon administration forced Abe Fortas off the Supreme Court, and Congress twice thwarted the president's attempts to name a replacement. Burger, then chief justice of the United States, promoted Blackmun. The 61-year-old, or ''Old Number Three,'' as Blackmun referred to himself ever after, since he was Nixon's third choice, got the nod in 1970 because he was so uncontroversial.</p>
        <p>Not for long. Burger assigned Roe to his old friend. After holing up in the Mayo Library to do medical research, Blackmun announced for the court that the right to privacy, read into the 14th Amendment's protection of ''liberty,'' required the decriminalization of abortion. ''Blackmun had not imagined that he alone would come to personify an opinion in which he had spoken for a 7-to-2 majority and that was the product, after all, of a collaborative effort,'' Greenhouse writes. Nor did Roe say what we remember: Blackmun focused more on doctors' right to perform abortions without fear of prosecution than women's right to have them.</p>
        <p>But Roe's words were ''lost to myth and the mists of memory,'' and Blackmun became the judicial symbol of the case -- to those who branded him a ''baby killer'' and used the backlash to boost conservatism; to many academics who condemned him for judicial activism run amok; and to feminists who made him their improbable ''icon.'' Blackmun was ambivalent about Roe, sometimes sounding as if he had grabbed the bull by the horns, sometimes as if he had been gored. Ultimately, Greenhouse says, ''the world's view that he was the creator of abortion rights in America gradually, perhaps inevitably, shaped his self-image.''</p>
        <p>He always perceived himself as ''Roe's primary defender,'' but his optimistic predictions about its impact proved -- to use Greenhouse's word -- ''naïve.'' Blackmun expected states to rush to make abortion available to all. Instead, many enacted laws making access difficult. The court's docket filled with cases seeking to chip away at Roe.</p>
        <p>Ronald Reagan's presidency posed a new peril to Roe because Reagan opposed abortion, and Blackmun's colleagues were retiring. By 1988, Reagan had named three justices. The last, Anthony Kennedy, was chosen to replace Lewis Powell only after the nominations of Robert Bork and Douglas Ginsburg failed. In a 1989 dissent to an abortion case, Blackmun despaired that ''a chill wind blows.'' Three years later, it seemed the court would effectively overrule Roe in Planned Parenthood v. Casey. Blackmun was drafting his dissent when Kennedy, the other member of Blackmun's ''good old No. 3 club,'' did an abrupt about-face and provided the crucial fifth vote to maintain the constitutional right to abortion.</p>
        <p>Even then, Blackmun worried. The two sides of the court were ''worlds apart,'' he wrote in Casey, separated by a single vote. At the Supreme Court, just one person can change the course of history. And ''I am 83 years old. I cannot remain on this court forever.''</p>
        <p>In another important new book about the Rehnquist years, ''A Court Divided,'' Mark Tushnet observes that Blackmun ''could not resist the pull of bathos'' in Casey. Or elsewhere, as Greenhouse shows. ''Poor Joshua!'' Blackmun famously began one dissent about an abused child. Convinced his colleagues sometimes forgot the ''live human beings . . . terribly affected by our decisions,'' he wrote in a personal and charged way. When he decided that the death penalty could not be applied fairly or constitutionally, he announced, ''From this day forward, I no longer shall tinker with the machinery of death.'' Strong words, these, for someone a writer for The New York Times Magazine had described in 1970 as ''a white Anglo-Saxon Protestant Republican Rotarian Harvard man from the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>Blackmun's journey surprised many, including Warren Burger. Blackmun's mother had seen the handwriting on the wall. She warned her disbelieving son that the relationship of ''the Minnesota Twins'' would sour when both joined the court. Greenhouse tells the story of the downward spiral beautifully. For poignancy, it rivals the split between Theodore Roosevelt and William Howard Taft. By the late 1970's, Blackmun's private comments about Burger had grown ''caustic,'' and Greenhouse notes ''the disrespectful way his law clerks felt free -- or even encouraged -- to refer to the chief justice.'' The two old friends changed on the court, Blackmun more than Burger.</p>
        <p>Greenhouse maintains that it was Roe and its reception that forced Blackmun to begin the rest of his life and become Justice Blackmun. Doubtless, conservatives would say that Greenhouse herself played a role in Blackmun's transformation. They have deplored ''the Greenhouse effect'' and accused Justices Blackmun and Kennedy of taking positions to curry favor with her and with others in the ''liberal establishment.'' Certainly, Blackmun was alert to his reputation.</p>
        <p>He would appreciate this book. The Blackmun whom Greenhouse paints in this page turner is a modest Minnesotan, who carries the weight of the world on his shoulders. He drives his Volkswagen to the court daily for breakfast with his clerks. A man of civility and compassion, he has a twinkle in his eye. He is kind to almost everyone, which makes his lack of sympathy for Burger as their friendship fades startling. Greenhouse's Blackmun is endearingly quirky, the justice from Lake Wobegon. Garrison Keillor himself called Blackmun ''the shy person's justice.''</p>
        <p>Biographers who follow Greenhouse may find other Blackmuns. Follow her they will. Indeed, she observes, ''anyone interested in the Supreme Court during the last quarter of the 20th century will turn to the Blackmun collection as well, for many generations to come, thanks to Harry Blackmun's gift.''</p>
        <p>Laura Kalman, a professor of history at the University of California, Santa Barbara, is the author of ''Abe Fortas: A Biography.'' Her latest book, ''Yale Law School and the Sixties,'' will be published this fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Kalman, a professor of history at the University of California, Santa Barbara, is the author of ''Abe Fortas: A Biography.'' Her latest book, ''Yale Law School and the Sixties,'' will be published this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
