<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Signs an Energy Bill That Had Been a Longtime Priority</title>
    <meta content="09bush" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/09/politics/09bush.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3D9173EF93AA3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Signs an Energy Bill That Had Been a Longtime Priority</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Signs an Energy Bill That Had Been a Longtime Priority</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush signs into law energy bill that he acknowledges would not immediately bring down price of gasoline, but that he says would give US start on reducing its dependence on foreign oil and help economy over long run; bill touches on many aspects of energy policy; many Democrats say it emphasizes wrong things and rewards energy industry while harming interests of consumers and putting environment at additional risk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day when oil and gasoline prices hit record highs, President Bush on Monday signed into law a bill that encourages increased domestic oil and gas production and the building of new nuclear power plants. It also creates incentives for alternative energy sources and requires modernization of the nation's electrical grid.</p>
        <p>At a ceremony at the Sandia National Laboratory here, Mr. Bush acknowledged that the measure would not immediately bring down the price of gasoline, but he said it would give the United States a start on reducing its dependence on foreign oil and help the economy over the long run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a day oil and gasoline prices set records, President Bush signed a bill that encourages increased domestic oil and gas production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a day when oil and gasoline prices hit record highs, President Bush on Monday signed into law a bill that encourages increased domestic oil and gas production and the building of new nuclear power plants. It also creates incentives for alternative energy sources and requires modernization of the nation's electrical grid.</p>
        <p>At a ceremony at the Sandia National Laboratory here, Mr. Bush acknowledged that the measure would not immediately bring down the price of gasoline, but he said it would give the United States a start on reducing its dependence on foreign oil and help the economy over the long run.</p>
        <p>''This bill will strengthen our economy, and it will improve our environment, and it's going to make this country more secure,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>''This bill is not going to solve our energy challenges overnight,'' he said after touring a research program here to generate electricity by capturing and concentrating sunlight in giant dishes. ''Most of the serious problems, such as high gasoline costs, or the rising dependence on foreign oil, have developed over decades. It's going to take years of focused effort to alleviate those problems.''</p>
        <p>The measure has been one of the White House's legislative priorities since 2001, when Mr. Bush, who got his start in business as a Texas oilman, put Vice President Dick Cheney, a former chairman of the oilfield services company Halliburton, in charge of developing recommendations for addressing the nation's energy needs. The final product did not contain a number of provisions backed by the administration, including one that would have opened part of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling.</p>
        <p>It won support from some Democrats in Congress, but it was criticized by many others and also by environmental and consumer groups, who said it gave away too much to energy companies at a time when they were benefiting from high oil prices, which neared $64 a barrel on Monday. The Energy Department reported on Monday that the average national price for a gallon of unleaded gasoline hit $2.37 last week, a record and 49 cents a gallon above where prices were a year ago.</p>
        <p>''It will not reduce America's dependence on oil and it will not create a cleaner energy future,'' said Anna Aurilio, legislative director of U.S. PIRG, the Washington lobbying office for state public interest research groups, which opposed the legislation. ''Instead the bill allows big oil companies to pollute water supplies, plunder the Treasury and attack our coastlines.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush cast the measure as ''an economic bill,'' reflecting the White House's concern that despite reasonably strong economic growth, many Americans feel they are struggling to make ends meet, a feeling made worse by high gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>''This economy is strong, and it's growing stronger,'' Mr. Bush said. ''And what this energy bill is going to do, it's just going to help keep momentum in the right direction so people can realize their dreams.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has summoned his economic team to his ranch in Crawford, Tex., on Tuesday, to focus attention again on what the White House says has been solid economic progress brought about by the president's policies.</p>
        <p>The bill he signed here touches on many aspects of energy policy. In addition to encouraging more domestic oil and gas production, it provides money for research into technology to help burn coal with less pollution and creates federal risk insurance for companies that build a new generation of nuclear power plants.</p>
        <p>It extends or creates tax incentives for alternative energy sources like wind, creates incentives for the use of more ethanol and finances research into the use of hydrogen to power automobiles. The bill contains incentives for oil companies to expand refineries to reduce periodic tightness in supplies of gasoline, and tax credits for conservation and energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>But many Democrats said it emphasized the wrong things and rewarded the energy industry while harming the interests of consumers and putting the environment at additional risk.</p>
        <p>''This new law is a historic failure,'' said Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts. ''It fails to do anything to increase the fuel efficiency of our cars and S.U.V.'s, even though more than two-thirds of the oil we consume goes into gasoline tanks. It fails to mandate increased use of renewable energy sources, such as solar and wind. It fails to address emissions of greenhouse gases from fossil fuel industries that are contributing to climate change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
