<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe and China in Accord Over End to a Textile Dispute</title>
    <meta content="06textile" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/06/business/worldbusiness/06textile.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1699925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE3DA1531F935A3575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe and China in Accord Over End to a Textile Dispute</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Europe and China in Accord Over End to a Textile Dispute</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BUCKLEY; Paul Meller contributed reporting from Brussels for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Sept. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China and the European Union agreed on Monday to end their dispute over Chinese-made clothes marooned on European docks, as both sides sought to use a high-level meeting in Beijing to stress broader cooperation.</p>
        <p>Europe's trade commissioner, Peter Mandelson, and China's commerce minister, Bo Xilai, reached the agreement after two days of negotiations about how to handle some 400 million euros ($501 million) of Chinese sweaters, shirts, trousers and bras that a June quota agreement threatened to keep off the shelves of European retailers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>China and the European Union agreed on Monday to end their dispute over Chinese-made clothes marooned on European docks, as both sides sought to stress broader cooperation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China and the European Union agreed on Monday to end their dispute over Chinese-made clothes marooned on European docks, as both sides sought to use a high-level meeting in Beijing to stress broader cooperation.</p>
        <p>Europe's trade commissioner, Peter Mandelson, and China's commerce minister, Bo Xilai, reached the agreement after two days of negotiations about how to handle some 400 million euros ($501 million) of Chinese sweaters, shirts, trousers and bras that a June quota agreement threatened to keep off the shelves of European retailers.</p>
        <p>The two officials signed a preliminary agreement on Monday night; if the deal is approved by European countries, it will unblock the stalled shipments.</p>
        <p>''They will sign an agreement that is fair and acceptable to both sides, and will benefit both consumers and businesses,'' the Chinese prime minister, Wen Jiabao, said at a news conference attended by the British prime minister, Tony Blair, and the European Commission president, José Manuel Barroso. Mr. Blair said he was confident that the European Union would approve the proposed agreement.</p>
        <p>''There are bound to be disagreements over trade, partly because of the very strength of China's economic performance,'' Mr. Blair said. Mr. Mandelson later said he had not considered what would happen if countries like France and Spain, where clothes manufacturers have denounced the Chinese exports, oppose the deal.</p>
        <p>In Brussels, the European Commission presented the agreement on Monday to officials from the 25 member countries. Representatives are to convene on Tuesday to debate the agreement, and a decision is expected in a few days, said a spokeswoman for the British government, which holds the six-month rotating presidency of the commission. She spoke on condition of anonymity, as is usual with European diplomats.</p>
        <p>Countries with large textile industries, including France, Italy, Spain and Poland, are known to be opposed to any deal that admits more Chinese textiles, and those countries could block an agreement. But the commission was confident that the deal would pass.</p>
        <p>The textile shipments in dispute are a sliver of the trade between China and Europe, which both sides expect to grow to more than $200 billion this year. After the lifting of worldwide textile trade quotas last January, Chinese textile exports to Europe ballooned 82 percent in the first four months, compared with the same period last year, according to Chinese customs statistics.</p>
        <p>European garment makers complained that their livelihood was in peril. But after an agreement was signed in June to limit export growth of Chinese-made clothes to 8 percent to 12.5 percent a year, European retailers complained that orders they had placed before the deal took effect were held up at ports, because quotas for 2005 had already been filled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandelson blamed intrinsic difficulties in the June deal for the dispute, and said China and Europe would share the burden of absorbing the unlicensed shipments stranded at European ports: China would subtract half the amount from its export quotas for subsequent years, and Europe would absorb the other half.</p>
        <p>The announcement of the textile resolution came on a day when Mr. Blair met China's prime minister and its president, Hu Jintao, to discuss cooperation between Brussels and Beijing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair led a delegation that signed six agreements in areas that include environmental protection and global warming, labor and social security, and energy.</p>
        <p>Both China and Europe had sought to portray the textile dispute as a passing squall that would not threaten the two sides' growing economic and political ties.</p>
        <p>''China-European relations have entered a new stage of maturity and self-sufficiency,'' Mr. Wen said. The textile dispute was ''temporary and localized,'' he said. ''It should not have larger negative effects.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandelson told a meeting of business executives that China's rapid economic rise posed a challenge to Europe. ''A challenge is not necessarily a threat,'' he said, but he added that in Europe ''there are growing public job fears and sometimes bitter questioning of whether we are giving away too much in the name of free trade.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bo mixed his praise for the agreement with criticism of what he said was a dangerous ''protectionist'' mood in some European countries and industries. He chided the United States for not following Europe's example of seeking compromise over Chinese garment exports. Washington has imposed quotas, and four rounds of talks have failed to produce an agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
