<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH MAY WEIGH USING INCENTIVES TO DISSUADE IRAN</title>
    <meta content="24PREX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BUSH IN EUROPE: MEETING IN GERMANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mainz (Germany)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Atomic Energy Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroder, Gerhard (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirac, Jacques (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hadley, Stephen J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED6163DF937A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1397" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH MAY WEIGH USING INCENTIVES TO DISSUADE IRAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>WIESBADEN, Germany, Feb. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush says he and leaders of Germany, Britain and France have discussed negotiating tactics to try to get Iran to give up its suspected nuclear weapons program, but he gives no sign that United States would directly join in talks, as Europeans want; national security adviser Stephen J Hadley says Bush might consider offering incentives to Iran, tactic favored by Europeans but rejected by Bush administration as recently as two weeks ago; Bush, at joint news conference with German Chancellor Gerhard Schroder in Mainz, seeks to soothe growing fears in Europe that Iran would become next battleground for US; calls that idea 'ridiculous' but then adds that 'all options are on the table'; Bush's discussions with Schroder on Iran come at crucial time, with European officials saying that negotiations at International Atomic Energy Agency are at impasse and will fail without Americans at the table; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said Wednesday that he and German, British and French leaders had discussed negotiating tactics to try to get Iran to give up its suspected nuclear weapons program, and his national security adviser later left open the possibility that Mr. Bush would consider offering incentives to dissuade Iran from its nuclear ambitions.</p>
        <p>The tactic of incentives, favored by the Europeans, had been roundly rejected by the Bush administration as recently as two weeks ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush said Wednesday that he and German, British and French leaders had discussed negotiating tactics to try to get Iran to give up its suspected nuclear weapons program, and his national security adviser later left open the possibility that Mr. Bush would consider offering incentives to dissuade Iran from its nuclear ambitions.</p>
        <p>The tactic of incentives, favored by the Europeans, had been roundly rejected by the Bush administration as recently as two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Despite the glimmer of what the national security adviser, Stephen J. Hadley, described as a ''convergence'' of the Americans and Europeans on the tactics to be used in negotiations with Iran, the president gave no indication that the United States would directly join in the talks, as the Europeans want.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush made his remarks in the Rhine city of Mainz at a joint news conference with Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany in the Electoral Palace, a reconstructed German Renaissance building that was once the home of the archbishop of Mainz. The president was on the third day of a four-day trip to Europe to repair relationships ruptured after the war with Iraq, and he and Mr. Schröder had talks that focused on Iran, touched on their disagreement over the Kyoto Treaty on global warming and generally helped publicly smooth over the rift between the nations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also sought to soothe growing fears in Europe that Iran would become the next battleground for the United States.</p>
        <p>''You know, yesterday I was asked about the U.S. position, and I said all options are on the table,'' he said, referring to comments he made at the European Union headquarters in Brussels. ''That's part of our position. But I also reminded people that diplomacy is just beginning. Iran is not Iraq.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday at a news conference at the European Union, Mr. Bush said bluntly, ''This notion that the United States is getting ready to attack Iran is simply ridiculous.'' But then he immediately added, to some laughter, ''And having said that, all options are on the table.''</p>
        <p>The president also emphatically declared that blame for any lack of progress in the talks should be placed on Iran, not on the White House or Europe.</p>
        <p>''The reason we're having these discussions is because they were caught enriching uranium after they had signed a treaty saying they wouldn't enrich uranium,'' Mr. Bush said of the Iranians. ''They're the party that needs to be held into account, not any of us.''</p>
        <p>In his public comments about Iran's uranium enrichment, Mr. Bush appeared to have misspoken, because the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty permits uranium enrichment for commercial purposes as long as a country declares the activity and allows inspections.</p>
        <p>In Iran's case, it hid enrichment facilities from the International Atomic Energy Agency for a number of years, but when caught, said all of its nuclear activities are solely for commercial purposes. The United States has charged that Iran is secretly pursuing weapons development, but the agency says that it has found no concrete evidence of such a weapons program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's discussions with Mr. Schröder on Iran come at a crucial time. Although Mr. Hadley denied any sense of urgency about the issue, European officials say the negotiations at the I.A.E.A. in Vienna are at an impasse, and they have become increasingly vocal in saying the talks will fail without the Americans at the table.</p>
        <p>The president has repeatedly said that he is ''consulting'' with the Europeans on the talks, but has never said why the Americans are not directly involved in the negotiations. The Europeans say one reason is Mr. Bush's staunch opposition to rewarding what he considers bad behavior by having the world's superpower at the same negotiating table with a nation he sees as a rogue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, when asked at the news conference if he thought incentives for Iran would work, sidestepped the question. But he did warmly praise the Europeans for their efforts in the talks.</p>
        <p>''I want to thank Gerhard for taking the lead, along with Britain and France, on this important issue,'' he said. ''It's vital that the Iranians hear the world speak with one voice that they shouldn't have a nuclear weapon.''</p>
        <p>A senior Bush administration official later said that Mr. Bush's praise represented a shift in the American attitude toward the talks. ''Last fall we were yelling at each other,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>In a briefing for reporters, Mr. Hadley said there had been discussions between Mr. Bush and Mr. Schröder about ''should there be a mix of carrots and sticks, and who should the carrots come from and what should they be.'' He said the president ''did a lot of listening'' and now ''has really got to go back and think about it, quite frankly.''</p>
        <p>Until now, the Europeans have in effect been offering Iran all the carrots in the talks, economic and political incentives if Iran disarms. In contrast, the United States has been offering sticks focused on the demand that the matter be referred to the United Nations Security Council, where political and economic sanctions would be considered.</p>
        <p>A growing body of international academics and former government officials say the only way to approach Iran is for there to be a ''convergence,'' the same phrase used by Mr. Hadley, and have both the United States and Europe join in presenting both incentives and threats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spent a total of nine hours in Germany on Wednesday, his first trip to the country since the invasion of Iraq, and his first extended meeting with Mr. Schröder since the chancellor had lunch at the White House in February 2004. The two have had a tense relationship since Mr. Schröder campaigned for re-election in 2002 on what many in the White House considered an anti-Bush, anti-American platform.</p>
        <p>People close to Mr. Bush said he had felt personally betrayed. Although the two leaders now seem to have reached a civil working relationship, the body language on Wednesday was anything but warm. Mr. Schröder looked stern and businesslike in his public appearances with Mr. Bush, who smiled as ''The Star Spangled Banner'' was played in a military welcoming ceremony under intermittent snow flurries.</p>
        <p>But the two men did what they came together to do, which was to publicly play down their differences and present a united front on Iran.</p>
        <p>''We absolutely agree that Iran must say no to any kind of nuclear weapon, full stop,'' Mr. Schröder said at the news conference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schröder said he and Mr. Bush had discussed other issues on which they disagree, most notably the Kyoto Treaty on global warming, which Europeans support and the Bush administration opposes.</p>
        <p>''The Kyoto Protocol was not appreciated by everybody, and that is something that has continued to exist,'' Mr. Schröder said. ''But I would like to emphasize that despite that, we would like to see practical cooperation with the reduction of problems in this area.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that ''I assured the chancellor that the United States cares about the quality of our air, obviously,'' and that the two countries should share research and technology that would improve the environment. Neither leader went much beyond those generalities.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, Mr. Bush spoke to American troops at the nearby Wiesbaden Army Airfield, where Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice, who was traveling with the president, served as a warm-up speaker. Ms. Rice was raucously greeted with shouts of ''We love you!''</p>
        <p>In a pep talk delivered without notes, Ms. Rice asked the crowd of 3,000: ''Do you know why America has the greatest military in the history of the world? Because it has the greatest soldiers, airmen and seamen in the history of the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush then left for Bratislava, Slovakia, for meetings with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia on Thursday.</p>
        <p>BUSH IN EUROPE: MEETING IN GERMANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
