<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watching America: Will It Listen to Foreigners, or Do as It Pleases?</title>
    <meta content="28NORR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/28/business/worldbusiness/28norris.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Economic Forum</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pricewaterhousecoopers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Novartis Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vasella, Daniel (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donaldson, William H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Floyd Norris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Economic Forum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D6173BF93BA15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watching America: Will It Listen to Foreigners, or Do as It Pleases?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Watching America: Will It Listen to Foreigners, or Do as It Pleases?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <dateline>DAVOS, Switzerland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Floyd Norris comment on opposition by foreign leaders and businessmen at World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, to new American accounting rules that also apply to foreign companies; notes PricewaterhouseCoopers survey of 1,324 chief executives shows bosses around world are less confident they can comply with rules outside their home countries; Novartis' chief executive Daniel L Vasella, who is attending forum, says chief executives of several smaller European countries told him they might try to leave American market; adds Securities and Exchange Commission chairman William H Donaldson addressed forum to try to ease concerns; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WHAT stresses me most,'' the chief executive of Novartis, Daniel L. Vasella, said, ''is that we are getting new regulations from abroad without any consultation.''</p>
        <p>This has been the World Economic Forum that the United States government largely passed by. In a world that both respects and fears American power, there is worry that the United States does not care what others think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This has been the World Economic Forum that the U.S. government passed by, making some worry that the U.S. does not care what others think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WHAT stresses me most,'' the chief executive of Novartis, Daniel L. Vasella, said, ''is that we are getting new regulations from abroad without any consultation.''</p>
        <p>This has been the World Economic Forum that the United States government largely passed by. In a world that both respects and fears American power, there is worry that the United States does not care what others think.</p>
        <p>Or, as Tony Blair, the prime minister of Britain, put it in a speech to the forum, ''If America wants the rest of the world to be part of the agenda it has set, it must be part of their agenda, too.'' He added, ''What people want is not for America to concede, but for America to engage.''</p>
        <p>It is a fair bet that Mr. Blair has given little thought to Section 404 of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act or to the way the Securities and Exchange Commission can adjust accounting rules, which is what concerns Mr. Vasella. Mr. Blair was more concerned with global warming and world poverty.</p>
        <p>The twin American deficits figured into concerns that the United States would do as it pleases regardless of the possible impact on the world economy. ''I don't see the budget deficit being dealt with,'' said Jacob Frenkel, the former head of Israel's central bank and now a vice chairman of the American International Group, a large insurance company. ''I am concerned with the U.S. current-account deficit, not because it cannot be dealt with but because of the way it is not being dealt with.''</p>
        <p>The explanation for less American government participation than in past years -- that this forum came at an awkward time just before the State of the Union address -- makes some sense. And there were Americans here, like John A. Thain, the chief executive of the New York Stock Exchange, who gently suggested that the current-account deficit would decline if Europe grew faster.</p>
        <p>Some Americans are listening. William H. Donaldson, the chairman of the S.E.C., gave a speech in London this week that dealt with some of the concerns, indicating the commission may delay enforcing rules against foreign companies that trade in the United States and may make it easier for foreign companies already registered in the United States to withdraw.</p>
        <p>The rule that has both American and foreign companies complaining is Section 404, which requires extensive reviews of internal controls in companies to assure they are effective -- and says outside auditors must certify the controls. ''It was an enormous, expensive exercise,'' Mr. Vasella said in an interview. ''It raised the question, for my employees, 'Is the trust broken?' because you control everything.'' Novartis has complied with the rule.</p>
        <p>The chief executive of PricewaterhouseCoopers, Samuel A. DiPiazza Jr., estimated that 10 percent of large American companies would fail to comply this year, either because they could not complete the work on time or because material problems were found.</p>
        <p>A survey of 1,324 chief executives by his firm found that bosses around the world were less confident they could comply with rules outside their home countries. Mr. Vasella said chief executives of several smaller European countries told him they might try to leave the American market. He said he asked them if they would do so because they had something to hide, or because of the expense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Donaldson is wise to try to assuage European concerns, but there is a risk that other parts of the American government are less sure of the need to take foreign views into account. That may prove to be unwise for a country that needs help in many areas, not the least of them being in borrowing money to finance the twin deficits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
