<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nature, Man and Politics At the Center of the Storm</title>
    <meta content="22mart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/22/arts/television/22mart.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1719493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1DB1F3EF931A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nature, Man and Politics At the Center of the Storm</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nature, Man and Politics at the Center of the Storm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY NED MARTEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonight, back-to-back episodes of ''Nova'' and ''Frontline'' pull together the strewn facts of Hurricane Katrina and put them in working order, with lessons for any city under meteorological, seismological or even terrorist siege. As is often the case, these two workhorse PBS series stare hard at complexity, explaining the natural and political systems that caused and exacerbated catastrophe.</p>
        <p>The two approaches -- scientific and sleuthing -- complement each other on the single topic of Katrina. In general, ''Nova'' focuses on the storm's approach and impacts, while ''Frontline'' is fixated on the aftermath. Both use archival clips to recall past storms, and both present experts who saw the whole thing coming but couldn't prevent the devastation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back-to-back episodes of "Nova" and "Frontline" pull together the strewn facts of Hurricane Katrina and put them in working order, with lessons for any city under meteorological, seismological or even terrorist siege.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tonight, back-to-back episodes of ''Nova'' and ''Frontline'' pull together the strewn facts of Hurricane Katrina and put them in working order, with lessons for any city under meteorological, seismological or even terrorist siege. As is often the case, these two workhorse PBS series stare hard at complexity, explaining the natural and political systems that caused and exacerbated catastrophe.</p>
        <p>The two approaches -- scientific and sleuthing -- complement each other on the single topic of Katrina. In general, ''Nova'' focuses on the storm's approach and impacts, while ''Frontline'' is fixated on the aftermath. Both use archival clips to recall past storms, and both present experts who saw the whole thing coming but couldn't prevent the devastation.</p>
        <p>As they speak frankly about what they foresaw, local emergency managers, federal relief planners and academics versed in the atmosphere sound like technocrats one second and then sad Cassandras the next. Over and over, they explain how they had the models for what would happen but not the mouthpiece.</p>
        <p>The best-known expert, Max Mayfield, is the avuncular head of the National Hurricane Center and appears often on news segments as the calm before any storm. A Jefferson Parish emergency-management official recalls Mr. Mayfield's phone call of warning -- a simple ''you'd better get ready'' -- and the Louisiana local knew that this cautious meteorologist was delivering as dire a warning as he could muster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mayfield is also shown on air disconnecting the unprecedented succession of powerful hurricanes from the phenomenon of global warming. His statement is brief and perhaps truncated, but it serves as the only suggestion in this program that human behavior might not be altering climate patterns. Mr. Mayfield is a government official, and he appears loath to wade into such a roiling political debate, but earlier in the segment, the program had offered ample data that the surface temperatures of the oceans have risen one degree Fahrenheit and that the extra energy is fueling fierce storms. It seems odd that the doubters aren't challenged to provide real evidence for their skepticism.</p>
        <p>Overall, the ''Nova'' episode provides a welcome wealth of information about storm patterns and even levee construction. The breaches were predicted, but the ways that the levees eventually tumbled still surprised some engineers. One storm surge, five feet higher than the walls, simply toppled the levee that had kept New Orleans's Ninth Ward dry for decades. That was predictable. But closer to downtown, lesser heights of water, having sloshed and slowed in the mazelike canals, literally undermined other levees. The watery rush loosened peaty soil and shoved the walls aside at their foundations.</p>
        <p>With each intense minute of ''Nova,'' the case is made against the silly spectacle of television reporters covering storms with wind monitors and raingear. These hardy preeners take corporal risks but never make the mental leap between their experience of the storm and new patterns of increased storm intensity. And when you hear such storms described as arguably preventable, there appears to be no more urgent news to impart. Instead of dabbling in Doppler radar, weather forecasters could use other available instruments to explain how and why -- not just when -- the weather is getting weird.</p>
        <p>For its part, ''Frontline'' corners the usual suspect, Michael Brown, the former Federal Emergency Management Agency director, who still defends his galling inaction. The reporter, Martin Smith, conducts an aggressive, on-camera interview, described as Mr. Brown's first since the storm, and the deposed political appointee says that he does not want to pass the buck and then does just that. Later, Mr. Smith coaxes the former Homeland Security secretary, Tom Ridge, into a state of peevishness, as Mr. Ridge justifies delays in supplying radio gear nationwide to law enforcers and rescue workers, who need to be in constant communication, no matter what the crisis.</p>
        <p>For a total of two hours, there are so many analyses imparted that a channel flipper might feel as well schooled in the latest finds as, say, a steady reader of Congressional Quarterly and Science magazines. The most upsetting parallel is drawn on ''Frontline,'' where Hurricane Andrew's havoc in Homestead, Fla., in 1992 comes back into view, with Federal officials griping that state and local folks failed to ask for help. The program slyly suggests that President George H. W. Bush's point man on spinning the Andrew devastation, Andrew H. Card Jr., transportation secretary at the time, is the current chief of staff in the White House, where an eerily similar blame game began in Katrina's wake.</p>
        <p>Frontline  The Storm  PBS, tonight at 9; check local listings.</p>
        <p>Written and reported by Martin Smith; Marcela Gaviria and Mr. Smith, producers; Chris Durrance, co-producer; Michael Hanna and Steve Audette, editors; David Fanning, executive producer. A co-production with RAINMedia Inc.; produced by WGBH Boston.</p>
        <p>Nova  The Storm That Drowned a City  PBS, tonight at 8; check local listings.</p>
        <p>Directed and produced by Caroline Davey; Mike Beckham, executive producer; Paula S. Apsell, series senior executive producer; Neil Ross, narrator. Produced by WGBH Boston.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
