<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Biodiesel Is Touted As Fuel of the Future</title>
    <meta content="01LIFUEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1669009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6D61331F932A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Biodiesel Is Touted As Fuel of the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCES CERRA WHITTELSEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST discussion these days about renewable energy focuses on wind and solar power, but Suffolk County is about to begin a pilot program using another option, biodiesel. And the Town of Brookhaven, which was already using biodiesel, is expanding its use of it.</p>
        <p>In the United States, biodiesel is usually made from soybeans, but can be made from virtually any plant oil or even waste grease. Blended with petroleum diesel fuel or home heating oil, it requires no basic modifications to oil burners or diesel engines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST discussion these days about renewable energy focuses on wind and solar power, but Suffolk County is about to begin a pilot program using another option, biodiesel. And the Town of Brookhaven, which was already using biodiesel, is expanding its use of it.</p>
        <p>In the United States, biodiesel is usually made from soybeans, but can be made from virtually any plant oil or even waste grease. Blended with petroleum diesel fuel or home heating oil, it requires no basic modifications to oil burners or diesel engines.</p>
        <p>Biodiesel is more expensive per gallon than conventional fuels but reduces emissions of greenhouse gases and other pollutants. It also does not require the purchase of new kinds of vehicles or heavy investment in new technology like solar panels or windmills.</p>
        <p>Brookhaven is using solar and wind power at Town Hall and plans to make biodiesel blends available at six facilities this year, up from three. The fuel will be used in trucks, sweepers and ambulances.</p>
        <p>Biodiesel has also been used for years by the Navy; by private truck fleets in the Midwest; by Windsor, Calif., for its garbage trucks; by Clark County, Nev., for its school buses; and by Denver for its heavy vehicles.</p>
        <p>''Biodiesel is really here now, a fuel for today and the future,'' William Horak, the chairman of the energy, sciences and technology department at Brookhaven National Laboratory, said at a workshop on biodiesel held at the lab in early April. It is a key technology, he said, for a ''world where petroleum is not our main source of energy.''</p>
        <p>The workshop highlighted the potential of biodiesel to reduce petroleum use and to reduce air pollution from home oil burners and heavy-duty diesel trucks, buses and construction equipment.</p>
        <p>Two Suffolk legislators, Daniel Losquadro, Republican of Shoreham, and Vivian Viloria-Fisher, Democrat of East Setauket, said that under legislation passed last November, the county would begin to use biodiesel within the next two months to replace 25 percent of the 350,000 gallons of diesel fuel it uses a year. To cover the additional cost, the county allocated $25,000 in its budget.</p>
        <p>''What makes biodiesel so appealing is that it can be put in the same tanks, pumped through the same pumps, and burned in the same engines'' as diesel made from petroleum, Mr. Losquadro said.</p>
        <p>When Brookhaven began using standard diesel fuel with a 20 percent blend of biodiesel for maintenance and utility vehicles in November 2002, the change was seamless, with ''no perceived performance reduction,'' said Dennis Lynch, the environmental liaison to the town supervisor. The town has used 112,000 gallons of biodiesel since then and expects to use 100,000 gallons this year.</p>
        <p>A major topic at the workshop was using biodiesel for home heating. Thomas Butcher, a research engineer at the Brookhaven lab, said he had found that a 20 percent mix of biodiesel with standard No.2 heating oil (a mix known as B20) is very compatible with traditional home heating equipment and provides ''positive emission benefits.''</p>
        <p>Biodiesel contains no sulfur, so a B20 blend cuts sulfur emissions by 20 percent and reduces the tiny particles implicated as a cause of asthma by about 15 percent, Dr. Butcher said. Biodiesel also lowers emissions of carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide, the Environmental Protection Agency said.</p>
        <p>Ralph Mills, who owns a heating oil company in Newburgh, N.Y., said at the workshop that when he tested B20 with about 100 customers this winter, he was concerned that the fuel might gel in very cold weather or clog filters and fuel lines. But he had no problems.</p>
        <p>B20 heating oil is sold by a small number of dealers in New England and Pennsylvania, but not yet on Long Island. Paul Nazzaro, a consultant to the National Biodiesel Board, a trade group supported by soybean farmers, said that the board had begun an effort to make biodiesel ''a standard part of home heating oil'' within three years.</p>
        <p>Skeptics point out that last year only about 30 million gallons of biodiesel were commercially produced in the United States; by comparison, 6.7 billion gallons of heating oil are used a year. But new production facilities, including a 30-million-gallon plant in Minnesota, will come on line this year.</p>
        <p>Until recently, 100 percent biodiesel cost 50 cents to $1 a gallon more than petroleum diesel or home heating oil. Prices for petroleum diesel and heating oil hit record highs recently, while a new federal excise-tax credit cut the price of biodiesel, making blends more competitive.</p>
        <p>David Schildwachter Sr., a diesel fuel wholesaler with a terminal near the Whitestone Bridge, said that his company sold more than a million gallons of B20 last year to the United States Postal Service, Consolidated Edison and other customers. John Shipman, the chief automotive engineer for Con Edison, said the company had experienced none of the leaks or other problems it worried about.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
