<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wal-Mart To Seek Savings In Energy</title>
    <meta content="25walmart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/25/business/25walmart.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20051028T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1712345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbaro, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, H Lee Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Scott, H Lee Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D7103FF936A15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wal-Mart To Seek Savings In Energy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wal-Mart to Seek Savings in Energy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL BARBARO and FELICITY BARRINGER; Michael Barbaro reported from Bentonville, Ark., for this article, and Felicity Barringer from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity; Barbaro, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>BENTONVILLE, Ark., Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wal-Mart chief executive H Lee Scott announces set of sweeping, specific environmental goals to reduce energy use in its stores, double its trucks' fuel efficiency, minimize its use of packaging and pressure thousands of companies in its worldwide supply chain to follow its lead; asserts that embracing energy-conscious and environmentally conscious goals will help both company's bottom line and its customers' needs; Scott's announcement signals that nation's largest retailer is joining nation's largest manufacturer, General Electric, in pursuing policies that set specific goals for environmental performance, while advertising those goals to shareholders and customers and public as strategic business decisions; Scott photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wal-Mart's chief executive is set to announce on Tuesday a set of sweeping, specific environmental goals to reduce energy use in its stores, double its trucks' fuel efficiency, minimize its use of packaging and pressure thousands of companies in its worldwide supply chain to follow its lead.</p>
        <p>Embracing energy-conscious and environmentally conscious goals will help both the company's bottom line and its customers' needs, H. Lee Scott said in an interview Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wal-Mart's chief executive is set to announce a set of sweeping, specific environmental goals to reduce energy use in its stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wal-Mart's chief executive is set to announce on Tuesday a set of sweeping, specific environmental goals to reduce energy use in its stores, double its trucks' fuel efficiency, minimize its use of packaging and pressure thousands of companies in its worldwide supply chain to follow its lead.</p>
        <p>Embracing energy-conscious and environmentally conscious goals will help both the company's bottom line and its customers' needs, H. Lee Scott said in an interview Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott's announcement signals that the nation's largest retailer is joining the nation's largest manufacturer, General Electric, in pursuing policies that set specific goals for environmental performance, while advertising those goals to shareholders and customers and the public as strategic business decisions.</p>
        <p>G.E. faced criticism for its own environmental practices; Wal-Mart has faced criticism as well, but largely over its low wages, scant health insurance coverage and what its critics have called poor treatment of workers. Those critics responded to Wal-Mart's environmental initiative by saying that, while admirable, it is intended to divert attention from the chain's image problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott told Wal-Mart's top officers here this morning, in an address broadcast to employees by video conference, that, ''As one of the largest companies in the world, with an expanding global presence, environmental problems are our problems.''</p>
        <p>His goals, he said, are to invest $500 million in technologies that will reduce greenhouse gases from stores and distribution centers by 20 percent over the next seven years; increase the fuel efficiency of the truck fleet by 25 percent over the next three years and double it within 10 years, and design a new store within four years that is at least 25 percent more energy-efficient.</p>
        <p>News of the upcoming announcement drew carefully parsed praise from leaders of environmental groups, including some, like Environmental Defense, which have a history of joint initiatives with large businesses, and others, like the Sierra Club, which have traditionally been more confrontational.</p>
        <p>In general, they applauded Wal-Mart's initiatives and commitments, but sought assurances that there would be a continuing public accounting -- using a concrete baseline -- of factors like energy use, fuel-efficiency and reduction in solid waste.</p>
        <p>''I thought G.E. was big,'' said Alyson Slater, a spokeswoman for the Global Reporting Initiative, a group based in Amsterdam that provides guidance to companies seeking to analyze and publicly report their environmental practices. ''But Wal-Mart? Whoa. That's big.''</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of people out there who are going to be skeptical,'' she added. ''But if they can prove it, if they can say: Here's our targets. Here's how we're meeting them,'' then the company could win over many skeptics, she said.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart's community activist and organized labor critics said the environmental goals failed to address what they said were the company's most pressing problems.</p>
        <p>''It is a diversionary tactic,'' said Chris Kofinis, of Wake Up Wal-Mart, a group founded by the United Food and Commercial Workers Union, which is trying to organize the chain's workers. ''Wal-Mart understands that they have a growing public relations disaster on their hands. American people are looking at a company with $10 billion in profit and $285 billion in sales that makes excuse after excuse about why it can't provide a living wage and health care to its workers.''</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Scott outlined a new health insurance plan with lower premiums but relatively high out-of-pocket deductible requirements that he said would make benefits more affordable to the company's 1.3 million United States workers. But Ron Pollack, executive director of Families U.S.A., a health care consumer advocacy group, criticized the plan, saying employees who signed up for it would be deterred from seeking medical care because of the out-of-pocket costs, which might exceed $2,500 a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott struck a defiant note on Wal-Mart's wages, which average less than $10 an hour, or less than $19,000 a year. ''Even slight overall adjustments to wages eliminate our thin profit margin,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In an unusual move, Mr. Scott asked Congress to consider raising the minimum wage. ''We can see first hand at Wal-Mart how many of our customers are struggling to get by,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The company's environmental initiative includes improving energy efficiency at its 1,876 supercenters, which now consume an average of 1.5 million kilowatts of electricity annually, according to Tara Stewart, a spokeswoman for the company. A model center in McKinney, Tex., has in its first few months shown an improvement of slightly less than 10 percent, she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott said that as the largest buyer of manufactured goods in the world, Wal-Mart has the power to encourage its more than 60,000 suppliers to adopt environmentally conscious business practices. ''Our most direct impact will be on our suppliers,'' he said. ''If we request that our suppliers use packaging that has less waste or materials that can be recycled, everybody who buys from that manufacturer will end up using that package.''</p>
        <p>As an example of how the company can encourage better packaging, Mr. Scott said he would ensure prime placement, at the end of store aisles, for a 32-ounce bottle of All laundry detergent that has been concentrated to reduce the container's size. The goal, the company said, is for all laundry detergent suppliers to offer similar packaging by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Asked why Wal-Mart, whose critics have railed against its wages and health insurance plan, chose to focus on the environment, Mr. Scott said: ''There is work going on in all of those areas. But there is not the ability to change as much in many of those areas as we can change in this area of environmental sustainability.''</p>
        <p>The company is also keenly aware that environmental issues are a high priority to the higher-income shopper that Wal-Mart is courting with a new line of urban fashions, 400-thread-count sheets and a line of baby clothes made with organic cotton.</p>
        <p>''That customer was not the inspiration'' for the proposals, Mr. Scott said, but added: ''I think an outcome of what we are doing with sustainability'' is ''that customer will have a better feeling about Wal-Mart and more positive reaction to Wal-Mart.''</p>
        <p>The commitments to environmental sustainability come after what the company described as an intense, yearlong listening tour that took Mr. Scott and his top managers to a maple syrup farm in New Hampshire, where they studied the impact of rising world temperatures, and the cotton farms of Turkey, where they examined the role of toxins in clothing manufacturing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scott said in the interview that company executives next week would talk to Chinese government officials to learn about, and try to influence, that country's embryonic program to encourage environmentally sound manufacturing practices.</p>
        <p>An Feng, the director of the Auto Project on Energy and Climate Change, based in Beijing, said in a telephone interview that the government was calling for business and nonprofit partners to help shape its efforts. ''It's a big challenge'' to come up with such a system, he said.</p>
        <p>The trucks in Wal-Mart's fleet, the nation's largest, have a fuel efficiency of about 6.5 miles per gallon. ''They can do at least 13,'' said Amory Lovins, chief executive of the Rocky Mountain Institute, a nonprofit organization that serves as a consultant to companies on energy efficiency and has performed work for Wal-Mart. ''They are a big enough buyer to get truck suppliers' undivided attention.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lovins added: ''The reason Wal-Mart's leadership in this area is so important is that they have the scale and market power to change what is offered, and to change it rapidly.''</p>
        <p>Carl Pope, the executive director of the Sierra Club and a board member of Wal-Mart Watch, a group critical of Wal-Mart, said that, from an environmental standpoint, Wal-Mart's stated goals would bring tangible improvements.</p>
        <p>But, he said, they had not addressed the land-use impact of locating new stores in rural areas, covering fields or wetlands and prompting customers to consume extra gasoline to reach them. Even so, ''these are positive steps,'' Mr. Pope said. ''If they do these things, it's not greenscamming. If they did what they say they will, it would be major shift.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 28, 2005, Friday  An article in Business Day on Tuesday about Wal-Mart's energy conservation proposal referred imprecisely to its plans to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases by 20 percent over the next seven years. The proposal covers only existing stores and distribution centers; the 20 percent reduction will be more than offset by the company's plans to add stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 28, 2005, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Tuesday about Wal-Mart's energy conservation proposal referred imprecisely to its plans to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases by 20 percent over the next seven years. The proposal covers only existing stores and distribution centers; the 20 percent reduction will be more than offset by the company's plans to add stores.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
