<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Only May, and the Tanorexics Are Already Complaining</title>
    <meta content="13FRI3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/13/opinion/13fri3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1672051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial Observer"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Carol E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suntan Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suntan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American Academy of Dermatology</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DD1130F930A25756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Only May, and the Tanorexics Are Already Complaining</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It's Only May, and the Tanorexics Are Already Complaining</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL E. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Carol E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial Observer by Carol E Lee on tanned skin as fashion statement; describes those who keep pursuing tan--by excessive sunbathing or frequent visits to tanning salon--as tanorexic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A friend of mine stopped by my apartment on the night she returned from a recent five-day vacation in the Dominican Republic. Her olive skin had tanned to a deep golden brown. But, she exclaimed, could I believe it? Her tan had faded on the four-hour airplane ride back to New York, and she needed to visit a tanning salon to get it back!</p>
        <p>I could not believe it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's something new (and bronze) under the sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A friend of mine stopped by my apartment on the night she returned from a recent five-day vacation in the Dominican Republic. Her olive skin had tanned to a deep golden brown. But, she exclaimed, could I believe it? Her tan had faded on the four-hour airplane ride back to New York, and she needed to visit a tanning salon to get it back!</p>
        <p>I could not believe it.</p>
        <p>My friend is ''tanorexic'' -- a term another friend and I first used in college when I roomed with a woman who couldn't get enough of the sun -- and the sun just couldn't get her tan enough. We knew there was no comparison with the devastating effects of being anorexic, but the syndromes seemed to have a lot more in common than just being health issues that largely affect women.</p>
        <p>Like an anorexic who looks in the mirror and sees a body that no one else sees, my roommate would inspect her bronzed limbs, press her index finger against her flesh and sincerely complain about being so pale. That her sounding board was a pasty blonde whose tanning potential was limited to various shades of pink did nothing to help her see her skin for what it was: tanned. Undeniably, extremely tanned.</p>
        <p>Never are tanorexics more evident than at the start of spring. That's usually when they become hypnotized by their first tan of the season, and they are unable to think sensibly until the fall.</p>
        <p>They're easily identifiable. Their ranks include that co-worker or that woman behind the counter at the drugstore who looks as if she's spent an entire summer in the tropics, even though the last bits of snow have barely melted. Some tanorexics appear orange or leathery, but more often they're just unseasonably or consistently overbronzed.</p>
        <p>Tanorexics live in constant fear that their color is fading. They cringe at the suggestion of sunblock and act as if SPF stands for ''sunless and pale forever.'' Rivaling the sun worshipping of the ancient Egyptians, they are the people at the beach who rotate their chairs with every slight movement of their deity. They disrobe on their lunch hours to bask outdoors. They want to out-tan everyone, even themselves. When the real sun isn't providing satisfactory color, they fake-bake at tanning salons -- sometimes year-round. When that isn't enough, and it usually isn't, they brush bronzer over faces, necks and beyond.</p>
        <p>In college, I was alarmed by my roommate's unabashed absorption of every UVA and UVB ray that found its way to her -- or that she sought in a tanning bed. But I rationalized it as one of the rites of youth. Some of my friends had unnervingly understanding parents who didn't respond to the shock value of bellybutton rings or purple hair, so a really satisfying rebellion sometimes had to take the form of something unhealthy, like smoking or a succession of sunburns. And 18 is the age to enjoy ignorant bliss before it gives way to adulthood and worries about wrinkles and skin cancer.</p>
        <p>Even so, my social circle should have aged out of its ultratanning phase by now. Surely knowing that the American Academy of Dermatology says that one in five Americans will develop some type of skin cancer, or that one American dies from melanoma nearly every hour, should put a stop to the obsession. Unfortunately, it doesn't.</p>
        <p>Tanorexics continue to fry in the face of skin cancer warnings and a dwindling ozone layer -- with only a coating of baby oil between them and the sun. In matters of health versus style, style always wins -- in the short term. The negative effects of tanning -- sagging skin, wrinkles, age spots and cancer -- often don't show up for years, while the immediate results are usually admired.</p>
        <p>But skin cancer, the most commonly diagnosed type of cancer in the United States, is not occurring just among middle-age sun worshippers. More and more doctors are finding skin cancer in women in their 20's. Melanoma is the most common form of cancer in women 25 to 29.</p>
        <p>Studies have shown that tanning bed use -- which is on the rise -- increases a person's risk of developing skin cancer. Some British dermatologists have even started using ''tanorexia'' to describe people who are addicted to sun beds.</p>
        <p>Perhaps tanorexics can't help themselves because sunshine stimulates the pineal gland below the brain, and the gland produces hormones that can improve mood. That's a generous thought, but it's more likely they are driven by vanity, and the perfectly bronzed bodies gracing fashion magazine covers.</p>
        <p>History is full of examples of humans' adopting the fashions of the day and suffering harm to their long-term health. Women of ancient Greece and Rome used lead paints and chalks to whiten their faces; later, in the 18th and 19th centuries, women swallowed arsenic to achieve a pale complexion.</p>
        <p>The tanning trend was popularized in the 1920's, but it was the decade's fashion icon, Coco Chanel, who tipped the scale when she returned from a vacation with -- gasp! -- a suntan. Pale-skinned women across the Western world emerged from beneath their wide-brimmed hats, and from there it was only a hop, skip and jump to George Hamilton, the ultimate overtanned man.</p>
        <p>Spray-on tanning may be the one realistic solution for the solar-obsessed. It is the safest way to get a tan, according to the Skin Cancer Foundation. People can have their bodies sprayed with a temporary skin-coloring agent, dihydroxyacetone, to the shade of their choice. The tan lasts about a week -- or, for tanorexics, about a day or two.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, there will be those who overdo it, and the rest of us will still have to look at their orange Oompa Loompa skin. But at least it's safer.</p>
        <p>Editorial Observer</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
