<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>But the Employees Are Really Spineless</title>
    <meta content="10NJTERRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fertilizer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Worms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Compost</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Terracycle (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Szaky, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fertilizer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DF173EF933A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>But the Employees Are Really Spineless</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on TerraCycle in Trenton, NJ, founded by Princeton dropout Tom Szaky, which turns solid waste into compost made by millions of worms and then into liquid plant food; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TOM SZAKY'S freshman friends at Princeton insisted he show them his native Canada, so off they drove to McGill University in Montreal.</p>
        <p>As it happened, one of Mr. Szaky's acquaintances had a terrarium in which worms ate solid waste and made compost out of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TOM SZAKY'S freshman friends at Princeton insisted he show them his native Canada, so off they drove to McGill University in Montreal.</p>
        <p>As it happened, one of Mr. Szaky's acquaintances had a terrarium in which worms ate solid waste and made compost out of it.</p>
        <p>It got Mr. Szaky to thinking: If a few worms can make a little bit of compost, then a lot of worms could eat a lot of waste and produce a lot of compost.</p>
        <p>Thus was born TerraCycle, what Mr. Szaky -- now a Princeton dropout -- calls the most environmentally friendly business around.</p>
        <p>''Everything we use is recycled, even, you might say, the worm poop,'' said Mr. Szaky, who would be graduating this spring from Princeton had he not taken what he calls an ''indefinite leave'' during his sophomore year to found TerraCycle.</p>
        <p>TerraCycle's main product, a liquid plant food not unlike Miracle-Gro, is manufactured in much the same way Mr. Szaky saw in his friend's terrarium. The company gets its organic waste primarily from those who would otherwise be dumping it in the Burlington County landfill. It is then sifted through containers holding millions of worms at the Rutgers EcoComplex, a greenhouse-like center in nearby Bordentown.</p>
        <p>The resulting worm excrement is then trucked to TerraCycle's offices and mixing plant in Trenton, where it is heated, liquefied and bottled for shipping.</p>
        <p>In about two years, the 22-year-old Mr. Szaky said he went from a university freshman to chief executive of a company with $3 million in sales projected for this year.</p>
        <p>The plant food is already stocked in places like Whole Foods, Home Depot, Shop-Rite and local hardware stores, but Mr. Szaky says that is only the beginning. For instance, he said he now has an arrangement with Wal-Mart in Canada as well.</p>
        <p>''The catch is, though, we are able to make an environmentally sound product and do it more cheaply than big manufacturers,'' he said. ''Basically, everything, from our workers -- the worms -- to our containers are recycled, and we get it for next to nothing.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of the containers, they may look familiar. In fact, the customer could have had soda from the bottle and pumped Windex with the spray nozzle. That is because TerraCycle either buys or collects old plastic soda bottles, washes them and reuses them for the plant food. Similarly, it gets recycled spray tops before they make it to the landfill.</p>
        <p>And because the liquid plant food can decompose in light, the bottle is wrapped tightly with recycled paper and plastic. Even the cardboard boxes in which TerraCycle is shipped are recycled or factory seconds.</p>
        <p>With that, Mr. Szaky proudly shows off some boxes -- with the word Dasani misspelled -- at the Trenton plant that will soon carry his product.</p>
        <p>''I have to admit that I am not all that much of an eco-freak, though I am glad we are doing things that way,'' Mr. Szaky said. ''But the point is that all this is cheaper, too. The bottles, the boxes, the organic waste -- we get it for nothing or next to nothing. Sometimes the suppliers even pay us to take it away.''</p>
        <p>Even some of the TerraCycle executives are recycled.</p>
        <p>Take Richard F. Ober Jr., the company's 61-year-old vice president and general counsel. Mr. Ober had been general counsel at Summit Bank for 26 years when it was bought out by FleetBoston in 2001. Casting about for something new to do, Mr. Ober saw an advertisement in a Princeton alumni networking e-mail newsletter about a start-up fertilizer business.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know all that much about this kind of business, but then, they didn't know that much about the kind of legal work I could help with,'' he said. ''I signed on, and it's been great working with these young people ever since.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Szaky got TerraCycle's first round of financing by ''begging relatives, maxing out credit cards, the usual story for start-ups'' -- and built his first huge terrarium on the Princeton campus, recycling waste from dining halls. The next round of capital came from winning prizes for business plans and a few angels in the form of investors. He said he even refused $1 million from one contest because the backers wanted him to stop recycling garbage, a move that would have sacrificed the ethical center of the company, according to Mr. Szaky.</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Ober said his main job is finding another $1.5 million so the company can expand.</p>
        <p>''The way we have to go is find what we call 'green angels,' people who are interested in the ecology and socially beneficial processes,'' Mr. Ober said.</p>
        <p>For now, TerraCycle has about 20 employees, mostly in sales and at the bottling plant, not to mention what Mr. Ober calls ''several million non-union, hard-working worms.''</p>
        <p>David Specca, the acting director of the Rutgers EcoComplex, is happy to have TerraCycle there.</p>
        <p>''We're part of Cook College and do applied research and business development,'' Mr. Specca said. ''Our focus is on controlled-environment agriculture, raising crops or animals in a controlled way, so we specialize in renewable energy and solid-waste management, which is what TerraCycle does. It's perfect that we have been an incubator for that kind of business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Szaky said he will employ as many as 50 interns, primarily from Princeton, this summer to do everything from sweeping floors at the Trenton plant to researching new plant-food formulas to setting up computer programs.</p>
        <p>''One of our former interns started a Toronto sales office,'' he said. ''We hope we can, I guess, recycle their talents in whatever ways we can find.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
