<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aftershocks From a Killing</title>
    <meta content="10WECROS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1686074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CROSS WESTCHESTER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EED6163DF933A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aftershocks From a Killing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Debra West</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the case proceeds against a homeless ex-convict accused of stabbing a woman to death in a White Plains parking garage in June, Westchester officials have offered various proposals to protect residents from violent sex offenders.</p>
        <p>Mayor Joseph Delfino of White Plains has threatened to sue the county to stop it from busing the homeless into downtown White Plains from the airport drop-in shelter every morning. (The shelter is closed during the day.) The suspect, Philip Grant, 43, was dropped off in White Plains by a county shuttle bus on the morning of the murder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the case proceeds against a homeless ex-convict accused of stabbing a woman to death in a White Plains parking garage in June, Westchester officials have offered various proposals to protect residents from violent sex offenders.</p>
        <p>Mayor Joseph Delfino of White Plains has threatened to sue the county to stop it from busing the homeless into downtown White Plains from the airport drop-in shelter every morning. (The shelter is closed during the day.) The suspect, Philip Grant, 43, was dropped off in White Plains by a county shuttle bus on the morning of the murder.</p>
        <p>''I am calling on the county to halt this practice which jeopardizes the safety of our residents,'' Mayor Delfino said in a prepared statement. ''If necessary I will initiate legal action to stop this practice. This can never happen here again.''</p>
        <p>District Attorney Jeanine Pirro has called for civil commitment laws, similar to those already on the books in 12 other states, which would allow indefinite confinement of violent sex offenders.</p>
        <p>And County Executive Andrew J. Spano, who has also been seeking civil commitment laws, is urging constituents to demand them from their state legislators as well. A link has been added to the county Web site, westchestergov.com, that will set up a blank e-mail connection with the state legislators who represent Westchester. (You have to fill in the subject line and write the e-mail message yourself.)</p>
        <p>Kayakers Welcome Here</p>
        <p>In addition to the tugboats, cargo ships and sailboats that normally coast along the Hudson, river watchers in the county will soon be seeing a pod of energetic kayakers making their way downstream.</p>
        <p>The Great Hudson River Paddle 2005 started July 8 in Albany. It is the fifth annual paddle intended to celebrate the Hudson River Greenway Water Trail and the cleanup of the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Nearly 35 kayakers are expected to paddle 146.2 miles in swells of up to three feet, fighting winds, tides and the strong wakes of low-riding cargo ships, before they reach New York Harbor on July 17. Along the way the paddlers will stop in several Westchester communities. On Thursday, they are scheduled to travel 10.5 miles from Cold Spring, in Putnam County, to Annsville Creek in Cortlandt Manor. On Friday, they are to arrive at Croton Point (after a 9.7-mile jaunt), and on Saturday they will paddle 17.3 miles to the new user-friendly riverfront in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>When they come ashore there, the paddlers are to kick off the Community Festival at the Beczak Environmental Education Center, which has interactive exhibits about river ecology and a great open lawn that stretches to the water. The site opened last year, but its inauguration ceremony was washed out by Hurricane Ivan.</p>
        <p>''This will be our first big community event, if the weather holds out,'' said Kathleen Savolt, director.</p>
        <p>The educational and environmental activities at Beczak, on Alexander Street, begin at 2 p.m., when children can set to work making a banner to welcome the paddlers -- who are expected between 3 and 4 p.m. Later the festivities will move on to the Yonkers downtown Waterfront Esplanade -- where, Ms. Savolt said, there will be music, food, storytelling and more.</p>
        <p>Beautiful Invaders</p>
        <p>Perhaps the definition of invasive nonnative plants is that they crowd out the native species, which migrating birds and other animals rely on for food and shelter. But one reason the problem exists is that alien plants can be so darned pretty. Homeowners demand them and landscapers readily plant them.</p>
        <p>Now an art exhibition at Lasdon Park Arboretum and Veterans Memorial, on Route 35 in Somers, seeks to help the public recognize some plants that will escape from the front yard and colonize the woods for miles around. The show, called ''Alive in New York, a Growing Invasion,'' also presents illustrations of alternative native species that are perceived as equally beautiful but are far less damaging to the environment.</p>
        <p>''Partially because of climate change,'' said Chris Sanders, an exhibition curator and featured artist, ''more plants survive longer, and somehow that may be a trigger to take a noninvasive plant and push it so that it escapes and takes over.''</p>
        <p>The exhibition of 43 paintings, drawings and etchings was organized by the Greater New York Chapter of the Guild of Natural Science Illustrators, 29 of whose members created the works. It can be found in the Main House Gallery at Lasdon Park, noon to 3:30 p.m. on weekends through Aug. 7. Lasdon Park is the first stop on its statewide tour.</p>
        <p>Some illustrations, like the black-and-white line drawing of the Multiflora rose, by Monika E. deVries Gohlke, are so delicate that it is hard to imagine the plant as a menace.</p>
        <p>''That's why they are a threat,'' Ms. Sanders said. ''Some of them are quite beautiful. Hopefully people will have the choice before them and be guided by their consciences to choose the native species.''</p>
        <p>CROSS WESTCHESTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
