<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Catch The Wind</title>
    <meta content="25njCOVER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/25/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/25njCOVER.ready.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1727381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D71430F936A15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="2664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Catch The Wind</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying to Catch the Wind</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ED McDONALD, a low roller at the Borgata Hotel Casino and Spa, was waiting for a jitney when he paused to gawk at what may turn out to be yet another of this city's tourist attractions -- the nation's first coastal wind farm, whose sleek 380-foot-high turbines stand like immense kinetic sculptures at the entrance to this seaside resort.</p>
        <p>''It's clean energy, it's futuristic, it doesn't block the view,'' said Mr. McDonald, 52, an unemployed warehouse worker who had just quit the blackjack tables after four hours and enough losing hands for one day. ''Offshore, out in the water, then I would say they'd be a problem, then you're taking away from the seashore itself, the view and everything.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A coastal wind farm at the shore represents a big first step in the search for new energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ED McDONALD, a low roller at the Borgata Hotel Casino and Spa, was waiting for a jitney when he paused to gawk at what may turn out to be yet another of this city's tourist attractions -- the nation's first coastal wind farm, whose sleek 380-foot-high turbines stand like immense kinetic sculptures at the entrance to this seaside resort.</p>
        <p>''It's clean energy, it's futuristic, it doesn't block the view,'' said Mr. McDonald, 52, an unemployed warehouse worker who had just quit the blackjack tables after four hours and enough losing hands for one day. ''Offshore, out in the water, then I would say they'd be a problem, then you're taking away from the seashore itself, the view and everything.''</p>
        <p>Federal and state officials are betting on wind power as an environmentally friendly and economically viable way to help reduce the ever-growing dependence on fossil fuels for generating electricity, particularly along New Jersey's rapidly growing Shore communities.</p>
        <p>The Jersey-Atlantic Wind Farm will be operated here by a Pennsylvania company known as Community Energy. It will be on the grounds of the Atlantic County Utility Authority's water treatment plant. Once they begin operating early next year, the farm's five wind turbines, built by GE Wind Energy, a division of General Electric, will spin out a total of 7.5 megawatts of electricity, enough to supply 60 percent of the treatment plant's power needs and electrify 2,500 households.</p>
        <p>Thousands of private and commercial turbines already harvest gusts along ridgelines, farm fields and windswept plains in 30 states, according to the American Wind Energy Association, a trade group in Washington. But the Atlantic City project, which state and industry officials say will be the first coastal wind farm in the United States, is perhaps most important because of its role as a demonstration project at a crucial moment in the development of wind power in New Jersey and the nation.</p>
        <p>''I think our project will give people a sense of what is being discussed,'' said Richard Dovey, executive director of the utility authority.</p>
        <p>But government and industry officials say New Jersey's real wind power potential lies offshore, where the strength and regularity of the wind far exceeds overland breezes. And in windmill circles, much of the discussion these days is on an ambitious proposal to plant a total of 1,019 turbines like those in Atlantic City in the seabed a few miles off that hallowed source of state pride and tourism dollars known as the Jersey Shore.</p>
        <p>Fueling doubts, speculation and controversy over the proposal is the fact that there have never been offshore windmills in United States waters, though Winergy is just one of several companies that have applied for permits to erect them in at least a half-dozen states. The issue is particularly sensitive in New Jersey, where residents take special pride in the state's 127-mile coastline, and much of the state's huge tourism industry depends on it.</p>
        <p>Opponents of offshore windmills can be assured that Winergy's plans, which call for five distinct wind farms from Seaside Heights to Cape May, are not likely to be realized soon. The Department of the Interiors Minerals Management Service, an agency that was given permitting and regulatory authority over offshore windmills by federal legislation in August, has tabled all but two proposals, one off Long Island and the other in Nantucket Sound, while it drafts permitting and operating guidelines for the nascent offshore wind power industry.</p>
        <p>A Moratorium and a Final Report</p>
        <p>Gary Strasburg, a spokesman for the minerals service, which also regulates natural gas and oil extraction on the continental shelf, said the wind regulations should be complete by May, when the agency will resume reviewing permit applications. The minerals service inherited the wind jurisdiction from the Army Corps of Engineers, which will continue to be involved in the permit process.</p>
        <p>Apart from any delays in approval resulting from the regulatory handoff, there is currently a moratorium in place on state financing or permitting of offshore wind projects that was imposed by Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey last December, when he also appointed a panel to study the issue. Even outside state waters, the federal Coastal Zone Management Act gives states a say in projects likely to have an effect on their coastlines.</p>
        <p>Last month, the nine-member panel appointed by Mr. Codey, formally known as the Blue Ribbon Panel on Development of Wind Turbine Facilities in Coastal Waters issued an interim report laying out the environmental, aesthetic and economic pros and cons of offshore windmills. In March, when the moratorium is scheduled to be lifted, the panel is to present a final report, with recommendations, to the new governor, Jon S. Corzine.</p>
        <p>The panel, which is being headed by Mayor Edward J. McKenna Jr. of Red Bank, includes leaders and officials from the environmental, tourism and energy fields. One member, Jeanne M. Fox, who is president of the New Jersey Board of Public Utilities, seemed to be leaning in favor of offshore wind power in remarks she made after a Dec. 12 dedication ceremony for Atlantic City's project, the state's first utility-level wind farm.</p>
        <p>''It's a small step in reducing fossil-fuel carbon emissions, but it's important in that millions of people who come to Atlantic City every year will be seeing these wind turbines,'' Ms. Fox said. ''Even though they are not offshore, they are about as close to offshore as you can get.''</p>
        <p>She and others are counting on wind to play a major role in the state's plans to reduce carbon emissions from fossil fuels. In 1999, the Legislature approved a law requiring energy companies to include renewable energy sources like the sun, wind and wood-burning furnaces, in their power portfolios. Standards developed by the utilities board call for 6.5 percent of the electricity used in New Jersey be from renewable sources. In September, the Board of Public Utilities proposed increasing the number to 20 percent by 2020.</p>
        <p>Nothing New in Europe</p>
        <p>Europe -- where windmills compete with tulips as national symbols and Cervantes tilted his quixotic hero at them 400 years ago -- is far ahead of the United States in the use of wind power, with more than 34,000 megawatts of capacity in 2004, or nearly two thirds of the world's wind energy supply, according to the European Wind Energy Association. Denmark, for example, derives about 20 percent of its electricity from the wind.</p>
        <p>The United States, by comparison, had a total wind power capacity of just 6,740 megawatts in 2004, providing less than one percent of the country's power, said Christine Real de Azua, a spokeswoman for the American Wind Energy Association, an affiliate of the European group under the Global Wind Energy Council.</p>
        <p>So far, Europe accounts for all of the world's offshore wind power, Ms. Azua said. The largest offshore facility is at Nysted, Denmark, where 72 light-gray turbines rise 360 feet above the North Sea, generating up to 165 megawatts of electricity, or enough to power 145,000 homes. But even in Europe, offshore wind power is still uncommon, accounting for only 600 megawatts in 2004.</p>
        <p>Right now, virtually none of New Jersey's electricity is generated by wind turbines. Rather, the state gets about half its power from its four nuclear reactors (the national average is 20 percent), while 30 percent is generated by natural gas, according to the federal Energy Information Administration. The state's third leading energy source, at 18 percent in 2004, is coal.</p>
        <p>The wind panel noted in its interim report that New Jersey consumes more electricity than it produces, forcing the state's power companies to import electricity from other plants within the Pennsylvania-New Jersey-Maryland (PJM) power grid, including upwind coal-burning plants that emit deadly sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide particles.</p>
        <p>''Many of these out-of-state facilities use fossil fuels and are upwind of New Jersey, adding to the state's air quality problems,'' the report says. ''All are beyond the state's regulatory authority to control air pollutants.''</p>
        <p>The report also notes the state's demand for energy is increasing at about 1.4 percent a year, much of that fueled by the growth of New Jersey's Shore communities.</p>
        <p>Other advantages to developing wind power cited in the report include reduced dependence on often-volatile foreign oil supplies, and potential cost savings; unlike oil prices, the cost of wind does not fluctuate.</p>
        <p>The disadvantages of wind power listed in the report include the hazards that turbine blades and poles pose to birds, boaters, fisherman and the shipping industry; disruption of the ocean floor and marine life during construction; potential contamination from lubricating oil; and their aesthetic impact and any resulting decline in tourism, which generates $32 billion a year in economic activity and accounts for 430,000 jobs, 40 percent of which are in the state's four oceanfront counties -- Monmouth, Ocean, Atlantic and Cape May.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who cares about New Jersey cares about the tourism industry,'' said Ms. Fox.</p>
        <p>Beyond New Jersey, federal permits have been sought for offshore farms in Delaware, Maryland, Virginia, Georgia and elsewhere. The Long Island Power Authority and a Florida company, FPL Energy, are jointly seeking a permit for a wind farm off Jones Beach.</p>
        <p>''We are in a bit of a race,'' said Bert Cunningham, a spokesman for the Long Island Power Authority.</p>
        <p>Controversy in Nantucket Sound</p>
        <p>But the most visible and most controversial proposal so far is one by a Massachusetts company known as Cape Wind Associates, which wants to erect 130 turbines in Nantucket Sound. A final decision on the project is scheduled for January 2007, following public hearings this summer, said Mr. Strasburg, the spokesman for the minerals service.</p>
        <p>The project has been vigorously opposed by Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts and his nephew, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., senior counsel to the Environmental Defense Fund, who has said he supports offshore wind power -- particularly once deep-water technology is developed -- but that he opposes the Cape Wind project on the ground that it would spoil a marine wilderness and recreation area, and because a study suggests it would cost the local economy over a billion dollars a year and more than 2,500 tourism jobs.</p>
        <p>''Cape Wind's proposal involves construction of 130 giant turbines whose windmill arms will reach 417 feet above the water and be visible for up to 26 miles,'' Mr. Kennedy wrote this month in an Op-Ed article in The New York Times. ''These turbines are less than six miles from shore and would be seen from Cape Cod, Martha's Vineyard and Nantucket. Hundreds of flashing lights to warn airplanes away from the turbines will steal the stars and nighttime views.''</p>
        <p>An amendment to a federal Coast Guard financing bill, now pending before a House-Senate conference committee, would bar wind farms within 1.5 miles of shipping lanes, and effectively kill the Cape Wind project. Mark Rogers, a spokesman for Cape Wind, noted that the project would be in view of the famous Kennedy family compound in Hyannisport, and he said that Mr. Kennedy was taking an all-too-common position on offshore windmills: they sound like a good idea, but not in my backyard -- or in this case, not off my beach.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what it means, frankly, to say you're in favor of wind energy as an abstract concept, but then to oppose real-world, practical projects that can be achieved soon and start delivering the benefits of wind energy to your community,'' Mr. Rogers said.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Mr. Cunningham said that Long Islanders were initially supportive of wind power, but that the reaction to the Jones Beach proposal was decidedly mixed once its location became clear.</p>
        <p>Specifics of Winergy's plans have not been subject to public hearings and the attendant news media coverage, and so far, the battle over offshore wind power in New Jersey has not been nearly as pitched as in Massachusetts. But once the debate begins, it seems likely to be intense, considering the scale of the project and the importance of the Shore in New Jersey's very identity.</p>
        <p>A Plan for 5 Farms Offshore</p>
        <p>According to the company's Web site (www.winergyllc.com), the New Jersey plans call for five farms set between 3.5 and 6.4 miles offshore, in 48 to 60 feet of water, spread over an area of 234 square miles. In all, the five farms would have a generating capacity of 3,648 megawatts of electricity, more than half the total generating capacity of all existing windmills in the entire United States.</p>
        <p>The largest of the five farms, known as Five Fathom Bank 1, would include 335 turbines spread over 88 square miles and be situated 3.5 miles off Cape May Point. The northernmost site, off the coast of Asbury Park, calls for 98 turbines set 3.5 miles off the beach. There is no cost estimate for the proposal, said Dennis Quaranta, the president of Winergy.</p>
        <p>Winergy originally applied for permits in 2002. There is no anticipated time frame for a response, said Mr. Strasburg, the spokesman for the Minerals Management Service. In the meantime, Mr. Quaranta said the controversy swirling about the Cape Wind and Jones Beach proposals has prompted him to consider locations much farther off the Jersey Shore than his current proposals, and he is following developments in deep-water turbine technology.</p>
        <p>''We know there's a problem that people aren't happy about seeing these turbines,'' said Mr. Quaranta, known in the industry as a ''wind prospector,'' a 55-year-old former restaurant owner whose experience applying for a federal fish-farm permit led to his interest in developing offshore wind power. ''The permitting is basically the same as a fish farm.''</p>
        <p>To face inland from the boardwalk at Asbury Park is, for all the talk of redevelopment, to look upon a bleak panorama of decaying amusements, crumbling hotels and unfinished apartments. But turn around to face the ocean, and the view is as rich and pristine as in Deal or Loch Arbor, Asbury Park's wealthy neighbors to the north. Even so, the prospect of dozens of wind turbines on the distant horizon was welcomed by Harold Rohrs, who was on the boardwalk recently, braving the December chill for a midday stroll from his home in neighboring Ocean Grove.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rohrs, a 65-year-old retired biology professor who has traveled widely and seen windmills in Europe and Australia, said that they ''certainly were not ugly.''</p>
        <p>''I didn't find them at all disruptive to the environment, to the aesthetics of the environment,'' he said. ''I guess, in truth, I was thinking how marvelous it was that they were using the wind as a renewable source of energy, without adding to the C02 in the environment.''</p>
        <p>The professor is not alone. The wind panel's interim report cites a survey taken in Vermont, which found that people's aesthetic judgment of windmills seemed to be influenced by their attitude toward renewable energy. Essentially, the more people like wind power, the better-looking windmills are to them.</p>
        <p>''Beauty is in the eye of the beholder,'' Mr. Quaranta said of wind turbines. ''People are going to look at them and say they're beautiful. Other people are going to look at them as say, 'Ugh, it's commercializing the ocean.' ''</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
