<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Texan Gets a Friendly Reception on the Steppes</title>
    <meta content="22notebook" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/22/international/asia/22notebook.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1719523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Reporter's Notebook"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mongolia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mongolia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Mongolia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Mongolia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DA1F3EF931A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Texan Gets a Friendly Reception on the Steppes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Texan Gets a Friendly Reception on the Steppes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David</byline>
      <dateline>ULAN BATOR, Mongolia, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook on friendly reception for Pres Bush in Mongolia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are an American president in need of just a few hours of temporary political asylum -- no debate about Iraq, no Chinese leaders resisting the American agenda and plenty of adulation -- here is an approach: Come to the endless steppes that Ghengis Khan made famous.</p>
        <p>When Air Force One descended low over the barren but breathtaking landscape here, few Mongolians had ever seen anything like it. None of the previous American presidents had made the journey while in office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At home, there may be questions about the war in Iraq, but there were not many for President Bush during his visit to Mongolia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you are an American president in need of just a few hours of temporary political asylum -- no debate about Iraq, no Chinese leaders resisting the American agenda and plenty of adulation -- here is an approach: Come to the endless steppes that Ghengis Khan made famous.</p>
        <p>When Air Force One descended low over the barren but breathtaking landscape here, few Mongolians had ever seen anything like it. None of the previous American presidents had made the journey while in office.</p>
        <p>And so Mongolians came into this tattered post-Soviet capital, past what will soon be a monument celebrating the spectacular victories eight centuries ago, when the Mongol empire stretched from the Yellow Sea to Baghdad, to hear George W. Bush tell them that today, ''Mongolia and the United States are standing together as brothers in the cause of freedom.'' If it was gratifying for Mongolians to hear that message from the leader of a country that billboards here proclaimed a ''third neighbor'' -- not Russia and not China -- their reaction was probably even more gratifying for President Bush.</p>
        <p>At home, there may be questions about the war in Iraq, but there are not many here. Mongolia recently sent its fifth rotation of troops to Iraq -- it sends roughly 160 at a time.</p>
        <p>In truth, there were four protesters as Mr. Bush bumped past the belching industrial complexes outside Ulan Bator. Two held a sign urging him to get out of Iraq. Two wanted him to sign the Kyoto Protocol on climate change. (For the record, Mongolia signed.)</p>
        <p>Anti-Americanism? ''I haven't heard any,'' said Brett Burkhart, a Peace Corps volunteer from California who has been living in a ger -- a traditional Mongolian domed tent -- in a rural village. ''Well, I did hear it once, but I think the guy was drunk.''</p>
        <p>There is something else that seemed to thrill Mr. Bush about Mongolia: presidential entertainment is vivid.</p>
        <p>As his limousine raced across the steppe, a team of Mongolian warriors -- carrying spears and shields and wearing the body armor that Ghengis Khan used to subdue territory that Mr. Bush is still grappling with 800 years later -- suddenly appeared and galloped alongside.</p>
        <p>Gone from Mr. Bush's face was the let's-get-on-with-it look he had at Gigkakuji, the famed temple he visited in Kyoto, Japan. He talked with the warriors and stepped around camels and yaks to make his way into a quite luxurious ger. Sitting by a wood-burning stove, he chatted with a family of herders. (The Mongolian government says the herders were the real thing, but they live 100 miles out of town, and were brought in to lend some authenticity to the small village erected for Mr. Bush's benefit.) The president sipped a bit of fermented mare's milk, nibbled on some cheese curd and listened to some throat singing.</p>
        <p>The man who once power-walked through Red Square in less than 10 minutes actually lingered. Then, reluctantly, four and a half hours after he landed, Mr. Bush boarded his plane and lifted off -- taking him back to the questions at home about how his presidency can regain its footing amid new debates on the Iraq war.</p>
        <p>Iraq, Every Day, Everywhere</p>
        <p>If Mongolia won its way into Mr. Bush's heart with its unflagging support for the war in Iraq, its attitude was the exception on his four-day trip. The war is deeply unpopular in Japan, his first stop, and his motorcade did not exactly attract huge crowds.</p>
        <p>Things were worse in South Korea, where the defense minister announced, as a fact, that South Korea planned to trim its more than 3,000 troops in Iraq by a third next year. Mr. Bush's aides scrambled to win a retraction. The president's national security adviser, Stephen J. Hadley, called the South Korean foreign minister and was reassured, he said, of the country's ''commitment to the mission.''</p>
        <p>The number of South Korean troops, Mr. Hadley told reporters, ''will depend on the political evolution and the security evolution.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, that evolution happened quickly; on Monday, 48 hours after Mr. Bush left South Korean soil, the country's cabinet approved the reduction of forces next year.</p>
        <p>Then came the Chinese, with their highly attuned sense of political leverage.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to say exactly what led President Hu Jintao to conclude that he would not pay a high price for making vague commitments on revaluing China's currency and for offering no commitments on improving human rights or increasing the pace of democratization.</p>
        <p>Administration officials were clearly surprised that not only did China fail to release any dissidents on a list of human rights cases turned over to Mr. Hu in September, but it also detained more dissidents just before Mr. Bush's arrival.</p>
        <p>Administration officials also seemed vexed that Mr. Bush's statements in China were largely unheard by most of the nation. So perhaps it was no surprise that aides traveling with Mr. Bush were striving to note some accomplishments. Talks with China are about long-term problems, they said, adding that Mr. Hadley had warned before the trip that the president was not seeking immediate ''deliverables,'' apparently referring to specific diplomatic and economic achievements.</p>
        <p>And Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice said that China's willingness to listen to talk about human rights issues was significant. ''I can remember times in the past where, both here and in a number of other countries, you were just told to mind your own business,'' she said when she met with reporters in Beijing on Sunday. ''Well, that's not the case now.''</p>
        <p>For Bush, No Horse of Any Color</p>
        <p>President Bush may love Texas, and his ranch, as he reminded Mongolians when he compared their land to his beloved state. But his enthusiasm does not extend to another Mongolian passion -- horses.</p>
        <p>When Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld was here a month ago, the Mongolians presented him with their highest honor: a beautiful gelding that he named Montana. So in a delicate act of diplomacy, the White House secured an agreement that President Enkhbayar Nambar would not give Mr. Bush a horse. But since the secretary of defense had to look his gift in the mouth -- leaving it here, at least temporarily, because it was a bit difficult to transport on his official plane -- Mr. Bush found another way to saddle up.</p>
        <p>''I'm here on an important international mission,'' Mr. Bush said at the opening of his speech in Government House. ''Secretary Rumsfeld asked me to check on his horse.''</p>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
