<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earthy Evangelist</title>
    <meta content="WLN140634" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/03/magazine/03QUESTIONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1661826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-3-05: QUESTIONS FOR RICHARD CIZIK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Evangelicals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cizik, Richard (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Assn of Evangelicals</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DB123FF930A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earthy Evangelist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Earthy Evangelist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Solomon interviews Richard Cizik, leader of National Association of Evangelicals, on why he believes Christians should care about pollution, global warming and other threats to environment that God gave them and why he prefers to call this 'creation care' rather than 'environmentalism'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: As a leader of the National Association of Evangelicals, you are going up against tradition by trying to persuade your 30 million members to care about pollution, global warming and environmentalism in general.</p>
        <p>The Scriptures themselves, right in Genesis 2:15, say watch over creation and care for it. The air, the water, the resources -- all have been given to us by God to protect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The leader of the country's largest evangelical group wants to get his fellow believers and the president interested in going green  but don't call him an environmentalist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: As a leader of the National Association of Evangelicals, you are going up against tradition by trying to persuade your 30 million members to care about pollution, global warming and environmentalism in general.</p>
        <p>The Scriptures themselves, right in Genesis 2:15, say watch over creation and care for it. The air, the water, the resources -- all have been given to us by God to protect.</p>
        <p>Yet evangelical Christians are famously suspicious of science, which has long been a synonym for atheism. Isn't that why they reject both evolution and environmentalism?</p>
        <p>A lot of conservative evangelicals have a problem with the environmental movement. I don't call myself an environmentalist. I say I'm an advocate of ''creation care.''</p>
        <p>''Creation care'' sounds like a division of Medicare.</p>
        <p>It's still better than environmentalism.</p>
        <p>What is wrong with that term?</p>
        <p>It's not the term. It's the environmentalists themselves. I was recently speaking with the leadership of the Sierra Club and the National Wildlife Federation, and I told them, ''Gentlemen, I respect you, but at this point don't plan on any formal collaborations.''</p>
        <p>Why? Because they lean to the left?</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have a bad reputation among evangelical Christians for four reasons. One, they rely on big-government solutions. Two, their alliance with population-control movements. Three, they keep kooky religious company.</p>
        <p>What is your idea of a kooky religion?</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists are pantheists who believe creation itself is holy, not the Creator.</p>
        <p>And what's No. 4?</p>
        <p>There's a certain gloom and doom about environmentalists. They tend to prophecies of doom that don't happen. Look at the movie ''The Day After Tomorrow,'' in which New York City freezes over.</p>
        <p>Talk about gloom and doom! What about evangelicals like Tim LaHaye, who discourage Christians from worrying about the environment because the earth will just be destroyed in the Second Coming?</p>
        <p>I don't agree with that.</p>
        <p>Do you believe in the Rapture?</p>
        <p>Yes. I believe that there will be a Second Coming of Jesus Christ, and the believers in Christ will rise to meet him in the air. The dead first, and then those who are still living.</p>
        <p>Do you think you will see it in your lifetime?</p>
        <p>If I do, that will be wonderful. But I'm not going to count on it.</p>
        <p>Have you met President Bush?</p>
        <p>On two informal occasions.</p>
        <p>Do you feel that you have good access to the White House?</p>
        <p>I have been in meetings at the White House where the president spoke and meetings outside of the White House at which Karl Rove was a speaker multiple times. As recently as a week ago, I had a phone call from a White House staffer, who said, ''Richard, about your environmentalism, do you have a disagreement with the administration?''</p>
        <p>I would think you do, since the president is under constant pressure from big business to roll back environmental protections.</p>
        <p>If the evangelicals can't convince the president, then no one can.</p>
        <p>Why would President Bush give evangelicals more say than he gives the business community?</p>
        <p>Look, the big corporate interests have an undue say in party policy. And into this reality come the evangelical Christians. And when confronted with making a choice, this administration will compromise. Because about 40 percent of the Republican Party is represented by evangelicals. They wouldn't want the two major constituencies of the Republican Party at war with each other.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 4-3-05: QUESTIONS FOR RICHARD CIZIK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
