<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="08obse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/08/science/08obox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1716023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DE153EF93BA35752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Advice to California Condors: Change Your Diet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Fountain</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Elephant Forgets</p>
        <p>Unlike humans, most other mammals show little concern about the dead. Most pay scant attention to carcasses of fellow members of their species, and ritual burying or caring for bodies is rare.</p>
        <p>African elephants have always been considered an exception. They have been reported to become agitated when they come upon an elephant corpse, poking at it with trunk and feet. They are thought to investigate old bones and tusks in this way, too. Some researchers have even suggested that elephants seek out the bones of dead kin. (Elephant graveyards, however, are just a legend.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>California condors, African elephants and the effects of Mount Pinatubo's 1991 eruption.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Elephant Forgets</p>
        <p>Unlike humans, most other mammals show little concern about the dead. Most pay scant attention to carcasses of fellow members of their species, and ritual burying or caring for bodies is rare.</p>
        <p>African elephants have always been considered an exception. They have been reported to become agitated when they come upon an elephant corpse, poking at it with trunk and feet. They are thought to investigate old bones and tusks in this way, too. Some researchers have even suggested that elephants seek out the bones of dead kin. (Elephant graveyards, however, are just a legend.)</p>
        <p>Karen McComb of the University of Sussex in England and colleagues systematically investigated this interest in bones, using elephants at Amboseli National Park in Kenya as their subjects.</p>
        <p>There is long-term data on more than 2,200 elephants in the park, so the researchers knew which animals were in the same family units, and could use bones of dead family members in the experiments.</p>
        <p>In the study, the researchers approached family groups in a vehicle, placing several objects -- bones or ivory from relatives, from nonrelatives, bones from other species like buffalo, and blocks of wood -- about 75 feet away.</p>
        <p>Then they drove a distance away and watched to see the elephants' reactions. If an elephant was interested in a particular object, the animal would smell it and touch it with the trunk and occasionally manipulate it with the feet.</p>
        <p>The researchers found that the elephants showed more interest in bones and ivory of their own species compared with those of other species or other objects.</p>
        <p>Between bones and ivory, the elephants were markedly more interested in ivory -- perhaps, the researchers said, because elephants sometimes touch the ivory of living elephants in social activities.</p>
        <p>But the study, reported in the journal Biology Letters, a publication of the Royal Society, did not find that elephants were particularly interested in bones or ivory of relatives. The researchers suggested that the reason elephants had sometimes been observed doing this was simply that they were more likely to come upon dead relatives in their home range.</p>
        <p>The Pinatubo Effect</p>
        <p>The 1991 eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines threw millions of tons of ash and sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere. All that gas and dirt reflected more sunlight away from the earth, causing global cooling and otherwise affecting the climate.</p>
        <p>Scientists in Australia have now determined another effect of Pinatubo. Its eruption, considered the second largest of the 20th century, lowered the average sea level.</p>
        <p>The oceans have been rising at a rate of about 1.8 millimeters (slightly more than one-sixteenth of an inch) a year since the 1950's. The rise stems from warmer temperatures, which cause greater melting of ice and also cause the oceans to expand (water takes up more volume as it heats up).</p>
        <p>But there is considerable variability in the rate of rise when viewed over a time frame of a decade or so. The reasons for this variability have not been well explained.</p>
        <p>John A. Church of the marine and atmospheric research division of the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization and colleagues developed climate simulation models to take into account the impact of Pinatubo and other major eruptions over the past century, using data on ocean heat content.</p>
        <p>Their analysis, reported in the journal Nature, showed that sea levels fell after eruptions because the ocean cooled.</p>
        <p>After Pinatubo (which has yielded the best data), the average level fell by five millimeters in about a year.</p>
        <p>The researchers found that this cooling effect slowly dissipated over a decade or possibly longer, causing a Pinatubo-related sea level rise of about half a millimeter a year after the initial dip.</p>
        <p>This recovery, in fact, appears to have contributed to a faster overall rate of sea level rise that has been measured since 1993 -- of about 3.2 millimeters a year, or nearly twice as much as the average rate since 1950.</p>
        <p>Advice to California Condors: Change Your Diet</p>
        <p>In trying to restore the California condor to the wild, conservation groups have run up against a potentially lethal problem: lead poisoning. The scavenging birds eat animal carcasses, including those left by hunters, which can contain lead bullet fragments. So conservation workers often leave stillborn dairy calves in condor areas as safer alternatives.</p>
        <p>But a Stanford scientist has a suggestion, based on his research into condor diets in the past. The scientist, C. Page Chamberlain, says that rather than eating lead-tainted carrion or relying on handouts, condors could go back to eating what they used to eat: seals, sea lions and other marine mammals.</p>
        <p>Along with colleagues from several other institutions and condor preservation organizations, Dr. Chamberlain analyzed the diets of three groups of the birds: those living at the end of the Pleistocene Epoch (11,000 to 36,000 years ago, preserved in the La Brea Tar Pits in Los Angeles), those from more recent history (1797 to 1965) and those from modern times (1993 to 2001).</p>
        <p>The analysis was an indirect one, measuring the ratios of certain isotopes of carbon and nitrogen in bones and feathers from condor specimens. Different foods produce different isotopic signatures in the tissues.</p>
        <p>The group reported in a paper in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences that at the end of the Pleistocene a significant number of condors lived on marine mammals. But by the 1800's, the diet had shifted to land mammals.</p>
        <p>The end of the Pleistocene was when many large mammals were wiped out in North America. ''The condors had nothing to feed on,'' Dr. Chamberlain said. ''They made it by feeding on the huge amount of seals and whales on the coast of California.''</p>
        <p>In the 1800's the Russian fur trade destroyed seal populations on the West Coast, so the condors found a new source of food -- cattle, brought in by the Spanish missions largely for leather and tallow.</p>
        <p>The study also confirmed that the birds' diet now consists largely of the calves provided by conservation groups. ''Half their diet is what we are feeding them,'' Dr. Chamberlain said. ''It's almost like a zoo without walls.''</p>
        <p>Since the study shows that condors can adapt, perhaps it is time for the birds to switch diets again, to the seals and sea lions whose populations are being restored along the California coast. ''The argument would be, 'They're on the beach; go get 'em,' '' Dr. Chamberlain said.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
