<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: Oct. 7 -- Oct. 13</title>
    <meta content="07thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1707711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDC1E30F934A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="14620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: Oct. 7 -- Oct. 13</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, showtimes and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'WAR IN PARAMUS' Previews begin tonight. Opens Tuesday. Spanning Woodstock to Watergate, this suburban comedy by Austin Pendleton finds a teenager angry with the members of her family, who are obsessing over her sister's wedding (1:20). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, June Havoc Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212)868-4444. 'EMILIA GALOTTI' Opens Wednesday. The Deutsches Theater Berlin production of Gotthold Ephraim Lessing's 1772 play about a woman whose virtue is compromised (1:15). Brooklyn Academy of Music's Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718)636-4100.</p>
        <p>'ABSURD PERSON SINGULAR' Opens Oct. 18. The latest production of this comedy by the unstoppably prolific Alan Ayckbourn is about three couples and takes place over three holiday seasons (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Oct. 16. The medieval epic poem becomes a 21st-century rock opera in this Irish Repertory Theater production, with a score by Lenny Pickett, the musical director of ''Saturday Night Live'' (1:15). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, (212)727-2737.</p>
        <p>'FIVE COURSE LOVE' Opens Oct. 16. On the menu are five dates in five restaurants, put to music in five different styles, including operetta and country-western (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212)307-4100.</p>
        <p>'IN MY LIFE'  Opens Oct. 20. Love blossoms between a musician with Tourette's syndrome and an insecure journalist in this Broadway musical, directed and written by Joseph Brooks (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' Opens Nov. 6. Straight from La Jolla Playhouse in California, this rags-to-riches musical tells the story of Frankie Valli and the Four Seasons, featuring hits including ''Big Girls Don't Cry'' and ''Rag Doll.'' Des McAnuff directs (2:30). Virginia Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Opens Oct. 27. A little Neil Simon revival you might have heard of, starring Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick as Oscar and Felix. Joe Mantello directs (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212)307-4100.</p>
        <p>'SEE WHAT I WANT TO SEE' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Oct. 30. Michael John LaChiusa's highly anticipated new musical stars Idina Menzel and Marc Kudisch and features three contemporary stories based on the work of the Japanese writer Ryonosuke Akutagawa (2:00). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SOLDIER'S PLAY' Opens Oct. 17. The first major New York revival of Charles Fuller's play about the trial of a black soldier during World War II. With Taye Diggs and James McDaniel (2:10). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212)246-4422.</p>
        <p>'SWEENEY TODD' Opens Nov. 3. Patti LuPone and Michael Cerveris star in this intimate revival of the Sondheim classic, featuring 10 actors who play their own instruments. It started at the Watermill Theater in England, before moving to West End and Broadway (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THIRD' Opens Oct. 24. A professor played by Dianne Wiest accuses a student of plagiarism in Wendy Wasserstein's latest. Daniel Sullivan directs (2:00). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHITTY CHITTY BANG BANG' The playthings are the thing in this lavish windup music box of a show: windmills, Rube Goldbergesque machines and the show's title character, a flying car. It's like spending two and a half hours in the Times Square branch of Toys ''R'' Us (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' On paper this musical tale of two mismatched scam artists has an awful lot in common with ''The Producers.'' But if you are going to court comparison with giants, you had better be prepared to stand tall. ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels,'' starring John Lithgow and Norbert Leo Butz, never straightens out of a slouch (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) Set in the Bronx in 1964, this play by John Patrick Shanley is structured as a clash of wills and generations between Sister Aloysius (Cherry Jones), the head of a parochial school, and Father Flynn (Brian F. O'Byrne), the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge. The play's elements bring to mind those tidy topical melodramas that were once so popular. But Mr. Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions (1:30). Walter Kerr, 219 West 48th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Still, it seems safe to say that such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence will find a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SWEET CHARITY' This revival of the 1966 musical never achieves more than a low-grade fever when what's wanted is that old steam heat. In the title role of the hopeful dance-hall hostess, the appealing but underequipped Christina Applegate is less a shopworn angel than a merry cherub (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around. (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212)239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>*'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 4, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'COLDER THAN HERE'  Judith Light plays a British wife and mother slowly succumbing to cancer but resisting low spirits to the last in Laura Wade's skillful but unexceptional play. Brian Murray, Sarah Paulson and Lily Rabe cope as best they can, admiring Mom's brave spirit as they heal the rifts that separate them (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)279-4200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CYCLING PAST THE MATTERHORN' A grating comedy-drama by Deborah Grimberg about the fractious relationship between a mother and daughter. Shirley Knight plays Esther, a needy, needling woman who discovers she's going blind just as her daughter leaves the nest. Carrie Preston is her needy, self-absorbed daughter (1:35). Harold Clurman Theater on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEDICATION, OR THE STUFF OF DREAMS' Portraying a terminally ill, rancidly rich misanthrope in Terrence McNally's play about a small-town children's theater troupe, Marian Seldes is a snappy advertisement for the time-defying benefits of a religious devotion to theater. She is, in fact, what ''Dedication'' is all about, or intends to be, anyway. Burdened with soap-operaish plot turns and artificially bright dialogue, this comedy of mortality never seems able to convince itself that life and art trump death and doubt. (2:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212)279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' This noisy novelty is a mixed blessing. Providing a two-foot drum on every seat, it offers an opportunity to exorcise aggressions by delivering a good beating, and on a slightly more elevated level, it presents a superficial introduction to African culture, lessons in drumming and 90 minutes of nonstop music, song and dancing by a good-natured cast (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200.(Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE GREAT AMERICAN TRAILER PARK MUSICAL' A terrific cast keeps the generator running in this bright but flimsy contraption. A few of David Nehls's dozen ditties raise a hearty chuckle, like the valedictory anthem in which the show's heroines collectively vow to ''make like a nail and press on.'' But Betsy Kelso's book all but dispenses with plot, and substitutes crude cartoons for characters (2:00). Dodger Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>*'THE INTELLIGENT DESIGN OF JENNY CHOW' In Rolin Jones's fanciful comedy, playfully directed by Jackson Gay, a lonely young woman in California embarks on an ambitious science project to help conquer her agoraphobia and trace her origins in China. Brisk, funny and engaging, the play disappoints only in its emphasis on flights of fancy over a nuanced depiction of its heroine's emotional dilemmas (2:10). Atlantic Theater Company, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE LADIES OF THE CORRIDOR' The Peccadillo Theater Company has revived this 1953 play by Dorothy Parker and Arnaud D'Usseau. A comedy set in an East Side hotel populated by widows and divorcees, it is an unyielding and coruscating portrait of women before feminism, relieved by Parker's dead-on wit. East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212)279-4200.(Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'LATE FRAGMENT'  Matthew, a World Trade Center employee who survived Sept. 11, and Marta are a desperate couple falling out of love in Francine Volpe's often perceptive if muddled drama named after a Raymond Carver poem. Under the direction of Michael Imperioli (Christopher from ''The Sopranos'') and Zetna Fuentes, the play has a wobbly style, building tension only to diffuse it with less-than-credible moments (1:30). Studio Dante, 257 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212)279-4200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'MEDEA' Sure, she gets most of the attention, but let's take a moment to acknowledge Jason, who, as embodied by Lawrence Winslow in the Classical Theater of Harlem's jolting production, contributes some terrific laughs to Euripides' grim tragedy. Yeah, that's right: laughs, the kind you get from the incongruity of the good ol' boys' network encountering Gloria Steinem (1:10). Classical Theater of Harlem, at the Harlem School of the Arts Theater, 645 St. Nicholas Avenue, near 141st Street, (212)868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MIRACLE BROTHERS' Kirsten Childs's show, about magical Brazilian river dolphins that assume human form to explore racial conflict in the 17th century, does indeed flow like a river -- a winding, muddy, very long river in a dry season (2:00). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)353-0303. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE MUSICAL OF MUSICALS!' The musical is the happy narcissist of theater; parody is the best form of narcissism. All it needs are smart writers and winning performers. That's what we get in this case (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 5, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Margo Jefferson)</p>
        <p>'NO FOREiGNERS BEYOND THIS POINT'  Two innocents abroad learn the limits of American idealism in Warren Leight's wistfully funny new play about the difficulty of doing good in a society rigged to accommodate only more cynical transactions. Based on Mr. Leight's own experience as a teacher of English in China before he established a career as a playwright (the Tony-winning ''Side Man''), the play is slight but appealing (2:00). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212)352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'ONCE AROUND THE SUN' The ''sun'' of the title could be the talent and energy of the show's impressive cast: you can warm your hands on them and on the catchy music. Unfortunately, the book fails to capitalize on these strengths, instead presenting a trite fable about a young rock singer seduced by celebrity, with cardboard characters, despite the actors' best efforts to give them dimension. Still, the performances are very entertaining (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212)239-6200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'ONE-MAN STAR WARS TRILOGY' With a storm trooper roaming the aisles and a woman in an Obi-Wan Kenobi get-up telling theatergoers to turn off their cellphones or they will be turned into ''cosmic dust,'' Charles Ross's sprint through Episodes IV through VI aims for the atmosphere of a ''Star Wars'' convention but ends up achieving something like a religious revival (which is sort of the same thing). True believers will love how Mr. Ross, a self-confessed geek who plays every major role in under an hour, simulates R2D2, but everyone else will scratch his head (1:00). Lamb's Theater, 130 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212)239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'ORSON'S SHADOW' Austin Pendleton's play, about a 1960 production of Ionesco's ''Rhinoceros,'' which was directed by Orson Welles and starred Laurence Olivier, is a sharp-witted but tenderhearted backstage comedy about the thin skins, inflamed nerves and rampaging egos that are the customary side effects when sensitivity meets success (2:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, Greenwich Village, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE PAVILION' Craig Wright's play about the speedy wheels of time's winged chariot and the dreams it grinds into dust is set at a small-town high school reunion. Brian D'Arcy James aches with longing as the cad who wants a second chance. Gracefully directed by Lucie Tiberghien (2:00). Rattlestick Theater, 224 Waverly Place, at 11th Street, West Village, (212)868-4444. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>*'SIDES: THE FEAR IS REAL' This hilarious collection of sketches may send up familiar targets -- the insecure thespian, the fraudulent acting teacher, the arrogant Juilliard grad -- but since it's performed with such specificity and comic charm by actors firing on all cylinders, you won't care a whit. Written by and starring an all-Asian-American cast, this slight but consistently entertaining satire is a primer on what not to do in an audition room (1:15). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212)307-4100. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SLUT'  This overamplified musical comedy about love and promiscuity among East Village friends leans heavily on obscenities to lend it a daring edge. Instead, it swamps even its brightest moments in tawdriness (2:00). American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>*'THOM PAIN (BASED ON NOTHING)' Is there such a thing as stand-up existentialism? If not, Will Eno has just invented it. Stand-up-style comic riffs and deadpan hipster banter keep interrupting the corrosively bleak narrative. Mr. Eno is a Samuel Beckett for the Jon Stewart generation (1:10). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WALKING DOWN BROADWAY' Dawn Powell's 1931 tale of young people looking for life and love in New York City is packed with smart dialogue and honest emotions. It is also well directed, well acted and smartly designed (2:30). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212)315-0231. (Jefferson)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BELLY OF A DRUNKEN PIANO' In this splendidly imperfect cabaret, Stewart D'Arrietta howls and growls convincingly through Tom Waits's three-decade song catalog, backed by a snappy trio. His patter and his piano playing are variable, but Mr. D'Arrietta makes a genial tour guide through Mr. Waits's wee-hours world (1:45). Huron Club at SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, between Avenue of the Americas and Varick Street, (212)691-1555. (Rob Kendt)</p>
        <p>*'POOR THEATER' Part homage and part anatomy, the Wooster Group's warm, witty tribute to the director Jerzy Grotowski and the choreographer William Forsythe demonstrates how imitation can be not just sincere flattery but also a hopeful attempt to crawl into someone else's skin to see how it fits. As identities and their representations morph and blur, this is not always a comfortable activity, but it is often an exhilarating one (1:30). Performing Garage, 33 Wooster Street, between Broome and Grand Streets, SoHo, (212)868-4444. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212)307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212)239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FIDDLER ON THE ROOF' The Shtetl Land pavilion in the theme park called Broadway. With Rosie O'Donnell and Harvey Fierstein. (2:55). The Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MOVIN' OUT' The miracle dance musical that makes Billy Joel cool (2:00). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'NAKED BOYS SINGING' That's who they are. That's what they do (1:05). Julia Miles Theater, 414 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin are stirring up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212)307-4100.(Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'DR. SEX' This harmless, fluffy musical about the life of Alfred Kinsey imagines that groundbreaking scientist and sex researcher as a good-time guy who likes to fool around at gay clubs and crack wise like a Catskills comic. As played by the very game Brian Noonan, Kinsey strips at a moment's notice, dances in front of a Busby Berkeley line of Kinsey Players and boils down his philosophy, quite deftly, actually, into ''When you're making whoop, you're part of a group'' (2:20). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200, closing Sunday.( Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'FRAN'S BED' Even the ever-radiant charms of Mia Farrow are not enough to dispel the pervasive gloom in this wan new play, written and directed by James Lapine, about an American family facing an unhappy ending. Ms. Farrow plays a comatose woman surveying, in her apparently still-active mind, an unhappy life. Intermittently fun, but mostly glum (1:45). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200, closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE SAUNDERS'S PASTORALIA' An often funny if ultimately disappointing stage adaptation of George Saunders's brilliantly entertaining and brazenly off-kilter novella about an impoverished, historically themed amusement park featuring everything from fake hermits to a simulated Jesus. The director Yehuda Duenyas faithfully adapts this chilling satire, but never figures out a theatrical way to articulate the inner life of its characters (1:25). P.S. 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212)352-3101, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE' An effort more commendable for its intention than its execution, this staging fails to capture either the tragedy or the comedy of the play, let alone the ironies of war (2:45). Jean Cocteau Repertory, at the Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212)279-4200, closing tomorrow. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'THE SAFETY NET' Christopher Kyle's thoughtful midlife-crisis drama touches on everything from the racial prejudices of the liberal elite to the nature-nurture debate in this finely tuned production about a man going through the motions. David, an immigration lawyer very close to making partner, has a very late coming of age after his brother dies in a car accident, leaving a pregnant fiancée (2:00). Michael Weller Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, sixth floor, Clinton, (212)397-2918, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'SPIRIT' Three men and one slippery slope of a stage. From these simple elements, the inspired London-based Improbable troupe maps a funny, melancholy and altogether entrancing journey into a land of dreams, warfare and actorly neurosis. A magical demonstration that theater can go places that no other art form can. (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212)239-6200, closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A WOMAN OF WILL' In this wrongheaded solo musical, Kate McNeill (Amanda McBroom) is a lyricist at a creative dead end, in a hotel room waiting for inspiration for a big second-act ballad. In the meantime, she imagines songs in the voices of the heroines of Shakespeare's plays, including a blues tune by Lady Macbeth, a disco number by Kate from ''The Taming of the Shrew'' and a pop anthem by Goneril from ''King Lear'' (''No more Mrs. Nice guy, she's such a dreadful bore./I'm into vivisection, not polishing the floor.'') (1:30). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)239-6200, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, showtimes and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>*'THE ARISTOCRATS' (No rating, 89 minutes) A rigorously scholarly documentary about the theory and practice of joke-telling that also happens to be one of the filthiest, vilest, most extravagantly obscene movies ever made -- and one of the funniest. (A.O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE BAXTER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) A ''Baxter,'' in the lingo of this romantic comedy written by, directed by and starring the comedian Michael Showalter, is the safe choice, the also-ran, the guy who is left at the altar when the hero shows up, as Dustin Hoffman did in ''The Graduate,'' to claim his true love. The film's tragic flaw is that Mr. Showalter is miscast -- or has miscast himself -- in the title role. In the end, ''The Baxter'' is a Baxter of a movie: well meaning and mildly likable, but unlikely to sweep you off your feet. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>'BEFORE THE FALL' (No rating, 110 minutes, in German) In Hitler's Germany, the National-Political Institutes of Learning, known as ''Napolas,'' were part of a network of elite schools used to train and indoctrinate future leaders with a sadistic combination of boot camp and brainwashing. Dennis Gansel's intensely beautiful film brings us inside a Napola to observe the fate of a young amateur boxer and his sensitive roommate. Though somewhat overdetermined, the film is a chilling testament to the seductiveness of groupthink and the allure of imagined superiority. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'BROKEN FLOWERS' (R, 105 minutes) Sweet, funny, sad and meandering, Jim Jarmusch's new film sends Bill Murray's aging Don Juan out in search of a son he never knew he had. He finds four former lovers, including Sharon Stone and Jessica Lange, and reveals once again that he is the quietest and finest comic actor working in movies today. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CHAIN' (No rating, 99 minutes) Jem Cohen's sad, lyrical evocation of the homogeneity of the global landscape views it through the eyes of two young women: a Japanese corporate functionary researching theme parks in the United States and a glum temp worker eking out a living in shopping malls and motels. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'CAPOTE' (R, 114 minutes) Philip Seymour Hoffman's portrayal of Truman Capote is a tour de force of psychological insight. Following the novelist as he works on the magazine assignment that will become ''In Cold Blood,'' the film raises intriguing questions about the ethics of writing. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'THE CONSTANT GARDENER' (R, 129 minutes) A superior thriller with a conscience, from John le Carré's novel. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'EL CRIMEN PERFECTO' (No rating, 105 minutes, in Spanish) In this antic and outrageous black comedy, Rafael González (Guillermo Toledo) is a salesman in the women's section of a Madrid department store. Rafael's fondest dream is to be floor manager; when his archrival for the position, Don Antonio (Luis Varela), is accidentally killed in a scuffle in the dressing room, Rafael's world begins to unravel. Like the Ferris wheel that serves as the setting for one of its climactic scenes, ''El Crimen Perfecto'' is a bright, gaudy and tremendously satisfying ride. (Stevens)</p>
        <p>'EVERYTHING IS ILLUMINATED' (PG-13, 104 minutes) From Jonathan Safran Foer's novel, a sentimental Holocaust tale; tender and funny in places, but also thin and soft. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE EXORCISM OF EMILY ROSE' (PG-13, 114 minutes) If you must see only one demonic-possession courtroom drama this year, wait for the next one. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FLIGHTPLAN' (PG-13, 93 minutes) To watch Jodie Foster storm through a phony airplane as a mother in search of her missing child has its very minor pleasures, but there is nothing in this thrill-free thriller to feed the head or fray the nerves. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'FORTY SHADES OF BLUE' (No rating, 108 minutes) Ira Sachs's Sundance prizewinner is the sad, lovely story of a Memphis record producer (Rip Torn), his much younger Russian girlfriend (Dina Korzun) and his grown-up son (Darren Burrows), who stumble into a love triangle. Great music and fine acting, with Mr. Torn, at 74, giving the performance of a lifetime. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'THE 40-YEAR-OLD VIRGIN' (R, 111 minutes) A sex comedy turned romantic bliss-out, with Steve Carell, in which the sound of one prophylactic snapping is just a single sweet note in the glorious symphony of love. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'FOUR BROTHERS' (R, 148 minutes)two hours, 28 minutes) In John Singleton's slick hybrid of urban western and modern blaxploitation movie, four young men, two black and two white, reunite in Detroit to avenge the shooting death of their saintly adoptive mother. Preposterous, amoral and exciting. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*'GOOD NIGHT, AND GOOD LUCK' (PG, 90 minutes) George Clooney, with impressive rigor and intelligence, examines the confrontation between the CBS newsman Edward R. Murrow (a superb David Strathairn) and Senator Joseph R. McCarthy (himself). Plunging you into a smoky, black-and-white world of political paranoia and commercial pressure, the film is both a history lesson and a passionate essay on power, responsibility and the ethics of journalism (Scott)</p>
        <p>'GOING SHOPPING' (PG-13, 106 minutes) As loquacious and scatterbrained as its female characters, this Henry Jaglom film explores women's shopping habits and fantasies. Its incomplete sketches revolve around an upscale dress shop on the verge of bankruptcy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GREATEST GAME EVER PLAYED' (PG, 115 minutes) A rousing, obvious re-creation of the 1913 United States Open, in which two sons of the working classes faced off in a game still dominated, on both sides of the Atlantic, by the well-born. Aims for par and makes it. ( Scott)</p>
        <p>*'GRIZZLY MAN' (R, 103 minutes) Werner Herzog's bold, enthralling documentary about one man's journey into the heart of darkness (and the belly of the beast) traces the life and strange times of the self-anointed grizzly expert Timothy Treadwell. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A HISTORY OF VIOLENCE' (R, 97 minutes) A masterpiece of indirection and pure visceral thrills about a seemingly average American family almost undone by cataclysmic violence, David Cronenberg's latest mindblower is the feel-good, feel-bad movie of the year. With Viggo Mortensen, Maria Bello, Ed Harris and William Hurt, all excellent. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'JUST LIKE HEAVEN' (PG-13, 95 minutes) Reese Witherspoon's disembodied spirit haunts Mark Ruffalo in a real estate dispute that runs into a sweet romantic comedy. Surprisingly lighthearted and brisk, considering its fairly morbid premise.(Scott)</p>
        <p>'LORD OF WAR' (R, 122 minutes) A misfire of a political satire about the international gun market from Andrew Niccol, a filmmaker whose words say no, but whose overworked visual style says lock and load, baby. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'MAGNIFICENT DESOLATION: WALKING ON THE MOON 3D' (No rating, 40 minutes) Tom Hanks narrates this Imax film that tries to give moviegoers the virtual experience of being on the lunar surface. At times it comes close. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>*'MARCH OF THE PENGUINS' (G, 80 minutes) This sentimental but riveting documentary follows the one-year mating cycle of emperor penguins in Antarctica when they leave the ocean and march inland to breed and lay eggs. Narrated by Morgan Freeman, the film has no qualms about playing on our emotions. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MIRRORMASK' (PG, 101 minutes) This British film, directed by Dave McKean from a screenplay by Neil Gaiman, blends live action with computer-generated animation by the Jim Henson Company into a provocative, murky surrealism. The story follows the Freudian nightmare of a 15-year-old girl whose parents work in the circus; it's strictly for cultists. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*'OCCUPATION: DREAMLAND' (No rating, 79 minutes) In early 2004, eight members of the Army's 82nd Airborne Division allowed the directors Ian Olds and Garrett Scott to shadow them for six weeks in a rapidly destabilizing Fallujah. The resulting film is a respectful and determinedly nonpartisan portrait of regular guys -- the smart and the average, the blusterers and the introverts, the gung-ho and the conflicted -- all doing their best to carry out orders in an untenable situation. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'OLIVER TWIST' (PG-13, 130 minutes) Roman Polanski's take on Dickens's classic emphasizes the darkness and cruelty of Victorian society. Vigorous and precise, it is a vivid reminder of the novelist's power as both a storyteller and a social critic. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PRIZE WINNER OF DEFIANCE, OHIO' (PG-13, 99 minutes) Julianne Moore is radiant as Evelyn Ryan, the real-life 1950's Ohio housewife and mother of 10 who kept her family afloat on her winnings from television jingle contests. Jane Anderson wrote and directed this tribute in a wonderfully zany, off-center style. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PROOF' (PG-13, 100 minutes) A terribly serious adaptation of David Auburn's prize-laden Broadway play, starring Gwyneth Paltrow as the daughter of a dead mathematician struggling to come to terms with both her father's legacy and her own troubled mind. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE RODNEES: WE MOD LIKE DAT!' (No rating, 73 minutes) Striving to be a mockumentary, ''The Rodnees: We Mod Like Dat!'' is a train wreck of a movie: messy, unfunny and unforgivably dull. The plot, such as it is, involves four young African American men from Brooklyn whose failure to succeed in hip-hop prompts them to reinvent themselves as a modern-day version of The Beatles. The film's rare sparks of surreal wit never come close to relieving its general listlessness and lack of organization. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'ROLL BOUNCE' (PG-13, 107 minutes) A drowsy comedy from Malcolm D. Lee about a handful of kids grooving and roller skating in the summer of 1978, ''Roll Bounce'' has heart and good vibes but little else to recommend it. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'SANTO DOMINGO BLUES' (No rating, 75 minutes, in Spanish) The story of the musical style known as bachata -- a guitar-based blues born in the brothels and dance halls of the Dominican Republic -- and of its most prominent singer and songwriter, Luis Vargas. The film shows the evolution of bachata, long reviled as the music of the poor, to the mainstream with the mass immigration of Dominicans to the United States in the 1980's. A lively, sexy, insightful documentary.(Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SEPARATE LIES' (R, 87 minutes) A hit-and-run accident near the country house of an imperious British lawyer (magnificently played by Tom Wilkinson) leads him into an ethical labyrinth that tests his moral mettle as well as that of his wife (Emily Watson) and her lover (Rupert Everett). (Holden)</p>
        <p>'SERENITY' (PG-13, 119 minutes) It probably isn't fair to Joss Whedon's ''Serenity'' to say that this unassuming science-fiction adventure is superior in almost every respect to George Lucas's aggressively more ambitious ''Star Wars: Episode III -- Revenge of the Sith.'' But who cares about fair when there is fun to be had? Scene for scene, ''Serenity'' is more engaging and certainly better written and acted than any of Mr. Lucas's recent screen entertainments. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SQUID AND THE WHALE' (R, 88 minutes) Mining his own childhood, Noah Baumbach has put together an unsparing, funny portrait of a family in crisis and a young man trying to figure out his parents and himself. Superbly written and acted, especially by Laura Linney and Jeff Daniels as a pair of divorcing writers. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THUMBSUCKER' (R, 96 minutes) A better-than-usual coming-of-age story, via Sundance but without the usual sensationalism or condescension, and with some very fine performances, notably by Lou Pucci as a teenage boy with a childish habit. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'TIM BURTON'S CORPSE BRIDE' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A necrophiliac animation for the whole family about a melancholic boy, the girl he hopes to marry and the bodacious cadaver that accidentally comes between them. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'TOUCH THE SOUND' (No rating, 99 minutes) As Thomas Riedelsheimer's enlightening, mystical documentary follows the deaf Scottish percussionist Evelyn Glennie around the globe, it illustrates her understanding that sound is a physical sensation experienced throughout the body, as well as an auditory one. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'TRANSPORTER 2' (PG-13, 88 minutes) Ex-Special Forces operative Frank Martin (Jason Statham), the blank-faced professional driver with more tricks -- and lives -- than James Bond, is back in this shallow, but never dull, sequel to ''The Transporter.'' This time, he's in Miami and will do whatever it takes to save the life of a boy who's been kidnapped and injected with a deadly virus. (Laura Kern)</p>
        <p>* '2046' (R, 129 minutes) An ecstatically beautiful story in which time is marked not by the hands of a clock, but by the women who pass through one man's life, ''2046'' is the eighth feature film from the Hong Kong director Wong Kar-wai and the long-awaited follow-up to his art-house favorite ''In the Mood for Love.'' A film about longing, loss and the delicate curve of a woman's back, it is also an unqualified triumph. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'AN UNFINISHED LIFE' (PG-13, 108 minutes) This contemporary Western starring Robert Redford, Jennifer Lopez and Morgan Freeman is a solemn, sentimental bore that suffocates in its own predictability and watered-down psychobabble. All three stars recycle stereotypes they've played before. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WALLACE AND GROMIT: THE CURSE OF THE WERE-RABBIT' (G, 85 minutes) The stop-motion pooch and his cheese-loving master, back again at feature length. Silly and sublime. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WEDDING CRASHERS' (R, 113 minutes) A wink-wink, nudge-nudge Trojan horse of a story, this amiably raunchy sex comedy pivots on two Lotharios persuasively inhabited by Owen Wilson and Vince Vaughn. They love the ladies but really and truly, cross their cheating hearts, just want a nice girl to call wife. Credited to the screenwriters Steve Faber and Bob Fisher. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>FILM SERIES</p>
        <p>AFTER WAR (Through Oct. 23) The Japan Society is commemorating the 60th anniversary of the end of World War II with this series of works about wartime and its aftermath. This Sunday's feature is ''Out of This World'' (''Kono yo no sotoe -- Club shinchugun''), Junji Sakamoto's 2003 film about five young postwar jazz musicians grudgingly playing at American military clubs. 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212)832-1155; $10.(Gates)</p>
        <p>THE BEAUTY OF THE EVERYDAY: JAPAN'S SHOCHIKU COMPANY AT 110 (Through Oct. 20) The Film Society of Lincoln Center presents a 44-film retrospective honoring Shochiku, the Japanese film studio. Films to be shown this weekend include ''Late Spring'' (1949), Yasujiro Ozu's tale of a father who wants his daughter to marry; ''Scandal'' (1950), Akira Kurosawa's drama about a singer falsely accused of an affair; and Kiju Yoshida's new wave classic ''Love Affair at Akitsu Spa'' (1962), about a terminally ill student and an innkeeper's daughter. Walter Reade Theater, 160 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212)875-5601; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>CALL FOR CHANGE: THIRD WORLD NEWSREEL (Through Sunday) BAMcinématek presents a weekend of documentaries about social issues. Films include ''The Healing Passage'' (2004), about the African diaspora; ''The People Are Rising'' (''El Pueblo se Levanta'') (1971), about Puerto Rican activism in East Harlem; and several programs of shorts. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718)636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FOREVER GARBO: A RETROSPECTIVE (Through Dec. 17) The American-Scandinavian Foundation's program honoring Greta Garbo's centennial continues tomorrow with ''Flesh and the Devil'' (1927), about a ruthless temptress and the man whose life she seems destined to ruin (John Gilbert), and on Wednesday with ''Love'' (1927), a silent version of ''Anna Karenina,'' with Gilbert as Vronsky. Scandinavia House, 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212)879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANÇOIS TRUFFAUT (Through Nov. 27). The IFC Center's Weekend Classics program is presenting a dozen Truffaut features and two shorts. This weekend's film, to be screened at noon, today through Monday, is ''Stolen Kisses'' (1968), about a soldier's post-discharge adventures. To be shown with the short ''Antoine and Colette'' (1962). At 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212)924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NO VISA REQUIRED: FILMS FROM THE MIDDLE EAST (Through Nov. 19) The TriBeCa Film Institute and ArteEast are collaborating on a five-program screening of six films, followed by discussions with the filmmakers. The event continues tomorrow with ''The Prince'' (Tunisia, 2004), Mohammad Zran's love story about a flower vendor and a beautiful bank manager. Cantor Film Center, New York University, 36 East Eighth Street, East Village, (212)941-3890; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>REPERTORY NIGHTS (Through Nov. 6) The Museum of the Moving Image continues its annual film series today, tomorrow and Sunday with Akira Kurosawa's 1954 classic ''The Seven Samurai,'' starring Toshiro Mifune. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718)784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SOME LIKE IT WILDER: THE COMPLETE BILLY WILDER (Through Nov. 13) The Museum of the Moving Image is sponsoring a 26-film retrospective of Wilder, the Austrian-born director and writer who gave the world ''Sunset Boulevard'' and ''Double Indemnity.'' This weekend's features are ''Love in the Afternoon'' (1957), starring Audrey Hepburn and Gary Cooper as May-December lovers; ''Sabrina'' (1954), in which Hepburn is courted by both William Holden and Humphrey Bogart; and ''Avanti!'' (1972), with Jack Lemmon as a staid businessman who finds love in Italy. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718)784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BECK (Tonight) Back to retro-ironic rock form after a while spent making sincere antifolk music, the self-aware soulman Beck Hanson aims to reclaim his mid-1990's role as pop's forward- and backward-looking prince of pastiche. At 6, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 279-7740 ; $42. (Laura Sinagra)</p>
        <p>DEAD CAN DANCE (Tomorrow) Mixing elements of Western medieval music, world beat and synth-rock's magisterial sweep, this theatrical band, fronted by the singer Lisa Gerrard, obliges its fans with its first tour in 10 years. 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212)247-4777; $34.50 to $59.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FALL OUT BOY, MOTION CITY SOUNDTRACK (Tuesday) What saves the slick emo pop-metal band Fall Out Boy from sounding like all the rest is a large dose of self-deprecation in its sing-along choruses. The pop-punk Motion City Soundtrack is influenced by the keyboard punctuations of early Weezer. 6 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212)777-6800 ; $25. (sold out) (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FOUR TET (Monday) Making laptop music under the name Four Tet, the Londoner Kieran Hebden conjures atmospheric jazztronica that can sound like a noisy pastiche of classic rock bits or take on a more hip-hop informed art-rock groove. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>GHOSTFACE (Sunday) The Wu-Tang Clan's jittery, wildly inventive Ghostface Killah raps with both short-fused intensity and narrative nuance; his hyperventilated flow is full of digressions that reward close listening. Recently he's been matching his paranoid clown rapping to the nostalgic soul beats of Pete Rock. The Canadian rappers Swollen Members open. 8 p.m., B.B. King's Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212)997-4144; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>PHILIP GLASS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Performing ''Orion,'' commissioned for the 2004 summer Olympics, Philip Glass plays keyboards at the center of a changing array of composition collaborators and guest musicians, including Mark Atkins on didgeridoo, Wu Man on stringed pipa and Foday Musa Suso on kora. 7:30, BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718)636-4100; $20 to $60. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JETHRO TULL (Tomorrow) Ian Anderson is still standing on one leg and growling through his flute as he leads Jethro Tull through his eccentric merger of hard rock, Celtic tunes, jazz and Bach. 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $40 to $80. . (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DANIEL LANOIS AND TORTOISE (Tonight)For this tour, the producer and roots-pop musician Daniel Lanois, whose recent music is contemplative, with pedal steel guitar, will be backed by the Chicago post-rock band Tortoise. The group, which has recently been working with the indie-folk chameleon Will Oldham, will also play its own set. Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212)777-6800; $22.50 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LYRICS BORN, THE PERCEPTIONISTS (Tomorrow) Lyrics Born is a Bay Area rapper who continues to fight the good fight with backpack-rap beats and smart wordplay. The Perceptionists do the same, with the politically outspoken Mr. Lif rapping against fascism with lithe candor. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $16 in advance, $18. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>MARIZA (Tonight) Mariza, who was born in Mozambique but grew up in Portugal, is one of the rising stars of fado, the Portuguese cafe music that sets haunted songs about fate and destiny to the pristine picking of the Portuguese guitar. She wrings emotion from the songs, with or without amplification. 8, Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $20 to $69. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>MESHUGGAH, GOD FORBID, THE HAUNTED (Tonight) The Swedish band Meshuggah barrels through songs characterized by intricate rhythms and apocalyptic rumble, over which the members spew angry, guttural, prelingual vocals. The like-minded God Forbid and the Haunted open. 6 p.m., B.B. King's Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, (212)997-4144; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>MY CHEMICAL ROMANCE (Thursday) The popular My Chemical Romance plays goth pop with metallic guitars and histrionic riffs that aim to engage every football player's inner theater-geek. Alkaline Trio's drummer and bandleader, Mike Skiba, continues to add 80's brood-pop wrinkles to his straightforward pop punk. 7 p.m., Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201)935-3900; $17.99 to $23. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>NADA SURF, SHIVAREE (Tonight) These Brooklyn alt-rockers tumbled into obscurity after a mid-90's hit, then re-emerged in 2002 with a sweet new style: wistful indie rock that squints nostalgically at imagined childhood bliss through a snowy pane. Shivaree plays loungey pop with archness. 8, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $18 in advance, $20 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>OLIVIA NEWTON-JOHN (Tuesday) This clear-voiced Australian songbird's got lots of hits from her dreamy faux-country phase in the early 70's (''Have You Never Been Mellow''), her faux-ingénue turn in ''Grease'' and her aerobic ''Physical'' era, but Ms. Newton-John's battles with cancer and other struggles ushered in a 90's round of un-faux new-age questing. Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street; ticketmaster.com or (212)307-7171; $44.50 to 59.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE NEW PORNOGRAPHERS, DESTROYER (Wednesday and Thursday) This revved-up Vancouver outfit's tight power-pop grandeur builds with a sort of time-release tension, until the voice of Neko Case cuts through like a triumphant skywriter. Ms. Case has not appeared at the band's recent shows in town, but she'll be here this time. New Pornographer co-songwriter Dan Bejar's band, the relentlessly quirky Destroyer, opens the show. 7:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212)353-1600; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>NICKEL CREEK (Tonight) This emo-bluegrass trio, which once covered a Pavement song, is at its best when the thin-voiced Chris Thile hands over the microphone to the fiddler and ethereal singer Sara Watkins. That is, it's better to sound like a wispier Allison Krauss than a simplistic Sufjan Stevens. 8, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street; ticketmaster.com or (212)307-7171, $24. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE RAVEONETTES, RADIO 4 (Tonight) Clearing away the garage noise of its debut, the Danish duo the Raveonettes now strives for pure 60's pop classicism. Its latest material incorporates rock history, from girl groups to surf rock to punk, as well as historic rock in the form of cameos by Ronnie Spector, the Suicide keyboardist Martin Rev and the Velvet Underground drummer Maureen Tucker. The local neo post-punkers Radio 4 open. 8, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718)387-0505; $16. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>IKE REILLY ASSASSINATION (Tomorrow) This St. Paul, Minn., rocker's visceral, outlandishly catchy tunes capture a certain kind of cockiness and bar clown wit that almost make the listener overlook its macho nudges and winks. Mr. Reilly and his band tear it up live. Shadow Box and Catfish Haven will open. 9:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212)260-4700; $10. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JONATHAN RICHMAN, VIC CHESNUTT (Wednesday) Recent albums haven't added much to the whimsically neurotic rock 'n' roll live wire Jonathan Richman's stream-of-consciousness classics, but live, he remains a goofy joy. Recent material by the Southern Gothic storyteller Vic Chesnutt leans to his darker side. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $15. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SIX ORGANS OF ADMITTANCE (Tonight) The guitarist Ben Chasny plays exploratory noise-rock that draws on rootsy weirdness and a kind of chime and drone that suggest a global search for transcendence. 11:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212)260-4700; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SONS AND DAUGHTERS (Tomorrow) These gloomy Scots play folk-rock with edgy pessimism that reminds us, as if we could forget, that life in the gray North isn't all delicate, Belle and Sebastian-style reverie. 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718)599-5103; $12. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>BRUCE SPRINGSTEEN (Sunday) The Boss made ''The Rising'' after the twin towers fell, beating the novelist Jonathan Safran Foer to the notion of reverse-collapse by four years. Mr. Springsteen's spare ''Devils and Dust'' (Sony) charts the way back down, meditating with other soul-searchers at the crossroads of humanism and religion. 7:30 p.m., Nassau Coliseum, Uniondale, N.Y., (631)888-9000; $56.50 to $86.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>STEW (Monday) This Los Angeles pop craftsman writes songs that slip just enough bitters into the 70's lite rock cocktail to make it subversive. His faux-big production on disc isn't required live, because his songs are cabaret to the core. And aside from chuckling at his own asides, he is a consummate performer. This show is evidently of a piece with performances on the following two Tuesdays. 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8770; $20 per show, $50 for all three shows only at Joe's Pub's box office. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SUFJAN STEVENS (Tonight) This indie folk singer-songwriter and banjoist is imbued with a Copland-esque musical vision and an expansive narcissism reminiscent of Walt Whitman's, though his lyrics can overreach and his compositions veer into the folksily baroque. 8:30 and 10:30, Peter Norton Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212)864-5400; $21. (sold out) (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TURBONEGRO (Tuesday) Making its mark in the late 90's by posing as a flamboyantly gay metal band, the hard-rocking Norwegians of Turbonegro have worn out their shtick. They still bring the riffs, but a recent song, ''All My Friends Are Dead,'' might sum up their ideas as they drift into self-parody. 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212)353-1600; $20 in advance, $23 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>U2, KEANE (Tonight, and tomorrow, Monday and Tuesday nights) After 2000's thrilling ''All That You Can't Leave Behind'' (Interscope), ''How to Dismantle an Atomic Bomb'' (Interscope) and the ''Vertigo'' tour itself focus on what humans can live without: namely, intercontinental ballistic missiles and, evidently, some of U2's more shopworn live staples. Hence the resurrection of decades-old rarities like ''Electric Co.'' Keane is a piano-drums-vocals band that piles on hooky melodic flourishes. 8, Madison Square Garden, (212)465-6741; $54 to $169.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>WACO BROTHERS BLOODSHOT REVUE (Wednesday) Jon Langford of the Mekons indulges his country side even more strongly in the Waco Brothers, where he trades off lead vocals with Dean Schlabowske and ricochets between revolution and beer-soaked self-pity while letting his electric guitar blare. The Mekons' Sally Timms joins the bill. 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201)653-1703; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>WARLOCKS (Thursday) With a deep affection for 60's downtown drug rock, especially the Velvet Underground, this band creates a heavy vibe while also making forays into free-form psychedelia. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $15. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>MAUDE MAGGART (Tonight and tomorrow night) The singer, accompanied by piano and violin, applies her singular voice, a hybrid of light opera and 1930's torch, to the early songs of Irving Berlin. 9 and 11:30, Oak Room, Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212)419-9331; $50, with a $20 minimum; $50 prix fixe dinner required at the early shows. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>JOHN AND BUCKY PIZZARELLI (Tonight and tomorrow night) The musical conversation between a father and son, both superb guitarists, makes for a warm-hearted generational dialogue. 8:30 and 11, Feinstein's at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212)339-4095; $60, with a $40 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Tomorrow) Cool, funny, swinging and indestructible, this 75-year-old singer and sometime actress exemplifies old-time hip in its most generous incarnation. 7 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212)265-8133; $25, with a $12 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'SINGING ASTAIRE' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The smart, airy revue that pays tribute to Fred Astaire, featuring Eric Comstock, Hilary Cole and Christopher Gines, has returned to Birdland. 5:30 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212)581-3080; $30, with a $10 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*ELAINE STRITCH (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) In a courageous and successful leap into the unknown, Ms. Stritch makes her cabaret debut at 80. Dispensing with her theatrical signature numbers, she weaves 16 songs new to her repertory into a funny running monologue of her adventures in and out of show business. 8:45, Cafe Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212)744-1600; $125 tonight and tomorrow, $105 Tuesday through Thursday, through Oct. 29 (all shows sold out). (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>*AACM 40TH-ANNIVERSARY CONCERT (Tonight) The Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, an influential avant-garde collective, continues its yearlong anniversary celebration with a concert featuring a founding member, Roscoe Mitchell, on saxophones, and a next-generation inheritor, Reggie Nicholson, on percussion; each musician will perform in a solo setting, and as the leader of a trio. 8, the Community Church of New York, 40 East 35th Street, Manhattan, (212)683-4988, aacm-newyork.org; $20. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ALL NITE SOUL (Sunday) The jazz Mass at St. Peter's is a New York tradition, and this year's installment pulls no punches; the lineup includes musicians like the trumpeters Ray Vega and Marcus Printup, and culminates in the Clark Terry Big Band, which kicked off the event some 35 years ago. 5 p.m., St. Peter's Lutheran Church, 619 Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, Manhattan, (212)935-2200; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*MULATU ASTATKE AND THE EITHER/ORCHESTRA (Thursday) Mr. Astatke is best recognized these days for his music's prominent place in the Jim Jarmusch film ''Broken Flowers''; here, he'll perform his dreamy brand of Ethiopian jazz backed by the Either/Orchestra, which has done more than any other stateside ensemble to broaden this music's base. 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8778; cover, $25, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BEY (Tomorrow) Intimacy is a hallmark of Mr. Bey's vocal style, which alternates between a burnished falsetto and an earthy baritone; here he inhabits the most intimate setting imaginable, backed only by the guitarist Peter Meyers. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $15; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL CHARLAP TRIO (Through Oct. 16) Bright and breezy yet unfailingly precise, Mr. Charlap, the pianist, has come to exemplify jazz's modern mainstream. So has his working trio, which keeps a Tin Pan Alley repertory percolating in the present tense. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212)255-4037; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>A DON CHERRY CELEBRATION (Through Oct. 23) This three-week festival, which commemorates the free-jazz trumpeter Don Cherry, assembles a roll call of improvisers who claim his influence. Highlights in the coming week include ensembles led by the tuba player Bob Stewart and the tenor saxophonist Dewey Redman (tonight), and the multi-instrumentalist Peter Apfelbaum (tomorrow night). 8 and 10, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELDAR (Tuesday through next Friday) Eldar Djangirov, a teenage piano prodigy from Kyrgyzstan, has elicited comparisons to the great Art Tatum; he will surely headline his second New York club residency with panache. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212)475-8592; cover, $25 at tables, with a $5 minimum, or $15 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELLERY ESKELIN TRIO (Monday) Mr. Eskelin is a tenor saxophonist known for gruff abandon; his longtime band with the accordionist Andrea Parkins and the drummer Jim Black handles abstraction as well as groove. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FIELDWORK (Tuesday and Wednesday) This collaborative trio throws down a gauntlet of jagged melodies and asymmetrical rhythmic forms; the heart of the group's sound is an ever-shifting rapport between the pianist Vijay Iyer, the saxophonist Steve Lehman and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GOLD SOUNDS (Tonight) Pavement, the quintessential low-fi indie-rock band, gets an unlikely jazz makeover from the saxophonist James Carter, the pianist and organist Cyrus Chestnut, the bassist Reginald Veal and the drummer Ali Jackson; the band comes celebrating a jaunty album on the Brown Brothers label. 9:30, Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8778; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLIE HADEN'S LIBERATION MUSIC ORCHESTRA (Through Sunday) Mr. Haden, the bassist, formed this large ensemble with the pianist and composer Carla Bley some 35 years ago; its current incarnation, as documented on the slyly subversive album ''Not in Our Name'' (Verve), is stocked with serious younger musicians like the alto saxophonist Miguel Zenon. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212)475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, with a $5 minimum, or $20 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOEL HARRISON'S STARFISH PARADE (Tuesday) Mr. Harrison is a guitarist whose singing and songwriting lean on American roots traditions; here he previews material from an album called ''Harrison on Harrison'' (High Note), with an ensemble consisting of violin, pocket trumpet, accordion, bass and drums. 9 to 10:30 p.m., Koze Lounge, 676 Fifth Avenue, at 20th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)832-8282; cover, $7. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*BILLY HART QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Hart, a loose but focused drummer with a highly accomplished résumé, fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212)576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HAYES/HICKS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The drummer Louis Hayes and the pianist John Hicks share a deep firsthand knowledge of post-bop tradition; the other half of their band consists of Abraham Burton, saxophonist, and Gerald Cannon, bassist. 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212)255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*ROY HAYNES FOUNTAIN OF YOUTH BAND (Wednesday through Oct. 16) The redoubtable drummer Roy Haynes turned 80 this year, although you'd never guess it by his playing; his edgy post-bop ensemble features musicians many years his junior, like the alto saxophonist Jaleel Shaw. 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212)582-2121; cover, $30 and $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HEBERT'S BYZANTINE MONKEY QUARTET (Tonight) This progressive ensemble features the original music and bass playing of Mr. Hebert, along with the contributions of Michael Attias, saxophonist, and Russ Lossing, pianist. 9, Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212)989-9319; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG AND CHRIS POTTER (Tuesday) A promising duet performance by two of the sharpest musicians in the modern mainstream: Mr. Potter, a saxophonist, and Mr. Hoenig, a drummer. 7 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MILT JACKSON TRIBUTE BAND (Tonight and tomorrow night) Milt Jackson, who died in 1999, was one of the top two or three vibraphonists in the history of jazz; here, as on the new album ''Rev-elation'' (Sharp Nine), he is feted by the mallet virtuoso Joe Locke, along with the pianist Mike LeDonne, the bassist Bob Cranshaw and the drummer Mickey Roker. 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212)885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP QUINTET (Wednesday) This sleek ensemble uses compositional forms as a springboard for open exploration; Mr. Lightcap, a bassist, has powerfully creative cohorts in the tenor saxophonists Mark Turner and Tony Malaby, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. 7:30 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY'S PALOMA RECIO (Wednesday ) Mr. Malaby, a versatile and increasingly prominent tenor saxophonist, leads a progressive ensemble with a Spanish tinge; his fellow travelers are Michael Rodriguez, trumpeter; Ben Monder, guitarist; Eivind Opsvik, bassist; and Rodney Green, drummer. 10 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN TRINITY (Tuesday through Oct. 16) This piano trio deserves the high-minded handle; its members are the soulful pianist Cyrus Chestnut, the erudite bassist George Mraz and the clean, crisp drummer Lewis Nash. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 p.m. set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, Jazz at Lincoln Center, (212)258-9595. Cover: $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DELFEAYO MARSALIS QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Marsalis, a resoundingly skillful trombonist and composer, leads a polished post-bop ensemble with Donald Harrison on saxophone, Mulgrew Miller on piano, Delbert Felix on bass and Ralph Peterson on drums. (Cyrus Chestnut replaces Mr. Miller tomorrow night only.) 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, Jazz at Lincoln Center, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY MARTIN AND DAVE BURRELL (Tonight) The drummer best known as the second surname in Medeski Martin and Wood joins forces with the venerable avant-garde pianist Dave Burrell for an unscripted and potentially intriguing dialogue. 8, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212)358-7501; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN MCNEIL'S INSOMNIA BAND (Tomorrow) Mr. McNeil, a trumpeter and confirmed insomniac, recently released a haunting album called ''Sleep Won't Come'' (OmniTone); he expands on that theme with this quintet. 9 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212)989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>T.S. MONK (Wednesday through Oct. 15) Thelonious Monk Jr. is a charismatic drummer and bandleader whose taste is a bit less idiosyncratic than his father's; he leads a polished hard-bop band. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212)581-3080; music charge, $40, with a $10 minimum at the tables, no minimum at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORGANISSIMO (Sunday) This Michigan-based organ trio resurrects the sound of 1960's soul jazz but with a touch less grit and grease; the members appear here in support of a likeable new album, ''This is the Place'' (Big O). 10:45 p.m., Kenny's Castaways, 157 Bleecker Street, West Village, (212)979-9762; call for cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO GROUP (Tonight) Ms. Parlato is a cosmopolitan vocalist who keeps unfailingly good company. The guitarist Lionel Loueke, the pianist Aaron Parks and the drummer Kendrick Scott make up her working band and share her ties to the trumpeter and composer Terence Blanchard. 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATT PAVOLKA QUARTET (Thursday) Mr. Pavolka, a bassist, leads a group of free-thinking but lyrical players: Pete Rende on keyboards, Ted Poor on drums, and Ben Monder on guitar. In the following set, Mr. Monder will lead a group of his own. 8 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARIO PAVONE SEPTET (Tonight) Mr. Pavone, a bassist with an expansive worldview, leads a group that includes Joe Magnarelli, trumpeter; Mike DiRubbo, alto saxophonist; Lauren Sevian, baritone saxophonist; Peter McEachern, trombonist; Peter Madsen, Fender Rhodes; and Gerald Cleaver, drummer. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PHAROAH SANDERS QUARTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Sanders, one of the most significant survivors of 1960's free jazz, has never stopped imbuing his performances with the tone of a spiritual quest; he has worthy acolytes in the pianist William Henderson, the bassist Ugonna Okegwo and the drummer Adam Cruz. 8 and 10 tonight and Sunday night, with an additional 11:30 show tonight; 8:15, 10 and 11:30 p.m. tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212)582-2121; cover, $30 and $32.50, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEORGE SCHULLER'S CIRCLE WIDE (Wednesday) Mr. Schuller, a drummer, leads a group inspired by the spacious and mysterious acoustic fusion of Miles Davis, circa 1968; the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin and the guitarist Brad Shepik apply an appropriate push and pull. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STRYKER/SLAGLE BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) The guitarist Dave Stryker and the saxophonist Steve Slagle have worked together in hard-driving settings since as far back as the mid-1980's; their rhythm section here consists of the eminently capable Ed Howard and Victor Lewis, on bass and drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212)576-2232; cover, $20 and $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ASSIF TSAHAR/JIM BLACK/MAT MANERI (Tuesday) On the recent album ''Jam'' (Hopscotch), this trio of improvisers -- Mr. Tsahar, a saxophonist; Mr. Maneri, a violinist; and Mr. Black, a drummer -- address open spaces with shifting timbres. They are joined here by the poet Steve Dalachinsky and the pianist Matthew Shipp. 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212)358-7501; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ARIADNE AUF NAXOS' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Admirers of Deborah Voigt may be disappointed that she is not singing her signature role in the Metropolitan Opera's revival of Strauss's ''Ariadne auf Naxos,'' but the strong Lithuanian mezzo-turned-soprano Violeta Urmana does not disappoint. And the cast, overall, is exceptional, especially the brilliant coloratura soprano Diana Damrau as Zerbinetta, and the radiant mezzo-soprano Susan Graham as the Composer. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $26 to $220. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'ARIANE ET BARBE-BLEUE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Even before the new production opens, the New York City Opera deserves thanks from opera buffs for presenting this rarity by Paul Dukas, best known as the composer of ''The Sorcerer's Apprentice.'' Dukas's delightful opera tells the story of Bluebeard from a woman's point of view. Renate Behle, in her company debut, sings Ariane. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday) Pity a small opera company: it only gets critical attention when it does something unusual, yet its audiences tend to like the same fare as everyone else. Which is to say that ''La Bohème'' at the 204-seat Dicapo Opera will get few reviews, but remains a company standby and a crowd favorite. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dicapo Opera, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212)288-9438; $47.50. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA CENERENTOLA' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Very few voice connoisseurs question the amazing gifts of the molten-voiced, temperamental Russian mezzo-soprano Olga Borodina. But the intense Ms. Borodina as a comic Rossini heroine? That may sound like a stretch. Actually, Ms. Borodina showed wonderful comic instincts in Rossini's ''Italiana in Algeri'' a couple seasons back, and her coloratura technique was impressive. So expect good things when she takes on Rossini's ''Cenerentola'' in a revival of Cesare Lievi's imaginative production. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $26 to $220. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'FALSTAFF' (Wednesday) The attention to detail that characterizes this production is truly unusual: it's well cast, well acted and well conducted by a masterly James Levine. It also features the reigning Falstaff of our day, Bryn Terfel, who is matched note for note by the fabulous Stephanie Blythe as Mistress Quickly -- she almost steals the show. 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000. $26 to $175. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow) Mark Lamos's production of Puccini's classic is one of New York City Opera's best. And there's a lot else to like here, from the intermittently good conducting of Ari Pelto to Jake Gardner's Sharpless. Shu-Ying Li, who was magnificent in the title role when the Dicapo Opera presented all three versions of the opera last year, has taken it over here, evidently with considerable success. 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MANON' (Tonight) Jean-Pierre Ponnelle's production of this Massenet tragedy, absent from the Metropolitan Opera since 2001, returns with Renée Fleming as the conflicted Manon, and Marcelo Álvarez as a passionate and unusually well-rounded des Grieux. Both are in fine voice, and have the support of a well-balanced cast, as well as vibrant conducting by Jésus López-Cobos. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $36 to $205. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'TOSCA' (Sunday and Thursday) Franco Zeffirelli's production of ''Tosca'' at the Metropolitan Opera may offer sumptuous and gargantuan realism, but Mark Lamos's striking production at the New York City Opera offers spare and contemporary theatricality. It returns to the repertory with the soprano Carla Thelen Hanson in her company debut as Tosca, and John DeMain conducting. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BOSTON SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Monday) You can almost see the fun James Levine is having, planning orchestral seasons, and this well-stuffed program is a prime example of a fertile imagination at play: Elliott Carter's ''Three Illusions,'' in its New York premiere; Lukas Foss's masterwork ''Time Cycle,'' with Dawn Upshaw as vocalist; Ives's ''Three Places in New England''; and Gershwin's Piano Concerto in F, with Jean-Yves Thibaudet. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $30 to $105. (James R. Oestreich)</p>
        <p>COMPOSER PORTRAITS (Tonight) George Antheil is the subject of the current installment of this important and enlightening series. Daniel Spalding will conduct the Philadelphia Virtuosi Chamber Orchestra, and Guy Livingston will be the soloist in the Piano Concerto No.2, the centerpiece of a program that also includes the Serenade No.2 and ''Dreams Ballet.'' 8 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212)854-7799; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>GUARNERI STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow). You have to admire the group's stick-to-itiveness, if not always its freshness and polish. Maybe the young violist Scott St. John will inject new energy into Mozart's Quintet in C (K. 515). 8 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212)570-3949; $50. (Oestreich)</p>
        <p>JUILLIARD SYMPHONY (Tuesday) The country's most famous conservatory is celebrating its centenary, and part of its celebration is this performance by the student orchestra, which has proved a superb group in past encounters. The program includes works by Webern, Rautavaara and Schubert, with Dennis Russell Davies conducting. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) The pianist Ilya Itin and the violinist Dmitri Berlinsky are the guests of this feisty ensemble, which in the spirit of its founder, Jens Nygaard, offers programs that combine oddities and major works. This time the fare includes Josef Myslivecek's Trio in G, Dvorak's Octet-Serenade (an arrangement of the Serenade for Strings, Op. 22) and the Brahms Trio in B. At 2 and 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Manhattan, (212)799-1259; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'THE VIRGIL FOX LEGACY' (Tonight through Monday) With a variety of organists on hand, these performances and discussions at various churches in Manhattan honor the memory of the ultimate switched-on master of the instrument on the 25th anniversary of his death. Don't expect the obsequies to be subdued. Most tickets: $25. Information: (212)799-9300, (800)486-6628 or www.legacyconcerts.com. (Oestreich)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>MARIA ELENA ANAYA DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Ms. Anaya's ''Caracolas de un Mar de Fuego'' includes traditional flamenco and dance inspired by a poem by the 17th-century Mexican poet Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz. 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212)475-7710 or lamama.org; $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BALLET AUSTIN (Tonight through Sunday) The company makes its New York City debut with a program of award-winning dances choreographed by its artistic director, Stephen Mills. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., the Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)242-0800; $38. (Erika Kinetz)</p>
        <p>DANCEOFF! (Tuesday and Wednesday) Ten modern-dance choreographers and companies, some famous and others not, have been chosen by Terry Dean Bartlett and Katie Workum for this showcase series. 8 and 10 p.m., P.S. 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212)352-3101 or ps122.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE THEATER ETC (Tomorrow) Thirty dancers dressed as angels will interact with 19th-century statuary in a free, combination two-hour performance and walking tour. Noon and 3 p.m. (Rain date, Sunday), Green-Wood Cemetery, 25th Street and Fifth Avenue, Greenwood Heights, Brooklyn, (718)788-7850 or dancetheatreetcetera.org (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EQUUS PROJECTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) JoAnna Mendl Shaw, who likes to pair dancers with horses and riders, choreographically gallops into a riding academy with ''Rules of Engagement,'' a collaboration with Janet Biggs, an artist and video creator, and Steve White, a composer. It is a multidisciplinary production involving dancing, a horse and rider and site-specific videos. 8 p.m., Claremont Riding Academy, 175 West 89th Street, Manhattan, (800)595-4849 or dancingwithhorses.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door; students and ages 65+, $20 in advance; $25 at the door). (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>JORDAN FUCHS (Tonight through Sunday night) In ''The Almost and the Nearly,'' unusual seating arrangements intentionally limit the performance space, and the choreography tries to blur distinctions between presence and absence as dancers are drawn together and apart. 8:30; Sunday at 7:30 p.m. Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212)674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>GINA GIBNEY DANCE (Thursday) A seasoned, subtle modern-dance choreographer who gives equal opportunity to her brain and heart, Ms. Gibney will present a new multimedia work, ''unbounded,'' that explores the tensions between clinging to the known and reaching for the unknowable. 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212)674-8194; $15 or T.D.F. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOKO HIGASHINO AND HIROAKI UMEDA (Tonight and tomorrow night) Two young Japanese dancers create their own surreal worlds. In ''Alarm! -- zero hour edition,'' Ms. Higashino suggests the unpredictability of a society under the siege of change. Strips of light keep appearing and vanishing, guiding and abandoning Mr. Umeda in ''while going to a condition.'' 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; students and 65+, $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>BEBE MILLER COMPANY (Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Miller, in her company's 20th anniversary, is the latest dance artist to take advantage of the impressive technological facilities at Dance Theater Workshop. In her new ''Landing/Place,'' Ms. Miller will integrate digital motion-capture technology, animation and video projections into a dance about traveling in Eritrea. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)924-0077; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHARLES MOORE DANCE THEATER (Tonight) A company featuring dances of Africa and the Caribbean performed with historical respect and contemporary elation offers its new ''Strength of the Spirit.'' 8, Peter Norton Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212)864-5400 or symphonyspace.org; $25; children, students and ages 65+, $20.(Anderson)</p>
        <p>PATRICIA NICHOLSON: 'DANCE WORDS SPEAK PEACE' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Nicholson believes in the power of socially conscious art to nurture weary souls. The program also includes choreography by KJ Holmes. 7:30, Clemente Soto Vélez, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212)696-6681 or visionfestival.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEXT WAVE FESTIVAL: NATIONAL BALLET OF CHINA (Tuesday through Thursday) The company will perform ''Raise the Red Lantern,'' which tells the story of a young concubine in 1920's China with a fusion of ballet, modern dance and traditional Chinese dance, set to music performed on Western and Chinese instruments and directed by Zhang Yimou, the noted film director. 7:30 p.m., BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718)636-4100; $20 to $70. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ODC/SAN FRANCISCO (Tuesday through Thursday) This program by two of this San Francisco-based company's resident choreographers includes dances by Brenda Way, among them one inspired by global warming, and by KT Nelson. 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)242-0800 or joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>REVERB FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) A new organization that seeks to brings together works derived from different cultural backgrounds and aesthetic perspectives offers its first programs. The participating choreographers are Ayako Kurakake, Ofelia Loret de Mola, Kate Hutter, Lane Gifford, Nelly van Bommel and Sidra Bell. 8, Joan Weill Center for Dance, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)280-3468 or (914)630-4505; $15; students, $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>HENNING RUBSAM'S SENSEDANCE (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Rubsam tends to mix ballet, modern dance and a kind of sunny optimism in dances that often probe the special qualities in his performers. This program includes choreography set to music by Beata Moon, Beethoven, Brahms, Django Reinhardt and Ricardo Llorca, with the guest artists Melissa Morrissey and Ramon Thielen from Dance Theater of Harlem. 8 p.m., Baruch Performing Arts Center, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street, (646)312-4085; $22 and $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MALLIKA SARABHAI AND THE DARPANA PERFORMING GROUP (Wednesday and Thursday) In the edible-sounding ''Hot Talas Cool Rasas,'' the artists promise a bouquet of styles and ideas that form the panorama of contemporary dance in India. Wednesday at 7 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Ailey Studios Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)529 2347. Wednesday, $150; Thursday, $35 and students and 65+, $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>2005 D.U.M.B.O. DANCE FESTIVAL (Thursday) Last year's festival was a lot of fun, with companies and individuals who looked as if they had been chosen with a sense of personal taste, perhaps that of the festival director, Young Soon Kim, and dance in a huge variety of styles spilling out across a small, shining studio-theater. And it's all free. 7 p.m., White Wave's John Ryan Theater, 25 Jay Street, on the waterfront, Brooklyn, (718)855-8822 or whitewavedance.com. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KRIOTA WILLBERG/DURA MATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Willberg has a wicked eye for the foibles of American dance, and she lets it rove, deliciously, in ''The Bentfootes,'' a beautifully costumed multimedia satire that tells the story of 200 years of dance by the fictitious Susan Bentfoote and her family of unerringly mediocre artists. 8, Dixon Place at University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side, (212)219-0736 or dixonplace.org; $10 to $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>AMERICAN FOLK ART MUSEUM: 'OBSESSIVE DRAWING,' through March 19. In the museum's first ''emerging talent'' show, one of the five artists selected is 83, lives in a home for the elderly in Pennsylvania and stopped painting two years ago because of failing eyesight. Overall, the work in the exhibition is abstract and spare, giving the problematic ''outsider'' category a new spin. 45 West 53rd Street, (212)265-1040. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'EXTREME TEXTILES,' through Oct. 30. Don't look for aesthetic pizazz in this intensely techy show of industrial fibers and fabrics, but don't rule it out. The show's raison d'être is solely use, but a lot of what's on view, in the first museum display of material made to function in extreme conditions, is visually exciting. 2 East 91st Street, (212)849-8400.(Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'RUSSIA!,' through Jan. 11. This survey of nine centuries of Russian art ranges from 13th-century religious icons to a smattering of 21st-century works, achieving its astounding effect without resorting to a single egg, or anything else, by Fabergé. It immerses us in two enormous, endlessly fascinating narratives: the history of painting and the history of Russia itself, forming a remarkable tribute to the endurance of the medium and the country, and the inescapable interconnectedness of art and life. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212)423-3600. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>*JAPAN SOCIETY: 'HIROSHI SUGIMOTO: HISTORY OF HISTORY,' through Feb. 19. A very personal, whimsical exhibition by this well-known Japanese photographer, who incorporates into his own work artifacts that he has collected over the years, particularly from East Asia and Japan. Mr. Sugimoto's reach is long, and his range is broad, from fossil stones to textiles to undersea dioramas to Japanese calligraphy to the trylon and perisphere (a mini-sculpture) that symbolized the New York World's Fair of 1939. It may not be all that enlightening, but as an artist's personal survey, it comes off. 333 East 47th Street, (212)832-1155. (Glueck).</p>
        <p>EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO: 'THE (S) FILES/THE SELECTED FILES 05,' through Jan. 29. The definition of what ''Latino art'' means is changing in a post-identity-politics time, and this modest biennial, drawn mostly from unsolicited proposals submitted by artists in the greater New York area, is an indicator of what that change looks like. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212)831-7272. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF BIBLICAL ART: 'THE NEXT GENERATION: CONTEMPORARY EXPRESSIONS OF FAITH,' through Nov. 13. Works in this juried show of artists who belong to the organization Christians in the Visual Arts range from traditional paintings and sculptures to an interactive video and photo documentation of a shamanistic performance in the woods. Ambitious, optically captivating collages by Mary Fielding McCleary and Anita Breitenberg Naylor are among the few pieces that exceed familiar generic limitations. 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212)408-1500. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>QUEENS MUSEUM OF ART: 'DOWN THE GARDEN PATH: THE ARTIST'S GARDEN AFTER MODERNISM,' through Nov. 6. This big, messy and uneven show, still a thought-provoking one for patient and interested viewers, surveys how artists like Vito Acconci, Ian Hamilton Finlay, Mel Chin, Ghada Amer, Stan Douglas and many more have cultivated gardens in fantasy and in reality. Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718)592-9700.(Johnson)</p>
        <p>* STUDIO MUSEUM IN HARLEM: 'SCRATCH: 2004-2005 ARTISTS-IN-RESIDENCE: WILLIAM CORDOVA, MICHAEL QUEENLAND AND MARC ANDRE ROBINSON,' through Oct. 23 . Rap, religion, Minimalism and Malcolm X all figure in this intricate, multilayered show of work by the three young residents, organized by the museum's associate curator, Christine Y. Kim. 144 West 125th Street, (212)864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*WHITNEY MUSEUM: ROBERT SMITHSON, through Oct. 23. Who knows whether Smithson is the most influential American postwar artist, as this show claims. Consisting mostly of drawings, photographs and films (he didn't make that many sculptures, not ones that could fit into a museum, anyway), this is the first full-scale overview of him in the country. It is consequently dry but still compelling testimony to a great exuberance cut drastically short when Smithson died at 35 in a plane crash in 1973. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212)570-3600. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>*ADAM DANT: 'STANDING UNDER' An extraordinarily imaginative and skillful draftsman, Mr. Dant makes large pen-and-brush drawings of complex scenes populated by chunky little people, all viewed as if from below through a transparent ground or floor. Adam Baumgold, 74 East 79th Street, (212)861-7338, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>HENRY WOLF Organized by the photography critic Vince Aletti, this exhibition presents works by the extraordinarily suave art director, designer and photographer Henry Wolf (1925-2005). Examples of his designs for magazine covers and pictures by photographers that he commissioned are on view, but the most interesting part is the selection of Wolf's own noncommercial photographs, which are compelling for their ultramodern ways with light, multiple spaces, speed and glamour. Howard Greenberg, 41 East 57th Street, (212)334-0010, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'SALUTE TO THE 130TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE ART STUDENTS LEAGUE' No gallery in the city regularly offers better small group exhibitions of American modernism than Washburn. And its homage to the Art Students League made up of work by four illustrious students -- Louise Nevelson, Jackson Pollock, Mark Rothko and David Smith -- is a sterling example. The Washburn Gallery, 20 West 57th Street, 8th floor, (212)397-6780, through Oct. 29. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>DENNIS ADAMS: 'MAKE DOWN' This brainy political artist presents a video in which he uses film stills from the movie ''Battle of Algiers'' to wipe dark green makeup off his face and body. It's about terrorism, gender, masking and unmasking. Kent, 541 West 25th Street, (212)627-3680, through Oct. 16. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*DIANE ARBUS: 'OTHER FACES OTHER ROOMS' If think you are suffering from Diane Arbus fatigue, this exhibition of 49 photographs that have not been widely published or exhibited will surely refresh your interest. Robert Miller, 524 West 26th Street, (212)366-4774, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*TOM BURCKHARDT: 'FULL STOP'  A painter of eclectically layered abstractions has produced a surprising environmental installation: a slightly old-fashioned, fully equipped painter's studio made of brown corrugated cardboard and black paint. Caren Golden, 539 West 23rd Street, (212)727-8304, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>WOUTER DERUYTTER: 'CROW WARRIORS' You could almost mistake Mr. Deruytter's black-and-white, subtly erotic photographs of Crow Indian warriors in face paint, feathered headdresses and loin cloths, riding bareback horses, for 19th-century ethnographic documents. In fact, they depict contemporary Indians gathered for an annual re-enactment of the Battle of the Little Bighorn. Briggs Robinson, 527 West 29th Street, (212)560-9075, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>TOM HUCK: 'THE BLOODY BUCKET SERIES' Extra-large black-and-white woodcuts by this Missourian look like the works of a Northern Renaissance artist who time-traveled to 1960's California and became an underground comic book artist. His jam-packed compositions are gleefully obscene and violent without being too offensive, and the prints are technically impressive. David Krut, 526 West 26th Street, (212)255-3094, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'MUD' This exceptional four-artist show of small sculpture features lively, insouciant ceramics by the painter Joanne Greenbaum; crusty, off-white ceramics by Elliott Levine that look like ancient artifacts; cartoonish sculptures about modern machines by Aga Ousseinov; and rough, semiabstract sculptures in Styrofoam and papier mâché, alluding to landscapes and furniture, by Yuh-Shioh Wong. Dinter, 547 West 27th Street, (212)947-2818, through Oct. 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MONIQUE PRIETO AND LYNDA BENGLIS Ms. Prieto has, in effect, boarded over her abstract paintings with rough-hewn monolithic letters quoting Samuel Pepys's famous diary. Both the wordiness and the klunkiness are a bit familiar, but extracting Pepys's phrases, which are all deliberately disembodied in reference, can be strangely satisfying. In ''The Graces,'' Ms. Benglis continues to evoke figures by other means, in this case three shimmering stacks of vaselike forms made of heavily textured, lavender-tinted resin. The material is perfect for the process-oriented Ms. Benglis. Cheim &amp; Read, 547 West 25th Street, (212)242-7727, through Oct. 15. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>IAN BURNS Mr. Burns's amusing whirligigs, small motorized contraptions and a large sit-in piece that directs your gaze to a series of illuminated screens like shadow-puppet theaters are roughly made of wood, with outsiderlike ingenuity. His cheerfully satiric cartoon imagery addresses terrorism and the war in Iraq. Spencer Brownstone, 39 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212)334-3455, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Claire Fontaine Politically charged works by this French artist include a neon-light work that outlines the image of a hooded Iraqi prisoner and child; a neon sign in the gallery's front window that says in Arabic, ''Foreigners Everywhere''; and a tiny sculpture called ''In God We Trust'' in the form of a 25-cent coin with a fold-out box cutter secreted inside. Reena Spaulings, 371 Grand Street, SoHo, (212)477-5006, through Oct. 21. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MACCHINE NATURALI: 'ABSTRACT COLLAGES BY JOSEPH STELLA' The largest New York show in some time of Stella's elegant, understated collages, made from dirt-stained scraps of paper, can thoroughly rearrange your grasp of his sensibility and the history of American modernism. Peter Freeman Inc., 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, SoHo (212)966-5349, through Oct. 29. (Smith).</p>
        <p>'PAPER MUSEUMS: THE REPRODUCTIVE PRINT IN EUROPE, 1500-1800' From the early 16th century to the beginning of the 19th, prints that reproduced the original work of artists were the only means of acquainting a broad public with the creative endeavors of Dürer, Raphael, Rubens, Michelangelo and the like. This show displays the variety and vitality of such reproductive prints, and points up how they effectively circulated artists' works and ideas in Europe. Don't expect lots of pictorial splash here. Grey Art Gallery, New York University, 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village, (212)998-6780, through Dec. 3. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>*PHILIP-LORCA diCORCIA: 'LUCKY THIRTEEN' Strippers are hardly a new subject for fine-art photographers, but Mr. diCorcia's monumental portraits of pole dancers are far from routine. Each of the 13 glossy pictures depicts a scantily dressed -- in one case, nude -- female dancer practicing her art in a dark and empty club. All but one assume upside-down positions, as if posing for a Renaissance painter of angels and crucifixions, and the effect is more of spiritual and athletic austerity than of cheesy eroticism. PaceWildenstein, 534 West 25th Street, (212)929-7000, closing tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*KIM JONES: 'WAR PAINT' Kim Jones has been best known since the late 1970's for his appearances on the streets, in subways and in galleries as the walking sculpture called Mudman. This show is made up of wearable shirts and jackets with boxy, three-dimensional ink-and-acrylic paintings attached to the back, each painting a cross between a computer game and a battle plan. Pierogi, 177 North Ninth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718)599-2144, closing on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*MARTIN McMURRAY: 'BLOODSHOT AND GLOWING' In a solo debut, small, fraught figurative paintings evoke some of the tragedies of American history and literature, and transcend a host of artistic influences with a flinty intensity. Jeff Bailey Gallery, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212)989-0156, closing tomorrow. (Smith).</p>
        <p>NATIONAL ACADEMY MUSEUM: JEAN HÉLION  Hélion's conversion, around 1940, from a suave, smartly synthetic mode of geometric abstraction to a like-minded figurative style doesn't put him in a league with great 20th-century apostates like Giacometti, Picabia or Guston. This meager show does not give a full account of his strengths or weaknesses, but is well worth a look. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212)369-4880, closing on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>*'Pop Politics Power' In this measured but intense three-artist show, Martha Rosler offers a continuation of her 1967-72 photomontage series ''Bringing the War Home''; Carolee Schneemann is represented by both a new film and by her mesmerizing 1965 ''Viet Flakes,'' in which a rush of grainy black-and-white war photographs looks like smoke billowing from a volcano; and Robert Boyd introduces two spooky videos about doomsday religious cults, past, present and (probably) future. LMAKprojects, 526 West 26th Street, No.310, Chelsea, (212)255-9707, closing tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Raqib Shaw: 'Garden of Earthly Delights' Labor-intensive and intensely active, Raqib Shaw's paintings look like X-rated, subaquatic hybrids of Hieronymous Bosch, Victorian fairy painting, Persian miniatures and Bollywood films of the Ramayana. Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, SoHo, (212)343-7300, closing tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*JANET SOBEL This self-taught, late-blooming artist introduced Jackson Pollock to his signature drip technique, playing Henri Rousseau to his Picasso. Here, her art veers between the semi-abstract works that Pollock saw in 1944 and folk-artish, happy-peasant landscapes (inspired by a Ukrainian childhood) in which inventively handled paint does most of the dancing. This stunning show reveals a wily, liberated artist whose closest European analogy may be Jean Dubuffet. DC Moore Gallery, 724 Fifth Avenue, near 57th Street, (212)247-1111, closing tomorrow. (Smith).</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM: 'REMOTE VIEWING' The vast information overload the world struggles with -- scientific theory, technological data, geopolitical facts, historical material and on and on -- is whipped into visual cosmologies by eight painters of widely different approaches and sensibilities. If the premise is fuzzy, the show has some sharp art. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212)570-3600, closing Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART AT ALTRIA: 'PAST PRESENCE: CHILDHOOD AND MEMORY' This modestly resonant show of works relating to juvenile experience presents a glass cabinet filled with 2,000 miniature white ceramic vessels by Charles LeDray; small, finely drawn, photo-based pictures of children by Peggy Preheim; and a politically suggestive chalkboard drawing by Gary Simmons. 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917)663-2453, closing on Thursday. (Johnson)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, showtimes and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'WAR IN PARAMUS' Previews begin tonight. Opens Tuesday. Spanning Woodstock to Watergate, this suburban comedy by Austin Pendleton finds a teenager angry with the members of her family, who are obsessing over her sister's wedding (1:20). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, June Havoc Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212)868-4444. 'EMILIA GALOTTI' Opens Wednesday. The Deutsches Theater Berlin production of Gotthold Ephraim Lessing's 1772 play about a woman whose virtue is compromised (1:15). Brooklyn Academy of Music's Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718)636-4100.</p>
        <p>'ABSURD PERSON SINGULAR' Opens Oct. 18. The latest production of this comedy by the unstoppably prolific Alan Ayckbourn is about three couples and takes place over three holiday seasons (2:30). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Oct. 16. The medieval epic poem becomes a 21st-century rock opera in this Irish Repertory Theater production, with a score by Lenny Pickett, the musical director of ''Saturday Night Live'' (1:15). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, (212)727-2737.</p>
        <p>'FIVE COURSE LOVE' Opens Oct. 16. On the menu are five dates in five restaurants, put to music in five different styles, including operetta and country-western (1:30). Minetta Lane Theater, 18 Minetta Lane, Greenwich Village, (212)307-4100.</p>
        <p>'IN MY LIFE'  Opens Oct. 20. Love blossoms between a musician with Tourette's syndrome and an insecure journalist in this Broadway musical, directed and written by Joseph Brooks (1:45). Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' Opens Nov. 6. Straight from La Jolla Playhouse in California, this rags-to-riches musical tells the story of Frankie Valli and the Four Seasons, featuring hits including ''Big Girls Don't Cry'' and ''Rag Doll.'' Des McAnuff directs (2:30). Virginia Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Opens Oct. 27. A little Neil Simon revival you might have heard of, starring Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick as Oscar and Felix. Joe Mantello directs (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212)307-4100.</p>
        <p>'SEE WHAT I WANT TO SEE' Previews start Tuesday. Opens Oct. 30. Michael John LaChiusa's highly anticipated new musical stars Idina Menzel and Marc Kudisch and features three contemporary stories based on the work of the Japanese writer Ryonosuke Akutagawa (2:00). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SOLDIER'S PLAY' Opens Oct. 17. The first major New York revival of Charles Fuller's play about the trial of a black soldier during World War II. With Taye Diggs and James McDaniel (2:10). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212)246-4422.</p>
        <p>'SWEENEY TODD' Opens Nov. 3. Patti LuPone and Michael Cerveris star in this intimate revival of the Sondheim classic, featuring 10 actors who play their own instruments. It started at the Watermill Theater in England, before moving to West End and Broadway (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THIRD' Opens Oct. 24. A professor played by Dianne Wiest accuses a student of plagiarism in Wendy Wasserstein's latest. Daniel Sullivan directs (2:00). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212)239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHITTY CHITTY BANG BANG' The playthings are the thing in this lavish windup music box of a show: windmills, Rube Goldbergesque machines and the show's title character, a flying car. It's like spending two and a half hours in the Times Square branch of Toys ''R'' Us (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' On paper this musical tale of two mismatched scam artists has an awful lot in common with ''The Producers.'' But if you are going to court comparison with giants, you had better be prepared to stand tall. ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels,'' starring John Lithgow and Norbert Leo Butz, never straightens out of a slouch (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) Set in the Bronx in 1964, this play by John Patrick Shanley is structured as a clash of wills and generations between Sister Aloysius (Cherry Jones), the head of a parochial school, and Father Flynn (Brian F. O'Byrne), the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge. The play's elements bring to mind those tidy topical melodramas that were once so popular. But Mr. Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions (1:30). Walter Kerr, 219 West 48th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Still, it seems safe to say that such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence will find a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SWEET CHARITY' This revival of the 1966 musical never achieves more than a low-grade fever when what's wanted is that old steam heat. In the title role of the hopeful dance-hall hostess, the appealing but underequipped Christina Applegate is less a shopworn angel than a merry cherub (2:30). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around. (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212)239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>*'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 4, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'COLDER THAN HERE'  Judith Light plays a British wife and mother slowly succumbing to cancer but resisting low spirits to the last in Laura Wade's skillful but unexceptional play. Brian Murray, Sarah Paulson and Lily Rabe cope as best they can, admiring Mom's brave spirit as they heal the rifts that separate them (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)279-4200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CYCLING PAST THE MATTERHORN' A grating comedy-drama by Deborah Grimberg about the fractious relationship between a mother and daughter. Shirley Knight plays Esther, a needy, needling woman who discovers she's going blind just as her daughter leaves the nest. Carrie Preston is her needy, self-absorbed daughter (1:35). Harold Clurman Theater on Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEDICATION, OR THE STUFF OF DREAMS' Portraying a terminally ill, rancidly rich misanthrope in Terrence McNally's play about a small-town children's theater troupe, Marian Seldes is a snappy advertisement for the time-defying benefits of a religious devotion to theater. She is, in fact, what ''Dedication'' is all about, or intends to be, anyway. Burdened with soap-operaish plot turns and artificially bright dialogue, this comedy of mortality never seems able to convince itself that life and art trump death and doubt. (2:15). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212)279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' This noisy novelty is a mixed blessing. Providing a two-foot drum on every seat, it offers an opportunity to exorcise aggressions by delivering a good beating, and on a slightly more elevated level, it presents a superficial introduction to African culture, lessons in drumming and 90 minutes of nonstop music, song and dancing by a good-natured cast (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200.(Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE GREAT AMERICAN TRAILER PARK MUSICAL' A terrific cast keeps the generator running in this bright but flimsy contraption. A few of David Nehls's dozen ditties raise a hearty chuckle, like the valedictory anthem in which the show's heroines collectively vow to ''make like a nail and press on.'' But Betsy Kelso's book all but dispenses with plot, and substitutes crude cartoons for characters (2:00). Dodger Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>*'THE INTELLIGENT DESIGN OF JENNY CHOW' In Rolin Jones's fanciful comedy, playfully directed by Jackson Gay, a lonely young woman in California embarks on an ambitious science project to help conquer her agoraphobia and trace her origins in China. Brisk, funny and engaging, the play disappoints only in its emphasis on flights of fancy over a nuanced depiction of its heroine's emotional dilemmas (2:10). Atlantic Theater Company, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE LADIES OF THE CORRIDOR' The Peccadillo Theater Company has revived this 1953 play by Dorothy Parker and Arnaud D'Usseau. A comedy set in an East Side hotel populated by widows and divorcees, it is an unyielding and coruscating portrait of women before feminism, relieved by Parker's dead-on wit. East 13th Street Theater, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212)279-4200.(Honor Moore)</p>
        <p>'LATE FRAGMENT'  Matthew, a World Trade Center employee who survived Sept. 11, and Marta are a desperate couple falling out of love in Francine Volpe's often perceptive if muddled drama named after a Raymond Carver poem. Under the direction of Michael Imperioli (Christopher from ''The Sopranos'') and Zetna Fuentes, the play has a wobbly style, building tension only to diffuse it with less-than-credible moments (1:30). Studio Dante, 257 West 29th Street, Chelsea, (212)279-4200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'MEDEA' Sure, she gets most of the attention, but let's take a moment to acknowledge Jason, who, as embodied by Lawrence Winslow in the Classical Theater of Harlem's jolting production, contributes some terrific laughs to Euripides' grim tragedy. Yeah, that's right: laughs, the kind you get from the incongruity of the good ol' boys' network encountering Gloria Steinem (1:10). Classical Theater of Harlem, at the Harlem School of the Arts Theater, 645 St. Nicholas Avenue, near 141st Street, (212)868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'MIRACLE BROTHERS' Kirsten Childs's show, about magical Brazilian river dolphins that assume human form to explore racial conflict in the 17th century, does indeed flow like a river -- a winding, muddy, very long river in a dry season (2:00). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)353-0303. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE MUSICAL OF MUSICALS!' The musical is the happy narcissist of theater; parody is the best form of narcissism. All it needs are smart writers and winning performers. That's what we get in this case (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 5, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Margo Jefferson)</p>
        <p>'NO FOREiGNERS BEYOND THIS POINT'  Two innocents abroad learn the limits of American idealism in Warren Leight's wistfully funny new play about the difficulty of doing good in a society rigged to accommodate only more cynical transactions. Based on Mr. Leight's own experience as a teacher of English in China before he established a career as a playwright (the Tony-winning ''Side Man''), the play is slight but appealing (2:00). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212)352-3101. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'ONCE AROUND THE SUN' The ''sun'' of the title could be the talent and energy of the show's impressive cast: you can warm your hands on them and on the catchy music. Unfortunately, the book fails to capitalize on these strengths, instead presenting a trite fable about a young rock singer seduced by celebrity, with cardboard characters, despite the actors' best efforts to give them dimension. Still, the performances are very entertaining (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, Manhattan, (212)239-6200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'ONE-MAN STAR WARS TRILOGY' With a storm trooper roaming the aisles and a woman in an Obi-Wan Kenobi get-up telling theatergoers to turn off their cellphones or they will be turned into ''cosmic dust,'' Charles Ross's sprint through Episodes IV through VI aims for the atmosphere of a ''Star Wars'' convention but ends up achieving something like a religious revival (which is sort of the same thing). True believers will love how Mr. Ross, a self-confessed geek who plays every major role in under an hour, simulates R2D2, but everyone else will scratch his head (1:00). Lamb's Theater, 130 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212)239-6200. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'ORSON'S SHADOW' Austin Pendleton's play, about a 1960 production of Ionesco's ''Rhinoceros,'' which was directed by Orson Welles and starred Laurence Olivier, is a sharp-witted but tenderhearted backstage comedy about the thin skins, inflamed nerves and rampaging egos that are the customary side effects when sensitivity meets success (2:00). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, Greenwich Village, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE PAVILION' Craig Wright's play about the speedy wheels of time's winged chariot and the dreams it grinds into dust is set at a small-town high school reunion. Brian D'Arcy James aches with longing as the cad who wants a second chance. Gracefully directed by Lucie Tiberghien (2:00). Rattlestick Theater, 224 Waverly Place, at 11th Street, West Village, (212)868-4444. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>*'SIDES: THE FEAR IS REAL' This hilarious collection of sketches may send up familiar targets -- the insecure thespian, the fraudulent acting teacher, the arrogant Juilliard grad -- but since it's performed with such specificity and comic charm by actors firing on all cylinders, you won't care a whit. Written by and starring an all-Asian-American cast, this slight but consistently entertaining satire is a primer on what not to do in an audition room (1:15). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212)307-4100. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SLUT'  This overamplified musical comedy about love and promiscuity among East Village friends leans heavily on obscenities to lend it a daring edge. Instead, it swamps even its brightest moments in tawdriness (2:00). American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>*'THOM PAIN (BASED ON NOTHING)' Is there such a thing as stand-up existentialism? If not, Will Eno has just invented it. Stand-up-style comic riffs and deadpan hipster banter keep interrupting the corrosively bleak narrative. Mr. Eno is a Samuel Beckett for the Jon Stewart generation (1:10). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'WALKING DOWN BROADWAY' Dawn Powell's 1931 tale of young people looking for life and love in New York City is packed with smart dialogue and honest emotions. It is also well directed, well acted and smartly designed (2:30). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212)315-0231. (Jefferson)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BELLY OF A DRUNKEN PIANO' In this splendidly imperfect cabaret, Stewart D'Arrietta howls and growls convincingly through Tom Waits's three-decade song catalog, backed by a snappy trio. His patter and his piano playing are variable, but Mr. D'Arrietta makes a genial tour guide through Mr. Waits's wee-hours world (1:45). Huron Club at SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, between Avenue of the Americas and Varick Street, (212)691-1555. (Rob Kendt)</p>
        <p>*'POOR THEATER' Part homage and part anatomy, the Wooster Group's warm, witty tribute to the director Jerzy Grotowski and the choreographer William Forsythe demonstrates how imitation can be not just sincere flattery but also a hopeful attempt to crawl into someone else's skin to see how it fits. As identities and their representations morph and blur, this is not always a comfortable activity, but it is often an exhilarating one (1:30). Performing Garage, 33 Wooster Street, between Broome and Grand Streets, SoHo, (212)868-4444. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212)307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212)239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FIDDLER ON THE ROOF' The Shtetl Land pavilion in the theme park called Broadway. With Rosie O'Donnell and Harvey Fierstein. (2:55). The Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MOVIN' OUT' The miracle dance musical that makes Billy Joel cool (2:00). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'NAKED BOYS SINGING' That's who they are. That's what they do (1:05). Julia Miles Theater, 414 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)239-6200. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212)239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin are stirring up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, Flatiron district, (212)307-4100.(Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212)307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'DR. SEX' This harmless, fluffy musical about the life of Alfred Kinsey imagines that groundbreaking scientist and sex researcher as a good-time guy who likes to fool around at gay clubs and crack wise like a Catskills comic. As played by the very game Brian Noonan, Kinsey strips at a moment's notice, dances in front of a Busby Berkeley line of Kinsey Players and boils down his philosophy, quite deftly, actually, into ''When you're making whoop, you're part of a group'' (2:20). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200, closing Sunday.( Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'FRAN'S BED' Even the ever-radiant charms of Mia Farrow are not enough to dispel the pervasive gloom in this wan new play, written and directed by James Lapine, about an American family facing an unhappy ending. Ms. Farrow plays a comatose woman surveying, in her apparently still-active mind, an unhappy life. Intermittently fun, but mostly glum (1:45). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212)279-4200, closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE SAUNDERS'S PASTORALIA' An often funny if ultimately disappointing stage adaptation of George Saunders's brilliantly entertaining and brazenly off-kilter novella about an impoverished, historically themed amusement park featuring everything from fake hermits to a simulated Jesus. The director Yehuda Duenyas faithfully adapts this chilling satire, but never figures out a theatrical way to articulate the inner life of its characters (1:25). P.S. 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212)352-3101, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'MOTHER COURAGE' An effort more commendable for its intention than its execution, this staging fails to capture either the tragedy or the comedy of the play, let alone the ironies of war (2:45). Jean Cocteau Repertory, at the Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212)279-4200, closing tomorrow. (Wilborn Hampton)</p>
        <p>'THE SAFETY NET' Christopher Kyle's thoughtful midlife-crisis drama touches on everything from the racial prejudices of the liberal elite to the nature-nurture debate in this finely tuned production about a man going through the motions. David, an immigration lawyer very close to making partner, has a very late coming of age after his brother dies in a car accident, leaving a pregnant fiancée (2:00). Michael Weller Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, sixth floor, Clinton, (212)397-2918, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'SPIRIT' Three men and one slippery slope of a stage. From these simple elements, the inspired London-based Improbable troupe maps a funny, melancholy and altogether entrancing journey into a land of dreams, warfare and actorly neurosis. A magical demonstration that theater can go places that no other art form can. (1:30). New York Theater Workshop, 79 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212)239-6200, closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A WOMAN OF WILL' In this wrongheaded solo musical, Kate McNeill (Amanda McBroom) is a lyricist at a creative dead end, in a hotel room waiting for inspiration for a big second-act ballad. In the meantime, she imagines songs in the voices of the heroines of Shakespeare's plays, including a blues tune by Lady Macbeth, a disco number by Kate from ''The Taming of the Shrew'' and a pop anthem by Goneril from ''King Lear'' (''No more Mrs. Nice guy, she's such a dreadful bore./I'm into vivisection, not polishing the floor.'') (1:30). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212)239-6200, closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, showtimes and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>*'THE ARISTOCRATS' (No rating, 89 minutes) A rigorously scholarly documentary about the theory and practice of joke-telling that also happens to be one of the filthiest, vilest, most extravagantly obscene movies ever made -- and one of the funniest. (A.O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE BAXTER' (PG-13, 91 minutes) A ''Baxter,'' in the lingo of this romantic comedy written by, directed by and starring the comedian Michael Showalter, is the safe choice, the also-ran, the guy who is left at the altar when the hero shows up, as Dustin Hoffman did in ''The Graduate,'' to claim his true love. The film's tragic flaw is that Mr. Showalter is miscast -- or has miscast himself -- in the title role. In the end, ''The Baxter'' is a Baxter of a movie: well meaning and mildly likable, but unlikely to sweep you off your feet. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>'BEFORE THE FALL' (No rating, 110 minutes, in German) In Hitler's Germany, the National-Political Institutes of Learning, known as ''Napolas,'' were part of a network of elite schools used to train and indoctrinate future leaders with a sadistic combination of boot camp and brainwashing. Dennis Gansel's intensely beautiful film brings us inside a Napola to observe the fate of a young amateur boxer and his sensitive roommate. Though somewhat overdetermined, the film is a chilling testament to the seductiveness of groupthink and the allure of imagined superiority. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'BROKEN FLOWERS' (R, 105 minutes) Sweet, funny, sad and meandering, Jim Jarmusch's new film sends Bill Murray's aging Don Juan out in search of a son he never knew he had. He finds four former lovers, including Sharon Stone and Jessica Lange, and reveals once again that he is the quietest and finest comic actor working in movies today. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CHAIN' (No rating, 99 minutes) Jem Cohen's sad, lyrical evocation of the homogeneity of the global landscape views it through the eyes of two young women: a Japanese corporate functionary researching theme parks in the United States and a glum temp worker eking out a living in shopping malls and motels. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'CAPOTE' (R, 114 minutes) Philip Seymour Hoffman's portrayal of Truman Capote is a tour de force of psychological insight. Following the novelist as he works on the magazine assignment that will become ''In Cold Blood,'' the film raises intriguing questions about the ethics of writing. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'THE CONSTANT GARDENER' (R, 129 minutes) A superior thriller with a conscience, from John le Carré's novel. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'EL CRIMEN PERFECTO' (No rating, 105 minutes, in Spanish) In this antic and outrageous black comedy, Rafael González (Guillermo Toledo) is a salesman in the women's section of a Madrid department store. Rafael's fondest dream is to be floor manager; when his archrival for the position, Don Antonio (Luis Varela), is accidentally killed in a scuffle in the dressing room, Rafael's world begins to unravel. Like the Ferris wheel that serves as the setting for one of its climactic scenes, ''El Crimen Perfecto'' is a bright, gaudy and tremendously satisfying ride. (Stevens)</p>
        <p>'EVERYTHING IS ILLUMINATED' (PG-13, 104 minutes) From Jonathan Safran Foer's novel, a sentimental Holocaust tale; tender and funny in places, but also thin and soft. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE EXORCISM OF EMILY ROSE' (PG-13, 114 minutes) If you must see only one demonic-possession courtroom drama this year, wait for the next one. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'FLIGHTPLAN' (PG-13, 93 minutes) To watch Jodie Foster storm through a phony airplane as a mother in search of her missing child has its very minor pleasures, but there is nothing in this thrill-free thriller to feed the head or fray the nerves. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'FORTY SHADES OF BLUE' (No rating, 108 minutes) Ira Sachs's Sundance prizewinner is the sad, lovely story of a Memphis record producer (Rip Torn), his much younger Russian girlfriend (Dina Korzun) and his grown-up son (Darren Burrows), who stumble into a love triangle. Great music and fine acting, with Mr. Torn, at 74, giving the performance of a lifetime. (Scott)</p>
        <p>*'THE 40-YEAR-OLD VIRGIN' (R, 111 minutes) A sex comedy turned romantic bliss-out, with Steve Carell, in which the sound of one prophylactic snapping is just a single sweet note in the glorious symphony of love. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'FOUR BROTHERS' (R, 148 minutes)two hours, 28 minutes) In John Singleton's slick hybrid of urban western and modern blaxploitation movie, four young men, two black and two white, reunite in Detroit to avenge the shooting death of their saintly adoptive mother. Preposterous, amoral and exciting. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*'GOOD NIGHT, AND GOOD LUCK' (PG, 90 minutes) George Clooney, with impressive rigor and intelligence, examines the confrontation between the CBS newsman Edward R. Murrow (a superb David Strathairn) and Senator Joseph R. McCarthy (himself). Plunging you into a smoky, black-and-white world of political paranoia and commercial pressure, the film is both a history lesson and a passionate essay on power, responsibility and the ethics of journalism (Scott)</p>
        <p>'GOING SHOPPING' (PG-13, 106 minutes) As loquacious and scatterbrained as its female characters, this Henry Jaglom film explores women's shopping habits and fantasies. Its incomplete sketches revolve around an upscale dress shop on the verge of bankruptcy. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE GREATEST GAME EVER PLAYED' (PG, 115 minutes) A rousing, obvious re-creation of the 1913 United States Open, in which two sons of the working classes faced off in a game still dominated, on both sides of the Atlantic, by the well-born. Aims for par and makes it. ( Scott)</p>
        <p>*'GRIZZLY MAN' (R, 103 minutes) Werner Herzog's bold, enthralling documentary about one man's journey into the heart of darkness (and the belly of the beast) traces the life and strange times of the self-anointed grizzly expert Timothy Treadwell. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'A HISTORY OF VIOLENCE' (R, 97 minutes) A masterpiece of indirection and pure visceral thrills about a seemingly average American family almost undone by cataclysmic violence, David Cronenberg's latest mindblower is the feel-good, feel-bad movie of the year. With Viggo Mortensen, Maria Bello, Ed Harris and William Hurt, all excellent. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'JUST LIKE HEAVEN' (PG-13, 95 minutes) Reese Witherspoon's disembodied spirit haunts Mark Ruffalo in a real estate dispute that runs into a sweet romantic comedy. Surprisingly lighthearted and brisk, considering its fairly morbid premise.(Scott)</p>
        <p>'LORD OF WAR' (R, 122 minutes) A misfire of a political satire about the international gun market from Andrew Niccol, a filmmaker whose words say no, but whose overworked visual style says lock and load, baby. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'MAGNIFICENT DESOLATION: WALKING ON THE MOON 3D' (No rating, 40 minutes) Tom Hanks narrates this Imax film that tries to give moviegoers the virtual experience of being on the lunar surface. At times it comes close. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>*'MARCH OF THE PENGUINS' (G, 80 minutes) This sentimental but riveting documentary follows the one-year mating cycle of emperor penguins in Antarctica when they leave the ocean and march inland to breed and lay eggs. Narrated by Morgan Freeman, the film has no qualms about playing on our emotions. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MIRRORMASK' (PG, 101 minutes) This British film, directed by Dave McKean from a screenplay by Neil Gaiman, blends live action with computer-generated animation by the Jim Henson Company into a provocative, murky surrealism. The story follows the Freudian nightmare of a 15-year-old girl whose parents work in the circus; it's strictly for cultists. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*'OCCUPATION: DREAMLAND' (No rating, 79 minutes) In early 2004, eight members of the Army's 82nd Airborne Division allowed the directors Ian Olds and Garrett Scott to shadow them for six weeks in a rapidly destabilizing Fallujah. The resulting film is a respectful and determinedly nonpartisan portrait of regular guys -- the smart and the average, the blusterers and the introverts, the gung-ho and the conflicted -- all doing their best to carry out orders in an untenable situation. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'OLIVER TWIST' (PG-13, 130 minutes) Roman Polanski's take on Dickens's classic emphasizes the darkness and cruelty of Victorian society. Vigorous and precise, it is a vivid reminder of the novelist's power as both a storyteller and a social critic. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PRIZE WINNER OF DEFIANCE, OHIO' (PG-13, 99 minutes) Julianne Moore is radiant as Evelyn Ryan, the real-life 1950's Ohio housewife and mother of 10 who kept her family afloat on her winnings from television jingle contests. Jane Anderson wrote and directed this tribute in a wonderfully zany, off-center style. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'PROOF' (PG-13, 100 minutes) A terribly serious adaptation of David Auburn's prize-laden Broadway play, starring Gwyneth Paltrow as the daughter of a dead mathematician struggling to come to terms with both her father's legacy and her own troubled mind. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE RODNEES: WE MOD LIKE DAT!' (No rating, 73 minutes) Striving to be a mockumentary, ''The Rodnees: We Mod Like Dat!'' is a train wreck of a movie: messy, unfunny and unforgivably dull. The plot, such as it is, involves four young African American men from Brooklyn whose failure to succeed in hip-hop prompts them to reinvent themselves as a modern-day version of The Beatles. The film's rare sparks of surreal wit never come close to relieving its general listlessness and lack of organization. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'ROLL BOUNCE' (PG-13, 107 minutes) A drowsy comedy from Malcolm D. Lee about a handful of kids grooving and roller skating in the summer of 1978, ''Roll Bounce'' has heart and good vibes but little else to recommend it. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'SANTO DOMINGO BLUES' (No rating, 75 minutes, in Spanish) The story of the musical style known as bachata -- a guitar-based blues born in the brothels and dance halls of the Dominican Republic -- and of its most prominent singer and songwriter, Luis Vargas. The film shows the evolution of bachata, long reviled as the music of the poor, to the mainstream with the mass immigration of Dominicans to the United States in the 1980's. A lively, sexy, insightful documentary.(Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SEPARATE LIES' (R, 87 minutes) A hit-and-run accident near the country house of an imperious British lawyer (magnificently played by Tom Wilkinson) leads him into an ethical labyrinth that tests his moral mettle as well as that of his wife (Emily Watson) and her lover (Rupert Everett). (Holden)</p>
        <p>'SERENITY' (PG-13, 119 minutes) It probably isn't fair to Joss Whedon's ''Serenity'' to say that this unassuming science-fiction adventure is superior in almost every respect to George Lucas's aggressively more ambitious ''Star Wars: Episode III -- Revenge of the Sith.'' But who cares about fair when there is fun to be had? Scene for scene, ''Serenity'' is more engaging and certainly better written and acted than any of Mr. Lucas's recent screen entertainments. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE SQUID AND THE WHALE' (R, 88 minutes) Mining his own childhood, Noah Baumbach has put together an unsparing, funny portrait of a family in crisis and a young man trying to figure out his parents and himself. Superbly written and acted, especially by Laura Linney and Jeff Daniels as a pair of divorcing writers. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THUMBSUCKER' (R, 96 minutes) A better-than-usual coming-of-age story, via Sundance but without the usual sensationalism or condescension, and with some very fine performances, notably by Lou Pucci as a teenage boy with a childish habit. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'TIM BURTON'S CORPSE BRIDE' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A necrophiliac animation for the whole family about a melancholic boy, the girl he hopes to marry and the bodacious cadaver that accidentally comes between them. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'TOUCH THE SOUND' (No rating, 99 minutes) As Thomas Riedelsheimer's enlightening, mystical documentary follows the deaf Scottish percussionist Evelyn Glennie around the globe, it illustrates her understanding that sound is a physical sensation experienced throughout the body, as well as an auditory one. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'TRANSPORTER 2' (PG-13, 88 minutes) Ex-Special Forces operative Frank Martin (Jason Statham), the blank-faced professional driver with more tricks -- and lives -- than James Bond, is back in this shallow, but never dull, sequel to ''The Transporter.'' This time, he's in Miami and will do whatever it takes to save the life of a boy who's been kidnapped and injected with a deadly virus. (Laura Kern)</p>
        <p>* '2046' (R, 129 minutes) An ecstatically beautiful story in which time is marked not by the hands of a clock, but by the women who pass through one man's life, ''2046'' is the eighth feature film from the Hong Kong director Wong Kar-wai and the long-awaited follow-up to his art-house favorite ''In the Mood for Love.'' A film about longing, loss and the delicate curve of a woman's back, it is also an unqualified triumph. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'AN UNFINISHED LIFE' (PG-13, 108 minutes) This contemporary Western starring Robert Redford, Jennifer Lopez and Morgan Freeman is a solemn, sentimental bore that suffocates in its own predictability and watered-down psychobabble. All three stars recycle stereotypes they've played before. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WALLACE AND GROMIT: THE CURSE OF THE WERE-RABBIT' (G, 85 minutes) The stop-motion pooch and his cheese-loving master, back again at feature length. Silly and sublime. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WEDDING CRASHERS' (R, 113 minutes) A wink-wink, nudge-nudge Trojan horse of a story, this amiably raunchy sex comedy pivots on two Lotharios persuasively inhabited by Owen Wilson and Vince Vaughn. They love the ladies but really and truly, cross their cheating hearts, just want a nice girl to call wife. Credited to the screenwriters Steve Faber and Bob Fisher. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>FILM SERIES</p>
        <p>AFTER WAR (Through Oct. 23) The Japan Society is commemorating the 60th anniversary of the end of World War II with this series of works about wartime and its aftermath. This Sunday's feature is ''Out of This World'' (''Kono yo no sotoe -- Club shinchugun''), Junji Sakamoto's 2003 film about five young postwar jazz musicians grudgingly playing at American military clubs. 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212)832-1155; $10.(Gates)</p>
        <p>THE BEAUTY OF THE EVERYDAY: JAPAN'S SHOCHIKU COMPANY AT 110 (Through Oct. 20) The Film Society of Lincoln Center presents a 44-film retrospective honoring Shochiku, the Japanese film studio. Films to be shown this weekend include ''Late Spring'' (1949), Yasujiro Ozu's tale of a father who wants his daughter to marry; ''Scandal'' (1950), Akira Kurosawa's drama about a singer falsely accused of an affair; and Kiju Yoshida's new wave classic ''Love Affair at Akitsu Spa'' (1962), about a terminally ill student and an innkeeper's daughter. Walter Reade Theater, 160 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212)875-5601; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>CALL FOR CHANGE: THIRD WORLD NEWSREEL (Through Sunday) BAMcinématek presents a weekend of documentaries about social issues. Films include ''The Healing Passage'' (2004), about the African diaspora; ''The People Are Rising'' (''El Pueblo se Levanta'') (1971), about Puerto Rican activism in East Harlem; and several programs of shorts. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718)636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FOREVER GARBO: A RETROSPECTIVE (Through Dec. 17) The American-Scandinavian Foundation's program honoring Greta Garbo's centennial continues tomorrow with ''Flesh and the Devil'' (1927), about a ruthless temptress and the man whose life she seems destined to ruin (John Gilbert), and on Wednesday with ''Love'' (1927), a silent version of ''Anna Karenina,'' with Gilbert as Vronsky. Scandinavia House, 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212)879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANÇOIS TRUFFAUT (Through Nov. 27). The IFC Center's Weekend Classics program is presenting a dozen Truffaut features and two shorts. This weekend's film, to be screened at noon, today through Monday, is ''Stolen Kisses'' (1968), about a soldier's post-discharge adventures. To be shown with the short ''Antoine and Colette'' (1962). At 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212)924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>NO VISA REQUIRED: FILMS FROM THE MIDDLE EAST (Through Nov. 19) The TriBeCa Film Institute and ArteEast are collaborating on a five-program screening of six films, followed by discussions with the filmmakers. The event continues tomorrow with ''The Prince'' (Tunisia, 2004), Mohammad Zran's love story about a flower vendor and a beautiful bank manager. Cantor Film Center, New York University, 36 East Eighth Street, East Village, (212)941-3890; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>REPERTORY NIGHTS (Through Nov. 6) The Museum of the Moving Image continues its annual film series today, tomorrow and Sunday with Akira Kurosawa's 1954 classic ''The Seven Samurai,'' starring Toshiro Mifune. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718)784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SOME LIKE IT WILDER: THE COMPLETE BILLY WILDER (Through Nov. 13) The Museum of the Moving Image is sponsoring a 26-film retrospective of Wilder, the Austrian-born director and writer who gave the world ''Sunset Boulevard'' and ''Double Indemnity.'' This weekend's features are ''Love in the Afternoon'' (1957), starring Audrey Hepburn and Gary Cooper as May-December lovers; ''Sabrina'' (1954), in which Hepburn is courted by both William Holden and Humphrey Bogart; and ''Avanti!'' (1972), with Jack Lemmon as a staid businessman who finds love in Italy. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718)784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>BECK (Tonight) Back to retro-ironic rock form after a while spent making sincere antifolk music, the self-aware soulman Beck Hanson aims to reclaim his mid-1990's role as pop's forward- and backward-looking prince of pastiche. At 6, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 279-7740 ; $42. (Laura Sinagra)</p>
        <p>DEAD CAN DANCE (Tomorrow) Mixing elements of Western medieval music, world beat and synth-rock's magisterial sweep, this theatrical band, fronted by the singer Lisa Gerrard, obliges its fans with its first tour in 10 years. 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212)247-4777; $34.50 to $59.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FALL OUT BOY, MOTION CITY SOUNDTRACK (Tuesday) What saves the slick emo pop-metal band Fall Out Boy from sounding like all the rest is a large dose of self-deprecation in its sing-along choruses. The pop-punk Motion City Soundtrack is influenced by the keyboard punctuations of early Weezer. 6 p.m., Roseland Ballroom, 239 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212)777-6800 ; $25. (sold out) (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FOUR TET (Monday) Making laptop music under the name Four Tet, the Londoner Kieran Hebden conjures atmospheric jazztronica that can sound like a noisy pastiche of classic rock bits or take on a more hip-hop informed art-rock groove. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $16 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>GHOSTFACE (Sunday) The Wu-Tang Clan's jittery, wildly inventive Ghostface Killah raps with both short-fused intensity and narrative nuance; his hyperventilated flow is full of digressions that reward close listening. Recently he's been matching his paranoid clown rapping to the nostalgic soul beats of Pete Rock. The Canadian rappers Swollen Members open. 8 p.m., B.B. King's Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212)997-4144; $22 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>PHILIP GLASS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Performing ''Orion,'' commissioned for the 2004 summer Olympics, Philip Glass plays keyboards at the center of a changing array of composition collaborators and guest musicians, including Mark Atkins on didgeridoo, Wu Man on stringed pipa and Foday Musa Suso on kora. 7:30, BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, (718)636-4100; $20 to $60. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JETHRO TULL (Tomorrow) Ian Anderson is still standing on one leg and growling through his flute as he leads Jethro Tull through his eccentric merger of hard rock, Celtic tunes, jazz and Bach. 7:30 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $40 to $80. . (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DANIEL LANOIS AND TORTOISE (Tonight)For this tour, the producer and roots-pop musician Daniel Lanois, whose recent music is contemplative, with pedal steel guitar, will be backed by the Chicago post-rock band Tortoise. The group, which has recently been working with the indie-folk chameleon Will Oldham, will also play its own set. Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212)777-6800; $22.50 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LYRICS BORN, THE PERCEPTIONISTS (Tomorrow) Lyrics Born is a Bay Area rapper who continues to fight the good fight with backpack-rap beats and smart wordplay. The Perceptionists do the same, with the politically outspoken Mr. Lif rapping against fascism with lithe candor. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $16 in advance, $18. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>MARIZA (Tonight) Mariza, who was born in Mozambique but grew up in Portugal, is one of the rising stars of fado, the Portuguese cafe music that sets haunted songs about fate and destiny to the pristine picking of the Portuguese guitar. She wrings emotion from the songs, with or without amplification. 8, Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $20 to $69. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>MESHUGGAH, GOD FORBID, THE HAUNTED (Tonight) The Swedish band Meshuggah barrels through songs characterized by intricate rhythms and apocalyptic rumble, over which the members spew angry, guttural, prelingual vocals. The like-minded God Forbid and the Haunted open. 6 p.m., B.B. King's Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, (212)997-4144; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>MY CHEMICAL ROMANCE (Thursday) The popular My Chemical Romance plays goth pop with metallic guitars and histrionic riffs that aim to engage every football player's inner theater-geek. Alkaline Trio's drummer and bandleader, Mike Skiba, continues to add 80's brood-pop wrinkles to his straightforward pop punk. 7 p.m., Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201)935-3900; $17.99 to $23. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>NADA SURF, SHIVAREE (Tonight) These Brooklyn alt-rockers tumbled into obscurity after a mid-90's hit, then re-emerged in 2002 with a sweet new style: wistful indie rock that squints nostalgically at imagined childhood bliss through a snowy pane. Shivaree plays loungey pop with archness. 8, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $18 in advance, $20 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>OLIVIA NEWTON-JOHN (Tuesday) This clear-voiced Australian songbird's got lots of hits from her dreamy faux-country phase in the early 70's (''Have You Never Been Mellow''), her faux-ingénue turn in ''Grease'' and her aerobic ''Physical'' era, but Ms. Newton-John's battles with cancer and other struggles ushered in a 90's round of un-faux new-age questing. Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street; ticketmaster.com or (212)307-7171; $44.50 to 59.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE NEW PORNOGRAPHERS, DESTROYER (Wednesday and Thursday) This revved-up Vancouver outfit's tight power-pop grandeur builds with a sort of time-release tension, until the voice of Neko Case cuts through like a triumphant skywriter. Ms. Case has not appeared at the band's recent shows in town, but she'll be here this time. New Pornographer co-songwriter Dan Bejar's band, the relentlessly quirky Destroyer, opens the show. 7:30 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212)353-1600; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>NICKEL CREEK (Tonight) This emo-bluegrass trio, which once covered a Pavement song, is at its best when the thin-voiced Chris Thile hands over the microphone to the fiddler and ethereal singer Sara Watkins. That is, it's better to sound like a wispier Allison Krauss than a simplistic Sufjan Stevens. 8, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street; ticketmaster.com or (212)307-7171, $24. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE RAVEONETTES, RADIO 4 (Tonight) Clearing away the garage noise of its debut, the Danish duo the Raveonettes now strives for pure 60's pop classicism. Its latest material incorporates rock history, from girl groups to surf rock to punk, as well as historic rock in the form of cameos by Ronnie Spector, the Suicide keyboardist Martin Rev and the Velvet Underground drummer Maureen Tucker. The local neo post-punkers Radio 4 open. 8, Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718)387-0505; $16. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>IKE REILLY ASSASSINATION (Tomorrow) This St. Paul, Minn., rocker's visceral, outlandishly catchy tunes capture a certain kind of cockiness and bar clown wit that almost make the listener overlook its macho nudges and winks. Mr. Reilly and his band tear it up live. Shadow Box and Catfish Haven will open. 9:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212)260-4700; $10. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JONATHAN RICHMAN, VIC CHESNUTT (Wednesday) Recent albums haven't added much to the whimsically neurotic rock 'n' roll live wire Jonathan Richman's stream-of-consciousness classics, but live, he remains a goofy joy. Recent material by the Southern Gothic storyteller Vic Chesnutt leans to his darker side. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $15. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SIX ORGANS OF ADMITTANCE (Tonight) The guitarist Ben Chasny plays exploratory noise-rock that draws on rootsy weirdness and a kind of chime and drone that suggest a global search for transcendence. 11:30 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212)260-4700; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SONS AND DAUGHTERS (Tomorrow) These gloomy Scots play folk-rock with edgy pessimism that reminds us, as if we could forget, that life in the gray North isn't all delicate, Belle and Sebastian-style reverie. 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718)599-5103; $12. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>BRUCE SPRINGSTEEN (Sunday) The Boss made ''The Rising'' after the twin towers fell, beating the novelist Jonathan Safran Foer to the notion of reverse-collapse by four years. Mr. Springsteen's spare ''Devils and Dust'' (Sony) charts the way back down, meditating with other soul-searchers at the crossroads of humanism and religion. 7:30 p.m., Nassau Coliseum, Uniondale, N.Y., (631)888-9000; $56.50 to $86.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>STEW (Monday) This Los Angeles pop craftsman writes songs that slip just enough bitters into the 70's lite rock cocktail to make it subversive. His faux-big production on disc isn't required live, because his songs are cabaret to the core. And aside from chuckling at his own asides, he is a consummate performer. This show is evidently of a piece with performances on the following two Tuesdays. 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8770; $20 per show, $50 for all three shows only at Joe's Pub's box office. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SUFJAN STEVENS (Tonight) This indie folk singer-songwriter and banjoist is imbued with a Copland-esque musical vision and an expansive narcissism reminiscent of Walt Whitman's, though his lyrics can overreach and his compositions veer into the folksily baroque. 8:30 and 10:30, Peter Norton Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212)864-5400; $21. (sold out) (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TURBONEGRO (Tuesday) Making its mark in the late 90's by posing as a flamboyantly gay metal band, the hard-rocking Norwegians of Turbonegro have worn out their shtick. They still bring the riffs, but a recent song, ''All My Friends Are Dead,'' might sum up their ideas as they drift into self-parody. 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212)353-1600; $20 in advance, $23 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>U2, KEANE (Tonight, and tomorrow, Monday and Tuesday nights) After 2000's thrilling ''All That You Can't Leave Behind'' (Interscope), ''How to Dismantle an Atomic Bomb'' (Interscope) and the ''Vertigo'' tour itself focus on what humans can live without: namely, intercontinental ballistic missiles and, evidently, some of U2's more shopworn live staples. Hence the resurrection of decades-old rarities like ''Electric Co.'' Keane is a piano-drums-vocals band that piles on hooky melodic flourishes. 8, Madison Square Garden, (212)465-6741; $54 to $169.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>WACO BROTHERS BLOODSHOT REVUE (Wednesday) Jon Langford of the Mekons indulges his country side even more strongly in the Waco Brothers, where he trades off lead vocals with Dean Schlabowske and ricochets between revolution and beer-soaked self-pity while letting his electric guitar blare. The Mekons' Sally Timms joins the bill. 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201)653-1703; $12. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>WARLOCKS (Thursday) With a deep affection for 60's downtown drug rock, especially the Velvet Underground, this band creates a heavy vibe while also making forays into free-form psychedelia. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212)533-2111; $15. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>MAUDE MAGGART (Tonight and tomorrow night) The singer, accompanied by piano and violin, applies her singular voice, a hybrid of light opera and 1930's torch, to the early songs of Irving Berlin. 9 and 11:30, Oak Room, Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212)419-9331; $50, with a $20 minimum; $50 prix fixe dinner required at the early shows. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>JOHN AND BUCKY PIZZARELLI (Tonight and tomorrow night) The musical conversation between a father and son, both superb guitarists, makes for a warm-hearted generational dialogue. 8:30 and 11, Feinstein's at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212)339-4095; $60, with a $40 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Tomorrow) Cool, funny, swinging and indestructible, this 75-year-old singer and sometime actress exemplifies old-time hip in its most generous incarnation. 7 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212)265-8133; $25, with a $12 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'SINGING ASTAIRE' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The smart, airy revue that pays tribute to Fred Astaire, featuring Eric Comstock, Hilary Cole and Christopher Gines, has returned to Birdland. 5:30 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212)581-3080; $30, with a $10 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>*ELAINE STRITCH (Tonight and tomorrow night, and Tuesday through Thursday nights) In a courageous and successful leap into the unknown, Ms. Stritch makes her cabaret debut at 80. Dispensing with her theatrical signature numbers, she weaves 16 songs new to her repertory into a funny running monologue of her adventures in and out of show business. 8:45, Cafe Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212)744-1600; $125 tonight and tomorrow, $105 Tuesday through Thursday, through Oct. 29 (all shows sold out). (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>*AACM 40TH-ANNIVERSARY CONCERT (Tonight) The Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians, an influential avant-garde collective, continues its yearlong anniversary celebration with a concert featuring a founding member, Roscoe Mitchell, on saxophones, and a next-generation inheritor, Reggie Nicholson, on percussion; each musician will perform in a solo setting, and as the leader of a trio. 8, the Community Church of New York, 40 East 35th Street, Manhattan, (212)683-4988, aacm-newyork.org; $20. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>ALL NITE SOUL (Sunday) The jazz Mass at St. Peter's is a New York tradition, and this year's installment pulls no punches; the lineup includes musicians like the trumpeters Ray Vega and Marcus Printup, and culminates in the Clark Terry Big Band, which kicked off the event some 35 years ago. 5 p.m., St. Peter's Lutheran Church, 619 Lexington Avenue, at 54th Street, Manhattan, (212)935-2200; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*MULATU ASTATKE AND THE EITHER/ORCHESTRA (Thursday) Mr. Astatke is best recognized these days for his music's prominent place in the Jim Jarmusch film ''Broken Flowers''; here, he'll perform his dreamy brand of Ethiopian jazz backed by the Either/Orchestra, which has done more than any other stateside ensemble to broaden this music's base. 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8778; cover, $25, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ANDY BEY (Tomorrow) Intimacy is a hallmark of Mr. Bey's vocal style, which alternates between a burnished falsetto and an earthy baritone; here he inhabits the most intimate setting imaginable, backed only by the guitarist Peter Meyers. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $15; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILL CHARLAP TRIO (Through Oct. 16) Bright and breezy yet unfailingly precise, Mr. Charlap, the pianist, has come to exemplify jazz's modern mainstream. So has his working trio, which keeps a Tin Pan Alley repertory percolating in the present tense. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212)255-4037; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>A DON CHERRY CELEBRATION (Through Oct. 23) This three-week festival, which commemorates the free-jazz trumpeter Don Cherry, assembles a roll call of improvisers who claim his influence. Highlights in the coming week include ensembles led by the tuba player Bob Stewart and the tenor saxophonist Dewey Redman (tonight), and the multi-instrumentalist Peter Apfelbaum (tomorrow night). 8 and 10, the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELDAR (Tuesday through next Friday) Eldar Djangirov, a teenage piano prodigy from Kyrgyzstan, has elicited comparisons to the great Art Tatum; he will surely headline his second New York club residency with panache. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212)475-8592; cover, $25 at tables, with a $5 minimum, or $15 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ELLERY ESKELIN TRIO (Monday) Mr. Eskelin is a tenor saxophonist known for gruff abandon; his longtime band with the accordionist Andrea Parkins and the drummer Jim Black handles abstraction as well as groove. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FIELDWORK (Tuesday and Wednesday) This collaborative trio throws down a gauntlet of jagged melodies and asymmetrical rhythmic forms; the heart of the group's sound is an ever-shifting rapport between the pianist Vijay Iyer, the saxophonist Steve Lehman and the drummer Tyshawn Sorey. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GOLD SOUNDS (Tonight) Pavement, the quintessential low-fi indie-rock band, gets an unlikely jazz makeover from the saxophonist James Carter, the pianist and organist Cyrus Chestnut, the bassist Reginald Veal and the drummer Ali Jackson; the band comes celebrating a jaunty album on the Brown Brothers label. 9:30, Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212)539-8778; cover, $20, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHARLIE HADEN'S LIBERATION MUSIC ORCHESTRA (Through Sunday) Mr. Haden, the bassist, formed this large ensemble with the pianist and composer Carla Bley some 35 years ago; its current incarnation, as documented on the slyly subversive album ''Not in Our Name'' (Verve), is stocked with serious younger musicians like the alto saxophonist Miguel Zenon. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212)475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, with a $5 minimum, or $20 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOEL HARRISON'S STARFISH PARADE (Tuesday) Mr. Harrison is a guitarist whose singing and songwriting lean on American roots traditions; here he previews material from an album called ''Harrison on Harrison'' (High Note), with an ensemble consisting of violin, pocket trumpet, accordion, bass and drums. 9 to 10:30 p.m., Koze Lounge, 676 Fifth Avenue, at 20th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)832-8282; cover, $7. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*BILLY HART QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Hart, a loose but focused drummer with a highly accomplished résumé, fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212)576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HAYES/HICKS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) The drummer Louis Hayes and the pianist John Hicks share a deep firsthand knowledge of post-bop tradition; the other half of their band consists of Abraham Burton, saxophonist, and Gerald Cannon, bassist. 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212)255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>*ROY HAYNES FOUNTAIN OF YOUTH BAND (Wednesday through Oct. 16) The redoubtable drummer Roy Haynes turned 80 this year, although you'd never guess it by his playing; his edgy post-bop ensemble features musicians many years his junior, like the alto saxophonist Jaleel Shaw. 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212)582-2121; cover, $30 and $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HEBERT'S BYZANTINE MONKEY QUARTET (Tonight) This progressive ensemble features the original music and bass playing of Mr. Hebert, along with the contributions of Michael Attias, saxophonist, and Russ Lossing, pianist. 9, Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212)989-9319; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARI HOENIG AND CHRIS POTTER (Tuesday) A promising duet performance by two of the sharpest musicians in the modern mainstream: Mr. Potter, a saxophonist, and Mr. Hoenig, a drummer. 7 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MILT JACKSON TRIBUTE BAND (Tonight and tomorrow night) Milt Jackson, who died in 1999, was one of the top two or three vibraphonists in the history of jazz; here, as on the new album ''Rev-elation'' (Sharp Nine), he is feted by the mallet virtuoso Joe Locke, along with the pianist Mike LeDonne, the bassist Bob Cranshaw and the drummer Mickey Roker. 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212)885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHRIS LIGHTCAP QUINTET (Wednesday) This sleek ensemble uses compositional forms as a springboard for open exploration; Mr. Lightcap, a bassist, has powerfully creative cohorts in the tenor saxophonists Mark Turner and Tony Malaby, the keyboardist Craig Taborn and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. 7:30 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY'S PALOMA RECIO (Wednesday ) Mr. Malaby, a versatile and increasingly prominent tenor saxophonist, leads a progressive ensemble with a Spanish tinge; his fellow travelers are Michael Rodriguez, trumpeter; Ben Monder, guitarist; Eivind Opsvik, bassist; and Rodney Green, drummer. 10 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN TRINITY (Tuesday through Oct. 16) This piano trio deserves the high-minded handle; its members are the soulful pianist Cyrus Chestnut, the erudite bassist George Mraz and the clean, crisp drummer Lewis Nash. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 p.m. set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, Jazz at Lincoln Center, (212)258-9595. Cover: $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DELFEAYO MARSALIS QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Marsalis, a resoundingly skillful trombonist and composer, leads a polished post-bop ensemble with Donald Harrison on saxophone, Mulgrew Miller on piano, Delbert Felix on bass and Ralph Peterson on drums. (Cyrus Chestnut replaces Mr. Miller tomorrow night only.) 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, 60th Street and Broadway, Jazz at Lincoln Center, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY MARTIN AND DAVE BURRELL (Tonight) The drummer best known as the second surname in Medeski Martin and Wood joins forces with the venerable avant-garde pianist Dave Burrell for an unscripted and potentially intriguing dialogue. 8, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212)358-7501; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN MCNEIL'S INSOMNIA BAND (Tomorrow) Mr. McNeil, a trumpeter and confirmed insomniac, recently released a haunting album called ''Sleep Won't Come'' (OmniTone); he expands on that theme with this quintet. 9 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212)989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>T.S. MONK (Wednesday through Oct. 15) Thelonious Monk Jr. is a charismatic drummer and bandleader whose taste is a bit less idiosyncratic than his father's; he leads a polished hard-bop band. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212)581-3080; music charge, $40, with a $10 minimum at the tables, no minimum at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORGANISSIMO (Sunday) This Michigan-based organ trio resurrects the sound of 1960's soul jazz but with a touch less grit and grease; the members appear here in support of a likeable new album, ''This is the Place'' (Big O). 10:45 p.m., Kenny's Castaways, 157 Bleecker Street, West Village, (212)979-9762; call for cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GRETCHEN PARLATO GROUP (Tonight) Ms. Parlato is a cosmopolitan vocalist who keeps unfailingly good company. The guitarist Lionel Loueke, the pianist Aaron Parks and the drummer Kendrick Scott make up her working band and share her ties to the trumpeter and composer Terence Blanchard. 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, South Village, (212)242-1063; cover, $12; members, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MATT PAVOLKA QUARTET (Thursday) Mr. Pavolka, a bassist, leads a group of free-thinking but lyrical players: Pete Rende on keyboards, Ted Poor on drums, and Ben Monder on guitar. In the following set, Mr. Monder will lead a group of his own. 8 p.m., Barbes, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718)965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARIO PAVONE SEPTET (Tonight) Mr. Pavone, a bassist with an expansive worldview, leads a group that includes Joe Magnarelli, trumpeter; Mike DiRubbo, alto saxophonist; Lauren Sevian, baritone saxophonist; Peter McEachern, trombonist; Peter Madsen, Fender Rhodes; and Gerald Cleaver, drummer. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PHAROAH SANDERS QUARTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Sanders, one of the most significant survivors of 1960's free jazz, has never stopped imbuing his performances with the tone of a spiritual quest; he has worthy acolytes in the pianist William Henderson, the bassist Ugonna Okegwo and the drummer Adam Cruz. 8 and 10 tonight and Sunday night, with an additional 11:30 show tonight; 8:15, 10 and 11:30 p.m. tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212)582-2121; cover, $30 and $32.50, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GEORGE SCHULLER'S CIRCLE WIDE (Wednesday) Mr. Schuller, a drummer, leads a group inspired by the spacious and mysterious acoustic fusion of Miles Davis, circa 1968; the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin and the guitarist Brad Shepik apply an appropriate push and pull. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212)929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STRYKER/SLAGLE BAND (Tomorrow and Sunday) The guitarist Dave Stryker and the saxophonist Steve Slagle have worked together in hard-driving settings since as far back as the mid-1980's; their rhythm section here consists of the eminently capable Ed Howard and Victor Lewis, on bass and drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212)576-2232; cover, $20 and $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ASSIF TSAHAR/JIM BLACK/MAT MANERI (Tuesday) On the recent album ''Jam'' (Hopscotch), this trio of improvisers -- Mr. Tsahar, a saxophonist; Mr. Maneri, a violinist; and Mr. Black, a drummer -- address open spaces with shifting timbres. They are joined here by the poet Steve Dalachinsky and the pianist Matthew Shipp. 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212)358-7501; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ARIADNE AUF NAXOS' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Admirers of Deborah Voigt may be disappointed that she is not singing her signature role in the Metropolitan Opera's revival of Strauss's ''Ariadne auf Naxos,'' but the strong Lithuanian mezzo-turned-soprano Violeta Urmana does not disappoint. And the cast, overall, is exceptional, especially the brilliant coloratura soprano Diana Damrau as Zerbinetta, and the radiant mezzo-soprano Susan Graham as the Composer. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $26 to $220. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'ARIANE ET BARBE-BLEUE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) Even before the new production opens, the New York City Opera deserves thanks from opera buffs for presenting this rarity by Paul Dukas, best known as the composer of ''The Sorcerer's Apprentice.'' Dukas's delightful opera tells the story of Bluebeard from a woman's point of view. Renate Behle, in her company debut, sings Ariane. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday) Pity a small opera company: it only gets critical attention when it does something unusual, yet its audiences tend to like the same fare as everyone else. Which is to say that ''La Bohème'' at the 204-seat Dicapo Opera will get few reviews, but remains a company standby and a crowd favorite. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Dicapo Opera, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212)288-9438; $47.50. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA CENERENTOLA' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Very few voice connoisseurs question the amazing gifts of the molten-voiced, temperamental Russian mezzo-soprano Olga Borodina. But the intense Ms. Borodina as a comic Rossini heroine? That may sound like a stretch. Actually, Ms. Borodina showed wonderful comic instincts in Rossini's ''Italiana in Algeri'' a couple seasons back, and her coloratura technique was impressive. So expect good things when she takes on Rossini's ''Cenerentola'' in a revival of Cesare Lievi's imaginative production. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $26 to $220. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'FALSTAFF' (Wednesday) The attention to detail that characterizes this production is truly unusual: it's well cast, well acted and well conducted by a masterly James Levine. It also features the reigning Falstaff of our day, Bryn Terfel, who is matched note for note by the fabulous Stephanie Blythe as Mistress Quickly -- she almost steals the show. 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000. $26 to $175. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MADAMA BUTTERFLY' (Tomorrow) Mark Lamos's production of Puccini's classic is one of New York City Opera's best. And there's a lot else to like here, from the intermittently good conducting of Ari Pelto to Jake Gardner's Sharpless. Shu-Ying Li, who was magnificent in the title role when the Dicapo Opera presented all three versions of the opera last year, has taken it over here, evidently with considerable success. 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'MANON' (Tonight) Jean-Pierre Ponnelle's production of this Massenet tragedy, absent from the Metropolitan Opera since 2001, returns with Renée Fleming as the conflicted Manon, and Marcelo Álvarez as a passionate and unusually well-rounded des Grieux. Both are in fine voice, and have the support of a well-balanced cast, as well as vibrant conducting by Jésus López-Cobos. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212)362-6000; $36 to $205. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'TOSCA' (Sunday and Thursday) Franco Zeffirelli's production of ''Tosca'' at the Metropolitan Opera may offer sumptuous and gargantuan realism, but Mark Lamos's striking production at the New York City Opera offers spare and contemporary theatricality. It returns to the repertory with the soprano Carla Thelen Hanson in her company debut as Tosca, and John DeMain conducting. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212)721-6500; $16 to $110. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BOSTON SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA (Monday) You can almost see the fun James Levine is having, planning orchestral seasons, and this well-stuffed program is a prime example of a fertile imagination at play: Elliott Carter's ''Three Illusions,'' in its New York premiere; Lukas Foss's masterwork ''Time Cycle,'' with Dawn Upshaw as vocalist; Ives's ''Three Places in New England''; and Gershwin's Piano Concerto in F, with Jean-Yves Thibaudet. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $30 to $105. (James R. Oestreich)</p>
        <p>COMPOSER PORTRAITS (Tonight) George Antheil is the subject of the current installment of this important and enlightening series. Daniel Spalding will conduct the Philadelphia Virtuosi Chamber Orchestra, and Guy Livingston will be the soloist in the Piano Concerto No.2, the centerpiece of a program that also includes the Serenade No.2 and ''Dreams Ballet.'' 8 p.m., Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212)854-7799; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>GUARNERI STRING QUARTET (Tomorrow). You have to admire the group's stick-to-itiveness, if not always its freshness and polish. Maybe the young violist Scott St. John will inject new energy into Mozart's Quintet in C (K. 515). 8 p.m., Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue and 82nd Street, (212)570-3949; $50. (Oestreich)</p>
        <p>JUILLIARD SYMPHONY (Tuesday) The country's most famous conservatory is celebrating its centenary, and part of its celebration is this performance by the student orchestra, which has proved a superb group in past encounters. The program includes works by Webern, Rautavaara and Schubert, with Dennis Russell Davies conducting. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212)247-7800; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>JUPITER SYMPHONY CHAMBER PLAYERS (Monday) The pianist Ilya Itin and the violinist Dmitri Berlinsky are the guests of this feisty ensemble, which in the spirit of its founder, Jens Nygaard, offers programs that combine oddities and major works. This time the fare includes Josef Myslivecek's Trio in G, Dvorak's Octet-Serenade (an arrangement of the Serenade for Strings, Op. 22) and the Brahms Trio in B. At 2 and 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Manhattan, (212)799-1259; $10 to $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'THE VIRGIL FOX LEGACY' (Tonight through Monday) With a variety of organists on hand, these performances and discussions at various churches in Manhattan honor the memory of the ultimate switched-on master of the instrument on the 25th anniversary of his death. Don't expect the obsequies to be subdued. Most tickets: $25. Information: (212)799-9300, (800)486-6628 or www.legacyconcerts.com. (Oestreich)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>MARIA ELENA ANAYA DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Ms. Anaya's ''Caracolas de un Mar de Fuego'' includes traditional flamenco and dance inspired by a poem by the 17th-century Mexican poet Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz. 7:30 p.m., La MaMa E.T.C., 74A East Fourth Street, East Village, (212)475-7710 or lamama.org; $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>BALLET AUSTIN (Tonight through Sunday) The company makes its New York City debut with a program of award-winning dances choreographed by its artistic director, Stephen Mills. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 2 and 7:30 p.m., the Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)242-0800; $38. (Erika Kinetz)</p>
        <p>DANCEOFF! (Tuesday and Wednesday) Ten modern-dance choreographers and companies, some famous and others not, have been chosen by Terry Dean Bartlett and Katie Workum for this showcase series. 8 and 10 p.m., P.S. 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212)352-3101 or ps122.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE THEATER ETC (Tomorrow) Thirty dancers dressed as angels will interact with 19th-century statuary in a free, combination two-hour performance and walking tour. Noon and 3 p.m. (Rain date, Sunday), Green-Wood Cemetery, 25th Street and Fifth Avenue, Greenwood Heights, Brooklyn, (718)788-7850 or dancetheatreetcetera.org (Dunning)</p>
        <p>EQUUS PROJECTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) JoAnna Mendl Shaw, who likes to pair dancers with horses and riders, choreographically gallops into a riding academy with ''Rules of Engagement,'' a collaboration with Janet Biggs, an artist and video creator, and Steve White, a composer. It is a multidisciplinary production involving dancing, a horse and rider and site-specific videos. 8 p.m., Claremont Riding Academy, 175 West 89th Street, Manhattan, (800)595-4849 or dancingwithhorses.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the door; students and ages 65+, $20 in advance; $25 at the door). (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>JORDAN FUCHS (Tonight through Sunday night) In ''The Almost and the Nearly,'' unusual seating arrangements intentionally limit the performance space, and the choreography tries to blur distinctions between presence and absence as dancers are drawn together and apart. 8:30; Sunday at 7:30 p.m. Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212)674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>GINA GIBNEY DANCE (Thursday) A seasoned, subtle modern-dance choreographer who gives equal opportunity to her brain and heart, Ms. Gibney will present a new multimedia work, ''unbounded,'' that explores the tensions between clinging to the known and reaching for the unknowable. 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212)674-8194; $15 or T.D.F. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOKO HIGASHINO AND HIROAKI UMEDA (Tonight and tomorrow night) Two young Japanese dancers create their own surreal worlds. In ''Alarm! -- zero hour edition,'' Ms. Higashino suggests the unpredictability of a society under the siege of change. Strips of light keep appearing and vanishing, guiding and abandoning Mr. Umeda in ''while going to a condition.'' 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; students and 65+, $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>BEBE MILLER COMPANY (Wednesday and Thursday) Ms. Miller, in her company's 20th anniversary, is the latest dance artist to take advantage of the impressive technological facilities at Dance Theater Workshop. In her new ''Landing/Place,'' Ms. Miller will integrate digital motion-capture technology, animation and video projections into a dance about traveling in Eritrea. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)924-0077; $25. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHARLES MOORE DANCE THEATER (Tonight) A company featuring dances of Africa and the Caribbean performed with historical respect and contemporary elation offers its new ''Strength of the Spirit.'' 8, Peter Norton Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212)864-5400 or symphonyspace.org; $25; children, students and ages 65+, $20.(Anderson)</p>
        <p>PATRICIA NICHOLSON: 'DANCE WORDS SPEAK PEACE' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Nicholson believes in the power of socially conscious art to nurture weary souls. The program also includes choreography by KJ Holmes. 7:30, Clemente Soto Vélez, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212)696-6681 or visionfestival.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEXT WAVE FESTIVAL: NATIONAL BALLET OF CHINA (Tuesday through Thursday) The company will perform ''Raise the Red Lantern,'' which tells the story of a young concubine in 1920's China with a fusion of ballet, modern dance and traditional Chinese dance, set to music performed on Western and Chinese instruments and directed by Zhang Yimou, the noted film director. 7:30 p.m., BAM Howard Gilman Opera House, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718)636-4100; $20 to $70. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>ODC/SAN FRANCISCO (Tuesday through Thursday) This program by two of this San Francisco-based company's resident choreographers includes dances by Brenda Way, among them one inspired by global warming, and by KT Nelson. 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212)242-0800 or joyce.org; $38. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>REVERB FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow night) A new organization that seeks to brings together works derived from different cultural backgrounds and aesthetic perspectives offers its first programs. The participating choreographers are Ayako Kurakake, Ofelia Loret de Mola, Kate Hutter, Lane Gifford, Nelly van Bommel and Sidra Bell. 8, Joan Weill Center for Dance, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)280-3468 or (914)630-4505; $15; students, $12. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>HENNING RUBSAM'S SENSEDANCE (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Rubsam tends to mix ballet, modern dance and a kind of sunny optimism in dances that often probe the special qualities in his performers. This program includes choreography set to music by Beata Moon, Beethoven, Brahms, Django Reinhardt and Ricardo Llorca, with the guest artists Melissa Morrissey and Ramon Thielen from Dance Theater of Harlem. 8 p.m., Baruch Performing Arts Center, 55 Lexington Avenue, at 25th Street, (646)312-4085; $22 and $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MALLIKA SARABHAI AND THE DARPANA PERFORMING GROUP (Wednesday and Thursday) In the edible-sounding ''Hot Talas Cool Rasas,'' the artists promise a bouquet of styles and ideas that form the panorama of contemporary dance in India. Wednesday at 7 p.m., Thursday at 8 p.m., Ailey Studios Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212)529 2347. Wednesday, $150; Thursday, $35 and students and 65+, $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>2005 D.U.M.B.O. DANCE FESTIVAL (Thursday) Last year's festival was a lot of fun, with companies and individuals who looked as if they had been chosen with a sense of personal taste, perhaps that of the festival director, Young Soon Kim, and dance in a huge variety of styles spilling out across a small, shining studio-theater. And it's all free. 7 p.m., White Wave's John Ryan Theater, 25 Jay Street, on the waterfront, Brooklyn, (718)855-8822 or whitewavedance.com. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>KRIOTA WILLBERG/DURA MATER (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Willberg has a wicked eye for the foibles of American dance, and she lets it rove, deliciously, in ''The Bentfootes,'' a beautifully costumed multimedia satire that tells the story of 200 years of dance by the fictitious Susan Bentfoote and her family of unerringly mediocre artists. 8, Dixon Place at University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side, (212)219-0736 or dixonplace.org; $10 to $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>AMERICAN FOLK ART MUSEUM: 'OBSESSIVE DRAWING,' through March 19. In the museum's first ''emerging talent'' show, one of the five artists selected is 83, lives in a home for the elderly in Pennsylvania and stopped painting two years ago because of failing eyesight. Overall, the work in the exhibition is abstract and spare, giving the problematic ''outsider'' category a new spin. 45 West 53rd Street, (212)265-1040. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'EXTREME TEXTILES,' through Oct. 30. Don't look for aesthetic pizazz in this intensely techy show of industrial fibers and fabrics, but don't rule it out. The show's raison d'être is solely use, but a lot of what's on view, in the first museum display of material made to function in extreme conditions, is visually exciting. 2 East 91st Street, (212)849-8400.(Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'RUSSIA!,' through Jan. 11. This survey of nine centuries of Russian art ranges from 13th-century religious icons to a smattering of 21st-century works, achieving its astounding effect without resorting to a single egg, or anything else, by Fabergé. It immerses us in two enormous, endlessly fascinating narratives: the history of painting and the history of Russia itself, forming a remarkable tribute to the endurance of the medium and the country, and the inescapable interconnectedness of art and life. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212)423-3600. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>*JAPAN SOCIETY: 'HIROSHI SUGIMOTO: HISTORY OF HISTORY,' through Feb. 19. A very personal, whimsical exhibition by this well-known Japanese photographer, who incorporates into his own work artifacts that he has collected over the years, particularly from East Asia and Japan. Mr. Sugimoto's reach is long, and his range is broad, from fossil stones to textiles to undersea dioramas to Japanese calligraphy to the trylon and perisphere (a mini-sculpture) that symbolized the New York World's Fair of 1939. It may not be all that enlightening, but as an artist's personal survey, it comes off. 333 East 47th Street, (212)832-1155. (Glueck).</p>
        <p>EL MUSEO DEL BARRIO: 'THE (S) FILES/THE SELECTED FILES 05,' through Jan. 29. The definition of what ''Latino art'' means is changing in a post-identity-politics time, and this modest biennial, drawn mostly from unsolicited proposals submitted by artists in the greater New York area, is an indicator of what that change looks like. 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, (212)831-7272. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF BIBLICAL ART: 'THE NEXT GENERATION: CONTEMPORARY EXPRESSIONS OF FAITH,' through Nov. 13. Works in this juried show of artists who belong to the organization Christians in the Visual Arts range from traditional paintings and sculptures to an interactive video and photo documentation of a shamanistic performance in the woods. Ambitious, optically captivating collages by Mary Fielding McCleary and Anita Breitenberg Naylor are among the few pieces that exceed familiar generic limitations. 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212)408-1500. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>QUEENS MUSEUM OF ART: 'DOWN THE GARDEN PATH: THE ARTIST'S GARDEN AFTER MODERNISM,' through Nov. 6. This big, messy and uneven show, still a thought-provoking one for patient and interested viewers, surveys how artists like Vito Acconci, Ian Hamilton Finlay, Mel Chin, Ghada Amer, Stan Douglas and many more have cultivated gardens in fantasy and in reality. Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, (718)592-9700.(Johnson)</p>
        <p>* STUDIO MUSEUM IN HARLEM: 'SCRATCH: 2004-2005 ARTISTS-IN-RESIDENCE: WILLIAM CORDOVA, MICHAEL QUEENLAND AND MARC ANDRE ROBINSON,' through Oct. 23 . Rap, religion, Minimalism and Malcolm X all figure in this intricate, multilayered show of work by the three young residents, organized by the museum's associate curator, Christine Y. Kim. 144 West 125th Street, (212)864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*WHITNEY MUSEUM: ROBERT SMITHSON, through Oct. 23. Who knows whether Smithson is the most influential American postwar artist, as this show claims. Consisting mostly of drawings, photographs and films (he didn't make that many sculptures, not ones that could fit into a museum, anyway), this is the first full-scale overview of him in the country. It is consequently dry but still compelling testimony to a great exuberance cut drastically short when Smithson died at 35 in a plane crash in 1973. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212)570-3600. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>*ADAM DANT: 'STANDING UNDER' An extraordinarily imaginative and skillful draftsman, Mr. Dant makes large pen-and-brush drawings of complex scenes populated by chunky little people, all viewed as if from below through a transparent ground or floor. Adam Baumgold, 74 East 79th Street, (212)861-7338, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>HENRY WOLF Organized by the photography critic Vince Aletti, this exhibition presents works by the extraordinarily suave art director, designer and photographer Henry Wolf (1925-2005). Examples of his designs for magazine covers and pictures by photographers that he commissioned are on view, but the most interesting part is the selection of Wolf's own noncommercial photographs, which are compelling for their ultramodern ways with light, multiple spaces, speed and glamour. Howard Greenberg, 41 East 57th Street, (212)334-0010, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'SALUTE TO THE 130TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE ART STUDENTS LEAGUE' No gallery in the city regularly offers better small group exhibitions of American modernism than Washburn. And its homage to the Art Students League made up of work by four illustrious students -- Louise Nevelson, Jackson Pollock, Mark Rothko and David Smith -- is a sterling example. The Washburn Gallery, 20 West 57th Street, 8th floor, (212)397-6780, through Oct. 29. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>DENNIS ADAMS: 'MAKE DOWN' This brainy political artist presents a video in which he uses film stills from the movie ''Battle of Algiers'' to wipe dark green makeup off his face and body. It's about terrorism, gender, masking and unmasking. Kent, 541 West 25th Street, (212)627-3680, through Oct. 16. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*DIANE ARBUS: 'OTHER FACES OTHER ROOMS' If think you are suffering from Diane Arbus fatigue, this exhibition of 49 photographs that have not been widely published or exhibited will surely refresh your interest. Robert Miller, 524 West 26th Street, (212)366-4774, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*TOM BURCKHARDT: 'FULL STOP'  A painter of eclectically layered abstractions has produced a surprising environmental installation: a slightly old-fashioned, fully equipped painter's studio made of brown corrugated cardboard and black paint. Caren Golden, 539 West 23rd Street, (212)727-8304, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>WOUTER DERUYTTER: 'CROW WARRIORS' You could almost mistake Mr. Deruytter's black-and-white, subtly erotic photographs of Crow Indian warriors in face paint, feathered headdresses and loin cloths, riding bareback horses, for 19th-century ethnographic documents. In fact, they depict contemporary Indians gathered for an annual re-enactment of the Battle of the Little Bighorn. Briggs Robinson, 527 West 29th Street, (212)560-9075, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>TOM HUCK: 'THE BLOODY BUCKET SERIES' Extra-large black-and-white woodcuts by this Missourian look like the works of a Northern Renaissance artist who time-traveled to 1960's California and became an underground comic book artist. His jam-packed compositions are gleefully obscene and violent without being too offensive, and the prints are technically impressive. David Krut, 526 West 26th Street, (212)255-3094, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'MUD' This exceptional four-artist show of small sculpture features lively, insouciant ceramics by the painter Joanne Greenbaum; crusty, off-white ceramics by Elliott Levine that look like ancient artifacts; cartoonish sculptures about modern machines by Aga Ousseinov; and rough, semiabstract sculptures in Styrofoam and papier mâché, alluding to landscapes and furniture, by Yuh-Shioh Wong. Dinter, 547 West 27th Street, (212)947-2818, through Oct. 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MONIQUE PRIETO AND LYNDA BENGLIS Ms. Prieto has, in effect, boarded over her abstract paintings with rough-hewn monolithic letters quoting Samuel Pepys's famous diary. Both the wordiness and the klunkiness are a bit familiar, but extracting Pepys's phrases, which are all deliberately disembodied in reference, can be strangely satisfying. In ''The Graces,'' Ms. Benglis continues to evoke figures by other means, in this case three shimmering stacks of vaselike forms made of heavily textured, lavender-tinted resin. The material is perfect for the process-oriented Ms. Benglis. Cheim &amp; Read, 547 West 25th Street, (212)242-7727, through Oct. 15. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>IAN BURNS Mr. Burns's amusing whirligigs, small motorized contraptions and a large sit-in piece that directs your gaze to a series of illuminated screens like shadow-puppet theaters are roughly made of wood, with outsiderlike ingenuity. His cheerfully satiric cartoon imagery addresses terrorism and the war in Iraq. Spencer Brownstone, 39 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212)334-3455, through Oct. 15. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Claire Fontaine Politically charged works by this French artist include a neon-light work that outlines the image of a hooded Iraqi prisoner and child; a neon sign in the gallery's front window that says in Arabic, ''Foreigners Everywhere''; and a tiny sculpture called ''In God We Trust'' in the form of a 25-cent coin with a fold-out box cutter secreted inside. Reena Spaulings, 371 Grand Street, SoHo, (212)477-5006, through Oct. 21. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MACCHINE NATURALI: 'ABSTRACT COLLAGES BY JOSEPH STELLA' The largest New York show in some time of Stella's elegant, understated collages, made from dirt-stained scraps of paper, can thoroughly rearrange your grasp of his sensibility and the history of American modernism. Peter Freeman Inc., 560 Broadway, at Prince Street, SoHo (212)966-5349, through Oct. 29. (Smith).</p>
        <p>'PAPER MUSEUMS: THE REPRODUCTIVE PRINT IN EUROPE, 1500-1800' From the early 16th century to the beginning of the 19th, prints that reproduced the original work of artists were the only means of acquainting a broad public with the creative endeavors of Dürer, Raphael, Rubens, Michelangelo and the like. This show displays the variety and vitality of such reproductive prints, and points up how they effectively circulated artists' works and ideas in Europe. Don't expect lots of pictorial splash here. Grey Art Gallery, New York University, 100 Washington Square East, Greenwich Village, (212)998-6780, through Dec. 3. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>*PHILIP-LORCA diCORCIA: 'LUCKY THIRTEEN' Strippers are hardly a new subject for fine-art photographers, but Mr. diCorcia's monumental portraits of pole dancers are far from routine. Each of the 13 glossy pictures depicts a scantily dressed -- in one case, nude -- female dancer practicing her art in a dark and empty club. All but one assume upside-down positions, as if posing for a Renaissance painter of angels and crucifixions, and the effect is more of spiritual and athletic austerity than of cheesy eroticism. PaceWildenstein, 534 West 25th Street, (212)929-7000, closing tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*KIM JONES: 'WAR PAINT' Kim Jones has been best known since the late 1970's for his appearances on the streets, in subways and in galleries as the walking sculpture called Mudman. This show is made up of wearable shirts and jackets with boxy, three-dimensional ink-and-acrylic paintings attached to the back, each painting a cross between a computer game and a battle plan. Pierogi, 177 North Ninth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718)599-2144, closing on Monday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*MARTIN McMURRAY: 'BLOODSHOT AND GLOWING' In a solo debut, small, fraught figurative paintings evoke some of the tragedies of American history and literature, and transcend a host of artistic influences with a flinty intensity. Jeff Bailey Gallery, 511 West 25th Street, Chelsea, (212)989-0156, closing tomorrow. (Smith).</p>
        <p>NATIONAL ACADEMY MUSEUM: JEAN HÉLION  Hélion's conversion, around 1940, from a suave, smartly synthetic mode of geometric abstraction to a like-minded figurative style doesn't put him in a league with great 20th-century apostates like Giacometti, Picabia or Guston. This meager show does not give a full account of his strengths or weaknesses, but is well worth a look. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212)369-4880, closing on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>*'Pop Politics Power' In this measured but intense three-artist show, Martha Rosler offers a continuation of her 1967-72 photomontage series ''Bringing the War Home''; Carolee Schneemann is represented by both a new film and by her mesmerizing 1965 ''Viet Flakes,'' in which a rush of grainy black-and-white war photographs looks like smoke billowing from a volcano; and Robert Boyd introduces two spooky videos about doomsday religious cults, past, present and (probably) future. LMAKprojects, 526 West 26th Street, No.310, Chelsea, (212)255-9707, closing tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Raqib Shaw: 'Garden of Earthly Delights' Labor-intensive and intensely active, Raqib Shaw's paintings look like X-rated, subaquatic hybrids of Hieronymous Bosch, Victorian fairy painting, Persian miniatures and Bollywood films of the Ramayana. Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, SoHo, (212)343-7300, closing tomorrow. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>*JANET SOBEL This self-taught, late-blooming artist introduced Jackson Pollock to his signature drip technique, playing Henri Rousseau to his Picasso. Here, her art veers between the semi-abstract works that Pollock saw in 1944 and folk-artish, happy-peasant landscapes (inspired by a Ukrainian childhood) in which inventively handled paint does most of the dancing. This stunning show reveals a wily, liberated artist whose closest European analogy may be Jean Dubuffet. DC Moore Gallery, 724 Fifth Avenue, near 57th Street, (212)247-1111, closing tomorrow. (Smith).</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM: 'REMOTE VIEWING' The vast information overload the world struggles with -- scientific theory, technological data, geopolitical facts, historical material and on and on -- is whipped into visual cosmologies by eight painters of widely different approaches and sensibilities. If the premise is fuzzy, the show has some sharp art. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212)570-3600, closing Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART AT ALTRIA: 'PAST PRESENCE: CHILDHOOD AND MEMORY' This modestly resonant show of works relating to juvenile experience presents a glass cabinet filled with 2,000 miniature white ceramic vessels by Charles LeDray; small, finely drawn, photo-based pictures of children by Peggy Preheim; and a politically suggestive chalkboard drawing by Gary Simmons. 120 Park Avenue, at 42nd Street, (917)663-2453, closing on Thursday. (Johnson)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
