<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sizing Up Judge Roberts</title>
    <meta content="23online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/23/technology/23online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1689289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Roberts, John G Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6DA143FF930A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sizing Up Judge Roberts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sizing Up Judge Roberts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dan Mitchell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE timing of President Bush's announcement Tuesday night that he would nominate John G. Roberts, a federal appeals court judge with a conservative record, to the Supreme Court left the print media a bit hamstrung (by design, some say). Deadline-pressured newspaper editors scrambled to publish (mostly) serviceable articles the next day.</p>
        <p>Online, the results were mixed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The timing of President Bush's nomination of John G. Roberts to the Supreme Court left newspaper editors scrambling to publish. Online, the results were mixed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE timing of President Bush's announcement Tuesday night that he would nominate John G. Roberts, a federal appeals court judge with a conservative record, to the Supreme Court left the print media a bit hamstrung (by design, some say). Deadline-pressured newspaper editors scrambled to publish (mostly) serviceable articles the next day.</p>
        <p>Online, the results were mixed.</p>
        <p>Forbes.com posted a report by 10 p.m. Daniel Fisher, a senior editor, pointed out that conservative doesn't always mean pro-business when it comes to Supreme Court justices. ''As corporate lawyers have learned to their chagrin under the generally conservative Rehnquist court, the justices farthest to the right -- Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas -- have refused to come to the aid of business if they can't find explicit authority in the Constitution,'' Mr. Fisher wrote.</p>
        <p>He didn't draw conclusions as to how Judge Roberts would rule on any particular issue, but he offered a useful framework for thinking about the pick as Congressional hearings begin.</p>
        <p>BusinessWeek Online, Bloomberg.com, MarketWatch.com and others quickly offered straightforward articles that at least touched on the business background of Judge Roberts. Bloomberg detailed his work representing Toyota and the cosmetics industry, as well as his recent rulings.</p>
        <p>Oddly, TheStreet.com chose not to cover the nomination at all.</p>
        <p>The technology news site CNET News.com also had no articles on how Judge Roberts might rule on technology issues (this despite the site's puzzling habit of running articles like ''Web reacts to Martha Stewart sentencing''), though a staff blogger, Paul Festa, wrote a short note about it.</p>
        <p>Wired News (wired.com), which closely covers the politics of technology, media and information, was silent on the nomination. (Both News.com and Wired News offer links to news wires.)</p>
        <p>As for blogs, they didn't seem to shed much light on his business background or judicial philosophy.</p>
        <p>Predictably, most political blogs instantly scattered to the left or the right to hurl ideological invective at one another. One exception was Wonkette (wonkette.com), where the main ideology is snark. The Washington-based blog spent most of Wednesday sticking needles into the inflated egos of everyone involved. Wonkette also cited polls showing how little the public knows about the Supreme Court. For example, only 9 percent of respondents could identify Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist, who has served 17 years. More people know Judge Wapner, who left ''The People's Court'' television series in 1993.</p>
        <p>FUEL FILTER -- A study released this month by the ecologist David Pimentel of Cornell University and the environmental engineer Tad W. Patzek of the University of California, Berkeley, determined that producing corn-based ethanol uses 29 percent more fuel than it generates. On Slate, the energy writer Robert Bryce said the study offered further proof that the claims of ethanol proponents were ''bogus.''</p>
        <p>Other biomass fuels, from soybeans to switchgrass, are also energy-negative, according to the new research. Such studies, from each side of the issue, come out a few times a year, with the ethanol lobby (which works hard for the $3 billion in government aid ethanol receives each year) citing (and often financing) the reports that show energy-positive results.</p>
        <p>We don't need ethanol, Mr. Bryce contends. ''There are sensible ways to reduce our motor-fuel use and bolster renewable energy,'' he wrote. ''They just don't help the corn lobby.''</p>
        <p>AND IN THE END -- CNBC's anchors can now randomly pick from a whole new set of causes for a given day's decline in the Dow. Armageddon Online examines all manner of potentially world-ending events, real and imagined, from war to pestilence to alien invasions. The disturbingly large and complex -- and high-quality -- site includes news, message boards and objective research that could keep the average doomsday aficionado engrossed for hours a day.</p>
        <p>DAN MITCHELL</p>
        <p>WHAT'S ONLINE E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: whatsonline@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
