<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Landscapes, Real and Imaginary, Intimate and Expansive</title>
    <meta content="26liart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1683197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D7103EF935A15755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Landscapes, Real and Imaginary, Intimate and Expansive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Helen A. Harrison</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Long Island Landscapes'  Spanierman Gallery, 68 Newtown Lane, East Hampton, (631)329-9530. Through July 18.</p>
        <p>Ranging from the late 19th century to the mid-20th century, this show inexplicably strays from its theme to include a costume portrait by William Merritt Chase, a charming but irrelevant floral still life by Evelina Mount and other pieces that, while they are landscapes, are not of Long Island. Their inclusion is all the more curious because the gallery contains ample material that fits the bill beautifully.</p>
        <p>Still, the selection is dominated by North Fork and South Fork subjects. The Island's more westerly reaches are the subject of Josephine E. Irving's small oils of autumn foliage in Glen Cove and Oyster Bay in the 1890's and Julia Redding Kelly's lively little 1915 oil, ''Boat Yard, Cold Spring Harbor.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Long Island Landscapes'  Spanierman Gallery, 68 Newtown Lane, East Hampton, (631)329-9530. Through July 18.</p>
        <p>Ranging from the late 19th century to the mid-20th century, this show inexplicably strays from its theme to include a costume portrait by William Merritt Chase, a charming but irrelevant floral still life by Evelina Mount and other pieces that, while they are landscapes, are not of Long Island. Their inclusion is all the more curious because the gallery contains ample material that fits the bill beautifully.</p>
        <p>Still, the selection is dominated by North Fork and South Fork subjects. The Island's more westerly reaches are the subject of Josephine E. Irving's small oils of autumn foliage in Glen Cove and Oyster Bay in the 1890's and Julia Redding Kelly's lively little 1915 oil, ''Boat Yard, Cold Spring Harbor.''</p>
        <p>To recall eastern Long Island's bygone rural character, one could hardly ask for more evocative scenes than Harry Roseland's 1888 canvas, ''The Peapickers of Long Island''; Bruce Crane's ''Pond at East Hampton,'' showing the aptly named Goose Pond, now called Town Pond, before it was tamed and tidied; and Chase's masterly impressionistic study of his backyard at Shinnecock and his views across the hills.</p>
        <p>Thomas Moran's Barbizon-inspired oil, ''Under the Trees,'' and a wonderful group of pencil and gouache studies of picturesque locales by his brother Peter are also full of period flavor.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the other regional landscapes have a timeless quality. Among them are Thomas Moran's delicate 1878 watercolor of East Hampton dunes, which still look much as they did then, and Arthur B. Davies's subtle 1914 watercolor of scudding clouds sweeping over a marshy expanse.</p>
        <p>Also ageless are Henry Prellwitz's oil ''The Gale,'' showing a storm-swept shore near Peconic; Alfred Thompson Bricher's ''White Caps,'' a view out to sea; and one of the show's latest works, ''Sunset, Greenport,'' a 1950 oil sketch of sailboats by Whitney M. Hubbard.</p>
        <p>'Contemporary Photography And the Garden'  Parrish Art Museum, 25 Job's Lane, Southampton, (631)283-2118. Through July 17.</p>
        <p>The landscape as a created environment, or even an imaginary one, is the subject of this traveling group show, organized by the American Federation of Arts and subtitled ''Deceits and Fantasies.''</p>
        <p>Today's penchant for large-scale prints has led some of the 16 participants to blow up images that might better have been left small. For example, Sally Apfelbaum's tricky multilayered views of Monet's garden, ''Giverny, Trellis Triptych,'' suffer from inflation, while her smaller details of the subject work nicely.</p>
        <p>One gallery is devoted to a boring installation by Peter Fischli and David Weiss. Projected slides of flowers -- no better than average snapshots -- dissolve into one another, filling a wall with pretty colors and shapes. Period.</p>
        <p>Among the big images that do work well are Marc Quinn's pair of ''Italian Landscapes,'' in which plants are impossibly juxtaposed, artificially preserved and lovingly documented in lurid colors; Gregory Crewdson's portraits of equally bizarre gardenlike studio setups incorporating exotic butterflies; and Sally Mann's deliberately eccentric forays into the surreal Mexican garden of Edward James, an English poet.</p>
        <p>Daniel Boudinet adopts a more intimate viewpoint for his medium-size black-and-white prints of the garden of Ian Hamilton Finlay, a so-called concrete poet whose work is incorporated into the terrain around his home in Scotland. The feeling in these images is of privately encountering Mr. Finlay's work in its natural setting, without fanfare or overemphasis.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, it is hard to imagine entering the sites in Lynn Geesaman's highly stylized views of formal garden architecture and plantings. These photographs bring out each scene's sculptural character, paradoxically eliminating the human element while suggesting that everything visible has been constructed or manipulated by human intervention.</p>
        <p>In her modestly scaled color pinhole prints, Linda Hackett lets nature take its course, although within the confines of landscaped settings. The technique requires long exposures, allowing the camera to capture the ephemeral effects of wind and weather. Shot from a plant's-eye vantage point, Ms. Hackett's garden details buzz with the energy of natural life.</p>
        <p>'Preserving the Land'  East End Arts Council, 133 East Main Street, Riverhead, (631)727-0900. Through July 3.</p>
        <p>Several of the 40-plus artists in this show -- as well as Janet Culbertson, whose harrowing ''Tomorrow's Landscape'' series is featured in the council's project room -- seem more concerned with condemning the land's desecration than with celebrating its preservation.</p>
        <p>The best-in-show award went to Rosamaria Eisler's monotype ''Chemical Rain Exodus,'' in which silhouetted figures flee from a toxic miasma. Layers of bilious color and gritty texture enhance the feeling of thick, suffocating fumes. Another prize winner, an honorable-mention collage by Jackie Zagon, is a stylized interpretation of the aftermath of the 1995 fire in the Long Island Pine Barrens, a man-made disaster.</p>
        <p>In comparison to such scenes of devastation, Anthony Lombardo's panoramic view of Water Mill farmland seems benign at first glance. But a closer look reveals evidence of the residential development that threatens to overwhelm the East End's open spaces. Not that farming is without blame for negative effects on the environment. Anna Jurinich's drawing, ''Black Plastic on an L.I. Landscape,'' examines the consequences of abandoning agricultural land. Similarly, ''Apathy,'' a color photograph by Bridget Walter, shames irresponsible citizens who expect others to clean up their mess.</p>
        <p>''Where Are All the Ice Floes Going?,'' Olive Reich's prize-winning watercolor and collage, expresses a broader vision of environmental ruin. Without literally depicting results of global warming, her image of a polar bear occupying a dwindling habitat implies that the earth's well-being is in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
