<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Review Of Energy To Include Atomic Power</title>
    <meta content="30britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/30/international/europe/30britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1721294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenpeace (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6DF1531F933A05752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Review Of Energy To Include Atomic Power</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Review of Energy to Include Atomic Power</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Nov. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Tony Blair says Britain may reverse current reluctance to build new nuclear power plants, despite opposition from environmental groups; Greenpeace protesters disrupt speech to Confederation of British Industry (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair announced Tuesday that Britain may reverse its current reluctance to build new nuclear power plants, despite opposition from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's announcement reflected a nascent European debate that could presage a significant shift in energy policies. Finland in particular has already broken ranks with the opposition to nuclear power that has seized much of the Continent since the Chernobyl disaster in 1986. And while France derives around 80 percent of its electricity from nuclear power, countries like Germany and Britain may be poised to re-evaluate their previous pledges to phase out nuclear power by the early 2020's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair announced that Britain may reverse its current reluctance to build new nuclear power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair announced Tuesday that Britain may reverse its current reluctance to build new nuclear power plants, despite opposition from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's announcement reflected a nascent European debate that could presage a significant shift in energy policies. Finland in particular has already broken ranks with the opposition to nuclear power that has seized much of the Continent since the Chernobyl disaster in 1986. And while France derives around 80 percent of its electricity from nuclear power, countries like Germany and Britain may be poised to re-evaluate their previous pledges to phase out nuclear power by the early 2020's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair said Britain would make its decision by next summer.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Blair spoke at an employers' meeting here, he was disrupted by two men wearing fluorescent yellow jackets over dark business suits who clambered into the steel rafters of the auditorium to start a protest by the environmental group Greenpeace.</p>
        <p>They carried banners saying ''Nuclear: wrong answer'' and scattered similar messages on ticker tape onto the crowd below. Greenpeace said the protest was the beginning of a ''fight back against a new nuclear era'' by preventing Mr. Blair from speaking.</p>
        <p>The protesters refused to abandon their perches, insisting that they wished to make a 10-minute speech to participants in the annual meeting of the Confederation of British Industry, a leading employers' group.</p>
        <p>'''I'm not prepared to accept that,'' said Digby Jones, the head of the Confederation. ''I don't give in to ultimatums.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair, regarded as an undeclared supporter of nuclear power, was forced to address business leaders in a cramped side room, surrounded by reporters and photographers. ''This is going to be a surreal occasion,'' Mr. Blair said. ''I'm going to give this speech if it's the last thing I do.''</p>
        <p>''Like most tough issues, what we actually need is an open and democratic debate, not one conducted by protests and demonstrations to stop people having the freedom to express their views,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The two protesters, identified by Greenpeace as Huw Williams and Nyls Verhauelt, had apparently infiltrated the building with unauthorized identification passes, the organizers said. They were later arrested.</p>
        <p>Their action recalled other demonstrations in recent years by people supporting hunting and fathers' rights who breached security systems at the House of Commons and Buckingham Palace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's speech had been widely expected as the trigger for a new energy debate only two years after the British authorities resolved to increase the use of renewable sources such as wind power to supply 10 percent of the country's needs by 2010 and 20 percent by 2020. At the same time, Britain's coal and nuclear power stations, currently accounting for around one-third of its electricity, would be phased out gradually by 2023.</p>
        <p>''The issue back on the agenda with a vengeance is energy policy,'' Mr. Blair said. ''Round the world you can see feverish rethinking. Energy prices have risen. Energy supply is under threat. Climate change is producing a sense of urgency.''</p>
        <p>Britain's looming energy crisis is depicted here as potentially acute because the country, which long relied on its North Sea reserves of oil and gas, has now become a net importer of both.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair said Britain's latest policy review ''will include specifically the issues of whether we facilitate the development of a new generation of nuclear power stations.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of nuclear power argue that it is costly, potentially dangerous, vulnerable to terrorist attack and dogged by the difficulties of nuclear waste disposal. Advocates maintain that nuclear power plants produce clean and cheap fuel, reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>In the United States, no new nuclear plants have been ordered since the Three Mile Island accident in Pennsylvania in 1979. Nuclear power contributes around one-fifth of the country's electricity needs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
