<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health-Conscious</title>
    <meta content="WLN141905" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/19/magazine/19QUESTIONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1681234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-19-05: QUESTIONS FOR RICHARD CARMONA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EED91F38F93AA25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health-Conscious</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Health-Conscious</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q: The U.S. Supreme Court just ruled to uphold a federal law forbidding patients from using physician-approved marijuana to ease their pain. Do you agree with their decision?</p>
        <p>I approach this not as a legal issue but as a health issue, and I cannot recommend to anyone that they smoke, first of all. Smoking is so bad for you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surgeon general talks about medical marijuana, stem-cell research and trying to be as memorable as C. Everett Koop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q: The U.S. Supreme Court just ruled to uphold a federal law forbidding patients from using physician-approved marijuana to ease their pain. Do you agree with their decision?</p>
        <p>I approach this not as a legal issue but as a health issue, and I cannot recommend to anyone that they smoke, first of all. Smoking is so bad for you.</p>
        <p>But what if someone ingested marijuana by eating it, as in a brownie?</p>
        <p>I can't say it would be safe to eat it, because no one has studied the long- or short-term gastrointestinal effects.</p>
        <p>Have you ever tried pot?</p>
        <p>When I was a young teenager. One time. And it just didn't do anything for me.</p>
        <p>Although you've been the surgeon general for a few years, many Americans still associate the post with C. Everett Koop. Do you wish you had a higher profile?</p>
        <p>Let me tell you about Koop, because this is a misconception. Dr. Koop is a dear friend of mine. It wasn't until his second term as surgeon general that he realized he needed to be more forceful on the AIDS issue. He didn't walk into office and become forceful.</p>
        <p>Perhaps you could become a major force by speaking out on stem-cell research.</p>
        <p>We need stem-cell research, no question about it. It is absolutely crucial for moving our medical science forward. We are trying to harness an untapped source of energy that can provide cures and possibly even prevent disease and suffering.</p>
        <p>Your views don't always mesh with those of the Bush administration, which has been accused of being hostile to science, not just on stem-cell research, but also on things like global warming and the teaching of evolution.</p>
        <p>I will not always get my way. I will disagree on some issues. But as frustrated as I might get on some days, you have to pick your battles. I have to ask myself whether I want to fall on a sword and make a career-ending move for something I might be able to accomplish in another way.</p>
        <p>You seem to feel hampered in your efforts to shape public-health policy.</p>
        <p>A lot of what I do every day is more than public health. I really think the most important thing I do is to protect the dignity and the integrity of the Office of the Surgeon General.</p>
        <p>What does that mean? How can the office have any dignity if you have no sway over public-health issues?</p>
        <p>I can speak up. I just don't necessarily affect policy.</p>
        <p>Are you a Republican?</p>
        <p>No, I am not. I am an Independent.</p>
        <p>Why do you think President Bush hired you?</p>
        <p>Because I was the most qualified person. I can't think of any other reason. I didn't know the president. I was far from a political junkie.</p>
        <p>Can you tell us something about your background?</p>
        <p>I grew up in Harlem. My grandmother was one of the best cooks around, but the first thing she did on Sunday mornings when she started cooking a daylong meal was to take a big block of lard from the back of the refrigerator and throw it into the pan. I know how Hispanics buy their food, and it is not always nutritious.</p>
        <p>Considering how big a health problem obesity is in America, maybe you could make your mark by requiring McDonald's to put a warning on all its Big Macs, saying, ''The U.S. surgeon general has determined that this burger could be harmful to your health.''</p>
        <p>It's an interesting concept. But there are so many products in our society that you could put that sign on.</p>
        <p>You were trained as a trauma surgeon. Do you still practice medicine?</p>
        <p>No, unfortunately. I take care of populations instead of patients now. I used to be a real doctor. Now I just play one on TV.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 6-19-05: QUESTIONS FOR RICHARD CARMONA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
