<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Do Need a Weatherman</title>
    <meta content="30CAHILLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/30/books/review/30CAHILLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cahill, Tim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burt, Christopher C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Extreme Weather: A Guide &amp; Record Book (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tidal Waves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tidal Waves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Extreme Weather: A Guide &amp; Record Book (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DA1038F933A05752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Do Need a Weatherman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Extreme Weather': You Do Need a Weatherman</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tim Cahill</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cahill, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tim Cahill reviews book Extreme Weather: A Guide &amp; Record Book by Christopher C Burt; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EXTREME WEATHER</p>
        <p>A Guide &amp; Record Book.</p>
        <p>By Christopher C. Burt.</p>
        <p>Cartography by Mark Stroud.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 304 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Paper, $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher C. Burt's guide to rainstorms and snowstorms, hurricanes and tornadoes, killer floods and gigantic hailstones is pleasantly obsessive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EXTREME WEATHER</p>
        <p>A Guide &amp; Record Book.</p>
        <p>By Christopher C. Burt.</p>
        <p>Cartography by Mark Stroud.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 304 pp. W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Paper, $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE sky is falling, temperatures are more extreme, tornadoes ravage the land, Buffalo is probably buried in snow at this very moment, and it is flooding somewhere in the world. Hailstones the size of pumpkins -- yes, pumpkins -- may be pummeling Bangladesh right now. Your town's temperature may hit a record high today. Or maybe a record low. Or your temperatures may reach a record high and a record low in a single 24-hour period. It happens: not necessarily at the same time all over the world -- that's a disaster movie scenario -- but pretty much every year there is a spate of appallingly anomalous weather somewhere, convincing most of us that the weather is changing, and for the worse.</p>
        <p>In 2004, Florida was pounded with a record four hurricanes in a single season, a disaster that cost 117 lives and destroyed 25,000 homes. In early January, five days of torrential rains in California triggered mudslides that killed at least 10 people. The same storm brought blizzard conditions to North Dakota, where the wind chill dropped to 50 below. And while it was more a geological event than a climatological one, a magnitude-9 earthquake off the north coast of Sumatra generated a tsunami that has, to date, killed some 150,000 people.</p>
        <p>Christopher C. Burt, the author of the excellent and addictive ''Extreme Weather: A Guide &amp; Record Book,'' strives to put all this in context. He reminds us that, eons ago, the earth experienced some mind-boggling temperatures: there were glaciers in Wisconsin, and palm trees littered northern Canada. That's climate, of course, not weather. Weather happens in the short term, and we humans haven't been keeping reliable records all that long. ''In the United States,'' Burt writes, ''weather records have been maintained by the official weather services since about 1870. In the 50 preceding years, records were kept intermittently by individuals and by some institutions, including the Smithsonian Institution.'' The figures we have ''represent only a fraction of human experience with weather,'' but may be used as a ''yardstick'' to determine climatic trends. By this yardstick, the weather is not becoming more extreme.</p>
        <p>Burt, who was born in Manhattan in October 1954, during New York's most severe hurricane on record, was a protégé of the weather historian David M. Ludlum and studied meteorology at the University of Wisconsin. The man is obsessed with violent weather in the pleasantly dotty, accuracy-infatuated manner of someone in the throes of elucidating a lifelong passion. And while extreme weather fascinates him, Burt himself seems to have no desire actually to experience it. He lives in Oakland, described as ''a city of unremitting weather dullness.'' (Earthquakes, apparently, have no dominion over his imagination.)</p>
        <p>Burt spends but a single page on global warming. ''There is little debate over the fact that over the past 25 years or so global temperatures have risen significantly, and the trend has escalated since 1990.'' Why? Well, he points out that many weather stations have been moved from cities to nearby airports, where acres of asphalt radiate more heat. Some weather stations, previously in the countryside, have been absorbed into urban areas, which are warmer in the winter. Still, deserts are expanding, glaciers are melting, and Burt is obliged to note that ''recent studies'' indicate that an increase in carbon dioxide in the atmosphere ''is inextricably associated with global temperature change.''</p>
        <p>How hot can it get? The weather station near Furnace Creek, Calif., in Death Valley, located 282 feet below sea level, records an average daily high of 115 degrees and a low of 87 degrees during July, making it the hottest location in North America and ''perhaps the hottest place in the world.'' Oddly, I found myself rooting for Death Valley in the worldwide temperature sweepstakes. The valley hit 134 degrees on July 10, 1913. That's the warmest temperature ever recorded in the Western Hemisphere, and is exceeded only by a reading of 136 degrees recorded in Al Aziziyah, Libya, and a ''questionable'' reading of 135 degrees in Algeria.</p>
        <p>The coldest reading in the United States was 79.8 degrees below zero at Prospect Creek, Alaska, on Jan. 23, 1971. Fort Yukon, Alaska, averaged 48.4 below zero during December 1917, the coldest American month on record. The coldest major city in the lower 48 is Minneapolis-St. Paul, where it hit 41 degrees below zero in January 1889. I am proud to point out that the lowest temperature ever reliably recorded in the lower 48 was in my home state of Montana, where it was 70 below at Rogers Pass on Jan. 20, 1954. I am also perversely proud of the fact that, on Jan. 14-15, 1972, the temperature in Loma, Mont., rose 103 degrees -- from 54 below to 49 above -- the greatest temperature change ever recorded anywhere during a 24-hour period.</p>
        <p>Burt's book is full of tables listing your state's highs and lows, its precipitation and snowfall records, but ''Extreme Weather'' also provides concise explanations for many of the odd and extreme phenomena he describes. For instance, I suspect many Americans may share my delight in the fact that our nation arguably experiences more severe thunderstorms than anywhere else on earth. Burt explains that this is a result of our unique geography: warm, unstable air from the subtropical waters of the Gulf of Mexico collides with cold, dry sub-Arctic air sweeping down from the north. Unlike Europe or Asia, America has no mountains running east to west to separate these antagonists. This country is made for lightning storms and torrential rains and heavy floods and hailstorms.</p>
        <p>In fact, the largest American hailstone ever measured -- a veritable volleyball, seven inches across -- fell in Aurora, Neb., in June 2003. It's disappointing to learn this was not the largest authenticated hailstone in the world. That honor belongs to the Gopalganj district of Bangladesh, where, in 1986, a stone weighed in at 2.25 pounds. ''Its diameter,'' Burt says, ''was not reported, although anecdotal evidence points to stones the size of 'pumpkins.' ''</p>
        <p>THERE are appendixes at the end of ''Extreme Weather,'' giving city and state snow, precipitation and temperature records. What's remarkable is that almost every place in America seems to hold a record for some bit of exceptional weather. You probably live in, or near, the wettest or the driest place, the windiest or most calm area, the coldest or the hottest place or the one most prone to tornadoes or hurricanes. Something happened where you live: something either fierce or strange or wondrous. For example, a dust storm over Illinois on April 11, 1902, lifted an immense quantity of dirt into the air. Winds pushed this dirt east, where it was sucked into storm clouds, and the next day it rained mud in New York.</p>
        <p>Burt's book explores killer floods, swirling dust storms, hurricanes, tornadoes, hail, snow and windstorms, as well as ''mud rains'' falling over New York. The weather in some places is extreme in its very lack of extremity. Honolulu is the major American city that exhibits the least extreme absolute range of temperature, which is 43 degrees (52 degrees to 95 degrees). I suspect the locals rarely feel as though the sky were falling. Perhaps there are some who, after spending another predictably perfect day in paradise, occasionally wish that it would.</p>
        <p>Tim Cahill is the author of nine books, including ''Lost in My Own Backyard: A Walk in Yellowstone National Park.'' He lives near the Yellowstone Plateau, the fourth-coldest region in the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tim Cahill is the author of nine books, including ''Lost in My Own Backyard: A Walk in Yellowstone National Park.'' He lives near the Yellowstone Plateau, the fourth-coldest region in the United States.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
