<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Print Media Work to Convince Advertisers They Still Matter</title>
    <meta content="02MAG.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/02/business/media/02mag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1669372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Magazine Publishers of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newspaper Assn of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Newsweek</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5D61E31F931A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Print Media Work to Convince Advertisers They Still Matter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Print Insists It's Here to Stay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fanciful views of what lies ahead on futuristic magazine covers are part of $40 million, three-year Magazine Publishers of America campaign to win advertisers and try to convince them that magazines will continue to survive; Newspaper Association of America has also begun multimillion-dollar, three-year drive to make over its image in eyes of advertisers from stodgy to contemporary; it is first time that magazines have joined together in large-scale marketing effort; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here's a Newsweek cover from 100 years into the future: an aerial view of the United States with California split off from the mainland and floating in the Pacific. The headline: ''California Island: More popular than ever 62 years after the Big Quake.''</p>
        <p>And here's Sports Illustrated 100 years hence: ''Hell Freezes Over! Cubs Win 2105 World Series.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The magazine industry is mounting a $40-million, three-year campaign to win advertisers and try to convince them that magazines are here for good.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here's a Newsweek cover from 100 years into the future: an aerial view of the United States with California split off from the mainland and floating in the Pacific. The headline: ''California Island: More popular than ever 62 years after the Big Quake.''</p>
        <p>And here's Sports Illustrated 100 years hence: ''Hell Freezes Over! Cubs Win 2105 World Series.''</p>
        <p>These faux futuristic covers are part of a $40-million, three-year campaign by the magazine industry to win advertisers and try to convince them that magazines, which have existed in the United States for nearly 250 years, are likely to be here for the next 250, come what may. At the same time, the newspaper industry has begun a multimillion-dollar, three-year campaign to make over its image in the eyes of advertisers.</p>
        <p>The Newspaper Association of America has hired the Martin Agency of Richmond, Va. -- whose clients include United Parcel Service, Geico and Miller beer -- to help change the perception of newspapers from stodgy to contemporary.</p>
        <p>The Magazine Publishers of America hired HotSpring, a brand development company in New York, for ideas on how the industry could reposition itself and the ad agency Fallon New York to reach the advertising industry. This is the first time that magazines have joined together in a large-scale marketing effort.</p>
        <p>It is no secret: Print feels threatened as never before. Newspapers and magazines may have complained when radio and television came along. But they seem to be in full panic mode now as readers and advertisers flock to the Internet.</p>
        <p>With their advertising campaigns, poor old print is declaring that it's not going to take it anymore.</p>
        <p>''Enough!'' John Kimball, chief marketing officer for the Newspaper Association of America, said in an interview. ''You read things that the industry is dead, that the Internet is eating our lunch, that everyone is watching television, that national advertising is declining in the major metros.''</p>
        <p>''But the medium is very strong,'' Mr. Kimball said. ''There are lots of ads in the papers, and not because those people think they're making a charitable contribution. They're investing in the medium because it's delivering results.''</p>
        <p>Newspapers are generally profitable but they leave Wall Street unenthusiastic. A Goldman, Sachs report last week warned investors that ''lackluster ad revenue growth, weak circulation revenues'' and ''a downward trend in earnings estimates'' reinforced its ''negative view'' of the newspaper industry. And recent disclosures of inflated circulation figures have soured the climate for some advertisers.</p>
        <p>Earl C. Cox, who is the Martin Agency's chief executive and is leading the newspapers' public relations campaign, told newspaper executives at a recent conference that the current perception of newspapers among advertisers was that they were ''static, inflexible and hard to buy.'' And, he added, ''It doesn't help any that media buyers are under 30 and their focus is elsewhere,'' mostly on the Internet.</p>
        <p>He said newspapers needed to retell their story to remind advertisers that their readers are highly engaged and influential and that they are paying attention, unlike some of the ''eyeballs'' darting around the Internet.</p>
        <p>His agency is to devise a strategic plan by this summer, but he already had one piece of advice: the industry should update its calling card from being ''the newspaper business'' to being ''in the business of news.'' Translation: the word newspaper is so yesterday.</p>
        <p>Magazines are in a somewhat different position. They appear to have recovered from the advertising slump of a few years ago. Ad pages for the industry in March were up 1.2 percent from March 2004. In the first quarter of this year, 76 new magazines appeared.</p>
        <p>''The magazine industry is extremely healthy,'' said Jay Kirsch, vice president of AdMedia Partners, financial advisers to magazines. ''The newsweeklies are in tough shape, but the monthlies and lifestyle and enthusiast magazines are doing fabulously.''</p>
        <p>Of the $141 billion spent on all forms of advertising in 2004, about 17 percent went to magazines, according to TNS Media Intelligence. Newspapers captured 20 percent of that, network television 18 percent, cable television 12 percent and the Internet 6 percent. But the newspaper share was down, the magazine share was flat and the Internet was growing fast. Advertising Age predicted last week that the combined advertising revenue of Google and Yahoo this year would rival those of the big three television networks, marking what it called a ''watershed moment'' in the evolution of the Internet.</p>
        <p>''We're really good at putting out products that consumers love, value and trust, and trust is very hard to find these days,'' said Jack Kliger, president and chief executive of Hachette Filipacchi Media U.S., which publishes Elle, Woman's Day and Car and Driver, among others. ''We've not been good at marketing our medium.''</p>
        <p>Readers of magazines, like readers of newspapers, are highly engaged.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kliger said research showed that when people are reading magazines, they are unlikely to be using any other form of media. But when they watch television, listen to the radio or wait to download something from the Internet, they are more likely to be listening, watching or reading something else at the same time. They are also likely to be fast-forwarding through commercials or deleting pop-up ads that they see as intrusions. But, he said, magazine readers often see ads as helpful and as part of the magazine experience.</p>
        <p>''Engagement improves return on investment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nina Link, president of the magazine publishers' group, said the marketing campaign was not intended to denigrate the competition.</p>
        <p>''We play nicely in the sandbox with other media,'' she said. ''We're not saying don't advertise in them.'' But, she said, ''We want a higher share of the revenue.''</p>
        <p>The idea behind the futuristic covers was to show advertisers that whatever earth-shattering changes might occur in the next 100 years, magazines will survive them, and endure. Mr. Kliger said some magazines might even start running the futuristic covers in between their real covers, just to reinforce the message with ordinary readers.</p>
        <p>Those readers, of course, may be less concerned about the future of magazines than with the future world the magazines predict: a world where cloning is common, women are giving birth at age 75 and global warming has created beaches in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
