<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>8 Leaders Hail Steps on Africa And Warming</title>
    <meta content="09SUMM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/09/international/europe/09summit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DF153DF93AA35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>8 Leaders Hail Steps on Africa And Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">8 Leaders Hail Steps on Africa and Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <dateline>AUCHTERARDER, Scotland, July 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Striking tones of optimism and defiance a day after the attacks in London, President Bush and the leaders of seven other big industrial nations concluded a summit meeting here on Friday saying they had made substantial progress in addressing African poverty, global warming and the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</p>
        <p>Wrapping up the gathering before rushing back to London, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain said the ability of the governments represented here to agree on steps to help some of the world's neediest people, protect the environment and sow peace was the most effective rebuttal to violence and extremism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The leaders of eight big industrial nations claimed progress in addressing African poverty, global warming and the Mideast conflict.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Striking tones of optimism and defiance a day after the attacks in London, President Bush and the leaders of seven other big industrial nations concluded a summit meeting here on Friday saying they had made substantial progress in addressing African poverty, global warming and the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</p>
        <p>Wrapping up the gathering before rushing back to London, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain said the ability of the governments represented here to agree on steps to help some of the world's neediest people, protect the environment and sow peace was the most effective rebuttal to violence and extremism.</p>
        <p>''We speak today in the shadow of terrorism,'' said Mr. Blair, who had returned here from London on Thursday evening and presided over the final sessions on Friday. ''But it will not obscure what we came here to achieve.''</p>
        <p>Despite the public show of unity on the Group of 8's agenda, Mr. Bush remained at odds with other leaders over many of the details of how best to address the issues being debated and gave little ground on them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair hailed a series of agreements to alleviate poverty in Africa, his signature issue, including commitments by the eight nations to double their aid to $50 billion a year by 2010, reduce trade barriers, cancel the debts of many countries and do more to fight diseases, including AIDS and malaria. The American aid pledge represents no new money beyond that which had already been promised.</p>
        <p>In an unusual step, Mr. Blair had all the leaders sign their joint statements on Africa in public to press them to keep their pledges.</p>
        <p>''It isn't the end of poverty in Africa,'' Mr. Blair said after the leaders met with their counterparts from seven African countries. ''But it is the hope that it can be ended. It isn't all everyone wanted, but it is progress, real and achievable progress.''</p>
        <p>He said the industrial nations had signed off on a plan to begin addressing global warming by opening talks this year with a group of developing countries, in the hopes of slowing and eventually reversing the increase in emissions of greenhouse gases into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blair acknowledged that deep differences between the United States and the other nations over the issue limited the scope of the agreement, saying it amounted to ''the possibility of re-establishing a consensus.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush blocked efforts by Mr. Blair to agree on specific targets for reducing emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>But he did agree to language in the final communiqué on climate change that, while hedged, acknowledges that the burning of fossil fuels contributes to global warming, a position that his administration has at times avoided endorsing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also signed off on the pledge by the eight nations to double aid to Africa in the next five years.</p>
        <p>But his point man for the summit meeting, Faryar Shirzad, a deputy national security adviser, said later that the aid commitment involved no new money from the United States. Instead, it only adds up increases agreed to previously. Mr. Bush's opposition also helped doom calls for the rich nations to commit themselves to providing a defined proportion of their national incomes for aid to Africa, a step that would have required much larger contributions from the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush left the summit meeting without making any public comment on the outcome. Mr. Shirzad, talking to reporters aboard Air Force One as Mr. Bush headed home, called the meeting ''a huge success.''</p>
        <p>But after a long campaign of advertising and lobbying, as well as the Live 8 concerts last Saturday, to press for action on the environment and Africa, members of interest groups assembled here to push their causes said the results were mixed.</p>
        <p>''The world's richest nations have delivered welcome progress for the world's poorest people, but the outcome here in Gleneagles has fallen short of the hopes of the millions around the world campaigning for a momentous breakthrough,'' Jo Leadbeater, who is in charge of policy for Oxfam International, a group that advocates more aggressive action to fight poverty, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Bob Geldof, the former rock star who helped lead the campaign for debt relief and more aid, said the agreements on aid and trade were a big step forward but still had to be carried out. ''Time only will tell if this has been historic or not,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tony Juniper, vice chairman of Friends of the Earth International, an environmental group, said the plan on addressing greenhouse gas emissions lacked the concrete commitments necessary to make a difference, largely because of Mr. Bush's opposition. Mr. Bush has long advocated investing in technology that can help industries reduce emissions caused by the use of fossil fuels but has opposed mandatory limits on emissions, saying that to do so could harm the economy.</p>
        <p>''To cut a long story short, we don't see anything new in the communiqué that's going to make action on global warming happen any more decisively or any more quickly,'' Mr. Juniper said.</p>
        <p>The leaders discussed a wide variety of foreign policy issues, including Iraq and the Middle East. Mr. Blair announced that the eight nations would try to raise as much as $3 billion a year in aid for the Palestinian Authority over the next three years, a step intended to help the Palestinians after Israel withdraws, beginning in August, from Gaza and sections of the West Bank. The Bush administration said last month that it would work with James D. Wolfensohn, a former president of the World Bank, to assemble the aid package by seeking contributions from other countries around the world, including Arab nations.</p>
        <p>For all the focus on the formal agenda of the summit meeting, behind the scenes much of the talk still concerned the attacks in London on Thursday. In his public comments, Mr. Blair said that terrorism was best countered by providing a hopeful alternative.</p>
        <p>''It is by its savagery designed to cover all conventional politics in darkness, to overwhelm the dignity of democracy and proper process with the impact of bloodshed and of terror,'' Mr. Blair said. ''There is no hope in terrorism nor any future in it worth living. And it is hope that is the alternative to this hatred. So we offer today this contrast with the politics of terror.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
