<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At NASA These Days, Clouds Are Just What You Zoom Through on the Way to Mars</title>
    <meta content="21NASA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/21/science/21nasa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1658842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Moon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Station</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, Cornelia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Donald (Science Magazine)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE4D81E3CF932A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At NASA These Days, Clouds Are Just What You Zoom Through on the Way to Mars</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At NASA, Clouds Are What You Zoom Through to Get to Mars</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dean, Cornelia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Accounting changes at NASA and Bush administration's emphasis on sending people to Moon and Mars threaten NASA's financing of other scientific research, including study of atmosphere and of components of universe, which was largely shielded from cost overruns in shuttle and space station programs until this year; new procedures have given officials much freer hand to shift money about; even though NASA will get 2.4 percent increase in financing under Bush administration's budget for coming fiscal year, many scientific programs could suffer; Donald Kennedy, editor of journal Science, says that mood among NASA scientists is 'odd combination of confusion, gloom and struggle'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until a few weeks ago, James C. Wilson, a professor of engineering at the University of Denver, thought he would be spending the summer using high-altitude NASA aircraft to carry instruments into tropical clouds to measure the movement of water vapor and particles like soot.</p>
        <p>Understanding these clouds is critical to understanding and predicting climate change. But the project has been canceled, Dr. Wilson says, a casualty of accounting changes at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and of the Bush administration's emphasis on sending people to the Moon and Mars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientific research at NASA could become a casualty of accounting changes and of the Bush administration's emphasis on sending people to the Moon and Mars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until a few weeks ago, James C. Wilson, a professor of engineering at the University of Denver, thought he would be spending the summer using high-altitude NASA aircraft to carry instruments into tropical clouds to measure the movement of water vapor and particles like soot.</p>
        <p>Understanding these clouds is critical to understanding and predicting climate change. But the project has been canceled, Dr. Wilson says, a casualty of accounting changes at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and of the Bush administration's emphasis on sending people to the Moon and Mars.</p>
        <p>While NASA is best known for its spaceflight programs, it has long financed other scientific research, including the study of the atmosphere and of components of the universe. Until this year, that research was largely shielded from cost overruns in the shuttle and space station programs.</p>
        <p>But under procedures instituted during the tenure of Sean O'Keefe, the administrator who left the agency in February, officials are much more free to shift money to the shuttle and the space station from other programs. Even though NASA would get a 2.4 percent increase in financing under the Bush administration's budget for the coming fiscal year, many scientific programs could suffer.</p>
        <p>''Those firewalls are coming down, and that's a cause for concern,'' said Representative Sherwood Boehlert, the New York Republican who is chairman of the House Committee on Science, which held a hearing on NASA spending last month.</p>
        <p>Also, in the fiscal year that began last October, the agency adopted ''full-cost accounting,'' a system under which the costs for NASA personnel and facilities, which once appeared separately in the agency's budget, are ascribed to the programs that use them. ''The idea is, that will more accurately reflect the true costs of the programs,'' said Sarah Keegan, a spokeswoman for NASA.</p>
        <p>But the agency does not always shift money along with this new budget responsibility. As a result, managers facing new costs without new money are delaying, shortening or even eliminating some of their programs. This was the problem that doomed the summer cloud study, Dr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>Also, the new focus on sending people to the Moon and Mars ''in some cases means a reconfiguration of priorities,'' Ms. Keegan said.</p>
        <p>In an editorial in the current issue of the journal Science, its editor, Donald Kennedy, called the mood among NASA scientists ''an odd combination of confusion, gloom and struggle.'' He added in an interview, ''Something major is happening with a redistribution of NASA's resources away from science.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kennedy says that the plan to send people to the Moon and Mars ''may not be a worthless boondoggle'' but that some researchers are calling it the scientific equivalent of ''extreme sports.''</p>
        <p>Other scientists said that in focusing on human spaceflight, the administration was ignoring the collaborative process in which scientists inside and outside NASA work together, through the National Research Council, to establish priorities for the agency. The priorities are typically reviewed every 10 years, in what are called decadal reports.</p>
        <p>''They are doing it totally from the top down,'' said Robert P. Kirshner, a professor of astronomy at Harvard and the president of the American Astronomical Society. He said the impetus for the Moon-Mars program came ''from the president, the political people,'' and added, ''That doesn't make it evil, but that's not where the community of scientists saw the opportunity.''</p>
        <p>For example, Dr. Kirshner said, the last 10-year report by astrophysicists, in 2002, assumed that shuttle astronauts would be sent to the Hubble Space Telescope to replace batteries and gyroscopes and to add new instruments, two of which are being built.</p>
        <p>But under the full-cost accounting system, Dr. Kirshner said, the Hubble budget would have to bear the full cost of the mission, estimated at a billion dollars or more, which is about a fifth of all NASA science spending that is not related to the shuttle or the space station.</p>
        <p>''What's funny about it is they don't charge shuttle trips to the space station in the new way,'' Dr. Kirshner said. ''And I would say the space station has very few uses we could think of and has produced almost nothing for physical science.''</p>
        <p>The Hubble telescope is widely regarded as a scientific triumph, but it will die in orbit in a few years unless it is refurbished.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilson said the cancellation of the cloud project was troubling not just because it left some associates out of work or contemplating unpaid summer vacations but also because ''it deprives us of access to the high clouds.''</p>
        <p>Only NASA has U-2 planes and other aircraft capable of carrying instruments high enough to observe tropical clouds, which rise to unusual altitudes. Without its participation, the research, and a related project planned for next winter, will not go forward.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to whine about NASA, because they allowed me to live my dream, which was to do interesting science on things I think are important,'' Dr. Wilson said in an interview. ''And I cannot complain about a proposal being turned down; it happens all the time.''</p>
        <p>But in 25 years of watching NASA research efforts, he said in an e-mail message, ''I have never seen an announced mission canceled.''</p>
        <p>Mark Sykes, director of the Planetary Science Institute, a nonprofit organization for scientists researching geology, astronomy and astrophysics, said planetary scientists completed a 10-year study in 2002 and listed exploration of the Moon as a priority, ''but only robotic exploration.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Sykes described himself as ''a big fan of human space exploration'' who was inspired to become a planetary scientist by the Mercury astronauts of the early 1960's. But, he said, ''For a lot of science it's really more cost-effective to do things robotically.''</p>
        <p>Ghassem Asrar, deputy associate administrator for the science mission directorate, rejected the idea that scientific merit, as determined in the decadal report system, had fallen by the wayside in the new environment at NASA.</p>
        <p>''Science has been, is and will continue to be a major component of NASA's program,'' Dr. Asrar said. ''NASA depends on the scientists from across the nation to help set its priorities and achieve those goals and objectives and priorities.''</p>
        <p>He added, though, that the agency did not look to scientists ''to pass judgment on the composition of the NASA program.'' When it comes to issues like an exploration program for the Moon, he said, ''that is a decision that is made by the executive branch and the legislative branch of our government.''</p>
        <p>Although the administration has not abandoned other efforts, its focus is on human exploration of the Moon and Mars, Frederick D. Gregory, deputy administrator of NASA, told the House Science Committee in testimony last month. For example, he said, robots may be sent again to Mars, but they would go ''in anticipation of eventual human visits.''</p>
        <p>David Goldston, chief of staff of the House Science Committee, agreed that NASA was setting its priorities in accord with President Bush's Moon-Mars program. ''One reason to be concerned about priority-setting is, what will happen if the exploration programs start having cost overruns?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Representative Boehlert applauded the president's plan and endorsed the idea of altering accounting to better reflect the true cost of NASA programs. He said recent changes had inspired an agency ''that in effect was in a collective funk.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Boehlert said it was important not to lose sight of earth science, aeronautics and other missions, and he added that he hoped these and other issues could be debated as Congress worked on the budget for next year.</p>
        <p>The idea of sending people to explore the Moon and Mars is ''a major goal,'' Mr. Boehlert said, but ''we are very concerned about the impact on earth science.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
