<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>While Supplies Last: Three Natural Wonders That Are Feeling the Heat</title>
    <meta content="26MELT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/26/travel/26melt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1682940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Glacier National Park</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3D6123BF935A15755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>While Supplies Last: Three Natural Wonders That Are Feeling the Heat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">While Supplies Last: Three Natural Wonders That Are Feeling the Heat</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK KAYE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades, scientists have been warning the world about global warming. And while skeptics still call the increase in the earth's temperature over the last century a natural evolution, its effects are beginning to show in some of the world's most famous tourist destinations. Here are three where the changes have been particularly dramatic in recent years.</p>
        <p>GLACIER NATIONAL PARK</p>
        <p>This park, consisting of 1,600 square miles straddling the Canadian border in the northern Rockies of Montana, became the country's 10th national park in 1910, later joining Canada's Waterton Lakes National Park to form Waterton-Glacier International Peace Park. But the glaciers that built its towering peaks and alpine lakes are steadily disappearing, forever altering the landscape and affecting the wildlife of one of the continent's largest untouched ecosystems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three famous tourist destinations where the changes from global warming have been particularly dramatic in recent years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades, scientists have been warning the world about global warming. And while skeptics still call the increase in the earth's temperature over the last century a natural evolution, its effects are beginning to show in some of the world's most famous tourist destinations. Here are three where the changes have been particularly dramatic in recent years.</p>
        <p>GLACIER NATIONAL PARK</p>
        <p>This park, consisting of 1,600 square miles straddling the Canadian border in the northern Rockies of Montana, became the country's 10th national park in 1910, later joining Canada's Waterton Lakes National Park to form Waterton-Glacier International Peace Park. But the glaciers that built its towering peaks and alpine lakes are steadily disappearing, forever altering the landscape and affecting the wildlife of one of the continent's largest untouched ecosystems.</p>
        <p>The park was home to about 150 glaciers in 1850. Now there are only 37, according to park officials, and some scientists believe that those will disappear within the next 30 to 50 years. One of the most accessible is Grinnell Glacier, on the east side of the park. ''You can actually get up there and you see where, quite recently, that glacier had extended to,'' said Steve Thompson, of the National Parks Conservation Association. ''And every year it retreats a bit more. We're getting to the point where this may become the park that's the park formerly known as Glacier National Park.''</p>
        <p>SEEING IT -- There are more than 700 miles of trails in Glacier, with maps available at visitor centers and online at www.nps.gov/glac. Glacier Wilderness Guides, (800) 521-7238, www.glacierguides.com, offers trips ranging from day hikes ($65 a person) to 10-day backpacking treks along the Continental Divide ($1,050).</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- The nearest major airport, about 25 miles southeast in Kalispell, Mont., is served by America West and Northwest, among other lines. Rental cars and shuttles to the park are available.</p>
        <p>MOUNT KILIMANJARO</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of Kilimanjaro National Park, in Tanzania, rises dramatically out of the dry plains. At 19,340 feet, it's Africa's tallest and most recognizable peak. But over time, the signature white cap of ice -- rare so near the Equator -- has thinned to the point that the top of the mountain now appears brown in places, even from afar. Huge chunks of the ice have been seen crumbling and falling off, and farming communities, animals and plants in the area are being affected by the warming climate. ''There are areas where we used to have rivers flowing in the park, and we don't have them anymore,'' said Gerald Bigurube, director of Tanzania National Parks.</p>
        <p>Steps are being taken, Mr. Bigurube said, to curb deforestation of the area, which is said to play a part in the loss of cloud cover that has exposed the mountain to the sun's ultraviolet rays. Some estimates say the ice cap could be gone by 2020, but Mr. Bigurube predicts little impact on tourism. ''The presence of ice and snow was like the icing on the cake,'' he said. ''Now when the icing is not there, the cake is still great to enjoy.''</p>
        <p>SEEING IT -- Climbing Kilimanjaro, the tallest free-standing mountain in the world, is usually done in six to eight days and is considered a tough hike rather than an actual climb. Good Earth Tours and Safaris, (877) 265-9003, www.goodearthtours.com, based in Arusha, Tanzania, with an office in Tampa, Fla., offers trips on routes of varying difficulty starting at $720 a person.</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- Kilimanjaro International Airport, near Moshi, Tanzania, is served by KLM and Ethiopian Airlines, among other lines.</p>
        <p>THE GREAT BARRIER REEF</p>
        <p>A chain of coral reefs off the northeastern coast of Australia that is more than 1,400 miles long, this is said to be the largest natural feature on earth, visible even from space. Formed by groups of tiny coral polyps encased in shells of calcium carbonate, the reef system supports rare wildlife and 1,500 species of fish. But as the ocean warms, the algae that support the polyps are expelled, causing the coral to bleach white and possibly die. The summers of 1998 and 2002 caused major bleaching episodes across large portions of the reef, and while much of it rebounded from the bleaching, up to 5 percent was permanently damaged.</p>
        <p>''Good management can't stop bleaching occurring, but it can maintain the conditions that enable it to bounce back,'' said Dr. Paul Marshall, manager of Great Barrier Reef Marine Park's climate change response program. The park, which sees about 1.8 million visitors a year, is fighting the reef bleaching by trying to improve the area's water quality and stop overfishing, said to hinder the ability of the coral to rehabilitate itself. Unlike glaciers, coral can evolve and adapt to climate change, but humans, as Dr. Marshall points out, are affecting the ecosystem in ways never before seen. ''We can afford to be hopeful but not too optimistic,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SEEING IT -- Among the many groups that offer diving and snorkeling trips is Reef Encounter, (61-7) 4031-7217, www.reeftrip.com, based in Cairns, Queensland, which has trips on a 115-foot luxury catamaran starting at $218 for two days (at $1.33 Australian to the U.S. dollar) and $331 for three days.</p>
        <p>GETTING THERE -- Cairns International Airport is served by Qantas, Continental, and Air New Zealand, among other lines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
