<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain Suspends Referendum on European Constitution</title>
    <meta content="07BRIT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/07/international/europe/07britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1678417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">European Union</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF1338F934A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain Suspends Referendum on European Constitution</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Britain Suspends Referendum on European Constitution</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deepening a crisis, Britain said Monday that it would suspend plans for a referendum on the European constitution, which was rejected last week by voters in France and the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>The announcement to Parliament by Jack Straw, the foreign secretary, laid bare the gulf between nations like France and Germany that want to keep alive a sense that the constitution can be rescued, and Britain, where the government is under pressure to declare it dead. The move seemed to make ratification of the constitution, a cornerstone of European unity, all the more remote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deepening a crisis, Britain said Monday that it would suspend plans for a referendum on the European constitution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deepening a crisis, Britain said Monday that it would suspend plans for a referendum on the European constitution, which was rejected last week by voters in France and the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>The announcement to Parliament by Jack Straw, the foreign secretary, laid bare the gulf between nations like France and Germany that want to keep alive a sense that the constitution can be rescued, and Britain, where the government is under pressure to declare it dead. The move seemed to make ratification of the constitution, a cornerstone of European unity, all the more remote.</p>
        <p>''The European Union does now face a period of difficulty,'' Mr. Straw said.</p>
        <p>Technically, the constitution can come into force only if it is ratified by all 25 European Union member governments. Nine have approved it by parliamentary votes and one -- Spain -- by referendum. The ''no'' votes in France and the Netherlands seemed to many British legislators to have brought the ratification process to a shuddering halt.</p>
        <p>But, confronted by French, German and European insistence that the ratification effort should continue, and not wanting to be the one to seal the constitution's demise, Britain has shied from saying explicitly that its referendum -- expected for next spring -- is canceled.</p>
        <p>''It is now for European leaders to reach conclusions on how to deal with the situation,'' Mr. Straw told Parliament, apparently seeking to shift the onus for the constitution's future away from Britain.</p>
        <p>To explain the suspension, he referred to the British legislative calendar, which requires a ''second reading'' of a law to allow a referendum to take place.</p>
        <p>''Until the consequences of France and the Netherlands being unable to ratify the treaty are clarified, it would not in our judgment now be sensible to set a date for a second reading,'' he said. ''There is also the need for further discussions with European Union partners and further decisions from European Union governments.''</p>
        <p>''We reserve completely the right to bring back the bill providing for a United Kingdom referendum should circumstances change,'' he said. ''But we see no point in proceeding at this moment.''</p>
        <p>However diplomatically couched, Mr. Straw's announcement seemed intended to send the message to Britain's European adversaries that many Britons are opposed to a referendum. As an opposition Conservative legislator, Liam Fox, put it, ''this constitution is a case for the morgue if ever I saw one.''</p>
        <p>In this largely Euroskeptic nation, Prime Minister Tony Blair had risked losing the referendum, shortening the third term in office that he won in elections in May. So the postponement offered him political advantage but could also reopen the debate about when he will hand over power, as widely speculated, to his heir apparent, Gordon Brown, the chancellor of the Exchequer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair is to meet President Bush in Washington on Tuesday to seek his backing for an array of difficult issues. The coincidence of the two events illuminated Mr. Blair's efforts to straddle European and trans-Atlantic diplomacy, despite his unpopularity with some Europeans, notably France and Germany, for his alliance with the United States in Iraq. Britain is this year's leader of the Group of 8 major industrialized nations and will assume the rotating presidency of the European Union on July 1.</p>
        <p>But on both counts, he is facing a fairly bleak agenda, confronted with hostility in Europe on an array of issues from the constitution to the European Union budget. At the same time, many political analysts in London expect that he is unlikely to win substantive White House support for his main issues, from relieving African poverty to global warming, at the G-8 summit meeting next month in Scotland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair has also cast Europe's division as one of profound dimensions between the so-called Anglo-Saxon economic model of relatively untrammeled capitalism that prevails in Britain and the cozier, socially oriented approaches of France and Germany.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Straw said Monday that ''these referendum results raise profound questions about the future direction of Europe.''</p>
        <p>Even as word of Mr. Straw's announcement leaked out in advance, other European nations seemed to be lining up either to question the British decision, or to interpret it in optimistic terms.</p>
        <p>José Manuel Barroso, the president of the European Commission, said in Brussels that it would be unfair for one country to determine the constitution's fate. But he added, according to Reuters, ''All the indications I have from all member states, including the United Kingdom, are that they want to discuss this issue in the European Council.''</p>
        <p>In Warsaw, Poland's foreign minister, Adam Rotfeld, told reporters that the British move ''does not change anything.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
