<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING IN/The Fairfield, Conn., Beach Area; A Beach Community in an Awkward Transition</title>
    <meta content="03livi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/03/realestate/03livi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1684754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Living In | Fairfield, Conn."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED71531F930A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING IN/The Fairfield, Conn., Beach Area; A Beach Community in an Awkward Transition</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Beach Community in an Awkward Transition</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA PREVOST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE transformation of Fairfield's central beach neighborhood is understandably disconcerting to residents who find themselves craning their necks to glimpse the tops of the three-story turreted houses rising around them. Yet at the same time, they can't help but marvel at their good fortune. Encroaching wealth has driven up land values such that the aging six-room Capes that once made the beach one of Fairfield's more affordable areas now get $700,000 or more as teardowns.</p>
        <p>Trish and Tom Sullivan moved into one of those Capes in 1997, when beach prices were still in the $200,000 to $300,000 range. By 2001, their family of four had outgrown the space, so the Sullivans expanded upward, essentially converting their house into a colonial. ''We were one of the first on our street to do that, and people were walking by gawking at it,'' said Mrs. Sullivan, a sales representative for a pharmaceutical company. ''Now, the joke around here is: 'Ha! Remember when we thought your house was big?'''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Fairfields central beach area, six-room Capes are going for $700,000 as teardowns, as buyers seek to be near the towns largest public beaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE transformation of Fairfield's central beach neighborhood is understandably disconcerting to residents who find themselves craning their necks to glimpse the tops of the three-story turreted houses rising around them. Yet at the same time, they can't help but marvel at their good fortune. Encroaching wealth has driven up land values such that the aging six-room Capes that once made the beach one of Fairfield's more affordable areas now get $700,000 or more as teardowns.</p>
        <p>Trish and Tom Sullivan moved into one of those Capes in 1997, when beach prices were still in the $200,000 to $300,000 range. By 2001, their family of four had outgrown the space, so the Sullivans expanded upward, essentially converting their house into a colonial. ''We were one of the first on our street to do that, and people were walking by gawking at it,'' said Mrs. Sullivan, a sales representative for a pharmaceutical company. ''Now, the joke around here is: 'Ha! Remember when we thought your house was big?'''</p>
        <p>Over the last three years, the Sullivans' house has shrunk relative to the 4,000- to 6,000-square-foot shingled colonials that have come to represent the new beach style. While Mrs. Sullivan, who grew up in Fairfield, said she worries that these huge multimillion-dollar houses will eventually outnumber the modest homes that give the neighborhood a casual family-friendly feel, she can't help but be pleased by the corresponding rise in her own property value.</p>
        <p>''We're fortunate we got in when we did,'' she said. ''I just never would have thought this could happen.''</p>
        <p>Buyers priced out of waterfront communities farther south along the Fairfield County commuter line have touched off an extended building boom in the neighborhoods around Fairfield's beaches. The makeover is particularly pronounced along the shady, suburban streetscapes between downtown's historic Old Post Road and the mile-plus stretch of uninterrupted beach along Long Island Sound. Though much of the beachfront is privately owned, the beauty and accessibility of the town's two largest public beaches -- Jennings and Penfield -- enhance the value of properties throughout the 1.6-square-mile area. Even after several years of explosive growth in beach-area home prices, property values continue to climb.</p>
        <p>Capes, ranches and bungalows are coming down so quickly that the town planner's office has lost count, said Joseph E. Bienkowski, the planner specializing in coastal development. He offers a ''conservative estimate'' of 20 beach teardowns and 10 substantial renovations in just the last year. Because most beach lots are little more than a quarter of an acre, yards are disappearing beneath houses designed to wring every dollar of value out of the land.</p>
        <p>''What we're seeing more of now, which we didn't see even 10 years ago, is builders taking advantage of the third-story allowance in these zones,'' Mr. Bienkowski said. ''Also, they'd never bumped up against the lot coverage allowance before. These old Capes typically cover 8 to 14 percent of the lot, but the new houses are right up against the 20-percent limit.''</p>
        <p>What You'll Find</p>
        <p>The resulting hodgepodge of cottages, Capes, newer colonials and contemporaries and palatial Nantucket-style houses exemplifies a community in the midst of an awkward transition. The shift is most prominently symbolized by the $2.249 million stone-and-shingle home towering above a row of humble bungalows on Fairfield Beach Road, the well-traveled avenue following the shoreline.</p>
        <p>Across the street from the beach, the house is loaded with luxuries, including a master suite with a fireplace, whirlpool tub and heated bathroom floors; a third-floor media room with a wet bar; and balcony views of the Long Island Sound. At 5,500 square feet, the house was able to accommodate some 175 people at a party given there recently by the builder, Bob Sabre of Beachside Estates.</p>
        <p>''I'd love to make a house a little smaller,'' said Mr. Sabre, who, with his partner Tom Kane has built and sold about a dozen houses at the beach and has eight more in various stages of development. ''But you know what? People want big. They want all the rooms, and all the space.''</p>
        <p>The destruction of older homes is encouraged, some residents complain, by regulations that make it prohibitively expensive for homeowners to renovate.</p>
        <p>Because the beach neighborhoods are in a flood zone, under federal regulations any homeowner making an improvement that costs more than 50 percent of the structure's value must fully comply with Federal Emergency Management Agency regulations for building in areas prone to flooding. In most cases, that means elevating the house and filling in the basement.</p>
        <p>The town's strict enforcement of the flood code is in homeowners' best interests, particularly in light of rising sea levels, said Mr. Bienkowski, the planner. According to a Connecticut College study, the water level of Long Island Sound rose three inches from 1979 to 1989 and another five inches from 1989 to 1999. As it is, Mr. Bienkowski noted, severe storms have been known to flood the parking lot of Town Hall three-fifths of a mile from the Sound.</p>
        <p>What They're Asking</p>
        <p>Prices in the beach area range from about $450,000 to more than $3 million, with an average list price of $1.1 million. Lower-priced properties are found along busy Reef Road, where the notorious rowdiness of Fairfield University students sharing rentals has resulted in frequent clashes with year-round residents. Elsewhere in the area, buyers in search of properties under $800,000 must be quick to act, according to Julie Vanderblue, president of the Higgins Group real estate agency.</p>
        <p>''If it's priced well, it's going to go overnight,'' Ms. Vanderblue said. ''You're not going to get 3,000 square feet for under $1 million, but if you can compromise on space or wait on a new kitchen, it's worth it because the property will definitely hold its value.''</p>
        <p>The median sale price of a single-family home in the beach area has more than doubled in the last five years, she said, to $745,000 from $340,000 in 2000. The highest sale to date, $2.287 million, occurred last year, but three higher-priced properties, including one listed at $5.25 million, recently went under contract.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago, we thought prices were going to level,'' said Mr. Sabre, the builder. ''They kept going up. Then a year ago, we thought it was going to happen. It didn't. Now, it seems like it's peaking, but I really don't know.''</p>
        <p>What to Do</p>
        <p>During warm months, Penfield and Jennings Beaches are hubs of activity from dawn to dusk. Throughout the summer, the Parks and Recreation Department adds sailing and swimming lessons, outdoor movie nights and a spectacular Fourth of July fireworks display. Parking restrictions on residential streets limit traffic spillover from the beach.</p>
        <p>Boaters have a full-service facility in the town-operated South Benson Marina, but nearly 1,300 residents are on the waiting list for the 600 boat slips, according to Robin Bimmel, the marina manager. The wait for a small slip is about four years, and twice that for large slips. Fees, at $320 to $800 for the season (April through November), are about one-third the cost of private marinas.</p>
        <p>The Schools</p>
        <p>The Roger Sherman Elementary School is a focal point for the beach neighborhoods -- the annual family cookouts and ice cream socials are community events. ''Everyone here seems to have either been through the school, will go through it or is currently at the school,'' said Michael Giarratano, who just completed his ninth and final year as principal.</p>
        <p>Enrollment at the school, which has kindergarten to Grade 5, hovers around 430; five classrooms are outside the school in separate portable structures. The school's academic performance on the 2003 Connecticut Mastery Test mirrored the district averages: 93 percent of Sherman students scored at the proficient level in math, and 90 percent showed proficiency in reading.</p>
        <p>Sherman students go on to Tomlinson Middle School for Grades 6 to 8, and then to the new Ludlowe High School. Both schools are downtown. SAT scores for the class of 2004 averaged 550 in verbal and 557 in math; state averages were 508 and 518, respectively.</p>
        <p>The Commute</p>
        <p>A crew of commuters can be seen making their daily morning trek from the beach area to the downtown train station. Walking is often preferable to trying to find a parking space, especially for residents whose names haven't yet risen to the top of the town's lengthy waiting list for station parking permits. The trip to Grand Central Terminal on Metro-North Railroad's New Haven line during peak commuting hours is 70 to 80 minutes.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Living at the Fairfield beaches wasn't fashionable until midway into the 20th century. During the late 1800's, trains arrived daily bringing wealthy vacationers from New York, but the visitors stayed well back from the beach in a fancy resort called Fairfield House. According to a town history written by Thomas J. Farnham, the first people to live at the beach were average folks who traveled down from Danbury in the 1890's, and their cluster of rustic summer cottages was dubbed Little Danbury.</p>
        <p>Shorefront living could be hard, as flooding was a recurring problem. After the hurricane of 1938 destroyed dozens of cottages along the shore, flood protections were put in place that enabled more permanent development. Development pressures increased in the 1970's, and the town bought 1.8 acres of land with 280 feet of shorefront along Fairfield Beach Road to preserve for public use.</p>
        <p>The town had earlier acquired 16 acres of beach property presented as a gift from Annie B. Jennings, the wealthy owner of a sprawling estate called Sunnie-holme that once stretched from Old Post Road to the shoreline.</p>
        <p>What We Like</p>
        <p>Refreshing in its economic diversity, Fairfield's beach area lacks the exclusivity of many shore communities to the south. Whether you live in a cottage or a castle, you enjoy the same access to the beaches and other amenities.</p>
        <p>What We'd Change</p>
        <p>In response to residents' complaints, the town made a meager attempt to rein in house sizes by lowering the maximum height from 40 feet to 32 feet. The effect is negligible, as much of the new construction continues to look grossly out of proportion to the rest of the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Living In | Fairfield, Conn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
