<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Couple</title>
    <meta content="09lipowe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/09/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/09lipowe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1708291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">KeySpan Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Power Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3D61130F93AA35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="2602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Couple</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Power Couple</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is probably the most important business relationship on Long Island: KeySpan and the Long Island Power Authority. And it seems like a rocky marriage, with the two sides pulling in different directions and chafing under the vows and prenuptial agreements that bind them. They may be headed for a breakup.</p>
        <p>Those watching from the outside say that despite their troubles, ranging from private disputes over contracts to public tiffs over who deserves credit for what, the two partners have nonetheless succeeded in delivering reliable and not too outrageously priced electricity to 1.1 million customers for nearly eight years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long Island's two energy utilities are enduring a stormy marriage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is probably the most important business relationship on Long Island: KeySpan and the Long Island Power Authority. And it seems like a rocky marriage, with the two sides pulling in different directions and chafing under the vows and prenuptial agreements that bind them. They may be headed for a breakup.</p>
        <p>Those watching from the outside say that despite their troubles, ranging from private disputes over contracts to public tiffs over who deserves credit for what, the two partners have nonetheless succeeded in delivering reliable and not too outrageously priced electricity to 1.1 million customers for nearly eight years.</p>
        <p>''It has always been difficult and contentious -- it's the way it is structured,'' said Ashok Gupta, the director of air and energy programs for the Natural Resources Defense Council in Manhattan. ''That they haven't managed to make things worse with all the havoc is pretty amazing.''</p>
        <p>LIPA's chairman and chief executive, Richard M. Kessel, and KeySpan's chairman and chief executive, Robert B. Catell, are friends, and in separate interviews they brushed off talk that all is not well. ''There are bumps along the way, but over all the relationship is very good,'' Mr. Kessel said. Mr. Catell said that despite the complexities of the situation, ''the good news is that eight years later it's working and it's been great for the consumers.''</p>
        <p>But now a crucial juncture is near for the relationship that couples LIPA, the state-sponsored not-for-profit authority created to succeed the Long Island Lighting Company and contain the cost of electricity for the Island's homes and businesses, and KeySpan, the for-profit corporation that began nearly a century ago as Brooklyn Union Gas and now has visions of becoming the premier energy company in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Decisions are looming about who will own the Island's power plants; when and how they will be repowered, or upgraded to be more efficient and less polluting; how to add generating capacity; and which alternative sources of energy and conservation efforts to pursue. And as these decisions approach, underlying strains that may have a lasting impact on Long Island's energy future are beginning to show more clearly.</p>
        <p>A complete divorce, most agree, could be perilous to the region and is probably not viable. But whether the two entities can get along well enough, in a period when soaring energy costs are becoming an overriding issue for the nation in general and Long Island in particular, remains a question.</p>
        <p>Few doubt the importance of the outcome. ''The relationship between LIPA and KeySpan is absolutely fundamental to the economic well-being of Long Island,'' said Matthew T. Crosson, the president of the Long Island Association, a business group.</p>
        <p>In a sign of the worsening toll of higher energy costs, Mr. Kessel on Sept. 30 announced an increase of 5.5 percent in the existing fuel surcharge, which will cost the average residential electric customer an extra $24 a month. He attributed the new increase to global gas and oil prices and the impact of Hurricane Katrina. LIPA, he said, was absorbing $150 million to avoid an 11.5 percent increase.</p>
        <p>KeySpan is separately passing on higher fuel costs to its natural gas customers, and home heating-oil customers are also paying more. The LIPA rates reflect the cost of imported power and of oil and gas that KeySpan burns at its Long Island plants.</p>
        <p>The higher energy prices and what LIPA and KeySpan can do to lessen the blow are the backdrop for renewed pressure for repowering. That would involve converting one or more KeySpan plants to what is called combined cycle technology, which could roughly double its capacity while using up to 30 percent less natural gas and cutting airborne emissions by up to 90 percent.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York and a leading advocate of repowering, has called on LIPA and KeySpan to report by January on steps to begin repowering, which also has strong support from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>More support for conversion came from the Suffolk County Legislature, which voted unanimously on Sept. 27 for a measure calling for the repowering or rebuilding of KeySpan's Northport plant. The plant, built in the 1960's and 1970's, has four 375-megawatt units fueled by oil and natural gas. Environmental groups have identified it as the second-highest emitter of carbon dioxide among power plants in the Northeast, and the resolution's sponsor, Jon Cooper, Democrat of Lloyd Neck, called the Northport plant a health risk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel and Mr. Catell both expressed interest in a repowering project but said it would have to wait until the Island had enough electricity to take a generating plant out of service during the summer, when electricity demand peaks. Repowering projects are estimated to take 12 to 18 months.</p>
        <p>''If we all of a sudden took away 300 or 400 or 500 megawatts, we would be very close to a dangerous margin if something went wrong,'' Mr. Kessel said.</p>
        <p>But first on LIPA's agenda is a decision, already delayed twice, on whether to buy the electric generators that KeySpan took over when it merged with the Long Island Lighting Company in 1998. That same year, LIPA took over Lilco's transmission and delivery system.</p>
        <p>The takeover deal gave LIPA a one-time option to buy more than 50 KeySpan generators, including aging plants in Northport, Port Jefferson, Island Park, Glenwood Landing and Far Rockaway. The five plants produce more than 4,000 megawatts of electricity and are the backbone of Long Island's electric supply.</p>
        <p>LIPA has until Dec. 15 to decide whether to buy the plants. Both Mr. Kessel and Mr. Catell said a further delay was unlikely.</p>
        <p>KeySpan sells power from the plants to LIPA and manages the LIPA delivery system under an agreement that runs until 2013 and two other contracts that are worth more than $300 million annually.</p>
        <p>KeySpan has more than 4,000 employees, mostly unionized workers in its Long Island electric and gas operations; many are former Lilco employees. LIPA, a thin executive shell over the KeySpan operations, has fewer than 100 employees.</p>
        <p>A takeover of the KeySpan plants would make LIPA one of the largest fully integrated municipal power systems in the country but would also increase what financial analysts say is an already high level of bonded debt -- now $7 billion -- and put pressure on electric rates. KeySpan would continue to own and operate the natural gas delivery system it acquired in the merger with Lilco.</p>
        <p>LIPA is continuing a protracted analysis of its future. It has been a year since it hired Bear Stearns, a financial adviser, as well as Hawkins Delafield &amp; Wood, its bond counsel, and others to study the options. Talks between LIPA and KeySpan are also continuing, but Mr. Kessel and Mr. Catell gave few details.</p>
        <p>Under one option, municipalization, LIPA would buy the KeySpan plants and become a full-scale public power company. A second option, privatization, would involve selling the transmission and delivery system to KeySpan or some other private company. A third option -- and perhaps the most likely -- would maintain the LIPA-KeySpan status quo with some contractual fine-tuning.</p>
        <p>Another possibility would be for LIPA eventually to replace KeySpan with another system manager. KeySpan argues that with its Long Island workforce and experience running the LIPA system, it would be tough to replace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said LIPA was considering all the options, including a purchase of the KeySpan plants. Mr. Catell said KeySpan would await a decision but believed a takeover of its plants would be a mistake.</p>
        <p>''I don't think Richie or the governor would do something that is not in the best interest of the consumer,'' he said of Mr. Kessel. ''The option agreement requires them to pay market value for our plants. I find it very difficult for them to pay market value and still keep rates down.''</p>
        <p>He estimated that the market value of the KeySpan plants would be more than $1 billion.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki brokered the 1998 deal that replaced the Long Island Lighting Company with KeySpan and LIPA. Mr. Kessel serves as the chairman of the LIPA board at Mr. Pataki's pleasure. Mr. Pataki's views on which option LIPA chooses would weigh heavily, many who are following the situation said; he has not publicly disclosed his views.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catell said KeySpan was interested in buying the LIPA transmission and delivery system if LIPA chooses to sell its assets and if the purchase was good for consumers and company shareholders.</p>
        <p>''We think that privatization is a viable option and we think there could be a scenario developed that could be good for the consumer,'' he said. ''But we would have to sit down with LIPA and the other government officials involved and develop that.''</p>
        <p>Such a purchase would make KeySpan Long Island's full-service gas and electric private utility. The company is already the largest distributor of natural gas in the Northeast, where it has 2.6 million customers, including those served by gas utilities it owns in Massachusetts and New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>KeySpan is also the largest generator of electricity in New York, but on Long Island it remains LIPA's hired hand. LIPA officials have been unhappy with a KeySpan advertising campaign that they thought overstated the KeySpan role. Mr. Catell restated the theme in a recent interview. ''I like to think of it as KeySpan essentially being the energy company on Long Island,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel saw it differently. ''In terms of the electric system, LIPA owns the system and we give direction and they follow it,'' he said. ''It's in our contract. We're the electric company, they're the gas company. Get used to it.''</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Kessel, LIPA has reached beyond KeySpan for 330 megawatts of power imported over the Cross Sound Cable from Connecticut and 660 megawatts from the planned Neptune cable from New Jersey, which is due to begin operating in 2007.</p>
        <p>In another move that would bring in power from outside KeySpan, LIPA is also backing a wind turbine complex in an eight-square-mile area off the South Shore, 3.7 miles southwest of Robert Moses State Park. The 40 wind turbines would produce up to 140 megawatts of electricity. The turbine towers would be 260 feet high with blades reaching more than 400 feet high and visible from the shore. The Army Corps of Engineers is reviewing the project.</p>
        <p>A group called the Ad Hoc Save Jones Beach Committee, whose members include several South Shore civic associations, says the project is an offshore industrial park that would forever ruin ocean views. But environmental groups on the Island and beyond strongly support the project.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said the outcome would show whether Long Island was ready to move beyond fossil fuels. ''If we can't stick our feet in the water and say it is time to declare independence from OPEC and the oil companies through this wind project, then I think we have a very bleak economic future in this country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catell, meanwhile, has been trying to win LIPA's support for a ''virtual repowering'' in which KeySpan would build a 250-megawatt combined-cycle generating plant on Spagnoli Road in Melville to allow an older, less efficient unit to shut down. In a combined-cycle plant, waste heat is used to make steam to drive a secondary turbine.</p>
        <p>KeySpan has a state permit to build the plant, but it needs a long-term agreement from LIPA to buy power before it will proceed. After a bidding process for new capacity in which KeySpan competed, though, LIPA backed a 350-megawatt plant that Caithness Energy plans in North Bellport instead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said state law required the bidding. ''I am not going to violate state law because Spagnoli Road may or may not be a good idea,'' he said. ''It did not win, it didn't come close to winning, and I would have no justification for bypassing more economical proposals.''</p>
        <p>He said that repowering older plants might be possible once the Caithness plant and the Neptune cable were operating.</p>
        <p>With future ownership of the aging main plants up to LIPA, KeySpan has had no incentive to repower, Mr. Gupta of the Natural Resources Defense Council said. ''Why would they make the investment, not knowing if they will own them?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Even if KeySpan continues to own the plants, LIPA's participation in repowering would be essential. Mr. Catell said KeySpan would need a long-term agreement from LIPA to buy power before it would undertake a repowering project.</p>
        <p>LIPA could also assist in a financial arrangement with KeySpan that took advantage of its tax-exempt status. ''That certainly would be helpful,'' Mr. Catell said, adding that KeySpan also had the ability to use tax-exempt financing.</p>
        <p>Matthew C. Cordaro, the director of the Center for Management Analysis at the C.W. Post campus of Long Island University, said repowering was overdue and should be given highest priority as LIPA and KeySpan redefine their relationship. ''Whatever the outcome, repowering makes sense,'' said Mr. Cordaro, a former Lilco vice president and the author of a 2002 report detailing how KeySpan plants could be converted to the combined-cycle technology.</p>
        <p>The report identified the E.F. Barrett plant in Island Park as an ideal candidate for conversion. But Mr. Catell and Mr. Kessel gave no hint that they were close to announcing a conversion project there or elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said a LIPA analysis showed lesser advantages from repowering than in Mr. Cordaro's report.</p>
        <p>''I like Matt Cordaro, but he was one of the architects of Shoreham,'' he said, referring to Mr. Cordaro's part as a Lilco executive in promoting the aborted Shoreham nuclear power plant project. ''We are not going to use the analysis of someone who was behind the biggest white elephant in the history of the world.''</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
