<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="25forsumms" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1720195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DE1731F936A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-25</p>
        <p>Iraqi Government Labors To Track Lost Prisoners  The Iraqi government has stepped up its hunt for insurgents, acting on tips from hot lines and rounding up suspects in neighborhoods near bombings. But the influx of new prisoners has overwhelmed the Iraqi authorities, human rights groups say. And while the scandal in Abu Ghraib prison ushered in reforms in American-run jails, the mushrooming Iraqi detention centers operate virtually unchecked.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In a rapidly growing prison population that now totals nearly 13,000 detainees in American military custody and another 12,000 held by Iraqi authorities, the American military is finding it difficult to distinguish insurgents from people rounded up who pose no security threat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Korean Cloner Admits Lying  The South Korean stem cell researcher who won world acclaim as the first scientist to clone a human embryo and extract stem cells from it apologized for lying about the sources of some human eggs used in his research.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pope's Rule Takes Active Turn  For many church experts, Pope Benedict XVI's document banning most gay men from the priesthood was an overdue sign that his papacy would be an active one -- though perhaps quieter, more deliberative and more surprising than many expected when this very subtle man took office seven months ago.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ancient Greenhouse Gases  Shafts of ancient ice pulled from Antarctica's frozen depths show that for at least 650,000 years three important heat-trapping greenhouse gases never reached recent atmospheric levels caused by human activities, scientists are reporting.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>China Blames Oil Company  The Chinese government blamed the country's biggest oil company for a pollution spill that allowed a 50-mile slick of toxic benzene to reach a northern city of almost four million people and threaten the safety of its drinking water.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Iran Referral Delayed for Talks  The International Atomic Energy Agency delayed taking any action on Iran's nuclear program even as the British delegate said that a process described in documents offered to Iran ''has no other application other than the production of nuclear warheads.''</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>U.S. to Close Italy Naval Base  The United States intends to close a base in Italy that is one of its two foreign naval bases that service nuclear submarines, a Navy spokesman confirmed.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>E.U. Rebukes Israeli Policy  The European Union's diplomatic representatives in East Jerusalem and Ramallah have sharply criticized Israel's policies in East Jerusalem, saying they ''are reducing the possibility of reaching a final-status agreement on Jerusalem that any Palestinian could accept.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A26-34</p>
        <p>Most States Experience Better Fiscal Outlooks  After four years of tight budgets and deepening debt, states from California to Maine are experiencing a marked turnaround in their fiscal fortunes. The windfall is leading to the restoration of school financing, investments in long-neglected roads and bridges, debt reduction and the return of money borrowed from cities and counties.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Vanishing Light Poles  Some 130 aluminum light poles have vanished from Baltimore's streets in the last several weeks, the authorities say, presumably sold for scrap metal. But so far the case of the pilfered poles has stumped the police and left many local residents wondering just how someone manages to make off with a metal pole some 30 feet tall.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Ocean Water for Sale  A Japanese company, the Koyo USA Corporation, has begun bottling desalted water pumped from 2,000 feet below the surface of the Pacific Ocean, off the coast of Hawaii, and marketing it to Japanese consumers as the purest, most nutritious beverage on earth. It is selling so fast that Koyo is expanding rapidly to keep pace with demand.</p>
        <p>A30</p>
        <p>Giving Thanks After Hurricane  It was not a traditional Thanksgiving on Salt Bayou. The hostess, who lost her house in Hurricane Katrina, has been sleeping in a van. And the turkey had to be cooked over a barbecue pit. But it was a celebration nonetheless for a band of survivors thrown together by the storm.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Governor's Overstatement  Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico has admitted that his claim to have been a draft pick of the Kansas City A's in 1966 was inaccurate. The claim was included in a brief biography released when Mr. Richardson, a right-handed pitcher who played at Tufts University, successfully ran for Congress in 1982.</p>
        <p>A33</p>
        <p>Nixon's Nuclear Worries  Widely considered a military hawk, President Richard M. Nixon fretted privately over the notion of any no-holds-barred nuclear war, newly released documents from his time at the White House reveal. The recently declassified papers show that Nixon wanted an alternative to the option of full-scale nuclear war.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Balloon Accident Hurts 2 At Thanksgiving Parade  A giant balloon in the Macy's Thanksgiving Day parade, swinging out of control in sudden bursts of wind, struck a light pole in Times Square. Two spectators were injured in a replay of an accident in 1997 that had prompted pledges of safety reforms.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conservative Party at Risk  The Conservative Party in New York, a minor party that has profoundly shaped the state's modern-day politics, is at risk of losing its place on the statewide ballot next year, political analysts say, and some Republicans are openly questioning the value of their longtime alliance with the party.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Four Injured in Fire  At least four people, including a city firefighter, were seriously injured in a blaze at an apartment building in Brooklyn that forced a 16-year old girl to jump out of a third-floor window, the authorities and residents said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-36; E37-44</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTSFRIDAY</p>
        <p>D1-6</p>
        <p>Football Coach Files Suit  The football game between the East Brunswick Bears and the Old Bridge Knights in New Jersey appeared to offer a heaping helping of tradition. But it was not Thanksgiving Day as usual for the Bears, whose coach Marcus Borden filed a lawsuit earlier this week against East Brunswick Public Schools, alleging that the district, by barring Borden from praying alongside his players, has infringed on his constitutional rights.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A37</p>
        <p>Kingsbury Browne  A prominent Boston tax lawyer and outdoorsman whose initiative and knowledge of land trusts spared large and small swaths of the American landscape from headlong development, he was 82.</p>
        <p>A37</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Rift on Rates in Europe  A debate continues over whether the European Central Bank should raise interest rates, with a series of troubling economic reports seeming to challenge the notion that Europe is on a sustainable growth path.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cities on the Move in China  Across China, dozens of cities, including Harbin in the northeast, are relocating their town centers or creating entirely new ones, hoping to revitalize their urban areas and cash in on the real estate surge.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Challenges for W.T.O. Chief  Pascal Lamy, the new director general of the World Trade Organization, faces a number of challenges as he tries to secure an agreement in global trade talks that have been deadlocked for four years.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Slow Progress After Katrina  The ongoing struggles of Liberty Bank and Trust, the largest black-owned bank in New Orleans, underscore how reconstruction of the city's economy is turning out to be slower and more complex than many people first thought.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Advertisers Turn to Blogs  New campaigns from Budget Rent a Car and Hasbro are a sign of the increasing appeal of blogs and other nontraditional media to once-conservative mainstay marketers.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A38-39</p>
        <p>Editorials: The million-year health standard; Bosnia, 10 years later; Verlyn Klinkenborg on demolition.</p>
        <p>Column: Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E28  TV List</p>
        <p>E34-35  Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-25</p>
        <p>Iraqi Government Labors To Track Lost Prisoners  The Iraqi government has stepped up its hunt for insurgents, acting on tips from hot lines and rounding up suspects in neighborhoods near bombings. But the influx of new prisoners has overwhelmed the Iraqi authorities, human rights groups say. And while the scandal in Abu Ghraib prison ushered in reforms in American-run jails, the mushrooming Iraqi detention centers operate virtually unchecked.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In a rapidly growing prison population that now totals nearly 13,000 detainees in American military custody and another 12,000 held by Iraqi authorities, the American military is finding it difficult to distinguish insurgents from people rounded up who pose no security threat.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Korean Cloner Admits Lying  The South Korean stem cell researcher who won world acclaim as the first scientist to clone a human embryo and extract stem cells from it apologized for lying about the sources of some human eggs used in his research.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pope's Rule Takes Active Turn  For many church experts, Pope Benedict XVI's document banning most gay men from the priesthood was an overdue sign that his papacy would be an active one -- though perhaps quieter, more deliberative and more surprising than many expected when this very subtle man took office seven months ago.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ancient Greenhouse Gases  Shafts of ancient ice pulled from Antarctica's frozen depths show that for at least 650,000 years three important heat-trapping greenhouse gases never reached recent atmospheric levels caused by human activities, scientists are reporting.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>China Blames Oil Company  The Chinese government blamed the country's biggest oil company for a pollution spill that allowed a 50-mile slick of toxic benzene to reach a northern city of almost four million people and threaten the safety of its drinking water.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Iran Referral Delayed for Talks  The International Atomic Energy Agency delayed taking any action on Iran's nuclear program even as the British delegate said that a process described in documents offered to Iran ''has no other application other than the production of nuclear warheads.''</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>U.S. to Close Italy Naval Base  The United States intends to close a base in Italy that is one of its two foreign naval bases that service nuclear submarines, a Navy spokesman confirmed.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>E.U. Rebukes Israeli Policy  The European Union's diplomatic representatives in East Jerusalem and Ramallah have sharply criticized Israel's policies in East Jerusalem, saying they ''are reducing the possibility of reaching a final-status agreement on Jerusalem that any Palestinian could accept.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A26-34</p>
        <p>Most States Experience Better Fiscal Outlooks  After four years of tight budgets and deepening debt, states from California to Maine are experiencing a marked turnaround in their fiscal fortunes. The windfall is leading to the restoration of school financing, investments in long-neglected roads and bridges, debt reduction and the return of money borrowed from cities and counties.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Vanishing Light Poles  Some 130 aluminum light poles have vanished from Baltimore's streets in the last several weeks, the authorities say, presumably sold for scrap metal. But so far the case of the pilfered poles has stumped the police and left many local residents wondering just how someone manages to make off with a metal pole some 30 feet tall.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Ocean Water for Sale  A Japanese company, the Koyo USA Corporation, has begun bottling desalted water pumped from 2,000 feet below the surface of the Pacific Ocean, off the coast of Hawaii, and marketing it to Japanese consumers as the purest, most nutritious beverage on earth. It is selling so fast that Koyo is expanding rapidly to keep pace with demand.</p>
        <p>A30</p>
        <p>Giving Thanks After Hurricane  It was not a traditional Thanksgiving on Salt Bayou. The hostess, who lost her house in Hurricane Katrina, has been sleeping in a van. And the turkey had to be cooked over a barbecue pit. But it was a celebration nonetheless for a band of survivors thrown together by the storm.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Governor's Overstatement  Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico has admitted that his claim to have been a draft pick of the Kansas City A's in 1966 was inaccurate. The claim was included in a brief biography released when Mr. Richardson, a right-handed pitcher who played at Tufts University, successfully ran for Congress in 1982.</p>
        <p>A33</p>
        <p>Nixon's Nuclear Worries  Widely considered a military hawk, President Richard M. Nixon fretted privately over the notion of any no-holds-barred nuclear war, newly released documents from his time at the White House reveal. The recently declassified papers show that Nixon wanted an alternative to the option of full-scale nuclear war.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Balloon Accident Hurts 2 At Thanksgiving Parade  A giant balloon in the Macy's Thanksgiving Day parade, swinging out of control in sudden bursts of wind, struck a light pole in Times Square. Two spectators were injured in a replay of an accident in 1997 that had prompted pledges of safety reforms.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conservative Party at Risk  The Conservative Party in New York, a minor party that has profoundly shaped the state's modern-day politics, is at risk of losing its place on the statewide ballot next year, political analysts say, and some Republicans are openly questioning the value of their longtime alliance with the party.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Four Injured in Fire  At least four people, including a city firefighter, were seriously injured in a blaze at an apartment building in Brooklyn that forced a 16-year old girl to jump out of a third-floor window, the authorities and residents said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-36; E37-44</p>
        <p>ESCAPES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTSFRIDAY</p>
        <p>D1-6</p>
        <p>Football Coach Files Suit  The football game between the East Brunswick Bears and the Old Bridge Knights in New Jersey appeared to offer a heaping helping of tradition. But it was not Thanksgiving Day as usual for the Bears, whose coach Marcus Borden filed a lawsuit earlier this week against East Brunswick Public Schools, alleging that the district, by barring Borden from praying alongside his players, has infringed on his constitutional rights.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A37</p>
        <p>Kingsbury Browne  A prominent Boston tax lawyer and outdoorsman whose initiative and knowledge of land trusts spared large and small swaths of the American landscape from headlong development, he was 82.</p>
        <p>A37</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Rift on Rates in Europe  A debate continues over whether the European Central Bank should raise interest rates, with a series of troubling economic reports seeming to challenge the notion that Europe is on a sustainable growth path.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cities on the Move in China  Across China, dozens of cities, including Harbin in the northeast, are relocating their town centers or creating entirely new ones, hoping to revitalize their urban areas and cash in on the real estate surge.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Challenges for W.T.O. Chief  Pascal Lamy, the new director general of the World Trade Organization, faces a number of challenges as he tries to secure an agreement in global trade talks that have been deadlocked for four years.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Slow Progress After Katrina  The ongoing struggles of Liberty Bank and Trust, the largest black-owned bank in New Orleans, underscore how reconstruction of the city's economy is turning out to be slower and more complex than many people first thought.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Advertisers Turn to Blogs  New campaigns from Budget Rent a Car and Hasbro are a sign of the increasing appeal of blogs and other nontraditional media to once-conservative mainstay marketers.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A38-39</p>
        <p>Editorials: The million-year health standard; Bosnia, 10 years later; Verlyn Klinkenborg on demolition.</p>
        <p>Column: Paul Krugman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E28  TV List</p>
        <p>E34-35  Weather</p>
        <p>D7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
