<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No-Confidence Vote in Canada Threatens U.N. Climate Change Meeting</title>
    <meta content="27canada" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/27/international/americas/27canada.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1720789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED61731F934A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No-Confidence Vote in Canada Threatens U.N. Climate Change Meeting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No-Confidence Vote in Canada Threatens U.N. Climate Change Meeting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Nov. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Monday was supposed to be the day Canada took the reins of international environmental leadership, playing host to a United Nations climate change conference in Montreal to begin a critical round of negotiations to decide how the world will confront global warming in the coming decades.</p>
        <p>But now Monday is also the day that Prime Minister Paul Martin's Liberal Party government is expected to fall in a no-confidence vote in the House of Commons. Many of the Canadian cabinet ministers and other members of Parliament who were supposed to attend the conference will now be scurrying to the campaign trail instead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the same day Canada is to play host to a crucial environmental conference, Prime Minister Paul Martin's Liberal Party government is expected to fall in a no-confidence vote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Monday was supposed to be the day Canada took the reins of international environmental leadership, playing host to a United Nations climate change conference in Montreal to begin a critical round of negotiations to decide how the world will confront global warming in the coming decades.</p>
        <p>But now Monday is also the day that Prime Minister Paul Martin's Liberal Party government is expected to fall in a no-confidence vote in the House of Commons. Many of the Canadian cabinet ministers and other members of Parliament who were supposed to attend the conference will now be scurrying to the campaign trail instead.</p>
        <p>''It's the nightmare scenario that environmental activists around the world have been hoping would be avoided,'' said Elizabeth May, executive director of the Sierra Club of Canada. Speaking of Stephane Dion, the country's environment minister -- the chairman of the conference as well as a major political player in the battleground province of Quebec -- Ms. May said, ''He is bound to be just a tad distracted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dion traveled around the world over the last year trying to build a consensus for long-range policies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions scientists have linked to warming. The new round of negotiations in Montreal is aimed at forging a new international agreement on cutting the emissions after 2012, when the Kyoto Protocol expires.</p>
        <p>That agreement, the first treaty requiring participating industrialized countries to reduce emissions, took effect in February and is an addendum to a 1992 pact that set only voluntary targets. The Bush administration rejected it, in part because it requires no reduction of emissions in developing countries. Without binding targets, environmentalists and many scientists warn, greenhouse gas emissions from China, India and other growing economies are likely to soar. Chances of agreement on emissions targets for after 2012 were seen as slim even before Canada's political turmoil intruded.</p>
        <p>''It's not an ideal situation, but the show must go on,'' Mr. Dion said.</p>
        <p>The conference will bring together 10,000 officials and advocates from more than 180 countries. Formally known as COP-11, or the 11th Conference of the Parties, it is an annual meeting of the countries, including the United States, that signed the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change at the 1992 Earth Summit in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dion is supposed to be the leader of the continuing negotiations until the next annual conference. But his tenure as environment minister may be over before he can push ahead with finding common ground between countries, including the United States, that do not want hard long-range targets for emission reductions and countries that do.</p>
        <p>Should the Liberals lose the vote now expected in January, a minister from the Conservative Party -- which is critical of the Kyoto Protocol and rooted in oil-rich Alberta Province -- would probably replace Mr. Dion as president of the conference for the rest of the year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dion, a mild-mannered man who wears a windmill pin on his lapel, has been credited by many environmentalists for his diplomatic skills with China, India and the Bush administration. He has pushed for international efforts to increase innovation like hydrogen fuel cells and methods for capturing carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas, before it is emitted from smokestacks. ''What Canada will attempt to do is reach a rapprochement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If politics were not distraction enough, the government has been buffeted recently by reports by environmental groups attacking its record on water and air pollution.</p>
        <p>A report released by the Pembina Institute and the David Suzuki Foundation noted that Canada was far behind in its pledge to reach Kyoto accord targets. ''Canada's energy policies, which include support for rapid expansion of highly greenhouse gas-intensive activities such as oil sands development, are sharply at odds with our climate policy,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Ms. May, of the Sierra Club, said: ''Using 1990 as the base year, Canada's emissions are now 24 percent higher, while the United States is up by 14 percent. The United States' performance is superior to Canada's, even though it is outside Kyoto.''</p>
        <p>When it signed the Kyoto agreement, Canada agreed to reduce its output of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases by 6 percent below 1990 levels from 2008 to 2012. The original commitment meant cutting emissions by 240 million metric tons a year, but it now needs to cut them by 270 million metric tons annually. The oil production from oil sands -- a far higher emitter of pollution than conventional oil production -- is estimated to triple from the current one million barrels a day by 2015 and sextuple by 2030.</p>
        <p>Canada's target has been made all the more difficult to reach by government arrangements with oil refineries and other large industries to reduce their annual emission cuts to 36 million metric tons from the 55 million metric tons first planned.</p>
        <p>Canada has given tax incentives and other support for renewable energy sources like biomass and tidal power. It has made federal facilities more energy efficient and improved public mass transit. Still, to keep to its Kyoto pledges, Canada will have to offset its high emissions by financing projects that will reduce emissions abroad. But such ''carbon trading'' may cost billions.</p>
        <p>''The deals made with industry was like giving away the store,'' said David L. Anderson, a Liberal member of Parliament and former environment minister. ''The increase in Canadian emissions at one of the higher levels among industrialized countries affects our credibility to discuss future targets.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
