<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Projects in Genetic Data and Physics Win Scholarships</title>
    <meta content="06science" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/06/nyregion/06science.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1722772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DB1331F935A35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Projects in Genetic Data and Physics Win Scholarships</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Science Projects in Genetic Data and Physics Win Scholarships</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As summer interns working at a laboratory in Phoenix, Anne Lee and Albert Shieh, two high school students, came across a problem reading computerized information on the human genome.</p>
        <p>Instead of giving up or switching to a less challenging project, Ms. Lee and Mr. Shieh persevered, and months later developed new software that experts believe may increase the rate of accuracy in genetic data analysis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anne Lee and Albert Shieh, two high school students, won the top prize yesterday as a team in the Siemens Westinghouse Math, Science and Technology competition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As summer interns working at a laboratory in Phoenix, Anne Lee and Albert Shieh, two high school students, came across a problem reading computerized information on the human genome.</p>
        <p>Instead of giving up or switching to a less challenging project, Ms. Lee and Mr. Shieh persevered, and months later developed new software that experts believe may increase the rate of accuracy in genetic data analysis.</p>
        <p>For their accomplishment, Ms. Lee, 17, and Mr. Shieh, 16, won the top prize yesterday as a team in the Siemens Westinghouse Math, Science and Technology competition -- a $100,000 scholarship that they will share.</p>
        <p>Michael Viscardi, a senior from San Diego, also won a $100,000 grand prize for his entry, a project that tackled a centuries-old puzzle in mathematical physics.</p>
        <p>The three were among 19 high school students from across the country who were awarded prizes during the annual competition's finale yesterday at New York University. The Siemens Westinghouse awards are among the nation's most prestigious science prizes, and range in value from $10,000 to $100,000.</p>
        <p>''It's really exciting,'' Mr. Shieh, a junior at Chaparral High School in Scottsdale, Ariz., said after his name was called. ''I'm still kind of in shock.''</p>
        <p>The finalists who were invited to New York for the awards ceremony had already won top honors in a series of regional competitions at six universities last month. More than 1,600 students submitted entries this year -- the greatest number in the competition's history, officials said. (The Siemens Westinghouse competition is separate from the Intel Science Talent Search, which was sponsored by Westinghouse from 1942 to 1998 and is now sponsored by Intel.)</p>
        <p>Peter von Siemens, the great-great-grandson of Werner von Siemens, who founded the Siemens company in the 1840's, commended the students as the next generation of ''great scientific architects.''</p>
        <p>Adam Solomon, a senior at John F. Kennedy High School in Bellmore, on Long Island, won a $40,000 scholarship for his research on brown dwarfs, the dim starlike objects. Another team, Benjamin Pollack and Abhinav Khanna, who are seniors at Plainview-Old Bethpage John F. Kennedy High School on Long Island, won a $50,000 prize for their genetic research on fruit flies.</p>
        <p>Huy Nguyen and Gerald Tiu, from Orange County in California, won a $40,000 scholarship for their research in the field of chemistry and the environment. Growing up close to Los Angeles, the young men said they felt the effects of polluted air early in life, and wanted to devote their spare time to studying the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Ran Li, 17, from Valley Stream on Long Island, developed what he called ''a better Band-Aid'' with his partner, Amardeep Grewal, of Beverly Hills, Mich. They will share a $20,000 scholarship. Their dressing may help in curing wounds that fail to heal on their own. Mr. Li said they were inspired by the number of soldiers in Iraq coming home with serious injuries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
