<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Makes Environment The Focus Of Energy Bill</title>
    <meta content="17ENER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/17/politics/17energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1680823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D6173BF934A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Makes Environment The Focus Of Energy Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Makes Environment the Focus of Energy Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heading toward a collision with the House and White House, the Senate sought Thursday to put an environmentally friendly stamp on its energy legislation as lawmakers and President Bush struggle to agree on an elusive national power policy.</p>
        <p>In an effort to strengthen their hand in looming negotiations with the House, senators voted 52 to 48 to require power companies to use more renewable fuels like wind and solar power to generate electricity. At the same time, the Finance Committee approved a $14 billion tax incentive package that rewards alternative fuels and energy efficiency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heading toward a collision with the House and White House, the Senate sought to put an environmentally friendly stamp on its energy legislation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heading toward a collision with the House and White House, the Senate sought Thursday to put an environmentally friendly stamp on its energy legislation as lawmakers and President Bush struggle to agree on an elusive national power policy.</p>
        <p>In an effort to strengthen their hand in looming negotiations with the House, senators voted 52 to 48 to require power companies to use more renewable fuels like wind and solar power to generate electricity. At the same time, the Finance Committee approved a $14 billion tax incentive package that rewards alternative fuels and energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>''Renewable energy will power our homes and businesses without polluting the air we breathe or the water we drink,'' said Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the Democratic leader.</p>
        <p>But the Senate did not go as far as he and other Democrats had urged, rejecting by a vote of 53 to 47 a Democratic proposal to establish a goal of a 40 percent reduction in oil imports within 20 years. Critics had called the target unattainable and pointed to a provision that calls on the president to try to reduce oil consumption by one million barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Yet the direction the Senate is taking on energy policy is putting it at odds with the House, where longtime oil industry allies have already produced a measure favoring traditional fossil fuels. The Bush administration also opposes the utility requirements approved by the Senate as well as the provision encouraging the drop in oil use.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers acknowledged that the contents of the tax package, which provides an array of tax breaks for alternative power, hybrid vehicles and energy-efficient appliances and home construction, was purposefully written to provide a sharp contrast with the House, where the weight was on tax breaks for the traditional power industry.</p>
        <p>''It was the greenest energy tax bill that the Finance Committee has ever done,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, about the tax plan expected to be incorporated in the overall energy legislation next week. ''If it comes out in the middle, it might be all right.''</p>
        <p>With the approval of the utility requirements, leaders of both parties said it was becoming more likely the Senate would pass its legislation in the days ahead, though potential fights remain over climate-change provisions, offshore oil drilling and where to locate facilities to receive imports of liquefied natural gas.</p>
        <p>But lawmakers are already preparing for the negotiations with the House. Senator Jeff Bingaman of New Mexico, the senior Democrat on the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, said resolving the wide gap between the House and Senate might require the deep involvement of the White House, which has been clamoring for an energy measure.</p>
        <p>''The White House can either be a big help in that process or they can be a hindrance,'' Mr. Bingaman said. ''I hope they will be a help.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bingaman was the chief author of the provision to require utilities to generate at least 10 percent of their electricity with renewable fuels by 2020 to reduce reliance on oil, coal and natural gas while increasing demand for emerging power sources such as wind, solar, biomass, geothermal and even wave energy.</p>
        <p>The Department of Energy would be required to create a market to trade renewable energy credits to allow utilities that cannot generate or purchase enough renewable power to meet the requirement. Currently, about 2 percent of the nation's electricity is estimated to be produced through renewable fuels.</p>
        <p>''The fact is, unless we start thinking about a new energy future, and setting some goals about how and when we ought to get there, we never will,'' said Senator Byron L. Dorgan, Democrat of North Dakota.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the plan said the new requirements would prove costly and disrupt utilities in regions where alternative energy is less available. Senator Lamar Alexander, Republican of Tennessee, said the energy department had estimated the program would cost utilities $18 billion, though Mr. Bingaman said the expense would be offset by less spending on natural gas and other fuels.</p>
        <p>''It's an $18 billion new tax on ratepayers to build tens of thousands of windmills and to spend $11 billion on solar power that would produce one-fifth of 1 percent of all the electricity we need by the year 2025,'' Mr. Alexander said.</p>
        <p>Senator Saxby Chambliss, Republican of Georgia, said he hoped the provision, known as the renewable portfolio standard, would be improved in talks with the House. ''It imposes a one-size-fits-all mandate on the whole country,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
