<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Fire Bell' In the Night</title>
    <meta content="27kristof" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/27/opinion/27kristof.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1705319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Columnist"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Nicholas D Kristof</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD81530F934A1575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Fire Bell' In the Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Fire Bell' in the Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most important decision we'll make in the aftermath of Hurricanes Katrina and Rita isn't whether to rebuild New Orleans. It's how to tackle global warming.</p>
        <p>Today we look back at the presidents who preceded the Civil War, and we can't understand how they could have sat on their hands in the face of a threat that proved so devastating to this country. Someday, I fear, Americans are going to look back at today's leaders and wonder the same thing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most important decision we'll make in the aftermath of the hurricanes isn't whether to rebuild New Orleans. It's how to tackle global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most important decision we'll make in the aftermath of Hurricanes Katrina and Rita isn't whether to rebuild New Orleans. It's how to tackle global warming.</p>
        <p>Today we look back at the presidents who preceded the Civil War, and we can't understand how they could have sat on their hands in the face of a threat that proved so devastating to this country. Someday, I fear, Americans are going to look back at today's leaders and wonder the same thing.</p>
        <p>Wait one second! You're trying to frightify Americans.</p>
        <p>Mr. President! How did you get into my keyboard?</p>
        <p>It was intelligently designed. But you're evadering  -- you know hurricanes aren't about global warming.</p>
        <p>No, Mr. President -- you're the one dodging the issue. Sure, there's no way to link any particular hurricane to global warming. But there's loads of evidence that global warming is already making hurricanes more intense. I don't suppose you saw the report this month in the journal Science that the proportion of hurricanes that are Category 4 or 5 has almost doubled since the 1970's?</p>
        <p>No, er, I missed that one. Laura might've read it.</p>
        <p>And did you see the study published in Nature that says hurricanes have almost doubled in intensity over the last 30 years? Or The Journal of Climate study suggesting that global warming will triple the number of Category 5 hurricanes?</p>
        <p>Ugh, I'm waiting for the movie. But how can we believe these studies? Tree-huggers are always exaggificating. A few decades ago, they talked about global cooling; now they worry about warming. They've got less credibility than my Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Fair enough -- many environmentalists have been far too quick to cry wolf. But the worriers today aren't just greens. They're scientists. They're even your buddies in business. And no wonder -- a new study of insurance industry prospects concluded, ''We are witnessing a precipitous rise in weather-related losses in the U.S., and numerous projections that climate change will likely magnify those losses in the years ahead.'' Why bury your head in the sand?</p>
        <p>Don't be impermanent. This is all unproven, and you may be misoverestimating the danger.</p>
        <p>A person who smokes may not get lung cancer, but that doesn't mean it's prudent to light up. It's nuts to ignore a threat just because it's hard to measure. We spend about $500 billion a year on a military budget, yet we don't want to spend peanuts to protect against climate change, which is a greater potential threat than any foreign military power. And uncertainty cuts both ways: experts expect the seas will rise about 2 feet by 2100, and maybe it'll be less -- but maybe the West Antarctic Ice Sheet will melt and raise the sea level by 20 feet.</p>
        <p>Look, the threat is pretty mushy, and the cost of cutting that carbon would be huge. You volunteering to pay a higher gas tax? To lose your job if the economy takes a hit?</p>
        <p>I used to be suspicious of the Kyoto accord because economic models suggested that it might cost hundreds of billions of dollars to curb greenhouse gas emissions. But it's increasingly clear that there are initial steps we can take to reduce carbon emissions that are very cheap -- like encouraging mass transit, hybrid vehicles, better insulation and energy-efficient light bulbs. One study indicated we could reduce global emissions by one-third for just one-tenth of 1 percent of worldwide G.N.P. That's why mayors and governors are willing to take the lead on this issue, while Washington twiddles its thumbs. Under Bill Richardson, New Mexico just became the first state to join the Chicago Climate Exchange, and committed itself to reduce the state government's greenhouse gas emissions by 4 percent by 2006. There's a leader!</p>
        <p>I don't appreciate your insinufications -- you really irrigate me. What's it to you, anyway? Shouldn't you be hollering about Darfur or someplace else in Asia?</p>
        <p>Mr. President, I've just returned from Louisiana and Mississippi, and I was frankly blown away by what I saw. The old beachfront homes, they're gone. There isn't even rubble left, just empty lots where everything got dragged out to sea. If this hurricane season doesn't wake us up to the dangers ahead, nothing will.</p>
        <p>In 1820, Thomas Jefferson described the extension of slavery in the Missouri Compromise as ''a fire bell in the night'' and a mortal threat to the Union, but a series of ineffective presidents refused to listen or respond as we drifted toward catastrophe. Now, Mr. President, these hurricanes constitute another fire bell in the night, calling on us to act on global warming -- before it's too late.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Columnist</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
