<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summit Leaders Still Differ And Protesters Still Protest</title>
    <meta content="05SUMM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/05/international/europe/05summit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Group of Eight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Edinburgh (Scotland)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland/Edinburgh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Group of Eight</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D71E3AF936A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summit Leaders Still Differ And Protesters Still Protest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Eve of Summit Talks, Leaders and Protesters Prepare</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Politicians and protesters prepare for Group of 8 summit meeting near Edinburgh, Scotland; leaders will focus on two main subjects--climate change and relieving African poverty through changes in policies on trade, aid and debt; Pres Bush, who seems to be at odds with Britain and most other members of group on accepting scientific evidence relating to causes of global warming, damps any expectation that he might reward Prime Min Tony Blair for his support in American effort to prevent terrorism, saying there is no 'quid pro quo'; photo of demonstrators being arrested (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With some signs of discord after a weekend of free rock concerts and celebrity urgings to end Africa's poverty, politicians and protesters prepared Monday for the Group of 8 summit meeting later in the week.</p>
        <p>The leaders of eight major industrial nations are to meet Wednesday through Friday at the luxurious Gleneagles golf estate north of Edinburgh, preoccupied by two main subjects -- climate change and relieving African poverty through changes in policies on trade, aid and debt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaders of the world's most industrialized nations are to meet Wednesday through Friday at a luxurious golf estate in Scotland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With some signs of discord after a weekend of free rock concerts and celebrity urgings to end Africa's poverty, politicians and protesters prepared Monday for the Group of 8 summit meeting later in the week.</p>
        <p>The leaders of eight major industrial nations are to meet Wednesday through Friday at the luxurious Gleneagles golf estate north of Edinburgh, preoccupied by two main subjects -- climate change and relieving African poverty through changes in policies on trade, aid and debt.</p>
        <p>In Edinburgh on Monday police officers drawn from the estimated 10,000 on duty to guard the meeting fought running scuffles with several hundred antiglobalization protesters. No injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>In an interview broadcast Monday on British television, President Bush seemed to damp any expectation that he might reward Prime Minister Tony Blair, the conference host, for his support in the American effort to prevent terrorism.</p>
        <p>''I really don't view our relationship as one of quid pro quo,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Tony Blair made decisions on what he thought was best for keeping the peace and winning the war on terror, as I did. So I go to the G-8 not really trying to make him look bad or good but with an agenda that I think is best for our country.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is generally seen to be at odds with Britain and most other members of the group on accepting the scientific evidence relating to the causes of global warming, and thus on the need for immediate steps to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases. Indeed, the United States is held by other group members to be the world's biggest polluter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's remarks seemed to conflict with a forecast on Sunday by President Jacques Chirac of France that the member countries -- the others are Canada, Germany, Italy, Japan and Russia -- were ''heading toward an agreement'' on global warming.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in London on Monday, Sir Michael Jay, Mr. Blair's representative at talks by senior officials in advance of the meeting, said climate change ''was never going to be an easy discussion,'' and added, ''There are differences of opinion, particularly about the science.''</p>
        <p>Asked about speculation that the meeting might split over climate change and produce two final statements -- one of them representing the United States' view and one agreed by the others -- he said, ''I'm not going to rule in or rule out anything.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush maintained his opposition to deals like the Kyoto Protocol, which set targets for lowering greenhouse gas emissions and which the United States has refused to accept.</p>
        <p>''If this looks like Kyoto, the answer is no,'' he said. ''The Kyoto agreement would have wrecked our economy. I think you can grow your economy and at the same time do a better job of harnessing greenhouse gases. That's exactly what I want to talk to our partners about.''</p>
        <p>His only apparent softening lay in remarks during the interview that climate change represented a ''significant long-term issue that we've got to deal with'' and that the problem was ''to some extent'' a result of human actions.</p>
        <p>At other talks in advance of the summit meeting, Group of 8 countries have apparently made some progress on increasing aid to Africa and canceling debt. But trade, said Sir Michael, the British representative, ''is going to be one of the most difficult issues.''</p>
        <p>In part, that is because a change in trade rules would affect huge farm subsidies in both the United States and the European Union -- an area in which Mr. Bush seemed to suggest the Europeans had more changes to make than the United States.</p>
        <p>''We've got agricultural subsidies, not nearly to the extent that our friends in the E.U. have,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In support of more aid for Africa, campaigners like the former rock singer Bob Geldof urged the leaders to heed the voices of millions of people who flocked to rock concerts across the globe over the weekend or took to the streets. More than 200,000 people demonstrated on Saturday in Edinburgh to reinforce the slogan: Make Poverty History.</p>
        <p>''We are asking them to be great,'' Sir Bob said on Monday, referring to the eight leaders. He said it would be a ''grotesque failure'' if the summit meeting failed to make a breakthrough.</p>
        <p>In Edinburgh, by Monday night, the police said, about 60 people had been arrested after skirmishes between protesters and officers wielding transparent riot-shields. The day of protests paralyzed Princes Street, a main thoroughfare near Edinburgh Castle. Witnesses said that the police, some on horseback, confronted protesters throwing paving stones and park benches. Television showed young children and shoppers caught up in the fray.</p>
        <p>The fighting raised worries among officers about the next few days, when tens of thousands more protesters plan to arrive in Edinburgh and attend a rock concert as the summit meeting formally opens on Wednesday. The police said the violence had been set off by a number of protesters, including some from around Europe.</p>
        <p>Protesters had billed a march through the city as a carnival, but Tom Halpin, a senior Scottish police officer, said the event had not been authorized. ''Those involved were determined to cause as much disruption as possible,'' he told reporters. ''We are facing a hard core of determined activists, supported by hangers-on.</p>
        <p>The leaders of several African countries, including South Africa, Nigeria, Ethiopia, Tanzania, Ghana, Senegal and Algeria, are to meet Friday with Group of 8 leaders.</p>
        <p>African leaders gathered Monday in Libya for a summit meeting of the African Union, whose president, Alpha Oumar Konare of Mali, said Africa would take part in this year's major development meetings ''proud, united and showing solidarity,'' Agence France-Presse reported.</p>
        <p>But he voiced some skepticism: ''Too many promises have been made to us in the course of too many meetings, but none has ever been honored.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Mad Cows and Englishmen</p>
        <p>(By The New York Times) PARIS, July 4 -- President Chirac joked about mad cow diseases and bad English food during a conversation on Sunday in Kaliningrad with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia and Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany, the French daily Libération reported Monday.</p>
        <p>''The only thing they [the British] have ever done for European agriculture is mad cow,'' Mr. Chirac joked, eliciting laughter from Mr. Schröder and Mr. Putin, the newspaper said. As for British food, Mr. Chirac apparently said, ''You can't trust people who cook as badly as that.''</p>
        <p>Asked to comment on the remarks, Mr. Chirac's chief spokesman, Jérôme Bonnafont, said, ''No reaction whatsoever.''</p>
        <p>Relations between France and Britain have been even more strained than usual after the collapse of a European Union summit meeting last month in which Mr. Chirac and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain blamed each other for its failure. Mr. Blair is determined to cut European Union farm subsidies, which mainly benefit France, while Mr. Chirac and other leaders want Britain to give up a generous rebate it receives each year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
