<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utility to Spend $500 Million on Cleanup</title>
    <meta content="08ENVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/08/politics/08enviro.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1655409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Illinois Power Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DC1F3DF93BA35750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utility to Spend $500 Million on Cleanup</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Utility to Spend $500 Million on Cleanup</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Dept says it reached agreement with Illinois Power over Clean Air Act violations that would require utility to spend $500 million on new pollution controls and to pay $9 million in fines, largest penalty imposed on power company for excessive emissions; installation of control devices at five plants is intended to reduce overall levels of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides by 54,000 tons a year; in addition, company agrees to spend $15 million to work on harmful effects of past emissions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department said on Monday that it had reached a settlement with Illinois Power over Clean Air Act violations that would require the utility to spend $500 million on new pollution controls and to pay $9 million in fines, the largest penalty imposed on a power company for excessive emissions.</p>
        <p>The installation of control devices at five plants is intended to reduce overall levels of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides by 54,000 tons a year. In addition, the company agreed to spend $15 million to work on the harmful effects of past emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department said that it reached a settlement with Illinois Power over Clean Air Act violations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department said on Monday that it had reached a settlement with Illinois Power over Clean Air Act violations that would require the utility to spend $500 million on new pollution controls and to pay $9 million in fines, the largest penalty imposed on a power company for excessive emissions.</p>
        <p>The installation of control devices at five plants is intended to reduce overall levels of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides by 54,000 tons a year. In addition, the company agreed to spend $15 million to work on the harmful effects of past emissions.</p>
        <p>''The citizens of Illinois could not have asked for a better result,'' said Thomas L. Sansonetti, assistant attorney general for the Environment and Natural Resources Division at the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>The settlement was the eighth since 1999 in cases in which the government has sued utilities, saying they violated the ''new source review'' provisions of the Clean Air Act. Seven other cases are in litigation involving a requirement to install pollution-reducing equipment any time plants undergo major renovations or expansions.</p>
        <p>The agreement was announced two days before the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee is scheduled to try, for the fourth time, to complete a bill, the Clear Skies Act of 2005, that would set new limits on pollutants and dates to meet them. Backers of the measure say it would eliminate the need for suits that use new source review rules to bring plants into compliance.</p>
        <p>The Clear Skies Act, a major overhaul of the Clean Air Act, is scheduled for a vote on Wednesday. But new source review remains a major point of disagreement.</p>
        <p>Republicans on the committee, as well as industry officials, argue that the Clear Skies bill, by setting specific targets for pollutants, would let producers know precisely when their plants needed to reach compliance, eliminating the need for suits.</p>
        <p>The proponents say settlements like the one with Illinois Power illustrate how complicated and costly litigating emission standards can become. After the suit was filed, Illinois Power became Dynegy Midwest Generation. It has since been acquired by the Ameren Corporation and operates under the name AmerenIP.</p>
        <p>''The results today took over six years to achieve and came at significant cost,'' said Scott Segal, director of the Electric Reliability Coordinating Council, a trade group. ''By contrast, adopting a Clear Skies proposal sets predictable standards and ensures compliance in a cost-effective and relatively litigation-free manner.''</p>
        <p>Democrats on the committee and environmental groups say the standards would be too low and take too long to go into effect, making suits on new source review an effective tool against violators.</p>
        <p>''This proves that the government saves lives by enforcing the Clean Air Act, not by wasting resources trying to weaken it,'' David McIntosh, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, said.</p>
        <p>The committee is also split over including caps on carbon dioxide emissions, which some scientists say cause global warming. The delays have generally reflected the inability of the committee chairman, Senator James M. Inhofe of Oklahoma, to gather a majority to move the bill to the floor. Unofficial counts have consistently produced 9-to-9 ties, with one Republican, Senator Lincoln Chafee of Rhode Island, joining seven Democrats and Senator James M. Jeffords, independent of Vermont, in opposition.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the vote on Wednesday, the Environmental Protection Agency is preparing to complete new regulations for emissions on the pollutants. As rules, rather than laws, they would be more vulnerable to legal challenges that could delay putting them into effect for years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
