<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Rules Set For Emission Of Mercury</title>
    <meta content="16MERC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/16/politics/16mercury.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1657381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Metal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED6123CF935A25750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Rules Set For Emission Of Mercury</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Rules Set for Emission of Mercury</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency releases its final rule on mercury emissions from power plants, asserting that allowing companies to buy and sell right to pollute will encourage control of biggest sources of mercury first; environmentalists who wanted uniform emission limits say new rule means that some plants will end up doing nothing to curb emissions, allowing mercury 'hot spots' to persist, affecting health of people living nearby; economists say cost of eliminating a ton of pollution is lower under EPA's 'cap and trade' system than under blanket rule (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency released its final rule on mercury emissions from power plants on Tuesday, asserting that allowing companies to buy and sell the right to pollute would encourage control of the biggest sources of mercury first.</p>
        <p>Mercury from smokestacks poses a hazard, especially to children and developing fetuses, because it eventually ends up in rivers and lakes, where it is absorbed by fish that are then caught and eaten by people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The E.P.A. asserted that allowing companies to buy and sell the right to pollute would encourage control of the biggest sources of mercury first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency released its final rule on mercury emissions from power plants on Tuesday, asserting that allowing companies to buy and sell the right to pollute would encourage control of the biggest sources of mercury first.</p>
        <p>Mercury from smokestacks poses a hazard, especially to children and developing fetuses, because it eventually ends up in rivers and lakes, where it is absorbed by fish that are then caught and eaten by people.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists said the agency should have simply required uniform emission limits, to reduce concentrations everywhere. They say the new rule means that some plants will end up doing nothing to curb emissions, allowing mercury ''hot spots'' to persist, affecting the health of people living nearby.</p>
        <p>But Jeffrey R. Holmstead, the assistant administrator, defended the ''cap and trade'' system, already used for a pollutant that causes acid rain. ''The highest deposition is in areas where there are concentrations of very large power plants,'' Mr. Holmstead said. ''Because of the economies of scale when it comes to pollution control, all of our analysis and experience with acid rain shows the largest plants are the ones that control the most, and control the soonest.''</p>
        <p>Economists say the cost of eliminating a ton of pollution is lower under cap and trade than under a blanket rule.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists disagreed, though, that the cap-and-trade concept would work for mercury. Fred Krupp, president of Environmental Defense, which is based in New York, said that while other pollutants were under a cap-and-trade system, they were also regulated with ''a cascade of other clean air programs to ensure that health standards are met everywhere.'' In contrast, he said, mercury is a highly potent neurotoxin and this is the only rule that applies to it.</p>
        <p>''In this case trading is just completely inappropriate because of the nature of the pollutant and the lack of other safeguards,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Holmstead said the system gave companies an incentive to start controls early, so they could save up credits and delay final compliance. He predicted that emissions by 2010 would fall to 31 tons, lower than the target of 38 tons. The current level is 48 tons per year.</p>
        <p>On March 10 the Environmental Protection Agency announced a ''clean air interstate rule'' that will further limit emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides, and in controlling those two pollutants, power plants will also be filtering out mercury.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
