<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mixed Views of Ponds To Control Mosquitoes</title>
    <meta content="18limosq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1725706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DC1F31F93BA25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mixed Views of Ponds To Control Mosquitoes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARTIFICIAL ponds, which sometimes spring up in new developments and golf courses, would start appearing in salt marsh tidal wetlands under a sweeping mosquito-control and pesticide-reduction plan that Suffolk County is considering.</p>
        <p>The excavated ponds, up to 100 feet across, and systems of serpentine artificial creeks built to lead to them are part of a technique called open-marsh water management that is central to the plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARTIFICIAL ponds, which sometimes spring up in new developments and golf courses, would start appearing in salt marsh tidal wetlands under a sweeping mosquito-control and pesticide-reduction plan that Suffolk County is considering.</p>
        <p>The excavated ponds, up to 100 feet across, and systems of serpentine artificial creeks built to lead to them are part of a technique called open-marsh water management that is central to the plan.</p>
        <p>The plan is a result of a three-year study that cost the county about $4 million. It involved a pilot project begun last year at the Wertheim National Wildlife Refuge in Shirley, where 11 ponds and connecting creeks were excavated in a 165-acre test area.</p>
        <p>The county and the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, the refuge manager, said the pilot project showed that the county plan could control mosquitoes and reduce pesticide use.</p>
        <p>But critics, including environmental groups, said that the study period was too short and that the plan lacked specifics.</p>
        <p>If approved by a county panel, the County Legislature and the state, the plan will introduce the open-marsh technique on Long Island for the first time, initially on at least 4,000 of the 17,000 acres of wetlands left in the county. Material excavated to make room for the ponds and creeks would be used to fill in ditches formerly used for mosquito control.</p>
        <p>County officials would assess 9,000 acres for future open-marsh water management. Ditches on the remaining 4,000 acres would be allowed to fill in naturally.</p>
        <p>Most of the remaining wetlands are on the South Shore and along the Peconic Bays, some are along Long Island Sound, and some are in each of Suffolk's 10 towns.</p>
        <p>Steve Levy, the Suffolk County executive, and county health and environmental officials say that the open-marsh approach will reduce mosquitoes by providing habitat for larvae-eating fish in wetlands where mosquitoes breed. Michael Deering, the county's director of environmental affairs, said the plan met the county's goal of using progressive methods to reduce the use of chemicals and improve wetland habitats.</p>
        <p>Areas identified as breeding grounds would be excavated for ponds, which fish, including minnowlike killifish, would reach by swimming up the artificial creeks built at the same time.</p>
        <p>If all went according to expectation, the fish would gobble up mosquito larvae, reducing the need for larvicides and spraying for adult mosquitoes. The county said that would also reduce the risks to the public of mosquito-borne illnesses, including West Nile virus and the rarely seen Eastern equine encephalitis.</p>
        <p>The county and others involved in the studies for the plan said the ponds and creeks would also provide habitat for ducks, migratory birds and other wildlife.</p>
        <p>Craig Kessler, the manager of conservation programs for Ducks Unlimited in Stony Brook, said what he called the success of the Wertheim refuge's pilot project, which the county paid the group to assist in, mirrored successes in marshlands in New Jersey, Connecticut and Massachusetts. Ducks Unlimited promotes habitats for wildfowl.</p>
        <p>But the proposal, which is at the core of a long-term plan that would determine far into the future how the county battles mosquitoes and manages wetlands, is encountering opposition questioning whether the open-marsh technique will unleash a mechanized march that will harm or destroy wetlands in the name of mosquito and disease control.</p>
        <p>''The county is proposing to manage the wetlands to reduce the mosquito population when it should be managing them to enhance their value and function,'' said Adrienne Esposito, the executive director of Citizens Campaign for the Environment in Farmingdale. She said the county had exaggerated the public health benefits of mosquito control to advance the plan.</p>
        <p>Sarah Newkirk, the coastal project director for the Long Island chapter of the Nature Conservancy in Cold Spring Harbor, said that the plan lacked details about mosquito spraying. ''It is not really specific enough so the public can understand why the county makes a specific mosquito-control decision,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The plan needs permits from the State Department of Environmental Conservation, which may raise questions.</p>
        <p>''The department is very interested in activities designed to restore tidal wetlands,'' said Peter A. Scully, the department's Long Island regional director. ''And we would be concerned about activities which could degrade wetlands or cause losses of wetland vegetation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deering, the county's environmental affairs director, said that each pond project would be extensively reviewed before work began and that he welcomed debate on the plan.</p>
        <p>''This was always expected to be a contentious issue,'' he said. ''We look forward to a productive dialogue.''</p>
        <p>The ponds and creeks would replace a ditching system, dating to the 1930's, designed to drain wetlands of standing water where mosquitoes breed. Though many of the 750 miles of ditches have deteriorated, they are blamed for drying out wetlands and harming marine life and wildlife.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy has ordered an end to ditching, and Kevin McAllister, the president of Peconic Baykeeper in Riverhead, said the county was right to do so.</p>
        <p>''But instead of digging ditches, are we now going to dig holes of the same magnitude?'' he said. ''You will be removing biomass that took centuries to develop, and in carving out these large ponds, that biomass will be forever lost and replaced by standing water.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McAllister, a longtime critic of the county's mosquito-control programs and chemicals used in them, said the lost vegetation also decreased a wetland's ability to filter pollutants.</p>
        <p>The plan was made public by the county in November and is now before the Council on Environmental Quality, a panel within the county's Planning Department. If the council accepts the environmental study, the plan will go to the County Legislature.</p>
        <p>At a council session in Hauppauge on Dec. 8, Councilman John Potente showed aerial photographs that he said demonstrated the damage ponds can cause in wetlands.</p>
        <p>Dr. Potente, a dentist from Hauppauge and a board member of the Long Island Botanical Society, said that the Suffolk plan would permit the use of heavy equipment to excavate and remove undisturbed wetlands. ''Go in, find out where the mosquitoes are, and go to town,'' he said, describing what would happen.</p>
        <p>Some other council members also voiced reservations about the plan.</p>
        <p>Some critics of open-marsh water management say adding ponds and creeks to wetlands already at risk from rising sea levels because of global warming makes no sense.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kessler, of Ducks Unlimited, said the county had to act in the present. ''In another 75 years, the sea might rise three centimeters,'' he said. ''You'll be dead, I'll be dead and everyone on Long Island will be dead. They are charged with managing the marsh now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
