<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="28bizdigest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1728004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E1D71230F93BA15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Former Enron Accountant to Plead Guilty And Could Testify Against Other Executives  In a reversal that transforms the criminal case involving Enron's former top officers, the company's former chief accounting officer has reached an agreement with prosecutors to plead guilty to violating federal law during his employment there, people briefed on the decision said. As a result of the deal, the former officer, Richard Causey, could serve as a witness for the government in the coming trial of two other executives, Kenneth Lay and Jeffrey Skilling. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>F.D.A. Warns Guidant of New Product Restrictions  The Food and Drug Administration released a warning letter it sent to the Guidant Corporation, restricting the ability of the troubled heart device maker to win approval for some new products. In its letter the agency said Guidant has not fully responded to its concerns about manufacturing procedures at the company's biggest facility. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Food Marketers Increase Exposure of Healthful Foods  With health problems like diabetes, high blood pressure, arthritis and digestive disorders all on the rise, a growing number of food marketers are selling what the food industry calls functional foods, which promise a host of health benefits, from cholesterol reduction to immunity boosts to cures for intestinal problems. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A Marketer's Work for Mexico Upsets Conservatives  Rob Allyn, a longtime Republican political strategist, has signed on to lead a campaign to strengthen the image of Mexico in the United States as an immigration bill winds through Congress, upsetting conservatives and Mexican Americans alike. Advertising. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Verizon's Stock Price Might Be Losing Its Edge  For the past few years, Verizon's stock has traded more than 30 percent above its Baby Bell peers because investors felt it had more valuable customers and because its cellular group, Verizon Wireless, was the industry's most profitable. But that premium might be fading. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Regulators Threaten Actions Against Refco Securities  Regulators have told the broker-dealer Refco Securities they may take action against it unless it gives customers immediate access to their accounts and property, its bankrupt parent, Refco, said in a court filing this week. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Fines by Brokerage Regulator Rose 21% This Year  The regulatory group for the brokerage industry says fines collected from its disciplinary actions this year increased 21 percent over 2004 as it brought more cases and stepped up scrutiny of mutual fund sales. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Scrushy Asks for Separate Trial in a Bribery Case  Richard M. Scrushy, founder of the HealthSouth Corporation, has asked to be tried separately from other defendants on charges that he arranged $500,000 in bribes to former Alabama Governor Don Siegelman. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Fall as Bond Prices Cause Concern  Stocks tumbled as the bond market gave signals that in the past have preceded economic slowdowns. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 105.50 points, to 10,777.77. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 12.12 points, to 1,256.54; the Nasdaq composite index fell 22.53 points, to 2,226.89. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Japanese Consumer Prices Post First Rise in Two Years  The Japanese government said consumer prices rose in November for the first time in two years, offering what economists called the most convincing sign yet that the country's bout of crippling price declines was ending. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Gazprom and Ukraine Heighten Dispute Over Gas  A dispute between Ukraine and Gazprom, Russia's state-owned natural gas monopoly, grew more intense as Ukraine threatened to take a portion of Russian gas exports to Europe and Gazprom, which plans to more than quadruple the price of natural gas exports to Ukraine, called such a move theft. [C5.]</p>
        <p>The most outspoken of President Vladimir V. Putin's senior advisers abruptly resigned on Tuesday, warning that Russia's nascent political freedoms have been lost and the Kremlin's economic choices have been poor. The adviser, Andrei N. Illarionov, left, also said he had no more ability to influence the government's course. [A8.]</p>
        <p>A Kyoto Protocol Paradox Means a Payoff for a Polluter  Russia's electricity monopoly, the world's largest polluter, hopes to receive $1 billion as a result of a paradox in the Kyoto Protocol on reducing emissions of global warming gases. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Goldman Sachs Excluded From Asset Role in Japan  The Japanese postal system, Japan Post, which operates the world's largest savings bank, said it would exclude the Goldman Sachs Group when it next selects asset managers to offer investment trusts to customers because Goldman's asset management broke Japan's investment advisory rules. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Former Enron Accountant to Plead Guilty And Could Testify Against Other Executives  In a reversal that transforms the criminal case involving Enron's former top officers, the company's former chief accounting officer has reached an agreement with prosecutors to plead guilty to violating federal law during his employment there, people briefed on the decision said. As a result of the deal, the former officer, Richard Causey, could serve as a witness for the government in the coming trial of two other executives, Kenneth Lay and Jeffrey Skilling. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>F.D.A. Warns Guidant of New Product Restrictions  The Food and Drug Administration released a warning letter it sent to the Guidant Corporation, restricting the ability of the troubled heart device maker to win approval for some new products. In its letter the agency said Guidant has not fully responded to its concerns about manufacturing procedures at the company's biggest facility. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Food Marketers Increase Exposure of Healthful Foods  With health problems like diabetes, high blood pressure, arthritis and digestive disorders all on the rise, a growing number of food marketers are selling what the food industry calls functional foods, which promise a host of health benefits, from cholesterol reduction to immunity boosts to cures for intestinal problems. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A Marketer's Work for Mexico Upsets Conservatives  Rob Allyn, a longtime Republican political strategist, has signed on to lead a campaign to strengthen the image of Mexico in the United States as an immigration bill winds through Congress, upsetting conservatives and Mexican Americans alike. Advertising. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Verizon's Stock Price Might Be Losing Its Edge  For the past few years, Verizon's stock has traded more than 30 percent above its Baby Bell peers because investors felt it had more valuable customers and because its cellular group, Verizon Wireless, was the industry's most profitable. But that premium might be fading. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Regulators Threaten Actions Against Refco Securities  Regulators have told the broker-dealer Refco Securities they may take action against it unless it gives customers immediate access to their accounts and property, its bankrupt parent, Refco, said in a court filing this week. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Fines by Brokerage Regulator Rose 21% This Year  The regulatory group for the brokerage industry says fines collected from its disciplinary actions this year increased 21 percent over 2004 as it brought more cases and stepped up scrutiny of mutual fund sales. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Scrushy Asks for Separate Trial in a Bribery Case  Richard M. Scrushy, founder of the HealthSouth Corporation, has asked to be tried separately from other defendants on charges that he arranged $500,000 in bribes to former Alabama Governor Don Siegelman. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Fall as Bond Prices Cause Concern  Stocks tumbled as the bond market gave signals that in the past have preceded economic slowdowns. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 105.50 points, to 10,777.77. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 12.12 points, to 1,256.54; the Nasdaq composite index fell 22.53 points, to 2,226.89. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Japanese Consumer Prices Post First Rise in Two Years  The Japanese government said consumer prices rose in November for the first time in two years, offering what economists called the most convincing sign yet that the country's bout of crippling price declines was ending. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Gazprom and Ukraine Heighten Dispute Over Gas  A dispute between Ukraine and Gazprom, Russia's state-owned natural gas monopoly, grew more intense as Ukraine threatened to take a portion of Russian gas exports to Europe and Gazprom, which plans to more than quadruple the price of natural gas exports to Ukraine, called such a move theft. [C5.]</p>
        <p>The most outspoken of President Vladimir V. Putin's senior advisers abruptly resigned on Tuesday, warning that Russia's nascent political freedoms have been lost and the Kremlin's economic choices have been poor. The adviser, Andrei N. Illarionov, left, also said he had no more ability to influence the government's course. [A8.]</p>
        <p>A Kyoto Protocol Paradox Means a Payoff for a Polluter  Russia's electricity monopoly, the world's largest polluter, hopes to receive $1 billion as a result of a paradox in the Kyoto Protocol on reducing emissions of global warming gases. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Goldman Sachs Excluded From Asset Role in Japan  The Japanese postal system, Japan Post, which operates the world's largest savings bank, said it would exclude the Goldman Sachs Group when it next selects asset managers to offer investment trusts to customers because Goldman's asset management broke Japan's investment advisory rules. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
