<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paperback Row</title>
    <meta content="11bestpaper-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1723800"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DD1231F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paperback Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ihsan Taylor</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PREP, by Curtis Sittenfeld. (Random House, $13.95.) Sittenfeld's sharp debut novel is a four-year, semester-by-semester tour of Ault, a fictional private boarding school in Massachusetts. Her heroine, Lee Fiora, is a Midwestern scholarship student thrust into a world of privilege. Our reviewer, Elissa Schappell, praised the ''incisive and evenhanded way'' Sittenfeld explores questions of class. In this issue, the Book Review names ''Prep'' one of the year's best books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PREP, by Curtis Sittenfeld. (Random House, $13.95.) Sittenfeld's sharp debut novel is a four-year, semester-by-semester tour of Ault, a fictional private boarding school in Massachusetts. Her heroine, Lee Fiora, is a Midwestern scholarship student thrust into a world of privilege. Our reviewer, Elissa Schappell, praised the ''incisive and evenhanded way'' Sittenfeld explores questions of class. In this issue, the Book Review names ''Prep'' one of the year's best books.</p>
        <p>JUST ENOUGH LIEBLING: Classic Work by the Legendary New Yorker Writer, by A. J. Liebling. (North Point, $15.) This is a judicious sampling of Liebling's (1904-63) vast body of work. The anthology is divided into six sections: pieces about Paris and about food; articles on the press; dispatches from World War II; writing about New York; boxing stories; and excerpts from ''The Earl of Louisiana,'' about Gov. Earl Long, Huey's brother.</p>
        <p>THE CLERKENWELL TALES, by Peter Ackroyd. (Anchor, $13.95.) Ackroyd's London melodrama, set in 1399, draws assorted characters -- and a bit of structure -- from Chaucer's ''Canterbury Tales,'' and situates them within the story of Sister Clarice, a mad nun in Clerkenwell who prophesies the death of King Richard II and the demise of the church.</p>
        <p>BOILING POINT: How Politicians, Big Oil and Coal, Journalists, and Activists Are Fueling the Climate Crisis -- and What We Can Do to Avert Disaster, by Ross Gelbspan. (Basic Books, $13.95.) Denouncing the oil and coal industries as ''criminals against humanity,'' Gelbspan, a former Boston Globe reporter and editor, also indicts the American media as dupes for treating global warming as a matter of open conjecture. ''Gelbspan's point is a powerful one and well argued,'' Al Gore wrote here.</p>
        <p>MEN AND CARTOONS: Stories, by Jonathan Lethem. (Vintage Contemporaries, $12.95.) Like Lethem's novel ''The Fortress of Solitude,'' this collection of old and new stories blends the literary with the fantastical. ''Super Goat Man,'' which our reviewer, Jay McInerney, called ''strangely poignant,'' is a deadpan evocation of the mediocre superhero next door: ''For us, as we ran and screamed and played secret games on the sidewalk,'' recalls the narrator, ''Super Goat Man was only another of the men who sat on the stoops in sleeveless undershirts on hot summer days.''</p>
        <p>THE KNOW-IT-ALL: One Man's Humble Quest to Become the Smartest Person in the World, by A. J. Jacobs. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $14.) Arranging his chapters alphabetically according to entries in the Encyclopaedia Britannica, Jacobs humorously recalls his quest to read all 32 volumes (44 million words), and describes the venture's effects on his marriage and his complicated relationship with his father.</p>
        <p>THE BOYS OF WINTER: The Untold Story of a Coach, a Dream, and the 1980 U.S. Olympic Hockey Team, by Wayne Coffey. (Three Rivers, $13.) Coffey combines detailed portraits of Coach Herb Brooks and his improbable team with a play-by-play analysis of their victory over the Russians.</p>
        <p>THE MOVIES OF MY LIFE, by Alberto Fuguet. Translated by Ezra E. Fitz. (Rayo/HarperCollins, $12.95.) In Fuguet's novel of shifting realities, Beltrán Soler, a Chilean seismologist on a trip to Japan, abruptly extends his layover in Los Angeles. Shut up in a hotel room, he pieces together the story of his childhood through a catalog of movies that influenced him at pivotal moments.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN BRUTUS: John Wilkes Booth and the Lincoln Conspiracies, by Michael W. Kauffman. (Random House, $15.95.) In this vivid telling, Booth was a flamboyant actor who fervently supported the South. Kauffman reconstructs Booth's scheme to topple the Union government (the vice president and secretary of state were also targeted) and the tumult that unfolded in its aftermath. Our reviewer, Jay Winik, called ''American Brutus'' a ''thoroughly researched book'' about the ''9/11 analogue of a previous era.''</p>
        <p>THE DEVIL'S HIGHWAY: A True Story, by Luis Alberto Urrea. (Back Bay/Little, Brown, $13.95.) This incisive report tracks 26 Mexican men who in May 2001 attempted to cross the United States border through a stretch of Arizona desert commonly called the Devil's Highway. They were abandoned by their guides under a scorching sun, and only 12 survived.</p>
        <p>Ihsan Taylor</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
