<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Somber Notes From a Weary Bill Clinton</title>
    <meta content="04HEFF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/04/arts/04hrff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1677445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="RADIO REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Public Radio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heffernan, Virginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Public Radio</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DF1438F937A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Somber Notes From a Weary Bill Clinton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Somber Notes From a Weary Bill Clinton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia Heffernan reviews NPR Talk of the Nation program that featured excerpt of 2004 speech by former Pres Bill Clinton followed by live broadcast with Clinton (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Politicians talk differently when no polls are at stake. In a 2004 speech by former President Bill Clinton, excerpted yesterday on NPR's ''Talk of the Nation,'' he sounded low-key, almost indifferent. He cautioned against overextending ourselves militarily. Moreover, he explained, ''for good or ill, we live in an interdependent world.''</p>
        <p>''For good or ill.'' No polemic there. It was almost as if -- and this is hard to contemplate -- he didn't care what we thought of him. In the live broadcast that followed the excerpts, Mr. Clinton returned to the same tone, though this time he sounded not just blasé but also utterly exhausted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>During Mr. Clinton's first live turn on an hourlong NPR series, his voice expressed a beaten-down, country-music melancholy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Politicians talk differently when no polls are at stake. In a 2004 speech by former President Bill Clinton, excerpted yesterday on NPR's ''Talk of the Nation,'' he sounded low-key, almost indifferent. He cautioned against overextending ourselves militarily. Moreover, he explained, ''for good or ill, we live in an interdependent world.''</p>
        <p>''For good or ill.'' No polemic there. It was almost as if -- and this is hard to contemplate -- he didn't care what we thought of him. In the live broadcast that followed the excerpts, Mr. Clinton returned to the same tone, though this time he sounded not just blasé but also utterly exhausted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is on a midsize media tour these days, talking up his adventures as a United Nations envoy for tsunami relief; reminding audiences that his memoir, ''My Life,'' will soon be available in paperback; and giving observers a chance to size up his health. His affecting appearance on ''Talk of the Nation'' was the sole radio component of the tour, as well as Mr. Clinton's first live turn on an hourlong NPR series. (The broadcast can be heard at www.npr.org.)</p>
        <p>For such an auspicious NPR occasion, it's a good thing that the questioners who called in were the cream of public radio's crop of famously left-leaning listeners. Among the first was a ''western liberal'' who said he lived ''on an island'' and thus was out of touch with what Americans thought; he wondered if Mr. Clinton might fill him in. (What he most wanted to know: Is everyone in America really, really intolerant now?) Later in the broadcast, a woman introduced herself by saying, ''I'm a playwright, and I'm an American.'' She was on her way to France, she said, and was concerned about having to sit through the anti-American tirades of her French friends, though she often agreed with them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton seemed to sympathize. He suggested that she use her friends' remarks as the opening to a frank discussion of both governments' strengths and weaknesses.</p>
        <p>Strained, hoarse and even doleful at times, Mr. Clinton's voice expressed a beaten-down, country-music melancholy, even as he reeled off facts and figures with his usual confidence. He laughed only once -- at the playwright's reference to French arrogance -- and he refrained from banter with the hosts, Neal Conan and Ira Flatow, who split a string of no-nonsense questions. Though Mr. Clinton insisted straightaway that tales of his fatigue on a recent trip to the Maldives had been exaggerated, he admitted that he had ''not quite 100 percent'' recovered from bypass surgery in September.</p>
        <p>Certain statements also conveyed moral exhaustion as Mr. Clinton discussed issues from stem-cell research to torture: ''It may be that I should have done more.'' ''I think we did about all we could.'' ''The country is growing a little weary of these cultural war elections.'' And finally, ''if you beat people bad enough, they'll confess anything.''</p>
        <p>He summed up his greatest regret about his current life: ''All I know is what I read,'' he said. ''I'm not in the line of information anymore.''</p>
        <p>To be out of the line of information can't be easy for this data-loving former president, who nonetheless supplied a stream of facts about tsunami relief, environmental policy, welfare reform, Rwanda, Darfur, gay marriage, gays in the military, hydrogen, health care and nuclear energy.</p>
        <p>Referring to one of his most recent initiatives to encourage service, a Davos-like conference to be held in New York City, Mr. Clinton said he planned to make participants promise to take action on one of four matters: poverty, AIDS and ignorance (that was one); climate change and global warming; religious reconciliation; or the quality of governing in fragile countries.</p>
        <p>With this lineup, Mr. Clinton, the polymath, seemed to have successfully found names for the four areas of global experience that for now concern him most.</p>
        <p>Strikingly, though Mr. Clinton deplored the influence of ''cultural conservatives and religious fundamentalists'' on American politics, he also expressed compassion for followers of those movements. ''A lot of people feel that our culture is not only decadent but uncaring,'' he said, because they're ''having to raise their children in a hostile world.'' Megachurches, he continued, offer an antidote to loneliness and fear.</p>
        <p>In a rare moment of enthusiasm in the broadcast, Mr. Clinton said of the churches, ''They're delightful places to be inside.''</p>
        <p>RADIO REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
