<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Automaker Mantra: Emissions? What Emissions?</title>
    <meta content="22ADCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/22/business/media/22adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1659020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising (Times Column)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toyota Motor Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bavarian Motors Works</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DC1F3CF931A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Automaker Mantra: Emissions? What Emissions?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Automaker Mantra: Emissions? What Emissions?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, March 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertising column on new campaign by several automakers, including Toyota, Ford and BMW, aimed at politicians that asserts that automobiles are 'virtually emission-free'; coalition is suing California to block new regulation to curb global warming emissions and is continuing to lobby against tougher fuel economy regulations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several automakers, among them Toyota, Ford Motor and BMW, are financing an advertising campaign aimed at politicians that asserts that automobiles are ''virtually emission-free.''</p>
        <p>The campaign is part of an effort by a broad coalition of automakers to present their vehicles as environmentally benign at a time when the coalition is suing California to block a new regulation to curb global warming emissions and is continuing to lobby in Washington against tougher fuel economy regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several automakers are financing an advertising campaign aimed at politicians that asserts that automobiles are "virtually emission-free."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several automakers, among them Toyota, Ford Motor and BMW, are financing an advertising campaign aimed at politicians that asserts that automobiles are ''virtually emission-free.''</p>
        <p>The campaign is part of an effort by a broad coalition of automakers to present their vehicles as environmentally benign at a time when the coalition is suing California to block a new regulation to curb global warming emissions and is continuing to lobby in Washington against tougher fuel economy regulations.</p>
        <p>A print version of the ad has appeared in Congressional journals like Roll Call, Congress Daily and Congressional Quarterly, as well as the industry trade publication Automotive News, according to the Alliance of Automobile Manufacturers, the lobbying group behind the campaign. A radio version of the ad has run on WTOP, a station in Washington.</p>
        <p>The ads have ignited a countercampaign by the Union of Concerned Scientists, an environmental group that says its efforts have generated 20,000 complaints asking the Federal Trade Commission to investigate whether the industry is making misleading claims.</p>
        <p>While regulations have indeed forced automakers to act against emissions of smog-forming pollutants, the advertisements essentially ignore greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide as an automotive emission. Smog-forming emissions also remain a public health issue, according to environmental and consumer groups, as the number of vehicles on the road continues to increase with the population.</p>
        <p>''Our advertising-practices division and our enforcement division are both aware of the ad and the campaign by U.C.S.,'' said Mitch Katz, a spokesman for the trade commission. ''We are evaluating the complaints we've received right now, but we don't have anything to say at this point.''</p>
        <p>He declined to say how many complaints the commission received.</p>
        <p>The auto alliance includes most major automakers: Toyota, General Motors, Ford, DaimlerChrysler, Mazda, BMW, Mitsubishi, Porsche and Volkswagen.</p>
        <p>The advertisements appear to be a turnabout from previous public statements by automakers regarding concerns about vehicle emissions.</p>
        <p>In a speech last August, Toyota's president, Fujio Cho, said that levels of both smog-forming emissions and greenhouse gas emissions remained significant enough that reducing them was a business imperative.</p>
        <p>''If automakers don't reduce smog-forming emissions, greenhouse gases and the need for petroleum, I believe we won't be in business,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The print version of the alliance ad shows a picture of a toddler sitting in a car seat eating a Popsicle.</p>
        <p>''Your car may never be spotless but it's 99 percent cleaner than you think,'' the ad says. ''Autos manufactured today are virtually emission-free. And that's a dramatic improvement over models from just thirty years ago.''</p>
        <p>Gloria Bergquist, a spokeswoman for the alliance, said the ad's use of the term ''virtually emission-free'' should be understood to refer only to emissions classified as pollutants by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Whether greenhouse gases are considered pollutants is a politically charged issue. While the Clinton administration determined that carbon dioxide is a pollutant, the Bush administration reversed the decision. Several states and environment groups are suing to force the E.P.A. to regulate carbon dioxide emissions as pollutants.</p>
        <p>But David Friedman, research director for the clean vehicles program at the Union of Concerned Scientists, said the advertisement itself made no such distinction -- it simply called vehicles ''virtually emission-free.''</p>
        <p>''It reminds you of the cigarette makers,'' he said. ''They're trying to hide the harmful emissions coming from their vehicles.''</p>
        <p>Though some cars on the road today are considered to emit roughly 99 percent fewer smog-forming particles than cars did in the pre-regulatory 1960's, Ms. Bergquist said in an interview that the statement could not be broadly applied to all new cars and trucks until new regulations of such emissions take effect by the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>Automotive emissions of greenhouse gases, however, have been rising for two reasons: the number of vehicles is increasing, and average fuel economy has declined since the late 1980's because of surging sales of sport utility vehicles and big pickup trucks. According to the E.P.A., carbon dioxide (CO2) and other greenhouse gas emissions from cars and light-duty trucks have risen about 20 percent since 1990, to 1.1 billion metric tons in 2003.</p>
        <p>Many scientists have raised potentially serious health concerns related to global warming, though there are dissenters. Most major automakers, however, have said in other forums that they do take the issue of global warming emissions quite seriously. In DaimlerChrysler's 2004 environmental report, for instance, the chief executive, Jürgen Schrempp, said in an opening statement that reducing ''CO2 emissions is the central topic as we strive for sustainable mobility.''</p>
        <p>But Dennis Fitzgibbons, a spokesman for Daimler in Washington, said last Thursday that the alliance's advertisement referred to emissions ''that have health-based effects that are defined under the Clean Air Act.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Toyota, an alliance member that has spent millions of dollars building a public image as an environmentally conscious company, dismissed the notion that greenhouse gases should be considered in the context of an ad that claimed autos were ''emission free.''</p>
        <p>''I think you're mixing apples and oranges,'' said Martha Voss, a Toyota spokeswoman. ''CO2 is technically an emission, but not a pollutant.''</p>
        <p>Toyota's most recent environmental report dwelled at length on the company's efforts to reduce global warming emissions.</p>
        <p>''We can no longer afford to ignore the signs of global warming,'' Josephine Cooper, the company's vice president for government and industry affairs, stated in the report.</p>
        <p>Ford's chairman and chief executive, William Clay Ford Jr., has long been one of the most outspoken executives in Detroit about the subject. His company published a newspaper advertisement in 2001 that read: ''Global warming. There. We said it.''</p>
        <p>In his company's environmental report last year he wrote that he had asked executives ''to develop a sensible approach to the issues of climate change, energy security and fuel economy.''</p>
        <p>The project was ''a key element in building our company for the next 100 years.''</p>
        <p>Privately, Ford executives laid out an internal goal last year to improve fuel economy 80 percent by 2030 as part of a plan to halt growth in global warming emissions.</p>
        <p>''Clearly automakers have made great strides in reducing E.P.A.-targeted pollutants,'' Oscar Suris, a Ford spokesman, said last week.. ''We are engaged in a meaningful dialogue on climate change that needs to continue.''</p>
        <p>Not all automakers appeared to agree with the alliance's blanket assessment that cars are now ''virtually emission-free.'' Honda, which is not an alliance member and has long been independent in its stance, said in a statement last Thursday that ''today's vehicles in many cases are virtually emissions-free with regards to smog-forming'' gases. ''However, CO2 emissions remain a significant contributor to global warming trends.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
