<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blair, Due to Meet Bush, Will Push 2 Issues</title>
    <meta content="07DIPL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/07/politics/07diplo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1678365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D71238F934A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blair, Due to Meet Bush, Will Push 2 Issues</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Bush Talks, Blair to Push Africa Aid and Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, in his first visit to the United States since winning re-election last month, will meet here on Tuesday with President Bush in the hope of securing American backing for two initiatives at the top of his agenda: increasing aid to Africa and doing more to fight global warming.</p>
        <p>Despite his status as Mr. Bush's most stalwart ally in Iraq -- and the political difficulties he has endured at home for sticking to that position -- Mr. Blair is likely to come away from the meeting with far less than he is seeking, administration officials, diplomats and outside analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House plans to announce that it will release $674 million in aid to Africa, drawn from approved funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, in his first visit to the United States since winning re-election last month, will meet here on Tuesday with President Bush in the hope of securing American backing for two initiatives at the top of his agenda: increasing aid to Africa and doing more to fight global warming.</p>
        <p>Despite his status as Mr. Bush's most stalwart ally in Iraq -- and the political difficulties he has endured at home for sticking to that position -- Mr. Blair is likely to come away from the meeting with far less than he is seeking, administration officials, diplomats and outside analysts said.</p>
        <p>In what appeared to be an effort to take some of the sting out of its differences with Mr. Blair, the White House plans to announce Tuesday that it will release $674 million in aid to Africa, drawn from money that has already been appropriated by Congress, an official of the National Security Council said late Monday, requesting anonymity in order to provide the information before its official public release.</p>
        <p>Nearly $500 million of the money will go to food aid, with much of it directed to Ethiopia and Eritrea, the official said.</p>
        <p>The meeting between Mr. Bush and Mr. Blair will cover a broad array of topics, including Iraq. The leaders are expected to reiterate their commitment to bring stability to Iraq in the face of pressures in both of their countries to begin bringing troops home, officials said.</p>
        <p>It will be the first meeting between them since the disclosure last month of a memo written by a foreign policy aide to Mr. Blair in 2002 that reported, based on a visit to Washington by a top British intelligence official, that the White House was fixing its ''intelligence and facts'' about the threat from Saddam Hussein ''around the policy'' of removing him from power through military action.</p>
        <p>They will also probably present a united face on their efforts to bring peace between the Israelis and Palestinians, American and British officials said, despite pressure from Mr. Blair on Mr. Bush to take a harder line with Israel.</p>
        <p>While the prime minister is under intense domestic pressure to show that his alliance with the president has yielded benefits for Britain, the view among some White House officials is that Mr. Blair will win political points at home on those issues on which he and Mr. Bush agree and that he will also win by standing up to him over issues on which they disagree.</p>
        <p>Since signing on to back the White House over Iraq, Mr. Blair has at times been portrayed at home as Mr. Bush's ''poodle,'' an eager follower whose loyalty is never really rewarded.</p>
        <p>''There is widespread concern in Britain that the Blair government has been on the giving side without having much to show policy-wise in return,'' said Philip Lader, who was the United States ambassador to Britain under President Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Mr. Blair comes to Washington in a position of strength. Not only did he survive domestic opposition to his backing of the Iraq war, albeit with a sharply reduced parliamentary majority, but he is arguably the strongest European leader left on the stage. President Jacques Chirac of France has been wounded politically by his voters' rejection last week of the proposed European constitution. Chancellor Gerhard Schröder of Germany is fighting for his political survival, as is Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi of Italy.</p>
        <p>With his re-election out of the way, Mr. Blair has made attacking poverty and disease in Africa the centerpiece of the summit meeting for the Group of 8 major industrialized nations for which he will be the host next month in Scotland.</p>
        <p>American officials had expressed some optimism in recent days about reaching a deal on the goal, backed in principle by both the United States and Britain, of eliminating debt payments by the poorest nations to the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund. But there was no agreement by the end of the day Monday, and it was unclear whether one could be reached during Mr. Blair's visit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has already rejected Mr. Blair's call for creation of an international body that could raise money to help Africa by borrowing against future pledges of governmental aid.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have also signaled that the White House is not inclined to commit itself to Mr. Blair's call for doubling aid to Africa. The officials said that in the last four years, the United States had roughly tripled, to $3.2 billion, the amount of money it provided to Africa. They said American aid would continue to increase, especially as existing programs to battle AIDS and provide financial assistance to well-functioning governments get more fully under way.</p>
        <p>They said the levels of aid the United States provides in the future should depend primarily on what African governments and aid organizations are able to use effectively. They also said government aid in any case was only part of the economic equation for Africa, with increased trade and private flows of investment capital capable of playing a far more potent role in the continent's development.</p>
        <p>On climate change, the administration and Downing Street are far apart. Mr. Bush has pushed an approach to reducing emissions of heat-trapping gases built around encouraging the development of technology that could be harnessed by industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair, by contrast, is a supporter of mandatory limits on those emissions, a stance shared by the other big European powers and one that is leading to higher energy costs in their nations. The White House has repeatedly rejected such an approach, saying it would extract too big a cost from the American economy.</p>
        <p>''The common ground is in research and in developing technologies that will deal with climate change and increase energy efficiency,'' said William K. Reilly, who was the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency under the first President Bush. ''The real difference of opinion between Bush and Blair is over measures that go beyond voluntary measures by industry.''</p>
        <p>James L. Connaughton, the chairman of the White House's Council on Environmental Quality, said there was a ''strong consensus for a broad portfolio of actions'' that the United States, Britain and other nations could take together. He cited as an example an initiative worked out by the United States, India and other nations to reduce emissions of methane.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
