<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beset by Opposition, Broadwater Bets On Washington and Time</title>
    <meta content="03ligas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/03/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/03ligas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1684692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Broadwater Energy</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D81431F930A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beset by Opposition, Broadwater Bets On Washington and Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beset by Opposition, Broadwater Bets on Washington and Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TEST the political winds swirling around the huge floating natural-gas terminal that Broadwater Energy wants to build in the Long Island Sound, and it is easy to conclude that the project is doomed.</p>
        <p>Many environmental and civic groups hate the idea. Questions have been raised about the terminal's safety, its security from attack and environmental hazards, and even whether it will be needed by the time it can be built.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Broadwater Energy, the backers of a huge floating natural-gas terminal in the Long Island Sound, believe they can make the platform a reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TEST the political winds swirling around the huge floating natural-gas terminal that Broadwater Energy wants to build in the Long Island Sound, and it is easy to conclude that the project is doomed.</p>
        <p>Many environmental and civic groups hate the idea. Questions have been raised about the terminal's safety, its security from attack and environmental hazards, and even whether it will be needed by the time it can be built.</p>
        <p>Senators, members of Congress, the Suffolk County Legislature, the Town of Riverhead and other towns in Suffolk have all lined up against it.</p>
        <p>Even the location of the office that Broadwater opened in Riverhead to promote the project seems ill starred: just a few doors from where the old Long Island Lighting Company rented space 30 years ago to talk up a Jamesport nuclear power plant that never came to be.</p>
        <p>But Broadwater executives express confidence that they can make the platform a reality, despite all the omens and objections.</p>
        <p>The company appears to be counting on two trump cards: Washington and wait-and-see. The energy bill now before Congress promises to give a federal agency the power to override state and local objections to the siting of gas terminals.</p>
        <p>And while few influential voices have come out squarely for the plan, many are declining to take a position until more specifics are known about the proposal and its impact, frustrating opponents' efforts to kill it quickly before it can gather momentum.</p>
        <p>For a century, America got all its natural gas from domestic sources or by pipeline from Canada and Mexico. But with those supplies no longer growing fast enough to keep up with booming demand, the energy industry, with the strong backing of the Bush administration, is trying to build new facilities to import gas from Asia, Africa, South America and the Middle East by tanker, transported in a supercold liquefied form known as L.N.G.</p>
        <p>Energy analysts and others who are watching the progress of more than 30 proposals for L.N.G. terminals around the United States say that Broadwater Energy, a partnership of Shell and the TransCanada Corporation, is clearly operating in an unfriendly climate.</p>
        <p>For one thing, of the 30 proposed terminals around the country, no more than 10 are expected to be built, experts say.</p>
        <p>Giant energy companies like Exxon Mobil are competing fiercely to build rival projects and are making rapid progress along the Gulf of Mexico, where there is much less local opposition and where one analyst says all the L.N.G. terminals that are needed will be built.</p>
        <p>New terminals are also proposed in eastern Canada that could supply the northeastern United States.</p>
        <p>But Broadwater's senior vice president, John Hritcko Jr., a Cornell graduate with more than 26 years of experience in the natural gas industry, seemed far from conceding in a recent interview that the project was in any trouble.</p>
        <p>''It's early in the process, and there is still a lot of time for people to change their minds,'' he said. ''Both Shell and TransCanada are firmly behind this project.''</p>
        <p>Broadwater has no intention of forcing a gigantic hazard down local throats, he said. ''If we can't build this thing and operate it safely, if it can't be done in an environmentally sound fashion, and if can't be consistent with the uses of the Sound, we won't build it,'' Mr. Hritcko said.</p>
        <p>Facts have been in somewhat short supply so far. When Broadwater announced its proposal last November, it released little more than an artist's rendering, a location and a few overall dimensions -- the shiplike terminal is expected to be 1,200 feet long and 180 feet wide.</p>
        <p>More will become known when the company files its formal application with the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission in November; it originally planned to file no later than September. Mr. Hritcko said the information the company is gathering for that application will convince the undecided that the terminal will be a boon to Long Island energy consumers.</p>
        <p>For their part, Broadwater's opponents -- including Senator Charles E. Schumer, Congressmen Timothy Bishop of Southampton and Steve Israel of Huntington, Suffolk County, the Town of Riverhead and several other municipalities, state legislators from eastern Long Island and an array of environmental and civic groups -- say the pertinent facts about the project are already on the table.</p>
        <p>Having two or three giant L.N.G. tankers a week delivering gas to the terminal, nine miles north of the Riverhead shore but still in New York State waters, would harmfully industrialize the eastern Sound, they say. The terminal, close to both a busy shipping lane and heavily used fishing and recreational waters, would be vulnerable to catastrophic accidents and present an all too tempting target for terrorists. It would spoil the view and require a security zone. And it would undermine efforts to develop renewable energy sources and reduce reliance on fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The economic benefits of greatly expanding the region's gas supply are central to Broadwater's case. It would supply about one billion cubic feet of gas a day, enough to satisfy one-quarter to one-third of total gas demand in downstate New York and southern Connecticut, depending on the season.</p>
        <p>About half the gas would go to New York City and almost one-third to its northern suburbs and Connecticut; only about 200 million cubic feet a day, or one-fifth of the total, would be for Long Island. Still, that is enough to supply all the gas used by customers of KeySpan, the Island's gas distribution utility, in the summer -- about 190 million cubic feet a day -- and about one-third of the 650 million cubic feet a day they now consume in winter. (Gas used by electric power plants is not counted in those figures.)</p>
        <p>The terminal will also be able to stockpile eight billion cubic feet of gas, the company said, helping stabilize supplies and prices in a region that is hungry for more gas than existing pipelines can deliver and helping encourage more users to switch from oil to gas, which burns much more cleanly.</p>
        <p>Tom Woods, a senior consultant and natural gas analyst for Platts Analytics and Forecasting, said that Broadwater's chosen location made the economics more attractive, because of proximity both to users and to sources of supply across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>''Shipping distance will be shorter, and when gas is delivered, it's right there by the customers,'' Mr. Woods said. ''If you send it all the way down to the Gulf, that's a lot more miles, and then you have to send it up again through pipelines.'' Cutting out all that distance would reduce prices, he said.</p>
        <p>Over all, Broadwater says that consumers would save $6 billion in energy costs from 2010 to 2020; it has not said how it calculated that figure.</p>
        <p>Opponents say there are better options for supplying more gas to Long Island that will soon make the Broadwater terminal unnecessary, including the Iroquois pipeline from Milford, Conn., to Northport, which is already operating, and several more in development.</p>
        <p>David J. Manning, executive vice president for corporate affairs of KeySpan, which has remained neutral on the Broadwater proposal, said new pipelines are central to the company's planning. ''We have continued to address the need for additional gas for Long Island,'' he said, ''and our focus specifically has been on the Islander East pipeline project and the Millennium project.''</p>
        <p>Islander East, a 50-mile pipeline meant to transport 260 million cubic feet a day through Connecticut to Yaphank, is a partnership of KeySpan and Duke Energy; it was supposed to be completed by 2003 but has been tied up by litigation in Hartford, where state agencies have refused to issue necessary permits.</p>
        <p>Millennium, inwhich KeySpan acquired a 21 percent stake last September, is a larger pipeline being built to supply the New York metropolitan area from west of the Hudson, starting in the winter of 2006-7. Millennium has so far not been able to win approval for a branch to cross the river and supply Long Island.</p>
        <p>KeySpan, which also operates gas- and oil-fired power plants, including four on Long Island, is applying for permission to expand its L.N.G. terminal on Narragansett Bay in Providence, R.I.; that project, too, faces intense political and public resistance on environmental and safety grounds.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, Broadwater has called for everyone to withhold judgment of its project until more information is available. Opponents say that is a strategy meant to delay intervention by crucial decision makers until it is too late.</p>
        <p>''Broadwater is asking elected officials to take a wait-and-see attitude, and they are waiting and seeing, and Broadwater is charging ahead full speed,'' said Richard Amper, the executive director of the Long Island Pine Barrens Society and a leader of an anti-Broadwater coalition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amper said the federal energy bill, which among other things would give the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission the power to override state and local objections to the siting of L.N.G. terminals, would be crippling. The bill has passed in the House and Senate in different versions to be reconciled in a conference committee; both versions include the gas-terminal siting provision.</p>
        <p>''If Long Islanders don't have anything to say about it, a powerful multinational company has a chance to get its approvals from the Fed whether we like it or not,'' Mr. Amper said.</p>
        <p>Others said there was still time to scrutinize the proposal and environmental studies that Broadwater must prepare for the commission. The board of the Long Island Association, a business group, approved a resolution in mid-June announcing its readiness to listen.</p>
        <p>''The region is going to need more energy, including natural gas, and these people should have the opportunity to make their case fully,'' said Matthew T. Crosson, the association's president. ''And everybody in the community, including public officials, should be heard by FERC prior to a decision being made.''</p>
        <p>Lee E. Koppelman, the executive director of the Long Island Regional Planning Board and Long Island's senior planner, was also withholding judgment. ''Some of the opposition is somewhat premature,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Almost alone among environmentalists, Ashok Gupta of the Natural Resources Defense Council in Manhattan said the Broadwater project deserved consideration. ''Let's try to look at it in a rational way,'' he said. Mr. Gupta said a small task force with New York and Connecticut members should be created to look into whether the gas was needed.</p>
        <p>Senator Schumer opposes the project and has called it a contentious waste of time for the region.</p>
        <p>''We do need a smart and comprehensive strategy to meet energy needs here on Long Island, but this L.N.G. terminal will take so long and be so controversial that it's going to take our attention away from the real issue at hand,'' he said in a statement in May. He voted against the Senate energy bill.</p>
        <p>But Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, who voted in support of the bill, has stopped short of taking an unequivocal stand. She raised environmental, economic and safety questions in a May 25 letter to the commission chairman, Pat Wood III, and seemed skeptical of the project in an interview last month on News 12 Long Island, but her office has not issued a statement confirming her views. Mr. Wood said in early June that Senator Clinton's concerns would be addressed when the commission considers Broadwater's permit application.</p>
        <p>Broadwater says that people concerned with safety should applaud the fact that its proposed terminal would be far offshore. ''We are talking nine miles away,'' Mr. Hritcko said. ''Its location is the biggest safety factor going for it.'' A 2004 report for the Energy Department by the Sandia Corporation said the effects of a fire at an L.N.G. terminal would probably be contained within one and a half miles.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard is in the process of assessing the safety and security risks of the terminal and will also look at whether the proposed site and its surrounding security zone would obstruct commercial shipping. Mr. Hritcko said the proposed site would pose no problems for shipping and should not be changed. But Broadwater also disclosed that it had already shifted the location 1.3 miles west to accommodate fishermen.</p>
        <p>While Broadwater and its two energy-giant parent companies say they are listening to local opinion, in the end a permit from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission could outweigh all but the most vigorous political opposition. Asked if Broadwater would go ahead even if the public overwhelmingly opposed the project, Mr. Hritcko declined to answer directly. ''We would have to look at it at that point in time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Opponents say popular opinion will prevail. ''Never doubt the strength of the public,'' said Adrienne Esposito, executive director of Citizens Campaign for the Environment in Farmingdale. ''If we get big enough opposition, we can stop this monstrosity.''</p>
        <p>Much may depend on where the Long Island Power Authority comes down on the issue. The authority, whose fuel costs and electric rates are among the highest in the country, is studying the possible economic effects of the terminal, with a report due in late summer or early fall.</p>
        <p>''We have a significant financial interest in the project because of its impact on rates, one way or the other,'' said Richard Kessel, the chairman of the authority.</p>
        <p>In the past, Mr. Kessel has had Gov. George E. Pataki's ear on Long Island energy issues, so results of the power authority's study may influence the state's stance on the project. Under current law, the terminal would need permits from the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation and from the New York Department of State, which would rule on whether it is consistent with the state's coastal zone management plan.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki has not taken a position. Jennifer Meicht, a spokeswoman for the governor, said that the need for new sources of energy for Long Island had to be balanced by the need for environmental protection, but that further comment was premature because the state had yet to receive a project proposal.</p>
        <p>For all that, at least one analyst believes time is not really on Broadwater's side at all. Philip Dodge, an energy analyst for the Stanford Group in Houston, said that the United States needs only about eight new L.N.G. terminals, and he predicted that Texas and Louisiana would build that many before proposals like Broadwater's in the Northeast or on the West Coast could get through the approval process.</p>
        <p>''A lot of these other projects are going to be left behind, because there will be so much capacity in four or five years'' that they won't be needed, Mr. Dodge said. ''What happens is that these things get delayed. They have to have all kinds of local permits, and that's when the delays start cutting in.''</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
