<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Nuclear Power Become Just Another Business?</title>
    <meta content="20nuke" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/20/business/yourmoney/20nuke.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1719079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DC1E3EF933A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Nuclear Power Become Just Another Business?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Can Nuclear Power Become Just Another Business?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GRAY</byline>
      <dateline>LONDONDERRY, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STAND among the pumpkins and purple mums in the gravel parking lot of Anna's Garden and Gift Center and you can glimpse beyond the trees a ghost that haunts the nuclear power industry.</p>
        <p>There hulk the twin cooling towers of Three Mile Island Unit 2, the nuclear reactor that had a partial meltdown in 1979. That event, paired with the Chernobyl explosion in Ukraine in 1986, halted the growth of the American nuclear power industry for a generation. No new plant has been ordered in the United States since the Three Mile Island accident. But existing plants have kept operating: the United States has 104 reactors, which make a fifth of its power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nuclear-power sector has been enjoying something of a revival, because of its operating-cost advantages over other forms of electricity production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STAND among the pumpkins and purple mums in the gravel parking lot of Anna's Garden and Gift Center and you can glimpse beyond the trees a ghost that haunts the nuclear power industry.</p>
        <p>There hulk the twin cooling towers of Three Mile Island Unit 2, the nuclear reactor that had a partial meltdown in 1979. That event, paired with the Chernobyl explosion in Ukraine in 1986, halted the growth of the American nuclear power industry for a generation. No new plant has been ordered in the United States since the Three Mile Island accident. But existing plants have kept operating: the United States has 104 reactors, which make a fifth of its power.</p>
        <p>Lately, the nuclear-power sector has been enjoying something of a revival, because of its operating-cost advantages over other forms of electricity production. That may prompt investors to bet on its resurgence by buying shares in nuclear power plant operators, equipment makers or fuel producers.</p>
        <p>The economic appeal of nuclear power has risen as prices for natural gas and coal -- fuels for the bulk of America's electricity -- have climbed. The price of natural gas, especially, has soared. In October, it touched $14 per million British thermal units. That was nearly double the price from October of last year. ''There's a big advantage for operating a nuclear plant when gas prices are in the $5 range, much less where they are today,'' said John C. Kohli, portfolio manager at the Franklin Utilities fund.</p>
        <p>Many people, of course, still worry about inadvertent releases of radiation and about the long-term storage of radioactive waste. But in some circles, those fears are beginning to be overtaken by an appreciation of nuclear power's competitive advantages. As concern about global warming has become mainstream, some investors are reminded that nuclear power produces no greenhouse gases. And while nuclear power plants could be vulnerable to a terrorist attack, war and recent hurricanes have underscored the fragility of fossil-fuel supplies. Federal lawmakers have given nuclear power a nudge, too, with a raft of subsidies in the Energy Policy Act this year.</p>
        <p>''The incentives in there were a bold statement that nuclear is going to be an important part of the U.S. electricity supply in the future,'' said Timothy P. O'Brien, manager of the Evergreen Utility and Telecommunications fund.</p>
        <p>Still, investors should understand that betting on nuclear power entails risks beyond the stock market's usual shimmies and shakes. Domestic plants have operated without a major accident since Three Mile Island, but another big stumble, in the United States or abroad, could hobble the industry. And many long-term issues remain, including the questions about waste storage and the proliferation of nuclear technology, said Ernest J. Moniz, a physicist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The construction of a long-promised waste repository at Yucca Mountain in Nevada, about 100 miles northwest of Las Vegas, has been delayed by years of legal arm-wrestling.</p>
        <p>If investors choose to go nuclear, perhaps the most conservative approach is to buy shares of utilities with big nuclear operations -- utilities like Exelon, Entergy, Dominion Resources and the FPL Group, said Mark C. Sadeghian, an analyst at Morningstar.</p>
        <p>Exelon, based in Chicago, has made a hefty wager on nuclear generation, he noted. It has 17 reactors at 10 sites. If it completes a pending acquisition of the Public Service Enterprise Group, based in Newark, it will have 20 reactors at 12 sites. Exelon's stock is up more than 15 percent this year.</p>
        <p>Among Exelon's plants is Three Mile Island Unit 1, a mirror image of its infamous sibling. Both occupy the same central Pennsylvania island, protected by glistening razor wire and guards toting assault rifles. Unit 1 generates about seven million megawatt-hours of power a year, while Unit 2 sits idle and entombed. Exelon does not own Unit 2, but monitors it for its owner, First-Energy of Akron, Ohio.</p>
        <p>''Several years ago, when the industry started to deregulate, many companies decided to sell off their nuclear plants, and very few companies had the bright idea to buy them, though they were being sold by pennies on the dollar,'' said Judith A. Saryan, portfolio manager at the Eaton Vance Utilities fund. ''Exelon was one of the companies that had the good sense to buy.''</p>
        <p>Operating a passel of plants helped Exelon to hone its nuclear expertise, Ms. Saryan said. ''Now its nuclear fleet runs at 95 percent capacity.''</p>
        <p>Entergy, with 10 reactors, is the second-biggest nuclear operator, after Exelon. Entergy's hometown utility, Entergy New Orleans, had to file for bankruptcy-court protection after Hurricane Katrina, but that division accounts for less than 5 percent of the parent's earnings, said Shelby G. Tucker, a principal at Banc of America Securities. ''About a third of their earnings comes from their large nuclear fleet in the Northeast,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Those plants could soon contribute even more to profits. Entergy sells its power at below-market prices because of risk-hedging contracts, he said. As the hedges expire, ''they'll be able to recontract at higher prices.''</p>
        <p>Eight power companies, including Exelon and Entergy, are trying to prepare the way for the eventual licensing of a new nuclear plant. Their coalition, called NuStart Energy, aims to test a streamlined federal licensing process and to develop a design for a new reactor.</p>
        <p>Other countries, especially China and India, are likely to build more nuclear plants and to do so sooner. ''People are talking about China building 20 to 21 new reactors,'' said David M. Schanzer, utility analyst at Janney Montgomery Scott.</p>
        <p>A company that may have a role in construction abroad is General Electric, which has designed and sold parts for plants for decades. But the nuclear business accounts for just a tincture of G.E.'s sales. Buying G.E. for its atomic expertise is like buying a bag of M&amp;M's just to eat the green ones.</p>
        <p>A foreign company with a focus on nuclear power is British Energy, which produces about a fifth of Britain's electricity, said Charlie B. Gaffney, an analyst at Eaton Vance. British Energy owns eight nuclear plants and one coal-fired one. ''So they're basically a pure-play nuclear generator,'' he said. ''They've had some problems in the past, and they're in restructuring mode.'' If the company succeeds, its cheap power could yield healthy returns, he said.</p>
        <p>Only one domestic company qualifies as a pure-play nuclear investment: USEC, a former government agency that chemically modifies uranium for use as reactor fuel; it is based in Bethesda, Md.</p>
        <p>Since being privatized in 1998, its earnings and stock price have zigzagged. This fall, the company reorganized, cutting its staff by 6 percent, to about 2,700, and bringing in a new boss, John K. Welch, from General Dynamics.</p>
        <p>USEC's government legacy has hampered it by saddling it with outdated technology, Mr. Welch said. Its enrichment plant was designed in the 1950's and uses more electricity than competitors abroad. That is why the company is betting on a giant centrifuge costing $1.7 billion. It should use about 5 percent of the electricity required by the current method, Mr. Welch said, adding that ''we hope to have that up and running by 2011 or 2012.''</p>
        <p>A competitor -- Louisiana Energy Services, yet another venture that includes Exelon and Entergy -- has announced plans to bring an enrichment plant in New Mexico online at about the same time.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, investors' best hope for nuclear power may be that it comes to be viewed as just another business, rather than the industrial offspring of a perilous technology.</p>
        <p>IN Londonderry, Anna M. and Daniel J. Angelo, owners of Anna's Garden and Gift Center, already seem to see the industry that way.</p>
        <p>They don't fret much about the past of Three Mile Island Unit 2. Sure, they tell tales about the huge nuclear plant -- about the iodine tablets, a radiation antidote, handed out at their children's school after Sept. 11, 2001, and about the way the warm-water discharge into the Susquehanna River draws fish and anglers in the winter. Otherwise, they accept the reactor, saying it brings well-paying jobs to their area.</p>
        <p>''We joke about having glow-in-the dark plants,'' Ms. Angelo said. ''Other than that, people don't talk that much about it. You get so used to it.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
