<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can't Take the Heat? Plant a Tree</title>
    <meta content="24CIdombeck" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/24/opinion/nyregionopinions/24CIdombeck.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1689648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Dombeck, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0DB143FF937A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can't Take the Heat? Plant a Tree</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Can't Take the Heat? Plant a Tree</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Dombeck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dombeck, Mike</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ancient Chinese proverb ''No shade tree? Blame not the sun, but yourself,'' offers practical advice for improving our urban areas. As with many proverbs, the message is both profound and obvious.</p>
        <p>Last week, while looking at the weather reports from New York City, I was reminded of just how profound this one is. While the temperature in Manhattan was listed at 90 degrees, in Times Square it was more like 100 degrees, and in Central Park, it was probably closer to 80.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>More foliage could do wonders for summer in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ancient Chinese proverb ''No shade tree? Blame not the sun, but yourself,'' offers practical advice for improving our urban areas. As with many proverbs, the message is both profound and obvious.</p>
        <p>Last week, while looking at the weather reports from New York City, I was reminded of just how profound this one is. While the temperature in Manhattan was listed at 90 degrees, in Times Square it was more like 100 degrees, and in Central Park, it was probably closer to 80.</p>
        <p>Temperature variations like this play out daily all over the world. Cities heat up more than rural areas because they contain more heat-trapping materials. They have less of the vegetation cover that dissipates heat. And our activities -- from driving to cooking to cooling our homes -- emit heat. As a result, many cities are about 6 to 8 degrees warmer than the forested areas around them. Improving the energy efficiency of these urban heat islands is not trivial. With the temperature hovering at more than 90 degrees and air-conditioners running marathons, Americans are again sweating over energy bills.</p>
        <p>More trees would help, because trees are nature's air-conditioners. When the sun shines on buildings, roads and bridges, they give off that solar energy as heat -- just think of the cliché about it being so hot you could cook eggs on the sidewalk. Trees not only provide shade, but also absorb the sun's energy to make biomass, the living matter that trees are made of. Trees also release water, which cools things down. The water they absorb passes to their leaf surfaces where it evaporates, cooling the air much the way perspiration cools our skin. With enough vegetation, evaporative cooling lowers air temperatures.</p>
        <p>Greg McPherson and his associates at the United States Forest Service Center for Urban Forest Research have found that trees planted around buildings in California reduce air-conditioning needs by an amount equal to the energy produced by a 700-megawatt power plant, and that the strategic planting of 50 million more trees in California would double the savings.</p>
        <p>This is good news, because our urban areas have room for lots of trees. In America, urban and other developed areas cover almost 100 million acres of land of which only about 25 percent is occupied by trees or other vegetation. That leaves room for up to 700 million more trees, according to the Forest Service. The nonprofit organization American Forests suggests that a 40 percent tree canopy in urban areas would result in better air quality and lower heating and cooling costs among other things.</p>
        <p>While some cities are doing well when it comes to tree cover, others are not. In New York City, the numbers vary. Brooklyn and Manhattan have about 12 percent tree cover, Queens and the Bronx have about 16 percent and Staten Island has 28 percent. As a whole, the city averages about 17 percent.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the trend in most places is for declining tree cover. Urban sprawl consumes about 9,000 acres a day and within America's cities, on average one tree is planted for every four removed. In Harrisburg, Pa., tree cover fell to 26 percent from 30 percent between 1973 and 2000, and in the Chesapeake Bay area it declined to 39 percent from 51 percent between 1973 and 1997.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, trees do more than make cities look good. An average tree can remove several pounds of pollutants and some 15 pounds of carbon from the air per year. They also collect solar energy, produce oxygen, regulate humidity and temperature, filter air and water, recycle nutrients, store carbon and provide wildlife habitat. Forests reduce the impact of storms, regulate water runoff and floods and help build soils.</p>
        <p>Trees are the quintessential multitaskers. They reduce energy consumption and carbon emissions while also absorbing carbon dioxide and pollutants. Trees improve air quality while reducing global warming and our air-conditioning costs. Cities and towns and residents across America would be smart to heed the ancient wisdom and plant more trees.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Mike Dombeck, a former chief of the United States Forest Service and director of the Bureau of Land Management, is a professor of global management at the University of Wisconsin at Stevens Point.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mike Dombeck, a former chief of the United States Forest Service and director of the Bureau of Land Management, is a professor of global management at the University of Wisconsin at Stevens Point.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
