<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="25OBOX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/25/science/25obse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1644683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fangblenny (Fish)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Camouflage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oriskany (Aircraft Carrier)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pensacola (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serengeti National Park (Tanzania)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tanzania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of East Anglia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Minnesota</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Science (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Illinois</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proceedings B (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Packer, Craig (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suarez, Andrew V (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Tanzania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Tanzania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Pensacola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4DE1F38F936A15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Argentine Ants at the Global Picnic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of East Anglia researchers find that bluestriped fangblenny fish, which is intense predator that rips off flesh and scales of its victims with its teeth, can change its appearance to blend in with environment; study, which is published in journal Nature, examined Indonesian fangblennies; Dr Craig Packer, University of Minnesota researcher, leads study on Serengeti National Park, Tanzania, lion population that explains population bursts in region; study, published in journal Science, explains that social structure of pride is primary cause for rapid population growth; asserts that when food becomes very abundant prides will split causing spike in numbers of lions; Oriskany, now obsolete United States Navy aircraft carrier, is being prepared to be sunk in 212 feet of water off Pensacola (Fla) coast as part of reef-making project; Navy is picking up most of $2.8 million cost of preparations on ship before its sinking; Dr Andrew V Suarez, University of Illinois entomologist, leads study on migration of Argentine ants to non-endemic areas; study, which is published in Proceedings B of Royal Society, utilizes computer models to predict ant distribution, if projected global warming for 2050 were to take place; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clever Fangblenny</p>
        <p>It's true that a leopard can't change its spots, but the bluestriped fangblenny fish -- now that's a different story. The fangblenny, it seems, can alter its stripes to suit its circumstances.</p>
        <p>The fangblenny is a small reef-dwelling fish with nasty table manners: it lunges at other fish and rips off flesh and scales with its teeth. That doesn't make it the most popular fish in the sea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Argentine ant is only about an eighth of an inch long, but among invasive species it is a colossus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clever Fangblenny</p>
        <p>It's true that a leopard can't change its spots, but the bluestriped fangblenny fish -- now that's a different story. The fangblenny, it seems, can alter its stripes to suit its circumstances.</p>
        <p>The fangblenny is a small reef-dwelling fish with nasty table manners: it lunges at other fish and rips off flesh and scales with its teeth. That doesn't make it the most popular fish in the sea.</p>
        <p>So the fangblenny disguises itself with a blue stripe along its otherwise black skin. This makes it resemble the bluestreak cleaner wrasse, a helpful fish that spends its days eating the parasites off the skin of other fish. With its stripe, the fangblenny can get within lunging range of its prey.</p>
        <p>In nature, mimicry like this is usually permanent. But researchers at the University of East Anglia in England, studying fangblennies in Indonesia, have found that the fish can change its coloring if its situation changes. When the researchers relocated single-striped fish from an area with cleaner wrasses to one without, within minutes the fangblennies took on a different coloring -- brown-olive or orange, with a second blue stripe.</p>
        <p>This alternative coloring, the researchers write in the journal Nature, gives the fangblenny another way to get near its prey. While with a single stripe it can operate in the open, in its double-striped coloring it blends in with mixed schools of fish. With a school as cover, it can lunge at unlucky fish that pass by.</p>
        <p>Leaping Lion Populations</p>
        <p>For creatures like the fangblenny, the prey's the thing. Populations rise or fall depending in large part on the amount of food available.</p>
        <p>But with some predators, population dynamics are much more complicated. Consider, for example, the lions of the Serengeti.</p>
        <p>A study of four decades of data from part of Serengeti National Park in Tanzania shows that, although the availability of prey and other factors that affect population size changed gradually, the number of lions remained stable for long periods, both in woodlands and open savannas. When the lion populations did change, they did so in great leaps.</p>
        <p>In the Science study, by Dr. Craig Packer of the University of Minnesota and colleagues, wildebeest and buffalo, for example, became much more abundant from the 1960's until the late 1970's. These are two of the lions' favorite prey, yet the woodlands lion population fluctuated only slightly for most of this time, until it increased greatly in 1973.</p>
        <p>The researchers also developed a detailed computer model of lion population dynamics. Their conclusion is that the population leaps are a result of the animal's social structure.</p>
        <p>Lions live in prides, groups of up to 18 related females and their young, along with up to 9 unrelated males. The females do the hunting, while the males defend the pride's territory. There is an optimal pride size that balance the number of mouths to feed with the ability to hunt food and provide protection.</p>
        <p>Gradual changes in the food supply won't affect population size very much because the prides won't grow much beyond the optimum. But at some point there will be enough food that prides will split, with several of the females taking off for a new territory. These prides grow rapidly, resulting in the population bursts.</p>
        <p>From Hulk to Reef</p>
        <p>An 888-foot obsolete aircraft carrier has arrived in Pensacola, Fla., where it is being prepared for sinking, to make one of the largest artificial reefs anywhere.</p>
        <p>The Oriskany, which was launched at the end of World War II and taken out of service in the mid-1970's, was originally intended to be scrapped. But a Navy program makes surplus ships available for artificial reef projects. The Oriskany will be the largest naval ship used for reef-making when it is scuttled in June, in 212 feet of water 25 miles off Pensacola. The hulk should become a major diving attraction.</p>
        <p>The Navy is paying most of the $2.8 million cost of preparing the ship for sinking. Workers are removing lubricating oils, loose asbestos, PCB-containing transformers and other potential contaminants.</p>
        <p>Argentine Ants at the Global Picnic</p>
        <p>The Argentine ant is only about an eighth of an inch long, but among invasive species it is a colossus. In the United States, Southerners and Californians have had to deal with these aggressive moisture-loving insects for decades, since the first colonies arrived in New Orleans from South America in the late 19th century, probably in the soil used as ballast on cargo ships.</p>
        <p>As bad as the situation is, it may get worse: the ants are a major household and agricultural pest and can also wipe out native ant species, with cascading effects on the food chain. A new study shows that there are parts of the world that are susceptible to invasion by the ants now, and other areas where they may spread with global warming.</p>
        <p>The study, published last month in Proceedings B of The Royal Society, used computer modeling to predict the distribution of the ants, weighing data from more than 1,000 places where they are found, both in their native central South America and elsewhere (including Australia, Africa and the Mediterranean, in addition to North America). The simulation also takes into account common predictions for global climate change into the 2050's.</p>
        <p>''One of the interesting things that came out of this model is that there are definitely parts of the world that are not yet invaded by the ants that appear to be very susceptible,'' said Dr. Andrew V. Suarez, an author of the study and an entomologist at the University of Illinois. Among the areas where the ants could spread (if they are not there already, just undetected) are tropical coastal Africa and Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>By 2050, the study found, the ants' range could extend to higher latitudes. In the United States, the ants could spread northward in vast ''supercolonies.'' (One quality that makes the ant so invasive is that colonies tend to cooperate instead of fighting one another.) The Northeast should be spared, though, Dr. Suarez said, since the winters will still be too cold.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the range may contract somewhat in the more tropical regions, as some areas become too hot and humid.</p>
        <p>One practical value of the study, Dr. Suarez said, is that by showing what parts of the world are susceptible to invasion by the ants, officials in those areas ''can be a bit more vigilant in making sure the species isn't introduced there.''</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
