<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Nelson Triumphed, a Battle Rages Over Windmills</title>
    <meta content="10TRAF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/10/international/europe/10trafalgar.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1640906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Cape Trafalgar Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuna</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Trafalgar (Spain)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Spain</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D61E39F933A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Nelson Triumphed, a Battle Rages Over Windmills</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Nelson Triumphed, a Battle Rages Over Windmills</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE TRAFALGAR, Spain</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two companies plan to build large clusters of windmills in Atlantic Ocean near Cape Trafalgar, Spain; projects are part of drive by Spain to expand its output of native renewable energy; fishermen in region say wind farms will disturb migration of young tuna and force their small vessels to make large detours in already treacherous waters near Strait of Gibraltar; reviews are still under way for Trafalgar wind fields, and it remains to be seen whether they will support fishermen's position; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Near this blustery headland where Admiral Nelson won his great naval victory over the French two centuries ago, a new battle of Trafalgar is brewing.</p>
        <p>But the ships involved today are only small fishing boats, wanting to protect their livelihood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fishermen argue that a plan to build large clusters of windmills in the sea just off Spain's southern shore will make their jobs tougher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Near this blustery headland where Admiral Nelson won his great naval victory over the French two centuries ago, a new battle of Trafalgar is brewing.</p>
        <p>But the ships involved today are only small fishing boats, wanting to protect their livelihood.</p>
        <p>Two companies plan to build large clusters of windmills in the sea just off this stretch of Spain's southern shore, a gritty place of sand dunes, lagoons and sharp brown reefs. With about 400 offshore turbines, they want to capture the power of the winds that blow almost constantly here, at the cusp of two seas, the Atlantic and the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>Fishermen respond that the phalanxes of giant towers near the coast will make their tough jobs even tougher. ''This is where the tuna pass, and this is where we work,'' said Manuel Ponce Alva, leader of a fishermen's protest movement, waving a marine map covered with ominous red arrows.</p>
        <p>The men from the fishing villages of Barbate, Vejer and Conil have knocked on many official doors to argue that the wind farms will disturb the migration of the young tuna and, more significantly, that their own lives may be at stake. They say the towers, to be based some 10 miles offshore, will force their small vessels to make large detours in the already treacherous waters near the Strait of Gibraltar.</p>
        <p>''We talk and talk, and we ask,'' said Antonio Varo, another angry fisherman. ''We get no answers.''</p>
        <p>Their protests may well fall on deaf ears. The windmill projects are part of a drive by Spain to expand its output of native renewable energy. Spain is already one of Europe's largest producers of wind power, second only to Germany, and its capacity of 8,500 megawatts can supply close to 5 percent of the country's electricity. Indications are that the output may double by 2010.</p>
        <p>In this country, where almost all oil, gas and coal must be imported, the wind rush has been under way for more than a decade. Privately owned ''wind parks,'' encouraged by official subsidies, first sprouted on the hills near here, behind Trafalgar and Tarifa. The gleaming white towers then spread, to Spain's windswept north and the central highlands.</p>
        <p>Like the old stone windmills that have dotted Spanish horizons for centuries, the modern turbines are all on land. But now Spanish entrepreneurs want to join Europe's boom in large wind farms offshore.</p>
        <p>The seabed off Cape Trafalgar, one of six marine sites being studied, is a favorite. There are no important tourist resorts nearby, although visitors often come here from Britain, where ''Trafalgar'' has a special ring. Binoculars in hand, people climb to the cape's tip, a knobby dune with a lighthouse on top. Here they peer out at where more than 60 British, French and Spanish warships clashed in 1805 in the battle that established Britain's naval supremacy for the next century.</p>
        <p>César del Campo, director of a consortium involved in the wind park plans, said that the site was difficult because of the water depth and the speed of the currents, but that the energy yield would be high. ''You have to see the Strait of Gibraltar like a huge fast-moving river that changes with the tides,'' he said. ''Some days there may be heavy gusts from Atlantic storms, but you can count on wind every day.''</p>
        <p>The building cost can be twice as high as on land, though, offsetting the larger yield. It means driving piles into the sea floor, laying cables to the shore and riskier maintenance work.</p>
        <p>But specialists say that the rush is on now for offshore wind energy, and that northern Europe is leading the way. Wind farms based at sea today still have a modest capacity of 600 megawatts, but that is expected to grow more than tenfold by 2010, said Corin Millais, director of the European Wind Energy Association. Companies have staked out tracts in the seas off Britain, Denmark, Germany, Ireland and the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>The incentive is evident, Mr. Millais said, because Europe's oil and natural gas reserves are running out, and energy imports, now at 50 percent, will rise further. The European Union, moreover, has been pushing for alternatives to fossil fuels as part of its commitment under the Kyoto treaty to reduce greenhouse gases, and it wants 22 percent of its electricity to come from renewable sources by 2010.</p>
        <p>Many projects have been delayed because officials everywhere are demanding stringent environmental impact studies. The reviews are still under way for the Trafalgar wind fields, and it remains to be seen whether they will support the fishermen's position. The area is on the flight path of tens of thousands of eagles, ducks, storks, swallows and many other birds crossing to winter in Africa. Daniel López Marijuan of the association of Ecologists in Action said, ''The first studies have shown that migrating birds do not fly very low here, unless a storm takes them off their course.''</p>
        <p>There are other stakeholders, including two nearby NATO bases, the operators of a gas duct that comes to Spain from North Africa and the heavy shipping traffic in and out of the Mediterranean, but planners say their studies show the windmills pose no obstruction.</p>
        <p>If that is true, the fishermen along the Trafalgar coast may be alone in confronting the powerful lobby of wind producers. ''There is good money in wind,'' said Rafael Bayo, an engineer and energy consultant. ''That is why many hilltops now have windmills. A farmer used to get nothing from his hill. Now he rents it to a utility or puts his own windmills there.''</p>
        <p>That may continue, he says, as long as the government pays grid operators the difference between conventional and wind-generated electricity, on average two or three cents per kilowatt-hour. Eventually, some experts think, wind power may become competitive as turbines get bigger and as pollution taxes are imposed on fossil fuel energy.</p>
        <p>Manuel Bustos, an official of the association of wind producers, said his group would try to persuade the fishermen that the project might benefit them. He said that in European pilot projects, fish farms have been attached to sea-based windmills. In another experiment, windmill foundations were used to create artificial reefs to act as fish nurseries. The Barbate fishermen said they had never heard of such things.</p>
        <p>Should the Trafalgar plans fail, then offshore parks may go elsewhere, given the Spaniards' hunger for wind profits. ''There are dozens of projects waiting for licenses, on land and offshore,'' Mr. Bustos said. ''Enough to produce another 50,000 megawatts.''</p>
        <p>Cape Trafalgar Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
