<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Royal Lovers Are U.S. Bound, Attended by Unloved Press</title>
    <meta content="28royals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/28/international/europe/28royals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1713002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="London Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Prince of Wales</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowles, Camilla Parker (Duchess of Cornwall)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">London (Eng)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bowles, Camilla Parker</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DD1E3FF93BA15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Royal Lovers Are U.S. Bound, Attended by Unloved Press</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Royal Lovers Are U.S. Bound, Attended by Unloved Press</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prince of Wales will visit United States in Nov, hoping to focus attention on issues that interest him, like global warming, organic farming and holistic medicine; he will be accompanied by his wife, former Camilla Parker Bowles, now Duchess of Cornwall; although trip will be full of serious events, British reporters traveling along will be eager for any signs of colonial snippiness or royal mishaps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preparing to visit the United States next month, the Prince of Wales naturally would like to focus attention on issues that interest him, like global warming, organic farming and holistic medicine.</p>
        <p>Yawn, said a British tabloid reporter who is joining him for the trip.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles and Camilla, preparing to visit the United States next month, are treating the media as an unwelcome vulgarity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preparing to visit the United States next month, the Prince of Wales naturally would like to focus attention on issues that interest him, like global warming, organic farming and holistic medicine.</p>
        <p>Yawn, said a British tabloid reporter who is joining him for the trip.</p>
        <p>''If you were given two stories, one about a worthy charity event and one about the prince's mistress, which would you rather read?'' asked the reporter, speaking on condition of anonymity on the ground that ''I don't want to have my bags dumped unceremoniously on the tarmac before the plane takes off.''</p>
        <p>The royal mistress, the former Camilla Parker Bowles, is now of course the royal wife, the Duchess of Cornwall. She will be on the American tour, too, venturing into possibly hostile territory; her glamorous predecessor, the late Diana, Princess of Wales, is still seen to hold the psychological edge among Americans. British reporters traveling along are keen to watch for any sign of colonial snippiness or, even better, royal mishaps.</p>
        <p>''She hasn't put her foot wrong in the last year or two,'' said Stephen Bates, who writes about the royal family for The Guardian, adding hopefully, ''but there are multiple possibilities for cock-ups and gaffes and all those sorts of things.''</p>
        <p>The trip is full of serious events. The couple are to meet with Secretary General Kofi Annan of the United Nations, visit Ground Zero, stop by an inner-city school in Washington and tour organic farms outside San Francisco. They are also to have lunch and dinner at the White House, engagements that raise unwelcome comparisons to a visit in 1985, when a thrilled-looking Diana, dressed in a swirly black dress, danced with John Travolta.</p>
        <p>The visit will be the first week in November, according to the royal Web site.</p>
        <p>Paddy Harverson, Charles's press secretary, is eager to banish such images from the public's mind. ''Everyone seems to know a lot about his personal life and his family life, the kids and so on, but not a lot about his working life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Unlike Diana, a brilliantly seductive mistress of spin who used the news media as cleverly and coldly as they used her, Charles and Camilla treat the media as an unnecessary evil, an unwelcome vulgarity. The prince, who pointedly does not read daily newspapers, was overheard last year muttering ''bloody people'' in reference to the royal press pack and saying of a BBC reporter, Nicholas Witchell, ''I can't bear that man.''</p>
        <p>The feeling sometimes seems to be mutual. British newspapers tend to lampoon the prince as a pampered, blunder-prone king-in-waiting who cheated on his first wife, talks to plants and cannot stop whining about how unloved and misunderstood he is. As preparation for the trip, British newspapers have focused on issues like the buzz about Camilla's new yoga regime, the unfairness of Charles's granting an interview to ''60 Minutes'' instead of to them, the royal tiara that Camilla wore to a recent state dinner and the threat by American Diana-lovers to wave anti-Camilla placards and yell mean things when the duchess appears in public.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, The Guardian printed a preview of the royal visit written by Kitty Kelley, the scandal-loving American author of ''The Royals,'' among other things, who argued that Charles's trip might not help British tourism as much as he hoped. The shared hostility between the prince and the press makes his office's recent overtures to the American news media here all the more unusual. Last week, some American correspondents went on a field trip to Home Farm, Charles's organic farm in Gloucestershire, and to Poundbury, the model village he founded in Dorset. Charles was not there, but his pigs were admired, organic standards and affordable housing were discussed, and at lunch salad, ham, cheese and quiche were served.</p>
        <p>This week, American reporters listened to a briefing about the prince's charities, which last year raised some £109 million, or $193 million, for causes like inner-city education, small-business development and complementary medicine. It was followed by a bona fide reception for 70 or so Americans at Clarence House, where the prince and duchess live, to which the American reporters were, shockingly, invited as actual live guests -- a cause of resentful muttering among some of their British counterparts.</p>
        <p>At the reception, in rooms crowded with photographs of Charles's relatives and paintings by people like Landseer and Monet, Charles revealed himself to be a master of small talk, an expert at looking fascinated while nervous strangers expounded on topics like the worrisome frequency of hurricanes in Florida, where in Europe to get ingredients for organic salad dressing and the difficulty of transporting armaments to Iraq.</p>
        <p>Normal rules of civilian contact with royals applied. Everyone had to take his or her place before the prince and the duchess arrived, and everyone had to wait in small prearranged conversational clumps for the two to work the room. Private chats were off the record.</p>
        <p>Both Charles and Camilla seemed smaller and cozier than their images would suggest. Charles said a few words at the end, touching his wife sweetly on the arm while calling her ''my darling Camilla.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the BBC broadcast a rare television interview with the prince on the subject of the environment.</p>
        <p>Writing about the interview, in which Charles called climate change ''the greatest challenge to face man,'' The Evening Standard quoted him at length on the English countryside, ''Somebody has to manage it and maintain it and sort out the hedges and the walls and all these other things that everybody loves.''</p>
        <p>It illustrated the article with a photograph of the prince, dressed in a double-breasted gray suit and a pair of dress shoes, staring intently down at a flock of chickens.</p>
        <p>London Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
