<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aqueduct Has Its First Pre-Race Drug Test</title>
    <meta content="17RACI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/17/sports/othersports/17racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1650578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aqueduct Race Track</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Racing Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Racing Assn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED8133AF934A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aqueduct Has Its First Pre-Race Drug Test</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Aqueduct Has First Pre-Race Drug Test</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Racing Association officials conduct first random pre-race drug tests on horses before Aqueduct races after suspicions arose about race fixing and horse doping; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eleven fillies were looking to beat the rain and one another to win a race for the first time. But an hour before the fourth race yesterday at Aqueduct, they were detoured to a barn, one by one, so New York Racing Association officials could perform a far more inauspicious first: random pre-race drug tests to see if their handlers had cheated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Celeste Kunz, chief examining veterinarian for the association, was waiting with a syringe to draw blood. She was as patient and gentle with the needle as her assistant was meticulous at labeling each horse's sample and establishing a chain of custody. Sometime tomorrow, veterinarians at Cornell University will begin examining the specimens for the presence of excessive alkalizing agents, or milkshakes, in racetrack parlance. The results will be available within 48 hours. If a horse tests positive, any purse winnings will be withheld.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York Racing Association officials performed an inauspicious first on Wednesday: random pre-race drug tests to see if their handlers had cheated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eleven fillies were looking to beat the rain and one another to win a race for the first time. But an hour before the fourth race yesterday at Aqueduct, they were detoured to a barn, one by one, so New York Racing Association officials could perform a far more inauspicious first: random pre-race drug tests to see if their handlers had cheated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Celeste Kunz, chief examining veterinarian for the association, was waiting with a syringe to draw blood. She was as patient and gentle with the needle as her assistant was meticulous at labeling each horse's sample and establishing a chain of custody. Sometime tomorrow, veterinarians at Cornell University will begin examining the specimens for the presence of excessive alkalizing agents, or milkshakes, in racetrack parlance. The results will be available within 48 hours. If a horse tests positive, any purse winnings will be withheld.</p>
        <p>''It's sad it's come to this,'' said Mike Lakow, the association's racing secretary, who watched the testing in Barn 12A.</p>
        <p>Like the Olympics and Major League Baseball, thoroughbred racing has long been plagued by suspicions and rumors that some trainers use chemistry to enhance performances.</p>
        <p>Last month, however, federal prosecutors charged three men, including the New York-based trainer Gregory Martin, for milkshaking a horse to fix a race as part of wider investigation into a gambling ring said to be operated by associates of the Gambino crime family. Last week, racing officials in California announced that horses trained by two prominent West Coast conditioners, Vladimir Cerin and Jeff Mullins, had tested positive for high bicarbonate levels.</p>
        <p>''Some people say it is the tip of the iceberg,'' the trainer Rich Schosberg said of the recent scandals. His filly Abbagione was one of the first horses in New York to be tested before a race, then finished fourth.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know they were going to test our race, but I have no problem with it,'' Schosberg said. ''It shows we're moving in the right direction. Hopefully, we can erode that tip until there is no iceberg.''</p>
        <p>The pre-race tests, for up to four races a day, will be conducted with less than an hour's notice. As in California, the threshold for a positive result in New York will be 37 millimoles of carbon dioxide per liter of plasma.</p>
        <p>''The average range for a horse is 25 to 31 millimoles,'' Kunz said. ''And to my knowledge only once horse ever, anywhere, tested consistently at 37 in a normal resting state. If a horse is above 37, he has been milkshaked, and that is messing around with its metabolic state.''</p>
        <p>Milkshaking entails filling a horse's stomach with a cocktail of sodium bicarbonate -- say, for example, three pounds of baking soda -- with water, sugar or perhaps a sports drink. That mixture can be fed through the nose with a garden hose or squirted down the throat with a turkey baster. The intention is to make the horse unaware of the accumulation of lactic acid in its muscles, thereby delaying its sense of fatigue as it runs.</p>
        <p>Kunz and other veterinarians in the industry acknowledged that scores of supplements available over the counter and mixed into a horse's feed may cause elevated carbon dioxide levels. In fact, a byproduct of the testing program is to collect enough blood samples to establish a foundation for future research.</p>
        <p>''But no matter how it got there,'' Kunz said, ''if a horse is above 37, it's not only an unfair advantage, but it's dangerous for the horse.''</p>
        <p>The New York Racing Association will impose harsh penalties on trainers whose horses test positive. A first offense sets off a 30-day probation period in which the trainer must send all horses to a NYRA-monitored barn by 5 p.m. the day before their races and pay for their security. After a second offense, the trainer will be permanently barred from Aqueduct, Belmont Park and Saratoga Racecourse, the three tracks the association governs.</p>
        <p>The association has also committed $75,000 to the pre- and postrace testing program and another $75,000 for Cornell researchers to determine and identify what other illegal medications and techniques may be enhancing horses' performances.</p>
        <p>''It's long overdue and definitely needed,'' the trainer Scott Schwartz said of the pre-race testing.</p>
        <p>He, too, had no idea that his filly, Allison's Princess, was going to have blood drawn before the fourth race yesterday. But after watching her make up eight lengths in the stretch to pick up a $24,600 first-place check, he was not complaining.</p>
        <p>''I tend to think there is something going on,'' he said. ''There's always someone out here trying to take advantage, looking for that edge. If they can stop them, it's fine with me.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
