<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Will It Take to Safeguard New Orleans?</title>
    <meta content="11reefs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/11/weekinreview/11marsh.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1701264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D61331F932A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Will It Take to Safeguard New Orleans?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What Will It Take to Safeguard New Orleans?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL MARSH
&lt;br&gt;&lt;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW ORLEANS has long lived with the hurricane protection that it, and the nation, were willing to pay for. Measured against the costs of Katrina's fury, however, better armor may suddenly seem more affordable.</p>
        <p>With officials vowing to rebuild New Orleans, the question of how fully to defend the city against another catastrophe will be examined as never before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>What you've heard about protecting New Orleans may not apply.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW ORLEANS has long lived with the hurricane protection that it, and the nation, were willing to pay for. Measured against the costs of Katrina's fury, however, better armor may suddenly seem more affordable.</p>
        <p>With officials vowing to rebuild New Orleans, the question of how fully to defend the city against another catastrophe will be examined as never before.</p>
        <p>Unlike San Francisco or Los Angeles, where there is no way to prevent widespread destruction from the most powerful earthquakes, New Orleans is uniquely dependent on one feature: its aging network of levees. If levees hold back the water, the city is spared. If they fail, much of the city is ruined.</p>
        <p>''For people to feel confident about coming back again, they're going to have to rebuild the levee system,' said Ivor van Heerden, deputy director of the Louisiana State University Hurricane Center. They must be taller and stronger, he said, built for the worst-case Category 5 storm. Existing levees were designed decades ago to withstand only a quickly receding Category 3.</p>
        <p>The success of levees in a restored New Orleans will depend partly on the resilience of other civil engineering, and on wetlands between the city and the Gulf of Mexico. Today, the condition of these outer defenses is poor: Barrier islands and wetlands are disappearing, and gates to protect against storm surges and waves are years away.</p>
        <p>Mississippi River levees have choked off the sediment that built and nourished surrounding wetlands. With the rise in sea levels, about 30 square miles is submerged every year.</p>
        <p>The slow march of the gulf shore toward New Orleans can only be bad for civil defense. Computer modeling shows that in smaller, more frequent hurricanes, storm surges increase as land is diminished.</p>
        <p>''Land absorbs wave energy; the physics have been well established,'' said Gregory W. Stone, a professor of coastal geology at Louisiana State University. His study found that coastal surges increased 8 to 10 feet from 1950 to the 1990's because of land loss.</p>
        <p>In another 15 years, models project, surges and waves on the coast will have increased a further 6 to 12 feet if the erosion continues.</p>
        <p>BUT the benefit of revived wetlands to New Orleans may be limited.</p>
        <p>''I don't think a city should depend on tall grass,'' said Hassan Mashriqui, a professor of engineering at Louisiana State. ''In general, if there is a barrier, that helps. If there is a 25-foot surge coming, does that make it two feet less in New Orleans? It has yet to be proven.''</p>
        <p>That's because a Katrina-size hurricane, on course to blow a large surge into the city, has yet to occur - an eventuality too serious, some say, to count on islands and marshes to stop the water.</p>
        <p>''The enemy is the Gulf of Mexico,'' said Roy K. Dokka, a professor of engineering at Louisiana State. ''If you're at sea level and the National Weather Service tells you you're going to have a 20-foot storm surge, you need to have a wall more than 20 feet high.''</p>
        <p>The engineering challenges are daunting and costly: The city is sinking, and old elevation measurements used to determine</p>
        <p>levee heights are obsolete. (They were inaccurate, anyway.) Bigger levees are heavier and more likely to sink. Gates that block surges entering Lake Pontchartrain might deflect the water elsewhere, perhaps to other coastal settlements, which would in turn need their own levee systems.</p>
        <p>Those gates were proposed and blocked on environmental and other grounds in the 1970's. ''Probably a lot of lives could have been saved if they had been in place,'' said Mr. Stone.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
