<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeing Orange</title>
    <meta content="20WECA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1651396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeanne-Claude (Artist)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caplow, Ted</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DB103AF933A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeing Orange</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TED CAPLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caplow, Ted</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Fish Navy executive director Ted Caplow discusses why he considers The Gates, art installation in Central Park by Christo and Jeanne-Claude, environmentally unfriendly</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR those of you who have traveled in from Westchester to bear witness to ''The Gates'' in Central Park, you know full well that it is many things to many people. For me and my beagle, Hazel, with whom I share a daily walk in the park, ''The Gates'' is just a distraction. What she wants to know is, where have all the squirrels gone? What I want to know is, from the standpoint of industrial ecology, how can Christo and Jeanne-Claude justify the environmental impact of this project?</p>
        <p>On their Web site, the artists, with apparent pride, declare that ''The Gates'' has required 10 1/2 million pounds of steel, 60 miles of vinyl tubing and one million square feet of nylon fabric, plus thousands upon thousands of steel plates, bolts and nuts to hold the whole thing together. The plastic tubes and fabric are described as ''recyclable,'' but no mention is made of the fate of the steel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR those of you who have traveled in from Westchester to bear witness to ''The Gates'' in Central Park, you know full well that it is many things to many people. For me and my beagle, Hazel, with whom I share a daily walk in the park, ''The Gates'' is just a distraction. What she wants to know is, where have all the squirrels gone? What I want to know is, from the standpoint of industrial ecology, how can Christo and Jeanne-Claude justify the environmental impact of this project?</p>
        <p>On their Web site, the artists, with apparent pride, declare that ''The Gates'' has required 10 1/2 million pounds of steel, 60 miles of vinyl tubing and one million square feet of nylon fabric, plus thousands upon thousands of steel plates, bolts and nuts to hold the whole thing together. The plastic tubes and fabric are described as ''recyclable,'' but no mention is made of the fate of the steel.</p>
        <p>According to the United States Department of Energy, the steel industry in this country uses about 18 million B.T.U.'s to produce one ton of steel. Assuming that the cast steel in ''The Gates'' is typical American steel in terms of energy consumption, then making it has required 97 billion B.T.U.'s of energy, equivalent to 28 million kilowatt hours (or the annual electricity consumption of 2,500 Westchester residences).</p>
        <p>Energy for the steel industry is supplied in roughly equal thirds by coal, natural gas and electricity. Using generally accepted rates of carbon dioxide emissions for these three sources, making steel for ''The Gates'' churned out 7,000 tons of carbon dioxide, equivalent to the combined output of about 1,600 average American cars for a year. We would have to plant more than 200 acres of trees and grow them for 10 years to remove this carbon dioxide from the atmosphere. Central Park has an area of about 800 acres, but only part of this has trees; besides, the mature trees that dominate the park do not absorb carbon dioxide effectively, so we cannot look to the park itself to clean up the mess.</p>
        <p>In terms of sheer mass, the amount of plastic in ''The Gates'' is dwarfed by the steel, but emissions of carbon dioxide, dioxins and other toxins from plastics manufacturing are a concern. The plastic chosen for the supports, structural vinyl, widely known as polyvinyl chloride, is a controversial material that releases dioxins and carcinogens when it is manufactured. Polyvinyl chloride has been designated the ''poison plastic'' by Greenpeace and other environmental groups and is no longer recommended for use in household water supply pipes. Of course, the squirrels have not been consulted on this choice.</p>
        <p>It has also been loudly declared that the artists are paying for all of this out of their own pockets, through the sale of spinoff drawings and paintings to art collectors. These drawings can be viewed on the artists' Web site, and all seem to share a pattern of coloration in which the city and the park, the buildings, the trees, the grass, are devoid of life, while the ''The Gates'' themselves are portrayed in vivid color -- the only objects of apparent interest to the artist.</p>
        <p>The setting could have just as easily been any other city, or no city at all, and little would change in the paintings. These depictions of a lifeless New York City are supposedly financing the materials, manpower and energy required to bring us ''The Gates,'' but there is no mention of any rent paid for the use of the park, the pollution of the air and the abuse of the squirrels.</p>
        <p>The choice of such an unfortunate orange hue -- ''saffron'' to the artists, but to the rest of us more evocative of sanitation trucks, prison uniforms or road pylons -- becomes clear: this is the color of hazard and danger. Hazel and I have chosen to interpret the whole business as an ecological warning sign.</p>
        <p>Ted Caplow, an environmental engineer, is the executive director of Fish Navy, a nonprofit organization that promotes sustainable technology.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ted Caplow, an environmental engineer, is the executive director of Fish Navy, a nonprofit organization that promotes sustainable technology.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
