<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long at Work, Congress Is Set On Energy Bill</title>
    <meta content="27energy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/27/politics/27energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1690418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liquified Natural Gas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Daylight Saving Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taxpayers for Common Sense (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barton, Joe L (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6D7133FF934A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long at Work, Congress Is Set On Energy Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Congress, After Years of Effort, Is Set to Pass Broad Energy Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE and MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl; Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congress, after coming up short for years, is preparing to enact mammoth energy plan that would provide generous subsidies to oil and gas industries, encourage new nuclear plants, try to encourage renewable fuels and give federal government new power to override local objections to terminals for LNG imports; Pres Bush will go to Capitol Hill to rally House members; Energy Committee chairman Joe Barton accepts Senate's refusal to go along with easing of air pollution rules he sought for his Texas district; bill sidesteps oil drilling in Arctic National Wildlife Refuge; would extend daylight savings time in 2007, from second Sunday in March until first Sunday in November; list of key provisions; Barton estimates direct spending of up to $12 billion; Taxpayers for Common Sense sees potential $80-billion cost; conservation groups also are critical of proposal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After coming up short for years, Congress is preparing to enact a broad energy plan that would provide generous federal subsidies to the oil and gas industries, encourage new nuclear power plant construction and try to whet the nation's appetite for renewable fuels like ethanol and wind power.</p>
        <p>The mammoth energy policy measure, whose final details were hammered together in nine hours of negotiations that went into the early morning hours Tuesday, also gives the federal government new power to override local objections to facilities for handling growing imports of liquefied natural gas and takes a swipe at China's bid for Unocal. [Page C3.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>House and Senate negotiators hope to finally deliver an energy policy that has been on the administration's to-do list since 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After coming up short for years, Congress is preparing to enact a broad energy plan that would provide generous federal subsidies to the oil and gas industries, encourage new nuclear power plant construction and try to whet the nation's appetite for renewable fuels like ethanol and wind power.</p>
        <p>The mammoth energy policy measure, whose final details were hammered together in nine hours of negotiations that went into the early morning hours Tuesday, also gives the federal government new power to override local objections to facilities for handling growing imports of liquefied natural gas and takes a swipe at China's bid for Unocal. [Page C3.]</p>
        <p>''It is a darn good bill, and it is going to help this country, and the sooner we get it done, the better,'' said Representative Joe L. Barton, the Texas Republican who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>House and Senate leaders hope to send the legislation to President Bush by week's end, finally delivering an energy policy that has been on the administration's to-do list since 2001. But it has remained out of reach despite a crippling summer blackout two years ago and soaring gasoline prices today.</p>
        <p>Hoping to spur action on the energy bill as well as a Central American trade agreement that faces a close vote this week, Mr. Bush is scheduled to travel to Capitol Hill on Wednesday to rally House members behind those initiatives and other measures Republican leaders want to push through before Congress leaves for a five-week recess.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barton, who in his second year as chairman was eager to deliver a measure that has eluded Congress for six years, dropped a contentious plan to provide legal immunity to manufacturers of a gasoline additive that has been blamed for pollution in order to get an agreement. He also did not balk at the Senate's refusal to go along with a relaxation of air pollution rules that he had sought for his district, another potential impediment to a bill.</p>
        <p>Senate negotiators suffered some losses as well, including a plan to require utilities to increase their use of renewable fuels in producing electricity and a proposal to direct the president to find ways to cut American oil use by one million barrels a day within 10 years.</p>
        <p>The bill also sidesteps the issue of opening part of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling, another past sticking point.</p>
        <p>While the authors of the energy legislation said it held the potential to transform the way the United States produces and consumes energy, other lawmakers and critics attacked it as a wrongheaded giveaway at a time of huge energy company profits. They said it represented a missed opportunity to take serious steps to reduce the nation's reliance on imported oil or to cut American energy consumption.</p>
        <p>''This bill is simply a failure,'' said Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California and a senior member of the energy committee. ''It is a huge waste of money.''</p>
        <p>Even advocates of the bill acknowledge it will do almost nothing to reduce gasoline prices immediately, though they say it sets the stage for diversity in the nation's energy mix in coming years by creating markets for emerging sources like ethanol, wind and biomass.</p>
        <p>In a provision that may be most noticed by Americans, daylight savings time would be extended in 2007, beginning on the second Sunday in March and lasting until the first Sunday in November, to save electricity.</p>
        <p>The final part of the energy package -- an estimated $11 billion in tax breaks for energy production and efficiency -- was still being negotiated Tuesday night, and some lawmakers said they were worried that some incentives to reward energy savings were being scaled back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barton estimated the overall cost of the measure in direct spending would be in the range of $10 billion to $12 billion, which he said was acceptable to the administration. But the group Taxpayers for Common Sense said its analysis showed there was a potential $80 billion in spending in the bill, though most of the projects would have to win separate Congressional approval.</p>
        <p>Much of the criticism of the legislation was tied to the billions of dollars that would flow to energy producers through tax breaks, relief from federal oil and gas royalties, grants for research into new ways to extract hard-to-reach deposits, loan guarantees and other financial aid.</p>
        <p>''It's outrageous that this bill helps line the pockets of the oil and gas industry, which is already making record profits,'' said Tiernan Sittenfeld, legislative director of the League of Conservation Voters.</p>
        <p>The bill's authors say that the aid to producers will ultimately pay big dividends in terms of domestic production and that the nuclear industry, which has been unable to build new plants partly because of environmental and safety concerns, needs federal assurances that it can recoup higher costs caused by permitting delays before moving ahead.</p>
        <p>Conservation groups also denounced the defeat of the provisions to cut oil use and increase use of renewable fuels as well as the fact that the measure sidestepped the issue of global warming and ignored automotive mileage standards. They complained, too, that sections of the bill created new exemptions in some of the nation's bedrock environmental laws, like the Clean Water Act, the Safe Drinking Water Act and the National Environmental Policy Act.</p>
        <p>The bill would also repeal the Depression-era Public Utility Holding Company Act, which limits utility mergers, an action that some consumer watchdog groups fear could lead to a wave of utility acquisitions and consolidation.</p>
        <p>With the nation's increasing demand for natural gas, the authors of the measure rejected objections from state officials and granted the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission new authority to approve the location of terminals to handle the imports.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
