<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawmakers Seek to Put Utility Funds In Budget</title>
    <meta content="15FUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/15/nyregion/15fund.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFD6103EF936A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawmakers Seek to Put Utility Funds In Budget</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lawmakers Seek to Shine Light on Fees for Utilities</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one of three budget vetoes he issued this week, Gov. George E. Pataki rejected the Legislature's bid to shine more light on two pots of money fed by hidden fees on utility bills: almost $1 billion that has been used to subsidize renewable energy projects and even pay for television advertisements featuring the governor.</p>
        <p>Aides to the governor, environmentalists and advocates of ''green'' energy, like wind, solar, fuel-cell and hydroelectric power, say the two steady revenue streams lure investors and jobs to New York and should be kept free from legislative politics in Albany, where money is often sucked into pork-barrel projects or bottled up in annual arguments over appropriations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY, April 14 - In one of three budget vetoes he issued this week, Gov. George E. Pataki rejected the Legislature's bid to shine more light on two pots of money fed by hidden fees on utility bills: almost $1 billion that has been used to subsidize renewable energy projects and even pay for television advertisements featuring the governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In one of three budget vetoes he issued this week, Gov. George E. Pataki rejected the Legislature's bid to shine more light on two pots of money fed by hidden fees on utility bills: almost $1 billion that has been used to subsidize renewable energy projects and even pay for television advertisements featuring the governor.</p>
        <p>Aides to the governor, environmentalists and advocates of ''green'' energy, like wind, solar, fuel-cell and hydroelectric power, say the two steady revenue streams lure investors and jobs to New York and should be kept free from legislative politics in Albany, where money is often sucked into pork-barrel projects or bottled up in annual arguments over appropriations.</p>
        <p>But in a year defined by public outcry over Albany's secretive ways, lawmakers from both houses and both parties say legislative oversight would inject a needed level of public accountability into how the money from the utility fees is spent.</p>
        <p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Democrat, referred to the fees as vehicles for the Republican governor to create a ''slush fund.'' Others in Albany have noted how $300,000 of the funds helped pay for television ads. Some featured the governor and ran in New York City, Albany and Rochester during last year's Republican and Democratic National Conventions and the Olympic Games.</p>
        <p>The issue is quickly becoming one of the nastiest post-budget fights this year. Lawmakers are counting heads to see if they can muster enough votes to try to override the veto while aides to the governor are calling the lawmakers' efforts a flawed policy wrapped in a process that violates the State Constitution.</p>
        <p>It was seven years ago when utilities first started funneling the proceeds of one fee, worth about $150 million a year, through the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority, which doles it out in contracts to help spur energy efficiency, lower bills and sustain a reliable supply of electricity. A second fee set to hit in October would collect $741.5 million over the next eight years and be used similarly.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Paul D. Tonko, a Democrat who is chairman of the Energy Committee, said he would urge Mr. Silver to push to override. ''I would advise that we do,'' Mr. Tonko said.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers in both parties say the money should be put onto the state's regular budget, just as billions of dollars in health care costs were added to the regular budget this year. And concerns are mounting in the Republican-led Senate, where the budget bill seeking to do that first passed on March 31. The governor vetoed it, and an override attempt would have to start in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''There is almost a billion dollars in moneys that are off-budget and being spent and we think there needs to be sufficient accountability and transparency and we are going to be reviewing our options on how to proceed,'' said John E. McArdle, a spokesman for Joseph L. Bruno, the Republican majority leader in the Senate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
