<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About Ice: Can't Live With It, Can't Live Without It</title>
    <meta content="26karl" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/26/books/26karl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1727671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karlen, Neal</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gosnell, Mariana</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ice (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gosnell, Mariana</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Ice: The Nature, the History and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DE1230F935A15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About Ice: Can't Live With It, Can't Live Without It</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All About Ice: Can't Live With It, Can't Live Without It</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEAL KARLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Karlen, Neal</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neal Karlen reviews book Ice: The Nature, the History and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance by Mariana Gosnell; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ice  The Nature, the History and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance  By Mariana Gosnell  Illustrated. 560 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>Abe Schwartz, 91, still the voluble dean of Minnesota winter anglers, recently explained his curious passion for spending hours dangling a hook into a hole augered through three feet of frozen lake, saying, ''Ice fishing isn't a sport, it's a punishment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This astonishingly boring-sounding book turns out instead to be an astonishment: an engaging, literate, encyclopedic look at hard water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ice  The Nature, the History and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance  By Mariana Gosnell  Illustrated. 560 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $30.</p>
        <p>Abe Schwartz, 91, still the voluble dean of Minnesota winter anglers, recently explained his curious passion for spending hours dangling a hook into a hole augered through three feet of frozen lake, saying, ''Ice fishing isn't a sport, it's a punishment.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, one approaches Mariana Gosnell's 560-page ''Ice'' with the queasy feeling that this book, subtitled ''The Nature, the History and the Uses of an Astonishing Substance,'' is less about reading than karmic retribution, perhaps for never having listened in eighth-grade science class. Yet this astonishingly boring-sounding book turns out instead to be an astonishment: an engaging, literate, mischievously written and only occasionally maddening voyage, far beyond everything most readers might possibly have wanted to know about hard water.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gosnell is not afraid to ask. A former science writer for Newsweek, and the author of the charming ''Zero Three Bravo: Solo Across America in a Small Plane,'' she grills and at times ribs grandiose scientists; marvels at, flatters and notes the historical idiocies of some polar explorers; and gets to the bottom of what really would happen if global warming melted the West Antarctic Ice Sheet, a frozen desert roughly the size of Europe.</p>
        <p>She learns that if these seven million cubic miles of ice were defrosted by humanity's addiction to fossil fuels, the world's sea level would rise 20 feet, sending Florida, most of Manhattan and almost half of America's population to swim with the fishes, literally. Ms. Gosnell repeats the findings of the man perhaps tied with the football coach Woody Hayes for the scariest Ohio State employee ever. That would be the polar scientist J. H. Mercer, who predicted -- in 1978 -- that the ice sheet might begin to ''deglaciate'' in as little as 50 years.</p>
        <p>Encyclopedic as it is, some may want to read ''Ice'' like an encyclopedia, using the index to guide them to the good parts. The Titanic will receive instant play from many pickers-and-choosers. The scant pages Ms. Gosnell devotes to what she refers to as ''the most famous piece of ice in the history of the world,'' and its 1912 luxury liner victim, is a mostly riveting narrative of a seemingly never-tired topic, never mind Walter Lord's 1955 book, ''A Night to Remember,'' or Leonardo DiCaprio's globally warming 1997 movie performance.</p>
        <p>''Everyone knows the story,'' Ms. Gosnell recounts, but nobody has packed so much of the harrowing tale into one sentence. Halfway into that sentence's clauses, Ms. Gosnell is still picking up steam as fast as the ship lost it, recreating ''the Titanic breaking in two and 46,000 tons of it sliding into the water, carrying tennis racquets, and golf clubs, stocks, bonds, potted palms, 15,000 bottles of ale and stout, 800 cases of shelled walnuts, 30,000 eggs, five grand pianos, a case of gloves, a jeweled copy of the Rubaiyat, an automobile, a telephone switchboard, a bracelet with 'Amy' written on it in diamonds, shuffleboard sticks, a silver duck press, and an ice-making machine (!) 13,000 feet down; the gulp the rent ship made as it vanished; the howling from people released into the freezing water and soon to perish.'' Whew. (!)</p>
        <p>Yet, Ms. Gosnell humanizes the enemy by also explaining the tragedy from the ice's point of view. Born of snow that fell ''a thousand years before Christ,'' she writes, ''the Iceberg has its midnight rendezvous with the great steamship, it drifts on, farther south, until it reaches the Gulf Stream, where the water temperature is many degrees higher, and there, after a journey of a year and a half, it succumbs.'' So will many readers, if they approach ''Ice'' head-on. Instead, those with a scientific bent can dip into entire chapters (or two) devoted to surging glaciers, sea ice, ground ice, icebergs and space ice. Significant room is also devoted to ice castles, ice houses and ice carving, polar bears (who may never set foot on land) and the Antarctic's now-famous emperor penguins, who ''manage to reproduce under the harshest circumstances of any vertebrate on earth''</p>
        <p>National Enquirer readers will thrill at the medical uses of ice (it's what saved John Wayne Bobbitt's penis), while littérateurs will read on both because of Ms. Gosnell's playful prose, and her quest to quote, often without context, seemingly every poem that has ever mentioned ice, kicking off the introduction to her book with some Seamus Heaney, and beginning to wind things up 494 pages later with a giblet of W. S. Merwin.</p>
        <p>By reading ''Ice'' as if it were a cousin of William S. Burroughs's cut-up prose, many will be ultimately surprised that they've consumed the whole book, albeit probably not in one season. Interestingly, the most exuberant voice in this story -- a chronicle that bears as many mixed directions and blind alleys as the Kabbalah -- comes not from scientists, poets or Ms. Gosnell herself. Instead, for words to describe the magic that ice can bring to humanity, she quotes Eric Nesterenko, who played right wing for the Chicago Blackhawks hockey team for more than 20 years.</p>
        <p>Even in the old days, when you'd throw and receive elbows without benefit of a helmet, mouth guard or many teeth, Mr. Nesterenko felt the almost supernatural enchantment of flying atop ice. ''You can wheel and dive and turn, you can lay yourself into impossible angles that you never could walking or running. You lay yourself at a 45-degree angle, your elbows virtually touching the ice as you turn,'' the former rink hero describes. ''Incredible! It's beautiful! You're breaking the bounds of gravity. I have a feeling this is the innate desire of man  just being in pure motion.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
