<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>International Rescue Team Wins Race to Free Sub Crew</title>
    <meta content="08russia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/08/international/europe/08russia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DD173EF93BA3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>International Rescue Team Wins Race to Free Sub Crew</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">International Rescue Team Wins Race to Free Sub Crew</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER DREW and STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The seven sailors on a small Russian submarine had only three to six hours of air left when a British submersible snipped chunks of old fishing net that had trapped them deep below the Pacific, freeing them to pop to the surface and enjoy a jubilant return to land, American and British rescue officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The men had been huddled together in the dark, cold vessel for three days, as American, British and Russian officials frantically plotted the complicated rescue, often communicating through little more than cellphone text messages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The seven sailors had only three to six hours of air left when a British submersible freed the Russian submarine trapped below the Pacific.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The seven sailors on a small Russian submarine had only three to six hours of air left when a British submersible snipped chunks of old fishing net that had trapped them deep below the Pacific, freeing them to pop to the surface and enjoy a jubilant return to land, American and British rescue officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The men had been huddled together in the dark, cold vessel for three days, as American, British and Russian officials frantically plotted the complicated rescue, often communicating through little more than cellphone text messages.</p>
        <p>And as the British and American rescuers rushed to the scene, delays repeatedly cropped up, largely because of a shortage of trucks and other delivery equipment on Russia's isolated Kamchatka Peninsula, participants said. Yet the stranded Russian crew was able to hang on longer than expected, probably because the 40-degree temperatures and an inevitable buildup of noxious gas made them drowsy, conserving energy and their dwindling oxygen supply, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Bill Orr, the coordinator of an international submarine rescue office, said Sunday that shortly before the British vessel clipped the last debris that had held the submarine in a stranglehold more than 600 feet below the waves, Russian officials estimated that the stranded crew had only three more hours of breathable air. The leader of the British rescue team, Cmdr. Ian Riches, told reporters in Kamchatka that the crew could not have lasted more than six hours longer.</p>
        <p>When the sailors finally crawled out of the vessel's hatch on Sunday, an American doctor at the scene found them to be ''a little hypothermic, a little on the weak side and very happy to be on the surface again,'' said Capt. Russell R. Ervin, a United States Navy officer in charge of submarine rescue operations.</p>
        <p>The rescue culminated a frenzied push by several nations to reach the men before time ran out. Participants said it was possible only because of intense efforts to build cooperation after the Russian submarine Kursk exploded and sank five years ago. But, they said, it also took extraordinary improvisation -- and a few strokes of luck -- to rush tons of equipment to an isolated site off Russia's Far East coast and disentangle the vessel as the hours ticked down.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't the Red Ball Express here,'' Captain Ervin said, referring to difficulties in unloading the rescue equipment at Kamchatka's antiquated air and sea ports.</p>
        <p>In the end, the American and British officials said, the main culprit was a discarded fishing net, which was wrapped so tightly around the submarine's propeller and hull that the layers of stretched nylon appeared to be as thick as a one-and-one-half-inch cable.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said the vessel, which was described as being on a training mission, also might have been caught on cables connected to an undersea surveillance system, a vestige of the cold war cat-and-mouse espionage that took place beneath the seas.</p>
        <p>The episode also summed up how much has changed since those days, as Russian officials, though once again embarrassed by their own navy's failures, released a statement expressing ''profound gratitude'' to the former Western adversaries who had rushed to help.</p>
        <p>Many Russians celebrated the return of the crew -- six sailors and a civilian involved in the construction of the submarine, a 44-foot-long vessel called the AS-28 Priz.</p>
        <p>The men appeared wan as they stepped off a ship that brought them back to a port near Kamchatka's capital, Petropavlovsk-Kamchatski. The submarine's commander, Lt. Vyacheslav Milashevsky, 25, debarked with a crisp salute, saying he was ''fine,'' and led the others down the gangplank before they were whisked to a local hospital.</p>
        <p>Defense Minister Sergei B. Ivanov, overseeing what could have become another tragedy for the country's beleaguered armed forces, reacted jubilantly, raising and shaking his fists in the air as the submarine surfaced and its crew members emerged, having opened the hatch and clambered out on their own.</p>
        <p>But Dmitry O. Rogozin, a leader of the Motherland Party in the lower house, called for a criminal investigation, suggesting that commanders were negligent for squandering recent increases in the military's budget.</p>
        <p>''It is an embarrassment for Russia because we see that our leaders can do nothing to save even a small submarine,'' he said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The outcome and the international cooperation involved in it starkly contrasted with Russia's response five years ago this month when an explosion sank the nuclear submarine Kursk in the Barents Sea, eventually killing all 118 men aboard.</p>
        <p>In that case Russia's commanders obfuscated, dismissed offers of assistance and even accused NATO submarines of having caused the disaster. But this time, the Russians sought Western help, issuing a request on Thursday night, within 10 to 12 hours after the submarine became disabled, American officials said.</p>
        <p>''The lessons of the Kursk have been learned and learned very well,'' Britain's top military attaché to Russia, Air Commodore Wils Metcalfe, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>Much of the increased international cooperation has been channeled through Mr. Orr's group, the International Submarine Escape and Rescue Liaison Office, based in Norfolk, Va.</p>
        <p>It conducted mock rescue drills off the coast of Italy in June, and Russia took part in the exercise. The group's goal is to send help to the scene of almost any submarine accident within 72 hours, and officials said its Web site lit up quickly late last week with offers of equipment from several countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orr, a former naval officer who is also still involved in the Navy's submarine rescue operations as a civilian, immediately plunged into helping the American and British rescue forces respond, acting ''as firemen do when they look over and see smoke.''</p>
        <p>The British submersible -- a crewless vessel with cameras to beam images to its operators on a surface ship and with robotic arms and cable clippers -- had already been readied for shipment for a training exercise, Commodore Metcalfe said. So it reached Kamchatka late Saturday local time, about two hours before two similar American submersibles, known as Super Scorpios.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orr said rescue officials had found out while the transport planes were in the air that Petropavlovsk-Kamchatski's airport did not have a device that was heavy enough to unload the control vans for the British and American submersibles. So the Americans flew in an unloading device from Japan and used it to help the British, who were already trucking other parts of their Scorpio system to the seaport 50 miles away.</p>
        <p>The Russians also had only a limited number of heavy-duty trucks, Captain Ervin said, so the Americans had to wait to unload their Scorpios until the trucks that carried the British gear returned.</p>
        <p>So even though it took a Russian ship six hours to carry the British submersible to the scene of the accident, and then six more hours to ready the Scorpio and clip all the debris from the submarine, the American submersibles were still at least three hours away when the rescue was completed Sunday.</p>
        <p>While all those operations stretched on, Russian officials continued to extend their estimates of how long the crew's air would last.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orr said one of the biggest concerns was a buildup of carbon dioxide as the crew members breathed in the enclosed space. All submarines take measures to control that buildup, because too much carbon dioxide can cause headaches and drowsiness and eventually be fatal.</p>
        <p>After their submarine was trapped, the crew members turned off the heat to conserve power for the breathing system, officials said. The temperature on board quicklydropped to that of the surrounding water, about 40 degrees, and crew members were forced to put on jackets and huddle together as their ordeal dragged on. Once the British Scorpio dove near the submarine, it quickly began snipping the tightly wound fishing net.</p>
        <p>But after about two and a half hours, in which the controllers used a joystick to keep the tethered submersible hovering next to the submarine, another snag arose: One of the guide lines on the cable cutter became bent, Neil Hopkins, a British submarine rescue official, said in a telephone interview. So the Scorpio had to be pulled to the surface for repairs before being lowered again to finish the job and free the submarine -- at 4:26 p.m. Sunday, local time (11:26 p.m. Saturday, Eastern time).</p>
        <p>Compared with what happened with the Kursk, ''this time, the Russian fleet commander didn't delay in asking for help,'' Captain Ervin said. ''And it's a darn good thing, because they were running out of air.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
