<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="09BIZD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DB143EF93AA35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cablevision Is Shutting Most of Its Voom Business  Cablevision Systems has decided to discontinue its Voom satellite business, but maintain ownership and sell rights to 21 high-definition television channels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cablevision Is Shutting Most of Its Voom Business  Cablevision Systems has decided to discontinue its Voom satellite business, but maintain ownership and sell rights to 21 high-definition television channels.</p>
        <p>The action resolves a standoff between the Cablevision chairman, Charles F. Dolan, and a son, who is the chief executive, over whether to continue to finance the operation. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Falls, but Is Up for the Week  The Nasdaq composite index lost 19.44 points, to close at 1,999.35, but had a gain of 0.73 percent for the week. So far this year, the Nasdaq is down 8.09 percent. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 84.98 points, to 10,461.34, and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index was down 9.94 points, or 0.8 percent, to 1,181.20. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Dismay From Painkiller Users  As Pfizer removed Bextra from the market under pressure from federal regulators, who also issued broad warnings that other popular painkillers could hurt the heart, stomach or skin, people who rely on such drugs responded with dismay and a sense of weariness. [A16.]</p>
        <p>A Sharp Audit Committee Pays Off  Shares of concerns with accounting expertise on their audit committees tended to rise higher, a study of 300 of companies found. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Italian Bank Approves Takeover Bid  Banca Nazionale del Lavoro approved a takeover bid of 6.5 billion euros ($8.4 billion) from Banco Bilbao Vizcaya Argentaria of Spain, shifting the spotlight to Italy's central bank, which has expressed doubts about the offer and could block it. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Scrushy Tries to Exclude Testimony  Richard M. Scrushy asked the judge in his fraud trial to exclude testimony he gave federal regulators that prosecutors contend proves he committed perjury. [C10.]</p>
        <p>E.P.A. Cancels a Pesticide Study  Stephen L. Johnson, left, acting administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, canceled a study of the effects of pesticides on infants and babies, a day after two Democratic senators said they would block his confirmation in his job if the research continued. A recruiting flier for the program, called Children's Environmental Exposure Research Study, offered $970, a free camcorder, a bib and a T-shirt to parents whose infants or babies were exposed to pesticides if the parents completed the two-year study. [A15.]</p>
        <p>A five-year effort to determine if the Environmental Protection Agency has the authority to regulate carbon dioxide emissions from motor vehicles reached an appeals court. [A17.]</p>
        <p>Willis Settles Insurance Inquiry  Willis North America agreed to pay $50 million to settle an investigation into anticompetitive practices involving incentive fees in property and casualty insurance sales. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Another Morgan Stanley Departure  Vikram Gandhi quit as Morgan Stanley's co-head of investment banking for financial institutions to join Credit Suisse First Boston, becoming at least the fifth high-ranking bank official to leave in the last two weeks. [C2.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Fines Swiss Biotech Company  Syngenta was fined $375,000 by the Agriculture Department for inadvertently selling unapproved genetically altered corn seed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Arrests in Call Center Scheme  Police arrested 12 men in western India, including three former employees at a call center, on charges of cheating four Citibank customers out of nearly $350,000. [C2.]</p>
        <p>No Resolution of Trade Dispute  The Bush administration said that a 90-day negotiation period had failed to resolve a trade dispute with the European Union over commercial airplane subsidies. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
