<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flouting the Law of Nail and Claw</title>
    <meta content="03NJNAILS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1661932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="WHERE WE LIVE: ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Gorce, Tammy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E3DF103FF930A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flouting the Law of Nail and Claw</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMMY LA GORCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Gorce, Tammy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tammy La Gorce essay on bucking trend in New Jersey by refusing to get her nails and toes done; photo (Special Issue: Where We Live) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE in S.U.V. land, it's the little things that define us. My friend Meg keeps ducks in her yard and allows shoes in her house. A mother I car-pool with reads ''The National Enquirer'' and kick-boxes. The couple who just moved in across the street, to judge by the rumble that rocks the block at 10 p.m. every other Monday, put away a case of wine every night and are responsible about recycling.</p>
        <p>Me? I don't get my nails done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE in S.U.V. land, it's the little things that define us. My friend Meg keeps ducks in her yard and allows shoes in her house. A mother I car-pool with reads ''The National Enquirer'' and kick-boxes. The couple who just moved in across the street, to judge by the rumble that rocks the block at 10 p.m. every other Monday, put away a case of wine every night and are responsible about recycling.</p>
        <p>Me? I don't get my nails done.</p>
        <p>If I didn't live in New Jersey, I suspect I would have to get by on some other quirk. But considering that there are 19 nail salons within walking distance of my house in Madison, and that every woman I have gotten to know in eight years of living here regularly schedules appointments at them or in towns nearby, my anti-mani/pedi stance might be -- probably is -- construed as both a measure of my refusal to assimilate and a defining characteristic.</p>
        <p>In a state full of finger and toe flaunters, none of whom seem overly concerned with the Jersey Girl cliché, my flip-flops come July flash nothing but neatly nipped unvarnished nail. And in this, I feel a tie with both Upper East Side anti-Botoxers and lobster-haters from Maine. On the one hand -- sorry about the pun -- the failure of ''Special! Manicure/Pedicure $25'' signs scattered about town to pique my interest has something to do with principle. On the other, I don't like the places themselves, and the process is pretty unappealing too.</p>
        <p>The whir of activity at the average New Jersey nail salon stops for no one. Walk in, and the non-English-speaking lady closest to the door momentarily quits her filing to point her emery board toward kiosks displaying painted acrylic nails by the hundred, each representing a specific polish. There, you must determine, based on mood and skin tone, what's right for you.</p>
        <p>If Cha-Ching Cherry, Royal Flush Blush or Argenteeny Pinkini don't seem right, chances are something in the I'm Not Really a Waitress and Italian Polish Love Affair groups might. If you're stuck, you could ask the person peering over your shoulder for advice, but she would be too preoccupied figuring out her own Coney Island Cotton Candy versus Ecuadoral Coral problem to help you, or else too polite to point out that the Pistol Packin' Pink family, not the Pompeii Purples, is where you belong in the first place.</p>
        <p>Color confusion is but a chip on the smooth, shiny surface of what makes visiting a nails place a soul-sucking experience, though. Far worse than the crinkled magazines, fake plants and acetone smell is the small talk, which can feel something like being rhetorically bludgeoned by a cuticle stick. In a sequence worthy of ''Groundhog Day,'' someone's daughter is always adjusting well to her first year away at college and somebody else is waving her fresh-dried hand halfway out the door, hurrying home to pack for a week in Bermuda.</p>
        <p>More terrible still is the guilt: in no way am I pampering averse (Ben, the gifted deep-tissue masseur at Westfield's On the Side spa, will back me up on this), but I am not unproud to say that I will never get used to somebody else, particularly a sad-eyed somebody else who is old enough to be my mother, washing my feet.</p>
        <p>But that is not where I object to the mani/pedi on principle. The truly contemptible part of the nails ritual comes at the end, at what those who have mastered the wet-toed waddle call drying stations. Here, aided by an air-blowing device equal in force to the breath you might expel to knock the fluff off a dandelion, you are directed to sit and watch paint dry. For 10 minutes. That you could be spending those minutes picking up your son's antibiotic or working on a dippy essay is, in itself, excruciating, but the implications I'm thinking of run larger.</p>
        <p>In terms of productivity alone, imagine how much might be accomplished if the women, girls and metrosexual men of New Jersey stopped drying -- just drying! -- their nails. Then, dare to dream bigger. Think of the reputation-reversing possibilities we in New Jersey would enjoy should the manicured masses blow off their appointments for a single week. Pooled toward a cause like environmentalism -- targeting, maybe, the ozone layer we've wreaked havoc on with all those hairspray cans -- our collective $25-spots would go a long way.</p>
        <p>The ragged of cuticle could rise up, proud to stamp out the Jersey Girl stereotype once and for all. And it would all happen faster than your Not So Bora Bora-ing Pink can dry.</p>
        <p>WHERE WE LIVE: ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
