<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abundant Energy Fuels Alberta's Economic Development and Growth in Influence</title>
    <meta content="06CANA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/06/international/americas/06canada.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050208T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1647895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alberta (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Ralph (Premier)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Canada</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D6113BF935A35751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abundant Energy Fuels Alberta's Economic Development and Growth in Influence</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Abundant Energy Fuels Alberta's Economic Development and Growth in Influence</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>CALGARY, Alberta</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alberta's vast oil, natural gas and coal resources put province at center of Canada's economic growth and innovation, and make it increasingly powerful cultural and social force; officials predict one million barrels of oil a day produced from oil sands will double by 2010 and triple by 2020; Premier Ralph Klein is outspoken conservative, and Alberta seems increasingly at odds with rest of liberal Canada; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is an old joke in this oil-rich province where a cowboy hat and boots are always in fashion: What is the difference between Alberta and Texas? Alberta has better relations with the United States.</p>
        <p>Of course, that may be an exaggeration even in a province where tall tales are still told around the prairie campfire. But it is all the more telling at a time when the rest of Canada seems to be moving away from the United States in social and foreign policy -- and all the more relevant as Alberta comes into its own as an economic powerhouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With conventional oil reserves declining, Alberta officials say time is on the side of a province that stands to grow all the more confident and assertive in Canadian politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is an old joke in this oil-rich province where a cowboy hat and boots are always in fashion: What is the difference between Alberta and Texas? Alberta has better relations with the United States.</p>
        <p>Of course, that may be an exaggeration even in a province where tall tales are still told around the prairie campfire. But it is all the more telling at a time when the rest of Canada seems to be moving away from the United States in social and foreign policy -- and all the more relevant as Alberta comes into its own as an economic powerhouse.</p>
        <p>Alberta's premier, Ralph Klein, is the most vociferous national political figure on opposing same-sex marriage, promoting a partnership with the United States on a missile defense system and contending that the Kyoto Protocol on global warming could smother economic growth.</p>
        <p>His newest crusade is to seek more private enterprise in Canada's public health care system, which, though ailing, remains an article of faith.</p>
        <p>In May, he plans to hold an international symposium here to study the best elements of health care systems around the world, trying to spur a national debate over how to deal with growing waiting lists for medical tests and nonemergency surgery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein might be seen around the country as a bumptious figure of little consequence if not for the vast oil, natural gas and coal resources of his province. Those resources put Alberta at the center of Canada's economic growth and innovation, and make this out-of-step province an increasingly powerful cultural and social force to be reckoned with.</p>
        <p>Alberta's 176 billion barrels of oil reserves are the greatest proven stock outside Saudi Arabia. But most of those reserves are in oil sands, a thick substance only profitable to extract and process when world energy prices are high as they are now.</p>
        <p>With conventional oil reserves declining, demand in China growing rapidly and new extraction methods making oil sands cheaper to process, Alberta officials say time is on the side of a province that stands to grow all the more confident and assertive in Canadian politics.</p>
        <p>They predict that the one million barrels of oil a day produced from oil sands last year will rise to two million by 2010 and to three million by 2020.</p>
        <p>''You can paint a picture that sees Alberta doing better and better,'' said Charlie Fischer, president and chief executive officer of Nexen Inc., a global oil company based in Calgary that is investing in the latest technology to extract oil sands. ''As Alberta becomes stronger financially it will have more influence overall in Canada.''</p>
        <p>For now, Alberta appears increasingly at odds culturally and politically with liberal Canada. Its Bible Belt is alarmed by same-sex marriage, making the province one of only three in Canada that have so far not changed the definition of marriage to include gay and lesbian unions. It is the only province with a flat tax and no retail sales tax, and it proudly lowers personal and corporate rates year after year. The provincial government has privatized many public services and reduced social services to create the country's only provincial budget surplus in recent years.</p>
        <p>Alberta has the money to be innovative, and whatever direction it takes the rest of North America will be watching. The high oil prices and huge building projects to develop the province's oil sands are encouraging all sorts of economic activity.</p>
        <p>Calgary and Edmonton are already two of the fastest-growing Canadian cities, with sprawling suburbs, snarling traffic and growing research centers. Engineers, doctors, teachers and architects from around Canada are moving here for higher salaries. With the price of oil at almost $50 a barrel, Alberta received royalties of $7 billion last year. The amount is so large that the province can risk experimenting and a cutoff of federal health care money for breaking guidelines prohibiting the privatization of health care, a course Mr. Klein has hinted he may try.</p>
        <p>''The province has a government with more money than it can spend,'' said Roger Gibbons, president of the Canada West Foundation, a policy research group in Calgary. ''Alberta has the chance to lead the country in health care reform. If the federal government cuts funding in retaliation, that's a financial loss Alberta can absorb.''</p>
        <p>With 3.2 million people, or slightly more than 10 percent of the Canadian population, Alberta remains far less influential than political powerhouses like Ontario and Quebec. But no province came close to its 10.3 percent population growth between the 1996 and 2001 censuses, and political scientists and businesspeople here predict that it is only a matter of time before Alberta reaches a tipping point of national influence.</p>
        <p>The newly united Conservative Party, the main opposition to the governing Liberals, was born out of Alberta politics, and its leader, Stephen Harper, comes from Calgary.</p>
        <p>''I have a hunch that what you saw in the United States with power moving out from east to west and south, you'll see a little more here the emergence of a different power base,'' predicted Kevin Libin, editor of Western Standard, a new Calgary-based conservative magazine.</p>
        <p>The swing toward the west accelerated in the 1960's and 1970's, when corporate headquarters fled Montreal as Quebec threatened to secede from Canada. Toronto benefited most, and remains the national financial center. But Calgary also grew, though it had a deep recession when oil prices slumped in the late 1970's and early 1980's.</p>
        <p>Now, with Canadian business looking to Asia for markets, investment is moving west again -- to Vancouver, British Columbia, and to Calgary.</p>
        <p>The China connection is likely to grow in importance as Enbridge Inc. proceeds with a $2.2 billion pipeline to move 400,000 barrels of Alberta crude a day to the Pacific coast for export. Chinese investment in the project is considered likely.</p>
        <p>The biggest potential risk to Alberta's plans appears to be environmental concerns about global warming. Because oil sands require huge amounts of energy to extract, the provincial government and several energy companies are stepping up efforts to make the process cleaner.</p>
        <p>They include proposals to reuse and store greenhouse emissions like carbon dioxide, to recycle the byproducts of oil sands development and to produce cleaner burning natural gas from coal. ''That is the vision,'' said James Dinning, a former provincial treasurer and a businessman. ''The beautiful thing about Alberta is we like to experiment and try new and different things.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 8, 2005, Tuesday  A picture caption on Sunday about economic growth in Alberta, Canada, referred incompletely in some copies to the location of the undeveloped land that was shown. It is near Calgary, the capital.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 9, 2005, Wednesday  A picture caption on Sunday with an article about economic growth in the Canadian province of Alberta referred incompletely in some copies to the location of the undeveloped land that was shown. And a correction in this space yesterday referred incorrectly to the city involved. The land is near Calgary; while that is one of Alberta's largest cities, the capital is Edmonton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 8, 2005, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Sunday about economic growth in Alberta, Canada, referred incompletely in some copies to the location of the undeveloped land that was shown. It is near Calgary, the capital.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: February 9, 2005, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Sunday with an article about economic growth in the Canadian province of Alberta referred incompletely in some copies to the location of the undeveloped land that was shown. And a correction in this space yesterday referred incorrectly to the city involved. The land is near Calgary; while that is one of Alberta's largest cities, the capital is Edmonton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
