<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Composers In a 5-Day Berkshires Jamboree</title>
    <meta content="10tang" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/10/arts/music/10tang.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tanglewood Festival of Contemporary Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tanglewood Music Center (Lenox, Mass)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Tanglewood Music Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0D7173EF933A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Composers In a 5-Day Berkshires Jamboree</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Composers in a 5-Day Berkshires Jamboree</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <dateline>LENOX, Mass., Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews five-day Festival of Contemporary Music at Tanglewood Music Center; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Time was when backstage politics and disputes about programming stole some of the spotlight from the music offered at the Festival of Contemporary Music, the annual series performed mainly by the students and faculty of the Tanglewood Music Center. Lately, though, a productive calm has prevailed as the composers and conductors who serve brief terms directing the festival have been free to present the music they consider important.</p>
        <p>This year's five-day festival, which ended on Monday night, was directed by the composer John Harbison, who described his programming as ''an anthology'' of contemporary styles, with the main focus on the last decade. Listeners attuned to new music could easily carp about composers or styles that were slighted, but Mr. Harbison touched on most of the bases. And it became clear over the five days that stylistic dogma interests him less than emotional depth and clarity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year's five-day festival, which was an anthology of contemporary styles from the last decade, stressed emotional depth and clarity over stylistic dogma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Time was when backstage politics and disputes about programming stole some of the spotlight from the music offered at the Festival of Contemporary Music, the annual series performed mainly by the students and faculty of the Tanglewood Music Center. Lately, though, a productive calm has prevailed as the composers and conductors who serve brief terms directing the festival have been free to present the music they consider important.</p>
        <p>This year's five-day festival, which ended on Monday night, was directed by the composer John Harbison, who described his programming as ''an anthology'' of contemporary styles, with the main focus on the last decade. Listeners attuned to new music could easily carp about composers or styles that were slighted, but Mr. Harbison touched on most of the bases. And it became clear over the five days that stylistic dogma interests him less than emotional depth and clarity.</p>
        <p>Unquestionably the most immediate knockout of the series was the last piece performed, Steven Stucky's Second Concerto for Orchestra (2004), an electrifying display of orchestral fireworks that won the Pulitzer Prize this year. Composed for the Los Angeles Philharmonic to play in its new Walt Disney Concert Hall, the piece uses a large orchestra and keeps all its sections busy creating textures that shimmer, sizzle and seduce. And that's just its surface charm; Mr. Stucky uses all this, along with a rich lyricism, in the service of an imaginative structure with a set of wide-ranging variations at the center and no padding whatsoever.</p>
        <p>The performance by the Tanglewood Music Center Orchestra, led by Stefan Asbury, was polished and fully engaged. Mr. Asbury also led Lee Hyla's ''Triadic Coast'' (2005), an appealing brassy score commissioned for the occasion, and Alan Pierson led Julian Philips's''Out of Light'' (2001), a lush, fluid score that evoked Barber and Britten, slightly updated.</p>
        <p>There were real finds in the chamber programs as well. Stanislaw Skrowaczewski's ''Musica a Quattro'' (1998), a plangent, dark-hued work for clarinet and strings, heard Friday, suggested that listeners who know Mr. Skrowaczewski only as a conductor are missing an important part of the picture. On the same program, Mr. Harbison's String Quartet No. 4 (2001) shared Mr. Skrowaczewski's dark coloration and deliberate pacing, but his work was more dramatic and shapely, and it gradually climbed into the light by way of a vigorous finale.</p>
        <p>Milton Babbitt's writing can be abstruse, but at a vocal concert on Saturday he was represented by three recent songs in which the vocal lines, though still angular at times, seemed to bend to the poetry in ways that Mr. Babbitt resisted in his early works.</p>
        <p>Margaret Brouwer's fantastically eclectic ''Light'' (2001) filtered fragments of medieval and Renaissance pieces through a prism of free-ranging melody. Her work and Shulamit Ran's ''Amichai Songs'' (1985) both use a harpsichord in their accompanying ensembles; Ms. Ran included a viola da gamba as well, although her assertively post-tonal music does not glance backward, as Ms. Brouwer's does. Augusta Read Thomas's ''In My Sky at Twilight'' (2001) bridges those worlds effectively, but also stands apart: where Mr. Babbitt, Ms. Brouwer and Ms. Ran offer focused song settings, Ms. Thomas's score is an expansive, unfolding drama built on text fragments that range from Sappho to W.S. Merwin.</p>
        <p>Steven Mackey, a polystylistic provocateur, was represented by two quirkily inventive works in a Sunday morning concert. His ''Gathering'' (2005), a premiere, is an Alleluia setting, easygoing and artfully articulated, and scored for the odd combination of trombones, vibraphones and voices. An earlier work, ''Indigenous Instruments'' (1989), uses detuned instruments and a sense of humor to suggest what Mr. Mackey called ''vernacular music from a culture that doesn't actually exist.''</p>
        <p>The highlight of a percussion concert on Saturday evening was Gunther Schuller's Grand Concerto for percussion and keyboards (2005), an involving 22-minute work in which eight percussionists, a harpist and two keyboardists used an enormous array of instruments to produce a sound in which gentleness and nuance trumped the aggressive noisemaking that the vast stage setup led listeners to expect. Its companions were nearly as appealing. In ''Acid Rain'' (1997), Edward Cohen used the timbres of glockenspiels, vibraphones and pianos to create an appealingly metallic but changeable texture. Joan Tower's ''DNA'' (2003) took the idea of continual timbral evolution even further.</p>
        <p>Space precludes listing the student soloists who brought all these performances to life. But the music aside, one of the joys of this festival is watching these musicians, occasionally augmented by faculty and guest performers, playing this music with the devotion, energy and precision they bring to it.</p>
        <p>The contributions of the professional music world gave them mixed messages, though. Ingo Metzmacher, a fine new-music conductor, was unable to coax more than a ragged, perfunctory account of Elliott Carter's ''Adagio Tenebroso'' (1994) on Friday evening. But on Sunday, the superb new-music band Eighth Blackbird played works by Derek Bermel, Gordon Fitzell, Frederic Rzewski and David Gordon -- some by memory -- and showed their younger colleagues that it can be both exciting and fun to play this music night after night.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
