<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Politics as Usual, And Then Some</title>
    <meta content="20rosenbaum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/20/weekinreview/20rosenbaum.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1719134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cheney, Dick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3D81E3EF933A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Politics as Usual, And Then Some</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Politics as Usual, and Then Some</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVY CROCKETT was so confident of his own judgment that he lived by the motto ''Be sure you're right, then go ahead.''</p>
        <p>For years now, critics have complained that the Bush administration is equally cocksure, pursuing its political and ideological goals even when they are in conflict with data collected by agencies, analysis provided by professionals and procedures set by law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Critics have complained that the Bush administration pursues its political and ideological goals even when they are in conflict with data collected by agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVY CROCKETT was so confident of his own judgment that he lived by the motto ''Be sure you're right, then go ahead.''</p>
        <p>For years now, critics have complained that the Bush administration is equally cocksure, pursuing its political and ideological goals even when they are in conflict with data collected by agencies, analysis provided by professionals and procedures set by law.</p>
        <p>Last week, this issue seemed to gain intensity as reports of the politicization of the government made the news almost every day. The pileup underscored what seems to be a consensus in political and academic circles -- not only among Democrats but also among Republicans who want Mr. Bush to take a strong hand in shaping policy -- that this administration seems more willing than its recent predecessors to bypass the bureaucracy to put its mark on government.</p>
        <p>''The Bush administration is certainly not the first administration to do this kind of thing,'' said Mickey Edwards, a former Republican congressman from Oklahoma who is now a lecturer at Princeton, ''but they seem much more heavy-handed about it.''</p>
        <p>All week the Democrats tried to drive home their argument that the White House had skewed intelligence to make the case to the public, to Congress and to the United Nations for going to war in Iraq, but other news developments played to the politicization drumbeat, too. On Monday, the nonpartisan examiners at the Government Accountability Office concluded that the Food and Drug Administration had relied on politics and ideology rather than solid science when it rejected over-the-counter sales of Plan B, the ''morning after'' contraceptive. The next day, the inspector general of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting found that the agency's former chairman, Kenneth Y. Tomlinson, had repeatedly crossed bounds established by law intended to protect public television and radio from political interference.</p>
        <p>In each instance, the administration rejected accusations of political malfeasance. Officials at the F.D.A. and Mr. Tomlinson said they had been pilloried by partisan investigators who had not looked at all the evidence. And President Bush and Vice President Dick Cheney, accusing critics of undermining the war effort, gave strong speeches denying that anyone had hyped intelligence about whether Saddam Hussein had stockpiles of banned weapons and ties to Al Qaeda.</p>
        <p>The White House rejects any suggestion that the administration has acted improperly in any of these instances. Dana M. Perino, a spokeswoman, said: ''As the chief executive, it is entirely appropriate that the president develop policies for implementation by the federal government. His policies are neither partisan nor political, but created to protect the American people, grow the economy and improve health and welfare.''</p>
        <p>There is no question that other presidents have also tried to break down the firewalls meant to keep politics out of parts of the government.</p>
        <p>President Bill Clinton's advisers rejected professional estimates from budget analysts about how much his abortive health care initiative would cost. His vice president, Al Gore, drove some environmental researchers out of government positions because their views on global warming and ozone depletion clashed with his own.</p>
        <p>In the Reagan and first Bush administrations, annual deficits almost always turned out to be far larger than the White House Office of Management and Budget had projected when the White House submitted its budget.</p>
        <p>In 1971, when monthly unemployment figures were worse than President Richard M. Nixon wanted to acknowledge, the White House ordered the commissioner of labor statistics to stop holding news conferences to interpret the data.</p>
        <p>Joel D. Aberbach, director of the Center for American Politics and Public Policy at the University of California, Los Angeles, says the normal government processes have become increasingly if not steadily politicized in the last 40 years or so.</p>
        <p>''It has happened in fits and starts,'' Mr. Aberbach said. Nixon, he said, tried aggressively to put a political stamp on government. The Ford and Carter administrations were much less political, but then Ronald Reagan took politicization even farther than Nixon. President George H. W. Bush had less of a political agenda, Mr. Aberbach said. But Mr. Clinton ran the White House like a permanent campaign, and ''the people in this administration seem to think they know all the answers.''</p>
        <p>The news last week, at least in the view of the president's critics, seemed to be part of a pattern.</p>
        <p>In August, the Justice Department demoted a statistician who had worked there for 23 years because, the statistician claimed, he refused to withhold data about racial profiling by police officers.</p>
        <p>Last year, referring to matters like climate change and embryonic stem cells, more than 60 prominent scientists signed a statement saying the administration had ''misrepresented scientific knowledge and misled the public about the implications of its policies.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most striking example of the administration's bypassing the bureaucracy to accomplish a political goal occurred in late 2003 when the Medicare actuary, Richard S. Foster, was told by his politically appointed boss that he would be fired if he gave Congress his best estimate of the cost of the administration's prescription-drug plan. If he had told the truth -- that his projections showed the bill would cost $500 billion to $600 billion over 10 years, not $400 billion, as the administration was saying publicly -- the bill surely would not have passed in the House, Republicans and Democrats agree.</p>
        <p>Three former high administration officials -- Richard A. Clarke, the White House counterterrorism chief; Paul H. O'Neill, Mr. Bush's first treasury secretary; and John J. DiIulio Jr., who headed the president's office of faith-based initiatives -- complained publicly after they left the government that the administration had repeatedly let politics trump sound policy analysis.</p>
        <p>For the most part, supporters of Mr. Bush do not deny that his administration has put an extra dose of politics in the government. They approve of it, even if some might draw the line before he draws his. Some say they would go even further, although no one would go as far as calling it acceptable to lead the country into war based on a lie, if that turns out to be the case.</p>
        <p>Michael Franc, vice president for government relations at the Heritage Foundation, said that presidential appointees ''see a lot of people who are their political enemies, who are in top positions and who are trying to impede what they want to accomplish.''</p>
        <p>The administration seems to be influenced, at least in part, by an innate mistrust of the civil service and the intelligence establishment, which many Republicans believe to be Democratic in outlook.</p>
        <p>Charles O. Jones, emeritus professor of political science at the University of Wisconsin, recalled that ''the same things that are being said about Bush in this regard were said about the Reagan administration and the Nixon administration.''</p>
        <p>''Most Republican presidents,'' Mr. Jones said, ''come into office believing that if they're going to get anything done in an entrenched bureaucracy, if they're going to go in a direction that suits their politics and their policy objectives, then they're going to have to find some way to get control of the bureaucracy.''</p>
        <p>Randy Simmons, the chairman of the political science department at Utah State University, who describes himself as a libertarian, said he had firsthand experience of how an entrenched bureaucracy can thwart political officials who want to make changes.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the Reagan administration, Mr. Simmons said, he joined the Interior Department as a policy analyst under the conservative secretary, James G. Watt, and was under instructions to find budget cuts through the department. ''We were resisted at every turn by the bureaucracy,'' Mr. Simmons said. ''They all had political constituencies. The Bureau of Mines had a constituency. The Bureau of Land Management had a constituency. The cuts were mostly not made.''</p>
        <p>Donald F. Kettl, a political scientist at the University of Pennsylvania, offered an explanation for the Bush approach: ''The facts are rarely 100 percent clear. There is almost always uncertainty and a need for interpretation. As long as that's the case, ideology is awfully handy because it provides a way to interpret the fuzzy area between what we know and what we don't know.''</p>
        <p>With the politicization overload of last week, there was one reminder that at least a few islands of impartiality lie in the sea of partisan polarization.</p>
        <p>Douglas J. Holtz-Eakin, a former economist in the Bush White House who became director of the nonpartisan Congressional Budget Office nearly three years ago, announced that he planned to leave government at the end of the year. In his tenure, Mr. Holtz-Eakin reported that the Republican tax cuts and spending plans would do little or nothing to stimulate economic growth. He found that the tax cuts were skewed heavily in favor of the wealthiest Americans. His office raised doubts about proposals to partly privatize Social Security, concluded that abolishing the estate tax would reduce charitable donations and calculated that allowing same-sex marriages would slightly increase federal revenues.</p>
        <p>In short, Mr. Holtz-Eakin adhered strictly to Budget Office's tradition of sticking to data. As committed as he was personally to conservative economics and Republican politics, he was a constant thorn in the side of the White House and the Republican leaders in Congress.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
