<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Urban Dread</title>
    <meta content="18jonas" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/18/books/review/18jonas.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1725594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Science Fiction"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mieville, China</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, M John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irvine, Alexander C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Kim Stanley</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Looking for Jake (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Viriconium (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Narrows, the (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fifty Degrees Below (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Harrison, M John</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Robinson, Kim Stanley</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0D91031F93BA25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Urban Dread</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Urban Dread</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerald Jonas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerald Jones reviews books Looking for Jake by China Mieville, Viriconium by M John Harrison, The Narrows by Alexander C Irvine and Fifty Degrees Below by Kim Stanley Robinson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''THESE writings are a strange mix of the scientifically exact and the imprecise.'' The quotation refers to a bundle of papers in one of the stories in China Miéville's LOOKING FOR JAKE (Del Rey/Ballantine, paper, $13.95), but the same description could apply to the narrative strategy he adopts throughout this fine collection. The story in question, ''Reports of Certain Events in London,'' deals with the attempts of a shadowy Brotherhood of self-appointed investigators to map what they call ''wild streets'' -- bits and pieces of lanes and alleys that suddenly manifest themselves in otherwise unremarkable neighborhoods, then vanish without leaving any physical trace. From this unlikely premise, Miéville wrests a compelling tale of obsession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In China Miéville's "Looking for Jake," A shadowy Brotherhood maps "wild streets"  bits of alleys that suddenly turn up elsewhere, then vanish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''THESE writings are a strange mix of the scientifically exact and the imprecise.'' The quotation refers to a bundle of papers in one of the stories in China Miéville's LOOKING FOR JAKE (Del Rey/Ballantine, paper, $13.95), but the same description could apply to the narrative strategy he adopts throughout this fine collection. The story in question, ''Reports of Certain Events in London,'' deals with the attempts of a shadowy Brotherhood of self-appointed investigators to map what they call ''wild streets'' -- bits and pieces of lanes and alleys that suddenly manifest themselves in otherwise unremarkable neighborhoods, then vanish without leaving any physical trace. From this unlikely premise, Miéville wrests a compelling tale of obsession.</p>
        <p>Miéville is a Poe-esque poet of urban dread. In story after story, his Londoners are besieged by mysterious forces like the ''unseen flapping things'' that ''burst into existence full-grown and ravenous'' in the title story, or the vampirelike ''imagos'' that escape from their other-dimensional imprisonment in the mirrors of our world in the concluding story. While these horrors are described in maddeningly vague terms, Miéville writes with pitiless precision about the uncomprehending survivors.</p>
        <p>The narrator of ''Looking for Jake'' searches for his lover in a city all but emptied by fear. Like most of Miéville's heroes, he fell prey to disaffection long before an external threat rendered it palpable. When he tries to imagine what will happen if he finds Jake, he can do no better than: ''We could at least be lost together.'' Without ever spelling it out, Miéville, who has been active in leftist politics in Britain, conveys the message that the disintegration of the social fabric and his characters' moral paralysis are inextricably linked.</p>
        <p>China Miéville is one of a group of British writers whose hard-edged approach to fantasy has been labeled the New Weird. In VIRICONIUM (Bantam Spectra, paper, $16), the doyen of the group, M. John Harrison, has gathered all the stories that make up his ambitious epic about a dying civilization at the end of time.</p>
        <p>Harrison's 2003 short-story collection, ''Things That Never Happen,'' was arranged chronologically by date of composition to show his maturation as a writer. Similarly, the novellas and stories in ''Viriconium'' -- written during the 1970's and early 1980's -- appear in order of publication. Readers new to Harrison's work will find the collection both disorienting and invigorating.</p>
        <p>Viriconium is the name some historians give to the largest Roman settlement in Shropshire. The hint of poison in the name suffuses Harrison's epic, which posits a time scale so vast that his Viriconium follows a human civilization powerful enough to write its name in the sky by moving stars into a new constellation. That long-gone civilization was one of what Harrison calls the Afternoon Cultures. Viriconium belongs to humanity's Evening, a last flicker of radiance before the darkness closes in forever.</p>
        <p>The first story in ''Viriconium'' was published in 1971. Harrison has said that he wrote it as a sendup of the commercial sword-and-sorcery genre, which has spawned endless imitations of J. R. R. Tolkien's ''Lord of the Rings.'' Yet today it's hard to distinguish Harrison's parody from its target. With its rival fighting queens, brotherly band of quarreling warriors, climactic battle and gimmicky plot resolution, it's notable mainly for a reliably literate tone and an underlying melancholy, a principled refusal to exult in the destruction of enemies.</p>
        <p>In the rest of the book, Harrison treats the story of Viriconium as raw material for a series of meditations on the mythological underpinnings of science fiction and fantasy. When Earth is invaded by insectoid aliens, the battle for survival involves not clashing superweapons but competing ways of perceiving reality. Step by step, Harrison methodically deconstructs the very stuff of narrative. Characters reappear in story after story, but their roles and histories vary. The focus shifts from feats of derring-do to cutthroat culture wars in which artists and pretenders, madmen and madder gods fight for the soul of Viriconium while disease and disorder gnaw at the city's vitals. In a final story that gives new meaning to the phrase ''surprise ending,'' he links the entire sequence to our own world, and to the dreams that sustain us.</p>
        <p>THE NARROWS (Del Rey/Ballantine, paper, $13.95), by Alexander C. Irvine, is a gritty urban fantasy set in Detroit during World War II. The first line establishes the tone: ''Midnight in the golem factory.'' Jared Cleaves, a 26-year-old assembly-line worker, has been classified 4F because two fingers on his right hand were crippled in a boyhood accident. He takes solace in the fact that he was chosen, for reasons he doesn't understand, to work in a secret war plant near the center of Henry Ford's River Rouge factory complex. There he and his buddies shape clay into golems, artificial men magically endowed with life by a refugee rabbi named Moises. In this alternate-history version of Detroit, magic is taken for granted as another technology contributing to the war effort; the golems are dispatched to fight as untiring soldiers against Hitler's evil regime.</p>
        <p>Jared himself is destined for an even bigger role in the conflict, but he doesn't know that yet. His more pressing concerns center on his family: improving his strained relationship with his pregnant wife, taking care of his toddler daughter and getting along with his crusty father, who works in the salt mines that extend beneath the city.</p>
        <p>''The Narrows'' (an alternate translation of détroit, French for ''strait'') offers an engaging mix of domesticated magic and domestic angst, with the fate of the world hanging in the balance.</p>
        <p>There's no magic in Kim Stanley Robinson's FIFTY DEGREES BELOW (Bantam Spectra, $25), unless you count the way he invests the details of scientific and bureaucratic decision making with high drama.</p>
        <p>The second volume of his trilogy on abrupt climatic change, ''Fifty Degrees Below'' stays close to Frank Vanderwal, who is in his second year as a consultant with the National Science Foundation in Washington. During his first year, a flood inundated the nation's capital, bringing home the problem of global warming to even the most blinkered politicians. (This is described in the trilogy's first volume, ''Forty Signs of Rain.'') Now the waters have receded, but a ''shutdown'' of the Gulf Stream threatens to lock the entire region into an Arctic-strength deep freeze.</p>
        <p>While working with his colleagues to steer the government toward ameliorative action, Frank has problems of his own. Bumped from his rented apartment after the flood, he decides to live outdoors in a tree house of his own devising in Rock Creek Park. Here he bonds with his fellow creatures, who range from a band of resourceful homeless men to a roaming squad of Frisbee players to assorted animals, small and large, that have escaped from the National Zoo. As a 43-year old primate hungry for a mate, he becomes infatuated with a government spook whose marital and occupational commitments allow the couple only the briefest encounters. When the temperature drops below freezing and keeps dropping, Frank and all those around him are put to the kind of test few humans have faced since the last ice age.</p>
        <p>For a writer who deals with world-class disasters, Robinson is incorrigibly optimistic. The most dire problems, he assures us, can be solved by the prompt application of scientific thinking and physical and moral courage. The catch comes in the word ''prompt.'' Even when the remedies are clear, it's not easy to marshal sufficient resources in time. Robinson's impressive body of work -- which includes the Mars trilogy (about the problematic terraforming of our planetary neighbor) and the California trilogy (about the dos and don'ts of constructing utopias) -- offers sound guidance for scientifically informed social action. I'd feel better about our future if more people were familiar with his ingeniously plotted and gracefully written books.</p>
        <p>Science Fiction</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
