<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just Your Standard Deviation</title>
    <meta content="20NJSOAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1658460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="SOAPBOX"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Graduate Record Examination</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubis, Anastasia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDC103CF933A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just Your Standard Deviation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANASTASIA RUBIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubis, Anastasia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anastasia Rubis Soapbox essay on taking Graduate Record Exam more than 20 years after graduating college in hope of applying to graduate school for teaching degree; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I RECENTLY took the Graduate Record Examination. Me, a not-so-happy-housewife more than 20 years out of college, had resolved to apply to graduate school for a teaching degree. As if the stress of being over 40 wasn't enough.</p>
        <p>The test was a prison-like experience at a place called Prometrics -- one of those dingy office buildings with gray carpet and gray walls designed to camouflage stains -- on a sad stretch of Route 4 in Fair Lawn and on a beastly day in February that was threatening snow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I RECENTLY took the Graduate Record Examination. Me, a not-so-happy-housewife more than 20 years out of college, had resolved to apply to graduate school for a teaching degree. As if the stress of being over 40 wasn't enough.</p>
        <p>The test was a prison-like experience at a place called Prometrics -- one of those dingy office buildings with gray carpet and gray walls designed to camouflage stains -- on a sad stretch of Route 4 in Fair Lawn and on a beastly day in February that was threatening snow.</p>
        <p>I was scared of getting lost, arriving late, not being permitted to eat my peanut butter sandwich and starving through the four-hour ordeal. Naturally, I was terrified of exponents, ratios and pi, concepts that -- let's face it -- I had hoped never to meet again. After all, when does life pose an urgent need to calculate slope? Right before the ER, when your child's tricycle is barreling down the driveway?</p>
        <p>I had allotted four weeks to rejuvenate my gray matter. One month was all I could sacrifice to the Pythagorean theorem and all those deadly reading comprehension passages about greenhouse gases. As I skipped around in The Princeton Review, scrupulously avoiding permutations and standard deviation, certain synapses began firing for the first time in a quarter-century, even if the connections were as stiff as morning joints.</p>
        <p>Shockingly, it all came back, though I gave it exactly the time it took to walk to my car after the exam to evaporate. Poof.</p>
        <p>At the 11th hour, I squeezed in a demo test online, since the GRE is now completely computer-based. That's right, no more No. 2 pencils shading in ovals. Just point and click with a mouse. Which means no more underlining those deadly boring passages on greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>You're brave, my mommy friends said. I'm nuts. I would like to go back to school. Maybe. Someday, was their common refrain. I wondered if other moms were as deadened by bedtime routines as I.</p>
        <p>NO! You didn't brush your teeth, because your toothbrush is dry! You see, Julia Roberts, Gwyneth Paltrow -- all of us who stay home with our children feel cut off from the big stuff of society. Hunkered down in our nests of domesticity, we fear the world has forgotten us, and we it. That the bridges to careers and commitments have been blown up, and there is no road back -- even if we may want one. So many of us don't risk wanting to.</p>
        <p>The weekend before the exams, I snapped at my daughter and husband for not making the beds (''I AM NOT THE MAID!'') and stormed off to Willowbrook Mall. My tension was multilayered. Would I choke? Be a joke? Blow $115 bucks? Who did I think I was, indulging myself with intellectual pursuits and abandoning the family? I would never complete a degree while knocking at death's door. Why didn't I begin earlier?</p>
        <p>But the lower I sank, an unknown force kept pushing me forward, as if to say that this situation was untenable. It's your move. Change. I still have 30 good years ahead, I rebuked the voices in my head. I was smart. Maybe I do have something to offer the world.</p>
        <p>The big day arrived. I actually found the place. A hefty proctor behind a glass wall handed me a clipboard. Copy over this statement in script, she said. I copied over a long passage swearing I was myself and that myself would never cheat. Put all your belongings in the locker. The proctor handed me a key. I locked away my purse, jacket and water bottle, taking a last swig as if it were the last supper.</p>
        <p>Solemnly, I went to the bathroom. ''Will I be able to go between sections?'' I asked nervously.</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' the proctor said with a shrug.</p>
        <p>But my bladder has never been the same since childbirth! I stemmed my panic. Big breath. Plunge. O.K. I'm ready. The proctor ushered me to a computer carrel inside the testing room. I was not permitted to take even a tissue and guiltily spit out a throat lozenge. All around, I could hear (younger) people thinking. At first, my hand shook on the mouse, but soon I was lobbing vocabulary answers like a pro. Opprobrium, pusillanimous, adumbrate. Never mind they were words I would be too embarrassed to utter in public.</p>
        <p>Math was another story. The questions fired past me like chocolates on the conveyor belt bypassing Lucy. Time ticked. I became a master of process of elimination, a strategy extolled by the prep gurus, as well as my own strategy of who cares.</p>
        <p>At last, the screen announced I was done. Do you want to cancel this test and forgo seeing your scores? (There is instant gratification in the computer age.) No way, I'm not going through this again. I braced myself. My scores popped onto the screen. I did fine, really fine, on the verbal portion, better than my College Boards. Worse, but respectably, on math.</p>
        <p>Goodbye, I waved to the proctor as I relinquished my locker key. There was a spring in my step as I walked to the car. I was still the mother of Kassandra, who is still the best part of me, but I had reclaimed something along with my gray matter. The growing, striving part of me.</p>
        <p>I did not know where it would lead. But I would go.</p>
        <p>SOAPBOX Anastasia Rubis is writing a comic novel about motherhood in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anastasia Rubis is writing a comic novel about motherhood in Manhattan.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
