<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Raphael Prefers Small Canvas</title>
    <meta content="28livine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/28/dining/28livine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1697814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND VINES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DD1E3EF93BA1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Raphael Prefers Small Canvas</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">This Raphael Prefers Small Canvas</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO visitors and customers, Raphael's impressive multimillion-dollar winery and carefully tended 54 acres of vineyards are synonymous with thorough attention to detail. So are Richard Olsen-Harbich's wines.</p>
        <p>Raphael's 2004 sauvignon blanc and 2004 rosé, his summer releases, are so sophisticated that a European collector, tasting them blindfolded, might attribute them to the Loire and Provence, respectively.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>To visitors and customers, Raphael's impressive multimillion-dollar winery and carefully tended 54 acres of vineyards are synonymous with thorough attention to detail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO visitors and customers, Raphael's impressive multimillion-dollar winery and carefully tended 54 acres of vineyards are synonymous with thorough attention to detail. So are Richard Olsen-Harbich's wines.</p>
        <p>Raphael's 2004 sauvignon blanc and 2004 rosé, his summer releases, are so sophisticated that a European collector, tasting them blindfolded, might attribute them to the Loire and Provence, respectively.</p>
        <p>Both treats from Raphael's Peconic estate are the equivalents not of oil paintings that deliver big statements but of masterly watercolors that tell subdued stories with delicacy.</p>
        <p>No surprise. Mr. Olsen-Harbich, who has made wine on Long Island for a quarter-century, is not a devotee of blockbusters. Neither is Raphael's consulting winemaker, Paul Pontallier, the managing director of Château Margaux in Bordeaux.</p>
        <p>Raphael shuns chardonnay, and Mr. Olsen-Harbich says that sauvignon blanc is ''the best white grape variety on the North Fork.''</p>
        <p>Using grapes reared by the seasoned Benjamin Sisson, Raphael's environmentally oriented vineyard manager, Raphael strives for wines that are prized by consumers whose tastes are guided not by 90-point numerical scores but by classical criteria like balance and grace.</p>
        <p>Those values define Raphael's Sancerre-like sauvignon blanc ($20), which is as light as a breeze.</p>
        <p>Using a production method that helps German producers heighten rieslings (especially J.J. Prüm in the Mosel), Mr. Olsen-Harbich fermented his sauvignon blanc grape juice at a very low temperature (45 degrees Fahrenheit) and bottled the wine soon after to retain carbon dioxide bubbles.</p>
        <p>This spritz, he said, ''keeps the wine extremely fresh and adds to its brightness and liveliness.'' Indeed it does, and, Mr. Olsen-Harbich says, makes his brisk, grapefruity sauvignon blanc the ''perfect wine to complement local seafood.'' He accurately finds gooseberry and kiwi characteristics in this white.</p>
        <p>Raphael specializes in merlot, which it uses in its vivid rosé ($16), called Saignée, a French term that means ''bled.'' During grape crushing and before fermentation began, the merlot grape juice was drawn off -- that is, bled -- from the vats, leaving a tincture of pink. The pink juice was then cold-fermented in stainless steel vessels to preserve its fruitiness.</p>
        <p>In effect, Saignée is two wines in one. When fully chilled, it is a refreshing rosé with hints of strawberry in the aroma and flavor; in Mr. Olsen-Harbich's view, cherry and guava characteristics are detectable, although I do not pick them up. Mouth-filling and tangy, Saignée is something of a dry confection.</p>
        <p>When allowed to warm up in bottle or glass, the wine becomes a light red and seems surprisingly concentrated on the palate. This means that I could first pour it as an aperitif, then put it aside for 20 minutes and return to it as an accompaniment to, say, pasta or light meat dishes. That's versatility.</p>
        <p>HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND VINES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
