<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Going for the Green</title>
    <meta content="LI$POWER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/10/opinion/nyregionopinions/LI_Power.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Power Authority</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DC163EF933A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Going for the Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Going for the Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial calls on Long Islanders to enroll in Long Island Power Authority's new Green Choice program and choose to devote half or all of monthly electric bills to buying power from marketers that sell energy from renewable sources</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Driving around Long Island in a hatchback Honda gives the feeling of being a tiny shrew in the late Cretaceous Period. To dart among Land Cruisers as they lumber between gas stations, and to gaze upward at their monstrous grilles, is to feel occasional pangs of terror, but also the comfort that in the long run, survival is the province of the wily mammal, not the gluttonous reptile.</p>
        <p>Barring some asteroidal catastrophe, though, there are no immediate signs that the fossil-fuel-based lifestyle we all enjoy -- of which the S.U.V. is the apotheosis -- will suddenly go extinct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Long Island, so hungry for power and with so far to go in the clean-energy game, small gestures are a worthy start.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Driving around Long Island in a hatchback Honda gives the feeling of being a tiny shrew in the late Cretaceous Period. To dart among Land Cruisers as they lumber between gas stations, and to gaze upward at their monstrous grilles, is to feel occasional pangs of terror, but also the comfort that in the long run, survival is the province of the wily mammal, not the gluttonous reptile.</p>
        <p>Barring some asteroidal catastrophe, though, there are no immediate signs that the fossil-fuel-based lifestyle we all enjoy -- of which the S.U.V. is the apotheosis -- will suddenly go extinct.</p>
        <p>Electricity use, in fact, is climbing rapidly on Long Island: it is up more than 20 percent since 1997, according to a recent report by the Long Island Power Authority. Our houses and cars are bigger, and we are sinking ever more dollars into running air-conditioners, computers, cellphone charges, home theaters, hot tubs and spas, even second refrigerators. Levittown, the report suggests, was a barren Sparta compared with the technological Babylon we live in now.</p>
        <p>This is a national and global issue, not just a Long Island one, although it seems that the discussion locally is confined to op-ed columnists and the usual cohort of tree-huggers talking among themselves. Most lawmakers -- certainly a majority in Congress -- seem content to dismiss conservation as one of those virtues, like faith and charity, that are highly resistant to a regulatory approach.</p>
        <p>But out-of-control energy use is, after all, the demon that lurks behind the hot debates about a liquefied natural gas operation in the middle of Long Island Sound, windmills off the South Shore and the relicensing of the Indian Point nuclear plant on the Hudson River. In the absence of political leadership, there should be something the committed citizen can do about it.</p>
        <p>There is, actually. Long Islanders can enroll in LIPA's new Green Choice program, and choose to devote half or all of a monthly electric bill to buying power from marketers that sell energy from renewable sources: wind farms, hydroelectric plants and biomass operations, which burn methane gas from landfills and agricultural waste products. Customers who are not ready or inclined to install solar panels or geothermal heat pumps can support clean, renewable energy with their cash. They will pay a premium -- about $7 to $12 a month or more, LIPA estimates -- but as more people enroll, the utility says, prices may drop as the market conditions for green power improve.</p>
        <p>It's a small gesture, and mostly symbolic. But on Long Island, so hungry for power and with so far to go in the clean-energy game, small gestures are a worthy start.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
