<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Fiddles While Oil Burns</title>
    <meta content="25heat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/25/garden/25heat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050901T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1697103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Energy Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Natural Resources Defense Council</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DD1E3EF936A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Fiddles While Oil Burns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Washington Fiddles While Oil Burns</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOWEVER painful it is to drive into a gasoline station this summer, it may be just as painful to heat your home this winter. The price of heating oil has nearly doubled since 2003, to about $2 a gallon retail, and natural gas, the heating fuel of choice in much of the country, has tripled since the late 90's. Where prices will be in February is anybody's guess.</p>
        <p>But homeowners shopping for a furnace will do so without benefit of long-awaited federal rules setting minimum standards for efficiency. That may be true in 2006 and 2007 as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>However painful it is to drive into a gasoline station this summer, it may be just as painful to heat your home this winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOWEVER painful it is to drive into a gasoline station this summer, it may be just as painful to heat your home this winter. The price of heating oil has nearly doubled since 2003, to about $2 a gallon retail, and natural gas, the heating fuel of choice in much of the country, has tripled since the late 90's. Where prices will be in February is anybody's guess.</p>
        <p>But homeowners shopping for a furnace will do so without benefit of long-awaited federal rules setting minimum standards for efficiency. That may be true in 2006 and 2007 as well.</p>
        <p>Call it one very overdue homework assignment. In 1987 Congress gave the Energy Department a deadline of 1994 to set new efficiency standards for home furnaces running on oil and gas, standards that would go beyond simple labeling. Congress is still waiting, along with the millions of Americans who buy furnaces each year.</p>
        <p>Part of the Energy Department's problem is having to grapple with different heating requirements in different areas: minimum efficiency requirements, because they increase the cost of a furnace, would make more sense in, say, Massachusetts than in Georgia, where an efficient air-conditioner would be a bigger priority.</p>
        <p>One way or another, however, the standard will be developed, said David K. Garman, the department's under secretary for energy, science and environment, explaining that his new boss, Samuel W. Bodman, ''has lit a fire under us.''</p>
        <p>Furnaces are expensive -- thousands of dollars -- but they can last 30 years. So minor increases in efficiency can pay off, especially in cold regions like the Northeast and even more so when fuel prices are high. Furnace makers are already required to post energy efficiency ratings on their products, an aid to consumers trying to comparison-shop. Setting a minimum standard would simply eliminate the least efficient models, which would help address ''on the truck'' syndrome: the tendency of consumers with suddenly deceased furnaces (or water heaters) to take the first replacement model a dealer can deliver, regardless of efficiency.</p>
        <p>Minimum standards would also help tenants who pay for their own heating and whose landlords might otherwise be tempted to buy a cheap, inefficient furnace.</p>
        <p>Setting such standards for any appliance takes time, of course (about six years, Mr. Garman said: three for the manufacturers, consumer advocates, utility companies and other interested parties to agree on a testing procedure, and three more for carrying out tests and deciding where to set the minimum).</p>
        <p>The system is cumbersome but was put in place after Congress, unhappy with a previous system for setting standards, imposed a moratorium until the department could come up with something more transparent and responsive to all parties.</p>
        <p>Now Congress is frustrated with the pace of that effort. The latest energy legislation, signed by President Bush in August, shortens the process for some equipment, either by specifying the testing methodology or by simply codifying a standard that has sometimes already been worked out informally by various parties. But furnaces were not on the list.</p>
        <p>''They've missed 28 deadlines for 23 individual products,'' said Kit Kennedy, a lawyer and an energy efficiency expert at the Natural Resources Defense Council, a nonprofit environmental advocacy organization that relies on private donations. ''This is a problem that has extended through several administrations.''</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a puzzlement,'' she said. The standards tend to be ''important but obscure issues'' that get lost in the shuffle.</p>
        <p>Comparison shoppers can meanwhile consider a furnace's ''annual fuel utilization efficiency,'' which measures the proportion of the heat in the fuel that actually goes to warm the house and the proportion that goes up the chimney. Efficiencies range from 78 to 96 percent; prices range accordingly.</p>
        <p>Standard Oil of Connecticut, which serves McMansion-rich Fairfield County, is currently selling heating oil for about $2.45 a gallon and furnaces for $3,600 to $5,000, with larger and more efficient ones clustered at the high end. The higher the efficiency -- and the higher the price of oil -- the faster the investment in a new furnace pays off.</p>
        <p>Some contractors are reluctant to install the most efficient models because they have less experience with them and fear breakdowns, said Keith Freischlag, the energy efficiency coordinator at Unitil, a utility that serves parts of Massachusetts and New Hampshire. A natural gas furnace with 80 percent efficiency is typically $500 cheaper than one that is 85 percent efficient, he said, and his company will pay the difference when consumers choose the more efficient model. (He also noted that installation of higher-efficiency models costs a little more.)</p>
        <p>Furnace efficiency is not always high on the customer's list, Mr. Freischlag noted, adding, ''Feds coming in with a minimum efficiency factor, that's a great idea.''</p>
        <p>Furnaces that heat air and blow it through the house also consume electricity. The ones with the best blower motors save about $50 on electricity bills a year. The government does not regulate the efficiency of the blowers in forced-air units, however.</p>
        <p>Homeowners who replace a furnace should aim to buy the smallest one that will do the job, experts say (because bigger furnaces cycle on and off more often, and they waste a bit of fuel each time they cycle off). Homeowners who have replaced their windows recently may want to consider a smaller furnace when the time comes for a replacement.</p>
        <p>In an economist's perfect world, buyers would calculate the value of an investment in efficiency and compel manufacturers to drive average efficiency higher. But that doesn't happen if many buyers are builders or landlords uninterested in operating costs, or homeowners in a hurry because the old furnace has quit.</p>
        <p>''The market's working, but it's not working for everybody,'' said Andrew deLaski, executive director of the Appliance Standards Awareness Project, a nonprofit consumer advocacy group in Boston financed by private foundations. That is one reason his group supports a minimum efficiency standard.</p>
        <p>In another ideal world, the law might allow the Energy Department to set different standards for different states. It does not, but Mr. Garman said, ''We're looking for a creative way of splitting that baby.''</p>
        <p>''We want to figure out a way to capture the maximum benefit but not put anybody under a ridiculous economic burden,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He would not elaborate, but energy efficiency experts said that the department might be able to set two standards and let the states choose between them, or perhaps set a standard and specify that it did not pre-empt the states from establishing a stricter one.</p>
        <p>Another issue is how to measure the benefits of increased efficiency. Usually the department multiplies the amount of money saved on fuel by the years of life of the appliance and applies an interest rate to reflect the lower value of savings in the distant future.</p>
        <p>But efficiency advocates say the potential value of reduced consumption is far higher. Quite apart from slowing the increase in global warming gases, they say that because natural gas prices are generally determined by supply and demand in North America, cutting demand for it in American homes could cut price.</p>
        <p>If millions of houses cut their consumption by a few percent, the Natural Resources Defense Council argues (along with one major user, DuPont), then total demand would fall, and the price would too, saving the economy billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department is still considering that argument.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 1, 2005, Thursday  An article last week about proposed efficiency standards for home furnaces misidentified the chemical company that joined an environmental group in urging the federal Energy Department to adopt stronger rules. It was Dow, not DuPont.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 1, 2005, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last week about proposed efficiency standards for home furnaces misidentified the chemical company that joined an environmental group in urging the federal Energy Department to adopt stronger rules. It was Dow, not DuPont.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
