<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Rough Political Road, Blair Comes Back as a Winner</title>
    <meta content="07BLAI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/07/international/europe/07blair.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2012)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D7163DF934A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Rough Political Road, Blair Comes Back as a Winner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Rough Political Road, Blair Comes Back as a Winner</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>GLENEAGLES, Scotland, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Tony Blair, who has undergone two bad months politically, is called 'king of the world' after London is chosen to be host of 2012 Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>People had started to forget that Tony Blair was once nicknamed Teflon Tony because nothing bad stuck to him. On Wednesday, they remembered why, when London was chosen over Paris, New York and other cities to be the host of the 2012 Olympics and Mr. Blair seemed to be, in the words of one French journalist here, ''king of the world.''</p>
        <p>Only two months ago, after his Labor Party's majority was slashed in elections, he seemed wounded by a legacy of mistrust from the war in Iraq. Even his supporters were asking how soon he would step aside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Host to the summit meeting for the Group of 8 and victor in the campaign to lure the Olympic Games away from Paris, Tony Blair stood proud on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>People had started to forget that Tony Blair was once nicknamed Teflon Tony because nothing bad stuck to him. On Wednesday, they remembered why, when London was chosen over Paris, New York and other cities to be the host of the 2012 Olympics and Mr. Blair seemed to be, in the words of one French journalist here, ''king of the world.''</p>
        <p>Only two months ago, after his Labor Party's majority was slashed in elections, he seemed wounded by a legacy of mistrust from the war in Iraq. Even his supporters were asking how soon he would step aside.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, though, just a day after he flew back from Singapore, where he had promoted London's effort to be named host for the Olympics, Mr. Blair stood proud.</p>
        <p>Host to the world's most powerful politicians at the summit meeting for the Group of 8 major industrial nations, which opened here on Wednesday night, he had become the victor in the campaign to lure the world's most prestigious sporting event away from Paris, stealing an enormous march on his rival, President Jacques Chirac, after weeks of French-British vituperation.</p>
        <p>So would he exult, or observe the diplomatic niceties of modest triumph? Probably, his aides suggested, the latter -- in public at least.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair, said a British official in return for customary anonymity, will be ''gracious in victory.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Chirac, when he arrived in Scotland from Singapore to a red-carpet welcome on Wednesday night, he managed a tight, tired smile as he, too, danced the diplomatic duet. As if to offer him some consolation, he was seated before a state banquet in a posed photograph between Queen Elizabeth II and her husband, Prince Philip.</p>
        <p>The Blair-Chirac entente was not always so cordial and may not remain so for long.</p>
        <p>After French voters rejected a new European constitution in a referendum on May 29, Mr. Chirac chose Mr. Blair as a scapegoat, shifting attention from his own humiliation to complaints about Britain's financial rebate from the European Union.</p>
        <p>Then, at a European summit meeting, normal diplomatic politesse gave way to palpable tension and recrimination between them. Even in recent days, Mr. Chirac stirred up British ire even more with remarks, reprinted in the French newspaper Libération, that British food was the second-worst in Europe, after Finland's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac's remarks haunted him as he, too, headed to Singapore to support the French effort on the Olympics, only to be greeted by an unruly gaggle of British reporters asking questions like, ''Do you like the rosbif?'' -- the French word for roast beef, and argot for British people. (Apparently in deference to Mr. Chirac -- and President Bush -- haggis, the spicy Scottish specialty made of sheep stomach and organs, was kept off Wednesday's menu here at the state banquet.)</p>
        <p>For Mr. Blair, the reversal has been long in coming.</p>
        <p>''He is shaking off the Iraq war,'' said Charles Grant, leader of the Center for European Reform, a private policy institute in London. ''He will never completely leave it behind, but he is succeeding -- and the Olympics helps him -- in being associated with something other than Iraq.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, with Britain holding the rotating presidency of the European Union since July 1, and with the prime minister as chairman of the Group of 8 this year, he said, ''Blair has the opportunity to do what he does best, and paint the big picture.''</p>
        <p>It may not be easy going. Mr. Blair and Mr. Chirac have emerged as champions of rival visions of Europe, one rooted in the social safety nets and state supports of France, and the other in an economic vision, closer to the American model, pursued in Britain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac's critics now contend that his setbacks have weakened him at a time when Mr. Blair seems only to be dealt winning hands.</p>
        <p>In a speech to the European Parliament last month, the prime minister emerged as the custodian -- albeit self-appointed -- of an alternative vision the continent's future.</p>
        <p>At home, his recovery has built in part on the deftly maneuvered imagery of his standing up to the French and the Germans -- the kind of pugnaciousness that goes down well with the tabloids, drawing political gain out of international debacle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair has also benefited from his campaign to increase aid, cut debt and improve trade with Africa -- themes that tapped a vein of idealistic and youthful sentiment manifest over the weekend when more than 400,000 people either attended a free Live 8 rock concert in London or paraded through the streets of Edinburgh under the banner of a campaign to ''make poverty history.''</p>
        <p>In a land besotted with sport from soccer to cricket and rugby, Mr. Blair's decision to spend two days in Singapore looks like a smart gamble that paid off. ''The name you keep hearing here is the prime minister's,'' said Adam Parsons, a BBC correspondent in Singapore, listing the reasons for London's victory. ''They were bowled over by the fact that he had taken two days out just before the G8, and that may well have been the key factor.''</p>
        <p>Of course, it may be more of a challenge to secure the same kind of unambiguous victory from the meeting.</p>
        <p>''I have been trying to work on the G8 stuff, but I have to say my mind has been in two places at once today,'' Mr. Blair said at a hastily convened news conference here. ''It is fantastic.''</p>
        <p>The prime minister, who is looking for Mr. Chirac's support at Gleneagles -- primarily against Mr. Bush -- said he did not believe that the French president would allow the Olympic result to change that backing. Mr. Chirac is ''someone who is deeply committed to Africa and supports what we have been saying on climate change, so I honestly do not think that is going to be the issue here,'' Mr. Blair said.</p>
        <p>''Whatever difficulties we may have in other areas, in these areas they have been tremendously helpful, France, even in the last few days, in trying to get agreement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And Jerome Bonnafont, Mr. Chirac's spokesman, told reporters that the president had come to Gleneagles in a ''spirit of full support.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
