<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking the Ice Up North</title>
    <meta content="19borgerson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/19/opinion/19borgerson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1710755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borgerson, Scott</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5D6153FF93AA25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking the Ice Up North</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Breaking the Ice Up North</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Scott Borgerson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borgerson, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>NEW LONDON, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott Borgerson Op-Ed article says thawing of Arctic ice cap, which has shrunk perhaps by nearly half in last 50 years, will produce major geopolitical shifts that will profoundly affect international relations and require adjustments in US policies on territorial borders, energy exploration and navigation; calls for US to articulate clear, sustainable, environmentally aware policy; points to 1961 Antarctic Treaty, which ended territorial claims and established demilitarized region (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLITICIANS and scientists may debate why the earth is warming, but the fact remains: the Arctic ice cap, estimates say, has shrunk by nearly half in the last 50 years.</p>
        <p>This is big news, and not just because the Arctic is a barometer for global climate change. The thawing of the Arctic will produce major geographical shifts, many of which will profoundly affect international relations. And the United States needs a foreign policy that takes account of this mutating Arctic map.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States needs a foreign policy that takes account of the shrinking Artic ice cap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLITICIANS and scientists may debate why the earth is warming, but the fact remains: the Arctic ice cap, estimates say, has shrunk by nearly half in the last 50 years.</p>
        <p>This is big news, and not just because the Arctic is a barometer for global climate change. The thawing of the Arctic will produce major geographical shifts, many of which will profoundly affect international relations. And the United States needs a foreign policy that takes account of this mutating Arctic map.</p>
        <p>For starters, conflicting territorial claims among the countries that border the Arctic Ocean will rapidly acquire a new urgency. A quarter of the world's oil and natural gas resources lie in the Arctic, but until recently polar ice rendered many of these deposits inaccessible.</p>
        <p>Now, with each passing year the warmest on record in the polar regions, the ice is melting, and more and more of these deposits are being tapped to feed the world's ravenous appetite for energy. With the price of oil soaring, wildcatters race to hoist derricks in waters where the ice has retreated. Miners, loggers and fishermen are also chasing newly exploitable natural resources.</p>
        <p>Yet perhaps the most significant consequence of the melt is the rising potential for Arctic navigation. The polar thaw may lead to what would be the most transformational maritime project since the Panama Canal: an Arctic Bridge.</p>
        <p>The holy grail of a shortcut from the North Atlantic to the North Pacific has lured explorers to extreme latitudes for centuries. Those explorers' dream could become a reality in our lifetime. An Arctic marine highway made possible by the dwindling of sea ice would cut existing oceanic transit times by days, saving shipping companies (and navies, smugglers and terrorists) thousands of miles in travel.</p>
        <p>Several studies show that a trip over the North Pole is on average 5,000 nautical miles, or up to a week of sailing time, shorter than traditional routes through the Panama and Suez canals or, for ballooning megaships unable to fit through the canals, around the Cape of Good Hope and Cape Horn.</p>
        <p>Airliners have routinely flown over the Arctic for years to cut flying time, but ocean liners have only recently become able to navigate circumpolar avenues like the Northern Sea Route in Russia and the Northwest Passage in Canada.</p>
        <p>A continued reduction in Arctic sea ice, supported by a growing network of ports, roads and railways, could radically transform trade patterns. Those able to adjust their mental maps and capitalize on this new seaway would surely benefit.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, even going by the most optimistic projection, a fully navigable Arctic is unlikely to emerge for a decade or more, and depending on whose climate change model you accept, it could take much longer. But unless warming trends come to an abrupt halt, the Arctic region will surely witness increased activity in the foreseeable future and could, in time, become a hub of global activity.</p>
        <p>The United States needs to articulate a clear, sustainable and environmentally aware Arctic policy that accounts for the changes now under way in the polar regions. Because the Arctic lacks a comprehensive legal framework akin to the 1961 Antarctic Treaty, which ended territorial claims and established Antarctica as a demilitarized region of international scientific cooperation, the United States should play a leading diplomatic role in adjudicating the growing international contest over the Arctic. It should also negotiate an Arctic security arrangement with Canada.</p>
        <p>Finally, the United States needs to bolster its ability to operate in the Arctic Ocean. Three Coast Guard ships, two of which are 30 years old and ''operationally challenged'' after years of hard work in harsh polar environments, are the sum total of our polar icebreaking capacity.</p>
        <p>The third ship is relatively new, but it isn't optimally configured for the traditional Coast Guard missions that will become increasingly important in a navigable Arctic. These include search and rescue, law enforcement, the regulation of mariners, the maintenance of navigation aids and -- a horrifying notion, with single-hulled tankers that aren't ice-strengthened already steaming near icebergs -- the cleaning up of the nearly inevitable oil spills in icy waters.</p>
        <p>The United States can certainly improve its ability to operate in the Arctic. Russia, for example, has 16 icebreakers, some of them nuclear-powered. With the comparably sized New York Police Department covering a lot less territory than our thinly stretched Coast Guard, even a small increase in manpower and money would greatly enhance American presence in the polar regions.</p>
        <p>Repairing the two tired icebreakers would cost only $500 million. Underscoring the need for action, the United States Commission on Ocean Policy last year described the refurbishment or replacement of Coast Guard icebreakers as a high priority.</p>
        <p>American foreign policy in the Arctic has been largely adrift since the cold war. But the region is growing more and more important, and we need to pay attention lest this sea change pass us by.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Scott Borgerson teaches maritime studies, political geography and American foreign policy at the United States Coast Guard Academy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Scott Borgerson teaches maritime studies, political geography and American foreign policy at the United States Coast Guard Academy.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
