<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debt Relief Deal for Poorest Nations May Need More Support</title>
    <meta content="11GROU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/11/international/europe/11group.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1679272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Group of Eight</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3D71138F932A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debt Relief Deal for Poorest Nations May Need More Support</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Debt Relief Deal for Poorest Nations May Need More Support</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As finance ministers from the world's richest countries gathered here on Friday, Gordon Brown, Britain's chancellor of the exchequer, said he believed they could make progress toward ''the biggest debt settlement the world has ever seen,'' a plan to erase billions of dollars owed by the world's poorest countries to international lenders.</p>
        <p>But other participants at the gathering adopted a more muted view, hinting that some nations may still need to be won over before endorsing the landmark formula for debt relief that the United States and Britain agreed on this week. In Washington, the White House officially announced the agreement on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some officials are hinting that some nations may still need to be won over before endorsing the formula for debt relief for the world's poorest countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As finance ministers from the world's richest countries gathered here on Friday, Gordon Brown, Britain's chancellor of the exchequer, said he believed they could make progress toward ''the biggest debt settlement the world has ever seen,'' a plan to erase billions of dollars owed by the world's poorest countries to international lenders.</p>
        <p>But other participants at the gathering adopted a more muted view, hinting that some nations may still need to be won over before endorsing the landmark formula for debt relief that the United States and Britain agreed on this week. In Washington, the White House officially announced the agreement on Friday.</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary John Snow of the United States and Mr. Brown are among the finance chiefs from the Group of 8 industrialized nations meeting for two days in London in advance of next month's Group of 8 summit meeting in Scotland.</p>
        <p>''Much is still to be done, but I think there is a will to do this,'' Mr. Brown said Friday in a radio interview, referring to the plan to free 18 nations, most of them in Africa, from obligations to repay an estimated $16.7 billion in debt to foreign lenders.</p>
        <p>As this year's head of the Group of 8, Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain has put the effort to relieve Africa's poverty and ease its debt burden at the head of an agenda that includes curbing global warming.</p>
        <p>A breakthrough on the debt issue would enhance his position as he prepares for what is likely to be a contentious summit meeting at a time of deepening strains between Britain and its European Union partners.</p>
        <p>But it was not clear whether all Group of 8 members accepted the debt relief plan. Besides the United States and Britain, the members are France, Germany, Italy, Canada, Japan and Russia.</p>
        <p>Arriving in London, for instance, Caio Koch-Weser, Germany's deputy finance minister, said: ''I can only say we are working on it.''</p>
        <p>Romilly Greenhill, a policy specialist with ActionAid International, an advocacy group based in South Africa, said the agreement had not yet won universal approval.</p>
        <p>''France, Germany and to a lesser extent Japan are holding back,'' Ms. Greenhill said, because of concerns over the cost of compensating the lenders for the assets they would have to write off. Initially, she said, those countries had favored extending more limited debt relief to only the five poorest countries.</p>
        <p>''It's by no means 100 percent certain'' that the talks here will produce an agreement, she said. Additionally, the Group of 8 may wish to wait until meeting to announce an agreement with greater fanfare, she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair announced through a spokesman on Friday that he would follow up his talks with President Bush by visiting Russia, Germany, Luxembourg and France next week. Luxembourg holds the rotating presidency of the European Union. Apart from the summit meeting preparations, Mr. Blair is embroiled in a dispute with President Jacques Chirac of France over the financing of the European Union's budget.</p>
        <p>In particular, Mr. Chirac wants Britain to relinquish an annual rebate of an amount equivalent to $6.4 billion negotiated by Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher in 1984. Britain argues that it still qualifies for the rebate because its net contributions to the European budget are far greater than those of France, whose farmers are major recipients of agricultural subsidies.</p>
        <p>The rebate is ''simply not up for negotiation,'' Mr. Brown, the chancellor of the exchequer, said Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
