<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Concerns Shift To Surge in Fuel Costs</title>
    <meta content="07liener" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1692969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DC1F3FF934A3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Concerns Shift To Surge in Fuel Costs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a hot summer, energy providers on Long Island and others who are conversant with the national and international energy picture are in a cold sweat about powering the regional economy at prices that people and businesses can afford.</p>
        <p>The region's most pressing energy problem, they agreed, was no longer meeting electric demand on the hottest summer days, a feat the Long Island Power Authority and its system manager, the KeySpan Energy Corporation, accomplished with hundreds of megawatts to spare during the steamiest days of July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a hot summer, energy providers on Long Island and others who are conversant with the national and international energy picture are in a cold sweat about powering the regional economy at prices that people and businesses can afford.</p>
        <p>The region's most pressing energy problem, they agreed, was no longer meeting electric demand on the hottest summer days, a feat the Long Island Power Authority and its system manager, the KeySpan Energy Corporation, accomplished with hundreds of megawatts to spare during the steamiest days of July.</p>
        <p>Instead, concerns have shifted decisively to the rising price of oil and gas in the global market and how to buffer Long Island from the worst of its ravages, judging by comments at an energy meeting the authority held at Suffolk County Community College in Brentwood on July 28.</p>
        <p>Participants said that a particular worry was the potentially devastating effect that sudden price spikes, supply disruptions and widely predicted future price increases would have on the Long Island economy, which depends heavily on fossil fuels and is already strained by $60-a-barrel oil and soaring gasoline prices. For electricity alone, fuel surcharges now add 27 percent to customers' bills on average.</p>
        <p>''Ladies and gentlemen, we are one terrorist attack in an oil field away from $80-to $100-a-barrel oil that would cripple the national economy and the Long Island economy,'' LIPA's chairman, Richard Kessel, said at the meeting. ''We are the most vulnerable, because we are so heavily dependent on oil in every sector of our lives.''</p>
        <p>The meeting was billed as Long Island's first energy summit and produced a consensus for regional energy planning involving producers, government leaders, businesses and environmental groups.</p>
        <p>It also demonstrated urgent new support for more aggressive energy conservation, reduced dependence on fossil fuels and continued emphasis on renewable power sources, including LIPA's proposal for a wind farm four miles off Babylon.</p>
        <p>''To those people who don't want to see windmills in the Atlantic Ocean, we have to say, what's the alternative?'' Mr. Kessel said. The choice, he said, comes down to ''windmills or stacks.''</p>
        <p>Gordian Raacke, the executive director of Renewable Energy Long Island in Bridgehampton, said the energy meeting, at which he was a panelist, ''puts energy efficiency and renewable energy on the agenda of all the major players on Long Island.''</p>
        <p>''This is just a first step, but it is remarkable,'' Mr. Raacke said.</p>
        <p>Robert Catell, KeySpan's chairman, said that renewable energy, conservation and greater efficiency, while crucial, would not be enough to address the Island's needs. With coal and nuclear power both ruled out for Long Island, he said, natural gas would be the preferred fuel in years to come, and new sources of supply are required.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catell said KeySpan and its partner, Duke Energy, were ''one local Connecticut permit away'' from beginning construction on the Islander East natural gas pipeline, which would transport up to 260 million cubic feet of gas daily from eastern Canada under the Long Island Sound to Shoreham.</p>
        <p>Another project, the Millennium pipeline, in which KeySpan holds an interest, would bring gas to Long Island from Midwest storage fields and possibly from Alaska, Mr. Catell said.</p>
        <p>Broadwater Energy, which has proposed a floating terminal in the eastern Sound to import and process liquefied natural gas, did not take part in the meeting. LIPA said that it had issued an open invitation to the event but had not directly invited Broadwater.</p>
        <p>Timothy F. Sutherland, the chief executive of Pace Global Energy Services in Fairfax, Va., and a consultant to LIPA, said electricity providers would be wise to seek long-term purchase agreements with natural gas suppliers.</p>
        <p>Kevin Rooney, the executive director of the Oil Heat Institute of Long Island, a trade group in Hauppauge for fuel-oil dealers, said there was currently no margin of error in the region's oil supply system. A Long Island energy plan would have to include ''maintaining, enhancing and expanding the petroleum supply infrastructure'' to avoid supply disruptions, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catell used the energy meeting to push for KeySpan's long-stalled proposal for a 250-megawatt power plant on Spagnoli Road in Melville. The plant would use combined-cycle technology, which generates power using 30 percent less fuel than conventional plants. Gas is burned to drive a primary turbine akin to a jet aircraft engine, and then waste heat is used to make steam to drive a secondary turbine; both turbines produce electricity. A conventional plant simply uses coal, oil, gas or nuclear fuel to heat water into steam to turn turbines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Catell said KeySpan had an approved site and all the necessary permits and was ready to begin construction immediately if LIPA would agree to buy the electricity the plant would produce.</p>
        <p>But the authority has chosen instead to back a plan by Caithness Energy to build a 350-megawatt combined-cycle plant in North Bellport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said the Caithness plant and the proposed Neptune underwater cable from New Jersey, which would deliver up to 660 megawatts of power to the South Shore, would be sufficient for Long Island until at least 2013.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
