<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Cold Is It? Not Very, If You Are a Statistician</title>
    <meta content="29COLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/29/nyregion/29cold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramirez, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miner, Todd</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DA143BF93AA15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Cold Is It? Not Very, If You Are a Statistician</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How Cold Is It? Not Very, if You Are a Statistician</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ; Patrick McGeehan contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ramirez, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Meteorologist Todd Miner says Jan 2005, as measured by temperatures in Central Park, has ranked as only 66th coldest on record; says at average of 31.6 degrees, Jan 2005 does not approach record of 21.7 degrees set in 1918; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The low yesterday morning was 5 degrees in Central Park, a single degree for every mitten-covered digit on one hand.</p>
        <p>The January nadir came at the end of a workweek of jumping across slush, slipping on ice and enduring transit distress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As of Friday, this January, as measured by temperatures in Central Park, has so far ranked as only the 66th coldest on record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The low yesterday morning was 5 degrees in Central Park, a single degree for every mitten-covered digit on one hand.</p>
        <p>The January nadir came at the end of a workweek of jumping across slush, slipping on ice and enduring transit distress.</p>
        <p>The week began with a fire that hobbled one New York subway line and closed another. It ended with downed power lines that slowed New Jersey commuter trains. Forecasters say today begins a week of thawing temperatures with a chance of reaching 40 degrees. In February.</p>
        <p>For New Jersey Transit passengers yesterday, the morning began with a break in the wires that run above the rails east of Secaucus, shutting down one of the two tracks into Manhattan. Twenty-three trains were rerouted to Hoboken and five others were canceled. Nineteen other trains that reached Pennsylvania Station ran up to 35 minutes late.</p>
        <p>Peter Dancy, a banker who lives in Glen Ridge, N.J., said that on Monday, rerouted trains caused his usual 65-minute commute, including the train ride to Penn Station and a subway ride to Lexington Avenue and 53rd Street, to stretch to two hours.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the rerouted trains slowed his commute again.</p>
        <p>And it was cold. How cold was it? Actually, not as cold as many thought -- relatively speaking.</p>
        <p>As of yesterday, this January, as measured by temperatures in Central Park, has so far ranked as only the 66th coldest on record, according to Todd Miner, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>At an average of 31.6 degrees, this January doesn't even begin to approach the record of 21.7 degrees, set in 1918. The lowest temperature that January, when Woodrow Wilson delivered his Fourteen Points speech, was minus 4 degrees.</p>
        <p>This month tied as the 16th snowiest so far, at 15.1 inches. But the lowest temperature recorded this January, 5 degrees yesterday, was far from the lowest temperature of minus 2 degrees recorded in the last 30 years (set in the Januarys of 1977, 1985 and 1994). The lowest temperature ever in Central Park was minus 15 degrees, on Feb. 9, 1934.</p>
        <p>So were any records set? Yes, and it is one explanation for why there has been so much kvetching about the weather recently. The first half of the month was unusually warm (11 degrees above normal) and the second half unusually cold (12 degrees below normal).</p>
        <p>Stephen Fybish, 68, an amateur weather enthusiast in Manhattan, said that if New Yorkers felt whipsawed, it was because the temperature swung a dizzying 61 degrees, the third biggest difference from the highest to lowest temperatures recorded in a month since 1869.</p>
        <p>Stanley Gedzelman, executive editor of Weatherwise, a magazine for weather enthusiasts, cited other reasons New Yorkers complain about the weather: short memories and television weathermen.</p>
        <p>''Isn't it stormier now with global warming than ever before, I'm always asked,'' said Mr. Gedzelman, 60, an earth and atmospheric sciences professor at City College of New York. ''And the answer is pretty much, no. When you listen to TV forecasts, it's not cold enough so they have to throw in the wind-chill factor. It adds drama.''</p>
        <p>Also, transit and other problems tend to multiply in the cold, he said.</p>
        <p>''Winter shuts the system down,'' Mr. Gedzelman said. ''If you're entranced at all by power, which the whole human race is entranced by, then you get swept away by the weather. Snowstorms shut down the rat race in New York City.''</p>
        <p>And for sheer dilapidated absurdity, today's winters don't rank with the fierce winters of the 1960's, Mr. Gedzelman said. One frigid night as an undergraduate at City College, the professor recalled, the doors to his subway car failed to close.</p>
        <p>''And there they were,'' he said. ''Snowdrifts in the A train.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
