<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Divers Say Net Tied Submarine to Listening Device</title>
    <meta content="09submarine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/09/international/europe/09submarine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drew, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D8173EF93AA3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Divers Say Net Tied Submarine to Listening Device</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Divers Say Net Tied Submarine to Listening Device</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER DREW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drew, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American divers who helped save crew members of trapped Russian submarine say craft became trapped beneath Pacific when old fishing net disabled its propeller and tied vessel to undersea Russian surveillance device larger than drive-in movie screen; describe tense, five-hour operation by Russians, British and Americans to free craft; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The small Russian submarine rescued Sunday had become trapped beneath the Pacific when an old fishing net disabled its propeller and tied the vessel to an undersea Russian surveillance device larger than a drive-in movie screen, according to American divers who helped save the boat's seven crew members.</p>
        <p>The divers, who spoke by telephone shortly after returning to San Diego yesterday, said the submarine had been knotted so tightly against the listening device that a British submersible could not maneuver close enough to clip all the netting during the tense, five-hour operation to free the craft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Russian sub had been knotted so tightly against the device that a British submersible could not maneuver close enough to clip all the netting, divers said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The small Russian submarine rescued Sunday had become trapped beneath the Pacific when an old fishing net disabled its propeller and tied the vessel to an undersea Russian surveillance device larger than a drive-in movie screen, according to American divers who helped save the boat's seven crew members.</p>
        <p>The divers, who spoke by telephone shortly after returning to San Diego yesterday, said the submarine had been knotted so tightly against the listening device that a British submersible could not maneuver close enough to clip all the netting during the tense, five-hour operation to free the craft.</p>
        <p>Instead, after the British vessel's robotic arm had snipped most of the snarled netting, Russian commanders on a nearby ship ordered the submarine's crew to blow pressurized air through its ballast tanks. That lightened the submarine, the divers said, and propelled it upward with enough force to break the last thick strands of nylon pinning it down.</p>
        <p>Four United States Navy divers were on a ship to help with the rescue. In telephone interviews, two of them said the red-and-white-striped Russian vessel floated to the surface, taking two to three minutes to rise from its trap 625 feet under the surface off the Kamchatka Peninsula.</p>
        <p>Though the submarine's ascent was uncontrolled, it popped safely to the surface between two rescue ships ''out of pure luck,'' said one of the divers, Lt. Cmdr. Gerard Demers.</p>
        <p>The account by the divers helped to sort out a mix of contradictory reports by Russian officials during the three-day race to reach the submarine before the sailors, huddled together in the cold and dark, would run out of air.</p>
        <p>After the 44-foot-long vessel became trapped Thursday, Russian fleet commanders first said it was entwined in a fishing net. But by Friday, some officials had shifted to saying that it was snagged on cables connected to an undersea antenna, a listening device meant to detect foreign submarines lurking off a major Russian naval base nearby.</p>
        <p>The device is thought to be a large hydrophone, which scans the depths for the sounds of submarines, and it seems to be a vestige of cold war cat-and-mouse games that took place beneath the sea. Some Russian officials said the vessel had been inspecting the device when it got snagged.</p>
        <p>Tom Perkins, a United States Navy master diver, said video images beamed up by the British craft had been hard to make out, ''kind of a dark puzzle,'' making it even more difficult for the British operators controlling the robotic cutting arm. They directed the cutting arm with a joystick from a control van that had been welded atop the Russian rescue ship. ''It was a real mess,'' he said in the telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The divers are part of the Navy's Deep Submergence Unit, based in San Diego. They flew to the Kamchatka Peninsula on Friday along with tons of rescue gear, including two American submersibles similar to the British one. The British vessel arrived first, and the American divers accompanied it to the rescue scene. Western officials have said the Russian sailors were rescued about three to six hours before they would have run out of air.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in interviews yesterday on Kamchatka, several of the rescued sailors confirmed what submarine experts had suggested throughout their ordeal: that they were lying in darkness, bunched close together in thermal suits in temperatures as low as 40 degrees.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that the men were under orders to breathe as lightly as possible -- to keep the carbon dioxide from rising to harmful levels -- and that water supplies were very low, limiting each man to three or four gulps a day.</p>
        <p>''We understood we were trapped,'' one crew member, Gennadi Volonin, told the news service.</p>
        <p>''It was cold, cold,'' said another crew member, who was not identified.</p>
        <p>The A.P. said some of the men began writing farewell letters to loved ones. But the submarine's commander, Lt. Vyacheslav Milashevsky, 25, said he and his crew never lost faith.</p>
        <p>''We believed the whole time that we would be saved,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
