<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abundant Energy or Floating Bombs?</title>
    <meta content="04njCOVER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/04/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/04njCOVER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1722275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Corzine, Jon S.</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grant, Bob</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D81531F937A35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="2665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abundant Energy or Floating Bombs?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Abundant Energy or Floating Bombs?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN WARNER</byline>
      <dateline>LOGAN TOWNSHIP</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FRIGID wind rips up the Delaware River and across the mucky shoreline, rustling the marsh grass. The chill makes the battle over British Petroleum's plan to build a $600 million terminal to receive liquefied natural gas from Trinidad all the more biting.</p>
        <p>As New Jersey residents hunker down for a long winter and brace for soaring energy prices, BP is quick to remind whoever chooses to listen that its proposed facility, which the company hopes to have up and running by 2008 here in Gloucester County, will help temper those bills in the years ahead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey battles residents, and Delaware, over a natural gas terminal on the Delaware River.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FRIGID wind rips up the Delaware River and across the mucky shoreline, rustling the marsh grass. The chill makes the battle over British Petroleum's plan to build a $600 million terminal to receive liquefied natural gas from Trinidad all the more biting.</p>
        <p>As New Jersey residents hunker down for a long winter and brace for soaring energy prices, BP is quick to remind whoever chooses to listen that its proposed facility, which the company hopes to have up and running by 2008 here in Gloucester County, will help temper those bills in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>So convincing is the energy giant that the notion of a facility to store and process liquefied natural gas, or L.N.G., has won the support of top state officials, including Jon S. Corzine, the governor elect. The state is even backing BP in a United States Supreme Court case challenging Delaware's efforts to block the project. On Monday, the Court decided to hear the dispute.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the proposed terminal call L.N.G. tankers ''floating bombs'' and contend that an accident or terror attack could set off a conflagration along this heavily industrialized stretch of the Delaware River separating New Jersey from Pennsylvania and Delaware, which is lined with oil refineries, hazardous chemical plants and the Salem and Hope Creek nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>''If, God forbid, anything happened, there would be a domino effect up and down the river,'' said Bob Grant, a retired truck driver from Logan Township who used to haul hazardous materials in and out of plants along the river.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grant's concerns are shared by Sharon Finlayson, chairwoman the New Jersey Environmental Federation, who says the benefits of liquefied natural gas are not worth the risk. ''We've had spills on the river and other accidents that were supposed to be one-in-a-million,'' Ms. Finlayson said. ''Then all of a sudden it happens. The dangers are real and have to be taken seriously.''</p>
        <p>After two years of debate over the wisdom of placing the facility along this stretch of river at a site known as Crown Landing, the Coast Guard on Thursday issued a preliminary finding in support of BP's proposal. After that, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission will decide whether to approve the terminal.</p>
        <p>Already, New Jersey and BP, which has a lease with an option to buy the site from Sunoco Inc., have arrived at a comfortable working relationship. State officials have offered to build and take ownership of a pier that would stretch 1,900 feet into the river. The terminal itself would consist of three storage tanks measuring 250 feet in diameter and 175 feet high. Only about 40 acres of the sprawling site, where soybeans currently grow, would be developed, leaving more than 130 acres as a buffer. In return, the state is asking BP to pay $50 million to $100 million to quasi-public agencies to manage the pier as well as to finance state economic-development projects in the area.</p>
        <p>In addition, BP has donated 130 acres of waterfront land six miles upriver, in Paulsboro, to develop a deepwater port that will be managed by the South Jersey Port Corporation.</p>
        <p>But Delaware has strenuously opposed construction of the pier, contending that under a pre-Colonial pact, it controls the riverbed up to the New Jersey shoreline. For its part, New Jersey argues it is protecting its right to control the shoreline. If the Supreme Court agrees that Delaware has the right to control the riverbed, the project could effectively be blocked.</p>
        <p>As winter descends and energy bills rise, the stakes seem clear to struggling homeowners. For the first seven months of 2005, the price of natural gas used in residences averaged $12.34 per thousand cubic feet, compared with $11.59 for all of 2004 and $8.51 for $2003, according to the Energy Information Administration of the federal Department of Energy.</p>
        <p>''Over the last couple of years, the cost of natural gas in New Jersey has skyrocketed,'' said Paul Fader, counsel to Acting Gov. Richard J. Codey. ''If this plant can come to New Jersey and be environmentally sound and secure, it's something that can benefit New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Still, residents in Logan and surrounding communities contend that New Jersey has sold them out in order to tap BP for pet development projects. ''I think there is a huge question surrounding why the State of New Jersey jumped right in to rescue BP to ensure this facility is built,'' Ms. Finlayson said. ''It leaves me very uncomfortable.''</p>
        <p>Tony Spadaccini, a Logan resident who is organizing opposition to the terminal, said: ''It's all about money: $50 million-plus. BP has a lot of money to throw around. That's nothing for them.''</p>
        <p>'Not Based on Any Facts'</p>
        <p>Despite the opposition and the claims of hidden agendas, Assemblyman John Burzichelli, a Democrat from Paulsboro, dismissed accusations that state officials had traded safety for development.</p>
        <p>''That is a reach and not based on any facts,'' Mr. Burzichelli said in a recent interview. ''All this noise from a handful of leaders of the opposition is misplaced.''</p>
        <p>L.N.G. is natural gas that has been super-cooled to minus-260 degrees Fahrenheit, reducing the gas by 600 times its original volume. The liquid is then loaded onto tankers and shipped to terminals like the one proposed here, where it is warmed, converted back to gas, and sent to homes and businesses through a network of pipelines.</p>
        <p>By converting the gas to liquid, tankers can carry much greater volumes long distances. But residents are concerned because the liquefied natural gas can vaporize when exposed to the air and ignite instantaneously.</p>
        <p>Today, most of the nation's natural gas is delivered by pipeline from fields in the Gulf Coast and from Mexico and Canada. But rising demand has stretched those resources, leading energy companies to turn to liquefied natural gas to increase supply.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's -- when the nation got its first taste of an energy shortage -- liquefied natural gas enjoyed brief popularity, and a handful of terminals opened in the United States. But in the 1980's, energy prices dropped and several natural gas plants in the United States were mothballed.</p>
        <p>Now, most of those plants are back in operation, and dozens of official and informal plans for terminals are cropping up around the nation. For instance, Philadelphia Gas Works has proposed a terminal in a heavily populated section of Northeast Philadelphia that would bring tankers up the Delaware River far north of the Logan site.</p>
        <p>As for the proposed Crown Landing project, Tom Mueller, external affairs director for BP's Crown Landing project, said the company considered other sites on the East Coast, but settled on Logan because it could accommodate deepwater vessels and was relatively remote from large populations. According to BP's application before the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, 82 people live within a mile of the plant and 383 live within two miles.</p>
        <p>''The remote location we've selected for this site really helps in terms of support that this project has received,'' Mr. Mueller said.</p>
        <p>Yet others question just how remote the facility will be if it is 6 miles north of Wilmington, 14 miles south of Philadelphia, a region with a combined population of at least three million people.</p>
        <p>What also makes the site attractive to BP is the presence of two major natural gas pipelines that cross the site, although a new 11-mile line would have to be built under the river to Pennsylvania, according to BP's plans. But it all comes down to supply and demand.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Mueller explained, New Jersey and the rest of the Northeast sit at a ''pinch point'' in the distribution network of natural gas, which comes north in pipelines from the Gulf of Mexico. ''There's growth all along from here to Texas, and those states are pulling off greater volumes of gas each year,'' he said. ''It is becoming more and more difficult to make it here in sufficient volumes to meet the growing demand.''</p>
        <p>Bradley M. Campbell, commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Protection, says the terminal may actually benefit the environment because the two existing pipelines will reduce the need to build additional lines, and the increased use of natural gas will lower the need for coal and other pollution-causing fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, several large utility companies -- which would receive gas from Crown Landing through the pipeline system -- have objected to the facility, contending that industrial and residential systems in the Northeast may not be compatible with the gas to be imported from overseas.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, Public Service Electric and Gas, wrote: ''This region is not only heavily industrialized and populated, but it is home to various high-tech industries, including the pharmaceutical industry, which is heavily dependent on consistent gas quality.''</p>
        <p>Resolving Safety Concerns</p>
        <p>Lauren Siegal, BP's vice president for the Crown Landing project, said that those concerns could be addressed by mixing other gases into the product in Logan, or along the pipeline.</p>
        <p>''The gas that goes into the pipeline will meet pipeline specs and we will not deviate,'' Ms. Siegal said. ''If they're looking for additional assurances, when we're closer to operating the facility they will have all their issues resolved.''</p>
        <p>Still, the biggest concern about the gas plant is safety, despite the industry's relatively unblemished record.</p>
        <p>The nation's first liquefied natural gas plant opened in Cleveland in 1941, and three years later 128 people died and a neighborhood was leveled when gas seeped into the sewer system and exploded. In 1973, an explosion at a liquefied natural gas storage facility on Staten Island killed 37 construction workers, and in 1979 a leak at a plant in Maryland lead to an explosion in an electrical control room that killed a worker.</p>
        <p>As for tanker safety, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission noted that during 33,000 shipments of liquefied natural gas over the last 40 years, there has not been one serious accident. Still, since the Sept. 11 attacks and the bombing of the U.S.S. Cole in 2000, port security has become a growing concern.</p>
        <p>To address security issues related to liquefied natural gas, the Department of Energy commissioned a report by Sandia Laboratories in New Mexico that lays out various scenarios for the potential damage from an accident involving a tanker or terminal as well as an intentional attack. The report, made public a year ago, described six scenarios, the most likely one involving radiant heat that could spread about one-third of a mile and cause second- and third-degree burns.</p>
        <p>In a worst-case scenario, an attack on a tanker could lead to the release of the liquid that would immediately become a vapor plume upon contact with the outside air and extend nearly three miles from the site. Under certain circumstances, the gas could then ignite, generating a fireball large enough to imperil Wilmington, the Delaware Memorial Bridge or the nearby Hope Creek and Salem nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>Capt. David Scott, commander of the Coast Guard's Delaware Bay sector, said an intentional attack is more worrisome than the possibility of an accident involving the tankers, which are double-hulled.</p>
        <p>''It would take an extraordinary thing to be able to breech the inner and outer hull and compromise a tanker, but it is not impossible to do,'' Captain Scott said. ''I think with intelligently applied security measures we can reduce the risk to an acceptable level with security procedures.''</p>
        <p>Alan Muller, director of Green Delaware, an environmental organization opposed to the facility, said the question becomes, ''What is acceptable?''</p>
        <p>''I don't want to have to worry about the effects on my property values of people seeing these floating bombs moving up and down the river,'' Mr. Muller said. ''If you look at the measures that would need to be taken if you are serious about protecting these ships, we are going to have cops up and down the river and people kept out of the public parks and a whole series of repressive measures laid on communities.''</p>
        <p>For their part, Delaware officials have vetoed the plan under what they say is their right to block projects that would harm the environment up to the Delaware River shoreline.</p>
        <p>''This has high potential for environmental impact,'' said Jane Brady, Delaware's attorney general. ''We've declined people who wanted to do this on our own shores, and we don't believe New Jersey should be allowed to engage in this kind of activity.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Siegal said BP has done a thorough analysis of all the safety and security concerns, and was willing to hire boats to protect the tankers as they come upriver, build security systems to protect the terminal and develop emergency procedures to shut the facility.</p>
        <p>''We have been proactive with everything from detectors and monitoring systems to engaging in collaborative plans with local police and state-level security,'' she said.</p>
        <p>With combined scrutiny of the Coast Guard, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and state officials, Ms. Siegal said, the project would be safe. ''I don't know of any other material, in any other industry, that has undergone this level of monitoring,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Mueller of BP pointed out that the plant would help improve the economy of the region by generating 550 construction jobs and 50 to 60 full-time jobs once the plant was opened. More important, said Mr. Fader, counsel to Mr. Codey, the availability of a new energy source would help keep costs down, particularly if electrical generation converted to the use of more liquefied natural gas.</p>
        <p>Ms. Siegal acknowledged that BP would have preferred to own the pier rather than lease it from the state, but Mr. Fader said state officials came up with the idea to own the pier as a way to gain more economic development rents from BP and to enhance the case against Delaware before the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>A Matter of Liability</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Spadaccini, the Logan resident opposed to the facility, said he was concerned that the state's ownership could lead to taxpayer liability in the event of an incident at the terminal. ''The state is really jeopardizing the taxpayers of New Jersey if one of these things blows up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fader countered that the state would craft a leasing agreement shifting liability to BP, saying, ''That is a legal hurdle that can be jumped with good lawyering.''</p>
        <p>To Ms. Finlayson of the New Jersey Environmental Federation, the debate over the project misses the point. She says that if $600 million were invested in research into alternative energy sources, there might be little demand for liquefied natural gas, and that becoming dependent on imported natural gas could lead to the same geopolitical problems that have gripped the United States as a result of its thirst for imported oil.</p>
        <p>''They're putting all this money into ensuring this is built,'' she said. ''All we are doing is creating a reliance on this energy source when I believe there are better, safer alternatives.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
