<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Natural Gas And Long Island Sound</title>
    <meta content="LTR231900" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1678026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DB1538F936A35755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Natural Gas And Long Island Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Battle in the Sound'' correctly concluded that the decisions over how we address Long Island's energy needs must be the product of an honest and transparent debate.</p>
        <p>Long Island suffers from some of the highest energy costs in the country. It's dependent on old, less efficient power generation predominantly fueled by oil. It receives failing grades for its air quality from the American Lung Association. The economy is burdened with a cost of living that makes housing unaffordable and imposes a not so hidden tax of astronomical energy prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Battle in the Sound'' correctly concluded that the decisions over how we address Long Island's energy needs must be the product of an honest and transparent debate.</p>
        <p>Long Island suffers from some of the highest energy costs in the country. It's dependent on old, less efficient power generation predominantly fueled by oil. It receives failing grades for its air quality from the American Lung Association. The economy is burdened with a cost of living that makes housing unaffordable and imposes a not so hidden tax of astronomical energy prices.</p>
        <p>Some of it has to do with geography and geology. The region is at the end of a long pipeline network that serves many others before it delivers natural gas here. The nation's domestic resources now struggle to keep up with the increasing demand for the popular fuel. We firmly believe that Broadwater, which would save consumers in the region up to $6 billion in energy costs over what they otherwise might be during its first 10 years of service, is the most reliable, economical and environmentally sound solution to this problem.</p>
        <p>Additional measures such as new electrical cables, natural gas pipelines and renewable energy projects may help, but will not provide the quantity of supply, security and economic advantages of Broadwater. There is no denying the benefits of having a new source of reliable natural gas located here and dedicated to this region. Broadwater should be one of the components of Long Island's multifaceted energy solutions.</p>
        <p>Broadwater hasn't asked anyone to embrace its proposal just yet. The proposal needs to be finalized and fully reviewed through the well-established federal and state regulatory process before informed decisions can be made. Broadwater believes that Long Islanders must have the opportunity to learn the facts both pro and con. We are committed to ensuring that the facts emerge and that Long Islanders get the opportunity to constructively engage in the process that is essential to their energy future.</p>
        <p>John Hritcko Jr.  Senior Vice President  Broadwater Energy  Riverhead</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
