<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki's Various Shades of Green; Preserving Land, but a Mixed Record on the Environment</title>
    <meta content="19PATA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/19/nyregion/19pataki.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <meta content="10 YEARS LATER: The Environment" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1681478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4D7153BF93AA25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki's Various Shades of Green; Preserving Land, but a Mixed Record on the Environment</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pataki's Various Shades of Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His timing was impeccable; his message clear as a mountain stream. It was Earth Day 2004, and Gov. George E. Pataki was announcing the largest land preservation deal in New York State history -- a quarter-million acres of true Adirondacks wilderness that would be thrown open to the public for the first time in a century.</p>
        <p>The historic deal brought Mr. Pataki within striking distance of his goal of preserving a million acres of open space, giving him a record on land preservation unmatched by any New York governor since Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The environmental record of Gov. George E. Pataki includes formidable achievements in land preservation and sometimes-halting steps on regulation and enforcement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His timing was impeccable; his message clear as a mountain stream. It was Earth Day 2004, and Gov. George E. Pataki was announcing the largest land preservation deal in New York State history -- a quarter-million acres of true Adirondacks wilderness that would be thrown open to the public for the first time in a century.</p>
        <p>The historic deal brought Mr. Pataki within striking distance of his goal of preserving a million acres of open space, giving him a record on land preservation unmatched by any New York governor since Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>But then, a little over a month later, the wheels temporarily seemed to come off Mr. Pataki's well-oiled green machine. A state judge threw out, on a technicality, the clean-air regulations that the governor more than four years earlier promised would be the toughest in the country. Embarrassed administration officials were forced to admit that state regulators had missed a crucial deadline.</p>
        <p>These two episodes frame the environmental record of Mr. Pataki during his 10 years in office: formidable achievements in land preservation and sometimes-halting steps on regulation and enforcement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki's positions on the environment have set him apart from many of his fellow Republican governors and the Bush administration on delicate issues like controlling greenhouse gases. And as the governor decides this summer whether to pursue a fourth term, even his harshest critics credit him with working vigorously to preserve huge swaths of land from development. But they say that in trying to create a friendly environment for business, he has too often failed to deliver on promises he made in other critical areas.</p>
        <p>In instance after instance, critics say, Mr. Pataki has announced bold proposals that then drifted through years of delays:</p>
        <p>$(6$)When the Bush administration refused to sign the Kyoto protocols on reducing greenhouse gases, Mr. Pataki vowed that he would lead a coalition of Northeastern states to control harmful emissions. So far, it has not happened.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki promised that if the federal government did not get tough on mercury emissions from power plants, New York would set strict standards on its own. But the state's latest power plant emissions standards do not include mercury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki repeatedly said environmental regulations would be enforced and polluters would be punished, but deep cuts in the staff at the State Department of Environmental Conservation have left it short of enforcers and regulators.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Pataki vigorously defended his record and firmly denied that he had gone easy on industry or allowed the Department of Environmental Conservation to wither. ''If you look at the environmental results in this state, whether it's in cleaning the air, remediating brownfields, preserving open space, reclaiming waterfronts, cleaning the actual waterfronts, working on habitat improvement, fighting against greenhouse gases, pursuing alternate energy sources, looking at energy conservation and trying to lead the country, then the record is one that I would be happy to compare with any other governor anywhere in America,'' he said, ''not just now but for the past decades.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Pataki arrived at the statehouse in 1995, following a campaign in which he had promised to keep government off the backs of business, all bets about his commitment to the environment were off. Then came an unexpected turning point.</p>
        <p>A powerful storm that year blew down millions of trees in the Adirondacks preserves, where logging is prohibited. Timber companies wanted permission to harvest the fallen trees. Mr. Pataki listened to conservationists who argued that when timber companies were permitted to salvage fallen trees after a similar storm in the 1950's, they went too far and also cut down standing trees.</p>
        <p>Despite intense pressure from the timber companies, Mr. Pataki decided to leave the trees where they fell. That action won over many environmentalists.</p>
        <p>''We offered him an olive branch,'' said John F. Sheehan, a spokesman for the Adirondack Council, a watchdog group. The council gave Mr. Pataki its Conservationist of the Year award that year.</p>
        <p>In 1996, Mr. Pataki campaigned hard for the $1.75 billion environmental bond act. His success in getting the measure passed set him apart from his predecessor, Mario M. Cuomo, who failed to pass a similar measure in 1990. Stymied by a lack of money, Mr. Cuomo's administration subsequently lost several significant chances to preserve land. During Mr. Cuomo's three terms, 310,698 acres around the state were protected. That is a third of what Mr. Pataki has to date.</p>
        <p>In contrast to Mr. Cuomo, Mr. Pataki says he genuinely enjoys being in the woods. It is not unusual for him to grab a big stick and use it as a hiking staff, dressed casually in jeans and hiking boots, with reporters and aides trying to keep up with him.</p>
        <p>He was able to put substance behind that image in 1997, when the state made a deal to buy 15,000 acres of Adirondack woodlands outright from the Whitney family, and also to preserve 35,000 more acres from development for at least a decade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki had hit on a successful environmental formula. Flush with money from the bond act and the expanding Environmental Protection Fund, Mr. Pataki found himself in a buyer's market. Big timber companies that had held onto Adirondack acreage for more than a century were being pressured by stockholders to get rid of underperforming assets. Some environmentalists call what resulted ''a golden age of conservation'' that is creating a legacy that will last as long as the Adirondack Park itself.</p>
        <p>''This has been a very impressive conservation track record by any measure,'' said Henry Tepper, New York State director of the Nature Conservancy, a group that has worked with the governor to protect more than 100,000 acres of open space. ''These are the kinds of things that earn you an environmental legacy.''</p>
        <p>The achievements in the Adirondacks were matched elsewhere. After decades of trying, the state finally bought most of Sterling Forest in Orange County and brokered a land preservation deal with communities in New York City's Catskill watershed. There were also important purchases in the Long Island Pine Barrens and the incomplete Hudson River Park.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has vowed to preserve a million acres of New York forest. As of now, his administration has taken action to protect 917,205 acres, although the state has closed the deals on and paid for only 418,000 acres. New York owes conservation groups around $20 million.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to create an artificial goal and say that we're going to do something stupid to get there,'' Mr. Pataki said of reaching the million-acre mark. ''It might make sense next week, it might make sense next year, it might not make sense for two years, but we're going to get there.''</p>
        <p>Besides land preservation, Mr. Pataki has won praise for other environmental initiatives. After waiting on the sidelines for years, he backed plans to force General Electric to clean up PCB's in the Hudson River. New York was one of the first states to adopt California's tough tailpipe emissions standards on automobiles and continues to follow them as they become more stringent.</p>
        <p>He got the Legislature to renew a state Superfund law so that the state's most contaminated sites could be cleaned up. He insisted on adding provisions to cover less-contaminated urban areas, known as brownfields. New York became one of the first states to add a special surcharge on energy bills to finance the development of renewable energy sources, like windmills, and in January six of the largest coal-burning power plants in New York agreed to slash emissions.</p>
        <p>But there were many disappointments, mostly over delays and the lack of follow-through. The Department of Environmental Conservation was battered by staff reductions. According to the union representing state workers at the department, manpower dropped to 3,201 budgeted full-time employees from 4,221 at the start of Mr. Pataki's first term.</p>
        <p>''Not only does that show that the professional staff here has taken a beating,'' said Stanley M. Byer, an air resources scientist and shop steward. ''When you have an organization that's lost a quarter of its long-term career professionals, things are going to slip under the table.''</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Pataki said all departments of state government had shrunk since he took office, without any decline in their performance.</p>
        <p>When the federal government refused to act on greenhouse gases, Mr. Pataki formed the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative to set up a program for controlling smokestack emissions among several Northeastern states. He has been applauded for taking the lead on a global issue, but several years later the plan is not yet a reality. Some environmentalists feel that if New York had enacted its own regulations right away, the other states would have followed.</p>
        <p>The power industry has supported the go-slow approach on emissions. Gavin J. Donohue, president of the Independent Power Producers of New York and a former aide to Mr. Pataki, said that acting unilaterally would have put New York at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot easier to go out and purchase a piece of property you're going to preserve using state and private money than to say you're going to implement some complex regulations to control the generation of electricity,'' Mr. Donohue said.</p>
        <p>Some critics said Mr. Pataki did not really seem to have much interest in regulating industry until Attorney General Eliot Spitzer, a Democrat and potential political rival, put industrial polluters in his sights. Mr. Pataki announced his Clean Air regulations in October 1999, a few weeks after Mr. Spitzer announced that he was preparing to sue 17 coal-fired power plants in the Midwest whose emissions drift eastward to pollute the air over New York.</p>
        <p>''The governor's promise was probably spurred on a little bit by Spitzer's plans to take on the power plants,'' said Peter M. Iwanowicz, director of environmental health at the American Lung Association of New York State. But he said the delays, and lack of focus, seemed a clear sign that the administration ''was more interested in perception than policy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki called such charges nonsense, and said that he always set what he called ''aggressive goals'' and then tried to achieve them. ''Sometimes there are circumstances beyond our control, like a lawsuit, that delays them,'' he said. Some of his initiatives, like a bill to widen the protection of wetlands in the state, have been blocked in the Legislature. Still, the governor insists, he will ''continue to push.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have generally been frustrated with the governor's handling of the state's Environmental Protection Fund. They laud him for increasing the fund to $150 million, but they strongly disapproved when he took millions out to balance the state budget, even though his aides say the money is always restored. And the environmental community fears that unless the staff cuts at the Department of Environmental Conservation are reversed, enforcement and oversight will suffer as the governor heads into what may the his last years in office.</p>
        <p>''The final chapter hasn't been written yet,'' said Eric A. Goldstein, a senior lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''History suggests that environmental leadership reaches full bloom as elected officials move into the homestretch and think about their legacy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki denied being in the homestretch.</p>
        <p>''If I live long enough, there'll be time to sit in a rocking chair and reflect back and say 'Hey, that was pretty good.' or 'Boy, we bungled that,''' the governor said. ''But I have no intention of doing that yet.''</p>
        <p>10 Years Later</p>
        <p>This is the fourth in a series of articles examining aspects of state government since Gov. George E. Pataki took office. Previous articles, which examined tax cuts, efforts to overhaul the government, and the state university system, are at nytimes.com/metro.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
