<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lee Raymond, Exxon Mobil's Chief Since 1999 Merger, to Step Down at Year's End</title>
    <meta content="05exxon" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/05/business/05exxon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1692500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Exxon Mobil Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Raymond, Lee R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5D61F3FF936A3575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lee Raymond, Exxon Mobil's Chief Since 1999 Merger, to Step Down at Year's End</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lee Raymond, Exxon Mobil's Chief Since 1999 Merger, to Step Down at Year's End</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAD MOUAWAD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exxon Mobil, the world's largest publicly traded oil company, announced yesterday that Lee R. Raymond, its chairman and chief executive, would retire at the end of the year, after 12 years during which he steered the company ahead of its rivals.</p>
        <p>He will be succeeded by Rex W. Tillerson, 53, Exxon Mobil's president and a longtime insider who recently emerged as the heir apparent to Mr. Raymond.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Helped by record oil prices, Lee R. Raymond will leave the company in its best-ever financial and operating form.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exxon Mobil, the world's largest publicly traded oil company, announced yesterday that Lee R. Raymond, its chairman and chief executive, would retire at the end of the year, after 12 years during which he steered the company ahead of its rivals.</p>
        <p>He will be succeeded by Rex W. Tillerson, 53, Exxon Mobil's president and a longtime insider who recently emerged as the heir apparent to Mr. Raymond.</p>
        <p>Mr. Raymond, who is 66, has spent the past 42 years at Exxon. Helped by record oil prices, he will leave the company in its best-ever financial and operating form.</p>
        <p>''Lee Raymond has been a very strong chairman in a line of very strong chairmen at Exxon,'' said James L. Smith, a business professor at Southern Methodist University in Dallas. ''He brought the majors back into the realm of the world's greatest oil companies, with a global presence, financial reach and diversity of holdings.''</p>
        <p>The company was born in 1999 with the $81 billion merger of Exxon, the former Standard Oil Company (New Jersey), and Mobil, once the Standard Oil Company of New York, or Socony. Each day, it pumps 2.5 million barrels of oil -- more than Kuwait, an OPEC producer -- and 10 billion cubic feet of natural gas. It is the world's top refiner and controls 22 billion barrels of oil reserves, the most among its publicly traded peers.</p>
        <p>To his critics, Mr. Raymond is one of the last hard-liners on global climate change. He remains skeptical that human activity is responsible for the current warming trends, saying that the science is not conclusive. Other industrial giants, including BP, General Electric and Ford, have all come out with a more environment-friendly posture in recent years, said Kert Davies, research director at Greenpeace USA.</p>
        <p>''There is a spectrum of corporate behavior on global warming and Exxon is the epitome of denial and deception,'' Mr. Davies said. ''Raymond is unrepentant on global warming and has boxed himself so far in that corner that there's no going back for him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Raymond is known for his direct, sometimes abrasive style and his limited tolerance for analysts, investors or journalists. In some ways, he is an old-fashioned oilman in an industry that has become more diverse, more international and more urbane.</p>
        <p>But the company's shareholders have had little to complain about, given the company's staggering profits, record dividends and stock performance. Last year, Exxon Mobil posted $25 billion in profits with sales of $291 billion -- a sum larger than the gross domestic product of countries like Austria or Saudi Arabia. This year, the company is on track for even better performance.</p>
        <p>Since the 1999 merger, Exxon Mobil has paid $33 billion in dividends to its shareholders and spent $24 billion buying back 8 percent of its shares.</p>
        <p>''Raymond has created a company that delivers through the cycles, through the peaks, through the troughs,'' said Benjamin Dell, an oil analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, who rates Exxon Mobil outperform and owns no shares in the company. ''Betting against Exxon over the past 15 years has been a very bad bet.''</p>
        <p>Exxon Mobil -- like Chevron, ConocoPhillips and BP -- convinced government regulators that megamergers, set off by the oil price collapse of 1998, were vital to the industry's survival. Some called it the greatest holdup in the industry's history, in which the majors took advantage of depressed commodity prices to argue successfully for greater concentration.</p>
        <p>''It was a little window of opportunity and they grabbed it,'' said Mr. Smith of Southern Methodist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Raymond, who was born in Watertown, S.D., joined Exxon in 1963 with a doctorate in chemical engineering from the University of Minnesota. He became president in 1987 and chief executive and chairman in 1993.</p>
        <p>At the board's request, he deferred his departure past 2003, the year he reached the company's mandatory retirement age of 65, and agreed to stay on to oversee the merged operations and pick a successor.</p>
        <p>His successor, Mr. Tillerson, was born in Wichita Falls, Tex. He joined Exxon in 1975 as a production engineer after graduating from the University of Texas at Austin with a degree in civil engineering. He rose through the company's ranks in the United States, Yemen and Russia, spending his entire career at Exxon's production units. He was named president in March 2004, an obvious steppingstone to succeeding Mr. Raymond.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell, the oil analyst, expects few changes in strategy from the succession. ''Rex is stepping into Lee's shoes and there will be little change at the top,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
