<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Thiller Stars the U.N., as Itself</title>
    <meta content="28LOST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/28/movies/28lost.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1668227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Sydney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Interpreter, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pollack, Sydney</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED71331F93BA15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Thiller Stars the U.N., as Itself</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Thriller Stars the U.N., as Itself</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James Critic's Notebook column on United Nations as backdrop for Sydney Pollack's new thriller, The Interpreter; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations serves several functions in Sydney Pollack's new thriller, ''The Interpreter'': it's a plot device, a film location and, most conspicuously, the centerpiece of the hype. Anyone who has heard or read a thing about the film must know that it was the first to shoot at the U.N., and on screen the General Assembly looks real enough. But then so does the fake Oval Office on the ''The West Wing.''</p>
        <p>By the end of the movie, you may wonder why Mr. Pollack went to the trouble of filming at the real U.N. for such a bogus story, about an interpreter, played by Nicole Kidman, who overhears what may be a plot to assassinate an African dictator. With Sean Penn in the irredeemably tired role of a Secret Service agent who protects her (is there a flicker of doubt he'll fall for her?), the film is such a swamp of clichés that the General Assembly seems its only authentic element. Well, what can you expect from a thriller?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The heavily publicized United Nations setting for Sydney Pollack's new thriller, "The Interpreter," promises an authenticity that the movie never approaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United Nations serves several functions in Sydney Pollack's new thriller, ''The Interpreter'': it's a plot device, a film location and, most conspicuously, the centerpiece of the hype. Anyone who has heard or read a thing about the film must know that it was the first to shoot at the U.N., and on screen the General Assembly looks real enough. But then so does the fake Oval Office on the ''The West Wing.''</p>
        <p>By the end of the movie, you may wonder why Mr. Pollack went to the trouble of filming at the real U.N. for such a bogus story, about an interpreter, played by Nicole Kidman, who overhears what may be a plot to assassinate an African dictator. With Sean Penn in the irredeemably tired role of a Secret Service agent who protects her (is there a flicker of doubt he'll fall for her?), the film is such a swamp of clichés that the General Assembly seems its only authentic element. Well, what can you expect from a thriller?</p>
        <p>In this case, a lot more. In movies as in politics, the expectations game is crucial, but a film has to deliver what it promises. For ''The Interpreter,'' the heavily publicized United Nations setting promises an authenticity of character and plot that the movie never approaches.</p>
        <p>Thrillers don't always promise such plausibility, even if they toss in topical references. ''The Day After Tomorrow'' willfully moves farther and farther from reality, as global warming sets off events that cause the East Coast of the United States to freeze over. Global warming is merely a tease, in a goofy action movie that doesn't really expect anyone to believe Dennis Quaid can walk from Washington to New York City in conditions that rival climbing Mount Everest. Movies with nightmare scenarios like ''The Day After Tomorrow'' extrapolate away from reality rather than clinging to it.</p>
        <p>''The Interpreter'' doesn't have that excuse. It falls into the genre of believable thrillers like ''Collateral,'' last year's first-rate Michael Mann film in which Jamie Foxx , as a taxi driver, tries to outsmart Tom Cruise as a hired killer. There are gunfights and car chases no one would be likely to survive (but could). Anyway, the point is the cat-and-mouse game. As in Hitchcock movies, successful thrillers have to be tangled and improbable, without straying into the land of the idiotic. By the time bodies start falling in ''Collateral,'' the audience is hooked enough to go along with it.</p>
        <p>In ''The Interpreter,'' for the plot to be set in motion at all, we have to accept a bizarre lack of U.N. security. The Kidman character was a rebel in her fictitious African country, the very country of the threatened dictator, and one character casually mentions that her background wasn't checked too carefully before she was hired because she seemed so perfect for the job. (When a film starts explaining its plot holes, it's in trouble.) Soon she's sneaking into an empty U.N. sound booth off hours because an infatuated colleague has bent the rules and let her store her flute there before her music lesson. This tortured premise sets her up to overhear the assassination threat, and events become decreasingly authentic after that.</p>
        <p>All this is especially disappointing because Mr. Pollack has created such sparkling examples of plausible thrillers in the past, as well as the classic comedy ''Tootsie'' and the romantic epic ''Out of Africa.'' He's as good a mainstream Hollywood director as there is, despite recent clunkers like ''Random Hearts.''</p>
        <p>Hype aside, an audience can legitimately bring high expectations to ''The Interpreter'' based on ''Three Days of the Condor,'' the 1975 Pollack movie with Robert Redford as a C.I.A. researcher who discovers a Company secret and is hunted by killers. The movie's outsize computers are laughably archaic now, but the film is still loaded with tension, and even has a current resonance when we hear that the plot the Redford character has uncovered involves the Middle East and America's need for oil. The movie holds up because the sleek plot depends on the hero's cleverness as he tries to figure out who's after him and why.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Pollack's efficient 1993 thriller, ''The Firm,'' Tom Cruise is the clever hero who finds himself in a lethal law firm. Like most movies based on John Grisham novels, its plausibility is so rooted in the thickets of the legal system that it takes a lawyer to poke holes in it.</p>
        <p>''The Interpreter,'' meant to be so up-to-the-minute, seems like a lumbering Hollywood dinosaur next to those films. That's odd because Mr. Pollack knows that faking authenticity can be the best route to realism. As he explained on ''Charlie Rose,'' the film creates an entire African language to go along with its fictional country because referring to a real country or person would have restricted the film too much. And it's true that the invented country and its leader, shadowy echoes of Zimbabwe and Robert Mugabe, work just fine. So why did he need the U.N.? The location adds little except self-importance, a deadly quality in a thriller.</p>
        <p>It might be tempting to think that a big Hollywood movie today has to fall into the traps of ''The Interpreter,'' and that smaller films have the edge over them. The most credible New York film to turn up recently is the very modest ensemble piece ''The Great New Wonderful'' (playing at the TriBeCa Film Festival tomorrow) about people going about their ordinary, messed-up lives a year after 9/11. The New York locations are simply part of its authenticity, though. The film's deeper realism comes from its refusal to sort out how many characters' problems are tied to 9/11 and how many would have cropped up anyway.</p>
        <p>The best and only authentic sequence in ''The Interpreter'' comes from a similar, unspoken reference to the legacy of 9/11. When a bomb is planted on a New York City bus, the episode invokes a fear that has been discussed so often in reality that it feels as if it could actually happen. The sequence is as big, tense and action-packed as any Hollywood movie requires, yet also daringly close to life (proving Mr. Pollack's theory that something fake can be the best approach to the truth). In every other instance, ''The Interpreter'' flees into safer, duller territory. That makes it a huge lost opportunity, because if Mr. Pollack, Ms. Kidman and Mr. Penn can't make an authentic Hollywood thriller, who can?</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
