<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Clean Pool: Just Add Salt And Relax</title>
    <meta content="24wepool" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1689579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="RECREATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DD173FF937A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Clean Pool: Just Add Salt And Relax</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARIN RUBENSTEIN</byline>
      <dateline>THORNWOOD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was concern about his wife's hair that persuaded Joseph Jensen to choose a saltwater pool for his new house here.</p>
        <p>''She never swam in our old chlorine pool, because her bleached blond hair doesn't take well to chlorine,'' Mr. Jensen said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was concern about his wife's hair that persuaded Joseph Jensen to choose a saltwater pool for his new house here.</p>
        <p>''She never swam in our old chlorine pool, because her bleached blond hair doesn't take well to chlorine,'' Mr. Jensen said.</p>
        <p>''I hate chlorine,'' said his wife, Donna, who explained to him that her hair is not bleached but highlighted. Even so, she acknowledged, it turned green on the few occasions she took dips in the old pool.</p>
        <p>Green-haired swimming is now a thing of the past for the Jensens: they left it behind in May, when they vacated their house in North White Plains and moved to Thornwood with their two sons.</p>
        <p>Their new pool is filled with salt water made from ordinary table salt, whose chemical contents -- sodium and chlorine -- are gradually separated by a small machine called a chlorine, or saline, generator. The agent that keeps the water clean is still chlorine -- but proponents find it less smelly and harsh than in traditional swimming pools. The equipment sits a few yards from the pool, along with a filter, a pump, a cleaning system and a heater.</p>
        <p>''More and more people are asking for saline generators,'' said Suzanne Barrows, a spokeswoman for the Association of Pool and Spa Professionals, an industry group in Alexandria, Va. ''It's an effective sanitation system that is gaining in popularity and, over the long run, can be less expensive.''</p>
        <p>Nationwide, she said, there are about 275,000 saline generating in-ground pools, out of a total of about 4.5 million. That number is growing at least 10 percent annually.</p>
        <p>On a sticky Friday afternoon at the Jensen home (where construction is not yet completed), the contents of the pool tasted more like tap water than ocean residue. Thrashing in the sparkling water, the Jensens' dog, Jagger, was trying to fetch a ball thrown in by Michael, 6, who was enthusiastically shoving Rocky, the family's ferret, down the water slide.</p>
        <p>''About 99 percent of our new pools are saltwater pools,'' said Nick Vitiello, project manager for Lang Pools in Norwalk, Conn., the company that installed the Jensen pool. ''We made the big shift to saltwater pools about two or three years ago.'' The company builds in-ground vinyl-lined pools, which start at $35,000 for a standard 20-by-40-foot model, he said.</p>
        <p>''Most of our pools take care of themselves,'' Mr. Vitiello said, alluding in part to the generator -- which needs just a few large bags of salt each season, he said. It comes with a digital remote device that records water temperature and salt content, advising owners when it is time to add another bagful.</p>
        <p>Jerry Gouldey, sales manager for the New York division of Anthony &amp; Sylvan Pools, says the water in such pools is ''a lot silkier and smoother,'' explaining that saline generators ''take in pure table salt and create chlorine, but with a lot less irritating pool water.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gouldey, whose company sells pools in 54 locations nationwide, says this chlorine-generating method of pool sanitation has become standard in California and Las Vegas, where it is installed 85 to 90 percent of the time.</p>
        <p>As recently as five years ago, virtually no companies in the Northeast were using chlorine generators, he said. But in another two years or so, he estimated, the majority of new pools in the New York area will probably include one.</p>
        <p>A 20-by-40-foot Anthony &amp; Sylvan pool, lined with Gunite rather than vinyl, costs about $50,000, not including patio and fencing, he said. The generator increases that price about 3 percent, but that is offset by the cost of a season's supply of salt, which is about $75, compared with $500 to $700 for a seasonal dosage of chlorine.</p>
        <p>Pool supply stores in the area, Mr. Gouldey said, are losing about 20 percent of their revenues from a resulting drop in chlorine sales.</p>
        <p>There is a third pool-cleaning option, using bromine rather than chlorine; it is by far the most expensive and least prevalent system, but dealers say it has several important advantages. ''We use a high-end ozone system, along with bromine, that burns off into oxygen and carbon dioxide,'' said John Gedney III, vice president of the family-owned E.L. Wagner Company in Darien, Conn., which builds about 100 pools a year in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>An ozone unit for a standard 20-by-40-foot pool costs about $12,500, and requires about $500 worth of bromine each season, Mr. Gedney said. A standard Wagner pool -- including the ozone unit -- costs about $70,000, not including patio or fencing.</p>
        <p>The system's advantages, Mr. Gedney said, are that it does not result in pitting of the metal fittings and screws used in pool construction, or produce any of the harmful byproducts of chlorine, like chloramine, an irritant with a strong odor. In addition, ''ozone is 3,000 times more potent at killing germs than chlorine,'' he said. ''The U.S. is very chlorine-centric, because it is a cheap way to sanitize water.''</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Gouldey said, with an ozone system, the filter must remain on constantly. With energy costs as high as they are, he said, this ends up being ''very, very expensive.''</p>
        <p>In the end, everything is relative anyway. Customers like the Jensens, who are used to heavily chlorinated pools, tend to be delighted with salt water.</p>
        <p>''When you come out of the pool, you don't smell like chlorine,'' said Ira Silver, enthusing about the renovated saltwater pool that replaced a chlorinated one at his Larchmont home. He described the water as ''extra soft, with no film, and it's very clear,'' adding, ''You can see underwater from one side of the pool to the other.''</p>
        <p>There is no word yet from Rocky, the Jensens' ferret, about which type of pool he prefers.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
