<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing Differences With Major Allies, Bush Arrives in Europe for Talks</title>
    <meta content="06PREX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/06/international/europe/06prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1685278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3D61F3AF935A35754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing Differences With Major Allies, Bush Arrives in Europe for Talks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Facing Differences With Major Allies, Bush Arrives in Europe for Talks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON; Alan Cowell contributed reporting from Edinburgh for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN, July 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush arrived Tuesday in Denmark, his first stop on a four-day European trip that even before it began seemed sure to show the United States at odds with many of the other big industrial nations on a variety of issues.</p>
        <p>It is the president's fourth trip to Europe since he began his second term in January, reflecting an effort by the White House to help address the tensions between the United States and its allies over Iraq. From Denmark, which he is visiting as a show of thanks for its commitment of troops to Iraq, Mr. Bush will fly on to the Gleneagles golf resort in Scotland on Wednesday for the annual summit meeting with the leaders of Britain, France, Germany, Japan, Italy, Canada and Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even before the trip began it seemed sure to show the U.S. at odds with other big industrial nations on a variety of issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush arrived Tuesday in Denmark, his first stop on a four-day European trip that even before it began seemed sure to show the United States at odds with many of the other big industrial nations on a variety of issues.</p>
        <p>It is the president's fourth trip to Europe since he began his second term in January, reflecting an effort by the White House to help address the tensions between the United States and its allies over Iraq. From Denmark, which he is visiting as a show of thanks for its commitment of troops to Iraq, Mr. Bush will fly on to the Gleneagles golf resort in Scotland on Wednesday for the annual summit meeting with the leaders of Britain, France, Germany, Japan, Italy, Canada and Russia.</p>
        <p>There, Mr. Bush will confront an agenda, developed primarily by Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, that has laid bare deep differences between the American administration and all or most of the other governments on hand when it comes to the best means of fighting global warming and attacking poverty and disease in Africa.</p>
        <p>Against the backdrop of unabated bloodshed in Iraq, the leaders are also expected to discuss how to nurture efforts to bring peace between Israel and the Palestinians, with the European nations pressing for steps to assure stability and economic progress in Gaza as Israel withdraws from that territory this summer. And the leaders will review the attempt by Britain, France and Germany to negotiate with Iran to end that nation's nuclear program.</p>
        <p>Despite the busy agenda, the policy rifts and the protests likely to greet the leaders in Scotland, Mr. Bush will make the trip with much of his attention still focused on the home front and his first Supreme Court nomination.</p>
        <p>Scott McClellan, the White House spokesman, said aboard Air Force One en route here that Mr. Bush had spent part of the flight reviewing dossiers on some of at least a half-dozen candidates under consideration to replace Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, who announced Friday that she was retiring.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the Group of 8 countries will meet here at a time of tension among them. Mr. Blair and President Jacques Chirac of France have been having an intense disagreement over the European Union's budget. The relationship between Mr. Bush and President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia has shown signs of strain. And even Mr. Bush's most rock-solid foreign alliance, with Mr. Blair, appears to have found its limits on many of the issues to be taken up in Scotland.</p>
        <p>Under prodding from Mr. Blair, Mr. Bush has announced a series of steps in recent weeks to show that the United States supports doing more to alleviate poverty in Africa.</p>
        <p>Just last week, Mr. Bush announced a new plan to fight malaria in sub-Saharan Africa. He has promised to do more to streamline his program for sending aid to Africa, the Millennium Challenge Account. And he points to a substantial increase in aid and a program to fight AIDS in Africa as concrete evidence of America's commitment to help the world's neediest people.</p>
        <p>But he has repeatedly refused to sign on to a commitment sought by many anti-poverty campaigners for the United States to increase aid to Africa to a specific level relative to total the size of the American economy. He has also rebuffed Mr. Blair and the leaders most other big industrial nations on proposals for reductions in emissions of greenhouse gases, refusing to agree to any plan that includes numerical limits on those emissions, saying such an approach would be economically ruinous.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the summit meeting's British hosts cautioned that the gathering may yield less than anti-poverty campaigners are expecting.</p>
        <p>Gordon Brown, the chancellor of the exchequer, provided a fresh indication that the world's most industrialized nations have not reached the kind of agreement on key issues like help for Africa and climate change that campaigners are demanding.</p>
        <p>Interviewed on the BBC, Mr. Brown, a prominent advocate of measures to alleviate poverty in Africa, said he had told campaigners: ''I know that you will tell us we've got to do more. I know that what you will say is that what we can achieve is perhaps not good enough.''</p>
        <p>''But we have got to bring the whole of the world together,'' he said. ''What Britain says is one thing; what we can persuade the rest of the world to do together is what we will get as the outcome of Gleneagles.'' Britain's caution drew a tart response from Sir Bob Geldof, the musician-turned-activist who organized huge rock concerts around the world last Saturday in support of his campaign to ease Africa's poverty by changing aid, trade and debt policies.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the chancellor should try lowering the bar at this stage,'' Sir Bob said as he left London for Edinburgh by train along with campaigners from France, Georgia, Mali, Sierra Leone and Britain. ''We have come for victory. It has to happen now. Not to do it now would be grotesquely irresponsible. It is unacceptable for politicians to say 'prepare to be disappointed.'''</p>
        <p>Sir Bob has urged a million people to march on Edinburgh Wednesday in what he has called a ''Long Walk to Justice'' to bring pressure to bear on the leaders at the summit meeting. But street demonstrations here on Monday have already raised worries that protests could turn violent.</p>
        <p>Scottish police warned on Tuesday that officers would not tolerate unauthorized or violent protests. ''We will not flinch where we encounter such behavior and will deal with it in a robust and measured way,'' said Chief Constable John Vine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
