<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poker-Faced Diplomat, Negroponte Is Poised For Role as Spy Chief</title>
    <meta content="29NEGR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/29/politics/29negroponte.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1660730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shane, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Negroponte, John D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Negroponte, John D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E2DE123FF93AA15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poker-Faced Diplomat, Negroponte Is Poised For Role as Spy Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Poker-Faced Diplomat, Negroponte Is Poised for Role as Spy Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SCOTT SHANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shane, Scott</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John D Negroponte, who is about to take office as first director of national intelligence, has often operated on fringes of secret world of intelligence during his four-decade diplomatic career; that career recalled;; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Duane R. Clarridge visited John D. Negroponte last summer in his barricaded compound in Baghdad, Mr. Negroponte, then the American ambassador, surprised his visitor by greeting him as ''Mr. Marone.''</p>
        <p>That was Mr. Clarridge's alias 20 years ago when they last met. He was running the Central Intelligence Agency's covert war against communism in Central America from Honduras, where Mr. Negroponte was in his first ambassadorial post.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the United States fights terrorism, John D. Negroponte is about to move to the center of that world, as the first director of national intelligence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Duane R. Clarridge visited John D. Negroponte last summer in his barricaded compound in Baghdad, Mr. Negroponte, then the American ambassador, surprised his visitor by greeting him as ''Mr. Marone.''</p>
        <p>That was Mr. Clarridge's alias 20 years ago when they last met. He was running the Central Intelligence Agency's covert war against communism in Central America from Honduras, where Mr. Negroponte was in his first ambassadorial post.</p>
        <p>The greeting was a reminder that in a four-decade diplomatic career, Mr. Negroponte, 65, has often operated on the fringes of the secret world of intelligence.</p>
        <p>Now, as the United States fights another borderless war against a different enemy, terrorism, he is about to move to the center of that world, as the first director of national intelligence. His task will be to coordinate 15 spy agencies so that the United States is never again surprised as it was on Sept. 11, 2001, nor as ill-informed as it was about Iraq's weapons programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte's career has been distinguished by an unflinching allegiance to his government's policies, whether he was helping arm the Nicaraguan contras or lining up support for the war in Iraq as ambassador to the United Nations. As he prepares for Senate confirmation hearings next month, a central question is whether the traits that served him well as a diplomat are suited to a post that may require him to tell the president what he does not want to hear.</p>
        <p>''It's a hugely different job,'' said Lee H. Hamilton, vice chairman of the commission that examined the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks and recommended creation of the intelligence czar's job.</p>
        <p>''The diplomat's job is to carry out the policy of the United States government, which is set by the president,'' said Mr. Hamilton, a former congressman from Indiana. ''In the intelligence job, John Negroponte will have to tell the president what we know and what we don't know -- whether the intelligence supports or undercuts the policy. It takes courage and considerable gumption to say, 'Mr. President, the intelligence does not run the way you'd like it to.'''</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mr. Negroponte has developed a reputation as a poker-faced diplomat who never betrays his personal views. If he harbored doubts before the war in Iraq, he never let it show, said Paul Heinbecker, who was Canadian ambassador to the United Nations at the time. ''He didn't expose whether he thought the position of his country was 100 percent sound, 90 percent sound or 20 percent sound,'' Mr. Heinbecker said. ''He's very much the United States' representative.''</p>
        <p>In five ambassadorships -- the others were Mexico and the Philippines -- and in Washington, Mr. Negroponte has helped broker peace in Vietnam, negotiated a treaty to protect the ozone layer, cajoled congressmen to accept the North American Free Trade Agreement and ushered Iraq through its first democratic elections.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte, who declined to be interviewed for this article, will go to work amid echoes of the disputes that surrounded the covert wars of the 1980's and have shadowed his career ever since. News coverage of the fight against terror includes near-daily reports of abuse of detainees, of the C.I.A. secretly transporting terrorism suspects to foreign prisons, of politicized intelligence and partisan debate about how to protect American security while preserving American values.</p>
        <p>Respected by Democrats as well as Republicans for his preference for quiet negotiation over public grandstanding, his unfailing courtesy and his knowledge of foreign affairs, Mr. Negroponte has inspired loyalty from many former colleagues. They say he is no ideologue but a nonpartisan pragmatist, a tough American conservative with deep European roots.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Negroponte has become a lightning rod for liberal activists, led by those who opposed the Reagan-era Central American intervention as brutal and unnecessary and view the current Bush policy of pre-emption as a rerun. They say Mr. Negroponte carried out harsh orders then and fear he will carry out harsher orders now.</p>
        <p>Michael Ratner, president of the Center for Constitutional Rights in New York, called Mr. Negroponte's nomination ''scary as heck.'' Mr. Ratner recalled a cool reception when he pressed human rights concerns with Mr. Negroponte in Honduras two decades ago. Today Mr. Ratner is an advocate for more than 100 Iraqis who say they were tortured in American detention centers.</p>
        <p>''Then, the feeling was they could use any means necessary to defeat communism,'' Mr. Ratner said. ''Today, the belief is they can use any means necessary to defeat terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Charles Hill, a retired diplomat now at Yale University, sees a different parallel. During the 1980's and today, he said, some Americans wrongly focused on scattered abuses, failing to comprehend that ''strength and diplomacy have to be worked together'' to overcome tyranny and terrorism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hill finds the notion of Mr. Negroponte as a defender of torturers a preposterous caricature. ''He's the ideal person for this intelligence job,'' Mr. Hill said. ''He's intellectually courageous and honest. He's held his positions against all kinds of pressure.''</p>
        <p>The son of a Greek shipping executive -- the family name comes from the old name of a Greek island -- Mr. Negroponte was born in London and grew up on Park Avenue in Manhattan and on Long Island. He graduated from Phillips Exeter Academy and Yale (in the same class as Porter J. Goss, the director of central intelligence) and took ski vacations at the family's home in Switzerland. His friends say he is driven by ambition and a sense of public service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte left Harvard Law School to join the Foreign Service in 1960. By 1964, he was in Vietnam -- Vietnamese is among the five languages he speaks -- and would be immersed in the country over the next decade as an aide to Henry A. Kissinger in Saigon, Paris and Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte eventually broke with his mentor, arguing that Dr. Kissinger's peace treaty undercut the South Vietnamese. It was a rare rebellion, and it slowed his career. But he never went public.</p>
        <p>''John just said, 'I want out,' and went off to the embassy in Ecuador as economics officer,'' said Robert B. Oakley, who shared an office with him in Saigon. ''His approach has always been to work from within.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte arrived in Honduras in 1981 just as President Ronald Reagan authorized paramilitary operations against the leftist government of Nicaragua. Honduras became the base for the Nicaraguan opposition, known as the contras, and their C.I.A. supporters.</p>
        <p>This period has haunted Mr. Negroponte. Not only rights activists but also Jack R. Binns, Mr. Negroponte's predecessor as ambassador, have accused him of discouraging reporting to Washington of abductions, torture and killings by notorious Honduran military units.</p>
        <p>''I think he was complicit in abuses, I think he tried to put a lid on reporting abuses and I think he was untruthful to Congress about those activities,'' said Mr. Binns, now retired in Arizona.</p>
        <p>A 1997 report by the inspector general of the C.I.A. seemed to support the accusations, saying Mr. Negroponte was ''particularly sensitive'' about reporting abuses.</p>
        <p>He has rejected the charges, and the evidence is equivocal. In 2001, at his confirmation hearing for the United Nations job, Mr. Negroponte labeled the C.I.A. assertion ''absolutely false.'' He said that democracy was the best guarantor of both human rights and peace, and that he had tried to nourish Honduras's fledgling elected government while complaining privately of abuses.</p>
        <p>''Could I have been more vocal?'' Mr. Negroponte said. ''Well, you know, in retrospect perhaps I could have been.''</p>
        <p>Two former subordinates in Honduras say they heard Mr. Negroponte raise specific cases of abuse with Gen. Gustavo Alvarez Martinez, the hard-line military chief. ''I remember very difficult conversations with Alvarez on the treatment of prisoners,'' said Raymond F. Burghardt, political counselor from 1982 to 1984.</p>
        <p>What appears indisputable is that Mr. Negroponte played an active role in managing the contra war. ''Negroponte was a big supporter of the agency's covert action mission,'' said Mr. Clarridge, the C.I.A. veteran.</p>
        <p>Declassified records from 1983 show Mr. Negroponte asking Washington to authorize 3,000 weapons to be shipped secretly to Honduras to arm the contras.</p>
        <p>''What you have is an ambassador putting on a C.I.A. station chief's hat,'' said Peter Kornbluh of the National Security Archive at George Washington University. ''Some people might say this makes him more qualified for the new intelligence job.''</p>
        <p>Leo Valladares Lanza, a law professor who as Honduras's human rights commissioner investigated 184 ''disappearances'' in the early 1980's, said Mr. Negroponte made aiding the contras a far higher priority than preventing abuses.</p>
        <p>''I think he could have stopped all these assassinations and torture,'' Dr. Valladares said. Of the intelligence job, he added: ''We're against this nomination. If he didn't see human rights violations in Honduras, it's possible he won't see human rights violations anywhere in the world.''</p>
        <p>After his stint in Honduras, Mr. Negroponte held a series of less-prominent posts over the next dozen years. As an assistant secretary of state, he worked on AIDS, ozone and sea law. He served in the Reagan White House as deputy national security adviser. As ambassador to the United Nations, Mr. Negroponte pressed on foreign colleagues American intelligence on Iraqi weapons that turned out to be profoundly flawed.</p>
        <p>If he was miffed, Mr. Negroponte never spoke out. ''Colin Powell was the good soldier, and John Negroponte was the good soldier to the good soldier,'' said Sir Jeremy Greenstock, then British ambassador to the United Nations. Dispatched last July to Iraq, Mr. Negroponte worked closely with what intelligence officials describe as the largest C.I.A. station in the world. He was deliberately as inconspicuous in public as his predecessor with the Coalition Provisional Authority, L. Paul Bremer III, had been visible.</p>
        <p>''He was told to play a low-key role and let the Iraqis be out front,'' said Mr. Clarridge, the C.I.A. retiree. ''And that's what he likes to do, anyway.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte shifted more than $1 billion to build up the Iraqi Army from reconstruction projects, a move prompted by his experience with the frailty of the South Vietnamese Army, said Mr. Oakley, the former colleague from Vietnam.</p>
        <p>Before the Jan. 30 election, Mr. Negroponte also defeated a plan proposed by some officials to send political consultants to Iraq to try to head off too big a victory by religious Shiites, said Bernard Aronson, a former assistant secretary of state and an old friend. Mr. Negroponte ''had the courage to say no,'' arguing that American meddling could undermine the legitimacy of the vote, Mr. Aronson said.</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Negroponte's new intelligence position, two dozen current and former government officials interviewed agreed that the job is fraught with hazards.</p>
        <p>''You have a bureaucracy, and you put another bureaucracy on top of it, and you expect the bureaucracy on top to solve the problems of the bureaucracy below?'' said Fred C. Iklé, a former defense official who worked with Mr. Negroponte in the Reagan administration. ''Good luck to him!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
