<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renting a Green Car: French Fries, Anyone?</title>
    <meta content="25GREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/25/automobiles/25green.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1652563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="DRIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tsui, Bonnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Volkswagen AG</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DC173DF936A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renting a Green Car: French Fries, Anyone?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Renting a Green Car: French Fries, Anyone?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BONNIE TSUI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tsui, Bonnie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on renting cars run on biodiesel fuel, made solely from recycled vegetable oil, hybrid gasoline-electric cars and those run on electricity or natural gas while on vacation; list; drawing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST October, Suzy Smith was looking for a rental car with good mileage for a weeklong vacation in Maui. She searched for ''rental cars on Maui'' on Google and found Maui Bio-Beetle, a company that rents cars that run on biodiesel fuel. She didn't know what to expect from a vehicle that used fuel made solely from recycled vegetable oil, but decided to give it a chance.</p>
        <p>''It was fun!'' said Ms. Smith, who owns a conference-call business in Seattle. She ended up renting a Volkswagen Golf from Bio-Beetle for the week. ''The car had 'This vehicle powered by vegetable oil' written all over it, and people would stop and look and ask a million questions,'' she said. ''Every now and again when we stopped at a stoplight, we'd get a whiff of something like burned French fries, but other than that it was like driving a regular car.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In several places across the nation, it is possible to rent - by the hour, the day or the week - environmentally friendly cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST October, Suzy Smith was looking for a rental car with good mileage for a weeklong vacation in Maui. She searched for ''rental cars on Maui'' on Google and found Maui Bio-Beetle, a company that rents cars that run on biodiesel fuel. She didn't know what to expect from a vehicle that used fuel made solely from recycled vegetable oil, but decided to give it a chance.</p>
        <p>''It was fun!'' said Ms. Smith, who owns a conference-call business in Seattle. She ended up renting a Volkswagen Golf from Bio-Beetle for the week. ''The car had 'This vehicle powered by vegetable oil' written all over it, and people would stop and look and ask a million questions,'' she said. ''Every now and again when we stopped at a stoplight, we'd get a whiff of something like burned French fries, but other than that it was like driving a regular car.''</p>
        <p>Bio-Beetle is part of a growing trend in environmentally friendly rental cars and other forms of for-hire transportation. In several places across the nation, it is possible to rent -- by the hour, the day or the week -- hybrid gasoline-electric cars or cars that run on electricity, natural gas or, as in the case of Bio-Beetle's VW, vegetable oil.</p>
        <p>Fueling the car, Ms. Smith found, proved to be fairly easy, with a Pacific Biodiesel station in a convenient location near Kahului Airport in Maui. And it was cheaper, too. ''When we refueled to go back to the airport, the price of biodiesel was quite a bit less,'' Ms. Smith said, about $2.30 a gallon versus $2.69 on average for regular unleaded.</p>
        <p>High gas prices are another reason why renting green is an attractive option. These days, alternative rental car companies like Bio-Beetle Rental Cars, which opened branches in Maui and Oahu in 2003, are seeing a rise in business, and larger rental corporations around the country like Budget and Enterprise have added environmentally friendly cars -- mostly hybrid gas-electric vehicles like the Toyota Prius and the Honda Civic Hybrid -- to their own fleets. Though still a small segment of the economy, the market for green cars is attracting attention in the rental car industry.</p>
        <p>Given the popularity of vehicles like the Prius and the Civic Hybrid, it seems logical that companies like Enterprise -- with 5,400 locations, it's the largest rental car company in North America -- would add them to their fleets. And they have: in 2004, Enterprise had 2,700 Toyota Prius cars available for rent. But the shortage of cars available for sale is also limiting the numbers being sent to rental agencies. Enterprise had to return most of its Priuses after a few months, when its short-term lease on them expired, and by May the company will have none available.</p>
        <p>''PART of our strategy is to offer products that reflect the driving public and the interests of the consumer, and customers want environmentally friendly cars,'' said Christy Conrad, a spokeswoman for Enterprise. She said that Enterprise was looking into other fuel-efficient vehicles, but that most were not marketed widely enough for its nationwide rental operation. For example, special fuel might be available only in one part of a city or not available at all in another.</p>
        <p>But a local company like Bio-Beetle manages to avoid fueling problems because of Hawaii's restricted geography. Similarly, in places like San Francisco, where city traffic is heavy and parking is limited, it's not only possible but preferable to have a small, efficient car that can squeeze in anywhere.</p>
        <p>Electric Time Car Rentals at Fisherman's Wharf, a prime tourist attraction, rents the GEM -- Global Electric Motorcar -- made by DaimlerChrysler. The quirky-looking vehicles (most are open-sided and have no doors) have zero emissions, reach a top speed of about 25 miles an hour, and have electric batteries that last for two hours of constant driving, or about 20 miles of city terrain.</p>
        <p>''In the summer, all 27 of our cars will be out and turned over a few times a day,'' said Bryant Benson, operations manager for Electric Time, which opened two and a half years ago.</p>
        <p>''Fifty percent of our clientele are folks from out of town, and the other 50 percent live within an hour of the Bay Area. So lots of people come in via public transportation and then take our cars to tour around the city. They feel a lot closer to the sights with our cars.''</p>
        <p>A larger regional company, EV Rental Cars, has found perhaps the biggest success in the market by catering to green-thinking Californians. Based in Los Angeles, the company supplies rental-car companies with environmentally friendly vehicles, including the Toyota Prius, Honda Insight, Honda Civic (both the Hybrid and a natural-gas model) and the brand-new 2005 Ford Escape hybrid.</p>
        <p>The cars are now rented exclusively through Fox Rent a Car; also based in Los Angeles, Fox is an independent car rental company with 21 rental locations in 9 states. Fox began its agreement with EV Rental Cars on Jan. 15, and Joe Knight, vice president for business development at Fox, said that the company had already seen a big response.</p>
        <p>''Southern Californians are very green here,'' Mr. Knight said. ''We're seeing that people who reserve these hybrid vehicles make up a very passionate, serious clientele.''</p>
        <p>Currently, Fox has 260 environmentally friendly cars available in its Los Angeles, San Diego, Orange County and Phoenix airport locations, but plans to have them in 10 more locations by the end of the year. By that time, EV also plans to double the number of rental cars available to Fox, to almost 500.</p>
        <p>''I think the potential of renting green is enormous,'' said Shaun Stenshol, president of Bio-Beetle Cars. He has worked on renewable energy issues for a decade and found out about biodiesel fuel in 1996. ''I went seven years without owning a car because I didn't want to support an industry that, in my opinion, is the primary cause of pollution in the world. Biodiesel is a great renewable alternative that's available now, and I wanted to do what I could to promote it.''</p>
        <p>MR. STENSHOL'S company has six dedicated biodiesel vehicles (a seventh, a 2005 Jeep Liberty, will arrive next month). Each gets 30 to 45 miles a gallon, and rental rates are competitive, ranging from $199 to $283 a week.</p>
        <p>Fortunately for earth-sensitive travelers, the network for renting green is beginning to expand beyond rental cars, to auto clubs and public transportation. Billing itself as an environmentally friendly alternative to AAA, the Better World Club (www.triplee.com) provides 24-hour nationwide roadside assistance -- for bicyclists as well as motorists -- while offering its members 10 percent discounts on hybrid and electric car rentals. One percent of all revenues go to environmental projects, it says.</p>
        <p>PlanetTran (www.planettran.com), based in Cambridge, Mass., offers scheduled transportation, mostly to Logan Airport in Boston, in hybrid cars. PlanetTran's owner and founder, Seth Riney, said the company would be doubling its fleet to 10 cars by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The best bet for renting green, at least for now, is to look locally. But if the big drawback to widespread use of environmentally friendly cars is their availability, manufacturers might have to rethink their strategy. The act of renting out the cars may be the best way to promote green driving.</p>
        <p>David Koyle, a 59-year-old Maui resident who drives a Volkswagen Touareg, rented a Bio-Beetle for relatives to use when they visited him last year. ''After that, I'm thinking my next vehicle will be a hybrid,'' he said. ''I'm looking and watching and waiting for some of the hybrids to come out here to the market.''</p>
        <p>RENTALS  From Biodiesel To All-Electric</p>
        <p>GOING green does not require a lot of green. Rental rates for alternative-fuel cars are often competitive with those for gasoline-powered cars, which offer no eco-cachet. The problem is finding the cars. Here are some rental companies:</p>
        <p>BIO-BEETLE RENTALCARS -- Available for rent at Maui Car Rentals, (800) 567-4659, and on Oahu at Tradewinds U-Drive, (888) 388-7368. Rates at each are $199 a week; daily rates available. More information is at www.bio-beetle.com.</p>
        <p>ELECTRIC TIME CAR RENTALS -- In Anchorage Alley off Leavenworth Street at Fisherman's Wharf in San Francisco, (415) 788-4300, www.etcars.com. Electric car rentals are $38.88 for the first hour for two-seat models, and half that for each additional hour.</p>
        <p>FOX RENT A CAR -- Available at four locations in California and Arizona; (310) 641-3838, www.foxrentacar.com; hybrid cars from $35.99 a day, offered exclusively in partnership with EV Rental Cars, www.evrental.com.</p>
        <p>ZIPCAR -- A car-sharing service specializing in short-term reservations, including hybrids, in Boston, New York, Washington and Chapel Hill, N.C.; (866) 494-7227; www.zipcar.com. Hourly rates begin at $8.50 and daily rates from $59, including gas, insurance and parking.</p>
        <p>DRIVING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
