<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The War on the War on Drugs</title>
    <meta content="RV023307" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/24/movies/24drug.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1682682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Catsoulis, Jeannette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Soling, Cevin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">War On the War On Drugs, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">War on the War on Drugs, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D61F3BF937A15755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The War on the War on Drugs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">And Now for Something Completely Wacky</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEANNETTE CATSOULIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Catsoulis, Jeannette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeannette Catsoulis reviews movie The War on the War on Drugs, written and directed by Cevin Soling (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opens today in Manhattan  Directed by Cevin Soling  Not rated, 74 minutes</p>
        <p>Destined for instant pairing with the 1936 exploitation classic ''Reefer Madness'' on the midnight-movie circuit, ''The War on the War on Drugs'' gleefully takes aim at United States drug policy with ingenuity and heavily disguised logic. Already the proud winner of a best experimental feature award at the New York Independent Film and Video Festival, the movie is 74 minutes of hilarious pro-drug vignettes, loosely strung together like a themed episode of ''Saturday Night Live.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seventy-four minutes of hilarious pro-drug vignettes, loosely strung together like a themed episode of "Saturday Night Live."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opens today in Manhattan  Directed by Cevin Soling  Not rated, 74 minutes</p>
        <p>Destined for instant pairing with the 1936 exploitation classic ''Reefer Madness'' on the midnight-movie circuit, ''The War on the War on Drugs'' gleefully takes aim at United States drug policy with ingenuity and heavily disguised logic. Already the proud winner of a best experimental feature award at the New York Independent Film and Video Festival, the movie is 74 minutes of hilarious pro-drug vignettes, loosely strung together like a themed episode of ''Saturday Night Live.''</p>
        <p>Opening with the near-hysterical 1937 Congressional testimony of the first drug czar himself, Harry J. Anslinger -- crediting marijuana for everything from jazz to the immoderate sexual preferences of white women -- ''War'' is a hodgepodge of wildly different cinematic styles and influences. Parodying 1950's public service announcements, present-day infomercials and antidrug campaigns aimed at children and young adults, the film leaps from comedy skit to puppet show to mockumentary with a nimbleness that belies its cumbersome title. Frequently ribald and always irreverent, each segment argues that our current drug laws are nothing more than government-sponsored mind control, an argument not necessarily diminished by its nostalgic evocation of burning incense and Grace Slick.</p>
        <p>The writer-director Cevin Soling, who also composed much of the film's music, is heavily steeped in the surreal influences of shows like ''Monty Python's Flying Circus'' and ''Rowan and Martin's Laugh-In,'' and some of his sequences strain too hard for hipness. The film is most successful when standing on solid factual ground, and a section dealing with our weakened constitutional protections against illegal search and seizure is particularly effective.</p>
        <p>Much of the time, however, the facts are obfuscated by Mr. Soling's relentless need to entertain, leading to a riotous comparison of the government's D.A.R.E. program and the Hitler Youth movement. By the time he blames the Partnership for a Drug-Free America for every modern calamity, including Kurt Cobain's death and the hole in the ozone layer, you'll be laughing too hard to care that reason has left the building.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, ''The War on the War on Drugs'' is a lively and well-executed satire that sweetens its occasional truths with rebellious humor. You may not care about the disturbing facts of the drug war, but if you want to know how to bake the perfect hash brownie or find a dealer you can trust, this is the film for you.</p>
        <p>JEANNETTE CATSOULIS</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
