<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boys Who Died Lived 17 Hours In Car Trunk, Lawyer Says</title>
    <meta content="19camden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/19/nyregion/19camden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050720T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1688533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DD1F30F93AA25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boys Who Died Lived 17 Hours In Car Trunk, Lawyer Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boys Who Died Lived 17 Hours in Car Trunk, Lawyer Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN and JOHN HOLL</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three boys who suffocated in the trunk of a car last month were alive for at least 17 hours and maybe up to 33 hours after they became trapped, a lawyer who represents one of the families involved said on Monday.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, Peter M. Villari, said he spoke with officials from the Camden County prosecutor's office who told him that further autopsy reports had indicated that the children, who were found dead in a car trunk in the yard where they were last seen, were alive well into the search for them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The three boys who suffocated in the trunk of a car last month were alive for at least 17 hours and maybe up to 33 hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The three boys who suffocated in the trunk of a car last month were alive for at least 17 hours and maybe up to 33 hours after they became trapped, a lawyer who represents one of the families involved said on Monday.</p>
        <p>The lawyer, Peter M. Villari, said he spoke with officials from the Camden County prosecutor's office who told him that further autopsy reports had indicated that the children, who were found dead in a car trunk in the yard where they were last seen, were alive well into the search for them.</p>
        <p>The time of death has become a significant issue in the aftermath of the troubling deaths because none of the 150 police officers assigned to the search checked the trunk of a broken-down Toyota parked steps away from where the children were last seen. When one boy's father opened the trunk two days after they had disappeared, he discovered the three curled-up bodies inside. The authorities said the first autopsy reports did not indicate when the children had died.</p>
        <p>Many people in Camden were outraged that the police did not find the children sooner and were pressing the authorities to determine if the children could have been saved had the police looked into the trunk early on. The police have said they looked inside the car and underneath it, but never opened the trunk.</p>
        <p>The Camden authorities opened an internal investigation to determine what went wrong. That report is due next week. Several community groups have also vowed to open their own independent investigations to get to the bottom of the oversight.</p>
        <p>The new autopsy information, Mr. Villari said, puts the blame ''squarely on the shoulders of the police'' because it means that the children could have been found alive.</p>
        <p>''I think the numbers speak for themselves,'' he said. ''They were certainly alive when the police arrived and certainly well after the search started.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Villari also said officials in the prosecutor's office apologized to the parents and promised this would never happen again in Camden.</p>
        <p>Bill Shralow, a spokesman for the Camden County prosecutor's office, said that the official report was likely to be released soon and that he would not discuss it beforehand.Lt. Mike Lynch, a spokesman for the Camden Police Department, said he was asked by the prosecutor's office not to comment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villari represents the family of Anibal Cruz Jr., an 11-year-old who had a severe learning disability and was known as a sweet but hyperactive child. It was at his house in the Cramer Hill neighborhood of Camden that Anibal and two friends, Daniel Agosto, 6, and Jesstin Pagan, 5, were last seen alive around 5:30 p.m. on June 22 when relatives were watching them play in the yard.</p>
        <p>Two of the boys' mothers said they went inside for half an hour to cook dinner and when they returned the three boys had disappeared. The families searched for three hours before calling the police.</p>
        <p>Many residents in Camden have also blamed them for not calling the police sooner and for not checking the trunk of the car, where one of the boys (the police have yet to say which one) was known to have enjoyed playing. The boys were found dead around 6:30 p.m. on June 24.</p>
        <p>Investigators concluded that boys died accidentally after they climbed into the trunk while playing and became trapped when the lid slammed shut. Originally, the police thought the children might have drowned in the nearby Delaware River, and they devoted extensive resources to scour the waterfront.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villari -- who has said that he was looking into negligence lawsuits against the Camden authorities and possibly Toyota -- said the information indicated that at a minimum, the boys were alive until 10:30 a.m. on June 23; at a maximum until 2:30 a.m. on June 24. He said the autopsy reports that were shared with the families were based on examinations of fluid and tissue samples and weather-related data.</p>
        <p>Mr. Villari said that Anibal's mother, Elba Nelly Cruz, did not say much when told about the findings. ''She was numb,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some outside medical examiners had speculated that the boys would not have survived long in the car trunk because in their panic they would have sucked down the little air and quickly replaced it with noxious carbon dioxide gas from their hurried exhaling.</p>
        <p>But Cyril H. Wecht, the coroner of Allegheny County, Pa., and past president of the American Academy of Forensic Sciences, said weeks ago that the boys could have lived 12 hours or maybe longer because the trunk of an older car is hardly airtight. The car the boys were trapped in was a 1992 Toyota Camry that had not moved in weeks.</p>
        <p>When told of the new information on Monday, Dr. Wecht said it seemed to point to negligence.</p>
        <p>''There is no reason why that trunk should not have been checked,'' he said. ''This is what kids do. They crawl into things -- refrigerators, grandma's trunk in the attic, car trunks. It's a very obvious place to look.''</p>
        <p>One mystery, though, is if the three boys were alive that long, why nobody heard them struggling to get out of the trunk. The police and family members have been unable to answer that question. Or why numerous tracking dogs used in the search failed to pick up on a scent in the yard and follow it to the trunk.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wecht said the boys probably slipped into unconsciousness a few hours after they got trapped and eventually went into comas. They probably would have suffered some brain damage had they been found 6 to 12 hours later but it would not necessarily have been permanent.</p>
        <p>Keith Walker, a former mayoral candidate and Camden businessman who is part of one of the independent investigations, said the latest report implies incompetence.</p>
        <p>''They blew this thing,'' he said. ''They blew it big time.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 20, 2005, Wednesday  An article yesterday about new findings on the estimated time of death for three boys from Camden, N.J., who suffocated in a car trunk last month misstated the minimum number of hours that the boys had lived after becoming trapped, according to results of autopsy reports shared with a lawyer for the family of one boy. They had lived at least 13 hours, not 17. The article also misstated the earliest estimated time of death. It was 6:30 a.m. on June 23, not 10:30 a.m. An article about the community's reaction to the release of the new findings appears today on Page B7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 20, 2005, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about new findings on the estimated time of death for three boys from Camden, N.J., who suffocated in a car trunk last month misstated the minimum number of hours that the boys had lived after becoming trapped, according to results of autopsy reports shared with a lawyer for the family of one boy. They had lived at least 13 hours, not 17. The article also misstated the earliest estimated time of death. It was 6:30 a.m. on June 23, not 10:30 a.m. An article about the community's reaction to the release of the new findings appears today on Page B7.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
