<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About the Oceans, He Says Firmly, Attention Must Be Paid</title>
    <meta content="26PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/26/science/earth/26prof.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1667834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENTIST AT WORK: JEREMY JACKSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D81231F935A15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About the Oceans, He Says Firmly, Attention Must Be Paid</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">About the Oceans, He Says Firmly, Attention Must Be Paid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
      <dateline>BOCAS DEL TORO, Panama</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Jeremy Jackson is in an open boat, speeding across the waters of Laguna de Chiriquí, on the Caribbean coast of Panama. His graying red pony tail is frizzing and flapping in the wind, and he is gesticulating wildly, waving his long arms, his lanky frame twisted toward his fellow passengers.</p>
        <p>Shouting above the engine's roar, he is explaining how the ancient geology of the Panamanian isthmus helps explain its environment today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr. Jeremy Jackson is telling everyone around about a world slipping into ecological degradation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr. Jeremy Jackson is in an open boat, speeding across the waters of Laguna de Chiriquí, on the Caribbean coast of Panama. His graying red pony tail is frizzing and flapping in the wind, and he is gesticulating wildly, waving his long arms, his lanky frame twisted toward his fellow passengers.</p>
        <p>Shouting above the engine's roar, he is explaining how the ancient geology of the Panamanian isthmus helps explain its environment today.</p>
        <p>Just then two Guaymi Indians emerge from behind a mangrove-fringed island, paddling a small canoe carved from a tree trunk. Dr. Jackson's listeners turn to follow the men's progress. ''Hey!'' he shouts, clapping his hands. ''Pay attention!''</p>
        <p>Getting people to pay attention is Dr. Jackson's mission. In scientific journals, in talks at places as diverse as Unesco headquarters and the Monterey Bay Aquarium, Dr. Jackson is telling everyone around about a world slipping into ecological degradation.</p>
        <p>From the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in San Diego, where he directs the Geosciences Research Division, and the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, or STRI, where he has a part-time appointment, Dr. Jackson has deplored declines in coral reefs, the virtual disappearance of large marine fish and losses of coastal and marine ecosystems. He helped create a Web site, shiftingbaselines.org, to point out that the changes people saw in their 20th-century lifetimes were just small snapshots in a larger picture of environmental decline that has been accelerating for 200 years.</p>
        <p>In March, he and colleagues published a call to arms in the journal Science on behalf of the world's corals. In many areas, they say, ''degraded reefs are little more than rubble, seaweed and slime.''</p>
        <p>They called on scientists to stop arguing about the relative importance of overfishing, pollution, climate change and other causes of coral death and instead to work together to turn things around. And they told them how to do it, in an accompanying list of recommended actions.</p>
        <p>It is unusual for academic researchers to offer this kind of aggressive scolding. Generally, they steer clear of the messy realms of politics and policy, but that is Dr. Jackson's milieu these days.</p>
        <p>''He is a rock star,'' said Daniel P. Schrag, director of the Harvard Center for the Environment, who said he stopped eating farm-raised salmon after hearing Dr. Jackson thoroughly denounce aquaculture.</p>
        <p>''This is someone who has deep insight into food webs and physical and biological ocean processes and marine ecology, and a deep understanding of geological time,'' Dr. Schrag said. ''He looks at the modern record and the last few centuries of spectacular and terrifying decline with deep understanding.''</p>
        <p>Hearing Dr. Jackson describe the problems of the oceans made Dr. Schrag think about ways to tell people about climate, his own area of specialty. ''His ability to communicate what's going on inspired me,'' Dr. Schrag said. ''He's my hero.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jackson started down this road after Hurricane Allen struck Jamaica in 1980.</p>
        <p>By then he had worked his way through George Washington University, earned a doctorate in geology at Yale and achieved a tenured professorship at Johns Hopkins. After the hurricane, he was among experts who went to Jamaica to study its effects on corals. ''We wrote a quite well-known paper that was published in Science,'' he recalled. ''Everybody loved it. We predicted how the reef would recover, and we got it 100 percent wrong. It became obvious there were things going on that we did not understand.''</p>
        <p>A few years after that, working at STRI (rhymes with try), he found himself leading a study of the effects of an oil spill. Corals in the spill area were dying, he said, but corals elsewhere were dying, too. Again, he said, ''There was something going on.''</p>
        <p>That something, he decided, was ''the cumulative impact of people.'' He elaborated at a scientific meeting in 1993 in Miami, saying he feared the world's corals could not survive humanity's collective assaults. ''I got this supernegative reaction,'' he said, ''that I was a Cassandra.''</p>
        <p>So he and his wife, Dr. Nancy Knowlton, who now directs the Center for Marine Biodiversity and Conservation at Scripps but was then at STRI, organized a conference where Dr. Jackson challenged the scientists in his audience to think of what the reefs of the Caribbean had been like when Columbus saw them, and to compare that vision with what they were seeing. ''I swear, you could have heard a pin drop,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But delivering this kind of message to scientists was not enough, he decided, after he published a paper on catastrophic declines in fish populations. The paper was celebrated in scientific circles, he said, but his daughter brought him down to earth. ''She said, 'You know, Papa, no one at my school has ever heard of the problem of overfishing.'''</p>
        <p>That was what inspired him to help organize shiftingbaselines.org. Its aim, he said, is to convey important information with humor -- because ''people have only so much tolerance for dead fish.'' The site includes short films, a blog, links to studies and news articles, information on events relating to marine ecology and even a photo, produced by the site's co-founder Randy Olsen, showing what Mount Rushmore would look like if it represented the Jackson Five -- Jesse, Michael, Andrew, Shoeless Joe and Jeremy.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it was inevitable that if Jeremy Bradford Cook Jackson were a scientist, he would be a scientist with panache. He was born in 1942 in Louisville, Ky., and his parents separated shortly after his birth. He and his mother moved to Gramercy Park in New York, and she went to work in advertising. His biological father died at an early age and young Jeremy did not see much of his paternal relations, the Cooks, who trace the family from the Mayflower pilgrim William Bradford.</p>
        <p>Instead, he recalls childhood days with his mother's family, descendants of German and Russian Jewish immigrants. They were a quarrelsome and eccentric bunch, as Dr. Jackson describes them, artists and writers always ready to try something new.</p>
        <p>When he was still a boy, his mother married Melvin Jackson and the family settled in Miami, where his new father earned a doctorate in history and became a professor at the University of Miami. They lived among the writers and artists of Coconut Grove.</p>
        <p>''That's where I first met Marjory Stoneman Douglas,'' Dr. Jackson related, the naturalist most famous for ''The Everglades: River of Grass,'' her paean to the vast wilderness. ''I used to go to her birthday parties. She would escape from the crowd, and we would go for little walks. I remember her as this feisty, independent woman, really a mountain of information.''</p>
        <p>The description fits Dr. Jackson today. For example, when some researchers questioned the conclusions of the recent corals paper, he urged them to write sharp letters challenging it, seemingly relishing the fight.</p>
        <p>Colleagues say it is not easy to work with a person with such enthusiasm for argument, and such a robust ego. They describe him as ''difficult,'' or ''a cantankerous collaborator,'' or ''impossible,'' if not ''absolutely impossible.'' Once he gets involved in something, they say, he pushes it relentlessly, urging that his projects be given precedence over the claims of others.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jackson is a highly proficient scientist who ''tends to be intolerant of colleagues who don't see things the way he does,'' said Dr. Ira Rubinoff, who brought Dr. Jackson and Dr. Knowlton to STRI.</p>
        <p>''His big ego can be very hard to take,'' said Dr. Eldredge Bermingham, an evolutionary biologist who is deputy director of STRI, ''but I admire his research, I admire his passion and I admire his willingness to speak out.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jackson says he does not encounter the criticism meted out to many other scientists who speak out, in part because he continues to publish findings from the Panama Paleontology Project, which he co-founded in 1986, and which brought him to Laguna de Chiriquí, en route to an outcrop of fossil corals at Caya Agua, a remote island.</p>
        <p>In the last five years, Dr. Jackson has undergone arduous treatment for prostate cancer and for a melanoma that he said he diagnosed himself. He said he was considering retiring, in part because he would like to return to New York City, where his son from his first marriage is a chef, but also to spend more time ''writing and synthesizing.''</p>
        <p>But then, he said, he teaches a class or gives a talk and is buoyed by his reception. ''People say, 'What can I do?''' he said. ''I tell them, 'Become an informed citizen.'''</p>
        <p>Progress is slow, he added, but ''the fact that more attention is being paid to the oceans is good.''</p>
        <p>The Q&amp;A column appears today on Page 8.</p>
        <p>SCIENTIST AT WORK: JEREMY JACKSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
