<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Boat Haven, Soaring Fuel Costs Bring Subtle Changes</title>
    <meta content="05boats" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/05/national/05boats.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1699814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Seattle Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle (Wash)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3DC1531F936A3575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Boat Haven, Soaring Fuel Costs Bring Subtle Changes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Boat Haven, Soaring Fuel Costs Bring Subtle Changes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW; David Carrillo Penaloza contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Sept. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The necklace of lakes and waterways that surround and flow through this city are giant playgrounds at this time of year as Seattle's short season of sun is ending.</p>
        <p>Tall masts rising from docked sailboats clank and chime in the wind, a summer ballad on quiet nights along Lake Washington. Motorboats zoom across Lake Union, ferrying giddy sun worshipers and seafaring sorts who live through months of darkness and rain for these clear but numbered days on the open water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEATTLE, Sept. 3 - The necklace of lakes and waterways that surround and flow through this city are giant playgrounds at this time of year as Seattle's short season of sun is ending.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The necklace of lakes and waterways that surround and flow through this city are giant playgrounds at this time of year as Seattle's short season of sun is ending.</p>
        <p>Tall masts rising from docked sailboats clank and chime in the wind, a summer ballad on quiet nights along Lake Washington. Motorboats zoom across Lake Union, ferrying giddy sun worshipers and seafaring sorts who live through months of darkness and rain for these clear but numbered days on the open water.</p>
        <p>So if there is one place right now where gasoline consumers are not feeling completely panicked over the fast-rising price of fuel, it might be the gas station at Morrison's North Star Marine on Lake Union, where Randy Jones, 55, affably paid $1,167 the other afternoon to fill half the tank of his 40-foot Tollycraft. The 20-year-old vessel gets the kind of mileage -- precisely one mile per gallon at cruising speed -- that makes a sport utility vehicle look as fuel efficient as a bicycle.</p>
        <p>Cruising around Seattle is ''a fascinating feeling,'' said Mr. Jones, the owner of a marketing company, who plans to permanently move onto the boat, the Dixie Ann, with his wife, Jan, in October, and dock it at Lake Union. ''It's like you're in a different world.''</p>
        <p>David Morrison, the owner of the Lake Union fuel dock, said this has been ''one of my busiest summers in years,'' despite charging boater owners $3.89 per gallon, a 40-cent increase in the wake of Hurricane Katrina. Still, boat dealers say they are seeing signs that higher fuel prices are taking a toll.</p>
        <p>Seattle, according to city officials, has more pleasure craft per capita than any other United States city, and in the summer, Mr. Morrison is always swamped.</p>
        <p>The average-size boat, about 22-feet, burns six to eight gallons of gasoline per hour, depending on speed, according to the Northwest Marine Trade Association, an industry group based here. Larger boats, like Mr. Jones's, which can burn up to 24 gallons an hour, use far more.</p>
        <p>''The prices deter me, but I'm a boater, so what can I do?'' said Devon Pulvino, a contractor who owns a 22-foot Bayliner and said he was spending about $50 on gasoline each weekend.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pulvino, 28, who was heading out for an early evening cruise around Lake Union, added, ''You have to take advantage, regardless of the gas prices. I have about a month and however many days until perpetual darkness.''</p>
        <p>Several boater owners and boat dealers said they had noticed people taking shorter trips this summer and going at slower speeds to save money on gas. Mr. Jones said he had been slowing the Dixie Ann down from its usual cruising speed of 14 knots, to 7 or 8 knots, saving several gallons of gas per hour.</p>
        <p>''If they already have a boat, they are not going as far and they are not going as fast,'' said Robbie Robinson, president of Signature Yachts, which says it is the largest dealer of sailboats in the Pacific Northwest. ''A significant number of people are staying local as opposed to going to Alaska or Canada.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson also said he had seen a number of customers seeking to trade in motorboats for sailboats.</p>
        <p>Boat owners have also begun overhauling their vessels so they can use diesel fuel, industry experts say, which is considered less harmful to the environment than gasoline.</p>
        <p>Officials with a new Seattle boat dealer, the Electric Boat Company, which began selling electrically powered boats in the last year and a half, said business had been brisk, as consumers expressed concerns both about the price of gasoline and about the environmental impact of gas-powered boats on the wildlife and general health of the region's lakes and on Puget Sound.</p>
        <p>Marine uses, including pleasure craft, account for less than 1 percent of gasoline consumption, according to Northwest Environment Watch, an advocacy group, which cited the latest data from the United States Department of Transportation.</p>
        <p>According to Eric de Place, a senior research associate for the advocacy group, marine gasoline released 10.76 million tons of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere nationally in 2003, about the equivalent of the emissions from 1.5 million cars.</p>
        <p>In 1999, the Union of Concerned Scientists, in a book titled ''The Consumer's Guide to Effective Environmental Choices,'' said that while there are far fewer motorboats on the water than cars on the road, the average marine engine ''causes considerably more environmental damage than a car engine for each hour it operates.''</p>
        <p>Seattle officials said the city was contemplating ways to measure the emissions of pleasure boats and supported the use of biodiesel for motorboats. Biodiesel is a biodegradable fuel made from farm produce and other vegetable oils that pollutes less than either gasoline or standard diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>A growing number of motorboat manufacturers are beginning to offer that option for pleasure craft, and Seattle has worked with the shipping, bus and ferry industry here to move some larger vessels and vehicles toward using biodiesel, said Steve Nicholas, director of the city's Office of Sustainability and Environment.</p>
        <p>Neither environmental concerns nor the rising price of gasoline have dampened the seafaring spirits of Albert Clement, 41, the owner of a computer service and parts company who bought his first boat this year, a 28-foot Bayliner. He itches to hit the water and savor the last long days of summer.</p>
        <p>''Mine is not a high-end boat; I'm not a high-end person,'' Mr. Clement said. ''But it's my first year, and I'm all over it.''</p>
        <p>Seattle Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
