<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unfinished Business</title>
    <meta content="CIlegacy05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1727448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5DB1530F936A15751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unfinished Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmental and energy issues have been near the top of Gov. George Pataki's agenda since the day he took office. His stewardship of this week's groundbreaking agreement among seven Northeastern states to limit greenhouse gases from power plants -- a welcome antidote to the Bush administration's negativism at the recent global warming conference in Montreal -- is only the latest in a string of progressive achievements.</p>
        <p>But his record will be considerably enhanced if he can win Senate approval of three measures that nearly everyone except a small band of Republicans, including the Senate majority leader, Joseph Bruno, seems to want.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Environmental and energy issues have been near the top of Gov. George Pataki's agenda since the day he took office. His stewardship of this week's groundbreaking agreement among seven Northeastern states to limit greenhouse gases from power plants -- a welcome antidote to the Bush administration's negativism at the recent global warming conference in Montreal -- is only the latest in a string of progressive achievements.</p>
        <p>But his record will be considerably enhanced if he can win Senate approval of three measures that nearly everyone except a small band of Republicans, including the Senate majority leader, Joseph Bruno, seems to want.</p>
        <p>Advocacy groups have been calling these measures Super Bills to increase their visibility. All three passed the Democratic-controlled State Assembly in the last session; not one made it to the Senate floor. They are:</p>
        <p>The Clean Water Protection/Flood Prevention Act, which would provide protection for smaller wetlands that are now vulnerable to development because of loopholes in state and federal law. Mr. Bruno has said that present wetlands law is protective enough. His critics suspect that the real reason for his opposition is his fealty to builders, real estate companies and other special interests.</p>
        <p>The Community Preservation Act, aimed at helping communities resist sprawl by protecting open space and farmland. The same special interests that opposed the wetlands measure kept this one off the Senate calendar. The bill would allow communities to tax themselves to acquire open space; Mr. Bruno argues, unconvincingly, that the higher taxes could depress house prices.</p>
        <p>The Bigger, Better Bottle Bill, an enhanced bottle-redemption law that would embrace noncarbonated beverages, like water and fruit juice, and steer unclaimed deposits to the state treasury to underwrite other useful programs, like municipal recycling. Mr. Bruno voted against the original bottle bill and described Assembly passage of this bill as ''one of the dumbest things that has happened this year.''</p>
        <p>Finally, and as a general matter, Governor Pataki should push for an sizable increase in the state's Environmental Protection Fund. Despite his efforts, New York lags many other states in per capita spending on environmental programs.</p>
        <p>It is not as if the Legislature is incapable of passing good legislation. A complex and contentious measure requiring higher efficiency standards on a wide range of appliances and electronic devices was approved by both houses in June and signed by the governor in July. But further progress will require the governor's personal intervention. He needs to act like a leader, not the lame duck he could so easily become.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
