<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Cover</title>
    <meta content="1106cover" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/06/arts/television/tv-storm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1715586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7DB143EF935A35752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Cover</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Category 7': The Film Before the Storm</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Eiffel Tower and Mount Rushmore are both obliterated before the first commercial break of ''Category 7: The End of the World,'' a two-part killer-storm drama that begins tonight on CBS, but they are not so much victims of the weather as they are victims of the ladies of Wisteria Lane.</p>
        <p>''We do start off with a bang,'' admitted Robert M. Sertner, one of the film's executive producers. ''You know what I blame that on? 'Desperate Housewives.'''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CBS's two-part killer-storm drama defies disaster-film conventions by having major destruction right off the bat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Eiffel Tower and Mount Rushmore are both obliterated before the first commercial break of ''Category 7: The End of the World,'' a two-part killer-storm drama that begins tonight on CBS, but they are not so much victims of the weather as they are victims of the ladies of Wisteria Lane.</p>
        <p>''We do start off with a bang,'' admitted Robert M. Sertner, one of the film's executive producers. ''You know what I blame that on? 'Desperate Housewives.'''</p>
        <p>The mini-series, showing in two-hour blocks tonight and next Sunday, goes head to head with ABC's popular nighttime soap opera. Mr. Sertner said he purposely defied disaster-film conventions by having major destruction (and major special effects) right off the bat because he wanted to catch those viewers who sit with the remote control in hand, ready to switch channels at the first hint of boredom.</p>
        <p>''You just can't stop, or you lose them,'' Mr. Sertner said.</p>
        <p>In fact, the calamity doesn't stop -- the series certainly lives up to its subtitle, as city after city is destroyed by ultrapowerful storms (a consequence, it turns out, of global warming). And if the special effects don't keep viewers tuned in, perhaps the eerie echoes of real life will. The series begins with Gina Gershon abruptly taking over the ineffective Federal Emergency Management Agency, though it was written long before the New Orleans debacle that cost Michael Brown his real FEMA job. And the story is bound to remind viewers of the pileup of natural disasters that has dominated the headlines recently. ''It's as if we all had crystal balls on our desks,'' Mr. Sertner said.</p>
        <p>The series was being filmed in Winnipeg even while Hurricane Katrina was developing. At one point it depicts a hurricane hitting Florida, and Ms. Gershon particularly remembers a fortuitous last-minute change in her dialogue for the scene.</p>
        <p>''There was a line that was cut out -- I said, 'Can you imagine what this would do to New Orleans?''' she recalled. ''The next day, New Orleans happened.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gershon said she was a bit worried that the film was accidentally so topical that it would seem as if it were exploiting the real-life suffering. Mr. Sertner, though, said he thought any such complaint would be headed off by the sheer outlandishness of the tale. The storms are deliberately over the top and so are some of the characters, like Tornado Tommy, a wild-eyed storm-chaser played by Randy Quaid.</p>
        <p>''It's not 'Katrina: The Movie,''' Mr. Sertner said. ''It's a roller coaster ride that's intended as entertainment.'' The audience, he said, is smart enough to know the difference.</p>
        <p>NEIL GENZLINGER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
