<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Northport's Dirty Burden</title>
    <meta content="LI--Energy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/21/opinion/nyregionopinions/LI_Energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1696251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Long Island Power Authority</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Schumer, Charles E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DC133EF932A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Northport's Dirty Burden</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Northport's Dirty Burden</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Northport's tidy downtown there is a little flower garden tucked into a parking lot. The blossoms are so luscious, it is possible to ignore the ugly metal sign that looms above them and defaces the tableau like a pimple on a lover's nose: VOLUNTEERS CREATED THIS VISUAL DELIGHT. BREAKING -- REMOVING -- DEMEANS THEIR EFFORT.</p>
        <p>This shrill nag's lament is a small-bore reminder that few things are so ugly or unpleasant they can't be overlooked. Out on the edge of Northport is an example far more monumental -- the dirtiest, nastiest power plant for hundreds of miles around. To those who live, work, sleep, swim, sail and fish in their long shadows, the towering stacks of the Long Island Power Authority's Northport plant are a familiar fact of life, a geographic benchmark the way the Twin Towers used to be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>KeySpan and the Long Island Power Authority need to commit to cleaning the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Northport's tidy downtown there is a little flower garden tucked into a parking lot. The blossoms are so luscious, it is possible to ignore the ugly metal sign that looms above them and defaces the tableau like a pimple on a lover's nose: VOLUNTEERS CREATED THIS VISUAL DELIGHT. BREAKING -- REMOVING -- DEMEANS THEIR EFFORT.</p>
        <p>This shrill nag's lament is a small-bore reminder that few things are so ugly or unpleasant they can't be overlooked. Out on the edge of Northport is an example far more monumental -- the dirtiest, nastiest power plant for hundreds of miles around. To those who live, work, sleep, swim, sail and fish in their long shadows, the towering stacks of the Long Island Power Authority's Northport plant are a familiar fact of life, a geographic benchmark the way the Twin Towers used to be.</p>
        <p>But they are generally not, in the public imagination, seen as an eyesore or a curse. A report from a coalition of New York environmental groups earlier in the month, exposing the Northport plant as the second-most-polluting in all the Northeast, did not send villagers to the barricades. They went on with their lives, as if 5.2 million metric tons of carbon dioxide -- the plant's annual output, second in the Northeast only to a decrepit plant in Massachusetts -- were nothing to get upset about .</p>
        <p>It took United States Senator Charles E. Schumer to raise the alarm, in a news conference at which he pressed KeySpan, which owns the Northport plant and two others on Long Island, and LIPA, which buys KeySpan's power, to upgrade the plant, which runs, dirtily and inefficiently, on oil and natural gas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schumer pointed out that investing in cleaner-burning technology would reduce greenhouse gases, increase power output and lower utility bills -- a ''triple win'' for Long Islanders, he said. But LIPA officials said they had higher priorities for now, including building a windmill farm off the South Shore as a crucial step in the long march away from fossil fuels. A KeySpan official, to his credit, seconded Mr. Schumer's point and said that moving swiftly to overhaul the plant -- the senator wants a plan in place by the end of the year -- was a sensible goal.</p>
        <p>We hope KeySpan is serious. Alternative energy is an important long-range priority, but global warming and the health risks from air pollution are immediate threats. The authors of the power plant report said that the prevalence of outdated, heavily polluting power plants in the Northeast underscores the vital importance of the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative, a nascent effort among nine Northeastern states to develop a cap-and-trade system to limit global-warming pollution from power plants. Cleaning up the dirtiest handful of aging plants would go a long way to achieving this goal.</p>
        <p>KeySpan and LIPA have done a good job of keeping up with Long Island's rising appetite for energy -- particularly during this long, hot summer. This short-term success is matched by a long-term campaign to develop more power cables and gas pipelines while promoting energy conservation and exploring forms of renewable power, like windmills. That effort needs to be matched by an equal commitment to cleaning the air.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
