<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayors Seek Regional Plan On Power Plant Gas Emissions</title>
    <meta content="25air" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/25/nyregion/25air.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1697136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Delaware</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Maine</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Massachusetts</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DC1E3EF936A1575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayors Seek Regional Plan On Power Plant Gas Emissions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mayors Seek Regional Plan on Power Plant Gas Emissions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mayors of more than 40 cities in the Northeast have urged the governors of New York and eight other states to quickly adopt a regional plan to regulate greenhouse gases that contribute to global warming, saying in a letter yesterday that climate change ''poses significant threat to the people and communities of the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>Officials in the nine states released a general outline of the plan, called the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative. While state officials have given it preliminary approval, some specifics are still unresolved, especially those involving the eventual cost to consumers. They need to be ironed out before the plan can go back to the individual states for legislative or regulatory approval, a process that could begin early next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mayors of more than 40 cities in the Northeast have urged the governors of New York and eight other states to quickly adopt a regional plan to regulate greenhouse gases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mayors of more than 40 cities in the Northeast have urged the governors of New York and eight other states to quickly adopt a regional plan to regulate greenhouse gases that contribute to global warming, saying in a letter yesterday that climate change ''poses significant threat to the people and communities of the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>Officials in the nine states released a general outline of the plan, called the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative. While state officials have given it preliminary approval, some specifics are still unresolved, especially those involving the eventual cost to consumers. They need to be ironed out before the plan can go back to the individual states for legislative or regulatory approval, a process that could begin early next year.</p>
        <p>The plan -- the first of its kind in the nation -- stabilizes carbon dioxide emissions from power plants in the nine states at roughly the current levels from 2009 through 2015, then calls for reductions reaching 10 percent by 2020. It also establishes a market system for trading emissions allowances.</p>
        <p>''We have to have leadership, and if it's not coming from the federal government we need it from the states and we need it from the cities,'' said Carolyn K. Peterson of Ithaca, N.Y., one of the 42 mayors who signed the letter. ''Small changes in the smallest of cities to the largest of cities are going to make a difference because we can show that change will work,'' she said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The mayors sent the letter yesterday to the governors of Connecticut, Delaware, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York, Rhode Island and Vermont, all participants in the Northeastern agreement.</p>
        <p>Most of the mayors who signed the letter represent small-to medium-size cities. Clean Air-Cool Planet, the environmental group that coordinated the effort, said it had not yet received a response from Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg. Earlier this year, however, the mayor did join a bipartisan national coalition of more than 130 mayors committed to fighting global warming on a local level.</p>
        <p>One principal sticking point in the plan, according to several people who have participated in or monitored the negotiations, appears to be how to allocate pollution allowances that generating companies will need to operate power plants that emit carbon dioxide. Experts believe that if this area is handled in an innovative way, the final cost to consumers could be minimal.</p>
        <p>In Europe and other areas using this system, emissions are capped and the companies that operate electric generators are given allowances to collectively emit carbon dioxide--the main greenhouse gas--at levels that do not exceed the established cap. Companies that do not use all their allowances can sell them to competitors.</p>
        <p>In an innovative change, officials of the Northeastern states are considering selling 20 percent or more of the allowances. Doing so would raise money to subsidize low-income ratepayers and otherwise offset higher costs caused by the emissions caps.</p>
        <p>The money raised by selling allowances could also be used to support innovative technology and reductions in energy consumption, which would not reduce rates but would benefit consumers in other ways.</p>
        <p>Sonny Popowsky, the consumer advocate of Pennsylvania, said that electricity rates could go up in the short run by 5 to 10 percent for residential customers when the regional program goes into effect in 2009. Pennsylvania is not one of the nine states in the regional pact, but it has been participating in meetings as an official observer and may eventually join. Maryland and the District of Columbia, along with several provinces in Eastern Canada, have also been official observers.</p>
        <p>The future rate increase ''is not going to be something that will require people to change their lifestyle,'' Mr. Popowsky said, ''but it really depends on what the states do with allowances and how they can be used.''</p>
        <p>Electric power companies have resisted the sale of allowances, arguing that it would put those companies in the region at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
        <p>''A plan like this has the potential to have a major impact on electricity prices,'' said Dan Riedinger, a spokesman for the Edison Electric Institute, which represents electric power companies.</p>
        <p>The companies are also concerned about proposed restrictions limiting their ability to import power from dirtier coal-fired plants in states outside the regional pact, which is still under discussion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
