<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Climate Debate: Incremental Gains</title>
    <meta content="11climate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/11/international/americas/11climate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1724230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5D61131F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Climate Debate: Incremental Gains</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Glacial Gains in Global Talks on Cleaner Air</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, Dec. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where do they go from here?</p>
        <p>Ever since the first international meeting on the changing atmosphere in 1988, negotiations over what to do about rising levels of heat-trapping smokestack and tailpipe gases have proceeded at a pace similar to that of climate change itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United Nations conference on climate change ended with only a modest agreement to keep talking about how to proceed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Where do they go from here?</p>
        <p>Ever since the first international meeting on the changing atmosphere in 1988, negotiations over what to do about rising levels of heat-trapping smokestack and tailpipe gases have proceeded at a pace similar to that of climate change itself.</p>
        <p>The two-week United Nations conference that ended here on Saturday was no exception. And as the delegates return to their own countries, with modest, last-minute agreements to keep talking about how to move beyond existing environmental treaties, many scientists and others who keep track of climate change say much more urgent action is needed.</p>
        <p>Summing up that view, James Hansen, director of NASA's Goddard Institute for Space Studies, said at a conference in San Francisco this week that a continuation of ''business as usual'' would result in so much warming as to ''constitute a different planet.''</p>
        <p>He said that a host of actions could be taken now to keep the temperature increase out of the danger zone, including big cuts in emissions of methane, a greenhouse gas emitted by everything from pipeline leaks to landfills, and shifts to more efficient vehicle designs.</p>
        <p>But he and other experts who see warming as a threat have begun to worry that existing efforts, both within and outside of international agreements, may not work in time.</p>
        <p>In Montreal, progress was measured in the tiniest of increments. It was really two meetings in one, aimed limiting global warming under a pair of separate but related international agreements -- the 1992 Framework Convention on Climate Change and its offspring document, the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>The first pact, in force for 189 countries, has voluntary goals for cutting emissions that were exceeded long ago.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto agreement, an addendum to the convention agreement that took effect this year, added binding, measurable targets and timetables for cutting emissions, but just for the three dozen industrialized countries of nearly 160 nations in all, that ratified it.</p>
        <p>In Montreal, the parties to the Kyoto treaty, under pressure mainly from Europe and environmental groups, agreed to start talking about what comes after its terms expire in 2012.</p>
        <p>But they did not set a hard deadline, only a goal of finishing talks ''as soon as possible'' so that new restrictions -- if they agree on any -- take effect right after the old ones expire.</p>
        <p>The United States, which has not ratified Kyoto, spent much of the meeting opposing language aimed at starting fresh talks on ways to increase the effectiveness of the original Framework Convention.</p>
        <p>In the wee hours of Saturday morning, the United States finally agreed to allow new discussions, but only after everyone consented to a huge escape clause saying any talks will be ''open and nonbinding,'' and ''will not open any negotiations leading to new commitments.''</p>
        <p>Developing countries, which have always been excused from any obligations under both treaties, showed hints that they might be willing to help in the fight to cut emissions, although with no firm targets.</p>
        <p>Then the gavel cracked at dawn.</p>
        <p>In subsequent news conferences, weary warriors from the talks, including Margaret Beckett, Britain's environment minister and head of the European Union delegation, proclaimed success, saying that a bigger, subtler shift had occurred behind the scenes -- a shift in tone from obstruction to cooperation -- particularly among poorer countries.</p>
        <p>''For those who actually take part in these negotiations this is a substantial achievement,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She said the Kyoto treaty has created markets for carbon credits, which are earned by cutting emissions, that would now expand to developing countries under several agreements completed in Montreal. That should be an engine promoting energy efficiency and innovations, she said.</p>
        <p>''There is growing recognition of the costs of not taking action,'' Mrs. Beckett said, ''and of the opportunities that come with taking action itself.''</p>
        <p>But an enormous roadblock remains: the continuing standoff between the largest developing nations, China and India, and the established industrial giants.</p>
        <p>The developing countries have repeatedly refused to commit themselves to greenhouse-gas limits until the established industrial states make meaningful progress. By contrast, the United States, the biggest source of the heat-trapping gases, insists on movement from these emerging economic competitors before it considers cuts.</p>
        <p>While the United States Senate passed a resolution earlier this year calling for mandatory limits, the House has shown no signs of movement. As Senator John McCain, the Arizona Republican who has been pushing for modest curbs on greenhouse gases, put it in a recent interview, ''Democracy isn't very good at addressing incremental problems.''</p>
        <p>Groups of scientists and engineers have called for far more aggressive investments in research on new technologies that could generate energy without emissions.</p>
        <p>But investments on that scale are unlikely to come without a big shift in national priorities, which are still focused more on homeland security than energy security.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, emissions have risen, and so has the globe's average temperature. It reached a temporary modern peak in 1998 when the Pacific Ocean had one of its periodic natural hot spells, El Niño.</p>
        <p>Now, even with no Niño in sight, 2005 is nearly a sure bet to be the warmest year in recorded history, Dr. Hansen said.</p>
        <p>One of the other achievements listed by the negotiators as the conference ended was a new financial contribution to a pot of money for developing countries -- to help them adapt to warming.</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
