<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's the Bushes And Clintons, Finding Ground In Common</title>
    <meta content="21clinton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/21/nyregion/21clinton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1791703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DB1131F932A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's the Bushes And Clintons, Finding Ground In Common</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It’s the Bushes and Clintons, Finding Common Ground</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK HEALY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Healy, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not often that you see a current American president and his predecessor in New York City, on the same morning, trying to foster peace in the Muslim world, and trying to burnish their own legacies as statesmen.</p>
        <p>Nor is it common to have the wife of one of them on hand to help out the other guy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was another day in the intriguing world of BushClinton as members of both families had pleasant run-ins during a United Nations conference in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not often that you see a current American president and his predecessor in New York City, on the same morning, trying to foster peace in the Muslim world, and trying to burnish their own legacies as statesmen.</p>
        <p>Nor is it common to have the wife of one of them on hand to help out the other guy.</p>
        <p>But there was President Bush meeting with the Palestinian president, Mahmoud Abbas, at the Waldorf-Astoria. And there was former President Bill Clinton convening a conference on global concerns at a nearby Sheraton, and listening to President Pervez Musharraf of Pakistan chastise Pope Benedict XVI for the pope's remarks about Islam. And there was the first lady, Laura Bush, giving the Clinton conclave some juice by announcing a new project to deliver clean water to 10 million Africans by 2010.</p>
        <p>Mr. Musharraf, echoing an old slogan of Mr. Clinton's, could have been reflecting the ethos of the Midtown diplomacy -- not to mention the Bushes and the Clintons -- when he told the conference that in dealing with all religious faiths, ''This is a time to build bridges and not burn bridges.''</p>
        <p>In truth, it was just another day in the intriguing world of BushClinton (or ClintonBush, if you will): A world in which a Bush presidency begat a Clinton presidency that begat a Bush presidency that may lead to -- well, one can speculate. In this world, the former presidents named Bush and Clinton are apparently thick as thieves, while son Bush and wife Clinton are regularly at odds over the geopolitical issues under discussion yesterday.</p>
        <p>Certainly, though, no one was calling a Bush (or a Clinton) a devil as the two families overlapped at Mr. Clinton's conference. President Bush and Mr. Clinton had a pleasant-looking run-in at the United Nations on Tuesday afternoon, and Mr. Clinton warmly welcomed Mrs. Bush to his conference dais yesterday to announce the $10 million federal commitment for the water project.</p>
        <p>She did so in front of an audience of hundreds of officials from developed and undeveloped nations, who first sat and listened to a list of Bush administration goals to support the third world. If there were Bush skeptics in the room, they were politely silent, and Mr. Clinton was beaming like a proud presidential spouse as he sat and listened to Mrs. Bush champion her husband's agenda.</p>
        <p>The major speakers at the conference were a little less love-soaked and a good bit more opinionated, apparently to the applauding audience's delight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Musharraf took the lead as news-making head of state. He said ''a lot of tensions in the Muslim world'' were caused by the furor involving Pope Benedict XVI's citation of a medieval text saying some of Muhammad's teachings were ''evil and inhuman.'' Mr. Musharraf added that the pope's remarks ''were most unwarranted.''</p>
        <p>''It is a time for interfaith harmony,'' Mr. Musharraf said later in the conference session. No one has the right, he continued, ''to hurt anybody else's feelings, least of all at this time.''</p>
        <p>Referring to Muslims, Mr. Musharraf added: ''The world thinks that we don't believe in democracy, we don't believe in modernization, we don't believe in secularism. Let me assure this house that Islam in theory believes in all of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Musharraf also said the continued presence of American troops in Afghanistan was contributing to the resurgence of the Taliban and was intensifying instability there.</p>
        <p>''They are coming back because of the presence of foreign troops,'' he said. ''There certainly is an antipathy to foreign presence in Afghanistan.''</p>
        <p>The Pakistani leader emphasized that in his view, the conflict between the Israeli and Palestinian governments remained the greatest threat to security and political stability in Iraq, Afghanistan, Pakistan and Lebanon.</p>
        <p>''It lies at the core of everything,'' he said. ''We must not open new fronts -- we must start closing fronts.''</p>
        <p>Javier Solana, the foreign policy chief of the European Union, said he believed that ''the Clinton parameters are still probably the best solution'' to bringing peace to the Middle East, referring to the former president's aggressive diplomacy to mediate the Israeli-Palestinian disputes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solana also said clashes of ideology, religion, politics and economics went beyond the Israeli and Palestinian governments.</p>
        <p>''The divide that persists in the world is more profound than we think, and we better be aware of that,'' he said. ''It's not getting smaller, but growing.''</p>
        <p>In remarks that seemed aimed at the news media, Mr. Solana also warned that the West should not carelessly provoke Muslims even in the spirit of free speech and open thought. He made the comment when asked about the newspaper cartoons lampooning Muhammad last winter that led to a spasm of violence worldwide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that so far he had secured more than $2 billion in ''commitments'' from businesses and others to help address the themes of his conference: energy and climate change; mitigating religious and ethnic conflict; alleviating poverty; and global health.</p>
        <p>The conference, known as the Clinton Global Initiative, lined up $2.5 billion from 300 sponsors last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
