<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wal-Mart Flirts With Being Green</title>
    <meta content="22online" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/22/business/22online.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1756075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grist.org</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daily Telegraph (London)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Business for Diplomatic Action</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Big Ox (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Failedsuccess.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Little, Amanda Griscom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, H Lee Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherwell, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blogs and Blogging (Internet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DC153FF931A15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wal-Mart Flirts With Being Green</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wal-Mart Flirts With Being Green</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Online column; Amanda Griscom Little, on grist.org, in introduction to Q and A session with Wal-Mart chief executive H Lee Scott, applauds company for joining call by group of energy executives for caps on greenhouse-gas emissions; Philip Sherwell, on Daily Telegraph Web site, says State Department and Business for Diplomatic Action will issue World Citizens Guide that will offer etiquette tips to American business travelers; Big Ox Web page claims that canned oxygen displaces harmful free radicals' and detoxifies blood; article on failedsuccess.com disputes claims and warns that pure oxygen can be dangerous or even deadly; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sheer magnitude of Wal-Mart's plans to become more environmentally friendly has been enough to give pause to all but the most vehement of the company's critics.</p>
        <p>The online environmental magazine Grist gave soft applause to Wal-Mart last week in its introduction to a Q. and A. session with H. Lee Scott Jr., the chief executive. When the company this month signed on to a call by a group of energy executives for caps on greenhouse-gas emissions, ''the heart of this monolithic retail Grinch grew three sizes that day,'' writes Amanda Griscom Little, a Grist reporter, on grist.org.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sheer magnitude of Wal-Mart's plans to become more environmentally friendly has been enough to give pause to all but the most vehement of the company's critics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sheer magnitude of Wal-Mart's plans to become more environmentally friendly has been enough to give pause to all but the most vehement of the company's critics.</p>
        <p>The online environmental magazine Grist gave soft applause to Wal-Mart last week in its introduction to a Q. and A. session with H. Lee Scott Jr., the chief executive. When the company this month signed on to a call by a group of energy executives for caps on greenhouse-gas emissions, ''the heart of this monolithic retail Grinch grew three sizes that day,'' writes Amanda Griscom Little, a Grist reporter, on grist.org.</p>
        <p>To be sure, it is a little startling to hear Wal-Mart's chief executive bandying about phrases like ''democratizing sustainability,'' but given that Wal-Mart plans to spend $500 million a year to, among other initiatives, reduce its greenhouse gases, build more energy-efficient stores and reduce packaging waste, even longtime naysayers have to take notice.</p>
        <p>Ms. Little points out that Wal-Mart's size -- the very thing that makes it so vulnerable to attack -- is precisely what ''could make it a powerful force for good for the planet.''</p>
        <p>''The company controls so much of the retail market, and has such sway over manufacturers, that any green initiatives on its part have huge ripple effects,'' she writes.</p>
        <p>But even more, Mr. Scott says, Wal-Mart's size ''enables us to help create markets for clean technologies that exist today, but don't yet have fully established markets.''</p>
        <p>''If Wal-Mart started using or selling those items all of a sudden, there would be enough scale that those would be viable alternatives,'' he added.</p>
        <p>One commenter on Grist's blog wondered if Ms. Little's ''glowing'' article was ''a cruel joke.'' The interview drew a lot of commentary in the blogosphere. Many bloggers seemed unsure how to react. Raven Brooks of buyblue.org, which ''supports businesses that share our progressive values and ideals,'' wrote that he found the interview ''shocking.'' He wondered about Wal-Mart's sincerity, but concluded that ''this is progress.''</p>
        <p>UGLY AMERICANS -- ''Loud and brash, in gawdy garb and baseball caps, more than three million of them flock to our shores every year,'' writes Philip Sherwell this week on www.telegraph.co.uk, the Web site of The Daily Telegraph of London.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherwell is describing Americans, of course, both tourists and business travelers. The latter group, Mr. Sherwell reports, is the target of an initiative by the State Department and a group of American companies who want to see their executives behave better abroad.</p>
        <p>Next month, Business for Diplomatic Action, a group financed by several big American companies, will issue a ''World Citizens Guide,'' which offers 16 tips for travelers (worldcitizensguide.org). Among them:</p>
        <p>''Listen at least as much as you talk.''</p>
        <p>''Think as big as you like, but talk and act smaller. (In many countries, any form of boasting is considered very rude. Talking about wealth, power or status -- corporate or personal -- can create resentment.)''</p>
        <p>''Slow down. (We talk fast, eat fast, move fast, live fast. Many cultures do not.)''</p>
        <p>''Save the lectures for your kids.''</p>
        <p>HOT AIR? -- For all the jokes about bottled water, there are good reasons for its being a $9 billion industry in the United States. It may seem silly, at first, to buy something you can get from a tap. But if you are out on a hot day, popping into a store for a chilled bottle of water can be convenient and refreshing.</p>
        <p>But what about oxygen in a can? The Big Ox is selling a product called Big Ox, for ''today's on-the-go people.''</p>
        <p>The Big Ox Web page, www.thebigox.com, makes a number of remarkable claims, among them that canned oxygen ''displaces harmful free radicals'' and ''detoxifies blood.''</p>
        <p>Scientists have been pooh-poohing such claims for several years. Indeed, many doctors warn that pure oxygen can be dangerous, and even deadly in some circumstances, notes an article on failedsuccess.com.</p>
        <p>DAN MITCHELL</p>
        <p>WHAT'S ONLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
