<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australia to Sell Uranium to China for Energy</title>
    <meta content="03australia" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/03/world/asia/03australia.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1751814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Australia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DB1330F930A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australia to Sell Uranium to China for Energy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Australia to Sell Uranium to China for Energy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Monday, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Australia, one of the United States' closest allies, signed an agreement with China on Monday to sell uranium for use in China's nuclear power plants, in its continuing drive to meet its soaring energy needs.</p>
        <p>The deal also opens the door for Chinese investment in Australian uranium mines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The deal also opens the door for Chinese investment in Australian uranium mines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Australia, one of the United States' closest allies, signed an agreement with China on Monday to sell uranium for use in China's nuclear power plants, in its continuing drive to meet its soaring energy needs.</p>
        <p>The deal also opens the door for Chinese investment in Australian uranium mines.</p>
        <p>The agreement, negotiated over the last year in Beijing, is the highlight of a three-day trip to Australia by Prime Minister Wen Jiabao of China, and underscores the importance of Australia as a base for China's widening demand for natural resources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wen spent Sunday in Western Australia, the state that provides much of the raw materials Australia exports to China.</p>
        <p>Australia is scheduled to deliver its first liquid natural gas to China from the North West Shelf gas development in Western Australia in the next several months and is already one of China's biggest suppliers of iron ore.</p>
        <p>But because uranium is used in nuclear weapons, it is in a different category from that of other commodities.</p>
        <p>The conservative government of Prime Minister John Howard has emphasized that China has agreed not to use Australian uranium in its weapons program, or for other military purposes.</p>
        <p>The Australians also emphasize that China, unlike India, which the Bush administration agreed last month to provide with nuclear technology, has signed the Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty. Australia described the accord as a safeguards agreement that stipulated conditions for the sale and will be monitored by the International Atomic Energy Agency.</p>
        <p>A senior Australian official in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade said Sunday that the United States was ''hardly in a position'' to criticize the sale of uranium for peaceful purposes to China after announcing that it would seek an exemption from Congress to sell fuel to India for its civilian nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Condoleezza Rice was informed of Australia's plans to sell uranium to China on her visit here last month. ''She simply listened to the fact we have negotiated an agreement within the framework of the'' nonproliferation treaty, the Australian official said.</p>
        <p>An American specialist on nuclear issues, George Perkovich, who criticized the Bush administration's accord with India as allowing India to amass nuclear weapons, said he did not consider China a similar case.</p>
        <p>Unlike India, China had all the fissile nuclear material it needed for weapons, said Mr. Perkovich, the director of studies at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace.</p>
        <p>''There is every reason to think China will be using uranium for civilian uses,'' he said. ''If you're a country that sells uranium to countries for nuclear power, there is no argument for not selling it to China.''</p>
        <p>The deal with China, which was signed in the capital, Canberra, has been greeted with fanfare in Australia, and was preceded by a long interview of Prime Minister Wen in the newspaper The Australian.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wen made clear that China's growing economic relationship with Australia locked in an important American ally as an important Chinese friend as well. ''We believe that countries which are allied with the United States can also be China's friends, and Australia is one of them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Howard government, while supportive of the Bush administration in Iraq, has told the United States that it cannot count on Australia to be at its side in the event of a conflict with China over Taiwan.</p>
        <p>The uranium accord comes as China tries to reduce its heavy reliance on fossil fuels. It has nine nuclear power reactors, but has announced an ambitious program to build as many as three reactors a year.</p>
        <p>Australia holds an estimated 40 percent of the world's reserves of easily extractable uranium and sells it in the form of uranium oxide to the United States, Canada and South Korea for use in civilian nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>The sale of uranium has long had opponents in Australia, who have argued that because uranium is used in nuclear weapons, it should be left in the ground. Australia has no nuclear power industry of its own, and uranium production has been limited to three operating mines. The argument that nuclear power can help reduce the emission of greenhouse gases has also cut opposition to the deal.</p>
        <p>But in an effort to show that it supports an economic boom that rides so heavily on exports of natural resources to China, the major opposition party, the Australian Labor Party, indicated this weekend that it would favor more expansive uranium production. That leaves the small Green Party as the major vocal opponent to the sale.</p>
        <p>After visiting India last month, Mr. Howard said his government might reconsider its current position on not selling uranium there.</p>
        <p>One of the features of the accord signed Monday for which China was most eager, Australian officials had said, is an agreement that China could invest in the Australian uranium industry.</p>
        <p>The Chinese ambassador to Australia, Fu Ying, last year went to the state of South Australia and visited the Olympic Dam uranium mine, which is owned by BHP Billiton, the world's largest mining company.</p>
        <p>The Australian foreign minister, Alexander Downer, said recently that once a safeguards agreement was reached on uranium sales, there was no reason that a Chinese company could not apply to the Foreign Investment Review Board for approval to invest in uranium mining.</p>
        <p>Amplifying on those remarks, an Australian official at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade said over the weekend that it was likely that the Chinese would seek minority equity in a uranium mining company as a way of assuring its supply. The agreement to be signed Monday paved the way for such an investment, he said.</p>
        <p>Formal negotiations for the accord with China began in Beijing in August, but informal talks began many months before, Australian officials said. The negotiations were led by John Carlson, director general of the Australian Safeguards and Nonproliferation Office, and were completed last month.</p>
        <p>According to an account by the Foreign Affairs and Trade Department, Australia will rely on China's inspections agreement with the International Atomic Energy Agency, the nuclear monitoring arm of the United Nations, to ensure that the Australian uranium is used only for nuclear power reactors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
