<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fallback</title>
    <meta content="312bwarner" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/12/magazine/312bwarner.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="EDITORS' NOTE APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060315T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Warner, Mark</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3D71531F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="8447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fallback</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Fallback</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Matt Bai</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Bai profile of Gov Mark Warner of Virginia, who is emerging as fallback candidates for those Democrats who think Hillary Clinton is not electable; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you harbor serious thoughts of running for the presidency, the first thing you do -- long before you commission any polls or make any ads, years before you charter planes to take you back and forth between Iowa and New Hampshire -- is to sit down with guys like Chris Korge. A real-estate developer in Coral Gables, outside Miami, Korge is one of the Democratic Party's most proficient ''bundlers.'' That is, in the last two presidential elections, he bundled together more than $7 million in campaign checks for Al Gore and John Kerry from his friends and contacts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those Democrats who think Hillary Clinton is not electable in 2008? Meet Mark Warner of Virginia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you harbor serious thoughts of running for the presidency, the first thing you do -- long before you commission any polls or make any ads, years before you charter planes to take you back and forth between Iowa and New Hampshire -- is to sit down with guys like Chris Korge. A real-estate developer in Coral Gables, outside Miami, Korge is one of the Democratic Party's most proficient ''bundlers.'' That is, in the last two presidential elections, he bundled together more than $7 million in campaign checks for Al Gore and John Kerry from his friends and contacts.</p>
        <p>For Korge, the 2008 presidential campaign began a few days after Kerry lost, when, he says, one prospective candidate -- he won't say who -- called to enlist his help. Having raised money for both of Bill Clinton's presidential campaigns, which earned him an overnight stay in the Lincoln Bedroom, Korge already knew he would support Hillary Clinton if she ran; he considers her the most impressive politician he has ever met, including her husband. But that didn't stop her potential rivals -- John Edwards, Joe Biden, Evan Bayh, Wesley Clark -- from dropping by, nor did it stop Korge, a guy who rightly prides himself on knowing just about everybody in Democratic politics, from taking the meetings. ''In the last six months, I've pretty much seen or talked with all of them, or they've tried to meet with me,'' Korge told me during a conversation in late January.</p>
        <p>A few weeks before we spoke, Korge had lunch at the Capital Grille in Miami with Mark Warner, who was then in his final weeks as Virginia's governor. Though little known nationally, Warner has emerged in recent months as the bright new star in the constellation of would-be candidates, a source of curiosity among Democrats searching for a charismatic outsider to lead the party. Pundits credit Warner's popularity in Republican-dominated Virginia -- his 80 percent approval rating when he left office made him one of the most adored governors in the state's history -- with enabling his Democratic lieutenant governor, Tim Kaine, to win the election to succeed him last November. Suddenly, Warner is being mentioned near the top of every list of candidates vying for the nomination in 2008.</p>
        <p>Over lunch with Korge and his real-estate partner, Warner made what has become, more or less, his standard pitch. Much as he likes John Kerry and worked hard for him in Virginia, Warner said, the Democratic Party had once again, in 2004, nominated a candidate who could not appeal on a cultural level to white, small-town voters in wide swaths of the country. Warner argued that he was more likely than any of the other potential Democratic candidates to break that cycle. The candidate he was really talking about, of course, was Clinton. It wasn't that she wouldn't do a great job in the White House, necessarily; what Warner was saying, without actually saying it, was that she couldn't get there. Democrats, he liked to say, could not afford to keep trotting out nominees who could expect to win only 16 blue states and then hope, just maybe, for the ''triple bank shot'' that might deliver Ohio or Florida. They needed a candidate who could compete everywhere.</p>
        <p>Korge had already heard some version of the same case from several of Warner's rivals. ''They can't help themselves,'' he told me. ''What you hear is two things: one, why Hillary can't win, and two, why they're going to be the other candidate who emerges in the showdown with Hillary.'' Korge told Warner the same thing he told the other suitors, including John Kerry: he was loyal to Hillary and intended to stay that way. That was fine, Warner said, but would Korge be willing to introduce him to friends who weren't yet decided? Korge deflected the request. To him, helping Warner raise money would have been ''counterproductive.''</p>
        <p>You might think this would have deflated Warner. It didn't. He knows that many of the money guys he goes to see at this early stage are going to pledge their allegiance to Clinton. But the path of a campaign is long and twisting, and there may come a time when Korge needs a fallback candidate. More to the point, aside from being a fund-raiser, Korge is a validator, the kind of guy to whom others in business and politics will listen. There are perhaps 20,000 activists and contributors whose choices influence the Democratic nominating process, and Korge talks with more than a few of them; his casual appraisals mean something.</p>
        <p>From this vantage point, Warner's meeting with Korge was an unqualified success. ''In my opinion, he's the one to watch as an outsider in this race,'' Korge told me. ''He seems presidential. He's a big guy.'' (By this he meant, literally, that Warner is well over six feet tall, with a well-coiffed head that requires extra-large baseball caps.) ''I think he has a presence. He's very confident. He speaks very well, but he also can speak plainly to people.''</p>
        <p>There are, as yet, no announced candidates for the 2008 Democratic nomination, and even those who expect to run probably won't make their final decisions before the end of the year. But the process is playing out earlier and more visibly than ever, in part because candidates like Warner are scrambling to make sure this nominating season isn't over before it begins. Usually when there isn't an incumbent Democratic president or a vice president with title to the nomination, the presidential field would feature a blended ensemble of candidates, some better known than others but each singing the part of some distinct constituency. At this time in 2002, for instance, the prospective Democrats included the candidate of the foreign-policy establishment (John Kerry); the candidate favored by many Clinton New Democrat types (John Edwards); the anti-Washington candidate (Howard Dean); the Big Labor candidate (Dick Gephardt); and the African-American protest candidate (Al Sharpton). Races like this winnow slowly. On the eve of the Iowa caucus in 2004, with the exception of Sharpton, each of these candidates -- and, additionally, Wesley Clark -- were still very much in contention for the party's nomination.</p>
        <p>The Democratic field now emerging, on the other hand, is looking a lot like Gladys Knight and the Pips -- and you can guess who gets to be Gladys. The party's insiders, expecting Clinton to be a virtually unstoppable force, seem to be falling in line behind her, which means there will be only so much additional money and organization left over for those who would challenge her. But more than anything, Democrats will tell you that they are desperate to win next time around, and a lot of pragmatic activists and voters worry that Clinton is simply too divisive a candidate to take back the White House. (In a Gallup poll in January, 51 percent of respondents said they would definitely not vote for her.) These Democrats are actively shopping for a candidate who can derail Clinton before the party, as they see it, dooms itself to yet another near miss. And so the conventional thinking holds that there may only be room for two serious candidates by the time the primaries roll around: Hillary and the anti-Hillary. What Mark Warner needs to do now, just as his rivals do, is to begin making the case, as subtly as possible and before most of the country has even started to think about 2008, that the senator from New York is the wrong candidate for the party -- and that he's the only guy who can stop her.</p>
        <p>If Hillary Clinton does decide to run for president, no matter who ultimately runs against her for the party's nomination, she will begin with the kind of institutional advantages that have been reserved, in the past, for vice presidents like Walter Mondale and Al Gore. It starts with money. At the end of last year, according to the Hotline, the venerable Washington online digest, Clinton had more than $17 million in the bank for her re-election campaign in New York -- and no serious opponent to spend it against. By contrast, Warner, capping what was widely considered a surprisingly sound fund-raising season, had amassed a little under $2.5 million for his political action committee, Forward Together. But that's not the whole story. Thanks to the inscrutable wonder of campaign finance laws, Clinton can roll every penny that she doesn't spend on her Senate campaign into a presidential account, which is why she could well start a bid for the White House with as much as $75 million, on course to obliterate the party's previous fund-raising records. No matter how much a governor like Warner raises in his political action committee, on the other hand, the rules say that he can't spend any of it on a presidential run; it can go only for general political activity, mostly backing other candidates. This means that should Warner decide to run, he'll have to start again from zero, while Clinton is backing up 18-wheelers to the bank.</p>
        <p>What's more, Clinton will arrive in early primary states with a built-in base of voters. She has been campaigning in these states, off and on, for 15 years and knows every stop along the way; she can count on the endorsements of most of the local elected officials and interest groups, all of whom come with their own e-mail lists and organizers. By contrast, Warner, during a recent trip to the foreign territory of New Hampshire, made the standard politician's pilgrimage to the Stonyfield Farm yogurt plant near Manchester and then wondered aloud just how many candidates in years past had also taken the tour. (Answer: So many that at the height of primary-season mania, they would seem to outnumber those Americans who actually eat Stonyfield Farm yogurt.)</p>
        <p>So formidable are the obstacles to challenging Clinton that even a lot of party operatives who don't think she's the best candidate are likely to work for her, just to be on the winning side. And this is precisely the strategy that her team has thus far cultivated. Just as Karl Rove set out to make George W. Bush's nomination seem inevitable in 2000, successfully freezing much of the money and talent that might have flowed to his competitors, so, too, do Clinton's advisers seem to be sending out signals that resistance is not only futile but also dangerous. When I asked Warner's aides for permission to attend some of his policy briefings in January, word came back that the outside experts who had been asked to make presentations, some of whom worked in the Clinton administration, balked because they were afraid the Clinton camp would find out that they were granting courtesies to another candidate. No one wants to cross the party's presumed nominee.</p>
        <p>Given all that, it's a wonder that so many Democrats are thinking seriously of offering themselves up as an alternative. There are various interpretations among the party's cognoscenti as to which hopefuls belong in the coveted ''top tier'' of potential candidates. As of the end of 2005, Kerry had more than $15 million in contributions stashed away for another bid, as well as a handful of major fund-raisers who remain loyal to him, but the general assessment among Democratic insiders is that his Swift boat has already sailed. Edwards and Clark, meanwhile, won three primary states between them last time around; both have the potential to be serious players in 2008, but neither will appeal to those Democrats who say that the party needs an unfamiliar face.</p>
        <p>What remains is a genuinely impressive field of hopefuls whose perceived flaws, in any other year and against any other opponent, might not prompt such dismissiveness from the party elite. Conventional wisdom holds that Joe Biden, who last ran in 1988, can't raise enough cash, and that the populist Russ Feingold has currency mostly as a protest candidate. Evan Bayh, a centrist senator and former governor, comes across as thoughtful and steady on foreign policy (he also looks the part, bearing a remarkable resemblance to the actor Kevin Kline), but the early word is that he's a bit too stilted and senatorial, prompting insiders to discourse, yet again, on how few sitting senators are ever elected president. (For the record, there have been only two, and both of them died in office, presumably a coincidence.) Among the governors, Tom Vilsack of Iowa gets high praise from big-time donors, but the next thing they tell you is that he can't compete financially. As a former United Nations ambassador and energy secretary, Bill Richardson, now New Mexico's governor, has as wide a range of experience as anyone in the race, but his aggressively extroverted personality makes party insiders uncomfortable -- and that was true even before his female lieutenant governor, a Democrat, publicly complained in December that he wouldn't stop poking her at official functions.</p>
        <p>That leaves Warner, onto whom a lot of anti-Hillary Democrats have suddenly projected their hopes. The negative rap on Warner is a lack of relevant experience; he's a one-term governor (he would still be in office if Virginia allowed its governors to serve consecutive terms), and critics argue that a credible candidate needs to have foreign-policy experience to run in the new, terror-obsessed world. Nonetheless, Warner, on paper, fits the party's most conventional and tested idea of what constitutes an electable candidate. Though he doesn't speak with a drawl (he grew up in Indiana, Illinois and Connecticut and moved to Virginia when he was 32), Warner was the popular centrist governor of a Southern state -- just like the last two Democrats to actually win the White House, Jimmy Carter and Bill Clinton. He's also really, sickeningly wealthy. As a co-founder of the cellular-telephone company that ultimately became Nextel, Warner has access to a personal fortune that is said to approach $200 million, and he has already demonstrated, during an unsuccessful run for the Senate and then in his gubernatorial campaign, that he's willing to use it.</p>
        <p>Because of his previous life as a businessman, Warner is also expected to tap a network of donors in the high-tech and venture-capital fields who are outside the orbit of traditional Democratic fund-raising, just as Bill Bradley did when he ran against Al Gore in 2000. To party insiders in search of a Clinton alternative, all of this is crucial; it means that even if she manages to suck up all the money flowing from the party's usual contributors, Warner might still have a lifeline that other candidates don't. ''The only one I think can get some traction is Mark Warner, because he can write his own checks,'' says Susan Estrich, who ran Michael Dukakis's 1988 campaign. Estrich recently wrote a book called ''The Case for Hillary Clinton'' (as if Clinton needed any help), but, she told me, if someone's going to stop Clinton, ''Warner's the only one who really makes sense.''</p>
        <p>That Warner has suddenly become a commodity, even among those who know little about him, was obvious at the Florida Democratic Party convention in December, where he swept into a party for the delegates, led by an escort of state police. ''That's Governor Warner!'' one woman said excitedly. ''He's so good-looking!''</p>
        <p>''He's got a huge head!'' her companion observed, craning her neck to see over the crowd as Warner signed autographs. ''He sort of looks like Schwarzenegger.''</p>
        <p>''I do think he has the best chance,'' I heard another delegate say knowingly. Warner's speech to the convention the next morning drew a more-than-perfunctory standing ovation.</p>
        <p>When a lot of National Democrats first took note of Warner in 2001, they didn't love what they saw. Running for governor in a state where Democrats were in sharp retreat, Warner courted the National Rifle Association and let it be known he'd support parental notification for minors seeking abortions. His outreach to Nascar devotees and bluegrass fans in southern Virginia struck Democrats in the urban North -- as well as many of those across the Potomac River in Washington -- as unseemly pandering.</p>
        <p>Warner was determined, however, not to let Republicans portray him as a cultural elitist. He never made any pretense of being an avid hunter or Nascar fan himself; he's a Presbyterian who wears pressed khakis, and he spends weekends at his private farm and vineyard outside historic Fredericksburg. But Warner, who is 51, grew up mostly in small towns, in a middle-class family, and in the 2001 campaign he made it clear that he genuinely appreciated the cultural pastimes of his rural voters. The respect he showed was reciprocated. Five years ago, I watched voters at the annual fiddlers' festival in Galax, Va., clap Warner on the back and dance along to his campaign song, an impossibly catchy bluegrass tune, while his Republican opponent, the state's former attorney general, milled about uncomfortably. Even after the terrorist attacks that September, which froze the campaign and rallied the country around the president and the Republican Party, Warner won by five points, scoring more support in rural Virginia than any Democrat in recent memory.</p>
        <p>Considering that he has served only four years in government, Warner has plenty to brag about. Relentlessly wooing his Republican Legislature at a time when the two parties in Washington were growing ever more belligerent toward each other, Warner managed to erase a potentially catastrophic $6 billion budget shortfall by working out a bipartisan deal to raise some taxes (on sales and cigarettes) and lower others (on income and food). He passed the plan, in part, by selling it in frequent meetings with voters across the state, earning him a reputation as a nonpartisan deal maker who was willing to deliver unpopular news.</p>
        <p>Warner's constant theme, which a lot of Washington politicians talk about but few seem to actually understand, was the need to modernize for a global economy. The days when you could walk down the street and get a job at the mill were over, Warner would say, and new jobs -- the state gained more than 150,000 of them on his watch -- would require new skills and infrastructure. So Warner, working with Nascar, pushed through an accelerated program that enabled 35,000 more Virginians to get high-school equivalency degrees, and he introduced a program to deliver broadband capacity to 20 Southern counties. ''In the 1800's, if the railroad didn't come through your small town, the town shriveled up and went away,'' he told me once, explaining his rural program. ''And if the broadband Internet doesn't come through your town in the next few years, the same thing will happen.''</p>
        <p>If he ultimately decides to run for president, Warner will try to build a national campaign around this same technology-driven approach. When I asked Warner to name the issues that would be most important to him, the four domestic issues he ticked off, before he got to terrorism and national security, were fairly standard for a Democratic candidate in the era after Bill Clinton: slashing the federal deficit, improving schools, working with business to reform the health-care system and devising a new energy strategy. What makes Warner, the former entrepreneur, sound more credible than your average Democrat is that he comes at these issues primarily from an economic, rather than a social, standpoint. On health care, for instance, most Washington Democrats will, as a matter of both habit and perspective, talk about the moral imperative of covering workers and the uninsured -- and only then might they add, as an afterthought, that the current morass is an impediment to business too. Warner, on the other hand, begins with the idea that if American businesses can't keep up with spiraling health-care costs, the nation will lose the competition with India and China for jobs. The same principle applies with education and the deficit. His fixation on the global economy brings a coherent framework to issues that otherwise seem disparate and abstract.</p>
        <p>He doesn't yet have the specific proposals he will need to make this vision feel as concrete in a national campaign as it did when he was governor. Instead, everywhere he goes, he emphasizes that Virginia was named the ''best-managed state in the country.'' (In fact, Governing magazine, the trade publication for state and local officials, gave both Virginia and Utah the overall highest grades of any state in its 2005 study.) ''Results matter,'' Warner often says, contrasting his record with what he characterizes as the Bush administration's incompetence. At times, it sounds a bit too much like Michael Dukakis's ''competence'' argument -- the kind of technocratic appeal for hands-on government that has never inspired voters to choose a candidate as president. (Dukakis had his ''Massachusetts miracle''; Warner talks up ''the Virginia story.'') It is possible that Warner and his top advisers, most of whom are loyalists from his days as a businessman or as governor, have overestimated the political value, even after Hurricane Katrina, of bland efficiency.</p>
        <p>This emphasis on reforming government, however, is part of a larger argument about electability that Warner is just now beginning to sharpen. Essentially, if he and Clinton ultimately run, he will campaign against her in much the same way that her husband campaigned against the Democratic establishment as a governor in 1992. Like Warner, Bill Clinton leapt into a race that was supposed to be dominated by a bigger name from the liberal Northeast. (That Mario Cuomo decided not to run was one of several lucky breaks that helped propel Clinton from anonymity to the White House.) Clinton's argument then was that the party had become too ideologically rigid, and that its adherence to dogmatic social policy was driving away middle-class voters who might otherwise respond to a new kind of economic agenda. It's easy to forget now, given how thoroughly the party has internalized Clinton's language on so many issues, that talking in the early 90's about the tragedy of abortion or the rethinking of welfare policy constituted a kind of apostasy to much of the party elite.</p>
        <p>Now it is Hillary Clinton of New York who represents that coastal elite, and while she employs much of the same rhetoric her husband used, Warner argues that, nationally, the cultural perception of the party and its most visible leaders -- Clinton, Kerry, Howard Dean, Nancy Pelosi -- isn't much different from what it was back then. Results do matter to voters, Warner says, but only if you make it impossible for Republicans to paint your nominee as another protester-turned-windsurfer who looks down on people who go to a megachurch and like to watch the stock cars race. ''You can't keep sending people out there who check every box of the Democratic orthodoxy, or that at least check every box of the East Coast-West Coast Democratic orthodoxy,'' Warner told me during a conversation in his Capitol office in his final days as governor. Only a Democrat who had a proven ability to transcend cultural issues, he said, could broaden the party's base.</p>
        <p>''You have to make that argument,'' Warner went on to say. ''You have to make it not just as a Democrat, but as an American. Let's assume the Democrats continue to run on a 16-state strategy and hope for a 17th state. Can you really govern? Can you govern if you cede two-thirds of the states?''</p>
        <p>It was hard not to notice, as we had this conversation, that Warner never mentioned Hillary Clinton. It is a perilous mission that Warner and other Democratic hopefuls undertake as they try to cast doubts about her electability without appearing to attack one of the party's iconic figures. And it's risky not just because she is a Clinton, beloved by most of the party's important interest groups, but also because she is a woman; a lot of voters may wonder if a woman can really be elected president, but they would most likely turn on any male candidate who was crass enough to imply as much.</p>
        <p>In his conversations with contributors and activists, Warner meanders up to the boundary of personal criticism, but he is careful not to step across it. His manner suggests that he himself would happily call Clinton ''Madame President,'' but he just doesn't think the voters he knows in Southside Virginia can ever be made to feel the same way. In contrast, Warner argues that there is a universe of moderate Republicans out there who would be comfortable in crossing party lines to vote for him.</p>
        <p>Is Clinton, I asked Warner, an ''electable'' Democrat? ''I think she's a very strong senator,'' he said slowly, pausing several times. ''And I think what she showed in New York was an ability to really make her case among people who might not initially be supportive.''</p>
        <p>We stared at each other. ''O.K.,'' I said. ''But is she electable?''</p>
        <p>''If she decides to run, she'll be the front-runner,'' Warner replied carefully.</p>
        <p>Even should it prove to be an achievable goal, persuading Democrats that Clinton can't win gets you only so far. Warner also has to persuade them, ultimately, that he's the best choice to oppose her. And so he must now travel the country more or less constantly, borrowing private planes from wealthy friends when possible, asking for meetings with contributors, activists and elected officials whose money and influence will matter in the later stages of the campaign. For all the perennial conjecture about which hopefuls seem ''presidential'' and which don't, the truth is that presidential candidates who lack national stature always start out looking somehow smaller than they should, hustling unrecognized from one conference room to the next, like interstate speed daters in search of a thousand soul mates.</p>
        <p>''I intend to be out campaigning for folks around the country who share some of the views I've shared tonight and the approach we've taken in Virginia,'' Warner told a crowd of about 60 at a fund-raiser given by a fellow entrepreneur in Chapel Hill, N.C., in January. ''If this makes some sense to you, I'm going to be in California next week, and I'm in New Hampshire Friday. I'm in Texas the week after next. If you like what you hear, maybe you can call your friend there and say: 'Hey, I heard this guy Warner the other night. You should go check him out.''' This was great -- maybe we could go out again sometime. Or if you've got some friends you're looking to set up.. . .</p>
        <p>Warner isn't what you'd call a natural candidate. He speaks haltingly and sometimes in circles. He likes personal contact, but he can be physically awkward with voters, stiffly patting their arms or crookedly grasping their shoulders in what looks like an impersonation of the Vulcan Death Grip. He compensates, however, with eagerness and perseverance; like all of the best politicians, Warner loves to be liked. It's easy to imagine Warner, the president of his high-school class, infiltrating the various social circles at Harvard Law School through the sheer discipline of remembering every name and hometown he came across. After graduating, rather than join some huge firm, Warner worked as a fund-raiser for the Democratic National Committee -- in a job that enabled him, even then, to collect new and wealthy friends who had an interest in politics.</p>
        <p>As governor, he was known for inviting his opponents over to the mansion for drinks and then inviting them back again, until he'd earned their trust. The less inclined you are to like Warner, the more inclined he is to court you, which probably explains his counterintuitive bond with Virginia's rural, less-educated voters.</p>
        <p>Among the wealthy contributors and liberal activists who have met Warner recently, the most common observation is that he genuinely listens. ''I think he will, over time, find a very strong following here,'' Mark Gorenberg, a San Francisco venture capitalist, told me. An important player in the politics of Silicon Valley and the Bay Area, which has supplanted Los Angeles as the epicenter of Democratic money on the West Coast, Gorenberg was Kerry's top bundler in the last election, and he told me he remains part of Kerry's national ''leadership team.'' But Warner clearly impressed him: ''He's a very interesting candidate, especially to the tech industry. He's garnered a lot of interest out here. What he's done differently is that he hasn't raised money. He's the only one who comes out here mostly to meet people.''</p>
        <p>For the past several months, the 2008 hopefuls have been attending a circuit of private dinners in Washington, as well as a series of meetings in the headquarters of powerful interest groups. In a party long dominated by single-issue constituencies, these meetings can take on the feel of a job interview with an especially inquisitive employer. ''First, I want to know why they're running,'' says Linda Lipsen, the top lobbyist for the Association of Trial Lawyers of America, describing the conversations she's had with most of the 2008 hopefuls in recent months. ''Not the pat answer that they've rehearsed, but why they really want to do this. Why they want to go through this ordeal. Who they really are. Where they take their vacations. What they do in their spare time. What books do they read?'' Of Warner, Lipsen says: ''He was very comfortable in his skin, very willing to learn. He doesn't make you feel uncomfortable.''</p>
        <p>The presidential cycle is just beginning, however, and the Oprahesque questions won't last very long. The problem for Warner is that, a year from now, liberals who like the idea of a Southern governor on the ticket will nonetheless want to know where he stands on the party's perennial issues. Then Warner will have to explain to his party's power brokers why he believes that Medicaid should be retooled and why he embraces free trade and why he believes that nuclear power should be explored. Bill Clinton managed to secure the nomination in 1992 even after confronting Big Labor and African-American activists, but he didn't face a serious challenge from the party's more liberal wing -- and he didn't have to run against his wife.</p>
        <p>Warner may have glimpsed a piece of his future when he attended a dinner of wealthy Democrats last summer at the Bay Area home of Mark Buell and his wife, Susie Tompkins Buell, well-connected contributors and close friends of the Clintons. Warner made some introductory comments about ''the Virginia story,'' but the first several questions were not about taxes or schools or health care, but about gay marriage (which he's against), the death penalty (which he's for) and abortion (he's in favor of parental notification but vetoed a bill banning all late-term abortions). Warner thought his liberal guests would be interested in his policies to improve Virginia schools and raise the standard of living in rural areas; instead, it seemed to him, they thought that they understood poverty and race in an intellectual way that he, as a red-state governor, could not. Like a lot of politicians, Warner can be snappish when he feels he isn't being heard, and the dialogue quickly grew testy.</p>
        <p>At the end of the evening, according to people who were there, as some of the guests walked Warner to his car, one woman vowed to educate him on abortion rights. That was all he could take. ''This is why America hates Democrats,'' a frustrated Warner blurted out before driving away. (Still piqued a month later, Warner, speaking to The Los Angeles Times, summarized the attitude of the assembled guests about their plans to save the country: ''You little Virginia Democrat, how can you understand the great opportunities we have?'')</p>
        <p>Warner seems unconcerned about the damage done by such comments. ''If somebody wants a purist, I'm not the guy,'' he told me. What struck Mark Buell about Warner that night, however, wasn't so much the substance of his answers as the time it took him to formulate them. To him, Warner seemed tentative and unpolished. ''You could see him thinking through the questions as he was up there,'' Buell recalled. ''If anybody's on a learning curve for national politics, it's going to be him.''</p>
        <p>This seems to be the concern arising about Warner as he introduces himself around the country. Normally, a governor like Warner, unschooled in foreign policy and military issues, would have at least until after the midterm elections coming up in November to study up and calibrate positions. It wasn't until 1999, for instance, that Karl Rove and Condoleezza Rice started running a virtual academy in Austin for Governor Bush, who had barely ever been out of the country. Warner, who is considerably worldlier but just as inexperienced in military matters, has started receiving dozens of briefings in his Alexandria office, just a few blocks from the stately house overlooking the Potomac where he lives with his wife and three daughters.</p>
        <p>What's different for Warner is that he has, in just the last few months, become the subject of scrutiny unusual for this early in the race, as more Democratic insiders speculate that he could be the guy to take on Clinton. He can feel the change; suddenly, audiences really want to know what his positions are on the Iraq war and the Iranian nuclear program, areas in which he acknowledges that he still has much to learn.</p>
        <p>In small meetings with donors or interest groups, Warner seems comfortable admitting that he doesn't yet know all the things he needs to know. Among larger crowds, however, or with the media, he sometimes seems to be improvising. This has been a particular problem on Iraq, an issue that arises, not surprisingly, everywhere he goes. Several times, I watched him string together a disconnected, banal series of observations -- the Sunnis need to be involved, the military should be seen as problem-solvers rather than as occupiers and so on -- while continually looking down and pausing, as if he were trying to recall a briefing paper. It was a sharp contrast to the confidence with which Warner discusses almost any domestic issue, and I had the sense that he felt compelled to demonstrate his proficiency in the specific details of Iraq policy rather than offer the more basic statements of principle that are sufficient for most candidates at this stage of an undeclared campaign.</p>
        <p>That Warner isn't ready for all the questions a presidential candidate must field was apparent during a somewhat calamitous interview in January with George Stephanopoulos on ABC's ''This Week.'' Warner seemed surprised and uncomfortable when the host tried to pin him down on questions that divided the country and his party. He refused to say whether he thought Samuel Alito should be confirmed for the Supreme Court or whether he thought the president had the authority to order domestic wiretaps without a court's permission.</p>
        <p>When Stephanopoulos pressed him to say whether he supported the Iraq invasion in 2003, Warner replied that it was pointless for Democrats to continue that argument. Logically, this wasn't an unreasonable response -- the decision to go to war is now well past debating, and Warner never had access to classified intelligence -- but it sounded oblivious to political reality. Whether the war was justified remains an important question for a lot of liberal voters, especially since Clinton and most of her potential challengers in the Senate (Feingold being the only exception) voted for the 2002 war resolution. It's unlikely that Warner can simply avoid the question.</p>
        <p>Having been through the 1992 Clinton campaign, an incredulous</p>
        <p>Stephanopoulos couldn't help asking, ''You think you can keep that position through the primaries?''</p>
        <p>''Time will tell,'' was Warner's uncertain response.</p>
        <p>The exchange with Stephanopoulos on the war hints at another, more tactical question that Warner will have to confront. If you accept the premise, however theoretical, that the Democratic race two years from now will come down to Clinton and a single challenger, then the candidate who gains enough anti-Hillary momentum to meet her head-on will, by definition, have to run an insurgent campaign against the party's Washington establishment, in the same mold as Jimmy Carter in 1976 or Gary Hart in 1984.</p>
        <p>To be a successful insurgent in 2008, a candidate probably needs a serious following online. The activists in the so-called Netroots, people who connect to politics primarily through MoveOn.org and the liberal blogs, will be even more populous and more motivated than in 2004, and while it's impossible to generalize, it seems that most of the Netroots are eager to find a candidate who isn't Hillary Clinton. Among the anti-Hillary contenders, Russ Feingold and Wesley Clark have the strongest constituencies online. But perhaps the most viable candidate who is making a strong bid to inherit Dean's activist base is John Edwards, who now directs an antipoverty center at the University of North Carolina. In the last year, Edwards's support among the Netroots appears to have surged as he has explored the world of blogging and podcasting, renounced his initial support for the Iraq war, campaigned for hotel workers in a union drive and railed against what he calls the ''phony'' culture of Washington. When I sat with him in a Chapel Hill cafe in January, Edwards, appearing more relaxed and confident than he did at any time during the 2004 campaign, told me that he now understood that specific policies weren't nearly as important in modern presidential politics as telegraphing a sense of conviction.</p>
        <p>''Just being myself and standing up for what I believe, and not being coached and not being consulted, is what it's all about,'' Edwards told me. ''I would be totally comfortable with myself as a candidate now. I don't need to spend time with advisers.'' He reached for an example. ''What do I think about the killing in Darfur? We have to stop it. That's what I think.''</p>
        <p>The political argument most often and most forcefully proffered online has very little to do with ideology, per se, and everything to do with partisanship. Rather than arguing for any particular agenda, what MoveOn.org and the bloggers demand from Democratic politicians is unwavering opposition to what they see as a corrupt Republican majority and to the supposed capitulation of Washington Democrats. Clinton encounters ambivalence online because she is a fixture of official Washington, and because she continues to emphasize her cooperation with like-minded Republicans. The party's online activists don't want to hear about the compromises it takes to govern; they want someone who will derail the Republican agenda, even if he (or she) has to strap himself to the tracks with two fistfuls of dynamite to do it.</p>
        <p>All this would seem to pose a problem for Warner, who does not make for an especially convincing partisan. He is, at heart, a cooperative, compromising kind of guy -- which, he would argue, is how he managed to get so much done in Virginia. ''I think there are still people of goodwill in both parties,'' he told me at one point. When I asked Warner if the G.O.P. was a corrupt party, as Democratic activists insist it is, he visibly cringed. ''I don't think you can paint with that broad a brush, just as I don't think in the 90's you could paint the Congressional Democrats with that broad a brush,'' he replied.</p>
        <p>When I asked him to assess Bush as a president, Warner went out of his way to praise his handling of the terrorist attacks of 2001, though he said Bush had failed to use that opportunity to ask the American people to sacrifice. He called Bush ''the president of missed opportunities'' -- a valid criticism, perhaps, but not exactly the moral condemnation that Kerry, Dean and other Democrats heaped on Bush during the last campaign, and that a lot of liberal activists long to hear. When I made this point, he shook his head. ''That's not going to be me,'' he said. ''If I choose to go down this path, it's going to be more about what I'm for than what I'm against.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Warner, an unapologetic pro-business Democrat, rejects the reflexive anti-corporatism that permeates much of the populist fervor online. Aides said Warner wants to set up a briefing with the American Enterprise Institute, a conservative policy center, to get its libertarian perspective on policy issues. ''If the move is truly back to old-line 70's populism, then I'm probably not the guy,'' Warner told me, in a variation on what was becoming a familiar theme.</p>
        <p>And yet, Warner, like most of his rivals, intends to make a play for Dean-style Democrats. One of Warner's first hires, even before he left office, was Jerome Armstrong, an architect of Dean's online strategy and the founder of the influential blog MyDD.com, which in 2003 and 2004 spawned many of the other well-trafficked liberal blogs. (Armstrong and Markos Moulitsas Zuniga, the founder of Dailykos.com, invented the term ''Netroots,'' and they have just published a book, ''Crashing the Gate,'' about the emerging power of online activism.) Armstrong's job is to design Warner's Web site -- it will include a miniaturized Warner strolling across your screen as he talks to you, like something out of Willy Wonka -- and to blog for the candidate. Just as important, Armstrong, like the fund-raisers Warner visits, is influential in his own milieu; his role is to give Warner street cred in the blogosphere.</p>
        <p>Over lunch a few months ago at Olives, the popular downtown restaurant for Washington consultants and lobbyists, Armstrong dismissed the idea that Warner was too centrist and bipartisan for the blogosphere. He reminded me that Warner started out as a Democratic fund-raiser and later served as chairman of Virginia's state party before he was governor, an unusual route to elective office that signaled a longstanding party loyalty.</p>
        <p>''Democrats have our backs against the wall with a Republican machine,'' Armstrong said. ''We want to know: are you going to stand with us? Or are you going to act like you're not a part of us?'' The Netroots activists would get their answer, he said, when they saw Warner out in critical states later this year, campaigning hard for Democratic candidates on the state and federal levels. ''Partisanship doesn't always have to deal with calling people names,'' Armstrong said. ''Partisanship can be working hard to elect Democrats and fighting for Democratic principles.''</p>
        <p>In fact, this may not be as wishful as it sounds. In an online poll on the Dailykos site a few weeks after Kaine won the Virginia governor's race last November, Warner, who had been near the bottom of the pack of potential candidates in previous iterations, shot up to third, behind only Clark and Feingold. Of course, the ''poll,'' which compiled the views of 11,000 volunteer respondents, had about as much scientific value as a Bush administration memo on global warming. But it did reflect an awareness that Warner had risked his personal prestige to help get Kaine elected, and that he had succeeded in reviving the Democratic Party in Virginia. For the moment, at least, whether he was soft on the enemy was immaterial; the point was that he knew how to win. To a lot of online activists -- and to Democrats everywhere -- that may yet be the thing that matters most.</p>
        <p>Democratic strategists have a kind of ''silver bullet'' theory of the 2008 race. The thinking goes that if Hillary Clinton is indeed running for president in the fall of 2007, then whoever emerges as the Hillary alternative will have just two shots at beating her, in either Iowa or New Hampshire. As Democrats learned in 2000, when Gore beat back Bradley in the first two contests, and again in 2004, when Kerry surged past Dean and Dick Gephardt in Iowa and never looked back, it is almost impossible to stop an establishment candidate if he or she rolls through the first few primaries. So the insurgent has to hope for an explosion of popular support in that first caucus -- or possibly, a week later, in New Hampshire -- that will send the front-runner reeling backward and puncture the notion that her nomination is preordained. If an insurgent can do that, then the resulting media frenzy might create enough momentum to propel him to victories in subsequent primaries, overwhelming the party apparatus.</p>
        <p>The problem with this theory, it should be said, is that the party's establishment has spent the last 35 years, more or less, making sure it won't be realized. The modern primary process was born in the period before the 1972 campaign, when antiwar activists seized control of the party's nominating rules from the bosses of the old urban machines and put in place a more participatory system, whereby voters would get to choose their candidate directly, rather than delegating the task to a bunch of aging men in a clubhouse. This was a good idea, except that, in just a few years' time, the 60's activists became insiders themselves, and they found, much to their dismay, that primary voters still tended to like outsiders -- even relatively conservative outsiders like Jimmy Carter. And so the story of the last two decades is one of insurgent candidates (Gary Hart, Jesse Jackson, Bill Bradley, Howard Dean) coming perilously close again and again to toppling the party's chosen nominees, while the party regulars respond, periodically, by tinkering with the rules -- collapsing the primary calendar, creating hundreds of ''superdelegates'' who can cast their convention votes however they like -- in order to tighten their hold on the process.</p>
        <p>The result of all these machinations is that an establishment candidate like Clinton can rely on a kind of built-in fire wall. Even if she loses in Iowa or New Hampshire, the process is front-loaded, as they say, so that the campaign immediately becomes a national contest, diffused into large states in every part of the country. This requires both huge sums of money and some amount of star power, as well as lots of surrogates -- that is, governors, senators and the like -- who will fan out across their states to do your campaigning for you.</p>
        <p>In 2008, the party is likely to add contests in a few more racially diverse states before and after the New Hampshire primary. But this, too, would seem to benefit Clinton, since her husband can be expected to campaign hard for her. As Donna Brazile, the veteran organizer who ran Gore's campaign, says, in critical black districts, ''Bill Clinton is beloved, and to the extent that these voters have a chance to cast their votes early in the process, it will be very difficult to stop her nomination.'' Little wonder, then, that when I asked Joe Trippi, the highly-caffeinated Internet genius who orchestrated Dean's insurgency, how Warner or one of the other candidates would go about taking the nomination from Clinton, he actually laughed at me. ''It's not possible,'' he said. ''The way for Mark Warner? Leave the freakin' party.''</p>
        <p>This is why, with almost two years to go before the first votes are cast, some insiders who question Clinton's electability dream of finding yet another candidate who has the national profile and who could generate enough excitement among the base to match her. The question is, Who? ''This sounds absolutely strange coming from me, because I never in life thought I would utter these words again,'' Brazile says, ''but Al Gore.'' It's true that Gore has been a fiery critic of Bush in recent months, but former advisers who still talk to him say he seems genuinely uninterested. Meanwhile, Barack Obama's keynote address to the Florida Democratic Party convention in December was interrupted by delegates who stood up and shouted for him to run in 2008. Obama, a first-term senator, has ruled it out -- at least for now.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, there is still reason to think that the barrier that has historically insulated insider candidates from outsider challenges may yet be breached. The best illustration of this is Dean, who came closer to upending the nominating process than any insurgent candidate since Hart. In gaining enough momentum to become, at one point, the presumed nominee, Dean highlighted two critical changes in American politics in recent years. The first is the proliferation of a cable-TV news media that can, virtually overnight, transform an unknown candidate into a coast-to-coast sensation, neutralizing the value of expensive ads and direct-mail campaigns. The second, and probably more transformative, is the advent of the Web as a fund-raising and organizing tool, which, under the right circumstances, can go a long way toward erasing a front-runner's advantage, especially if the insurgent manages to win one of the early primaries. ''The fire wall is more vulnerable now,'' Susan Estrich says. If Clinton should falter in Iowa or New Hampshire, ''whoever beats her won't have to put out buckets to collect cash. He'll have the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Because of these changes, the process of choosing a candidate is now more democratic, less predictable and harder for the party elite to control than it has been for 20 years. The question for a potential candidate like Mark Warner is just what kind of outsider he intends to be. The problem with Warner's theory of the race -- that he can run, like Carter and Clinton, as a centrist, electable Southern governor -- is that neither Carter nor Clinton had the misfortune of having to unseat a de facto nominee. They ran as outsiders pounding at the door of the party apparatus, but the weary party more or less invited them in. That won't happen in 2008. If Hillary Clinton does decide to run, the best Warner or any other rival can hope for is that this next election will be more like 1984, when Mondale, the insider, had to use every advantage at his disposal, including the superdelegates, to hold off Gary Hart's torrid attack on the interest groups that made up the Democratic establishment.</p>
        <p>It's fine for Warner to say now that he doesn't need purists or populists, that he wants to run a campaign that is about what he's for rather than what he's against. But such aspirations are a luxury generally afforded to front-runners and fools, and Warner is neither. The party's more successful insurgents have all had one thing in common, whether they came from the left or center: each ran hard against the party machine itself. However much Warner may want to avoid this kind of populist appeal, recent history suggests that if you want to emerge as the alternative candidate in 2008, you probably have to be willing to harness and exploit the anger of Democrats who feel disconnected from the Washington establishment and who resent the idea that powerful insiders seem to be choosing a nominee for them. You have to be ready, as an earlier generation of Democrats would have put it, to take on the Man -- even if the Man this time happens to be a woman.</p>
        <p>Matt Bai, a contributing writer who covers national politics for the magazine, is working on a book about Democratic politics.</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  March 15, 2006, Wednesday  The cover photograph in The Times Magazine on Sunday rendered colors incorrectly for the jacket, shirt and tie worn by Mark Warner, the former Virginia governor who is a possible candidate for the presidency. The jacket was charcoal, not maroon; the shirt was light blue, not pink; the tie was dark blue with stripes, not maroon.</p>
        <p>The Times's policy rules out alteration of photographs that depict actual news scenes and, even in a contrived illustration, requires acknowledgment in a credit. In this case, the film that was used can cause colors to shift, and the processing altered them further; the change escaped notice because of a misunderstanding by the editors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: March 15, 2006, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The cover photograph in The Times Magazine on Sunday rendered colors incorrectly for the jacket, shirt and tie worn by Mark Warner, the former Virginia governor who is a possible candidate for the presidency. The jacket was charcoal, not maroon; the shirt was light blue, not pink; the tie was dark blue with stripes, not maroon.</p>
        <p>The Times's policy rules out alteration of photographs that depict actual news scenes and, even in a contrived illustration, requires acknowledgment in a credit. In this case, the film that was used can cause colors to shift, and the processing altered them further; the change escaped notice because of a misunderstanding by the editors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matt Bai, a contributing writer who covers national politics for the magazine, is working on a book about Democratic politics.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
