<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Would You Like A Gas Guzzler With That?</title>
    <meta content="10adco" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/10/business/media/10adco.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fast Food Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sierra Club</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6DA1F3FF933A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Would You Like A Gas Guzzler With That?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Would You Like a Gas Guzzler With That?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melanie Warner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Warner, Melanie</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN General Motors introduced the three-ton, 11-miles-to-the-gallon Hummer H2 four years ago, it redefined American extravagance. But now, with gas prices hovering at $3 a gallon and threatening to go higher, sales of Hummers are declining as Americans become increasingly conscious of gas mileage.</p>
        <p>McDonald's, however, appears not to have gotten the message. This week, the restaurant chain started putting toy Hummers in children's Happy Meal boxes, calling it the ''Hummer of a Summer'' promotion. Television and radio ads, which started running this week, feature a family riding in a Hummer on the way to a McDonald's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>McDonalds has started putting toy Hummers in childrens Happy Meal boxes, calling it the Hummer of a Summer promotion. Not surprisingly, environmental groups are appalled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN General Motors introduced the three-ton, 11-miles-to-the-gallon Hummer H2 four years ago, it redefined American extravagance. But now, with gas prices hovering at $3 a gallon and threatening to go higher, sales of Hummers are declining as Americans become increasingly conscious of gas mileage.</p>
        <p>McDonald's, however, appears not to have gotten the message. This week, the restaurant chain started putting toy Hummers in children's Happy Meal boxes, calling it the ''Hummer of a Summer'' promotion. Television and radio ads, which started running this week, feature a family riding in a Hummer on the way to a McDonald's.</p>
        <p>With enough visits to McDonald's, children will be able to collect eight different Hummers in a variety of colors, including two versions of the H1, the original and most monstrous member of the Hummer family, which General Motors stopped making in June.</p>
        <p>The promotion runs until the end of August and is aimed at young boys. Girls can choose to get Polly Pocket fashion dolls in their Happy Meals instead.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, environmental groups are appalled. Brendan Bell, an energy policy analyst at the Sierra Club, says that Hummers in Happy Meals are about as responsible as ''dipping a Big Mac in the fry oil and serving it to your kids.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell says that McDonald's is trying to make Hummers look cool, but that the vehicles are anything but. ''The technology is passé,'' he said. ''For the H1 and H2, they're running it off an engine that hasn't been fundamentally redesigned since the 1950's. What the next generation needs is better technology in our vehicles so that we can cut our dependence on oil and curb global warming.''</p>
        <p>In a written statement, Bill Lamar, McDonald's chief marketing officer, said the promotion was intended to bring ''the fun and excitement of Hummer vehicles'' to ''McDonald's youngest guests.'' The company did not make anyone available for an interview.</p>
        <p>General Motors says the H2 and H3 benefit from a ''host of advanced technologies'' and that the H2's Vortec ''is one of the most efficient engines in production today.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Davis, president of Sandelman &amp; Associates, a restaurant industry research firm, said that since McDonald's long-term partnership with Disney ended last year, the chain had faced a challenge in finding toys for its Happy Meals. ''They're in a tough position and certainly the toy truck is going to be a popular thing among kids,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>Charlie Miller, a spokesman for Environmental Defense, said he thought that McDonald's might be trying to help an ailing General Motors win some future customers. Sales of the H2, which currently costs about $96 to fill up at the pump, are down 34 percent for the first seven months of this year versus the same period in 2005, and General Motors has sold only 229 H1's this year, according to Autodata, an auto industry statistics firm in Woodcliff Lake, N.J.</p>
        <p>''Anything that sends a message to kids that these are the cool vehicles to buy is the wrong message,'' Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>Consumers have turned away not just from Hummers, but also from other large, gas-hungry vehicles. ''People used to never ask about fuel economy numbers,'' said Jesse Toprak, an analyst at the car-buying site Edmunds.com. ''Now, it's one the primary factors for many people in making car purchase decisions.''</p>
        <p>Twenty-eight percent of sport utility vehicle owners surveyed in October 2005 by AutoPacific Research, a California consulting firm, said they would shift to a different kind of vehicle for their next purchase.</p>
        <p>Some policy analysts say there are reasons other than environmental ones that McDonald's should not be promoting Hummers. Anne Korin, co-director of the Institute for the Analysis of Global Security, a policy research group based in Washington, said that large, inefficient vehicles were unpatriotic and detrimental to America's national security.</p>
        <p>With toy Hummers, McDonald's is ''sending a message to children that utter waste of this precious resource that is causing us such national security problems is O.K.,'' she said.</p>
        <p>McDonald's decision to include Hummers in its Happy Meals is surprising given that the fast-food chain has strived in recent years to bolster its image as an environmentally aware company. It has also promoted healthier menu choices and has avoided introducing indulgent 1,000-calorie-plus items, as some of its rivals have done. The company has also earned praise for its work with animal rights advocates.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
