<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Soft Breezes to Sandblasting Gales</title>
    <meta content="28book" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/28/books/28book.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1757584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">de Villiers, Marq</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Windswept: The Story of Wind and Weather (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">de Villiers, Marq</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Windswept: The Story of Wind and Weather (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D8133FF93BA15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Soft Breezes to Sandblasting Gales</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Soft Breezes to Sandblasting Gales</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews book Windswept: The Story of Wind and Weather by Marq de Villiers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Windswept  The Story of Wind and Weather  By Marq de Villiers  Illustrated. Walker &amp; Company. 344 pages. $25.</p>
        <p>Wind is simple. It is nothing more than air moving between zones of high pressure and low pressure, traveling in a straight line until deflected by the rotation of the earth. Unfortunately things get very complicated after that, as Marq de Villiers explains in ''Windswept: The Story of Wind and Weather,'' his lively, engaging treatise on wind and the weather it makes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marq de Villiers's lively, engaging treatise on wind serves up a little history, a fair amount of science and many colorful stories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Windswept  The Story of Wind and Weather  By Marq de Villiers  Illustrated. Walker &amp; Company. 344 pages. $25.</p>
        <p>Wind is simple. It is nothing more than air moving between zones of high pressure and low pressure, traveling in a straight line until deflected by the rotation of the earth. Unfortunately things get very complicated after that, as Marq de Villiers explains in ''Windswept: The Story of Wind and Weather,'' his lively, engaging treatise on wind and the weather it makes.</p>
        <p>The devil is in the details. As it moves across the earth, wind takes innumerable local detours and appears in a thousand guises, like the sirocco that blows sand from the Sahara as far north as Britain, the mistral that rips tiles off Provençal roofs, the foehn that whistles through the Alps.</p>
        <p>Everywhere felt but nowhere seen, wind can be the merest whisper, barely powerful enough to scatter the seeds of a dandelion, or it can blast with mind-numbing fury, taking the form of a cyclone, tornado, waterspout or hurricane. A hurricane that today would be classified as Category 5 struck the Florida Keys in 1935 and sandblasted some of its victims into particles, leaving only bones, leather belts and shoes.</p>
        <p>Like other ''ingredient'' books, which treat single topics -- like codfish, oak or clay -- almost as if they were biographical subjects, ''Windswept'' serves up a little history, a fair amount of science and many colorful stories. Mr. de Villiers, the co-author of ''Sahara'' and ''Sable Island,'' blends these elements with a skillful hand.</p>
        <p>He explains the science clearly, and he describes the workings of wind, weather and the natural world with enormous gusto. He is a greedy observer, with plenty of wind and storms to watch from his seaside home in Eagle Head, Nova Scotia.</p>
        <p>Simply as a catalog of statistics, ''Windswept'' is a grabber. In one day a moderate hurricane releases the energy equivalent of 400 20-megaton nuclear bombs: enough, if converted to electricity, to power New England for a decade. Even during a powerful storm, in an open field with no obstructions, the wind velocity at ground level is zero. Fungal spores and bacterial cysts riding on African sand travel as far as the Caribbean, where they are destroying coral. That same dust accounts for the red sunrises in Miami.</p>
        <p>Wind is perplexing and always has been. Aristotle was stumped. He argued that it was absurd to think that wind was flowing air. That would mean that all winds were one wind since all air is one air, a self-evident absurdity, like saying that all rivers are the same river. As late as the 17th century Dr. Martin Lister proposed that the trade winds were caused by the breathing of seaweed.</p>
        <p>Sailors, for their part, ignored the philosophers and developed a rough, practical understanding of winds and storms. Columbus, after experiencing just one hurricane in the Caribbean, knew enough to recognize the warning signs of the second one. But neither he nor anyone else understood that weather traveled. ''Even the most apocalyptic storms were thought to develop, wreak havoc and then dissipate, in one place,'' Mr. de Villiers writes.</p>
        <p>In time, scientists mapped the winds. But the complex interactions of wind and weather, and the maddening unpredictability of both, still keep them busy. The broad patterns are fairly well understood, but in a sense all weather is local. On Corsica, in the Mediterranean, to take a striking example, there can be gale-force winds on its west coast while the east coast is calm and an unrelated gale blows in the Strait of Bonifacio, three places only a dozen miles apart.</p>
        <p>In a running subplot Mr. de Villiers tracks the course of Hurricane Ivan, which came to life in spring 2004 as a turbulent air system in the Darfur region of Sudan, slowly made its way across the Atlantic to the Caribbean and, with erratic zigs and zags, slammed the Gulf Coast and split, one half heading all the way up the Eastern seaboard to Mr. de Villiers's home in Nova Scotia. Along the way Ivan reached Category 5 three times, the only recorded hurricane ever to do so. The storm that devastated Galveston, Tex., in 1900 made it all the way to Europe and onward to Siberia.</p>
        <p>Small local events can translate into big changes in the nature and direction of a storm. Mr. de Villiers gives a sympathetic account of how weather data is gathered, and notes its increasing accuracy, while conceding that prediction remains half art, half science.</p>
        <p>Wind, as the sailors in ''The Odyssey'' found out when they untied the wind-filled bags given by Aeolus, can be full of surprises. In 2002 a team of wind-tunnel researchers tried to unravel the mysteries of the hellish winds that torment players at the 12th hole at Augusta National golf course. The scientists created a scale model of the so-called Amen Corner, with tiny trees and tiny people (all men, presumably) and artificial wind. After painstaking study, they concluded that there was no relation between the prevailing winds and the winds that blew over the hole, so golfers teeing off might as well pray.</p>
        <p>Maddening, unpredictable wind might offer a way out of the global energy crisis however. Mr. de Villiers concludes by examining the debate over global warming and the commercial potential of wind farms. He is lucid and skeptical. Both sides exaggerate shamelessly. But look to the Danes, who have designed quiet, stylish windmills that generate nearly all of the renewable-source energy that accounts for 27 percent of that country's power.</p>
        <p>The wind still bloweth where it listeth, but everybody has some, and some have a lot. In a beautiful, wind-powered world, Scotland could be the new Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
