<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Exit Date From Blair, Who Tells Critics to Stop 'Obsessing'</title>
    <meta content="02britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/02/world/europe/02britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1786925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Times of London</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Labor Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Gordon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cameron, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Blunkett, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DE1F3EF931A3575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Exit Date From Blair, Who Tells Critics to Stop 'Obsessing'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Exit Date From Blair, Who Tells Critics to Stop ‘Obsessing’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Tony Blair, in interview published in Times of London, castigates his foes and tells them to stop 'obsessing' about possible duration of his tenure and get on with business of government; his remarks draw renewed protests from Labor legislators and labor unionists urging Blair to set timetable for his departure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a summer of grumbles about Tony Blair, Britain's political season got under way Friday to a familiar libretto: The prime minister said he would not be quitting any time soon; his adversaries within his own party said he should.</p>
        <p>In an interview published in The Times of London, Mr. Blair castigated his foes and told them to stop ''obsessing'' about the possible duration of his tenure and ''get on with the business of government.'' His remarks drew renewed protests from Labor legislators and labor unionists urging Mr. Blair to set a timetable for his departure. The bookmaker company William Hill shortened the odds on Mr. Blair's resigning in 2007.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The British prime minister said he would not be quitting any time soon, while his adversaries within his own party said he should.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a summer of grumbles about Tony Blair, Britain's political season got under way Friday to a familiar libretto: The prime minister said he would not be quitting any time soon; his adversaries within his own party said he should.</p>
        <p>In an interview published in The Times of London, Mr. Blair castigated his foes and told them to stop ''obsessing'' about the possible duration of his tenure and ''get on with the business of government.'' His remarks drew renewed protests from Labor legislators and labor unionists urging Mr. Blair to set a timetable for his departure. The bookmaker company William Hill shortened the odds on Mr. Blair's resigning in 2007.</p>
        <p>The timing of Mr. Blair's remarks was significant. Later this month, he faces the annual conference of his Labor Party, now in its ninth year of office and showing signs of the third-term fatigue to which British administrations have often been heir. The divisions within the party have deepened, particularly over Mr. Blair's close alliance with President Bush in dealings with the Muslim world and what has been depicted by critics as a tilt toward Israel in the latest war.</p>
        <p>Some among his foes had urged him to use the conference to announce a schedule for redeeming a two-year-old pledge to step down as Labor Party leader -- and thus as prime minister -- before the next national election, to be held by 2010.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blair declined to commit to a formal schedule. ''I've said I won't fight another election,'' he told The Times of London.</p>
        <p>He added, ''If people want stable and orderly change they should not keep obsessing about it in the meantime, but instead, get on with the business of government.''</p>
        <p>The debate reflects a concern among some Laborites that Mr. Blair has become an electoral liability and should make way for his anointed successor, Gordon Brown, the chancellor of the exchequer. ''If an election was run tomorrow,'' said Tony Woodley, a prominent labor union leader, ''Labor would be most likely to lose.''</p>
        <p>He declared, ''The sooner we do it the better now.''</p>
        <p>The calls for Mr. Blair's departure come from within his own party. The opposition Conservatives, buoyed by a recent poll showing they command 40 percent of the vote, seem happy to bide their time. The Conservative strategy suggests that they are focusing on burnishing the image of their leader of nine months, David Cameron.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Blair debated his future, Mr. Cameron spent Friday burnishing his ecological credentials, addressing a joint news conference with an environmental group and urging the creation of a new law on climate change.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has not recently been embroiled in the succession debate.</p>
        <p>The extent of support for the Labor rebellion against Mr. Blair is difficult to gauge, as the contest over his future is generally fought out in surreptitious background briefings by the protagonists or their champions. Currently, the word from such oracles is, according to The Guardian on Friday, that Mr. Blair wants another year or so and would announce a timetable for his departure before the local elections set for next May, then quit during the summer.</p>
        <p>David Blunkett, a former cabinet minister, urged Labor supporters to give Mr. Blair time to orchestrate his departure in a leisurely and ''perfectly civilized way.''</p>
        <p>''We have got three and a half years before the general election, and I am absolutely certain discussions have taken place with very, very senior colleagues ensuring that there will be a lengthy period before that general election date had to be chosen,'' he told BBC radio.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blair's standing at home has been damaged by his decision to lead Britain into an unpopular conflict in Iraq and by seeming to be an excessively pliant junior partner in his dealings with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>During the summer he ignored demands from his followers to urge an immediate cease-fire in Lebanon or label Israel's military tactics as disproportionate. Some critics also questioned his decision to remain in the Caribbean while Britain went through one of its highest security alerts after the discovery of what the police called a conspiracy to bomb trans-Atlantic airliners.</p>
        <p>But he has spoken dismissively of those who demand a schedule for his departure, effectively challenging them to show their hand or be silent before the Labor Party conference.</p>
        <p>''I really think it is absurd for the people who say we must stop this continual speculation about the leadership to continue to speculate about it,'' he told The Times of London. ''I have done what no other prime minister has done before me. I've said I'm not going to go on and on, and said I'll leave ample time for my successor.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
