<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paperback Row</title>
    <meta content="29bestpaper-1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D6153FF93AA15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paperback Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ihsan Taylor</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FREE WORLD: America, Europe, and the Surprising Future of the West, by Timothy Garton Ash. (Vintage, $14.95.) In this eloquent call for trans-Atlantic unity, Garton Ash, an Oxford scholar and self-described ''historian of the present,'' builds his case on a close reading of American and European history since World War II, and highlights several concerns -- terrorism, global warming, poverty in the developing world -- that should unite both sides of the Atlantic. Our reviewer, Serge Schmemann, said Garton Ash ''is a wonderful writer, with a bottomless bag of anecdotes, quotes, historical precedents and pithy judgments.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FREE WORLD: America, Europe, and the Surprising Future of the West, by Timothy Garton Ash. (Vintage, $14.95.) In this eloquent call for trans-Atlantic unity, Garton Ash, an Oxford scholar and self-described ''historian of the present,'' builds his case on a close reading of American and European history since World War II, and highlights several concerns -- terrorism, global warming, poverty in the developing world -- that should unite both sides of the Atlantic. Our reviewer, Serge Schmemann, said Garton Ash ''is a wonderful writer, with a bottomless bag of anecdotes, quotes, historical precedents and pithy judgments.''</p>
        <p>THE MEMORY OF RUNNING, by Ron McLarty. (Penguin, $14.) McLarty's first novel follows a picaresque hero's recovery from loneliness. Going through his parents' possessions after their sudden deaths, Smithson Ide, known as Smithy, a 43-year-old Vietnam veteran, learns that his long-lost sister has turned up in a Los Angeles morgue. Getting on his childhood bicycle, the 279-pound Smithy leaves his home in Rhode Island, eventually pedaling cross-country to reclaim her body. Chapters alternate between Smithy's on-the-road adventures and Ide family history. Bonnie Marson explores the transformative power of music in her first novel, SLEEPING WITH SCHUBERT (Ballantine, $13.95). Her heroine, a lawyer in present-day Brooklyn, is inhabited by the spirit of the 19th-century composer Franz Schubert, and her debut performance on a department store piano leads to a full-fledged world tour.</p>
        <p>TATTOO FOR A SLAVE, by Hortense Calisher. (Harvest/ Harcourt, $14.) Calisher's elliptical memoir stretches across two centuries, and wrestles with a grim legacy as she comes to believe that her family -- Southern, German and Jewish -- may have been slaveholders.</p>
        <p>QUEEN OF SCOTS: The True Life of Mary Stuart, by John Guy. (Mariner/Houghton Mifflin, $16.95.) A great-granddaughter of Henry VII, Mary Stuart was crowned queen of Scots before her first birthday in 1543 and married the French dauphin at 15. In Guy's scrupulous account, Mary was a shrewd and charismatic young ruler who had to cope with scheming Protestant noblemen and the wrath of her cousin, Elizabeth I of England. (Elizabeth's prisoner for 18 years, Mary was executed in 1587.) ''Guy's scholarly biography, as enthralling as a detective story, provides a wider vision of Tudor history and shows with stunning clarity how the historical narrative was shaped,'' Gerard Kilroy wrote here.</p>
        <p>NEW AND SELECTED POEMS, by Michael Ryan. (Mariner/ Houghton Mifflin, $14.) This collection represents three decades of work, gathering together new poems with selections from three previous volumes. Cruelty, pain and the inescapability of our past are recurring themes; in ''The Use of Poetry,'' a free-verse narrative blends the tragic (a child's disappearance) with the trivial (Christmas party chitchat).</p>
        <p>STEALING GOD'S THUNDER: Benjamin Franklin's Lightning Rod and the Invention of America, by Philip Dray. (Random House, $14.95.) This compact, absorbing book deals first and foremost with the invention of the lightning rod, but it also does justice to Franklin's curiosity about smallpox, botany, wood-burning stoves, musical glass disks, mesmerism, fossils and ballooning. In EDISON AND THE ELECTRIC CHAIR: A Story of Light and Death (Walker, $15), Mark Essig recounts the race between Thomas Edison and George Westinghouse to build an electrical empire in the 1880's, and Edison's furtive contribution to the invention and use of the electric chair.</p>
        <p>SIGHTSEEING: Stories, by Rattawut Lapcharoensap. (Grove, $12.) The seven stories in this dazzling debut are set in Thailand, where Lapcharoensap, now 26, has lived much of his life. His narrators, spirited and idiosyncratic, tap into both the Thailand of Westerners' dreams and the Thailand plagued by social and economic inequality. ''Cockfighter,'' about a young girl whose father trains fighting cocks, displays the author's gift for quick details that capture not only his Thai milieu, but teenage life everywhere. ''When he's really going strong, Lapcharoensap is a commanding, animated tour guide,'' Darin Strauss wrote here.</p>
        <p>LEONARDO DA VINCI: Flights of the Mind, by Charles Nicholl. (Penguin, $18.) Nicholl vividly tells Leonardo's well-known life story. He pores over Leonardo's manuscripts, searching for ''the real man, who lived in real time'' as opposed to ''Leonardo the superhuman.'' Our reviewer, David Gelernter, called Nicholl ''witty, penetrating and fetchingly romantic.''</p>
        <p>Ihsan Taylor</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
