<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE LISTINGS | APRIL 28-MAY 4</title>
    <meta content="28thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060429T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1757565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D9133FF93BA15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="15377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE LISTINGS | APRIL 28-MAY 4</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater  Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BRUNDIBAR' and 'BUT THE GIRAFFE, A CURTAIN RAISER TO HANS KRASA'S 'BRUNDIBAR' ' Previews start today. Opens May 7. Tony Kushner has written a new adaptation of Hans Krasa's World War II-era libretto about a brother and a sister who join forces with three talking animals to outwit a sinister organ grinder. Maurice Sendak has designed the sets, and Euan Morton stars. ''But the Giraffe,'' a curtain raiser, is a new short by Mr. Kushner. (1:35). New Victory Theater, 209 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE CAINE MUTINY COURT-MARTIAL' In previews. Opens May 7. Try not to think of Ross from ''Friends'' when you see David Schwimmer in this revival of Herman Wouk's adaptation of his Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about a lawyer who defends a Navy lieutenant accused of mutiny. With Tim Daly and Zeljko Ivanek. Jerry Zaks directs (2:15). The Gerald Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'CIRQUE DU SOLEIL -- CORTEO' In previews. Opens Thursday. A clown imagines his own festive funeral procession in the latest extravaganza from this ever-growing Canadian circus troupe. It features 55 artists from 16 countries (2:30). Grand Chapiteau at Randall's Island, (800) 678-5440.</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' In previews. Opens Monday. This little-musical-that-could about an unscrupulous Broadway producer in the 1920's (some things never change) began at the Toronto Fringe Festival and now makes its unlikely premiere on the Great White Way. Directed by Casey Nicholaw (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'FAITH HEALER' In previews. Opens Thursday. Ralph Fiennes, Cherry Jones and Ian McDiarmid make up the dream cast of this revival of Brian Friel's classic collection of Rashomonesque monologues about a man peddling salvation, his long-suffering wife and his manager (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FAUST, PARTS I AND II' In previews. Opens Sunday. Target Margin stages an ambitious new six-hour translation of Goethe's epic. David Herskovits directs (6:00). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' In previews. Opens Sunday. Earth, Wind and Fire get in on the jukebox musical trend with this new show about a woman who dreams of dancing on Broadway. Maurice Hines directs and choreographs (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' In previews. Opens Wednesday. The Atlantic Theater Company's acclaimed production of Martin McDonagh's very bloody, exceptionally black comedy about Irish terrorism moves to Broadway (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' Previews start tomorrow. Opens May 10. Nilaja Sun plays teachers, students and janitors in the Epic Theater Center's one-woman examination of the public school system. Hal Brooks directs (1:10). Beckett Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SHINING CITY' In previews. Opens May 9. A guilt-ridden man tells his therapist that he has seen the ghost of his wife in Conor McPherson's new play, which received good reviews at the Royal Court in London. Brian F. O'Byrne, Martha Plimpton and Oliver Platt star (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SORE THROATS' In previews. Opens Sunday. Theater for a New Audience presents a revival of Howard Brenton's Strindbergian study of what happens to a 39-year-old housewife when her marriage falls apart. (2:10). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPALDING GRAY MATTER' Previews start Wednesday. Opens May 6. In a New Group production, the solo artist Michael Brandt explores the tragic final days of Spalding Gray and their parallels to his own life (1:10). Clurman Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' In previews. Opens May 10. Phil Collins lends his invisible touch to the score of the latest Disney musical. David Henry Hwang wrote the book (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'AWAKE AND SING!' Dreams and disappointments, hopes and fears, encouraging words and bitter put-downs clash by day and night in Clifford Odets's turbulent comedy-drama about a Jewish family struggling to stay afloat in the 1930's. A gifted roster of performers -- including Mark Ruffalo, Lauren Ambrose, Zoë Wanamaker and Ben Gazzara -- manage to locate the dreaming centers of their characters, buried beneath layers of political sloganeering, everyday gripes or street slang. And even when the focus occasionally blurs in Bartlett Sher's ultimately moving revival, Odets's zesty dialogue, in which jazzy period colloquialisms are slung around like punches at a prize fight, is a joy to hear (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'BAREFOOT IN THE PARK' For a work that celebrates the liberating force of spontaneity, this revival of Neil Simon's 1963 comedy doesn't have one scene that feels organic, let alone impromptu. Directed by Scott Elliott, and starring Patrick Wilson and a miscast Amanda Peet as newlyweds in Greenwich Village, this ''Barefoot'' has the robotic gait of Frankenstein's monster (2:20). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York City, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FESTEN' An intensely staged, indifferently acted production of David Eldridge's adaptation of a 1998 Danish film about a grim family reunion, which was a big hit in London under the same director, Rufus Norris. While the mise en scène remains unsettlingly stark, the Broadway cast (which includes Michael Hayden, Julianna Margulies, Jeremy Sisto and Ali MacGraw) registers the tension and testiness of people suffering from a collective bad hair day. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' Madly enjoyable. Alan's Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LESTAT' A musical sleeping pill, adapted from Anne Rice's ''Vampire Chronicles'' and featuring songs by Elton John and Bernie Taupin, that could well give the makers of Ambien a run for their money. Dare to look upon this tale of the undead and keep your eyelids from growing heavier and heavier and heavier (2:30). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, near 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Odd is not the word for this couple. How could an adjective suggesting strangeness or surprise apply to a production so calculatedly devoted to the known, the cozy, the conventional? As the title characters in Neil Simon's 1965 comedy, directed as if to a metronome by Joe Mantello, Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick reprise their star performances from ''The Producers,'' and it's not a natural fit. Don't even consider killing yourself because the show is already sold out (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PAJAMA GAME' Sexual chemistry in a Broadway musical? Isn't that illegal now? If it were, then Harry Connick Jr. and Kelli O'Hara -- the white-hot stars of Kathleen Marshall's delicious revival of this 1954 musical -- would be looking at long jail terms. This intoxicating production, which features a charming supporting cast led by Michael McKean, allows grown-up audiences the rare chance to witness a bona fide adult love affair translated into hummable songs and sprightly dance (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THREE DAYS OF RAIN' (2:30). In this revival of Richard Greenberg's slender, elegant drama of family disconnectedness, Julia Roberts is stiff with self-consciousness, glancingly acquainted with the two characters she plays and deeply, disturbingly beautiful. Otherwise, it is almost impossible to discern the virtues of the play itself in this wooden and splintered production, directed by Joe Mantello and also starring Paul Rudd and Bradley Cooper, who have little chance of capturing the audience's attention (2:30). Bernard B. Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Presented as a long, pansexual orgy, Scott Elliot's numbing revival of the Brecht-Weill classic feels like a party where the hangover begins almost as soon as the evening does. The starry cast includes Alan Cumming (as Mac the Knife) and a Dietrich-like Cyndi Lauper, though only Jim Dale and Nellie McKay appear to have a clue as to what the show is about (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did on Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'WELL' Lisa Kron's sparkling autobiographical play about illness, integration and her mother (portrayed with majestic warmth and weariness by Jayne Houdyshell) helps restore the honor of that tarnished literary form, the memoir. Though it shows the strain of scaling up for Broadway, this singular work, which stars Ms. Kron as herself, opens windows of insight and emotion found in no other show (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ASSISTED LOVING' This warm and witty monologue by Bob Morris, who contributes the Age of Dissonance column to the Sunday Style section of The New York Times, is performed by the author, who chronicles his widowed father's and his own search for love in and around New York. Engaging, subtle and winning (1:10). Daryl Roth Theater, D-Lounge, 103 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200.(George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'BASED ON A TOTALLY TRUE STORY' A chatty, autobiographical comedy by Roberto Aguirre-Sacasa about a writer for comic books who moonlights as a screenwriter and playwright. Juggling his two jobs, the busy writer begins backsliding in his unofficial third, ''being a loving, giving, emotionally available boyfriend.'' Minor-key angst ensues in this perky two hours of comic navel-gazing (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE CONTRAST' Royall Tyler's slender 1787 romantic comedy -- one of the first professional American plays ever produced -- should be of more interest to historians than to theatergoers (2:30). Theater at St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Jason Zinoman).</p>
        <p>'DEFIANCE' The second in John Patrick Shanley's cycle of morality plays that began with ''Doubt,'' this ambitious tale of racial relations and the military mindset on a North Carolina marine base feels both overcrowded and oddly diffuse. If ''Doubt'' has an elegant and energy-efficient sprinter's gait, ''Defiance'' progresses with a flustered air of distraction. The excellent Margaret Colin, as an officer's wife, provides a welcome shot of credibility (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club, Theater 1, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' This noisy novelty is a mixed blessing. Providing a two-foot drum on every seat, it offers an opportunity to exorcise aggressions by delivering a good beating, and, on a slightly more elevated level, it presents a superficial introduction to African culture, lessons in drumming and 90 minutes of nonstop music, song and dancing by a good-natured cast. So, while literally and figuratively giving off many good vibes, it adds up to lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'ENTERTAINING MR. SLOANE' Scott Ellis's underpowered production of Joe Orton's great farce of sexual hypocrisy, which stars Alec Baldwin in a comedy sketch of a performance, is breezy, often funny and rarely convincing. (2:00). Laura Pels Theater at the Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE M. COHAN TONIGHT!' The all-singing, all-dancing Jon Peterson summons the spirit of this legendary Broadway entertainer in this engaging one-man musical, devised and directed by Chip Deffaa (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'GUARDIANS' Peter Morris's play juxtaposes the moral decline of two disparate characters caught up in the destructive tailwinds of the American invasion of Iraq: a cold-blooded tabloid journalist in London and a soldier in the United States Army. Lee Pace and Katherine Moennig give persuasive performances as the sleazy hack and the scapegoated grunt, but Mr. Morris's play is more flashily provocative than truly thoughtful (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 253-9983. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE IMPORTANCE OF BEING EARNEST' Lynn Redgrave is an unusually vigorous Lady Bracknell in Sir Peter Hall's new production of Oscar Wilde's peerless comedy from 1895. A satisfactory production that works effectively as a romantic farce but more erratically as a vehicle for Wilde's paradox-perfumed wit. (2:25) Brooklyn Academy of Music, Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best. (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'LANDSCAPE OF THE BODY' This terrific revival, directed by Michael Greif, identifies the unbearable wistfulness of being in John Guare's delirious heartbreaker of a comedy from 1977. The top-flight cast is led by Lili Taylor and Sherie Rene Scott as sisters -- one living, one a singing ghost -- who move in and out of a lyrical and sordid world where tabloid prurience has become a religion. Signature Theater's Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LOS BIG NAMES' In the lesbian comic Marga Gomez's friendly new solo show, she measures out affection and mockery in equal doses as she recalls her parents, Willy and Margarita, a comedian and a dancer who lived a splashy life on a small scale in the circumscribed world of New York Latino culture in the 1960's. Ms. Gomez pairs stories of their performing careers with comic tales of her own struggles to pursue success in the entertainment industry. A sendup of the movie ''Sphere'' is particularly delicious (1:30). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MACRUNE'S GUEVARA' The Young Mirror arm of Mirror Repertory revives John Spurling's odd 1969 play about an artist who left behind a wall full of drawings of Che Guevara, and the man who saw something profound in them. Parts of the play read today like a funny sendup of art critics who see too much brilliance in outsider-art gibberish; other parts seem a bit like gibberish of their own (2:15). St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE MISTAKES MADELINE MADE' An unhappy office worker rebels by boycotting bathing in Elizabeth Meriwether's frenetic new comedy, which reveals some compelling theatrical moments but doesn't totally cohere (1:20). Culture Project, 45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Zinoman).</p>
        <p>'THE PROPERTY KNOWN AS GARLAND' Adrienne Barbeau as Judy, backstage on the night of her last concert in Copenhagen. Billy Van Zandt's play is tawdry and dull, and Ms. Barbeau's performance offers neither the minor rewards of a decent impersonation nor the guilty pleasures of an indecent one. (1:30). The Actors Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'RED LIGHT WINTER' A frank, occasionally graphic story of erotic fixation and the havoc it can wreak on sensitive types. Written and directed by Adam Rapp, this play is both a doomy romantic drama and a morbid comedy about the anxieties of male friendship. Although somewhat contrived, it features a lovely performance by Christopher Denham as a lonely soul starved for intimacy (2:25). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'STUFF HAPPENS' Daniel Sullivan's sharp, invigorating production of David Hare's journalistic drama about the road to war in Iraq is conducted on the modest scale of a town-hall meeting. The characters (who have names like Bush and Blair) seem less like destiny-shaping gods than the ego trippers in your office. If that means they're too close for comfort, then ''Stuff Happens'' is doing its job (2:50). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TRYST' A suspense drama of a distinctly old-fashioned stamp about the romance between a handsome cad (Maxwell Caulfield) and a lonely spinster (Amelia Campbell). Will the wily predator seduce and abandon the mousy milliner? Karoline Leach's play springs a few twists that lack psychological credibility but keep the plot on the boil (2:00). Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ADVENTURES OF CAVEMAN ROBOT: THE MUSICAL' A disjointed but vivid homage and musical parody, by Jeff Lewonczyk and Debby Schwartz, of comic books and superheroes. Sloppy and long, too (2:10). Brick Theater, 575 Metropolitan Avenue, at Lorimer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 907-3457. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'CHAMPION' and 'THE STUTTERING PREACHER' Two new one-act plays, one a well-drawn family drama and the other a brash and ribald romantic comedy, from the New Federal Theater and Black Spectrum Theater. Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Hunka)  'GREY GARDENS' As the socialite in limbo called ''Little'' Edie Beale, Christine Ebersole gives one of the most gorgeous performances ever to grace a musical. Unfortunately, she's a pearl of incalculable price in a show that is mostly costume jewelry. Adapted from the Maysles brothers' 1975 cult documentary movie, a camp favorite, and directed by Michael Greif, with the excellent Mary Louise Wilson as Edie's bedridden mother (2:40). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RING OF FIRE' The man in black turns sunshine yellow in a show that strings songs associated with Johnny Cash into a big, bright candy necklace of a musical revue, created and directed by Richard Maltby Jr. In the current bio-flick ''Walk the Line,'' Cash wrestles demons; ''Ring of Fire'' wrestles with a really bad case of the cutes (2:00). Ethel Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A SAFE HARBOR FOR ELIZABETH BISHOP' The life of a great poet becomes the stuff of stale prose in this one-woman bio-play by Marta Góes, starring Amy Irving (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOW PEOPLE' Paul Weitz's eyebrow-pencil-thin comedy about a man who hires actors to impersonate his family feels like one long, occasionally amusing party game whose players don't know when to call it a night. The excellent four-member cast, led by Debra Monk and directed by Peter Askin, finds charm and energy amid the vaporous bait-and-switch plot reversals (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 353-0303; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN DREAMZ' (PG-13, 107 minutes) In Paul Weitz's seriously unfunny comedy about a faltering American president, a wildly popular television talent show and the Svengalis behind them both, the jokes don't just fizzle into insignificance; they flop about with gaudy ineffectualness. With Hugh Grant, Dennis Quaid and Mandy Moore. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ATL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) A couple of rap stars make respectable starts on acting careers in this tale of black teenagers in Atlanta, despite a script marred by clichés and predictability. Tip Harris -- the rapper T. I. -- is intriguing as a young man who takes on the responsibility of raising his younger brother when their parents are killed, and Antwan Andre Patton -- Big Boi from OutKast -- makes a terrific drug lord. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BEAUTY ACADEMY OF KABUL' (No rating, 74 minutes, in English and Dari) In the summer of 2004, a group of volunteer American hairstylists arrived in Kabul to open a school. In ''The Beauty Academy of Kabul,'' the director Liz Mermin documents the hilarious, moving and sometimes fractious meeting of diametrically different cultures, one having suffered unimaginable horrors and the other believing a good perm is the answer to everything. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'DEVIL AND DANIEL JOHNSTON' (PG-13, 110 minutes) The romantic cliché that all artists are a little bit mad is put through its paces (if never seriously questioned) in this documentary about Daniel Johnston, a mentally ill songwriter whom Kurt Cobain, the lead singer for Nirvana, once called the greatest living. Jeff Feuerzeig, who won the best director award at the 2005 Sundance Film Festival, cobbles together a moving portrait of the artist as his own ghost, using a wealth of material provided by Mr. Johnston, from home movies to audiocassette diaries to dozens of original, and often heartbreakingly beautiful, songs. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'DRAWING RESTRAINT 9' (No rating, 135 minutes) Most of this stately film of few words, conceived and directed by the artist Matthew Barney, who stars with his wife, Bjork, takes place on a Japanese whaling ship afloat in Nagasaki Bay. Steeped not only in Japanese seafaring lore but also in centuries-old traditions of Japanese ritual, the film could be described as Mr. Barney's ''Moby-Dick.'' (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'ICE AGE: THE MELTDOWN' (PG, 93 minutes) Creative exhaustion haunts ''Ice Age: The Meltdown,'' as the characters from 2002's ''Ice Age'' face global warming and the submersion of their valley. While the animals head for safety in a giant, arklike boat, the director, Carlos Saldanha, indulges in biblical imagery and bad science. Over all, a flat and uninspired follow-up to a vastly superior movie. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INSIDE MAN' (R, 128 minutes) The latest from Spike Lee takes a familiar setup -- in this case, a Wall Street bank heist that mutates into a hostage crisis -- and twists it ever so slightly and nicely. Among the film's most sustained pleasures are its holy trinity -- Denzel Washington, Clive Owen and Jodie Foster -- and the best lineup of pusses and mugs outside ''The Sopranos.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'KINKY BOOTS' (PG-13, 106 minutes) In this silly, quasi-inspirational British comedy, a staid shoe factory in Northern England avoids ruin by switching from the manufacture of men's dress shoes to that of thigh-high, stiletto-heeled boots worn by drag queens. The recipe for this feel-good movie, which cries out to be made into a musical, comes from the same cookbook that gave us ''The Full Monty.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'L'ENFANT (THE CHILD)' (R, 100 minutes, in French) The latest from the Belgian brothers Jean-Pierre and Luc Dardenne involves a young thief (Jérémie Renier) who one day sells his newborn son for a fat envelope of cash. What interests the Dardennes -- what invests their work with such terrific urgency -- is not only how a man would sell a child as casually as a slab of beef, but also whether a man like this, having committed such a repellent offense, can find redemption. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LUCKY NUMBER SLEVIN' (R, 110 minutes) This star-studded jigsaw puzzle of revenge and mistaken identity thinks that it's terribly smart, although it amounts to an empty, self-satisfied imitation of ''Pulp Fiction'' that reputable actors like Morgan Freeman and Ben Kingsley can't salvage. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NOTORIOUS BETTIE PAGE' (R, 91 minutes) With the help of her charmingly enthusiastic star, Gretchen Mol, the director Mary Harron unwraps the great 1950's pinup queen Bettie Page, who for years was a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside a web of expertly tied rope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SCARY MOVIE 4' (PG-13, 83 minutes) This parasitic franchise is back to feed on last year's disposable distractions, proving, if nothing else, that there's a laugh or two left in ''Brokeback Mountain'' parodies and Viagra overdoses. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE SENTINEL' (PG-13, 108 minutes) The question is why: why would a star of Michael Douglas's stature and obvious intelligence attach himself to a Washington thriller as deeply ridiculous, suspense-free and potentially career-damaging as ''The Sentinel''? (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'SIR! NO SIR!' (No rating, 84 minutes) In this smart, very timely documentary, the filmmaker David Zeiger revisits one of the memorable and least revisited chapters of the Vietnam War, the antiwar movement inside the military. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SISTERS IN LAW' (No rating, 106 minutes, in English and pidgin) Grass-roots feminism thrives in a Cameroon village, thanks to the pair of warmhearted, tough-minded women of law profiled in this excellent verité documentary. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'SOMERSAULT' (No rating, 106 minutes) The story of a beautiful 16-year-old runaway (an astonishing lead performance by Abbie Cornish) was garlanded by 13 awards by the Australian Film Institute. Cool-headed and emotionally distanced from its characters, it trains an X-ray eye on their precarious balancing of civilized and bestial impulses. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'TAKE THE LEAD' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Hip-hop and ballroom dancing styles fuse in a South Bronx high school at which a dance teacher, Antonio Banderas, turns gawky ducklings into gliding swans. It's sloppy but mildly endearing. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THANK YOU FOR SMOKING' (R, 92 minutes) The director Jason Reitman has made a glib and funny movie from Christopher Buckley's glib and funny novel about a Big Tobacco lobbyist, but the real attraction here is the hard-working star, Aaron Eckhart. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'V FOR VENDETTA' (R, 131 minutes) James McTeigue directs this D-for-dumb future-shock story about a masked avenger (Hugo Weaving) and his pipsqueak sidekick (Natalie Portman) at war against a totalitarian British regime. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE WILD' (G, 94 minutes) Filled with softness and texture, ''The Wild'' follows Samson the lion (voiced by Kiefer Sutherland) as he escapes from the zoo to rescue his cub, who has stowed away on a ship bound for Africa. With inspired voice work from Eddie Izzard as a pukka koala and William Shatner as a menacing wildebeest, the movie also finds time to explore the travails of single fatherhood and the evils of oppression. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BAC 40TH INTERNATIONAL FILM AND VIDEO FESTIVAL (Through May 7) The Brooklyn Arts Council's festival of work by independent and student filmmakers continues this weekend. Tomorrow and Sunday's screenings include Micah Schaffer's ''Death of Two Sons,'' about Amadou Diallo and a Peace Corps volunteer who lived with his family; Kevin Burget's ''Harold Weston: A Bigger Belief in Beauty,'' a portrait of Weston, the Modernist painter; and ''Sometimes the Silence Can Seem So Loud: Teen Suicide,'' an 18-minute documentary with almost a dozen directors. Brooklyn Museum, Cantor Auditorium, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 625-0080 ; most screenings free with museum admission. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>THE FILMS OF MIKIO NARUSE (Through May 10) BAMcinématek's tribute to Naruse (1905-69), the Japanese realist filmmaker, continues tonight with ''Sound of the Mountain'' (1954), Naruse's own personal favorite, about an ignored housewife who bonds with her father-in-law. Tomorrow's feature is ''Repast'' (1951), also about an unhappy housewife. ''Mother'' (1952), the story of a struggling single mother, will be shown on Sunday. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 17) The IFC Center's weekend series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''I Live in Fear'' (1955), starring Toshiro Mifune as an elderly man obsessed with the prospect of nuclear war. Other films in the series will include Kurosawa's classics ''Ran'' (1985), May 12 through 14; ''Rashomon'' (1950), May 19 through 21; ''Seven Samurai'' (1954), May 26 through 29; and ''Yojimbo'' (1961), June 30 and July 2 and 4. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PRIX JEAN VIGO (Through Dec. 30) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Vigo (1905-34), the French filmmaker, with a series of 41 films from directors who have won the prize that bears his name. Thursday's features are Joël Farges's ''Pondichéry, Juste Avant l'Oubli'' (1987), an ode to the director's hometown in South India. It will be shown with Alain Resnais and Chris Marker's short about African sculpture in museums, ''Les Statues Meurent Aussi,'' and the original English version of Mr. Marker's science-fiction short ''La Jetée'' (1962). (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>REDISCOVERING ROSCOE: THE CAREER OF FATTY ARBUCKLE (Through May 15). The Museum of Modern Art's 54-film retrospective of the acting and directing career of the scandal-ridden Arbuckle (1887-1933) continues tomorrow with a program that includes ''Fatty's Faithful Fido'' (1915), ''Bridge Wives'' (1932) and ''Fatty and Mabel Adrift'' (1916), with Mabel Normand. Three other programs will be shown next week, including ''Early Keystones,'' a collection of eight silents made in 1913 and 1914. (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop  Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AQUALUNG (Monday) Matt Hales, the piano-playing Briton who records as Aqualung, studiously borrows all the most tedious and indulgent aspects of Coldplay and Radiohead -- the slow-motion brooding, the epic self-pity -- while missing their joyful grandeur. With David Ford. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BENEVENTO-RUSSO DUO (Tonight) The keyboardist Marco Benevento and the drummer Joe Russo have made a gradual rise on the jam-band circuit with kinetic meanderings that often begin in peaceful soul-funk and end up in poundingly insistent climaxes that might as well be punk rock. Figo opens. At 9, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $15 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>'BROADWAY BY THE YEAR: THE MUSICALS OF 1968' (Monday) The year 1968 might be remembered for student protests, escalation in Vietnam and the assassinations of Robert F. Kennedy and the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., but on Broadway it was the year of the grooviest musical ever, ''Hair.'' That show, along with ''Zorba,'' ''Promises, Promises,'' ''The Happy Time'' and others, will get the oh-what-a-time treatment from Brad Oscar, Scott Coulter, Annie Golden, Chip Zien, Lorinda Lisitza and friends. 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824; $40 and 45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROSANNE CASH (Thursday) Ms. Cash performs the live premiere of the songs on her new album, ''Black Cadillac'' (Capitol), a contemplative cycle about the deaths, over two years, of her stepmother, June Carter Cash; her father, Johnny Cash; and her mother, Vivian Liberto Cash Distin. 8 p.m., St. Ann's Warehouse, 38 Water Street, at Dock Street, Brooklyn, (718) 254-8779; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CITIZEN COPE (Tomorrow) Clarence Greenwood, a k a Citizen Cope, is the umpteenth singer-songwriter to use hip-hop beats and drawled rap-sung vocals in search of novelty. 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $26. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CULTURE (Tuesday) Culture, led by Joseph Hill, has been a steadfast roots reggae band since the 1960's, singing about Rastafarian faith and everyday suffering and putting a groove behind its messages. In Culture's songs, a dance party and a gospel service are never far apart. 11 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door.(Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* DJ A-TRAK (Tonight) Born Alain Macklovitch in Montreal, DJ A-Trak has been a turntable celebrity since 1997, when he won DMC's World D.J. Championship at age 15. Still a baby-faced prodigy, he is now Kanye West's D.J., and on this solo tour, watching his arms flail back and forth as he scratches records at cartoon speed should be half the fun. He appears with a small posse of guests, including DJ Ayres and Cosmo Baker, two of the hosts of the Rub, a regular hip-hop dance party in Brooklyn; GLC, a phlegmatic rapper from Chicago; and Cuizinier and DJ Orgasmic of the French hip-hop crew TTC. 10 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THOMAS DOLBY (Wednesday and Thursday) Thomas Dolby entered pop eternity in the guise of a bespectacled, wild-haired mad scientist, with the 1983 novelty hit ''She Blinded Me With Science.'' He returns after a long absence -- in his other life he has been an innovative creator of ring tones -- with a tour that finds him largely in the same gearhead persona (sans the hair), surrounded by bizarre-looking doohickeys with colorful gauges and oversize knobs. Wednesday at 10 p.m., Thursday at 7 (with the singer-songwriter Carey Ott) and 10 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DRAGONFORCE (Tuesday) A six-man metal army from London -- with members from Ukraine, Hong Kong, New Zealand and South Africa -- DragonForce sounds like some combination of Iron Maiden, the Scorpions and Yngwie Malmsteen on frantic fast-forward: all the chant-along major-key melodies and fretboard-tickling guitar solos of those 80's metal heroes are there, but sped up to an exhilarating degree. With Protest the Hero and Sanctity. 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or (212) 307-7171; $15 and $17. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FAUN FABLES (Thursday) On a bed of ghostly acoustic folk, Faun Fables's Dawn McCarthy and Nils Frykdahl build an astonishing and unpredictable kind of pop theater, at once grandiose and nightmarish and silly. The band's new album, ''The Transit Rider'' (Drag City), is a creepily obsessive song cycle about the commuting life, begun by Ms. McCarthy in 1994 and done as a theater piece in San Francisco four years ago. Here it comes on tour, complete with costumes, film and a cast of four. Bonfire Madigan and Transmitting open the show. At 9 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FORRÓ IN THE DARK (Sunday) For three years, this group has been leading one of New York's best and lowest-tech dance parties at the East Village bar Nublu. The groove is a humble and sexy two-beat dance from northeastern Brazil called forró, made with accordion, hand-held percussion and, since this is New York, whiffs of distorted electric guitar. It travels well, and on Sunday the band comes to S.O.B.'s for a special forró night that includes dance lessons. 9 and 11 p.m., 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $7. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FRUIT BATS (Tonight and tomorrow) Centered on the guitarist and singer-songwriter Eric Johnson, Fruit Bats, from Chicago, play weightless little nuggets of psych-folk that are deceptively wistful. Behind their apparent melancholy is a playful wit and a modest awe: ''It takes cold fronts and sackcloth skies,'' Mr. Johnson sings. ''It takes leviathans down in the abyss/ The hidden messages of the things that you missed.'' Tonight at 9, with Amandine and Jason Friedman (of the Boggs), at the Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., with Amandine and Sam Jayne (of Love Is Laughter), at Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703. Both are $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HANGDOGS (Tonight) With weary voices and staunch, down-home roots-rock guitars, the Hangdogs sing about unglamorous, hard-drinking men and the women they love and leave. At 10, Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>COLIN HAY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Not all forgotten pop stars age as gracefully as Mr. Hay, who in the 1980's was the voice and face of the Australian new wave goofballs Men at Work. Recently he has been developing a new following with gentle, ruminative acoustic songs; one, ''I Just Don't Think I'll Ever Get Over You,'' was a heart-stopper in the film ''Garden State.'' 8 p.m., Canal Room, 285 West Broadway, at Canal Street, TriBeCa, (212) 941-8100; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISIS, DALEK (Thursday) Isis creates a fearsomely beautiful sludge out of atonal guitars and a permanently distorted bass. As it works its way to repeated climaxes, the music can feel like a glorious release or the last thrashings of a captured animal. Dalek is a hip-hop trio from Newark led by a rapper of the same name, who intones apocalyptic rhymes over noisy, atmospheric backing tracks. 7:30 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or (212) 307-7171; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROBY LAKATOS ENSEMBLE (Tonight) A fiery Gypsy violinist from Hungary descended from Janos Bihari, a legendary player from the early 19th century, Mr. Lakatos is equally at home in classical, jazz and folk repertories. Backed by cimbalom, guitar, bass and piano, he plays everything from traditional pieces and a Liszt dance to a Russian tango and ''Honeysuckle Rose.'' At 8:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LL COOL J (Tonight) One of the first bigger-than-the-block personalities of rap, LL Cool J still follows the same few guidelines of self-representation that have served him throughout his long career: be photographed shirtless as often as possible, title all your albums either after yourself (''Todd Smith,'' his latest, refers to his given name, James Todd Smith) or some superlative that Muhammad Ali might have used (''Phenomenon,'' ''Greatest of All Time'') and be as sweatily vigorous a performer as possible. At 8, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE MOONLIGHTERS (Monday) Few would expect members of Helmet and the Pain Teens to play ukulele-strumming, steel-guitar-sliding, sweetly harmonized, optimistic Hawaiian-style songs. But the Moonlighters do just that, writing anachronistic ballads and swing-style tunes that Bliss Blood sings without a hint of campiness. 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* JOSH RITTER, HEM (Thursday) Mr. Ritter's guileless, boy-next-door voice is the first clue that he doesn't need a lot of fancy tricks to make a point. Powerfully minimal songwriting is another. But there is no limit to the depth and ambition of his songs, whether he is confessing a simple crush or following his thoughts on a long, Whitmanesque incantation, as he does for more than nine minutes on ''Thin Blue Flame'' from his new album, ''The Animal Years'' (V2). Hem plays somewhat prosaic alt-country, but in such delicate, sensuous arrangements that it doesn't matter. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $15 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUPER DIAMOND (Tonight and tomorrow night) A tribute to the songs of Neil Diamond, particularly his triumphal 1970's material. Smirking is optional. At 8:30, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $26.50 in advance, $30 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* TINARIWEN (Monday) ''Welcome to the desert,'' announced one member of Tinariwen, wrapped in a turban and a long robe, at a recent concert. It was an unnecessary statement: from the first droning electric guitar lines and hypnotically repetitive handclaps, the audience was already there. Tinariwen, a group of Tuareg nomads from northern Mali, play stark, seemingly endless patterns of modal blues that occasionally snarl in anger or align into stately funk. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Cabaret  Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) The regal cabaret singer and the brassy songs of Kander and Ebb that she is offering in her new show may not be an obvious fit. But Ms. Akers locates the heart inside the brass and sass. 9 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; cover, $60, with a $20 minimum; $60 prix fixe dinner required on Thursdays and at the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. 2 p.m., the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $55, including brunch at noon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* DIAHANN CARROLL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Carroll's first New York nightclub appearance in 40 years is a grand but unpretentious summing up by a performer (accompanied by an eight-member band) who has breached racial boundaries while exploring the four corners of show business. Historic anecdotes, nuggets of practical wisdom and show-stopping renditions of songs popularized by Frank Sinatra, Sophie Tucker and others blend into a complex and winning self-portrait. 8:30 and 11 p.m., Feinstein's at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095; $60, with a $40 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER (Tomorrow) This booming pop-blues contralto may not be demure, but she is tasteful in a smart, regal, big-mama way, and she is astute in her choices of often obscure soul, blues and jazz songs that play to her contradictory mixture of the lusty and the philosophical. 7 p.m., Helen's, 169 Eighth Avenue, near 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0609; $20, with a $15 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* MARY CLEERE HARAN  (Tonight and tomorrow) A wonderful no-frills singer with a sophisticated wit, Ms. Haran has a remarkable talent for simultaneously interpreting standards in the spirit in which they were written and looking at them through 21st-century eyes. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $60. (Holden)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Wednesday) Cool, funny, swinging and indestructible, this 75-year-old singer and sometime actress exemplifies old-time hip in its most generous incarnation. 9:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $12 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz  Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CLAUDIA ACUÑA QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A vocalist guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile, Ms. Acuña sounds best when supported and stretched by sympathetic musicians, like the pianist Jason Lindner, the cellist and trombonist Dana Leong, the bassist Omer Avital and the percussionist Pernell Saturnino. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15; students, $10. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>WES ANDERSON QUARTET (Tuesday through May 7) Mr. Anderson, known as Warmdaddy, is an alto saxophonist with a tart and bluesy sound. The strength of his quartet has a lot to do with the presence of Marc Cary, an adventurous but well-grounded pianist. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FAHIR ATAKOGLU TRIO (Tonight) An accomplished symphonic composer in his native Turkey, Mr. Atakoglu recently released ''If'' (Far &amp; Here), an album featuring his piano playing in a trio setting. As on the album, he plays here with the rhythm team of Anthony Jackson on electric bass and Horacio (El Negro) Hernandez on drums. At 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAËL ATTIAS QUARTET (Thursday) Mr. Attias assembles a texturally minded and exploratory ensemble consisting of his fellow saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. 8 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BROOK'S QAWWALI PARTY (Tonight) The Sufi devotional music of Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan provides a mandated repertory for this sprawling ensemble, led by the drummer Brook Martinez. Faithful to its source mainly in exuberance, the group creates a roiling polyphony of percussion, saxophones and brass, bass, harmonium and guitar. At 9 and 10:30, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHEL CAMILO TRIO (Through Sunday) A percussive, often cathartic pianist, Mr. Camilo recently released a recording of Gershwin's ''Rhapsody in Blue'' (Telarc) with a 95-piece symphony orchestra. His trio, with the bassist Charles Flores and the drummer Dafnis Prieto, can sometimes seem nearly as expansive. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables with a $5 minimum, or $20 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE DOUGLAS QUINTET (Tuesday through May 7) The trumpeter Dave Douglas always seems on the verge of forming a new band, but this one -- with Uri Caine on piano and Fender Rhodes, James Genus on bass and Clarence Penn on drums -- has been a solid entity for several years. Here they celebrate a new album, ''Meaning and Mystery'' (Greenleaf), and a valuable new member, the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LIBERTY ELLMAN SEXTET (Tuesday) ''Ophiuchus Butterfly'' (Pi), Mr. Ellman's ambitious new album, knowingly takes a page or two from his frequent employer, the saxophonist and composer Henry Threadgill. Its hyper-literate polyphony should sound even better live, as performed by Mr. Ellman's acoustic guitar and an ensemble consisting of two alto saxophones, a tuba, an acoustic bass and drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20; students, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORRIN EVANS QUINTET (Tomorrow) Mr. Evans is a percussive pianist equally attuned to hip-hop and hard bop, and he often surrounds himself with rhythmically assertive compatriots. Here that roll call includes Ralph Bowen, tenor and soprano saxophones; J. D. Walter, vocals; Mark Kelly, bass; and Donald Edwards, drums. 8 and 10 p.m. and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KENNY GARRETT QUARTET (Wednesday through May 6) Mr. Garrett is a bulldozer on the alto saxophone, which he uses for blazing post-Coltrane calisthenics, and an introspective artisan on the soprano, with which he investigates East Asian folk timbres. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30; $35 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum.(Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAFAYETTE GILCHRIST (Tomorrow) On his recent album ''Towards the Shining Path'' (Hyena), Mr. Gilchrist reconciles avant-garde pianism with the backbeat swagger of hip-hop, creating a compellingly funky amalgam. Tomorrow night at 12:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $8, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* A GREAT NIGHT IN HARLEM (Thursday) The Jazz Foundation of America, a nonprofit musicians' aid organization that has been hard at work in the months since Hurricane Katrina, has stocked this edition of its annual gala with appearances by the Rebirth Brass Band, the trumpeter Clark Terry, the singers Abbey Lincoln and Odetta, and dozens of other guests (including nonmusical luminaries like Bill Cosby, Dick Parsons and Danny Glover). 8 p.m., Apollo Theater, 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 245-3999, ext. 29, www.jazzfoundation.org; $100 and $250 for the concert seats; $500 for the concert with the after party; $1,500 for full package, including dinner. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CURTIS HASSELBRING'S DECOUPAGE (Wednesday) Mr. Hasselbring, a trombonist, aims for a chamber-improv ideal in this collaboration with the vibraphonist Matt Moran, the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the percussionist Satoshi Takeishi. 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GERRY HEMINGWAY QUARTET (Sunday) Texture is more of a priority than tempo in Mr. Hemingway's drumming, and his compositions reveal a fruitful fascination with polytonality. He plays here with his longtime collaborators Herb Robertson, a trumpeter, and Mark Helias, a bassist, as well as James Finn on tenor saxophone. 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near North Third Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOE LOVANO AND HANK JONES (Through Sunday) Mr. Jones, a pianist in his 80's, and Mr. Lovano, a tenor saxophonist in his 50's, model an exquisitely responsive duologue that would seem rarefied if not for its absolute lack of pretension. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY TRIO (Tonight) Mr. Malaby, a versatile and increasingly prominent tenor saxophonist, enlists the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Gerald Cleaver in a program of original music and choice standards, with an exploratory ethos prevailing. At 9, Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEIKO MATSUI (Through Sunday) Sometimes billowing and ethereal, sometimes crisp and gently funky, the music of Keiko Matsui has been celebrated in smooth jazz and New Age circles. At times, it can also suggest the worldly fusion of Weather Report, which isn't such a bad thing. At 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER GROUP (Sunday) ''Oceana'' (Sunnyside), the most recent album by the guitarist Ben Monder, was one of last year's great surprises: a small-scale but ambitious suite of original music that didn't sound quite like anything else. Mr. Monder presents much of the same material here, with the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Ted Poor. At 8 and 10 p.m., BAR4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, www.bar4.net; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NEW ORLEANS: CONGO SQUARE (Thursday through May 6) Jazz at Lincoln Center concludes its city-hopping season with a focus on New Orleans, a place that had deep resonance for the organization long before Hurricane Katrina. In the Rose Theater, Wynton Marsalis and the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra will present new music inspired by Congo Square, with help from the African percussionists Yacub Addy and Odadaa. In the Allen Room, the trombonist Wycliffe Gordon will play spirituals and gospel tunes. 7:30 p.m. in the Allen Room, 8 p.m. at Rose Theater, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500; $105.50 and $135.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH QUARTET (Tuesday) Mr. Sabbagh, an unassumingly self-assured tenor saxophonist and composer in the postmodern mainstream, leads a sleek ensemble with Lage Lund on guitar, Gary Wang on bass and Ted Poor on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIERNEY SUTTON / LOSTON HARRIS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Sutton's clear, sweetly sonorous voice isn't inherently a jazz timbre, but she is irrefutably a jazz singer, as she has demonstrated on a number of recent engagements. She shares a bill with Mr. Harris, a singer and pianist with a style patterned after Nat King Cole. At 7:30, Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500; $135.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TERRASSON-OKEGWO-PARKER TRIO (Through Sunday) Throughout the latter half of the 1990's, the pianist Jacky Terrasson led one of jazz's fresher-sounding acoustic piano trios, distinguished not only by his fluid pianism but also by the resonant bass tone of Ugonna Okegwo and the pared-down percussive drive of Leon Parker. Regrouping here, the musicians present themselves as a collective. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow night. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE TURRE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Turre, the trombonist and conch shell player, applies both virtuosity and restraint to the conventions of small-group hard bop, in a group including the tenor saxophonist Javon Jackson, the pianist Ronnie Mathews, the bassist Buster Williams and the drummer Dion Parsons. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ZIMMER QUARTET (Tomorrow) The hard bop of the 1960's provides thematic sustenance for Mr. Zimmer, a drummer, and his working band, which features the smartly assertive tenor saxophonist Joel Frahm. At 9 p.m., Night and Day, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, www.nightanddayrestaurant.com; cover, $10, with a $7 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical  Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera  'CENDRILLON' (Tonight and Sunday) Massenet's version of the Cinderella fairy tale, first seen in 1899, is not produced that often, which is surprising, since French opera connoisseurs consider it among his finest and most approachable works. Opera buffs should thank the Manhattan School of Music for staging a production, directed by Chuck Hudson and conducted by Laurent Pillot. Tonight at 8 and Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Manhattan School of Music, Broadway and 122nd Street, Morningside Heights, (917) 493-4428; $20. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'DON PASQUALE' (Tonight) The veteran Austrian director Otto Schenk, who is also an acclaimed comic actor in his homeland, understands that the way to make a rich comic opera like Donizetti's ''Don Pasquale'' work is to treat it seriously. In his wonderful new production for the Met, he accomplishes this vividly. The cast is splendid, especially the charismatic soprano Anna Netrebko, the robust dynamic young baritone Mariusz Kwiecien and, in the title role, the stylish Italian bass Simone Alaimo. Derrick Inouye conducts. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'LOHENGRIN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) The revival of Robert Wilson's 1998 production of Wagner's ''Lohengrin'' is not the same show that earned the director lusty boos at its premiere. The abstract sets are as haunting as ever. But this time the singers seem more comfortable with the glacial movements and stylized hand and arm gestures, which have been simplified. The riveting cast is headed by the dramatic tenor Ben Heppner in the title role and the charismatic soprano Karita Mattila, in glorious voice as Elsa. (Klaus Florian Vogt makes his Met debut on Wednesday, filling in for Mr. Heppner as Lohengrin.) The conductor Philippe Auguin draws incisive playing from the Met orchestra. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., Wednesday at 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out tomorrow; $26 to $175 on Wednesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>OPERA ORCHESTRA OF NEW YORK (Thursday) Montemezzi's ''Amore Dei Tre Re'' receives an infrequent, if unstaged, hearing from an organization that specializes in such things. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $25 to $125. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'RIGOLETTO' (Monday and Thursday) Though Anna Netrebko and Rolando Villazón, the opera world's hottest soprano-tenor couple, have moved on to other things, Verdi's ''Rigoletto'' is still with us at the Met, but with an entirely new cast. Paolo Gavanelli sings the title role, with Norah Amsellem as Gilda, and Roberto Aronica as the Duke, Italian opera's most caddish character. Monday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to 175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'RODELINDA' (Tuesday) The Met's premiere production of Handel's ''Rodelinda,'' a highlight last season that played to sold-out houses, returns in the handsome staging by Stephen Wadsworth. Renée Fleming again brings her rich voice and courageous vulnerability to the title role. The countertenor Andreas Scholl makes his Met debut as Bertarido, Rodelinda's husband, the Lombard king of Milan, who has been usurped and is thought dead, but returns to the court incognito. Patrick Summers conducts. 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'SUSANNAH' (Tonight through Sunday) It's easy to poke fun at Carlisle Floyd's opera for its folksy score, run through with hymn tunes, square dances and Appalachian ditties. Yet this opera, the story of a sensual young woman in rural Tennessee who inadvertently stirs up envy and desire among the townspeople, is more sophisticated than it appears. Mr. Floyd deftly blends folk music elements with a pungently dissonant harmonic language to achieve emotional richness and genuine tragedy. The Dicapo Opera Theater presents a 50th-anniversary production, directed by Michael Capasso and conducted by Steven Osgood. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., St. Jean-Baptiste Church, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 289-9438; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'TOSCA' (Tomorrow) The soprano Deborah Voigt will not be everyone's idea of a Tosca. Her bright and penetrating singing recalls the Nordic sound and temperament of Birgit Nilsson's in the role. Ms. Voigt invests the part with personal touches, bringing out Tosca's vulnerability. And she sings with daring abandon during the confrontation with the villainous Scarpia, here the bass James Morris, who sounds terrific. 8:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN COMPOSERS ORCHESTRA (Wednesday) A cluster of pieces new to most of us and titled ''Erotic Spirits'' offers Deborah Voigt as visiting soprano and Steven Sloane as conductor: with music by Derek Bermel, Brian Current, Kristin Kuster and Stephen Paulus. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $15 to $42. (Holland)</p>
        <p>BRENTANO STRING QUARTET (Tonight) This first-rate quartet tilts toward the contemporary in a program that begins with Debussy's Quartet in G minor and ends with Shostakovich's Quartet No. 15. Between them, the ensemble gives the premiere of David Horne's Quartet No. 4. 7:30, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $42. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CONTINUUM (Sunday) This adventurous new-music band performs a program billed as ''A Celebration of Modern American Jewish Composers,'' with works by Paul Schoenfield, Osvaldo Golijov Darius Milhaud and Samuel Adler. 3 p.m., Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, between Court and Clinton Streets, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn, (718) 875-1550; $20. (Jeremy Eichler)</p>
        <p>* EMERSON STRING QUARTET (Sunday and Thursday) Among the great composers of the 20th century, Shostakovich was the most inscrutable. But in his 15 string quartets he came closest to showing his hand. These works are like entries in a diary, and he never imagined that they would become as popular as they are today. The Emerson Quartet plays these seminal works compellingly and has recorded them complete. They are performing them in chronological order, a chance to follow Shostakovich's development. No. 4 through No. 6 will be performed Sunday at 5 p.m., and No. 7 through No. 9 on Thursday at 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $60. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC  (Tonight, tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday) Sir Colin Davis returns with some of the composers who have long been his calling cards. Tonight and tomorrow, Ian Bostridge sings Berlioz's exquisite ''Nuits d'Été'' on a program that also includes Mozart's ''Haffner'' Serenade. On Wednesday and Thursday, the program is split between Mozart (the overture to ''La Clemenza di Tito,'' the Piano Concerto No. 26 and the aria ''Ch'io mi scordi di te?'') and Sibelius (''Luonnotar'' and the Third Symphony), with the pianist Mitsuko Uchida and the soprano Soile Isokoski. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Wednesday and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $26 to $94. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* SPECULUM MUSICAE (Monday) One of New York City's most venerable new-music ensembles, Speculum Musicae offers a contemporary classic, Lukas Foss's ''Paradigm,'' as well as works by Louis Andriessen, Harrison Birtwistle and Hughes Dufourt. 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance  Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>BALLET FIESTA MEXICANA (Tonight through Sunday) Yloy Ybarra's company returns in a program of work from Mexico, with live music performed by the group Semilla. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Thalia Spanish Theater, 41-17 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens, (718) 729-3880; $25 to $30. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LA BOULE BLANCHE (Monday) The one, the only, the incomparable Katherine Dunham will be celebrated on her 96th birthday in a program of readings from ''Kaiso!,'' a new book of writings by and about Ms. Dunham, and performances of her dances by artists including Loretta Abbott, Glory Van Scott and the Charles Moore Dance Theater. Ms. Dunham is expected to be present. And wear white (it's required). 7 p.m., Theater of the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue, Morningside Heights, (212) 502-0895; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* H. T. CHEN &amp; DANCERS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Chen, a longtime presence on the city's modern-dance scene, will present what he teasingly calls a dim sum dance experience with programming in honor of Asian Heritage Month. It includes a revival of his 1984 ''Mott Street,'' a celebration of the bustling life of Chinatown, set to music by Charlie Chin. (Through May 7.) 7 p.m., Mulberry Street Theater, 70 Mulberry Street, at Bayard Street, Chinatown, (212) 349-0126; front row, $25; general admission, $15; students and 65+, $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NAI-NI CHEN DANCE COMPANY (Tomorrow) The company will perform Ms. Chen's new ''American Landscape,'' a collaboration with the composer and singer Joan LaBarbara that examines immigration in America. 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722 or www.njpac.org; $32. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE FILMS ASSOCIATION (Sunday) This association celebrates its 50th anniversary and Isadora Duncan with ''The Sensual Woman,'' a program of short films and live performances. 7 p.m., Galapagos Art Space, 70 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 782-5188, galapogosartspace.com; $10. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DANCES PATRELLE (Thursday) Francis Patrelle's new ''Pop,'' set to music by Noël Coward and Jerry Lee Lewis and a medley of songs about New York City, focuses on three different nightclubs from three eras, from the 1930's to the 1950's. (Through May 6.) 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400 or symphonyspace.org; $40 and $35; students and 65+, $36 and $31; $20 for Saturday children's matinee. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DAO ANH KHANH/STEPHAN KOPLOWITZ (Thursday through Sunday). Vietnam meets America, only this time it's not a war but ''A Walk Between Two Worlds.'' At 7:30 p.m. through tomorrow, with a 2 p.m. performance on Sunday, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $15 and $25. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* E-MOVES (Tonight through Sunday) They've thought of everything here, with programs of ''E-Merging'' and ''E-Volving'' dance by 13 choreographers and companies (tomorrow night) and ''E-Stablished'' dance by Cynthia Oliver's COCo Dance Theater and Arthur Aviles's Typical Theater, the latter in choreography set to 1950's music by Tito Puente and Celia Cruz (tonight and Sunday). Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Aaron Davis Hall, City College, Convent Avenue and West 135th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 650-7100; $18 per program, $26 for both. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE FORSYTHE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) The United States debut of William Forsythe's new company, which he founded after the demise of his Frankfurt Ballet and which first performed in Frankfurt last year. The program consists of his ''Kammer/Kammer'' (2000), with live video projected around the theater. (Through May 6.) 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100 or bam.org; $20 to $70. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>HEDWIG DANCES (Tonight through Sunday) From Chicago, this august modern-dance troupe will perform works by Jan Bartoszek (the company's artistic director), Jan Eckert and Maray Gutierrez that has been inspired by themes ranging from Goya's ''Caprichos'' to the intimate rules of the bath. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $18; students and 65+, $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARK JARECKE PROJECT (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Jarecke's ''Everything Up Until Now and Including'' is an evening-long and physically demanding solo performed by, and created in collaboration with, Andrea Johnston. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St, Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>JOYCE SOHO PRESENTS 2006 (Thursday) Twelve new choreographers will be featured in this showcase in programs that will be performed Thursdays through Saturdays through May 20. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; $12 for students and 65+; $35 for a three-weekend pass. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* AKRAM KHAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) The United States premiere performances of a commissioned work, ''ma'' (''earth''), by this fashionable and successful London-based, Kathak-trained choreographer. At 8, Rose Theater, Jazz at Lincoln Center, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500 or lincolncenter.org; $30 to $58. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* MIAMI CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday) Edward Villella's Balanchine-flavored company, offering repertory by Balanchine, Robbins, Paul Taylor and Twyla Tharp in theaters around but not in New York City. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, C. W. Post College campus of Long Island University, Brookville, N.Y., (516) 299-3100 or tillescenter.org; $40 to $70. Sunday at 5 p.m., the Performing Arts Center, Purchase College, State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6200 or www.artscenter.org; $42 to $62. Tuesday at 8 p.m., McCarter Theater, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787 or (888) 278-7932 or mccarter.org; $42 to $55. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* RICHARD MOVE (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Move, fresh from his appearance as Martha Graham and his duet with Desmond Richardson at the Graham Dance Company gala, presents ''The Show (Achilles Heels).'' This mega-hip take on things Greek will offer Deborah Harry (a k a Blondie) singing live songs as Athena, and Rasta Thomas in the title role, originally performed by Mikhail Baryshnikov in the piece's out-of-town White Oak Dance Project premiere in 2002. The cast also includes Katherine Crockett from the Graham company. Arto Lindsay did the score. Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through May 6, at 8, at the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, ext. 11 or thekitchenorg; $20.(Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL DANCE THEATER COMPANY OF JAMAICA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Dance and music reflecting Jamaican culture, by the company director Rex Nettleford, Arsenio Andrade and Christopher Walker. Tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Center at Brooklyn College, one block from the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Flatbush, Brooklyn, (718) 951-4500 or brooklyncenter.com; $20 to $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL DANCE WEEK (Sunday) The celebration in New York concludes this weekend with a free performance and film screenings, also free. The United States Latin Dance Champion Melanie LaPatin will join six professional and studio companies in a performance. 2:30 p.m., Dance Times Square, 156 West 44th Street, Manhattan, ndw-nyc.org. The film programs include Henry Chalfont's ''Mambo to Hip-Hop,'' which will be screened on Sunday at 3 p.m. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company's intermittent run of Balanchine's full-evening ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' can be seen tonight, tomorrow afternoon and Sunday afternoon. The Diamond Project, with its seven premieres, gets under way tomorrow night with a new ballet by Eliot Feld, part of an all-Feld program repeated Wednesday, and continues on Thursday with a premiere by Mauro Bigonzetti. The season runs until June 25. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 2 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. The New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org; $30 to $86; student rush tickets, $15. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) This chamber ballet company wraps up its spring season with a program honoring Agnes de Mille as a dancer in ballets like Anthony Tudor's ''Judgment of Paris,'' and as the choreographer of classic musicals, including ''Oklahoma!'' and ''Brigadoon.'' At 7:30, Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100 or ticketmaster.com; $30; $15 for 65+ and students. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>PERIPHERAL DANCES (Sunday) The program includes dances by choreographers including Gail Accardi, Laurie DeVito, Akiko Tomikawa and Mami and Maki, and dance film by Kristina Jones. (Sundays through May 14.) 7:30 p.m., Green Space Studio Theater, 34-24 24th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 995-8089; $10. (Dunning).</p>
        <p>PMT SPRING SHOWCASE (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company of the hip-hop teacher Pavan Thimmaiah will perform with six other troupes and individuals in a program of modern, jazz and hip-hop dance. At 8, Martin Luther King Jr. Auditorium, 122 Amsterdam Avenue, between 65th and 66th Streets, Manhattan, (212) 924-5694; $16. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SILVER-BROWN DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company will perform dances by Eva Silverstein to music by Otis Redding. At 8, Alvin Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-0255 or theatermania.com; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEANETTE STONER &amp; DANCERS (Thursday) Ms. Stoner, who has performed with Alwin Nikolais and Nancy Meehan, will present multimedia dance that includes her new ''Light,'' an exploration of different kinds of illumination. (Through May 7.) 8 p.m., Stoner Loft, 83 Leonard Street, between Broadway and Church Street, SoHo, (212) 226-1576; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB S.L.A.M. (Tonight through Sunday) Batten down the hatches. Elizabeth Streb's fearless high-flyers are at it again in ''Wild Blue Yonder,'' a new spring program paying tribute to early heroes of aviation, presented informally with popcorn. (Through May 14.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Streb Lab for Action Mechanics, 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $15; $10 for children; under 4, free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN FOLK ART MUSEUM: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. Few exhibitions this size (35 pieces) present quite such a vivid and rewarding picture of artistic assimilation and transformation. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* BARD GRADUATE CENTER: 'AMERICAN STREAMLINED DESIGN: THE WORLD OF TOMORROW,' through June 11. Streamlining, a particularly American design concept born of our love of speed and admiration for industrial production, peaked in the 1930's and 40's, and is now said to be undergoing a revival. This tribute to it includes more than 180 objects, from boring but useful items like a receipt printer designed by Walter Dorwin Teague in 1946 to a plastic bicycle helmet of flowing teardrop shapes designed by John Larkin in 2000. The show doesn't shy away from the grittier aspects of industrial design, presenting objects like air compressors and electric sanders along with those of higher style, like a harmonica of chromium-plated and enameled steel with rounded edges and a ribbed binding, designed by John Vassos about 1939. The show is perhaps too packed with repetitive examples -- do we need to see three similar electric drills? -- but don't let that stop you. There's no shortage of wonderful things to look at here. 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to, and settlement in, the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: WILLIAM WEGMAN: 'FUNNEY/STRANGE,' through May 28. Descended from Marcel Duchamp and Buster Keaton, Mr. Wegman has straddled high and low for more than three decades, using his signature Weimaraners to make the art world's funniest videos, as well as television commercials, calendars and children's books. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>DAHESH MUSEUM OF ART: 'STORIES TO TELL: MASTERWORKS FROM THE KELLY COLLECTION OF AMERICAN ILLUSTRATION,' through May 21. During the Golden Age of Illustration -- the 1880's to the 1930's -- images made by painters for magazines and books captivated the collective American psyche. Original works by some of the best of those artists, including J. C. Leyendecker, N. C. Wyeth and Charles Dana Gibson, are included in this extensive and well-selected exhibition. 580 Madison Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'GOYA'S LAST WORKS,' through May 14. This compact show is sublime. The most humane portraits are mixed with sketches, like diary entries, in which society is an irredeemable mob of lunatics and murderers. In exile in Bordeaux, Goya spent his last days in physical misery, lamenting man's essential evil while experimenting with the new medium of lithography and inventing the most exquisite, luminous paintings on tiny chips of ivory. Like the late works of Titian or Rembrandt, Goya's late works achieve a whole new level of freedom and depth, haunted by death but exalted. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' through July 16. Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love.'' (See above.) (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'DAVID SMITH: A CENTENNIAL,' through May 14. David Smith is best known for his worst work, bulky sculptures of the ''important'' kind that museums and banks like to buy. Much (though not all) of that material has been excised from this survey in favor of smaller, earlier, nonmonumental pieces that the curator, Carmen Gimenez, presents with plenty of air and light. The result is exemplary as a David Smith experience, an American Modernism experience and a Guggenheim Museum experience. (212) 423-3500. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'SNAP JUDGMENTS: NEW POSITIONS IN CONTEMPORARY AFRICAN PHOTOGRAPHY,' through May 28. If Martians tuned into our television news broadcasts, they'd have a miserable impression of life on Earth. War, disease, poverty, heartbreak and nothing else. That's exactly how most of the world sees Africa: filtered through images of calamity. The Nigerian-born curator Okwui Enwezor offers a bracing alternative view in this show of recent photography from Africa. He isn't interested in simply exchanging an upbeat Africa for a downbeat one, smiles for frowns, but in engineering a slow, complex, panoptical turn in perspective, one that takes in many moods and directions. The results are stimulating, astringent, brimming with life. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'HATSHEPSUT,' through July 9. Can a queen be a king, too? Consider the case of Hatshepsut, an Egyptian ruler of the 15th century B.C. She assumed the supreme title of pharaoh and ruled Egypt in that powerfully masculine role until her death. Hatshepsut is the subject of a celebratory show at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, one that commemorates the 100th anniversary of the Met's department of Egyptian art. Organized by the Met and the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, it includes many objects from the Met's own extensive holdings, excavated at its digs in the 1920's and 30's. But it isn't so easy to follow Hatshepsut's trail in this ambitious show, what with the number of relatives, subordinates, minor officials and such who also have a place in it, along with scarabs, jewelry, pottery, furniture and other artifacts. (212) 535-7710. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>MET: KARA WALKER AT THE MET: 'AFTER THE DELUGE,' through July 30. The Metropolitan Museum of Art's first foray into artist-organized shows is a small tour de force of curatorial creativity. Inspired partly by Hurricane Katrina, Ms. Walker has combined works from the Met with examples of her own art, connecting shared themes of race, poverty and water to illuminate contemporary art's inevitable dialogue with past art. The show has as many crosscurrents and undertows as a river. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'EDVARD MUNCH: THE MODERN LIFE OF THE SOUL,' through May 8. This affecting, full-scale retrospective is the first survey of this Norwegian painter in an American museum in almost 30 years. Its more than 130 oils and works on paper cover Munch's entire career, from 1880 to 1944. (212) 708-9400. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'WITHOUT BOUNDARY: SEVENTEEN WAYS OF LOOKING,' through May 22. This excellent group show considers what ''Islamic'' means in the work of several contemporary artists, and it means many things, none simple. Just to see the uses made of calligraphy by Shirazeh Houshiary, Rachid Koraichi and Shirin Neshat is to understand the lesson in variety put forward here. At the same time, the show is far from didactic. It's beautiful, sexy and, in the case of Raqib Shaw's painting and Kutlug Ataman's video of Sufi meditation, ecstatic. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NEUE GALERIE: 'KLEE AND AMERICA,' through May 22. For a long time, the Swiss-born artist Paul Klee (1879-1940), regarded as a leading Modernist figure in Europe, didn't believe his delicate, chimerical work had much of a future in the United States. Yet, thanks to artists, collectors and dealers with close contacts in Germany who had begun to discover his work, by the early 1920's, Klee's impact began to be felt here. This show of more than 60 paintings and drawings assembled exclusively from American holdings covers the wide spectrum of Klee's work. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE STUDIO MUSEUM IN HARLEM: 'ENERGY/EXPERIMENTATION: BLACK ARTISTS AND ABSTRACTION, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art: abstraction. This show is stylishly installed (one gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer); the 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. One, the sculptor Tom Lloyd (1921-96), opened the Studio Museum with a solo show in 1968. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'WHITNEY BIENNIAL 2006: DAY FOR NIGHT,' through May 28. This biennial will provoke much head-scratching by uninitiated visitors. A hermetic take on what has been making waves, it's packaged -- branded might be the better word -- as a show long on collaboration and open-endedness: several shows under one roof, including a revival of the 1960's ''Peace Tower,'' which rises like a Tinker Toy construction from the Whitney courtyard, with contributions by dozens of artists. As a counter to the image of the art world as rich, youth-besotted and obsessed with crafty little nothings, the ethos here is provisional, messy, half-baked, cantankerous, insular -- radical qualities art used to have when it could still call itself radical and wasn't like a barnacle clinging to the cruise ship of pop culture. That was back in the 1970's. And much of what's here (including works by bohemians and other senior eccentrics around then) harks back to that moment. (800) 944-8639 or www.whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>BALÁZS KICSINY: 'EXACT TIME' Representing Hungary in the 2005 Venice Biennale, Mr. Kicsiny showed the surrealistic, Matthew Barneyesque video on view here. Called ''The Cobbler's Apprentice,'' it presents the overhead view of a giant clock; a woman at each numeral strikes the hour with a shoemaker's hammer, as a man crawls endlessly around the rim. Also on view are a video of a performance called ''In the Pump Room'' and a series of small surrealistic watercolors. Janos Gat, 1100 Madison Avenue, at 82nd Street, (212) 327-0441, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* ECHOES FROM THE STEPPES: MONGOLIAN 17TH-, 18TH- AND 19TH-CENTURY BRONZES AND PAINTINGS The bronzes represent the four styles of Mongolian religious sculpture, but the main event is the 77 sakhuis paintings -- small, finely wrought, richly colored portraits of Buddhist priests and protective or wrathful deities that the nomadic Mongols wore, framed in silver, as amulets. E. &amp; J. Frankel, 1040 Madison Avenue, at 79th Street, (212) 879-5733, through May 6. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>DARREN ALMOND /JANICE KERBEL: 'THE IMPOSSIBLE LANDSCAPE' Nothing is obvious in this handsome show of works by two London-based Conceptualists. The connection is that both make visible things that are in different ways impossible. Ms. Kerbel's elegantly abstracted designs for gardens in an office, a Laundromat and other unlikely places are meant to be imagined but never actually built. Mr. Almond's sumptuous, subtly eerie landscape photographs were shot at night using long exposures, making visible what would be invisible to the naked eye. The Horticultural Society of New York, 128 West 58th Street, (212) 757-0915, through May 5. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>'THE GARDEN PARTY' This crowded group show on the theme of the erotic garden looks as if it were produced by a college fraternity for its spring festival. It includes high-profile artists like Vanessa Beecroft, Olafur Eliasson and Yoko Ono. Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, near Greene Street, (212) 343-7300, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>HANNA LIDEN: 'HAIRFACES, SCAPEGOATS, BIRDS, BLOODSUCKERS, SQUAREHEADS &amp; A FEW DEATHS' A Swedish artist who is in this year's Whitney Biennial, Ms. Liden produces staged color photographs that resemble stills from a low-budget gothic horror movie. With young people in tribal masks menaced by black shrouded figures of death in beautiful wilderness settings, they suggest a meeting of Ingmar Berman and ''The Road Warrior.'' Rivington Arms, 4 East Second Street, East Village, (646) 654-3213, through May 14. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>ED CLARK: 'REBIRTH' Mr. Clark, who turns 80 on May 6, uses push brooms to sweep great quantities of paint across medium-large canvases, creating bold, suave and sensuous Abstract Expressionist evocations of oceanic flux. G. R. N'Namdi, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 929-6645, through May 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>JAMES SURLS: 'COMPLETE FRAGMENTS' Mr. Surls, who lives in Carbondale, Colo., used to cultivate a funky, Southwestern Outsider style in his carved- and burnt-wood sculpture. Now under the influence of Miró and Picasso, his constructions of abstracted flowers in wood and metal have acquired a curious, kitschy Modernist elegance. Charles Cowles, 537 West 24th Street, (212) 741-8999, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>DAVOR VRANKIC With impressively skillful application of graphite on paper, this Paris-based Croatian artist creates darkly comical images of big-eyed, E.T.-like monsters who appear to be undergoing some terrible psychological suffering. The Proposition, 559 West 22nd Street, (212) 242-0035, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'AN AMERICAN ABROAD: SANDRA FISHER AND HER SCHOOL OF LONDON FRIENDS' Fisher, who was married to the painter R. B. Kitaj, was an American who lived in London until her death in 1994 at age 47. This show of more than 60 drawings and paintings, mostly portraits or nudes, reveals a modestly talented traditionalist with a deft, painterly touch and a down-to-earth affection for her subjects. Also included are some portraits of Fisher by artists like Frank Auerbach, Avigdor Arikha and Mr. Kitaj. New York Studio School, 8 West Eighth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 673-6466, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>*AL HANSEN A lively, compact retrospective of the career of an artist known for silhouettes of curvy women made by collaging cut-up pieces of Hershey candy bar wrappers. Andrea Rosen, 525 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-6000; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MIYOKO ITO (1918 to 1983) was an inspiration for many artists who came of age in Chicago in the 1960's and 70's. This beautiful exhibition of paintings from that time is the first presentation of her work in New York since 1978. Adam Baumgold, 74 East 79th Street, (212) 861-7338; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>SIOBHAN LIDDELL: 'LIMINAL' Best known for slight, ephemeral forms of sculpture and installation, this British artist is now attempting more substantial fare in unglazed ceramic and cut-paper collage. The result is a nervy but unfocused array. The high point may be her embroidery of a dragon, hanging in the office. CRG Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 229-2766; closes Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>GIANNI MOTTI: 'SPIRIT OF JOHN LENNON' Can a psychic hired by an artist summon the ghost of this Beatle to a large, dark, closed-off gallery in Chelsea? Don't hold your breath. And don't expect the video installation orchestrated around the concept to be too entertaining, either. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>ANDY WARHOL'S WORLD: 'PHOTOGRAPHY &amp; TELEVISION' A wall-to-wall selection of 313 previously unpublished, unexhibited photographs from the mid-1970's to the mid-1980's offers further proof of Andy Warhol's extraordinary talent and the offhand yet driven way he wielded it, while also forming a visual diary of his peripatetic social life. Zwirner &amp; Wirth, 32 East 69th Street, (212) 517-8677; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater  Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'BRUNDIBAR' and 'BUT THE GIRAFFE, A CURTAIN RAISER TO HANS KRASA'S 'BRUNDIBAR' ' Previews start today. Opens May 7. Tony Kushner has written a new adaptation of Hans Krasa's World War II-era libretto about a brother and a sister who join forces with three talking animals to outwit a sinister organ grinder. Maurice Sendak has designed the sets, and Euan Morton stars. ''But the Giraffe,'' a curtain raiser, is a new short by Mr. Kushner. (1:35). New Victory Theater, 209 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE CAINE MUTINY COURT-MARTIAL' In previews. Opens May 7. Try not to think of Ross from ''Friends'' when you see David Schwimmer in this revival of Herman Wouk's adaptation of his Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about a lawyer who defends a Navy lieutenant accused of mutiny. With Tim Daly and Zeljko Ivanek. Jerry Zaks directs (2:15). The Gerald Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'CIRQUE DU SOLEIL -- CORTEO' In previews. Opens Thursday. A clown imagines his own festive funeral procession in the latest extravaganza from this ever-growing Canadian circus troupe. It features 55 artists from 16 countries (2:30). Grand Chapiteau at Randall's Island, (800) 678-5440.</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' In previews. Opens Monday. This little-musical-that-could about an unscrupulous Broadway producer in the 1920's (some things never change) began at the Toronto Fringe Festival and now makes its unlikely premiere on the Great White Way. Directed by Casey Nicholaw (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'FAITH HEALER' In previews. Opens Thursday. Ralph Fiennes, Cherry Jones and Ian McDiarmid make up the dream cast of this revival of Brian Friel's classic collection of Rashomonesque monologues about a man peddling salvation, his long-suffering wife and his manager (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'FAUST, PARTS I AND II' In previews. Opens Sunday. Target Margin stages an ambitious new six-hour translation of Goethe's epic. David Herskovits directs (6:00). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' In previews. Opens Sunday. Earth, Wind and Fire get in on the jukebox musical trend with this new show about a woman who dreams of dancing on Broadway. Maurice Hines directs and choreographs (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' In previews. Opens Wednesday. The Atlantic Theater Company's acclaimed production of Martin McDonagh's very bloody, exceptionally black comedy about Irish terrorism moves to Broadway (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' Previews start tomorrow. Opens May 10. Nilaja Sun plays teachers, students and janitors in the Epic Theater Center's one-woman examination of the public school system. Hal Brooks directs (1:10). Beckett Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SHINING CITY' In previews. Opens May 9. A guilt-ridden man tells his therapist that he has seen the ghost of his wife in Conor McPherson's new play, which received good reviews at the Royal Court in London. Brian F. O'Byrne, Martha Plimpton and Oliver Platt star (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SORE THROATS' In previews. Opens Sunday. Theater for a New Audience presents a revival of Howard Brenton's Strindbergian study of what happens to a 39-year-old housewife when her marriage falls apart. (2:10). The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A SPALDING GRAY MATTER' Previews start Wednesday. Opens May 6. In a New Group production, the solo artist Michael Brandt explores the tragic final days of Spalding Gray and their parallels to his own life (1:10). Clurman Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' In previews. Opens May 10. Phil Collins lends his invisible touch to the score of the latest Disney musical. David Henry Hwang wrote the book (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'AWAKE AND SING!' Dreams and disappointments, hopes and fears, encouraging words and bitter put-downs clash by day and night in Clifford Odets's turbulent comedy-drama about a Jewish family struggling to stay afloat in the 1930's. A gifted roster of performers -- including Mark Ruffalo, Lauren Ambrose, Zoë Wanamaker and Ben Gazzara -- manage to locate the dreaming centers of their characters, buried beneath layers of political sloganeering, everyday gripes or street slang. And even when the focus occasionally blurs in Bartlett Sher's ultimately moving revival, Odets's zesty dialogue, in which jazzy period colloquialisms are slung around like punches at a prize fight, is a joy to hear (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'BAREFOOT IN THE PARK' For a work that celebrates the liberating force of spontaneity, this revival of Neil Simon's 1963 comedy doesn't have one scene that feels organic, let alone impromptu. Directed by Scott Elliott, and starring Patrick Wilson and a miscast Amanda Peet as newlyweds in Greenwich Village, this ''Barefoot'' has the robotic gait of Frankenstein's monster (2:20). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York City, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FESTEN' An intensely staged, indifferently acted production of David Eldridge's adaptation of a 1998 Danish film about a grim family reunion, which was a big hit in London under the same director, Rufus Norris. While the mise en scène remains unsettlingly stark, the Broadway cast (which includes Michael Hayden, Julianna Margulies, Jeremy Sisto and Ali MacGraw) registers the tension and testiness of people suffering from a collective bad hair day. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' Madly enjoyable. Alan's Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LESTAT' A musical sleeping pill, adapted from Anne Rice's ''Vampire Chronicles'' and featuring songs by Elton John and Bernie Taupin, that could well give the makers of Ambien a run for their money. Dare to look upon this tale of the undead and keep your eyelids from growing heavier and heavier and heavier (2:30). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, near 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Odd is not the word for this couple. How could an adjective suggesting strangeness or surprise apply to a production so calculatedly devoted to the known, the cozy, the conventional? As the title characters in Neil Simon's 1965 comedy, directed as if to a metronome by Joe Mantello, Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick reprise their star performances from ''The Producers,'' and it's not a natural fit. Don't even consider killing yourself because the show is already sold out (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PAJAMA GAME' Sexual chemistry in a Broadway musical? Isn't that illegal now? If it were, then Harry Connick Jr. and Kelli O'Hara -- the white-hot stars of Kathleen Marshall's delicious revival of this 1954 musical -- would be looking at long jail terms. This intoxicating production, which features a charming supporting cast led by Michael McKean, allows grown-up audiences the rare chance to witness a bona fide adult love affair translated into hummable songs and sprightly dance (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THREE DAYS OF RAIN' (2:30). In this revival of Richard Greenberg's slender, elegant drama of family disconnectedness, Julia Roberts is stiff with self-consciousness, glancingly acquainted with the two characters she plays and deeply, disturbingly beautiful. Otherwise, it is almost impossible to discern the virtues of the play itself in this wooden and splintered production, directed by Joe Mantello and also starring Paul Rudd and Bradley Cooper, who have little chance of capturing the audience's attention (2:30). Bernard B. Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Presented as a long, pansexual orgy, Scott Elliot's numbing revival of the Brecht-Weill classic feels like a party where the hangover begins almost as soon as the evening does. The starry cast includes Alan Cumming (as Mac the Knife) and a Dietrich-like Cyndi Lauper, though only Jim Dale and Nellie McKay appear to have a clue as to what the show is about (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did on Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'WELL' Lisa Kron's sparkling autobiographical play about illness, integration and her mother (portrayed with majestic warmth and weariness by Jayne Houdyshell) helps restore the honor of that tarnished literary form, the memoir. Though it shows the strain of scaling up for Broadway, this singular work, which stars Ms. Kron as herself, opens windows of insight and emotion found in no other show (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ASSISTED LOVING' This warm and witty monologue by Bob Morris, who contributes the Age of Dissonance column to the Sunday Style section of The New York Times, is performed by the author, who chronicles his widowed father's and his own search for love in and around New York. Engaging, subtle and winning (1:10). Daryl Roth Theater, D-Lounge, 103 East 15th Street, at Union Square, (212) 239-6200.(George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'BASED ON A TOTALLY TRUE STORY' A chatty, autobiographical comedy by Roberto Aguirre-Sacasa about a writer for comic books who moonlights as a screenwriter and playwright. Juggling his two jobs, the busy writer begins backsliding in his unofficial third, ''being a loving, giving, emotionally available boyfriend.'' Minor-key angst ensues in this perky two hours of comic navel-gazing (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE CONTRAST' Royall Tyler's slender 1787 romantic comedy -- one of the first professional American plays ever produced -- should be of more interest to historians than to theatergoers (2:30). Theater at St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Jason Zinoman).</p>
        <p>'DEFIANCE' The second in John Patrick Shanley's cycle of morality plays that began with ''Doubt,'' this ambitious tale of racial relations and the military mindset on a North Carolina marine base feels both overcrowded and oddly diffuse. If ''Doubt'' has an elegant and energy-efficient sprinter's gait, ''Defiance'' progresses with a flustered air of distraction. The excellent Margaret Colin, as an officer's wife, provides a welcome shot of credibility (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club, Theater 1, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' This noisy novelty is a mixed blessing. Providing a two-foot drum on every seat, it offers an opportunity to exorcise aggressions by delivering a good beating, and, on a slightly more elevated level, it presents a superficial introduction to African culture, lessons in drumming and 90 minutes of nonstop music, song and dancing by a good-natured cast. So, while literally and figuratively giving off many good vibes, it adds up to lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'ENTERTAINING MR. SLOANE' Scott Ellis's underpowered production of Joe Orton's great farce of sexual hypocrisy, which stars Alec Baldwin in a comedy sketch of a performance, is breezy, often funny and rarely convincing. (2:00). Laura Pels Theater at the Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE M. COHAN TONIGHT!' The all-singing, all-dancing Jon Peterson summons the spirit of this legendary Broadway entertainer in this engaging one-man musical, devised and directed by Chip Deffaa (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'GUARDIANS' Peter Morris's play juxtaposes the moral decline of two disparate characters caught up in the destructive tailwinds of the American invasion of Iraq: a cold-blooded tabloid journalist in London and a soldier in the United States Army. Lee Pace and Katherine Moennig give persuasive performances as the sleazy hack and the scapegoated grunt, but Mr. Morris's play is more flashily provocative than truly thoughtful (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 253-9983. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE IMPORTANCE OF BEING EARNEST' Lynn Redgrave is an unusually vigorous Lady Bracknell in Sir Peter Hall's new production of Oscar Wilde's peerless comedy from 1895. A satisfactory production that works effectively as a romantic farce but more erratically as a vehicle for Wilde's paradox-perfumed wit. (2:25) Brooklyn Academy of Music, Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best. (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'LANDSCAPE OF THE BODY' This terrific revival, directed by Michael Greif, identifies the unbearable wistfulness of being in John Guare's delirious heartbreaker of a comedy from 1977. The top-flight cast is led by Lili Taylor and Sherie Rene Scott as sisters -- one living, one a singing ghost -- who move in and out of a lyrical and sordid world where tabloid prurience has become a religion. Signature Theater's Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'LOS BIG NAMES' In the lesbian comic Marga Gomez's friendly new solo show, she measures out affection and mockery in equal doses as she recalls her parents, Willy and Margarita, a comedian and a dancer who lived a splashy life on a small scale in the circumscribed world of New York Latino culture in the 1960's. Ms. Gomez pairs stories of their performing careers with comic tales of her own struggles to pursue success in the entertainment industry. A sendup of the movie ''Sphere'' is particularly delicious (1:30). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MACRUNE'S GUEVARA' The Young Mirror arm of Mirror Repertory revives John Spurling's odd 1969 play about an artist who left behind a wall full of drawings of Che Guevara, and the man who saw something profound in them. Parts of the play read today like a funny sendup of art critics who see too much brilliance in outsider-art gibberish; other parts seem a bit like gibberish of their own (2:15). St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'THE MISTAKES MADELINE MADE' An unhappy office worker rebels by boycotting bathing in Elizabeth Meriwether's frenetic new comedy, which reveals some compelling theatrical moments but doesn't totally cohere (1:20). Culture Project, 45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Zinoman).</p>
        <p>'THE PROPERTY KNOWN AS GARLAND' Adrienne Barbeau as Judy, backstage on the night of her last concert in Copenhagen. Billy Van Zandt's play is tawdry and dull, and Ms. Barbeau's performance offers neither the minor rewards of a decent impersonation nor the guilty pleasures of an indecent one. (1:30). The Actors Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'RED LIGHT WINTER' A frank, occasionally graphic story of erotic fixation and the havoc it can wreak on sensitive types. Written and directed by Adam Rapp, this play is both a doomy romantic drama and a morbid comedy about the anxieties of male friendship. Although somewhat contrived, it features a lovely performance by Christopher Denham as a lonely soul starved for intimacy (2:25). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'STUFF HAPPENS' Daniel Sullivan's sharp, invigorating production of David Hare's journalistic drama about the road to war in Iraq is conducted on the modest scale of a town-hall meeting. The characters (who have names like Bush and Blair) seem less like destiny-shaping gods than the ego trippers in your office. If that means they're too close for comfort, then ''Stuff Happens'' is doing its job (2:50). The Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TRYST' A suspense drama of a distinctly old-fashioned stamp about the romance between a handsome cad (Maxwell Caulfield) and a lonely spinster (Amelia Campbell). Will the wily predator seduce and abandon the mousy milliner? Karoline Leach's play springs a few twists that lack psychological credibility but keep the plot on the boil (2:00). Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ADVENTURES OF CAVEMAN ROBOT: THE MUSICAL' A disjointed but vivid homage and musical parody, by Jeff Lewonczyk and Debby Schwartz, of comic books and superheroes. Sloppy and long, too (2:10). Brick Theater, 575 Metropolitan Avenue, at Lorimer Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 907-3457. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'CHAMPION' and 'THE STUTTERING PREACHER' Two new one-act plays, one a well-drawn family drama and the other a brash and ribald romantic comedy, from the New Federal Theater and Black Spectrum Theater. Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, at Pitt Street, Lower East Side, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Hunka)  'GREY GARDENS' As the socialite in limbo called ''Little'' Edie Beale, Christine Ebersole gives one of the most gorgeous performances ever to grace a musical. Unfortunately, she's a pearl of incalculable price in a show that is mostly costume jewelry. Adapted from the Maysles brothers' 1975 cult documentary movie, a camp favorite, and directed by Michael Greif, with the excellent Mary Louise Wilson as Edie's bedridden mother (2:40). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RING OF FIRE' The man in black turns sunshine yellow in a show that strings songs associated with Johnny Cash into a big, bright candy necklace of a musical revue, created and directed by Richard Maltby Jr. In the current bio-flick ''Walk the Line,'' Cash wrestles demons; ''Ring of Fire'' wrestles with a really bad case of the cutes (2:00). Ethel Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'A SAFE HARBOR FOR ELIZABETH BISHOP' The life of a great poet becomes the stuff of stale prose in this one-woman bio-play by Marta Góes, starring Amy Irving (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOW PEOPLE' Paul Weitz's eyebrow-pencil-thin comedy about a man who hires actors to impersonate his family feels like one long, occasionally amusing party game whose players don't know when to call it a night. The excellent four-member cast, led by Debra Monk and directed by Peter Askin, finds charm and energy amid the vaporous bait-and-switch plot reversals (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 353-0303; closing Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN DREAMZ' (PG-13, 107 minutes) In Paul Weitz's seriously unfunny comedy about a faltering American president, a wildly popular television talent show and the Svengalis behind them both, the jokes don't just fizzle into insignificance; they flop about with gaudy ineffectualness. With Hugh Grant, Dennis Quaid and Mandy Moore. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'ATL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) A couple of rap stars make respectable starts on acting careers in this tale of black teenagers in Atlanta, despite a script marred by clichés and predictability. Tip Harris -- the rapper T. I. -- is intriguing as a young man who takes on the responsibility of raising his younger brother when their parents are killed, and Antwan Andre Patton -- Big Boi from OutKast -- makes a terrific drug lord. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BEAUTY ACADEMY OF KABUL' (No rating, 74 minutes, in English and Dari) In the summer of 2004, a group of volunteer American hairstylists arrived in Kabul to open a school. In ''The Beauty Academy of Kabul,'' the director Liz Mermin documents the hilarious, moving and sometimes fractious meeting of diametrically different cultures, one having suffered unimaginable horrors and the other believing a good perm is the answer to everything. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'DEVIL AND DANIEL JOHNSTON' (PG-13, 110 minutes) The romantic cliché that all artists are a little bit mad is put through its paces (if never seriously questioned) in this documentary about Daniel Johnston, a mentally ill songwriter whom Kurt Cobain, the lead singer for Nirvana, once called the greatest living. Jeff Feuerzeig, who won the best director award at the 2005 Sundance Film Festival, cobbles together a moving portrait of the artist as his own ghost, using a wealth of material provided by Mr. Johnston, from home movies to audiocassette diaries to dozens of original, and often heartbreakingly beautiful, songs. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'DRAWING RESTRAINT 9' (No rating, 135 minutes) Most of this stately film of few words, conceived and directed by the artist Matthew Barney, who stars with his wife, Bjork, takes place on a Japanese whaling ship afloat in Nagasaki Bay. Steeped not only in Japanese seafaring lore but also in centuries-old traditions of Japanese ritual, the film could be described as Mr. Barney's ''Moby-Dick.'' (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'ICE AGE: THE MELTDOWN' (PG, 93 minutes) Creative exhaustion haunts ''Ice Age: The Meltdown,'' as the characters from 2002's ''Ice Age'' face global warming and the submersion of their valley. While the animals head for safety in a giant, arklike boat, the director, Carlos Saldanha, indulges in biblical imagery and bad science. Over all, a flat and uninspired follow-up to a vastly superior movie. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INSIDE MAN' (R, 128 minutes) The latest from Spike Lee takes a familiar setup -- in this case, a Wall Street bank heist that mutates into a hostage crisis -- and twists it ever so slightly and nicely. Among the film's most sustained pleasures are its holy trinity -- Denzel Washington, Clive Owen and Jodie Foster -- and the best lineup of pusses and mugs outside ''The Sopranos.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'KINKY BOOTS' (PG-13, 106 minutes) In this silly, quasi-inspirational British comedy, a staid shoe factory in Northern England avoids ruin by switching from the manufacture of men's dress shoes to that of thigh-high, stiletto-heeled boots worn by drag queens. The recipe for this feel-good movie, which cries out to be made into a musical, comes from the same cookbook that gave us ''The Full Monty.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'L'ENFANT (THE CHILD)' (R, 100 minutes, in French) The latest from the Belgian brothers Jean-Pierre and Luc Dardenne involves a young thief (Jérémie Renier) who one day sells his newborn son for a fat envelope of cash. What interests the Dardennes -- what invests their work with such terrific urgency -- is not only how a man would sell a child as casually as a slab of beef, but also whether a man like this, having committed such a repellent offense, can find redemption. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LUCKY NUMBER SLEVIN' (R, 110 minutes) This star-studded jigsaw puzzle of revenge and mistaken identity thinks that it's terribly smart, although it amounts to an empty, self-satisfied imitation of ''Pulp Fiction'' that reputable actors like Morgan Freeman and Ben Kingsley can't salvage. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE NOTORIOUS BETTIE PAGE' (R, 91 minutes) With the help of her charmingly enthusiastic star, Gretchen Mol, the director Mary Harron unwraps the great 1950's pinup queen Bettie Page, who for years was a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside a web of expertly tied rope. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SCARY MOVIE 4' (PG-13, 83 minutes) This parasitic franchise is back to feed on last year's disposable distractions, proving, if nothing else, that there's a laugh or two left in ''Brokeback Mountain'' parodies and Viagra overdoses. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE SENTINEL' (PG-13, 108 minutes) The question is why: why would a star of Michael Douglas's stature and obvious intelligence attach himself to a Washington thriller as deeply ridiculous, suspense-free and potentially career-damaging as ''The Sentinel''? (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'SIR! NO SIR!' (No rating, 84 minutes) In this smart, very timely documentary, the filmmaker David Zeiger revisits one of the memorable and least revisited chapters of the Vietnam War, the antiwar movement inside the military. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SISTERS IN LAW' (No rating, 106 minutes, in English and pidgin) Grass-roots feminism thrives in a Cameroon village, thanks to the pair of warmhearted, tough-minded women of law profiled in this excellent verité documentary. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'SOMERSAULT' (No rating, 106 minutes) The story of a beautiful 16-year-old runaway (an astonishing lead performance by Abbie Cornish) was garlanded by 13 awards by the Australian Film Institute. Cool-headed and emotionally distanced from its characters, it trains an X-ray eye on their precarious balancing of civilized and bestial impulses. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'TAKE THE LEAD' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Hip-hop and ballroom dancing styles fuse in a South Bronx high school at which a dance teacher, Antonio Banderas, turns gawky ducklings into gliding swans. It's sloppy but mildly endearing. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THANK YOU FOR SMOKING' (R, 92 minutes) The director Jason Reitman has made a glib and funny movie from Christopher Buckley's glib and funny novel about a Big Tobacco lobbyist, but the real attraction here is the hard-working star, Aaron Eckhart. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'V FOR VENDETTA' (R, 131 minutes) James McTeigue directs this D-for-dumb future-shock story about a masked avenger (Hugo Weaving) and his pipsqueak sidekick (Natalie Portman) at war against a totalitarian British regime. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE WILD' (G, 94 minutes) Filled with softness and texture, ''The Wild'' follows Samson the lion (voiced by Kiefer Sutherland) as he escapes from the zoo to rescue his cub, who has stowed away on a ship bound for Africa. With inspired voice work from Eddie Izzard as a pukka koala and William Shatner as a menacing wildebeest, the movie also finds time to explore the travails of single fatherhood and the evils of oppression. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>BAC 40TH INTERNATIONAL FILM AND VIDEO FESTIVAL (Through May 7) The Brooklyn Arts Council's festival of work by independent and student filmmakers continues this weekend. Tomorrow and Sunday's screenings include Micah Schaffer's ''Death of Two Sons,'' about Amadou Diallo and a Peace Corps volunteer who lived with his family; Kevin Burget's ''Harold Weston: A Bigger Belief in Beauty,'' a portrait of Weston, the Modernist painter; and ''Sometimes the Silence Can Seem So Loud: Teen Suicide,'' an 18-minute documentary with almost a dozen directors. Brooklyn Museum, Cantor Auditorium, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 625-0080 ; most screenings free with museum admission. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>THE FILMS OF MIKIO NARUSE (Through May 10) BAMcinématek's tribute to Naruse (1905-69), the Japanese realist filmmaker, continues tonight with ''Sound of the Mountain'' (1954), Naruse's own personal favorite, about an ignored housewife who bonds with her father-in-law. Tomorrow's feature is ''Repast'' (1951), also about an unhappy housewife. ''Mother'' (1952), the story of a struggling single mother, will be shown on Sunday. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 17) The IFC Center's weekend series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues this weekend with ''I Live in Fear'' (1955), starring Toshiro Mifune as an elderly man obsessed with the prospect of nuclear war. Other films in the series will include Kurosawa's classics ''Ran'' (1985), May 12 through 14; ''Rashomon'' (1950), May 19 through 21; ''Seven Samurai'' (1954), May 26 through 29; and ''Yojimbo'' (1961), June 30 and July 2 and 4. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>PRIX JEAN VIGO (Through Dec. 30) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Vigo (1905-34), the French filmmaker, with a series of 41 films from directors who have won the prize that bears his name. Thursday's features are Joël Farges's ''Pondichéry, Juste Avant l'Oubli'' (1987), an ode to the director's hometown in South India. It will be shown with Alain Resnais and Chris Marker's short about African sculpture in museums, ''Les Statues Meurent Aussi,'' and the original English version of Mr. Marker's science-fiction short ''La Jetée'' (1962). (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>REDISCOVERING ROSCOE: THE CAREER OF FATTY ARBUCKLE (Through May 15). The Museum of Modern Art's 54-film retrospective of the acting and directing career of the scandal-ridden Arbuckle (1887-1933) continues tomorrow with a program that includes ''Fatty's Faithful Fido'' (1915), ''Bridge Wives'' (1932) and ''Fatty and Mabel Adrift'' (1916), with Mabel Normand. Three other programs will be shown next week, including ''Early Keystones,'' a collection of eight silents made in 1913 and 1914. (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop  Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>AQUALUNG (Monday) Matt Hales, the piano-playing Briton who records as Aqualung, studiously borrows all the most tedious and indulgent aspects of Coldplay and Radiohead -- the slow-motion brooding, the epic self-pity -- while missing their joyful grandeur. With David Ford. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BENEVENTO-RUSSO DUO (Tonight) The keyboardist Marco Benevento and the drummer Joe Russo have made a gradual rise on the jam-band circuit with kinetic meanderings that often begin in peaceful soul-funk and end up in poundingly insistent climaxes that might as well be punk rock. Figo opens. At 9, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $15 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>'BROADWAY BY THE YEAR: THE MUSICALS OF 1968' (Monday) The year 1968 might be remembered for student protests, escalation in Vietnam and the assassinations of Robert F. Kennedy and the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., but on Broadway it was the year of the grooviest musical ever, ''Hair.'' That show, along with ''Zorba,'' ''Promises, Promises,'' ''The Happy Time'' and others, will get the oh-what-a-time treatment from Brad Oscar, Scott Coulter, Annie Golden, Chip Zien, Lorinda Lisitza and friends. 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824; $40 and 45. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* ROSANNE CASH (Thursday) Ms. Cash performs the live premiere of the songs on her new album, ''Black Cadillac'' (Capitol), a contemplative cycle about the deaths, over two years, of her stepmother, June Carter Cash; her father, Johnny Cash; and her mother, Vivian Liberto Cash Distin. 8 p.m., St. Ann's Warehouse, 38 Water Street, at Dock Street, Brooklyn, (718) 254-8779; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CITIZEN COPE (Tomorrow) Clarence Greenwood, a k a Citizen Cope, is the umpteenth singer-songwriter to use hip-hop beats and drawled rap-sung vocals in search of novelty. 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171; $26. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CULTURE (Tuesday) Culture, led by Joseph Hill, has been a steadfast roots reggae band since the 1960's, singing about Rastafarian faith and everyday suffering and putting a groove behind its messages. In Culture's songs, a dance party and a gospel service are never far apart. 11 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door.(Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* DJ A-TRAK (Tonight) Born Alain Macklovitch in Montreal, DJ A-Trak has been a turntable celebrity since 1997, when he won DMC's World D.J. Championship at age 15. Still a baby-faced prodigy, he is now Kanye West's D.J., and on this solo tour, watching his arms flail back and forth as he scratches records at cartoon speed should be half the fun. He appears with a small posse of guests, including DJ Ayres and Cosmo Baker, two of the hosts of the Rub, a regular hip-hop dance party in Brooklyn; GLC, a phlegmatic rapper from Chicago; and Cuizinier and DJ Orgasmic of the French hip-hop crew TTC. 10 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THOMAS DOLBY (Wednesday and Thursday) Thomas Dolby entered pop eternity in the guise of a bespectacled, wild-haired mad scientist, with the 1983 novelty hit ''She Blinded Me With Science.'' He returns after a long absence -- in his other life he has been an innovative creator of ring tones -- with a tour that finds him largely in the same gearhead persona (sans the hair), surrounded by bizarre-looking doohickeys with colorful gauges and oversize knobs. Wednesday at 10 p.m., Thursday at 7 (with the singer-songwriter Carey Ott) and 10 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DRAGONFORCE (Tuesday) A six-man metal army from London -- with members from Ukraine, Hong Kong, New Zealand and South Africa -- DragonForce sounds like some combination of Iron Maiden, the Scorpions and Yngwie Malmsteen on frantic fast-forward: all the chant-along major-key melodies and fretboard-tickling guitar solos of those 80's metal heroes are there, but sped up to an exhilarating degree. With Protest the Hero and Sanctity. 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or (212) 307-7171; $15 and $17. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* FAUN FABLES (Thursday) On a bed of ghostly acoustic folk, Faun Fables's Dawn McCarthy and Nils Frykdahl build an astonishing and unpredictable kind of pop theater, at once grandiose and nightmarish and silly. The band's new album, ''The Transit Rider'' (Drag City), is a creepily obsessive song cycle about the commuting life, begun by Ms. McCarthy in 1994 and done as a theater piece in San Francisco four years ago. Here it comes on tour, complete with costumes, film and a cast of four. Bonfire Madigan and Transmitting open the show. At 9 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236; $10 in advance, $12 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FORRÓ IN THE DARK (Sunday) For three years, this group has been leading one of New York's best and lowest-tech dance parties at the East Village bar Nublu. The groove is a humble and sexy two-beat dance from northeastern Brazil called forró, made with accordion, hand-held percussion and, since this is New York, whiffs of distorted electric guitar. It travels well, and on Sunday the band comes to S.O.B.'s for a special forró night that includes dance lessons. 9 and 11 p.m., 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $7. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>FRUIT BATS (Tonight and tomorrow) Centered on the guitarist and singer-songwriter Eric Johnson, Fruit Bats, from Chicago, play weightless little nuggets of psych-folk that are deceptively wistful. Behind their apparent melancholy is a playful wit and a modest awe: ''It takes cold fronts and sackcloth skies,'' Mr. Johnson sings. ''It takes leviathans down in the abyss/ The hidden messages of the things that you missed.'' Tonight at 9, with Amandine and Jason Friedman (of the Boggs), at the Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; tomorrow at 9:30 p.m., with Amandine and Sam Jayne (of Love Is Laughter), at Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703. Both are $12. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>HANGDOGS (Tonight) With weary voices and staunch, down-home roots-rock guitars, the Hangdogs sing about unglamorous, hard-drinking men and the women they love and leave. At 10, Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>COLIN HAY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Not all forgotten pop stars age as gracefully as Mr. Hay, who in the 1980's was the voice and face of the Australian new wave goofballs Men at Work. Recently he has been developing a new following with gentle, ruminative acoustic songs; one, ''I Just Don't Think I'll Ever Get Over You,'' was a heart-stopper in the film ''Garden State.'' 8 p.m., Canal Room, 285 West Broadway, at Canal Street, TriBeCa, (212) 941-8100; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ISIS, DALEK (Thursday) Isis creates a fearsomely beautiful sludge out of atonal guitars and a permanently distorted bass. As it works its way to repeated climaxes, the music can feel like a glorious release or the last thrashings of a captured animal. Dalek is a hip-hop trio from Newark led by a rapper of the same name, who intones apocalyptic rhymes over noisy, atmospheric backing tracks. 7:30 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or (212) 307-7171; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>ROBY LAKATOS ENSEMBLE (Tonight) A fiery Gypsy violinist from Hungary descended from Janos Bihari, a legendary player from the early 19th century, Mr. Lakatos is equally at home in classical, jazz and folk repertories. Backed by cimbalom, guitar, bass and piano, he plays everything from traditional pieces and a Liszt dance to a Russian tango and ''Honeysuckle Rose.'' At 8:30, Zankel Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>LL COOL J (Tonight) One of the first bigger-than-the-block personalities of rap, LL Cool J still follows the same few guidelines of self-representation that have served him throughout his long career: be photographed shirtless as often as possible, title all your albums either after yourself (''Todd Smith,'' his latest, refers to his given name, James Todd Smith) or some superlative that Muhammad Ali might have used (''Phenomenon,'' ''Greatest of All Time'') and be as sweatily vigorous a performer as possible. At 8, Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE MOONLIGHTERS (Monday) Few would expect members of Helmet and the Pain Teens to play ukulele-strumming, steel-guitar-sliding, sweetly harmonized, optimistic Hawaiian-style songs. But the Moonlighters do just that, writing anachronistic ballads and swing-style tunes that Bliss Blood sings without a hint of campiness. 10 p.m., Rodeo Bar, 375 Third Avenue, at 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-6500; free. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* JOSH RITTER, HEM (Thursday) Mr. Ritter's guileless, boy-next-door voice is the first clue that he doesn't need a lot of fancy tricks to make a point. Powerfully minimal songwriting is another. But there is no limit to the depth and ambition of his songs, whether he is confessing a simple crush or following his thoughts on a long, Whitmanesque incantation, as he does for more than nine minutes on ''Thin Blue Flame'' from his new album, ''The Animal Years'' (V2). Hem plays somewhat prosaic alt-country, but in such delicate, sensuous arrangements that it doesn't matter. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $15 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SUPER DIAMOND (Tonight and tomorrow night) A tribute to the songs of Neil Diamond, particularly his triumphal 1970's material. Smirking is optional. At 8:30, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $26.50 in advance, $30 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* TINARIWEN (Monday) ''Welcome to the desert,'' announced one member of Tinariwen, wrapped in a turban and a long robe, at a recent concert. It was an unnecessary statement: from the first droning electric guitar lines and hypnotically repetitive handclaps, the audience was already there. Tinariwen, a group of Tuareg nomads from northern Mali, play stark, seemingly endless patterns of modal blues that occasionally snarl in anger or align into stately funk. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Cabaret  Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) The regal cabaret singer and the brassy songs of Kander and Ebb that she is offering in her new show may not be an obvious fit. But Ms. Akers locates the heart inside the brass and sass. 9 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; cover, $60, with a $20 minimum; $60 prix fixe dinner required on Thursdays and at the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. 2 p.m., the Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $55, including brunch at noon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* DIAHANN CARROLL (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Carroll's first New York nightclub appearance in 40 years is a grand but unpretentious summing up by a performer (accompanied by an eight-member band) who has breached racial boundaries while exploring the four corners of show business. Historic anecdotes, nuggets of practical wisdom and show-stopping renditions of songs popularized by Frank Sinatra, Sophie Tucker and others blend into a complex and winning self-portrait. 8:30 and 11 p.m., Feinstein's at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095; $60, with a $40 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER (Tomorrow) This booming pop-blues contralto may not be demure, but she is tasteful in a smart, regal, big-mama way, and she is astute in her choices of often obscure soul, blues and jazz songs that play to her contradictory mixture of the lusty and the philosophical. 7 p.m., Helen's, 169 Eighth Avenue, near 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0609; $20, with a $15 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* MARY CLEERE HARAN  (Tonight and tomorrow) A wonderful no-frills singer with a sophisticated wit, Ms. Haran has a remarkable talent for simultaneously interpreting standards in the spirit in which they were written and looking at them through 21st-century eyes. At 8:45 and 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $60. (Holden)</p>
        <p>ANNIE ROSS (Wednesday) Cool, funny, swinging and indestructible, this 75-year-old singer and sometime actress exemplifies old-time hip in its most generous incarnation. 9:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $12 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz  Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>CLAUDIA ACUÑA QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A vocalist guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile, Ms. Acuña sounds best when supported and stretched by sympathetic musicians, like the pianist Jason Lindner, the cellist and trombonist Dana Leong, the bassist Omer Avital and the percussionist Pernell Saturnino. At 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15; students, $10. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>WES ANDERSON QUARTET (Tuesday through May 7) Mr. Anderson, known as Warmdaddy, is an alto saxophonist with a tart and bluesy sound. The strength of his quartet has a lot to do with the presence of Marc Cary, an adventurous but well-grounded pianist. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FAHIR ATAKOGLU TRIO (Tonight) An accomplished symphonic composer in his native Turkey, Mr. Atakoglu recently released ''If'' (Far &amp; Here), an album featuring his piano playing in a trio setting. As on the album, he plays here with the rhythm team of Anthony Jackson on electric bass and Horacio (El Negro) Hernandez on drums. At 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAËL ATTIAS QUARTET (Thursday) Mr. Attias assembles a texturally minded and exploratory ensemble consisting of his fellow saxophonist Tony Malaby, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Gerald Cleaver. 8 and 10 p.m., Jimmy's Restaurant, 43 East Seventh Street, East Village, (212) 982-3006; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BROOK'S QAWWALI PARTY (Tonight) The Sufi devotional music of Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan provides a mandated repertory for this sprawling ensemble, led by the drummer Brook Martinez. Faithful to its source mainly in exuberance, the group creates a roiling polyphony of percussion, saxophones and brass, bass, harmonium and guitar. At 9 and 10:30, Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHEL CAMILO TRIO (Through Sunday) A percussive, often cathartic pianist, Mr. Camilo recently released a recording of Gershwin's ''Rhapsody in Blue'' (Telarc) with a 95-piece symphony orchestra. His trio, with the bassist Charles Flores and the drummer Dafnis Prieto, can sometimes seem nearly as expansive. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables with a $5 minimum, or $20 at the bar, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVE DOUGLAS QUINTET (Tuesday through May 7) The trumpeter Dave Douglas always seems on the verge of forming a new band, but this one -- with Uri Caine on piano and Fender Rhodes, James Genus on bass and Clarence Penn on drums -- has been a solid entity for several years. Here they celebrate a new album, ''Meaning and Mystery'' (Greenleaf), and a valuable new member, the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LIBERTY ELLMAN SEXTET (Tuesday) ''Ophiuchus Butterfly'' (Pi), Mr. Ellman's ambitious new album, knowingly takes a page or two from his frequent employer, the saxophonist and composer Henry Threadgill. Its hyper-literate polyphony should sound even better live, as performed by Mr. Ellman's acoustic guitar and an ensemble consisting of two alto saxophones, a tuba, an acoustic bass and drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20; students, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ORRIN EVANS QUINTET (Tomorrow) Mr. Evans is a percussive pianist equally attuned to hip-hop and hard bop, and he often surrounds himself with rhythmically assertive compatriots. Here that roll call includes Ralph Bowen, tenor and soprano saxophones; J. D. Walter, vocals; Mark Kelly, bass; and Donald Edwards, drums. 8 and 10 p.m. and midnight, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KENNY GARRETT QUARTET (Wednesday through May 6) Mr. Garrett is a bulldozer on the alto saxophone, which he uses for blazing post-Coltrane calisthenics, and an introspective artisan on the soprano, with which he investigates East Asian folk timbres. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30; $35 on Friday and Saturday, with a $10 minimum.(Chinen)</p>
        <p>LAFAYETTE GILCHRIST (Tomorrow) On his recent album ''Towards the Shining Path'' (Hyena), Mr. Gilchrist reconciles avant-garde pianism with the backbeat swagger of hip-hop, creating a compellingly funky amalgam. Tomorrow night at 12:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $8, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* A GREAT NIGHT IN HARLEM (Thursday) The Jazz Foundation of America, a nonprofit musicians' aid organization that has been hard at work in the months since Hurricane Katrina, has stocked this edition of its annual gala with appearances by the Rebirth Brass Band, the trumpeter Clark Terry, the singers Abbey Lincoln and Odetta, and dozens of other guests (including nonmusical luminaries like Bill Cosby, Dick Parsons and Danny Glover). 8 p.m., Apollo Theater, 253 West 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 245-3999, ext. 29, www.jazzfoundation.org; $100 and $250 for the concert seats; $500 for the concert with the after party; $1,500 for full package, including dinner. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CURTIS HASSELBRING'S DECOUPAGE (Wednesday) Mr. Hasselbring, a trombonist, aims for a chamber-improv ideal in this collaboration with the vibraphonist Matt Moran, the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the percussionist Satoshi Takeishi. 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GERRY HEMINGWAY QUARTET (Sunday) Texture is more of a priority than tempo in Mr. Hemingway's drumming, and his compositions reveal a fruitful fascination with polytonality. He plays here with his longtime collaborators Herb Robertson, a trumpeter, and Mark Helias, a bassist, as well as James Finn on tenor saxophone. 10 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near North Third Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOE LOVANO AND HANK JONES (Through Sunday) Mr. Jones, a pianist in his 80's, and Mr. Lovano, a tenor saxophonist in his 50's, model an exquisitely responsive duologue that would seem rarefied if not for its absolute lack of pretension. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TONY MALABY TRIO (Tonight) Mr. Malaby, a versatile and increasingly prominent tenor saxophonist, enlists the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Gerald Cleaver in a program of original music and choice standards, with an exploratory ethos prevailing. At 9, Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEIKO MATSUI (Through Sunday) Sometimes billowing and ethereal, sometimes crisp and gently funky, the music of Keiko Matsui has been celebrated in smooth jazz and New Age circles. At times, it can also suggest the worldly fusion of Weather Report, which isn't such a bad thing. At 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER GROUP (Sunday) ''Oceana'' (Sunnyside), the most recent album by the guitarist Ben Monder, was one of last year's great surprises: a small-scale but ambitious suite of original music that didn't sound quite like anything else. Mr. Monder presents much of the same material here, with the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Ted Poor. At 8 and 10 p.m., BAR4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, www.bar4.net; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* NEW ORLEANS: CONGO SQUARE (Thursday through May 6) Jazz at Lincoln Center concludes its city-hopping season with a focus on New Orleans, a place that had deep resonance for the organization long before Hurricane Katrina. In the Rose Theater, Wynton Marsalis and the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra will present new music inspired by Congo Square, with help from the African percussionists Yacub Addy and Odadaa. In the Allen Room, the trombonist Wycliffe Gordon will play spirituals and gospel tunes. 7:30 p.m. in the Allen Room, 8 p.m. at Rose Theater, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500; $105.50 and $135.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JEROME SABBAGH QUARTET (Tuesday) Mr. Sabbagh, an unassumingly self-assured tenor saxophonist and composer in the postmodern mainstream, leads a sleek ensemble with Lage Lund on guitar, Gary Wang on bass and Ted Poor on drums. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIERNEY SUTTON / LOSTON HARRIS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ms. Sutton's clear, sweetly sonorous voice isn't inherently a jazz timbre, but she is irrefutably a jazz singer, as she has demonstrated on a number of recent engagements. She shares a bill with Mr. Harris, a singer and pianist with a style patterned after Nat King Cole. At 7:30, Allen Room, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500; $135.50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TERRASSON-OKEGWO-PARKER TRIO (Through Sunday) Throughout the latter half of the 1990's, the pianist Jacky Terrasson led one of jazz's fresher-sounding acoustic piano trios, distinguished not only by his fluid pianism but also by the resonant bass tone of Ugonna Okegwo and the pared-down percussive drive of Leon Parker. Regrouping here, the musicians present themselves as a collective. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow night, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow night. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE TURRE QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Turre, the trombonist and conch shell player, applies both virtuosity and restraint to the conventions of small-group hard bop, in a group including the tenor saxophonist Javon Jackson, the pianist Ronnie Mathews, the bassist Buster Williams and the drummer Dion Parsons. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ZIMMER QUARTET (Tomorrow) The hard bop of the 1960's provides thematic sustenance for Mr. Zimmer, a drummer, and his working band, which features the smartly assertive tenor saxophonist Joel Frahm. At 9 p.m., Night and Day, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, www.nightanddayrestaurant.com; cover, $10, with a $7 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical  Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera  'CENDRILLON' (Tonight and Sunday) Massenet's version of the Cinderella fairy tale, first seen in 1899, is not produced that often, which is surprising, since French opera connoisseurs consider it among his finest and most approachable works. Opera buffs should thank the Manhattan School of Music for staging a production, directed by Chuck Hudson and conducted by Laurent Pillot. Tonight at 8 and Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Manhattan School of Music, Broadway and 122nd Street, Morningside Heights, (917) 493-4428; $20. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'DON PASQUALE' (Tonight) The veteran Austrian director Otto Schenk, who is also an acclaimed comic actor in his homeland, understands that the way to make a rich comic opera like Donizetti's ''Don Pasquale'' work is to treat it seriously. In his wonderful new production for the Met, he accomplishes this vividly. The cast is splendid, especially the charismatic soprano Anna Netrebko, the robust dynamic young baritone Mariusz Kwiecien and, in the title role, the stylish Italian bass Simone Alaimo. Derrick Inouye conducts. 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'LOHENGRIN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) The revival of Robert Wilson's 1998 production of Wagner's ''Lohengrin'' is not the same show that earned the director lusty boos at its premiere. The abstract sets are as haunting as ever. But this time the singers seem more comfortable with the glacial movements and stylized hand and arm gestures, which have been simplified. The riveting cast is headed by the dramatic tenor Ben Heppner in the title role and the charismatic soprano Karita Mattila, in glorious voice as Elsa. (Klaus Florian Vogt makes his Met debut on Wednesday, filling in for Mr. Heppner as Lohengrin.) The conductor Philippe Auguin draws incisive playing from the Met orchestra. Tomorrow at 1 p.m., Wednesday at 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out tomorrow; $26 to $175 on Wednesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>OPERA ORCHESTRA OF NEW YORK (Thursday) Montemezzi's ''Amore Dei Tre Re'' receives an infrequent, if unstaged, hearing from an organization that specializes in such things. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $25 to $125. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'RIGOLETTO' (Monday and Thursday) Though Anna Netrebko and Rolando Villazón, the opera world's hottest soprano-tenor couple, have moved on to other things, Verdi's ''Rigoletto'' is still with us at the Met, but with an entirely new cast. Paolo Gavanelli sings the title role, with Norah Amsellem as Gilda, and Roberto Aronica as the Duke, Italian opera's most caddish character. Monday at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to 175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'RODELINDA' (Tuesday) The Met's premiere production of Handel's ''Rodelinda,'' a highlight last season that played to sold-out houses, returns in the handsome staging by Stephen Wadsworth. Renée Fleming again brings her rich voice and courageous vulnerability to the title role. The countertenor Andreas Scholl makes his Met debut as Bertarido, Rodelinda's husband, the Lombard king of Milan, who has been usurped and is thought dead, but returns to the court incognito. Patrick Summers conducts. 7:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to $175. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'SUSANNAH' (Tonight through Sunday) It's easy to poke fun at Carlisle Floyd's opera for its folksy score, run through with hymn tunes, square dances and Appalachian ditties. Yet this opera, the story of a sensual young woman in rural Tennessee who inadvertently stirs up envy and desire among the townspeople, is more sophisticated than it appears. Mr. Floyd deftly blends folk music elements with a pungently dissonant harmonic language to achieve emotional richness and genuine tragedy. The Dicapo Opera Theater presents a 50th-anniversary production, directed by Michael Capasso and conducted by Steven Osgood. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., St. Jean-Baptiste Church, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 289-9438; $47.50. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* 'TOSCA' (Tomorrow) The soprano Deborah Voigt will not be everyone's idea of a Tosca. Her bright and penetrating singing recalls the Nordic sound and temperament of Birgit Nilsson's in the role. Ms. Voigt invests the part with personal touches, bringing out Tosca's vulnerability. And she sings with daring abandon during the confrontation with the villainous Scarpia, here the bass James Morris, who sounds terrific. 8:30 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN COMPOSERS ORCHESTRA (Wednesday) A cluster of pieces new to most of us and titled ''Erotic Spirits'' offers Deborah Voigt as visiting soprano and Steven Sloane as conductor: with music by Derek Bermel, Brian Current, Kristin Kuster and Stephen Paulus. 8 p.m., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $15 to $42. (Holland)</p>
        <p>BRENTANO STRING QUARTET (Tonight) This first-rate quartet tilts toward the contemporary in a program that begins with Debussy's Quartet in G minor and ends with Shostakovich's Quartet No. 15. Between them, the ensemble gives the premiere of David Horne's Quartet No. 4. 7:30, Weill Recital Hall, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800; $42. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>CONTINUUM (Sunday) This adventurous new-music band performs a program billed as ''A Celebration of Modern American Jewish Composers,'' with works by Paul Schoenfield, Osvaldo Golijov Darius Milhaud and Samuel Adler. 3 p.m., Kane Street Synagogue, 236 Kane Street, between Court and Clinton Streets, Cobble Hill, Brooklyn, (718) 875-1550; $20. (Jeremy Eichler)</p>
        <p>* EMERSON STRING QUARTET (Sunday and Thursday) Among the great composers of the 20th century, Shostakovich was the most inscrutable. But in his 15 string quartets he came closest to showing his hand. These works are like entries in a diary, and he never imagined that they would become as popular as they are today. The Emerson Quartet plays these seminal works compellingly and has recorded them complete. They are performing them in chronological order, a chance to follow Shostakovich's development. No. 4 through No. 6 will be performed Sunday at 5 p.m., and No. 7 through No. 9 on Thursday at 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $60. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC  (Tonight, tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday) Sir Colin Davis returns with some of the composers who have long been his calling cards. Tonight and tomorrow, Ian Bostridge sings Berlioz's exquisite ''Nuits d'Été'' on a program that also includes Mozart's ''Haffner'' Serenade. On Wednesday and Thursday, the program is split between Mozart (the overture to ''La Clemenza di Tito,'' the Piano Concerto No. 26 and the aria ''Ch'io mi scordi di te?'') and Sibelius (''Luonnotar'' and the Third Symphony), with the pianist Mitsuko Uchida and the soprano Soile Isokoski. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Wednesday and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $26 to $94. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* SPECULUM MUSICAE (Monday) One of New York City's most venerable new-music ensembles, Speculum Musicae offers a contemporary classic, Lukas Foss's ''Paradigm,'' as well as works by Louis Andriessen, Harrison Birtwistle and Hughes Dufourt. 8 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance  Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>BALLET FIESTA MEXICANA (Tonight through Sunday) Yloy Ybarra's company returns in a program of work from Mexico, with live music performed by the group Semilla. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 4 p.m., Thalia Spanish Theater, 41-17 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens, (718) 729-3880; $25 to $30. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>* LA BOULE BLANCHE (Monday) The one, the only, the incomparable Katherine Dunham will be celebrated on her 96th birthday in a program of readings from ''Kaiso!,'' a new book of writings by and about Ms. Dunham, and performances of her dances by artists including Loretta Abbott, Glory Van Scott and the Charles Moore Dance Theater. Ms. Dunham is expected to be present. And wear white (it's required). 7 p.m., Theater of the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue, Morningside Heights, (212) 502-0895; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* H. T. CHEN &amp; DANCERS (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Chen, a longtime presence on the city's modern-dance scene, will present what he teasingly calls a dim sum dance experience with programming in honor of Asian Heritage Month. It includes a revival of his 1984 ''Mott Street,'' a celebration of the bustling life of Chinatown, set to music by Charlie Chin. (Through May 7.) 7 p.m., Mulberry Street Theater, 70 Mulberry Street, at Bayard Street, Chinatown, (212) 349-0126; front row, $25; general admission, $15; students and 65+, $10. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NAI-NI CHEN DANCE COMPANY (Tomorrow) The company will perform Ms. Chen's new ''American Landscape,'' a collaboration with the composer and singer Joan LaBarbara that examines immigration in America. 7:30 p.m., New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (888) 466-5722 or www.njpac.org; $32. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DANCE FILMS ASSOCIATION (Sunday) This association celebrates its 50th anniversary and Isadora Duncan with ''The Sensual Woman,'' a program of short films and live performances. 7 p.m., Galapagos Art Space, 70 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 782-5188, galapogosartspace.com; $10. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DANCES PATRELLE (Thursday) Francis Patrelle's new ''Pop,'' set to music by Noël Coward and Jerry Lee Lewis and a medley of songs about New York City, focuses on three different nightclubs from three eras, from the 1930's to the 1950's. (Through May 6.) 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400 or symphonyspace.org; $40 and $35; students and 65+, $36 and $31; $20 for Saturday children's matinee. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>DAO ANH KHANH/STEPHAN KOPLOWITZ (Thursday through Sunday). Vietnam meets America, only this time it's not a war but ''A Walk Between Two Worlds.'' At 7:30 p.m. through tomorrow, with a 2 p.m. performance on Sunday, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $15 and $25. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>* E-MOVES (Tonight through Sunday) They've thought of everything here, with programs of ''E-Merging'' and ''E-Volving'' dance by 13 choreographers and companies (tomorrow night) and ''E-Stablished'' dance by Cynthia Oliver's COCo Dance Theater and Arthur Aviles's Typical Theater, the latter in choreography set to 1950's music by Tito Puente and Celia Cruz (tonight and Sunday). Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30, Sunday at 3 p.m., Aaron Davis Hall, City College, Convent Avenue and West 135th Street, Hamilton Heights, (212) 650-7100; $18 per program, $26 for both. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* THE FORSYTHE COMPANY (Tuesday through Thursday) The United States debut of William Forsythe's new company, which he founded after the demise of his Frankfurt Ballet and which first performed in Frankfurt last year. The program consists of his ''Kammer/Kammer'' (2000), with live video projected around the theater. (Through May 6.) 7:30 p.m., Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100 or bam.org; $20 to $70. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>HEDWIG DANCES (Tonight through Sunday) From Chicago, this august modern-dance troupe will perform works by Jan Bartoszek (the company's artistic director), Jan Eckert and Maray Gutierrez that has been inspired by themes ranging from Goya's ''Caprichos'' to the intimate rules of the bath. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $18; students and 65+, $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARK JARECKE PROJECT (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Jarecke's ''Everything Up Until Now and Including'' is an evening-long and physically demanding solo performed by, and created in collaboration with, Andrea Johnston. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St, Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org; $15. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>JOYCE SOHO PRESENTS 2006 (Thursday) Twelve new choreographers will be featured in this showcase in programs that will be performed Thursdays through Saturdays through May 20. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; $12 for students and 65+; $35 for a three-weekend pass. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* AKRAM KHAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) The United States premiere performances of a commissioned work, ''ma'' (''earth''), by this fashionable and successful London-based, Kathak-trained choreographer. At 8, Rose Theater, Jazz at Lincoln Center, Broadway at 60th Street, (212) 721-6500 or lincolncenter.org; $30 to $58. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* MIAMI CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday) Edward Villella's Balanchine-flavored company, offering repertory by Balanchine, Robbins, Paul Taylor and Twyla Tharp in theaters around but not in New York City. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Tilles Center for the Performing Arts, C. W. Post College campus of Long Island University, Brookville, N.Y., (516) 299-3100 or tillescenter.org; $40 to $70. Sunday at 5 p.m., the Performing Arts Center, Purchase College, State University of New York, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (914) 251-6200 or www.artscenter.org; $42 to $62. Tuesday at 8 p.m., McCarter Theater, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787 or (888) 278-7932 or mccarter.org; $42 to $55. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* RICHARD MOVE (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Move, fresh from his appearance as Martha Graham and his duet with Desmond Richardson at the Graham Dance Company gala, presents ''The Show (Achilles Heels).'' This mega-hip take on things Greek will offer Deborah Harry (a k a Blondie) singing live songs as Athena, and Rasta Thomas in the title role, originally performed by Mikhail Baryshnikov in the piece's out-of-town White Oak Dance Project premiere in 2002. The cast also includes Katherine Crockett from the Graham company. Arto Lindsay did the score. Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through May 6, at 8, at the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, ext. 11 or thekitchenorg; $20.(Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL DANCE THEATER COMPANY OF JAMAICA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Dance and music reflecting Jamaican culture, by the company director Rex Nettleford, Arsenio Andrade and Christopher Walker. Tomorrow night at 8, Sunday at 2 p.m., Brooklyn Center at Brooklyn College, one block from the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Flatbush, Brooklyn, (718) 951-4500 or brooklyncenter.com; $20 to $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL DANCE WEEK (Sunday) The celebration in New York concludes this weekend with a free performance and film screenings, also free. The United States Latin Dance Champion Melanie LaPatin will join six professional and studio companies in a performance. 2:30 p.m., Dance Times Square, 156 West 44th Street, Manhattan, ndw-nyc.org. The film programs include Henry Chalfont's ''Mambo to Hip-Hop,'' which will be screened on Sunday at 3 p.m. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK CITY BALLET (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday through Thursday) The company's intermittent run of Balanchine's full-evening ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' can be seen tonight, tomorrow afternoon and Sunday afternoon. The Diamond Project, with its seven premieres, gets under way tomorrow night with a new ballet by Eliot Feld, part of an all-Feld program repeated Wednesday, and continues on Thursday with a premiere by Mauro Bigonzetti. The season runs until June 25. Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 2 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m.; Tuesday and Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. The New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org; $30 to $86; student rush tickets, $15. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK THEATER BALLET (Tonight and tomorrow night) This chamber ballet company wraps up its spring season with a program honoring Agnes de Mille as a dancer in ballets like Anthony Tudor's ''Judgment of Paris,'' and as the choreographer of classic musicals, including ''Oklahoma!'' and ''Brigadoon.'' At 7:30, Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100 or ticketmaster.com; $30; $15 for 65+ and students. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>PERIPHERAL DANCES (Sunday) The program includes dances by choreographers including Gail Accardi, Laurie DeVito, Akiko Tomikawa and Mami and Maki, and dance film by Kristina Jones. (Sundays through May 14.) 7:30 p.m., Green Space Studio Theater, 34-24 24th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 995-8089; $10. (Dunning).</p>
        <p>PMT SPRING SHOWCASE (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company of the hip-hop teacher Pavan Thimmaiah will perform with six other troupes and individuals in a program of modern, jazz and hip-hop dance. At 8, Martin Luther King Jr. Auditorium, 122 Amsterdam Avenue, between 65th and 66th Streets, Manhattan, (212) 924-5694; $16. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SILVER-BROWN DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) The company will perform dances by Eva Silverstein to music by Otis Redding. At 8, Alvin Ailey Citigroup Theater, 405 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-0255 or theatermania.com; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>JEANETTE STONER &amp; DANCERS (Thursday) Ms. Stoner, who has performed with Alwin Nikolais and Nancy Meehan, will present multimedia dance that includes her new ''Light,'' an exploration of different kinds of illumination. (Through May 7.) 8 p.m., Stoner Loft, 83 Leonard Street, between Broadway and Church Street, SoHo, (212) 226-1576; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>STREB S.L.A.M. (Tonight through Sunday) Batten down the hatches. Elizabeth Streb's fearless high-flyers are at it again in ''Wild Blue Yonder,'' a new spring program paying tribute to early heroes of aviation, presented informally with popcorn. (Through May 14.) Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 3 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Streb Lab for Action Mechanics, 51 North First Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $15; $10 for children; under 4, free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN FOLK ART MUSEUM: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' through Sept. 17. The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. Few exhibitions this size (35 pieces) present quite such a vivid and rewarding picture of artistic assimilation and transformation. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* BARD GRADUATE CENTER: 'AMERICAN STREAMLINED DESIGN: THE WORLD OF TOMORROW,' through June 11. Streamlining, a particularly American design concept born of our love of speed and admiration for industrial production, peaked in the 1930's and 40's, and is now said to be undergoing a revival. This tribute to it includes more than 180 objects, from boring but useful items like a receipt printer designed by Walter Dorwin Teague in 1946 to a plastic bicycle helmet of flowing teardrop shapes designed by John Larkin in 2000. The show doesn't shy away from the grittier aspects of industrial design, presenting objects like air compressors and electric sanders along with those of higher style, like a harmonica of chromium-plated and enameled steel with rounded edges and a ribbed binding, designed by John Vassos about 1939. The show is perhaps too packed with repetitive examples -- do we need to see three similar electric drills? -- but don't let that stop you. There's no shortage of wonderful things to look at here. 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to, and settlement in, the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: WILLIAM WEGMAN: 'FUNNEY/STRANGE,' through May 28. Descended from Marcel Duchamp and Buster Keaton, Mr. Wegman has straddled high and low for more than three decades, using his signature Weimaraners to make the art world's funniest videos, as well as television commercials, calendars and children's books. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>DAHESH MUSEUM OF ART: 'STORIES TO TELL: MASTERWORKS FROM THE KELLY COLLECTION OF AMERICAN ILLUSTRATION,' through May 21. During the Golden Age of Illustration -- the 1880's to the 1930's -- images made by painters for magazines and books captivated the collective American psyche. Original works by some of the best of those artists, including J. C. Leyendecker, N. C. Wyeth and Charles Dana Gibson, are included in this extensive and well-selected exhibition. 580 Madison Avenue, near 57th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'GOYA'S LAST WORKS,' through May 14. This compact show is sublime. The most humane portraits are mixed with sketches, like diary entries, in which society is an irredeemable mob of lunatics and murderers. In exile in Bordeaux, Goya spent his last days in physical misery, lamenting man's essential evil while experimenting with the new medium of lithography and inventing the most exquisite, luminous paintings on tiny chips of ivory. Like the late works of Titian or Rembrandt, Goya's late works achieve a whole new level of freedom and depth, haunted by death but exalted. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' through July 16. Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love.'' (See above.) (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'DAVID SMITH: A CENTENNIAL,' through May 14. David Smith is best known for his worst work, bulky sculptures of the ''important'' kind that museums and banks like to buy. Much (though not all) of that material has been excised from this survey in favor of smaller, earlier, nonmonumental pieces that the curator, Carmen Gimenez, presents with plenty of air and light. The result is exemplary as a David Smith experience, an American Modernism experience and a Guggenheim Museum experience. (212) 423-3500. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL CENTER OF PHOTOGRAPHY: 'SNAP JUDGMENTS: NEW POSITIONS IN CONTEMPORARY AFRICAN PHOTOGRAPHY,' through May 28. If Martians tuned into our television news broadcasts, they'd have a miserable impression of life on Earth. War, disease, poverty, heartbreak and nothing else. That's exactly how most of the world sees Africa: filtered through images of calamity. The Nigerian-born curator Okwui Enwezor offers a bracing alternative view in this show of recent photography from Africa. He isn't interested in simply exchanging an upbeat Africa for a downbeat one, smiles for frowns, but in engineering a slow, complex, panoptical turn in perspective, one that takes in many moods and directions. The results are stimulating, astringent, brimming with life. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'HATSHEPSUT,' through July 9. Can a queen be a king, too? Consider the case of Hatshepsut, an Egyptian ruler of the 15th century B.C. She assumed the supreme title of pharaoh and ruled Egypt in that powerfully masculine role until her death. Hatshepsut is the subject of a celebratory show at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, one that commemorates the 100th anniversary of the Met's department of Egyptian art. Organized by the Met and the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, it includes many objects from the Met's own extensive holdings, excavated at its digs in the 1920's and 30's. But it isn't so easy to follow Hatshepsut's trail in this ambitious show, what with the number of relatives, subordinates, minor officials and such who also have a place in it, along with scarabs, jewelry, pottery, furniture and other artifacts. (212) 535-7710. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>MET: KARA WALKER AT THE MET: 'AFTER THE DELUGE,' through July 30. The Metropolitan Museum of Art's first foray into artist-organized shows is a small tour de force of curatorial creativity. Inspired partly by Hurricane Katrina, Ms. Walker has combined works from the Met with examples of her own art, connecting shared themes of race, poverty and water to illuminate contemporary art's inevitable dialogue with past art. The show has as many crosscurrents and undertows as a river. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'EDVARD MUNCH: THE MODERN LIFE OF THE SOUL,' through May 8. This affecting, full-scale retrospective is the first survey of this Norwegian painter in an American museum in almost 30 years. Its more than 130 oils and works on paper cover Munch's entire career, from 1880 to 1944. (212) 708-9400. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'WITHOUT BOUNDARY: SEVENTEEN WAYS OF LOOKING,' through May 22. This excellent group show considers what ''Islamic'' means in the work of several contemporary artists, and it means many things, none simple. Just to see the uses made of calligraphy by Shirazeh Houshiary, Rachid Koraichi and Shirin Neshat is to understand the lesson in variety put forward here. At the same time, the show is far from didactic. It's beautiful, sexy and, in the case of Raqib Shaw's painting and Kutlug Ataman's video of Sufi meditation, ecstatic. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NEUE GALERIE: 'KLEE AND AMERICA,' through May 22. For a long time, the Swiss-born artist Paul Klee (1879-1940), regarded as a leading Modernist figure in Europe, didn't believe his delicate, chimerical work had much of a future in the United States. Yet, thanks to artists, collectors and dealers with close contacts in Germany who had begun to discover his work, by the early 1920's, Klee's impact began to be felt here. This show of more than 60 paintings and drawings assembled exclusively from American holdings covers the wide spectrum of Klee's work. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* THE STUDIO MUSEUM IN HARLEM: 'ENERGY/EXPERIMENTATION: BLACK ARTISTS AND ABSTRACTION, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art: abstraction. This show is stylishly installed (one gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer); the 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. One, the sculptor Tom Lloyd (1921-96), opened the Studio Museum with a solo show in 1968. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART: 'WHITNEY BIENNIAL 2006: DAY FOR NIGHT,' through May 28. This biennial will provoke much head-scratching by uninitiated visitors. A hermetic take on what has been making waves, it's packaged -- branded might be the better word -- as a show long on collaboration and open-endedness: several shows under one roof, including a revival of the 1960's ''Peace Tower,'' which rises like a Tinker Toy construction from the Whitney courtyard, with contributions by dozens of artists. As a counter to the image of the art world as rich, youth-besotted and obsessed with crafty little nothings, the ethos here is provisional, messy, half-baked, cantankerous, insular -- radical qualities art used to have when it could still call itself radical and wasn't like a barnacle clinging to the cruise ship of pop culture. That was back in the 1970's. And much of what's here (including works by bohemians and other senior eccentrics around then) harks back to that moment. (800) 944-8639 or www.whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>BALÁZS KICSINY: 'EXACT TIME' Representing Hungary in the 2005 Venice Biennale, Mr. Kicsiny showed the surrealistic, Matthew Barneyesque video on view here. Called ''The Cobbler's Apprentice,'' it presents the overhead view of a giant clock; a woman at each numeral strikes the hour with a shoemaker's hammer, as a man crawls endlessly around the rim. Also on view are a video of a performance called ''In the Pump Room'' and a series of small surrealistic watercolors. Janos Gat, 1100 Madison Avenue, at 82nd Street, (212) 327-0441, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* ECHOES FROM THE STEPPES: MONGOLIAN 17TH-, 18TH- AND 19TH-CENTURY BRONZES AND PAINTINGS The bronzes represent the four styles of Mongolian religious sculpture, but the main event is the 77 sakhuis paintings -- small, finely wrought, richly colored portraits of Buddhist priests and protective or wrathful deities that the nomadic Mongols wore, framed in silver, as amulets. E. &amp; J. Frankel, 1040 Madison Avenue, at 79th Street, (212) 879-5733, through May 6. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>DARREN ALMOND /JANICE KERBEL: 'THE IMPOSSIBLE LANDSCAPE' Nothing is obvious in this handsome show of works by two London-based Conceptualists. The connection is that both make visible things that are in different ways impossible. Ms. Kerbel's elegantly abstracted designs for gardens in an office, a Laundromat and other unlikely places are meant to be imagined but never actually built. Mr. Almond's sumptuous, subtly eerie landscape photographs were shot at night using long exposures, making visible what would be invisible to the naked eye. The Horticultural Society of New York, 128 West 58th Street, (212) 757-0915, through May 5. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>'THE GARDEN PARTY' This crowded group show on the theme of the erotic garden looks as if it were produced by a college fraternity for its spring festival. It includes high-profile artists like Vanessa Beecroft, Olafur Eliasson and Yoko Ono. Deitch Projects, 76 Grand Street, near Greene Street, (212) 343-7300, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>HANNA LIDEN: 'HAIRFACES, SCAPEGOATS, BIRDS, BLOODSUCKERS, SQUAREHEADS &amp; A FEW DEATHS' A Swedish artist who is in this year's Whitney Biennial, Ms. Liden produces staged color photographs that resemble stills from a low-budget gothic horror movie. With young people in tribal masks menaced by black shrouded figures of death in beautiful wilderness settings, they suggest a meeting of Ingmar Berman and ''The Road Warrior.'' Rivington Arms, 4 East Second Street, East Village, (646) 654-3213, through May 14. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>ED CLARK: 'REBIRTH' Mr. Clark, who turns 80 on May 6, uses push brooms to sweep great quantities of paint across medium-large canvases, creating bold, suave and sensuous Abstract Expressionist evocations of oceanic flux. G. R. N'Namdi, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 929-6645, through May 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>JAMES SURLS: 'COMPLETE FRAGMENTS' Mr. Surls, who lives in Carbondale, Colo., used to cultivate a funky, Southwestern Outsider style in his carved- and burnt-wood sculpture. Now under the influence of Miró and Picasso, his constructions of abstracted flowers in wood and metal have acquired a curious, kitschy Modernist elegance. Charles Cowles, 537 West 24th Street, (212) 741-8999, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>DAVOR VRANKIC With impressively skillful application of graphite on paper, this Paris-based Croatian artist creates darkly comical images of big-eyed, E.T.-like monsters who appear to be undergoing some terrible psychological suffering. The Proposition, 559 West 22nd Street, (212) 242-0035, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'AN AMERICAN ABROAD: SANDRA FISHER AND HER SCHOOL OF LONDON FRIENDS' Fisher, who was married to the painter R. B. Kitaj, was an American who lived in London until her death in 1994 at age 47. This show of more than 60 drawings and paintings, mostly portraits or nudes, reveals a modestly talented traditionalist with a deft, painterly touch and a down-to-earth affection for her subjects. Also included are some portraits of Fisher by artists like Frank Auerbach, Avigdor Arikha and Mr. Kitaj. New York Studio School, 8 West Eighth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 673-6466, through May 13. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>*AL HANSEN A lively, compact retrospective of the career of an artist known for silhouettes of curvy women made by collaging cut-up pieces of Hershey candy bar wrappers. Andrea Rosen, 525 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 627-6000; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>*MIYOKO ITO (1918 to 1983) was an inspiration for many artists who came of age in Chicago in the 1960's and 70's. This beautiful exhibition of paintings from that time is the first presentation of her work in New York since 1978. Adam Baumgold, 74 East 79th Street, (212) 861-7338; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>SIOBHAN LIDDELL: 'LIMINAL' Best known for slight, ephemeral forms of sculpture and installation, this British artist is now attempting more substantial fare in unglazed ceramic and cut-paper collage. The result is a nervy but unfocused array. The high point may be her embroidery of a dragon, hanging in the office. CRG Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 229-2766; closes Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>GIANNI MOTTI: 'SPIRIT OF JOHN LENNON' Can a psychic hired by an artist summon the ghost of this Beatle to a large, dark, closed-off gallery in Chelsea? Don't hold your breath. And don't expect the video installation orchestrated around the concept to be too entertaining, either. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, (212) 206-7100; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>ANDY WARHOL'S WORLD: 'PHOTOGRAPHY &amp; TELEVISION' A wall-to-wall selection of 313 previously unpublished, unexhibited photographs from the mid-1970's to the mid-1980's offers further proof of Andy Warhol's extraordinary talent and the offhand yet driven way he wielded it, while also forming a visual diary of his peripatetic social life. Zwirner &amp; Wirth, 32 East 69th Street, (212) 517-8677; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 29, 2006, Saturday  Because of a production error, a photograph of a scooter was published in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday without a caption. It showed a Rideout Skippy-Racer scooter that is on view in the show ''American Streamlined Design: The World of Tomorrow'' at the Bard Graduate Center, 18 West 86th Street, Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 29, 2006, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, a photograph of a scooter was published in the Listings pages of Weekend yesterday without a caption. It showed a Rideout Skippy-Racer scooter that is on view in the show ''American Streamlined Design: The World of Tomorrow'' at the Bard Graduate Center, 18 West 86th Street, Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
