<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Field Trip Guzzling Gas, Among the Environmentalists</title>
    <meta content="25hummer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/25/automobiles/autospecial/25hummer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUMMER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4D71130F936A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Field Trip Guzzling Gas, Among the Environmentalists</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Field Trip Guzzling Gas, Among the Environmentalists</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>TAKOMA PARK, MD.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S hard to be inconspicuous in a banana-yellow Hummer H2, especially in this politically correct suburb of Washington. Takoma Park was one of the first cities in America to declare itself nuclear-free, and its churches have held screenings of ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' Al Gore's documentary on the perils of climate change caused by the reckless burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>So it was particularly difficult for Dan Becker, the director of the Sierra Club's global warming program, to be seen high up in the H2 cab as we rumbled through the leafy lanes here, past compost piles, rainbow flags and recycling bins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After six years on the market, G.M.'s big beast is no longer a novelty, although it is still a favorite target of environmentalists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S hard to be inconspicuous in a banana-yellow Hummer H2, especially in this politically correct suburb of Washington. Takoma Park was one of the first cities in America to declare itself nuclear-free, and its churches have held screenings of ''An Inconvenient Truth,'' Al Gore's documentary on the perils of climate change caused by the reckless burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>So it was particularly difficult for Dan Becker, the director of the Sierra Club's global warming program, to be seen high up in the H2 cab as we rumbled through the leafy lanes here, past compost piles, rainbow flags and recycling bins.</p>
        <p>''This is where I should put a bag over my head,'' Mr. Becker said as we crossed the city's border, pausing from a rapid-fire monologue on the role of the automobile industry, and the sport-utility vehicle in particular, in the heating of the planet. The 6,400-pound Hummer H2 is the ultimate symbol of automotive excess, he said, a rolling one-vehicle climate wrecking crew. I had invited Mr. Becker to ride with me in a Hummer to hear his take on it and see the reactions -- if any -- it evoked here. Mr. Becker had never ridden in a Hummer, though he has often commented on its contribution to global warming. And I had wanted to experience driving one before the melting glaciers washed them all out to sea.</p>
        <p>The Hummer, however, attracted relatively little attention on this rainy Saturday afternoon, except for an occasional sidelong glance as we tried to navigate the narrow streets. After six years on the market, the big beast is no longer a novelty, although it is still a favorite target of environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker referred to it as the Valdez, and at one point asked, ''Shouldn't we have cigars?''</p>
        <p>Surely no other vehicle has a Web site devoted to pictures of people saluting with a single finger. The Sierra Club has a Web site of its own devoted just to the Hummer, sierraclubplus.org/hummerdinger, which shows a dinosaur on its back in tribute to the end of production of the original Hummer H1, the civilian model of the military Humvee.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the allure of the big truck appears to be waning, as gasoline prices have soared. General Motors, which makes the machine, sold only 34 H1's in July as collectors snapped up the last production models. Sales of the relatively more street-worthy H2 were down by more than half from last July, to 1,291 from 2,783, and are off about 40 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>But the latest model, the H3, the ''cute'' Hummer meant to appeal to suburban mothers, is selling briskly, with nearly 30,000 rolling out of showrooms so far this year. The automakers' other giants -- S.U.V.'s like the Escalade, Armada, Navigator and Excursion -- continue to move, albeit with substantial discounts.</p>
        <p>It's enough to make Mr. Becker weep.</p>
        <p>''Even as gas prices have doubled and trebled over the past several years, we see little change in driving behavior,'' he said, fumbling around the H2 cockpit for what he thought would be an ejector-seat button for liberals. ''There is little increase in car-pooling; the use of mass transit is flat. There is some switching of vehicles to smaller cars, but only at the margins. The drop-off in S.U.V. sales is about 6 or 7 percent, not tens of percents as you would expect.''</p>
        <p>Instead of investing heavily in new technologies for fuel efficiency, he said, automakers are continuing to churn out gas guzzlers and paying lawyers to lobby against mileage standards and California's tough new laws on tailpipe emissions and greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The oil companies are little better, Mr. Becker said. ''Most of the oil companies are not spending much on alternative fuels,'' he said. ''BP has invested some, a couple of others are spending at the margins. But look at where their profits are going -- to executive pay, not solar power.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker also dismissed the experiment to convert one of Arnold Schwarzenegger's fleet of Hummers to hydrogen fuel. ''It's just a really dumb idea,'' he said. ''It's like putting wings on a sow. It takes a lot of electricity to separate the H2 from the O, which for now can only be done by burning fossil fuels. It's wasteful for any kind of vehicle. For this thing, it's ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Becker, no surprise, drives a Toyota Prius hybrid, the original 2000 model. It is the only car in his four-person household in Chevy Chase, Md., not far from Takoma Park, and he drives it less than 10,000 miles a year. It is powered by a 58-horsepower four-cylinder gasoline engine, which is supplemented by an electric motor that produces the equivalent of 40 horsepower. He says it gets 48 miles a gallon on the highway and in the mid-40's in town. Two Priuses and an 800-pound heifer weigh less than an empty H2.</p>
        <p>G.M. helpfully provides a fuel consumption computer right on the H2's dash. On a round trip from Philadelphia (the closest place to Washington I could find to rent a Hummer), I coaxed a highway average of 12.4 miles a gallon from the thing. But the fuel consumption setting was more fun to watch. Starting up from a stoplight, the Hummer burned fuel at the rate of three miles a gallon. Merging on a freeway ramp brought it down to one mile a gallon, at which point the brute would have an effective cruising range of 32 miles on a full tank of gas.</p>
        <p>On our jaunt around Takoma Park, the consumption gauge fluctuated between 6 to 10 miles a gallon, although it registered 39 as we coasted down a hill.</p>
        <p>After about an hour, Mr. Becker had had enough. He asked me to drop him off in the alley behind his house. ''Please don't park it in front,'' he said. ''I have my reputation to protect.''</p>
        <p>I rumbled toward home, too, hoping not to encounter anyone I knew, either. Though no one had pelted me with eggs or waved rudely, I was delighted to return to my inconspicuous blue Saab.</p>
        <p>THE HUMMER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
