<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>M.B.A.'s With Three Bottom Lines: People, Planet and Profit</title>
    <meta content="mba" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/08/education/edlife/mba.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1730196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hewlett-Packard Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of California</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC1530F93BA35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>M.B.A.'s With Three Bottom Lines: People, Planet and Profit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">M.B.A.'s With Three Bottom Lines: People, Planet and Profit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Abby Ellin</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN business schools, ''green'' thinking means more than concern for the environment. Social responsibility (no sweatshops, no Enrons) and economic viability (this is business) are also part of the definition making its way into the mainstream. Many traditional M.B.A. programs have begun to recognize a triple bottom line -- of people, planet and profit -- and at a few institutions, the marriage of commerce and social responsibility is the guiding principle.</p>
        <p>New College of California has gone so far as to trademark the phrase Green M.B.A. The college opened in San Francisco in the 1970's as an educational haven for social activists; in 2003, it began offering an M.B.A. in sustainable business. The Bainbridge Graduate Institute in Washington State and the Presidio School of Management at Presidio World College in San Francisco also focus their entire curriculums on sustainable business -- what Gifford Pinchot, Bainbridge's chairman, defines as ''good business practices in the present that leave the world better off for future generations.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In business schools, "green" thinking means more than concern for the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN business schools, ''green'' thinking means more than concern for the environment. Social responsibility (no sweatshops, no Enrons) and economic viability (this is business) are also part of the definition making its way into the mainstream. Many traditional M.B.A. programs have begun to recognize a triple bottom line -- of people, planet and profit -- and at a few institutions, the marriage of commerce and social responsibility is the guiding principle.</p>
        <p>New College of California has gone so far as to trademark the phrase Green M.B.A. The college opened in San Francisco in the 1970's as an educational haven for social activists; in 2003, it began offering an M.B.A. in sustainable business. The Bainbridge Graduate Institute in Washington State and the Presidio School of Management at Presidio World College in San Francisco also focus their entire curriculums on sustainable business -- what Gifford Pinchot, Bainbridge's chairman, defines as ''good business practices in the present that leave the world better off for future generations.''</p>
        <p>Along with traditional courses like accounting and inventory management, students learn about toxic waste, marketing eco-friendly businesses, emissions regulations and the effect of environmental actions on profits. Presidio, an accredited decade-old college directed at midcareer diploma completion, began its program in 2002 and has conferred 20 M.B.A.'s so far. New College has granted 35. Bainbridge, which also opened in 2002 and is seeking accreditation, has 15 graduates.</p>
        <p>One of them is now environmental product steward for Hewlett-Packard's inkjet printer line. Most, however, have started their own companies.</p>
        <p>Joey Shepp, a graduate of the University of California, Santa Cruz, received a master's from New College last spring. He chose New College for its smaller classes and ''an education that was more on the cutting edge,'' he says. ''None of the bigger schools had incorporated that level of sustainability in their curriculum.'' A self-described visionary artist, entrepreneur, technologist and, yes, tree hugger, he is now Internet marketing director of Green Festival, which organizes marketplaces for eco-friendly entrepreneurs, and helped found a company that designs Web sites for sustainable businesses and another that grades corporations for their social responsibility.</p>
        <p>Those in the field say that the focus of these M.B.A. programs is the wave of the future, although their narrow scope is not without its limitations.</p>
        <p>''They're providing fundamentals, but they may not be as deep as your traditional M.B.A.,'' says Mark Milstein, a business research director at the World Resources Institute in Washington and a lecturer at the graduate business school at Cornell. ''They're innovative programs with interesting faculty,'' he says. ''But they're not part of a larger institution, so students are getting a very limited offer.''</p>
        <p>While traditional M.B.A. programs may not satisfy an activist, they are increasingly shrewd about social responsibility: Case Western Reserve, Northwestern, Stanford, the University of Michigan and George Washington University all have concentrations in sustainable enterprise. Yale School of Management has offered a joint degree -- an M.B.A. and Master of Environmental Management -- in conjunction with the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies for more than 25 years.</p>
        <p>A survey of 91 business schools released in October by the World Resources Institute and the Aspen Institute found that 54 percent require a course in ethics, corporate social responsibility, sustainability or business and society, up from 34 percent in 2001.</p>
        <p>''More and more students are interested in socially responsible business,'' says Matt Cheney, chief executive at Renewable Ventures, which finances and operates solar power plants. ''They want to make a difference, and there is a confidence that business can produce results quickly and significantly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, whose M.B.A. comes from Stanford, thinks big business is ready.</p>
        <p>''Given the high prices of oil and the growing frustration with global warming, people are concerned but they aren't necessarily taking action,'' he explains. ''Businesses and individuals take action when there are solutions, when companies can do something good for the environment and help the bottom line, when individuals can work for a company selling a product from a sustainable source. An M.B.A. that provides students with the tools to help find those solutions will always be in demand.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
