<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Case for Inherited Wealth; A Likable Heir To the Throne</title>
    <meta content="02AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/02/automobiles/02AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1773259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Land Rover</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ulrich, Lawrence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Land Rover</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D91430F931A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Case for Inherited Wealth; A Likable Heir To the Throne</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Likable Heir to the Throne</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE ULRICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ulrich, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of 2006 Range Rover Sport utility vehicle; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE luxury S.U.V. is out of fashion, we're told, its cultural moment over. Sure. And hip-hop is dead, replaced by a new wave of folkie protest singers.</p>
        <p>Certainly, many Americans have tired of gluttonous, monstrous S.U.V.'s. But deluxe trucks still attract those who feel no financial or psychic distress over $3-a-gallon gasoline. From urban hip-hoppers to suburban fashionistas, such buyers can ignore those who preach that the holy hybrid is the only path to automotive righteousness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new Range Rover Sport is so seductive that it might wash anxieties about global warming and oil right out of your mind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE luxury S.U.V. is out of fashion, we're told, its cultural moment over. Sure. And hip-hop is dead, replaced by a new wave of folkie protest singers.</p>
        <p>Certainly, many Americans have tired of gluttonous, monstrous S.U.V.'s. But deluxe trucks still attract those who feel no financial or psychic distress over $3-a-gallon gasoline. From urban hip-hoppers to suburban fashionistas, such buyers can ignore those who preach that the holy hybrid is the only path to automotive righteousness.</p>
        <p>Let me state up front that I'd rather drive a Mini Cooper than a monster truck. But the new Range Rover Sport is so seductive that it might wash anxieties about global warming and Middle East oil right out of your mind. Consider it a 5,700-pound Xanax.</p>
        <p>In fact -- and I urge Land Rover to consider this a compliment -- the Rover Sport is so good that there's little reason to come aboard the flagship Range Rover.</p>
        <p>This continues a trend in which upscale car makers draft unheralded rookies that make their big-name veterans seem overpriced. In attitude and performance, the Sport is to the original Range Rover as the new Porsche Cayman is to the classic 911: fresher, edgier and lighter on its feet.</p>
        <p>Like the Cayman, the Sport is a relative bargain: The 300-horsepower HSE model starts at $57,250, the 390-horsepower supercharged version is $70,250 -- roughly $20,000 less than its Range Rover stablemates.</p>
        <p>So you get an S.U.V. that looks hotter than the boxy Range Rover, that handles better and that uses interior space more efficiently -- and with spare change left over for a Honda Civic. Some of the Sport's neatest features aren't even available on the Range Rover, including a computer-controlled active suspension and a user-friendly selectable ''terrain response'' system that adjusts the truck to handle any imaginable surface.</p>
        <p>Riding on a platform modified from the Land Rover LR3, the Sport is eight inches shorter and an inch slimmer than the Range Rover, with a chopped roof, lower stance and tauter suspension.</p>
        <p>The Sport does have a more intimate cockpit, with tighter footwells and a narrower back seat. But in luxury and appointments it's not far off the Range Rover standard. One clever feature is an optional electric console cooler that keeps drinks fresh and chocolate bars intact on hot days.</p>
        <p>Now, about that name: the ''sport'' in sport utility once referred largely to off-road hijinks. But with city slickers piloting most of today's models, the word increasingly promises a good time on pavement.</p>
        <p>Attuned to changing tastes in S.U.V.'s, Land Rover has dialed up the Sport's on-road performance. The stout chassis and double-wishbone suspension were sharpened on Germany's tortuous Nürburgring test circuit. Yet with more than half a century of four-wheeling heritage, Land Rover couldn't skimp on the back-country skills.</p>
        <p>That makes the Rover Sport something of a tweener. With ''only'' 300 horsepower from the Jaguar-based 4.4-liter V-8 in the base (HSE) model, acceleration lags some hot-blooded rivals. The 4.2-liter V-8 in the Supercharged, even with its atmospheric assist, runs from 0 to 60 m.p.h. in 7.1 seconds -- quick, but not rock-your-world fast.</p>
        <p>Still, despite the auto press's obsession with acceleration times, I'll argue that most people don't buy sporty S.U.V.'s to drag-race Corvettes. They want a blend of power and prestige, ride and handling, luxury and utility, and the Rover Sport's balance of those factors may be unmatched in its class.</p>
        <p>Handling is remarkably agile for such a weighty beast. Much like the latest Range Rover, the Sport has an uncanny feel for the straight-ahead, and its reflexes and road-holding are even sharper. Few S.U.V.'s convey its sense of unshakable command.</p>
        <p>The new Dynamic Response System monitors g-forces to keep the body settled in corners, and also improves off-road performance. Supercharged models get powerful four-piston Brembo brakes in the front.</p>
        <p>The Sport does have one embarassing talent: It chug-a-lugs like a Hummer H2 or Porsche Cayenne. I got 12 m.p.g. over all; the official E.P.A. estimate is 13 m.p.g. in the city and 18 on the highway.</p>
        <p>As mentioned, the Sport will off-road beautifully, in the way that Angelina Jolie could use her muscles to scrub hospital floors -- that is, the concept is plausible but the reality would be disturbing.</p>
        <p>On an off-road stretch in the Shawangunk mountains of New York, the Sport yawned over obstacles, though I winced as the pricey undercarriage scraped across prehistoric rocks. The air suspension adjusts to three ride heights and gives an emergency full-up boost if the body gets hung up off-road.</p>
        <p>The Terrain Response System's knob twiddles up settings for all sorts of surfaces: dry highways, snow, muddy ruts, ''rock crawl'' and bubbling lava -- all right, nothing molten, though my test model did flaunt a hot shade called Vesuvius Orange.</p>
        <p>Hill descent control lets novices negotiate steep slopes without touching either the gas or brake pedals.</p>
        <p>Back in civilization, the Sport distinguishes itself with knockout design. If most S.U.V.'s are shaped like bricks, the Sport is at least hand-hewn marble, blunt yet elegant. Traditional Rover cues like the clamshell hood and coachlike proportions merge with the raked roofline and honeycomb grille. It's a truck and proud of it, an antidote to blurry crossovers that can't decide what they're supposed to be. (The Cayenne looks like a station wagon wearing a Porsche 911 mask).</p>
        <p>At these prices, image and heritage count. Descended from truck royalty, the Rover exudes natural authority, with no need for the jewelry favored by sport-ute parvenus.</p>
        <p>Still, you must overlook potential trouble spots in those British genes, including Land Rover's perennially poor reliability scores. A pair of maddeningly skinny metal bars serve as horn buttons; by the time you locate them, any danger is long past. The audio controls are fussy and the tiny display is hard to read.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the adaptive cruise control, which beams radar to maintain a gap behind the traffic in front of you, isn't worth adapting to. Unlike rival systems that smoothly regulate speed, the Rover's felt as if a teenage hooligan had seized control, surging alarmingly toward cars in front only to suddenly jerk back.</p>
        <p>Those missteps aside, the Rover Sport's style, performance and desirability will dazzle a certain type of buyer, who may identify himself through a simple psychological quiz:</p>
        <p>Can you return the glares of Prius drivers with haughty disdain?</p>
        <p>Can you cackle maniacally as the gas pump spins to $70 and more?</p>
        <p>Have you dreamed of velvet ropes falling and burly doormen cowering before your 20-inch alloy rims?</p>
        <p>If you answered yes to at least two out of three, you'll love the Range Rover Sport.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
