<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boston Mob, Party of 4: Authors Publish in Packs</title>
    <meta content="11clus" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/11/books/11clus.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1753688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Motoko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED91E30F932A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boston Mob, Party of 4: Authors Publish in Packs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boston Mob, Party of 4: Authors Publish in Packs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOTOKO RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Motoko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>It is common for multiple books on same subject to be published at same time, but sometimes it is calculation rather than coincidence that drives synchronicity as publishers want to cash in on hot topics in news and culture; this can also have negative consequences when publishers and authors must scramble to distinguish their books from pack, often altering release dates and marketing plans; some authors and publishers comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Birds travel in flocks, fish in schools. Sometimes books arrive in cohorts, too, testing the attention spans of booksellers, reviewers and, most of all, readers. In a publishing twist of fate, there are four books on the Boston mob battling for primacy on best-seller lists this spring, while three books on climate change are clamoring for notice, too. Then there are the two books on Barry Bonds, the two on yellow fever and a pair of historical novels about La Malinche, Cortés's Aztec lover and guide.</p>
        <p>That's not even counting the numerous knockoffs of ''The Da Vinci Code'' climbing the fiction best-seller list, or the profusion of volumes on the Iraq war jostling for shelf space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a publishing twist of fate, there are four books on the Boston mob battling for primacy this spring, along with three books on climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Birds travel in flocks, fish in schools. Sometimes books arrive in cohorts, too, testing the attention spans of booksellers, reviewers and, most of all, readers. In a publishing twist of fate, there are four books on the Boston mob battling for primacy on best-seller lists this spring, while three books on climate change are clamoring for notice, too. Then there are the two books on Barry Bonds, the two on yellow fever and a pair of historical novels about La Malinche, Cortés's Aztec lover and guide.</p>
        <p>That's not even counting the numerous knockoffs of ''The Da Vinci Code'' climbing the fiction best-seller list, or the profusion of volumes on the Iraq war jostling for shelf space.</p>
        <p>In those cases, it's perhaps more calculation than coincidence that drives the synchronicity. News catalysts ranging from notorious murder cases to natural disasters, as well as fashions in fiction, will often drive the simultaneous rush to publish. But from time to time, random concurrences point to something more ephemeral in the culture. ''It's almost as if ideas are floating overhead, and you reach up and pull them down,'' said Frances Sherwood, whose ''Night of Sorrows'' is one of the two novels about La Malinche.</p>
        <p>For publishers and authors, these pileups can lead to a scramble to distinguish their books from the pack, with moved release dates and changed marketing plans. Authors battle to snag talk-show spots. Book reviews often pair books, and booksellers clump them onto a themed table. For readers, this can create confusion, or worse, fatigue.</p>
        <p>''You never want to get in a sweepstakes with somebody else, because very often books do cannibalize each other,'' said William Shinker, president and publisher of Gotham Books, the division of Penguin Group USA that published ''Game of Shadows,'' the first of two books about the baseball giant Barry Bonds out this spring. ''I've always said that publishing is about timing, timing, timing. The race is to the swift.'' (This Sunday, ''Game of Shadows'' will rise to No. 2 on the New York Times hardcover nonfiction best-seller list.)</p>
        <p>Perhaps it's not surprising that the authors of the Boston mob books, three of whom are convicted gangsters, are in a verbal slugfest.</p>
        <p>Kevin Weeks, the author of ''Brutal: The Untold Story of My Life Inside Whitey Bulger's Irish Mob,'' chuckled when asked about ''Rat Bastards: The Life and Times of South Boston's Most Honorable Irish Mobster,'' a memoir by John (Red) Shea. ''He was a mid-level drug dealer,'' said Mr. Weeks, who spent five years in prison for racketeering and murder. ''He's exaggerating his role.''</p>
        <p>In turn, Mr. Shea, who ran a drug operation for Mr. Bulger and spent 12 years in prison on narcotics charges, lambastes Mr. Weeks for testifying against other gang members in exchange for a reduced sentence. ''I don't think any rat deserves any publicity,'' Mr. Shea said.</p>
        <p>Adding to the coincidence, both books come from imprints of HarperCollins: ''Brutal'' is published by Regan Books and ''Rat Bastards'' by William Morrow.</p>
        <p>Doug Grad, the senior editor at Regan Books who edited Mr. Weeks's memoir, said he had moved up the publication date, mainly to coincide with ''The Brothers Bulger: How They Terrorized and Corrupted Boston for a Quarter Century'' by Howie Carr, the popular Boston Herald columnist and radio show host whose book, published by Warner Books, profiles both Mr. Bulger and his brother Billy, the former president of the University of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>So far, it is Mr. Carr's book that is leading in sales, rising as high as No. 6 on the New York Times hardcover nonfiction list earlier this month. Mr. Weeks went as high as No. 15, and Mr. Shea made the extended list -- which appears online -- just once. Patrick Nee, the author of ''A Criminal &amp; an Irishman: The Inside Story of the Boston Mob-I.R.A. Connection,'' the fourth book in the bunch, has yet to crack the list.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr has the advantage of being able to promote his book, based on nearly 25 years of reporting on the Bulgers, in his column and syndicated radio show. But Mr. Weeks, who writes in his book that Mr. Carr ''was an oxygen thief who didn't deserve the right to breathe,'' may have inadvertently given the reporter even more publicity.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Weeks appeared on ''60 Minutes'' last month, he recounted an episode from his book in which he planned to shoot Mr. Carr, but did not pull the trigger because the journalist came out of his house holding his young daughter's hand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr, whose book was delayed from last fall to bring it down to manageable size, said Mr. Weeks ''didn't have the stones'' to kill him. But perhaps because he is still the comfortable leader, Mr. Carr is not above helping the competition: Mr. Shea appeared on his radio show, and Mr. Nee was invited. But not Mr. Weeks: ''I'm drawing the line about Weeks, even though I think it was a fantasy about killing me,'' Mr. Carr said. ''I don't think I have to pay back that favor.''</p>
        <p>The authors of the current crop of books on climate change are more collegial, but they are still divided about whether the confluence of titles on the same subject helps or hinders sales.</p>
        <p>Eugene Linden, author of ''The Winds of Change: Climate, Weather, and the Destruction of Civilizations,'' said that he could not help wishing that his book were not part of a crowd. ''A little voice inside me says, 'God, it would be better if it was two or one,' '' he said. But he acknowledged that had he published on time -- he was originally scheduled to deliver a manuscript by 2001 -- it ''would have sunk without a trace,'' despite having a more exclusive hold on the topic.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Kolbert's book ''Field Notes From a Catastrophe: Man, Nature and Climate Change'' was released by Bloomsbury Publishing last month. She is philosophical about the multiple titles. ''When you're claiming that something is the biggest problem facing the world, you cannot be surprised that other people are writing about the same topic,'' she said. ''You'd be insane.''</p>
        <p>In some ways the debate reflects an age-old question pondered by economists when discussing retail behavior. ''If you're a restaurant, are you better off putting yourself across town to get away from competition, or would you be better off being on the same street with all the other restaurants?'' asked Austan Goolsbee, professor of economics at the University of Chicago Graduate School of Business.</p>
        <p>The answer, Mr. Goolsbee said, comes down to a complicated set of tradeoffs between losing sales by being too close to the competition and gaining customers because more people overall are attracted to a concentrated group.</p>
        <p>A similar dynamic seems to be playing out in the publishing world. ''I don't think somebody is going to trot home four books on global warming,'' said David Rosenthal, executive vice president and publisher of Simon &amp; Schuster, which published ''The Winds of Change.'' ''Then again, if there weren't that many books, they may not get the shelf position in the stores that they are getting.''</p>
        <p>According to Bob Wietrak, vice president of merchandising at Barnes &amp; Noble, sales of Mr. Linden's book are trailing ''The Weather Makers: How Man Is Changing the Climate and What It Means for Life on Earth,'' by the Australian writer Tim Flannery, and ''Field Notes.'' This Sunday, ''The Weather Makers,'' published by Grove/Atlantic, will be on the New York Times extended nonfiction hardcoverlist at No. 33.</p>
        <p>The phenomenon that leads to the simultaneous appearance of several books on similar subjects has a parallel in science. ''People in a research field tend to share a sense of what the important problems are,'' said Susan E. Cozzens, professor of public policy at Georgia Institute of Technology in Atlanta. ''There's a chance that a lot of them will come to the same answer at the same time.''</p>
        <p>But in book publishing, the source of convergence is not always clear. When two books came out about Abraham Lincoln last fall, David Hirshey, senior vice president and executive editor of HarperCollins (which is publishing the second book on Barry Bonds this season), said he wondered, ''Why now?''</p>
        <p>William Morrow, a HarperCollins imprint, brought out its own book, ''Manhunt: The 12-Day Chase for Lincoln's Killer,'' earlier this year. ''It's obviously due to the new steroid allegations about Lincoln having come out,'' Mr. Hirshey said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
