<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE LISTINGS | JULY 14-JULY 20</title>
    <meta content="14theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060718T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1775757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDC1E30F937A25754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="14754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE LISTINGS | JULY 14-JULY 20</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' Previews start Monday. Opens July 27. A romantically ambitious poet balances relationships with three women in this new play by Rajiv Joseph. Presented by Second Stage Theater (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway; (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Previews start Thursday. Opens July 25. Based on the lives of the five cast members, this play, which incorporates dance and song, is about growing up in apartheid-era South Africa (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'BULLY' In previews. Opens on Tuesday. William Walsh plays Theodore Roosevelt in this solo show (2:00). Irish Arts Center, 553 West 51st Street, Manhattan; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' In previews. Opens on Tuesday. ''School of the Americas'' playwright José Rivera revives this Los Angles romance about a man who picks up a hitchhiker who says she has been pregnant for two years (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL Through July 30. This always buzzed-about summer showcase includes ''DruidSynge,'' the complete works of John Millington Synge; and ''Grendel,'' an opera directed by Julie Taymor. Sites in and around Lincoln Center; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' In previews; opens on Sunday. The chameleonic Nilaja Sun returns with her acclaimed solo show about the New York public school system (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village; (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Starts previews tonight; opens Thursday. When it originally opened in February, Charles Isherwood wrote: ''Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens'' (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to the music of Earth, Wind and Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, back in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich, who replaces Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' José Rivera, who wrote the screenplay to ''The Motorcycle Diaries,'' penned this rickety piece of historical speculation about the final two days of Che Guevara's life (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' Orran Farmer's two-character drama about a struggling playwright and a drug-addicted actress-stripper is well-meaning but tedious and often trite (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'TROUBLE IN PARADISE' Ernst Lubitsch's 1932 film comedy about a con man, the con woman he loves and a wealthy Parisian widow lives again as a giddy, good-looking, quietly amusing play (1:30). Hudson Guild Theater, 441 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching, beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). The Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>BURLEIGH GRIME$' A feeble-witted comedy by Roger Kirby about dirty dealings on Wall Street, featuring a pair of skilled actors known for recent television work -- Wendie Malick of ''Just Shoot Me'' and Mark Moses of ''Desperate Housewives'' -- and incidental music by David Yazbek, who wrote the score for Broadway's ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels.'' These putative assets are painfully ill served by Mr. Kirby's play, which is long on ludicrous plot and short on fresh humor (2:10). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NOT A GENUINE BLACK MAN' Brian Copeland's solo memoir about his African-American family moving into a white suburb in the early 1970's is an engaging, if stiltedly performed, show (1:30). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'SHINING CITY' Quiet, haunting and absolutely glorious. Conor McPherson's impeccably assembled ghost story about being alone in the crowded city of Dublin has been brought to American shores with a first-rate cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Oliver Platt, Martha Plimpton and Peter Scanavino), directed by Robert Falls (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF &amp; GRENDEL' (R, 102 minutes) The director Sturla Gunnarsson boils this classic epic down into a generic action flick, complete with sweeping vistas, clanging fights, a chiseled hero and a witchy woman who keeps her front door unlocked for both the good guy and the bad. Every so often a severed head lazily rolls across the frame, though, alas, not often enough. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE BLOOD OF MY BROTHER' (No rating, 84 minutes, in English and Arabic) Another documentary about the occupation of Iraq; another heartbreak; another protest; another dead brother; another necessity. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright, and Antony are among the featured performers. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'DOWN IN THE VALLEY' (R, 114 minutes) This allegorical neo-western set in the San Fernando Valley has dreams as big as the fantasies that consume its protagonist, a Stetson-wearing suburban cowboy (Edward Norton) who is not what he appears to be. How much you like it will depend on your appetite for the kind of cultural metaphors that David Jacobson flings onto the screen with a reckless abandon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GREAT NEW WONDERFUL' (R, 88 minutes) The post-9/11 self-absorption of a handful of New Yorkers. Occasionally well observed, but mostly irritating and contrived. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-age white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LOVERBOY' (R, 86 minutes) This cautionary mother-child drama, directed by Kevin Bacon, is a star vehicle for his wife, Kyra Sedgwick, who plays a pathologically possessive single mother. After starting out warm and fuzzy, this tonally uncertain film stealthily pulls out the rug until you suddenly find yourself standing on a cold stone floor, barefoot and shivering. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MISSION: IMPOSSIBLE III' (PG-13, 126 minutes) Er, this time it's personal, as Tom Cruise plays a dashing operative for a clandestine organization who sweeps a simpering brunette off her feet. Directed, without much flair, by J. J. Abrams, the small-screen auteur behind ''Lost'' and ''Alias.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE OMEN' (R, 110 minutes) The supremely unnecessary remake of ''The Omen,'' the 1976 horror show that, along with ''Rosemary's Baby'' and ''The Exorcist,'' plunked everyone's favorite baddie, Satan, into the Hollywood mainstream, wants to capitalize on the tabloid theology in the air. Except for a few contemporary touches (the World Trade Center in flames as a portent of Armageddon) it slavishly recycles the original. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'ONLY HUMAN' (No rating, 85 minutes, in Spanish) When a Jewish girl takes her Palestinian fiancé home to meet the parents, the encounter sets off a series of zany, romantic and potentially tragic misadventures during one eventful night in Madrid. (Laura Kern)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'RUSSIAN DOLLS' (No rating, 129 minutes, in English, Russian, French and Spanish) The sequel to the international hit ''L'Auberge Espagnole'' belongs to a long line of airy French films that induce a pleasant buzz of Euro-envy. Like its forerunner, it is a generational group portrait of young, smart, sexy, well-educated Europeans at work and play filmed in a style that might be called Truffaut Lite. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WASSUP ROCKERS' (R, 105 minutes) The latest provocation from the director and photographer Larry Clark follows a group of teenage Hispanic skateboarders from South Central Los Angeles on a 24-hour adventure that takes them from one hell (the inner city) to another (decadent Beverly Hills) and back. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. ( Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ANIMATION AROUND THE WORLD (Through July 31) BAMcinématek's festival of animated films begins Monday with a program of shorts by the Dutch director Paul Driessen, who worked on ''Yellow Submarine.'' Tuesday's program is ''Best of Ottawa 2005,'' a selection of shorts from the animation festival in that city, including Mary Newland's very short (50 seconds) comedy ''Signal Film.'' BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, between St. Felix Street and Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>ESSENTIAL WILDER (Through Thursday) Film Forum's three-week retrospective of the work of the Polish-born director and screenwriter Billy Wilder (1906-2002) continues today and tomorrow with ''Ace in the Hole'' (1951), starring Kirk Douglas as an unscrupulous newspaper reporter. Sunday's feature is ''The Apartment'' (1960), Wilder's Oscar-winning comedy about a corporate love nest. The retrospective's closing-night film is ''The Fortune Cookie'' (1966), one of Jack Lemmon and Walter Matthau's lesser-known collaborations. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-9110; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962), the first director to win an Oscar (for ''Seventh Heaven''), begins tomorrow at the Museum of the Moving Image. This weekend's films include ''Man's Castle'' (1933), a naughty romantic comedy with Spencer Tracy and Loretta Young, and ''History Is Made at Night'' (1937), a romantic drama set on a Titanic-like ship, starring Jean Arthur and Charles Boyer. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through July 30) BAMcinématek is honoring movie bad guys, including Bela Lugosi in ''Dracula'' (1931) and Fredric March in ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde'' (1931). The weekend's other features are Hitchcock classics: ''Psycho'' (1960), starring Anthony Perkins as the disturbed motel owner Norman Bates, and ''Rebecca'' (1940), which stars Laurence Olivier (but the film's real villain is the dead title character). BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HEROIC GRACE: THE CHINESE MARTIAL ARTS FILM, PART II (Through Thursday) The U.C.L.A. Film &amp; Television Archive and the Film Society of Lincoln Center's sequel to a 2003 festival focuses on movies from the 1970's and early 80's. This weekend's films include Lau Kar-leung's kung-fu comedy ''My Young Auntie'' (1980) and Zhang Che's ''Five Venoms'' (1978), about a dying master seeking revenge on his former disciples. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Aug. 3) This fifth annual outdoor festival continues Wednesday night with Cheik Doukouré's ''Golden Ball'' (1992), a film from Guinea about a very young football fan. Thursday night's feature is ''Buckle Brothers'' (2005), Marquette Williams's documentary about cowboys in South-Central Los Angeles. St. Nicholas Park, 135th Street and St. Nicholas Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DAVE ALVIN (Tonight) In the Blasters, in X and now on his own, Mr. Alvin has written and sung about outcasts, lovers and criminals, some of the people who share the road with an itinerant musician. He sets his narratives in country and rockabilly tunes that strive for classic American simplicity, though his words detail an uncertain moral landscape. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* AMADOU AND MARIAM (Sunday) Known throughout West Africa as the Blind Couple From Mali, Amadou Bagayoko and Mariam Doumbia have reached American listeners with a smooth eclecticism that on their album ''Dimanche à Bamako,'' last year, folded in reggae and some loose-limbed rock. With Daby Touré and Birdy Nam Nam. At 3 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN IDOLS LIVE' (Tonight through Sunday) The 10 finalists from Season 5 of ''American Idol'' logged about a million yeah-yeah's and baby-baby's on television, and here they come on tour with who knows how many more: Taylor Hicks (the winner), Katharine McPhee (the runner-up), Ace Young, Bucky Covington, Chris Daughtry, Elliott Yamin, Kellie Pickler, Lisa Tucker, Mandisa and Paris Bennett. Tonight at 7, Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900; tomorrow and Sunday nights at 7, Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (631) 888-9000; $36.50 to $70.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BON JOVI (Tuesday and Wednesday) Bon Jovi, the band that titled its 1998 album ''New Jersey,'' is back in its home state. Jon Bon Jovi's band conquered the airwaves in the 1980's and 90's by sticking together everything catchy about 70's rock: Bruce Springsteen's earnestness, Led Zeppelin's crunch, Boston's harmonies, and lyrics that paint romance as nothing less than a titanic adventure. A photogenic lead singer doesn't hurt, either. With Nickelback. At 5 p.m., Giants Stadium, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900; $37.50 to $125. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BRAVE COMBO (Wednesday) Brave Combo, on a lifelong mission to prove the malleability of polka, plays an all-request show at Midsummer Night Swing, Lincoln Center's outdoor series of low-dipping, high-kicking music and dancing. At 7:30 p.m., with a dance lesson at 6:30 p.m., Josie Robertson Plaza, Columbus Avenue at 63rd Street, (212) 875-5460; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAVO SILVA, RAISING THE FAWN (Wednesday) Drawing on the spiky and melodic sound of the early Police and U2, the New York band Bravo Silva sings deadpan odes to the city of strangers, though not so deadpan as to exclude playing soaring, ecstatic choruses and having some fun with kitschy keyboards. This month the band has a Wednesday-night residency at Pianos. Also on the bill this week is Raising the Fawn, a group connected to the great Toronto indie-prog collective Broken Social Scene. At 6:30 p.m., 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KELLY CLARKSON (Tomorrow) The first ''American Idol'' champion, who won two Grammys and had the third-best-selling album of 2005, Ms. Clarkson is the best proof yet that reality television might not be a bad idea. With Rooney. At 8 p.m., New England Dodge Music Center, Hartford, (860) 548-7370; $25 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DIPLO, CSS, BONDE DO ROLE (Wednesday and Thursday) Diplo, born Wesley Pentz -- his stage name is taken from diplodocus, a dinosaur -- is the influential and eclectic D.J. who has worked with the Sri Lankan-British rapper M.I.A., and is also half of Hollertronix, a virtuoso mixtape team from Philadelphia. He has been borrowing from Brazilian baile funk for years, and the first release on his new record label, Mad Descent, is by the Brazilian group Bonde do Role. Diplo is touring with that band and another Brazilian group, CSS, whose come-ons are shouted in robotic, broken English (''Kiss-kiss-kiss will make this earth quake'') over bare but exuberant art-funk. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780; Thursday at 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOHN HIATT, NORTH MISSISSIPPI ALLSTARS (Tuesday) Mr. Hiatt has rhymed amoeba with Queen of Sheba; his songs get to the heart of human frailty, loyalty and love, even if they take a sidelong route. He performs with a deep-diving baritone, a twang-happy band and enough strange facial expressions to rival Jim Carrey. The North Mississippi Allstars play an asymmetrical, cantankerous blues from the hill country near where the members grew up, then turn it into jam-band music. At 8 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>I LOVE YOU BUT I'VE CHOSEN DARKNESS (Wednesday) All is cold, echoey gloom in the music of this five-piece band from Austin, Tex., which borrows its spacious sound from Joy Division and its faint vocals from the shoe-gazer British bands of the late 1980's like My Bloody Valentine. With the Big Sleep and Asobi Seksu, a Brooklyn group whose new album, ''Citrus'' (Friendly Fire), shows a fine command of the shoe-gazer sound. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $14 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MADONNA (Tuesday and Wednesday) Part 10 (or so), in which our heroine strikes such poses as Jesus on the cross, James Brown in his cape and John Travolta in his white disco suit, all while performing dance-floor hits in new remixes and reconfigurations. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $354.50 tickets remaining. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MISSION OF BURMA (Tonight) In the early 1980's this innovative and widely influential Boston band brought sharp, brainy guitar minimalism to American postpunk, and since reuniting in 2002 after almost 20 years, it still plays with passion and smarts. With Major Stars. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOBB DEEP, RAEKWON (Wednesday) Mobb Deep, a rap duo from Queens long admired by connoisseurs for its grim and vivid rhymes, was recently taken under 50 Cent's wing, with one result that you might expect: its new album, ''Blood Money'' (G Unit/Interscope), had its debut in the Top 10. Also on the bill is Raekwon of the Wu-Tang Clan, and a long lineup of opening acts including the Boot Camp Clik. At 9 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL WASTE (Tonight) Seemingly everything about the mid-1980's thrash metal of groups like D.R.I. and Anthrax is lovingly and skillfully recreated by this band from Richmond, Va., from the high-octane riffs and stomping mosh-pit rhythms all the way to the cartoonish, apocalyptic album-cover art. With Annihilation Time, Splitting Headache, Clockcleaner and Dustheads. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $9. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NORTEC COLLECTIVE (Tomorrow) A loose confederation of musicians and visual artists, the Nortec Collective is devoted to the cutting, rearranging and pasting of norteño, the vibrant border style of oompah brass and accordion known on this side of the border as Tex-Mex. With Grupo Soñador. At 7:30 p.m., Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OZOMATLI (Tonight) Ozomatli makes what might be called political party music. It's a Los Angeles band that is determined to annex every pan-American party groove from funk to samba to Mexican cumbia in its consciousness-raising songs. With Outernational. At 7 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>RBD (Tomorrow) This teen-pop sextet began on a spinoff of a Mexican soap opera and is now aiming for the American market with an English-language album. Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $49.50 to $115. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOSH ROUSE (Thursday) Mr. Rouse wraps folk-rock melodies around wistful thoughts about regrets, near-misses and forlorn hopes. At 7 p.m., Castle Clinton National Monument, Battery Park, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free tickets available at 5 p.m., two per person. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* SIREN MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) One of the most tastefully programmed indie-rock festivals in the country, The Village Voice's annual afternoon of noise and sea mist takes place on two stages beside the Coney Island boardwalk, surrounded by hot-dog vendors and the screams of roller-coaster riders. The lineup this year includes the neo-disco Scissor Sisters; the exuberantly sarcastic Art Brut; the Stills, a Canadian band with a moody, shimmering take on the sound of New York bands like Interpol and the Strokes; Stars, a witty and eloquent indie-cabaret band from Toronto; She Wants Revenge and Dirty on Purpose, two more groups with gloom fetishes; Tapes 'n Tapes, from Minneapolis, whose dry rhapsodies recall Pavement and the early Pixies; the bluesy and rough-hewn Deadboy and the Elephantmen; and Man Man, the Rogers Sisters, Priestess, Celebration, Serena Maneesh and the Cribs. From noon to 9 p.m., Surf Avenue, Coney Island, Brooklyn, (212) 475-4022; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUNDS OF THE UNDERGROUND TOUR (Tomorrow) An afternoon of fast, pummeling heavy metal characterized by lots of death-and-gore-obsessed lyrics, with As I Lay Dying, Cannibal Corpse, In Flames, Trivium, Terror, Black Dahlia Murder and Through the Eyes of the Dead. And since the vaudevillian horror-metal band Gwar is on the bill, there will also be a fair complement of monsters with ripped limbs spurting fake, multicolored blood. At noon, Starland Ballroom, 570 Jernee Mill Road, Sayreville, N.J., (732) 238-5500; $32 in advance, $36 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MATTHEW SWEET AND SUSANNA HOFFS (Monday) Mr. Sweet, the power-pop songwriter with a sensitive side (''Girlfriend''), and Ms. Hoffs, the lead singer of the Bangles, indulge their love of jangly 1960's pop, playing songs from ''Under the Covers, Vol. 1'' (Shout Factory), their recent joint album of loving versions of songs by the Beatles, Love, the Zombies, the Mamas and the Papas, and others. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>A.C.T.I.O.N. 4 (Wednesday) It may sound like a coalition of superheroes, or a TV news team, but this quartet is actually a progressive jazz ensemble built around the compositions of the bassist Sean Conly. The group's other members are Michaël Attias and Tony Malaby, saxophonists, and Take Toriyama, drummer. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>BRUCE BARTH TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow) As a pianist, Mr. Barth prefers subtlety and fluency to any kind of flash. His trio, with the bassist Doug Weiss and the drummer Montez Coleman, performs original compositions alongside less-than-obvious covers, including material by the Grateful Dead. At 8, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, Manhattan, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOU DONALDSON QUARTET (Through Sunday) Bebop, blues and boogaloo are all fair game for Mr. Donaldson, a veteran alto saxophonist who receives strong support here from Kyle Koehler on Hammond B-3 organ, Randy Johnston on guitar and Fukushi Tainaka on drums. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAYNARD FERGUSON &amp; HIS BIG BOP NOUVEAU BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) His signature high notes have inevitably lost some luster, but Mr. Ferguson is still a bravura trumpeter and charismatic front man, and this 11-piece ensemble, under the musical direction of the drummer Stockton Helbing, suits both sets of skills. (Through July 23.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>4INOBJECTS (Sunday) An experimental but tuneful collective composed of Yoon Sun Choi on vocals, Jacob Sacks on keyboards, Jacob Garchik on trombone, Dave Ambrosio on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. At 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK GAYTON QUINTET (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Gayton, a sharp trombonist, has worked in a colorful array of horn sections, including his current gig with Bruce Springsteen's Seeger Sessions Band. As a leader, he brings a jazz flexibility to dub and reggae, gospel and soul. At 9 p.m., 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., Zinc Bar, 90 West Houston Street at LaGuardia Place, Greenwich Village, (212) 477-8337; cover, $5, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GOOD FOR COWS (Tonight and tomorrow) The bassist Devin Hoff and the drummer Ches Smith comprise this Bay Area duo, which interrogates jazz and punk with equal rigor. On the second night, they're joined by the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the violist Jessica Pavone, two musicians with a duo rapport of their own. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAZZ IN JULY (Tuesday through Thursday) A year ago, the pianist Bill Charlap presided over his first season as artistic director of this venerable traditional jazz series, successfully clearing the bar set by his predecessor, Dick Hyman. The new season begins next week, with guest-laden tributes to Duke Ellington (Tuesday), Mr. Hyman (Wednesday) and Thelonious Monk (Thursday). Wynton Marsalis, making an appearance on the Monk evening, provides the most potent dose of jazz celebrity; but among this festival's regular patronage, Mr. Hyman himself looms just as large. Tickets will go quickly, if they haven't already. At 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, Manhattan, (212) 415-5500 or www.92y.org, $50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LATIN IN MANHATTAN FESTIVAL (Through Thursday) Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola's second annual Latin jazz festival started this week with Claudia Acuña, a vocalist guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile, who plays through Sunday with a strong quintet. Tuesday marks the start of a six-night engagement with Grady Tate and Latin Flavor, a heavily rhythmic sextet led by Mr. Tate on vocals. (Through July 30.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Friday and Saturday, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHUCK MANGIONE (Through Sunday) Mr. Mangione's fluegelhorn has been a staple of instrumental pop for more than 30 years, and his trademark hit, ''Feels So Good,'' helped pave the way for smooth jazz. He leads a polished group that includes the saxophonist and flutist Gerard Niewood and the guitarist Coleman Mellett. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KATE McGARRY (Tomorrow) Ms. McGarry is a quiet but potent singer who recasts jazz and folk material alike with a quavering sincerity. She performs here with the guitarist Keith Ganz, the keyboardist Gary Versace and the drummer Dan Rieser. At 6 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER GROUP (Sunday) ''Oceana'' (Sunnyside), the most recent album by the guitarist Ben Monder, is a small-scale but ambitious suite of original music that doesn't sound quite like anything else. Mr. Monder presents much of the same material here, with the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Ted Poor. At 8 and 10 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, www.bar4.net; suggested donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARK MURPHY (Tomorrow) Mr. Murphy is a singer known mainly for sly insouciance, but on his recent album ''Once to Every Heart'' (Verve), he opted for a burnished and broken romanticism. He performs here in the most intimate of settings, accompanied only by the guitarist Jack Wilkins. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID (FATHEAD) NEWMAN QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Newman, a surefooted tenor saxophonist best known for his long and fruitful tenure with Ray Charles, leads an ensemble consisting of Javon Jackson on tenor and soprano saxophones, David Leonhardt on piano, John Menagon on bass and Yoron Israel on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with midnight sets tonight and tomorrow. Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SANGHA QUARTET (Monday) This ensemble, led by the keyboardist Kevin Hays, creates an electronic jazz hybrid with a sensibility that hovers somewhere between pop and experimental fusion. In addition to Mr. Hays, the group consists of the saxophonist Seamus Blake, the bassist Doug Weiss and the drummer Bill Stewart. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE GROUP (Wednesday) Mr. Sickafoose is a bassist-composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, as he demonstrated on an evocative recent album, ''Blood Orange'' (Secret Hatch). He performs here with the trumpeter Russ Johnson and the trombonist Alan Ferber; the guitarists Adam Levy and Mike Gamble; and the percussionists Mike Dillon and Ches Smith. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DR. LONNIE SMITH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Under Dr. Smith's command, the Hammond B-3 organ can be subtly atmospheric or growlingly ecstatic; together with the guitarist Peter Bernstein and the drummer Alison Miller, he delivers a searching brand of soul jazz. Continues through July 23. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HENRY THREADGILL'S ZOOID (Thursday) The august composer and multireedist Henry Threadgill has always nursed a fascination with timbre; in this superb ensemble, his flute and alto saxophone are flanked by cello, oud, acoustic guitar, tuba, and drums. Continues through July 23. At 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN WALTZER TRIO (Thursday) Mr. Waltzer, a pianist, manages a thoughtful modernism that coexists more than peaceably with a buoyant, un-self-conscious sense of swing. His trio, with Matt Penman and Gerald Cleaver on bass and drums, is first-rate. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119; no cover, $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID WEISS AND THE POINT OF DEPARTURE QUINTET (Thursday) An assertive trumpeter and accomplished arranger, Mr. Weiss leads an ensemble well stocked with young talent: J. D. Allen on tenor saxophone, Nir Felder on guitar, Luques Curtis on bass and Kendrick Scott on drums. At 10 p.m., Fat Cat, 75 Christopher Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 675-6056; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL WEISS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow) Mr. Weiss is an exceedingly proficient pianist, well versed in a multitude of jazz styles. Leading a quartet, he spotlights another versatile player, the alto and soprano saxophonist Steve Wilson. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK WESS QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Wess, a venerable tenor saxophonist and flutist, marks the release of a likable new album, ''Hank &amp; Frank,'' with this one-night engagement. His ensemble here does not include Hank Jones, the Hank in the album title; but it does feature the bassist John Webber, the drummer Leroy Williams and a guitarist, Ilya Lushtak, who released the album on Lineage, his own new label. At 10 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOE WILDER QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The trumpeter Joe Wilder, still playing well in his mid-80's, has had a wealth of professional experience both in and out of jazz. But he has hardly ever led his own group in a New York club residency: only once, in fact, at the Village Vanguard this year. He returns to the club next week with the same supporting cast of Michael Weiss on piano, John Webber on bass and Lewis Nash on drums. Continues through July 23. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tomorrow and Sunday) This company's productions almost invariably end up at the New York City Opera, and lots of people drive up to Cooperstown, N.Y., to get an early glimpse of what's on the way. But Glimmerglass, with its intimate, comfortable and up-to-date house, is a vastly superior place to see and hear these productions than the cavernous New York State Theater. The company opened its season with a light work, the Gilbert and Sullivan operetta ''The Pirates of Penzance'' in a production by Lillian Groag. This week's schedule also includes Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia,'' in a production by Leon Major. ''Pirates'': tomorrow night at 8; ''Barbiere'': Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255; $64 to $112. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'GRENDEL' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The wall works! The Lincoln Center Festival is breathing easy. As everyone seems to know by now, the Los Angeles Opera's premiere of ''Grendel,'' the operatic adaptation of John Gardner's 1971 novel, a retelling of the epic poem ''Beowulf,'' composed by Elliot Goldenthal and directed by Julie Taymor, had to be postponed when the 16-ton rotating wall that dominated the set would not rotate. Now installed at the New York State Theater, the wall is operating smoothly and the elaborate production, complete with Ms. Taymor's trademark puppets, tree-man creatures and flying dancers, seems glitch-free. Alas, Mr. Goldenthal's derivative music is like an ominous and obvious film score and the opera is weighted down with philosophical mumbo-jumbo. At 7:30 p.m., (212) 721-6500; $40 to $200. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>New Jersey Opera Theater (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Founded in 2002, the New Jersey Opera Theater is striving to become the pre-eminent opera company for the state. Besides presenting performances, the company offers master classes and educational outreach programs. The productions include Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore,'' directed by David Grabarkewitz and conducted by Brent McMunn, and an intriguing double bill of Puccini's comedy ''Gianni Schicchi'' and ''Buoso's Ghost,'' a one-act work from 1996 by Michael Ching, which picks up the story of the clever Schicchi where Puccini's opera leaves off. Steven Condy sings Schicchi in both works; James Caraher conducts. ''L'Elisir d'Amore'': tonight at 8, Sunday at 2 p.m. and Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; ''Schicchi'' and ''Buoso'': tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Berlind Theater at the McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787; $42 to $49. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) This venerable early-music festival focuses on Mozart and Schubert this weekend, with Sharon Baker as the soprano soloist in groups of songs by each composer, and the violinist Daniel Stepner and the fortepianist Kristian Bezuidenhout offering sonatas and fantasies. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156. $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) This floating concert hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River offers the intimacy that chamber music needs, as well as a wonderful view of Lower Manhattan through the bay windows behind the stage. Tonight Steven Beck, the pianist, plays works by Stravinsky, Brahms, Haydn and Schubert. The Sequenza Trio, with the violinist Mark Kaplan, the cellist Adrian Brendel and the pianist Yael Weiss, takes over tomorrow and Sunday to play works by Martinu, Schubert (the great E-flat Trio, Op. 100) and Paul Chihara's ''Ain't No Sunshine.'' On Thursday, the Gala String Quartet and Olga Vinokur, the pianist, join forces for Mozart's chamber version of his Piano Concerto No. 12 (K. 414) and the Schumann Piano Quintet (Op. 44). Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35 tonight, tomorrow and Sunday; $40 on Thursday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'BEOWuLF' (Tuesday and Wednesday) The Lincoln Center Festival offers Benjamin Bagby's smaller, faster take on ''Beowulf'' as a complement to the opera ''Grendel'' playing nearby. At 8:30 p.m., Drama Theater at La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500; $45, with limited availability. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tonight through Sunday, Thursday) The chamber ensemble Opus One frames its program of piano quartets tonight in favorites, with Mozart's Quartet in E flat (K. 493) to begin and Dvorak's Quartet in E flat (Op. 87) to close. Between them it offers a more recent adventure, George Tsontakis's Piano Quartet No. 3. Tomorrow night Michael Barrett conducts the Orchestra of St. Luke's in the premiere of a Piano Concerto by John Musto, Caramoor's stylistically omnivorous composer in residence. Also on the program are Beethoven's ''Leonore'' Overture No. 3 and Schumann's ''Spring'' Symphony. On Sunday afternoon, Will Crutchfield leads an all-Mozart program that includes ''Exsultate, Jubilate'' and arias and ensembles from ''Le Nozze di Figaro,'' ''Don Giovanni'' and other works. The soloists are Sumi Jo, soprano; Maria Zifchak, mezzo-soprano; Steven Tharp, tenor; and Daniel Mobbs, bass-baritone. On Thursday, the brilliant American pianist Christopher Taylor will perform Messiaen's complete ''Vingt Regards sur l'Enfant-Jésus,'' a two-hour workout that includes some of the most difficult and complex yet sublime and ecstatic music ever written for piano. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday at 4:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252; $27 and $37 tonight, $17.50 to $67.50 tomorrow, $19 to $49 on Sunday, $17 and $27 on Thursday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL KEYBOARD INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL (Sunday through Thursday) This expansive festival of master classes and concerts runs through the rest of July, and tends to draw the biggest crowds of all the Mannes College of Music's summer series. Jerome Rose, the institute's director, plays the first faculty concert on Sunday, with works by Mozart, Schumann, Chopin (the four Ballades) and Paul Schoenfield. On Monday Fabio Bidini plays Schumann's ''Carnaval'' and Beethoven's ''Waldstein'' and ''Appassionata'' Sonatas. On Tuesday Steven Mayer offers a virtuoso program that moves from Weber and Schumann through Ives, Gottschalk and James P. Johnson into jazz pieces by Jelly Roll Morton and Art Tatum. On Wednesday Nikolai Demidenko plays Schubert, Liszt and Bach. On Thursday Jeffrey Swann offers a lecture-recital, ''In Search of Lost Time: Music in the World of Marcel Proust,'' that includes works by Franck, Fauré, Saint-Saëns, Debussy, Reynaldo Hahn and Wagner. At 8 p.m., Mannes College, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4858; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC'S CONCERTS IN THE PARKS (Tonight, tomorrow, Monday and Tuesday) The Philharmonic has left the air-conditioned confines of Avery Fisher Hall for its annual series of free concerts in the parks. Notably, the conductors and soloists for both programs this summer are dynamic women. The orchestra's impressive associate conductor, Xian Zhang, offers two Tchaikovsky works, the ''Coronation March'' and the Violin Concerto (with the charismatic violinist Jennifer Koh as soloist), and Dvorak's exuberant Symphony No. 8. The series ends on Tuesday with the adventurous Marin Alsop conducting John Adams's ''Chairman Dances,'' Prokofiev's Violin Concerto No. 1, with the virtuosic Leila Josefowicz as soloist, and Beethoven's always-popular Fifth Symphony. Expect these concerts, as usual, to draws tens of thousands of people for picnics in the parks and music under the stars (if nature cooperates). There will be fireworks after each performance. Tonight at 8, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Staten Island; tomorrow at 8 p.m., Heckscher State Park, East Islip, N.Y.; Monday at 8 p.m., Van Cortlandt Park, Broadway and West 246th Street, the Bronx; Tuesday at 8 p.m., Great Lawn, Central Park; (212) 875-5709. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight) A host of chamber musicians play an all-Russian evening. At 8, Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000; $15 to $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>SVET STOYANOV (Monday) The River to River Festival this week includes a performance by Mr. Stoyanov, a Bulgarian percussionist. At 7:30 p.m., Schimmel Center for the Arts, 3 Spruce Street, near Park Row, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free tickets available after 4 p.m. (Holland)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) James Levine's return to action with the Boston Symphony Orchestra includes Schoenberg's gigantic oratorio ''Gurrelieder'' tonight, and Strauss's equally large opera ''Elektra,'' performed in concert tomorrow. Andrew Davis conducts a mixed program on Sunday afternoon. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200; $18 to $87 tonight, with $8.50 lawn tickets; $18 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, with $17 lawn tickets. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow) The company's spring season ends with three performances of Kenneth MacMillan's highly theatrical ''Romeo and Juliet,'' to Prokofiev's haunting score. Julie Kent (celebrating her 20th anniversary with Ballet Theater) and Marcelo Gomes take the lead roles tonight, Paloma Herrera and David Hallberg tomorrow afternoon, and Alessandra Ferri and José Manuel Carreño tomorrow night. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 or abt.org; $23 to $100. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>CAPACITOR (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) From San Francisco, Capacitor creates pieces based on science. In ''Digging in the Dark'' the focus is on modern geophysics and acrobatic, virtuosic movement. Through July 30. Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101 or capacitor.org; $35. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE (Tonight) The Stephen Petronio Company, known for its stylish, cheeky, high-energy dance, will perform a program featuring two pieces set to music by Rufus Wainwright that will be sung live in part by the Young People's Chorus of New York City. At 8 p.m. Rumsey Playfield, Central Park, enter at Fifth Avenue and 69th Street or Central Park West and 72nd Street, (212) 360-1399 or summerstage.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHASHAMA OASIS FESTIVAL 2006 (Today and Monday through Thursday) Artists of all disciplines -- some, we suspect, wildly undisciplined, in the grand tradition of Chashama productions -- will perform in a Midtown window. Today, and Monday through next Friday from noon to 1:30 p.m. and 5:30 to 7 p.m., 217 East 42nd Street, between Second and Third Avenues, chashama.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Chunky Move (Tonight and tomorrow) Australian men apparently have dancing difficulties too; perhaps not these particular men, though. Using video montages and interviews, the members of the physical Australian troupe Chunky Move channel their inner wallflowers in ''I Want to Dance Better at Parties.'' Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $36. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>COMPANY C CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Opens Thursday). A 12-member ballet troupe from San Francisco with an eclectic repertory presents works by Twyla Tharp, Patrick Corbin, Alexander Proia and its director, Charles Anderson. Through July 23. At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, SoHo, (212) 334-7479; $25, $20 students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>PAULA HUNTER (Today through Thursday) Ms. Hunter will perform ''I Am Karen Finley,'' an absurdist performance solo, as a free dance installation in a window in the Theater District. Through July 22. Today through Thursday at 5 and 7:30 p.m., Chashama, 112 West 44th Street, (212) 391-8151 or chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL 2006 (Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) The Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company examines issues relating to patriotism in ''Blind Date.'' At 8 p.m., LaGuardia Concert Hall, Amsterdam Avenue and 65th Street, (212) 721-6500 or lincolncenter.org; $50. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tomorrow, Sunday and Wednesday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, has settled into the intimate Theater 80 until the end of the month. Tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 5 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, maybe, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Monday is a special opening event combining parts of the two programs that will alternate for the rest of the run. Through Aug. 12. Monday through Thursday nights at 8, Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org. $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'RIVER DEEP, A TRIBUTE TO TINA TURNER'  (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Gabrielle Lansner pays tribute to this singer, who is played by Pat Hall, in a multimedia production set to music by Philip Hamilton. Through July 29. Tonight, and Tuesday through Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, between Ninth and Tenth Avenues, (212) 279-4200 or gabriellelansner.com; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SUMMER IN THE SQUARE (Wednesday). A series of Wednesday events featuring music, storytelling, yoga and dance, this week includes modern dance by the Battery Dance Company. Through Aug. 16. At 6 p.m., Union Square Park, Broadway and 14th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 460-1208 or unionsquarenyc.org; free. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* TAP CITY 2006 (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) The festivities continue with performances of ''Tap Internationals'' tonight; ''Tap Forward,'' a program of contemporary choreography, tomorrow, Tuesday and Thursday nights; and ''Tap and Song,'' whose performers include Mable Lee and the festival director, Tony Waag, on Sunday and Wednesday nights. Tonight at 7 and 9:30; tomorrow and Sunday at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; Wednesday at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; and Tuesday and Thursday at 7 and 9:30 p.m. The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, (212) 239-6200 and atdf.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THOMAS/ORTIZ DANCE (Wednesday through Thursday) Ted Thomas and Frances Ortiz combine urban athleticism and Latin sensuality in choreographic explorations of socially relevant themes. Through July 22. At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077; $15, $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>DUSAN TYNEK DANCE THEATER  (Tonight through Sunday) Dusan Tynek, from Czechoslovakia, trained with Aileen Passloff at Bard College. He will present two premieres, one inspired by sinister 19th-century Czech ballads and set to string music by classical and contemporary composers, and the other set to music by Michael Galasso. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for students, artists and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>VON USSAR DANCEWORKS (Tonight through Sunday) Astrid von Ussar, a Slovenian modern-dance choreographer now based in New York City, will present four new and recent pieces, including her new ''23 hours,'' set to music by Graeme Ravell. The program features a dance by Mojca Ussar, her sister. Tonight through Sunday at 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $20; $15, students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Bruce Museum: 'Best in Show: Dogs in Art From the Renaissance to the Present,' through Aug. 27. This show is a dog lover's picnic, with paintings that celebrate canis lupus familiaris and its wayward ways. 1 Museum Drive, Greenwich, Conn.; (203) 869-0376. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedekers, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Sept. 3. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including the young Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM: 'EVA HESSE: SCULPTURE,' through Sept. 17. Assembled by Elizabeth Sussman, curator at the Whitney Museum of American Art, and Fred Wasserman, a curator at the Jewish Museum, this show focuses on a pivotal Hesse exhibition, ''Chain Polymers,'' at the Fischbach Gallery -- known for promoting Minimalist painters -- in 1968. Arguably a compilation of her best work, it was her first and only solo show of sculpture during her lifetime, and most of the objects in it -- along with some earlier and later pieces -- are here. One of the earliest is ''Compart'' (1966), a four-panel vertical that starts at the top with a fully formed, round, breastlike image of neatly wound cord that mysteriously breaks up into part of the same image on each of the three panels beneath. The last, most startling and most impressive work is ''Untitled (Rope Piece),'' of 1970, made as Ms. Hesse was dying, finished with the help of friends. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Metropolitan museum of art: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. Further sharpness comes from the placement of all parts of the altarpiece at eye level, creating a viewing intensity that more than compensates for the fact that they have not been reassembled. (212) 535-7710. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Morgan Library and Museum: 'Masterworks from the Morgan,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's splendid four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels, medieval objects made with so much silver and gold that they seem to give off heat. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels, devotional sculptures and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Individual show closings can be checked by telephone or through the Web site.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3. Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and useable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/ Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art : 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. If ''Full House'' is about one thing, it is about discord, about how harmonious America never was. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West Second Street, (212) 243-0200, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Small Wonders' Bucking the big-picture trend, this absorbing show presents 45 black-and-white photographs ranging from palm to postage-stamp size. They include classic portraits by Edward Weston and Berenice Abbott; André Kertesz's William-Blake-like image of a naked man walking into a field of tall grass; and Walter Auerbach's picture of Willem de Kooning's studio circa 1950. Robert Mann, 210 11th Avenue, (212) 989-7600, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>'About Light' Some works in this show, like Sean Scully's blocky grid painting and Philip Guston's smudgy gray abstraction, absorb more than emit light. Others, including Thomas Pihl's smooth, pink monochromes; Alex Katz's small nocturnal pictures of lighted apartment-building windows; and Richard Pousette-Dart's pulsating, pointillist field, seem to glow from within. Galerie Lelong, 528 West 26th Street, (212) 315-0470, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Air' This appealing, understated show organized by the painter Amy Sillman includes Benjamin Butler's lush, Mondrian-style painting of trees; Pat Palermo's semi-abstract drawings of wrecked cars and other curious subjects; John White Cerasulo's watercolor of a bare-chested wilderness giant; Pamela Wilson-Ryckman's flickering picture of a scattering crowd of people; and abstractions in various styles by Robert Bordo, Jenny Monick, Howard Smith, Laura Newman and Patricia Treib. Monya Rowe, 526 West 26th Street, (646) 234-8645, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 East 22nd Street, (212) 229-2766, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Everywhichway' This lively show of artists working inventively between abstraction and representation includes Katherine Bradford's whimsical images of ships and the sea; Chris Martin's updated Tantric art; Sigrid Sandström's Arctic icescapes; suave, retro-Modernist pattern paintings by Jennifer Riley and Colin Thomson; Harvey Tulcensky's finely textured ballpoint-pen fields; and compact, sensuous ceramic slabs by Joyce Robins. Edward Thorp, 210 11th Avenue, at 24th Street, (212) 691-6565, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'I'm not here. This isn't happening' With possibly the best title of the summer season, this group show includes Michelle Lopez's canny, neo-Surrealistic sculptures; Ronnie Bass's incantatory sound-and-video installation in a simulated old ship's cabin; Terry Haggerty's mesmerizing pattern paintings; Katarina Burin's noirish combinations of watercolor and found photography; Damien Cadio's enigmatic, painterly narratives; and Jim Gaylord's explosive, loosely Cubist paintings of natural and artificial fragments. Grimm/Rosenfeld, 530 West 25th Street, (212) 352-2388, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE NAME OF THIS SHOW IS NOT GAY ART NOW Characterized by its organizer, the artist Jack Pierson, as an ode to the passing of ''the notion of Gay Art,'' this exhibition embraces the work of about 60 artists (gay, straight and otherwise) to create a cacophonous celebration and suggest that everyone is a little bit gay, if they are lucky. Paul Kasmin Gallery, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474, through tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'The Sanctuary and the Scrum' A diverting, pluralistic show inaugurates a new Northwest Chelsea exhibition space. It includes good abstract and semi-abstract paintings by Jessica Dickinson and Andrew Guenther; a stuffed swan shorn of its feathers from the head down by Jane Benson; a gleaming crutch covered by tiny mirror facets by Kristian Kozul; and a funny photo-conceptual project about grocery store shopping carts by Julian Montague. Black &amp; White, 636 West 28th Street, (212) 244-3007, through July 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Martin Schoeller: 'Close Up' Extraordinarily large and detailed mug-shot-like portraits of celebrities like Jack Nicholson, Angelina Jolie and Bill Clinton. Hasted Hunt, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 627-0006, through Sept. 1. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Vivan Sundaram: 'Re-Take of Amrita' The photographs in this beautiful, time-haunted show are all of past generations of the Indian artist Vivan Sundaram's family, and include images of his aunt, the famed modernist painter Amrita Sher-Gil (1913-1941). Thanks to digital technology, those generations mix in logically impossible combinations. The resulting pictures embody the past the way it survives in the mind: edited, layered, compressed, as if in a dream. Sepia International, 148 West 24th Street, 11th floor, (212) 645-9444, through July 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'How I Finally Accepted Fate' The memoir is the loosely defined theme of this interesting 10-person show. It includes Matt Keegan's video of cheerleaders celebrating his grandmother's 90th birthday; Angela Dufresne's vivid painting of a shirtless man called ''Me as a Communist Male in 'The Red and the White' ''; Carolee Schneemann's patchwork tale about modern love in photographs and typewritten words; and Maureen Duncan's three-and-a-half-hour monologue about her CD collection. EFA Gallery, 323 West 39th Street, (212) 563-5855, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Christine Osinski: 'Notes From West Brighton' Ms. Osinski took the visually and sociologically gripping photographs in this exhibition on Staten Island, where she lives, in the early 1980's and the early 90's. These exceptionally lucid black-and-white pictures of nondescript neighborhoods, grocery store customers, small-town parades, self-consciously posing teenagers and abandoned wrecked cars were made with an affectionately cool, clear eye for the beauty and weirdness of ordinary people and places. Silo, 1 Freeman Alley, East Village, (212) 505-9156, through July 30. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>Philippe Decrauzat: 'Plate 28' A conceptually perplexing but visually striking installation by this young Swiss artist includes a black-and-white grid painted on the walls, a sculpture based on a Russian Constructivist design, and a grainy, flickering black-and-white film showing glimpses of ominous landscapes from ''The Twilight Zone.'' Swiss Institute, 495 Broadway, at Broome Street, (212) 925-2035, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love,'' depicting the goddess of love and the god of war in an intimate moment brokered by Cupid, as Mars's sexy horse looks on. The other works are a little more staid, but the painting in them is equally gorgeous. (See above.) 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, closes Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>EVA HESSE: 'DRAWING'  This show deals in depth with Ms. Hesse's works on paper, ranging from rough sketches or notes, to test pieces made from various materials that function as drawings, to finished projects that stand on their own. A zealous researcher, Ms. Hesse made all kinds of thumbnail notations and calculations to explore the properties of her malleable materials. Many of these sheets, perhaps too many, are shown, too. Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, (212) 219-2166; closes tomorrow. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Cosima von Bonin: 'Relax, It's Only a Ghost' Various two- and three-dimensional objects -- including stuffed animals like the ones you might find in a high-end toy store -- and Rorschach test patterns stitched to colorful bedspreads add up to a familiar critique of consumerism. Friedrich Petzel, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 680-9467; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Invisible Might: Works from 1965-1971' This luminous group show about the euphoric convergence of Minimalism and new technologies in the late 1960's and early 70's includes a smoky glass cube by Larry Bell; a solid black plastic cube by John McCracken; a tall, clear acrylic prism by Robert Irwin; a beautiful aqua-green light projection by James Turrell; a yellow molded plastic relief by Craig Kauffman; and a corner composition of elastic cords and bent metal rods by Fred Sandback. Nyehaus, 15 Gramercy Park South, (212) 995-1785; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'ALL THIS INTIMACY' Previews start Monday. Opens July 27. A romantically ambitious poet balances relationships with three women in this new play by Rajiv Joseph. Presented by Second Stage Theater (1:45). McGinn/Cazale Theater, 2162 Broadway; (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'AMAJUBA: LIKE DOVES WE RISE' Previews start Thursday. Opens July 25. Based on the lives of the five cast members, this play, which incorporates dance and song, is about growing up in apartheid-era South Africa (1:30). Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'BULLY' In previews. Opens on Tuesday. William Walsh plays Theodore Roosevelt in this solo show (2:00). Irish Arts Center, 553 West 51st Street, Manhattan; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' In previews. Opens on Tuesday. ''School of the Americas'' playwright José Rivera revives this Los Angles romance about a man who picks up a hitchhiker who says she has been pregnant for two years (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street; (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL Through July 30. This always buzzed-about summer showcase includes ''DruidSynge,'' the complete works of John Millington Synge; and ''Grendel,'' an opera directed by Julie Taymor. Sites in and around Lincoln Center; (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD' In previews; opens on Sunday. The chameleonic Nilaja Sun returns with her acclaimed solo show about the New York public school system (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village; (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Starts previews tonight; opens Thursday. When it originally opened in February, Charles Isherwood wrote: ''Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens'' (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' A dancing encyclopedia of clichés set to the music of Earth, Wind and Fire. Numbing (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, back in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich, who replaces Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SCHOOL OF THE AMERICAS' José Rivera, who wrote the screenplay to ''The Motorcycle Diaries,'' penned this rickety piece of historical speculation about the final two days of Che Guevara's life (2:00). Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SHAKESPEARE IS DEAD' Orran Farmer's two-character drama about a struggling playwright and a drug-addicted actress-stripper is well-meaning but tedious and often trite (1:00). Paradise Factory, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'TROUBLE IN PARADISE' Ernst Lubitsch's 1932 film comedy about a con man, the con woman he loves and a wealthy Parisian widow lives again as a giddy, good-looking, quietly amusing play (1:30). Hudson Guild Theater, 441 West 26th Street, Chelsea, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching, beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). The Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, between Second and Third Avenues, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>BURLEIGH GRIME$' A feeble-witted comedy by Roger Kirby about dirty dealings on Wall Street, featuring a pair of skilled actors known for recent television work -- Wendie Malick of ''Just Shoot Me'' and Mark Moses of ''Desperate Housewives'' -- and incidental music by David Yazbek, who wrote the score for Broadway's ''Dirty Rotten Scoundrels.'' These putative assets are painfully ill served by Mr. Kirby's play, which is long on ludicrous plot and short on fresh humor (2:10). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NOT A GENUINE BLACK MAN' Brian Copeland's solo memoir about his African-American family moving into a white suburb in the early 1970's is an engaging, if stiltedly performed, show (1:30). DR2 Theater, 103 East 15th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>*'SHINING CITY' Quiet, haunting and absolutely glorious. Conor McPherson's impeccably assembled ghost story about being alone in the crowded city of Dublin has been brought to American shores with a first-rate cast (Brian F. O'Byrne, Oliver Platt, Martha Plimpton and Peter Scanavino), directed by Robert Falls (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEOWULF &amp; GRENDEL' (R, 102 minutes) The director Sturla Gunnarsson boils this classic epic down into a generic action flick, complete with sweeping vistas, clanging fights, a chiseled hero and a witchy woman who keeps her front door unlocked for both the good guy and the bad. Every so often a severed head lazily rolls across the frame, though, alas, not often enough. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE BLOOD OF MY BROTHER' (No rating, 84 minutes, in English and Arabic) Another documentary about the occupation of Iraq; another heartbreak; another protest; another dead brother; another necessity. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright, and Antony are among the featured performers. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'DOWN IN THE VALLEY' (R, 114 minutes) This allegorical neo-western set in the San Fernando Valley has dreams as big as the fantasies that consume its protagonist, a Stetson-wearing suburban cowboy (Edward Norton) who is not what he appears to be. How much you like it will depend on your appetite for the kind of cultural metaphors that David Jacobson flings onto the screen with a reckless abandon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GREAT NEW WONDERFUL' (R, 88 minutes) The post-9/11 self-absorption of a handful of New Yorkers. Occasionally well observed, but mostly irritating and contrived. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-age white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LOVERBOY' (R, 86 minutes) This cautionary mother-child drama, directed by Kevin Bacon, is a star vehicle for his wife, Kyra Sedgwick, who plays a pathologically possessive single mother. After starting out warm and fuzzy, this tonally uncertain film stealthily pulls out the rug until you suddenly find yourself standing on a cold stone floor, barefoot and shivering. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MISSION: IMPOSSIBLE III' (PG-13, 126 minutes) Er, this time it's personal, as Tom Cruise plays a dashing operative for a clandestine organization who sweeps a simpering brunette off her feet. Directed, without much flair, by J. J. Abrams, the small-screen auteur behind ''Lost'' and ''Alias.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LA MOUSTACHE' (No rating, 86 minutes, in French) Emmanuel Carrière's psychological mystery prepares you to bask in one of those sexy, bittersweet marital comedies that are a hallmark of sophisticated French cinema. Then, by degrees, it subverts those expectations to spiral down a rabbit hole of ambiguity and doubt. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE OMEN' (R, 110 minutes) The supremely unnecessary remake of ''The Omen,'' the 1976 horror show that, along with ''Rosemary's Baby'' and ''The Exorcist,'' plunked everyone's favorite baddie, Satan, into the Hollywood mainstream, wants to capitalize on the tabloid theology in the air. Except for a few contemporary touches (the World Trade Center in flames as a portent of Armageddon) it slavishly recycles the original. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'ONLY HUMAN' (No rating, 85 minutes, in Spanish) When a Jewish girl takes her Palestinian fiancé home to meet the parents, the encounter sets off a series of zany, romantic and potentially tragic misadventures during one eventful night in Madrid. (Laura Kern)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'RUSSIAN DOLLS' (No rating, 129 minutes, in English, Russian, French and Spanish) The sequel to the international hit ''L'Auberge Espagnole'' belongs to a long line of airy French films that induce a pleasant buzz of Euro-envy. Like its forerunner, it is a generational group portrait of young, smart, sexy, well-educated Europeans at work and play filmed in a style that might be called Truffaut Lite. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'WASSUP ROCKERS' (R, 105 minutes) The latest provocation from the director and photographer Larry Clark follows a group of teenage Hispanic skateboarders from South Central Los Angeles on a 24-hour adventure that takes them from one hell (the inner city) to another (decadent Beverly Hills) and back. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. ( Dargis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ANIMATION AROUND THE WORLD (Through July 31) BAMcinématek's festival of animated films begins Monday with a program of shorts by the Dutch director Paul Driessen, who worked on ''Yellow Submarine.'' Tuesday's program is ''Best of Ottawa 2005,'' a selection of shorts from the animation festival in that city, including Mary Newland's very short (50 seconds) comedy ''Signal Film.'' BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, between St. Felix Street and Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>ESSENTIAL WILDER (Through Thursday) Film Forum's three-week retrospective of the work of the Polish-born director and screenwriter Billy Wilder (1906-2002) continues today and tomorrow with ''Ace in the Hole'' (1951), starring Kirk Douglas as an unscrupulous newspaper reporter. Sunday's feature is ''The Apartment'' (1960), Wilder's Oscar-winning comedy about a corporate love nest. The retrospective's closing-night film is ''The Fortune Cookie'' (1966), one of Jack Lemmon and Walter Matthau's lesser-known collaborations. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-9110; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962), the first director to win an Oscar (for ''Seventh Heaven''), begins tomorrow at the Museum of the Moving Image. This weekend's films include ''Man's Castle'' (1933), a naughty romantic comedy with Spencer Tracy and Loretta Young, and ''History Is Made at Night'' (1937), a romantic drama set on a Titanic-like ship, starring Jean Arthur and Charles Boyer. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through July 30) BAMcinématek is honoring movie bad guys, including Bela Lugosi in ''Dracula'' (1931) and Fredric March in ''Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde'' (1931). The weekend's other features are Hitchcock classics: ''Psycho'' (1960), starring Anthony Perkins as the disturbed motel owner Norman Bates, and ''Rebecca'' (1940), which stars Laurence Olivier (but the film's real villain is the dead title character). BAM Rose Cinemas, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HEROIC GRACE: THE CHINESE MARTIAL ARTS FILM, PART II (Through Thursday) The U.C.L.A. Film &amp; Television Archive and the Film Society of Lincoln Center's sequel to a 2003 festival focuses on movies from the 1970's and early 80's. This weekend's films include Lau Kar-leung's kung-fu comedy ''My Young Auntie'' (1980) and Zhang Che's ''Five Venoms'' (1978), about a dying master seeking revenge on his former disciples. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Aug. 3) This fifth annual outdoor festival continues Wednesday night with Cheik Doukouré's ''Golden Ball'' (1992), a film from Guinea about a very young football fan. Thursday night's feature is ''Buckle Brothers'' (2005), Marquette Williams's documentary about cowboys in South-Central Los Angeles. St. Nicholas Park, 135th Street and St. Nicholas Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DAVE ALVIN (Tonight) In the Blasters, in X and now on his own, Mr. Alvin has written and sung about outcasts, lovers and criminals, some of the people who share the road with an itinerant musician. He sets his narratives in country and rockabilly tunes that strive for classic American simplicity, though his words detail an uncertain moral landscape. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* AMADOU AND MARIAM (Sunday) Known throughout West Africa as the Blind Couple From Mali, Amadou Bagayoko and Mariam Doumbia have reached American listeners with a smooth eclecticism that on their album ''Dimanche à Bamako,'' last year, folded in reggae and some loose-limbed rock. With Daby Touré and Birdy Nam Nam. At 3 p.m., Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777; free, but a donation is suggested. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>'AMERICAN IDOLS LIVE' (Tonight through Sunday) The 10 finalists from Season 5 of ''American Idol'' logged about a million yeah-yeah's and baby-baby's on television, and here they come on tour with who knows how many more: Taylor Hicks (the winner), Katharine McPhee (the runner-up), Ace Young, Bucky Covington, Chris Daughtry, Elliott Yamin, Kellie Pickler, Lisa Tucker, Mandisa and Paris Bennett. Tonight at 7, Continental Airlines Arena, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900; tomorrow and Sunday nights at 7, Nassau Coliseum, 1255 Hempstead Turnpike, Uniondale, N.Y., (631) 888-9000; $36.50 to $70.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BON JOVI (Tuesday and Wednesday) Bon Jovi, the band that titled its 1998 album ''New Jersey,'' is back in its home state. Jon Bon Jovi's band conquered the airwaves in the 1980's and 90's by sticking together everything catchy about 70's rock: Bruce Springsteen's earnestness, Led Zeppelin's crunch, Boston's harmonies, and lyrics that paint romance as nothing less than a titanic adventure. A photogenic lead singer doesn't hurt, either. With Nickelback. At 5 p.m., Giants Stadium, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900; $37.50 to $125. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>BRAVE COMBO (Wednesday) Brave Combo, on a lifelong mission to prove the malleability of polka, plays an all-request show at Midsummer Night Swing, Lincoln Center's outdoor series of low-dipping, high-kicking music and dancing. At 7:30 p.m., with a dance lesson at 6:30 p.m., Josie Robertson Plaza, Columbus Avenue at 63rd Street, (212) 875-5460; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAVO SILVA, RAISING THE FAWN (Wednesday) Drawing on the spiky and melodic sound of the early Police and U2, the New York band Bravo Silva sings deadpan odes to the city of strangers, though not so deadpan as to exclude playing soaring, ecstatic choruses and having some fun with kitschy keyboards. This month the band has a Wednesday-night residency at Pianos. Also on the bill this week is Raising the Fawn, a group connected to the great Toronto indie-prog collective Broken Social Scene. At 6:30 p.m., 158 Ludlow Street, near Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 505-3733; $8. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>KELLY CLARKSON (Tomorrow) The first ''American Idol'' champion, who won two Grammys and had the third-best-selling album of 2005, Ms. Clarkson is the best proof yet that reality television might not be a bad idea. With Rooney. At 8 p.m., New England Dodge Music Center, Hartford, (860) 548-7370; $25 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DIPLO, CSS, BONDE DO ROLE (Wednesday and Thursday) Diplo, born Wesley Pentz -- his stage name is taken from diplodocus, a dinosaur -- is the influential and eclectic D.J. who has worked with the Sri Lankan-British rapper M.I.A., and is also half of Hollertronix, a virtuoso mixtape team from Philadelphia. He has been borrowing from Brazilian baile funk for years, and the first release on his new record label, Mad Descent, is by the Brazilian group Bonde do Role. Diplo is touring with that band and another Brazilian group, CSS, whose come-ons are shouted in robotic, broken English (''Kiss-kiss-kiss will make this earth quake'') over bare but exuberant art-funk. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780; Thursday at 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOHN HIATT, NORTH MISSISSIPPI ALLSTARS (Tuesday) Mr. Hiatt has rhymed amoeba with Queen of Sheba; his songs get to the heart of human frailty, loyalty and love, even if they take a sidelong route. He performs with a deep-diving baritone, a twang-happy band and enough strange facial expressions to rival Jim Carrey. The North Mississippi Allstars play an asymmetrical, cantankerous blues from the hill country near where the members grew up, then turn it into jam-band music. At 8 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $30. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>I LOVE YOU BUT I'VE CHOSEN DARKNESS (Wednesday) All is cold, echoey gloom in the music of this five-piece band from Austin, Tex., which borrows its spacious sound from Joy Division and its faint vocals from the shoe-gazer British bands of the late 1980's like My Bloody Valentine. With the Big Sleep and Asobi Seksu, a Brooklyn group whose new album, ''Citrus'' (Friendly Fire), shows a fine command of the shoe-gazer sound. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $14 in advance, $16 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* MADONNA (Tuesday and Wednesday) Part 10 (or so), in which our heroine strikes such poses as Jesus on the cross, James Brown in his cape and John Travolta in his white disco suit, all while performing dance-floor hits in new remixes and reconfigurations. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $354.50 tickets remaining. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MISSION OF BURMA (Tonight) In the early 1980's this innovative and widely influential Boston band brought sharp, brainy guitar minimalism to American postpunk, and since reuniting in 2002 after almost 20 years, it still plays with passion and smarts. With Major Stars. At 8 p.m., Warsaw, 261 Driggs Avenue, at Eckford Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (718) 387-0505; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MOBB DEEP, RAEKWON (Wednesday) Mobb Deep, a rap duo from Queens long admired by connoisseurs for its grim and vivid rhymes, was recently taken under 50 Cent's wing, with one result that you might expect: its new album, ''Blood Money'' (G Unit/Interscope), had its debut in the Top 10. Also on the bill is Raekwon of the Wu-Tang Clan, and a long lineup of opening acts including the Boot Camp Clik. At 9 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171; $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL WASTE (Tonight) Seemingly everything about the mid-1980's thrash metal of groups like D.R.I. and Anthrax is lovingly and skillfully recreated by this band from Richmond, Va., from the high-octane riffs and stomping mosh-pit rhythms all the way to the cartoonish, apocalyptic album-cover art. With Annihilation Time, Splitting Headache, Clockcleaner and Dustheads. At 9, Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $9. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NORTEC COLLECTIVE (Tomorrow) A loose confederation of musicians and visual artists, the Nortec Collective is devoted to the cutting, rearranging and pasting of norteño, the vibrant border style of oompah brass and accordion known on this side of the border as Tex-Mex. With Grupo Soñador. At 7:30 p.m., Celebrate Brooklyn, Prospect Park Bandshell, Prospect Park West and Ninth Street, Park Slope, (718) 855-7882; $3 suggested donation. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OZOMATLI (Tonight) Ozomatli makes what might be called political party music. It's a Los Angeles band that is determined to annex every pan-American party groove from funk to samba to Mexican cumbia in its consciousness-raising songs. With Outernational. At 7 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>RBD (Tomorrow) This teen-pop sextet began on a spinoff of a Mexican soap opera and is now aiming for the American market with an English-language album. Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $49.50 to $115. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOSH ROUSE (Thursday) Mr. Rouse wraps folk-rock melodies around wistful thoughts about regrets, near-misses and forlorn hopes. At 7 p.m., Castle Clinton National Monument, Battery Park, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free tickets available at 5 p.m., two per person. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* SIREN MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) One of the most tastefully programmed indie-rock festivals in the country, The Village Voice's annual afternoon of noise and sea mist takes place on two stages beside the Coney Island boardwalk, surrounded by hot-dog vendors and the screams of roller-coaster riders. The lineup this year includes the neo-disco Scissor Sisters; the exuberantly sarcastic Art Brut; the Stills, a Canadian band with a moody, shimmering take on the sound of New York bands like Interpol and the Strokes; Stars, a witty and eloquent indie-cabaret band from Toronto; She Wants Revenge and Dirty on Purpose, two more groups with gloom fetishes; Tapes 'n Tapes, from Minneapolis, whose dry rhapsodies recall Pavement and the early Pixies; the bluesy and rough-hewn Deadboy and the Elephantmen; and Man Man, the Rogers Sisters, Priestess, Celebration, Serena Maneesh and the Cribs. From noon to 9 p.m., Surf Avenue, Coney Island, Brooklyn, (212) 475-4022; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUNDS OF THE UNDERGROUND TOUR (Tomorrow) An afternoon of fast, pummeling heavy metal characterized by lots of death-and-gore-obsessed lyrics, with As I Lay Dying, Cannibal Corpse, In Flames, Trivium, Terror, Black Dahlia Murder and Through the Eyes of the Dead. And since the vaudevillian horror-metal band Gwar is on the bill, there will also be a fair complement of monsters with ripped limbs spurting fake, multicolored blood. At noon, Starland Ballroom, 570 Jernee Mill Road, Sayreville, N.J., (732) 238-5500; $32 in advance, $36 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MATTHEW SWEET AND SUSANNA HOFFS (Monday) Mr. Sweet, the power-pop songwriter with a sensitive side (''Girlfriend''), and Ms. Hoffs, the lead singer of the Bangles, indulge their love of jangly 1960's pop, playing songs from ''Under the Covers, Vol. 1'' (Shout Factory), their recent joint album of loving versions of songs by the Beatles, Love, the Zombies, the Mamas and the Papas, and others. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $25. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>A.C.T.I.O.N. 4 (Wednesday) It may sound like a coalition of superheroes, or a TV news team, but this quartet is actually a progressive jazz ensemble built around the compositions of the bassist Sean Conly. The group's other members are Michaël Attias and Tony Malaby, saxophonists, and Take Toriyama, drummer. At 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>BRUCE BARTH TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow) As a pianist, Mr. Barth prefers subtlety and fluency to any kind of flash. His trio, with the bassist Doug Weiss and the drummer Montez Coleman, performs original compositions alongside less-than-obvious covers, including material by the Grateful Dead. At 8, 10 and 11:30 p.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, Manhattan, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOU DONALDSON QUARTET (Through Sunday) Bebop, blues and boogaloo are all fair game for Mr. Donaldson, a veteran alto saxophonist who receives strong support here from Kyle Koehler on Hammond B-3 organ, Randy Johnston on guitar and Fukushi Tainaka on drums. At 7:30, 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $30. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MAYNARD FERGUSON &amp; HIS BIG BOP NOUVEAU BAND (Tuesday through Thursday) His signature high notes have inevitably lost some luster, but Mr. Ferguson is still a bravura trumpeter and charismatic front man, and this 11-piece ensemble, under the musical direction of the drummer Stockton Helbing, suits both sets of skills. (Through July 23.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>4INOBJECTS (Sunday) An experimental but tuneful collective composed of Yoon Sun Choi on vocals, Jacob Sacks on keyboards, Jacob Garchik on trombone, Dave Ambrosio on bass and Dan Weiss on drums. At 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK GAYTON QUINTET (Tuesday and Wednesday) Mr. Gayton, a sharp trombonist, has worked in a colorful array of horn sections, including his current gig with Bruce Springsteen's Seeger Sessions Band. As a leader, he brings a jazz flexibility to dub and reggae, gospel and soul. At 9 p.m., 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., Zinc Bar, 90 West Houston Street at LaGuardia Place, Greenwich Village, (212) 477-8337; cover, $5, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GOOD FOR COWS (Tonight and tomorrow) The bassist Devin Hoff and the drummer Ches Smith comprise this Bay Area duo, which interrogates jazz and punk with equal rigor. On the second night, they're joined by the guitarist Mary Halvorson and the violist Jessica Pavone, two musicians with a duo rapport of their own. At 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village, www.thestonenyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JAZZ IN JULY (Tuesday through Thursday) A year ago, the pianist Bill Charlap presided over his first season as artistic director of this venerable traditional jazz series, successfully clearing the bar set by his predecessor, Dick Hyman. The new season begins next week, with guest-laden tributes to Duke Ellington (Tuesday), Mr. Hyman (Wednesday) and Thelonious Monk (Thursday). Wynton Marsalis, making an appearance on the Monk evening, provides the most potent dose of jazz celebrity; but among this festival's regular patronage, Mr. Hyman himself looms just as large. Tickets will go quickly, if they haven't already. At 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, Manhattan, (212) 415-5500 or www.92y.org, $50. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LATIN IN MANHATTAN FESTIVAL (Through Thursday) Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola's second annual Latin jazz festival started this week with Claudia Acuña, a vocalist guided by the pulse and passion of her native Chile, who plays through Sunday with a strong quintet. Tuesday marks the start of a six-night engagement with Grady Tate and Latin Flavor, a heavily rhythmic sextet led by Mr. Tate on vocals. (Through July 30.) At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Friday and Saturday, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CHUCK MANGIONE (Through Sunday) Mr. Mangione's fluegelhorn has been a staple of instrumental pop for more than 30 years, and his trademark hit, ''Feels So Good,'' helped pave the way for smooth jazz. He leads a polished group that includes the saxophonist and flutist Gerard Niewood and the guitarist Coleman Mellett. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KATE McGARRY (Tomorrow) Ms. McGarry is a quiet but potent singer who recasts jazz and folk material alike with a quavering sincerity. She performs here with the guitarist Keith Ganz, the keyboardist Gary Versace and the drummer Dan Rieser. At 6 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN MONDER GROUP (Sunday) ''Oceana'' (Sunnyside), the most recent album by the guitarist Ben Monder, is a small-scale but ambitious suite of original music that doesn't sound quite like anything else. Mr. Monder presents much of the same material here, with the bassist Chris Lightcap and the drummer Ted Poor. At 8 and 10 p.m., Bar 4, 444 Seventh Avenue, at 15th Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 832-9800, www.bar4.net; suggested donation, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARK MURPHY (Tomorrow) Mr. Murphy is a singer known mainly for sly insouciance, but on his recent album ''Once to Every Heart'' (Verve), he opted for a burnished and broken romanticism. He performs here in the most intimate of settings, accompanied only by the guitarist Jack Wilkins. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID (FATHEAD) NEWMAN QUINTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Newman, a surefooted tenor saxophonist best known for his long and fruitful tenure with Ray Charles, leads an ensemble consisting of Javon Jackson on tenor and soprano saxophones, David Leonhardt on piano, John Menagon on bass and Yoron Israel on drums. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with midnight sets tonight and tomorrow. Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SANGHA QUARTET (Monday) This ensemble, led by the keyboardist Kevin Hays, creates an electronic jazz hybrid with a sensibility that hovers somewhere between pop and experimental fusion. In addition to Mr. Hays, the group consists of the saxophonist Seamus Blake, the bassist Doug Weiss and the drummer Bill Stewart. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TODD SICKAFOOSE GROUP (Wednesday) Mr. Sickafoose is a bassist-composer equally fond of rough edges and rounded forms, as he demonstrated on an evocative recent album, ''Blood Orange'' (Secret Hatch). He performs here with the trumpeter Russ Johnson and the trombonist Alan Ferber; the guitarists Adam Levy and Mike Gamble; and the percussionists Mike Dillon and Ches Smith. At 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DR. LONNIE SMITH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Under Dr. Smith's command, the Hammond B-3 organ can be subtly atmospheric or growlingly ecstatic; together with the guitarist Peter Bernstein and the drummer Alison Miller, he delivers a searching brand of soul jazz. Continues through July 23. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* HENRY THREADGILL'S ZOOID (Thursday) The august composer and multireedist Henry Threadgill has always nursed a fascination with timbre; in this superb ensemble, his flute and alto saxophone are flanked by cello, oud, acoustic guitar, tuba, and drums. Continues through July 23. At 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BEN WALTZER TRIO (Thursday) Mr. Waltzer, a pianist, manages a thoughtful modernism that coexists more than peaceably with a buoyant, un-self-conscious sense of swing. His trio, with Matt Penman and Gerald Cleaver on bass and drums, is first-rate. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119; no cover, $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID WEISS AND THE POINT OF DEPARTURE QUINTET (Thursday) An assertive trumpeter and accomplished arranger, Mr. Weiss leads an ensemble well stocked with young talent: J. D. Allen on tenor saxophone, Nir Felder on guitar, Luques Curtis on bass and Kendrick Scott on drums. At 10 p.m., Fat Cat, 75 Christopher Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 675-6056; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL WEISS QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow) Mr. Weiss is an exceedingly proficient pianist, well versed in a multitude of jazz styles. Leading a quartet, he spotlights another versatile player, the alto and soprano saxophonist Steve Wilson. At 8 and 9:45 p.m., Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, (212) 885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK WESS QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Wess, a venerable tenor saxophonist and flutist, marks the release of a likable new album, ''Hank &amp; Frank,'' with this one-night engagement. His ensemble here does not include Hank Jones, the Hank in the album title; but it does feature the bassist John Webber, the drummer Leroy Williams and a guitarist, Ilya Lushtak, who released the album on Lineage, his own new label. At 10 p.m., Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* JOE WILDER QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) The trumpeter Joe Wilder, still playing well in his mid-80's, has had a wealth of professional experience both in and out of jazz. But he has hardly ever led his own group in a New York club residency: only once, in fact, at the Village Vanguard this year. He returns to the club next week with the same supporting cast of Michael Weiss on piano, John Webber on bass and Lewis Nash on drums. Continues through July 23. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tomorrow and Sunday) This company's productions almost invariably end up at the New York City Opera, and lots of people drive up to Cooperstown, N.Y., to get an early glimpse of what's on the way. But Glimmerglass, with its intimate, comfortable and up-to-date house, is a vastly superior place to see and hear these productions than the cavernous New York State Theater. The company opened its season with a light work, the Gilbert and Sullivan operetta ''The Pirates of Penzance'' in a production by Lillian Groag. This week's schedule also includes Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia,'' in a production by Leon Major. ''Pirates'': tomorrow night at 8; ''Barbiere'': Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255; $64 to $112. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'GRENDEL' (Tomorrow and Sunday) The wall works! The Lincoln Center Festival is breathing easy. As everyone seems to know by now, the Los Angeles Opera's premiere of ''Grendel,'' the operatic adaptation of John Gardner's 1971 novel, a retelling of the epic poem ''Beowulf,'' composed by Elliot Goldenthal and directed by Julie Taymor, had to be postponed when the 16-ton rotating wall that dominated the set would not rotate. Now installed at the New York State Theater, the wall is operating smoothly and the elaborate production, complete with Ms. Taymor's trademark puppets, tree-man creatures and flying dancers, seems glitch-free. Alas, Mr. Goldenthal's derivative music is like an ominous and obvious film score and the opera is weighted down with philosophical mumbo-jumbo. At 7:30 p.m., (212) 721-6500; $40 to $200. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>New Jersey Opera Theater (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Founded in 2002, the New Jersey Opera Theater is striving to become the pre-eminent opera company for the state. Besides presenting performances, the company offers master classes and educational outreach programs. The productions include Donizetti's ''Elisir d'Amore,'' directed by David Grabarkewitz and conducted by Brent McMunn, and an intriguing double bill of Puccini's comedy ''Gianni Schicchi'' and ''Buoso's Ghost,'' a one-act work from 1996 by Michael Ching, which picks up the story of the clever Schicchi where Puccini's opera leaves off. Steven Condy sings Schicchi in both works; James Caraher conducts. ''L'Elisir d'Amore'': tonight at 8, Sunday at 2 p.m. and Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; ''Schicchi'' and ''Buoso'': tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Berlind Theater at the McCarter Theater Center, 91 University Place, Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., (609) 258-2787; $42 to $49. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) This venerable early-music festival focuses on Mozart and Schubert this weekend, with Sharon Baker as the soprano soloist in groups of songs by each composer, and the violinist Daniel Stepner and the fortepianist Kristian Bezuidenhout offering sonatas and fantasies. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156. $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) This floating concert hall on the Brooklyn side of the East River offers the intimacy that chamber music needs, as well as a wonderful view of Lower Manhattan through the bay windows behind the stage. Tonight Steven Beck, the pianist, plays works by Stravinsky, Brahms, Haydn and Schubert. The Sequenza Trio, with the violinist Mark Kaplan, the cellist Adrian Brendel and the pianist Yael Weiss, takes over tomorrow and Sunday to play works by Martinu, Schubert (the great E-flat Trio, Op. 100) and Paul Chihara's ''Ain't No Sunshine.'' On Thursday, the Gala String Quartet and Olga Vinokur, the pianist, join forces for Mozart's chamber version of his Piano Concerto No. 12 (K. 414) and the Schumann Piano Quintet (Op. 44). Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday at 7:30 p.m.; Sunday at 4 p.m., Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35 tonight, tomorrow and Sunday; $40 on Thursday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>'BEOWuLF' (Tuesday and Wednesday) The Lincoln Center Festival offers Benjamin Bagby's smaller, faster take on ''Beowulf'' as a complement to the opera ''Grendel'' playing nearby. At 8:30 p.m., Drama Theater at La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500; $45, with limited availability. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>CARAMOOR (Tonight through Sunday, Thursday) The chamber ensemble Opus One frames its program of piano quartets tonight in favorites, with Mozart's Quartet in E flat (K. 493) to begin and Dvorak's Quartet in E flat (Op. 87) to close. Between them it offers a more recent adventure, George Tsontakis's Piano Quartet No. 3. Tomorrow night Michael Barrett conducts the Orchestra of St. Luke's in the premiere of a Piano Concerto by John Musto, Caramoor's stylistically omnivorous composer in residence. Also on the program are Beethoven's ''Leonore'' Overture No. 3 and Schumann's ''Spring'' Symphony. On Sunday afternoon, Will Crutchfield leads an all-Mozart program that includes ''Exsultate, Jubilate'' and arias and ensembles from ''Le Nozze di Figaro,'' ''Don Giovanni'' and other works. The soloists are Sumi Jo, soprano; Maria Zifchak, mezzo-soprano; Steven Tharp, tenor; and Daniel Mobbs, bass-baritone. On Thursday, the brilliant American pianist Christopher Taylor will perform Messiaen's complete ''Vingt Regards sur l'Enfant-Jésus,'' a two-hour workout that includes some of the most difficult and complex yet sublime and ecstatic music ever written for piano. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday at 4:30 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., Caramoor, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-1252; $27 and $37 tonight, $17.50 to $67.50 tomorrow, $19 to $49 on Sunday, $17 and $27 on Thursday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* INTERNATIONAL KEYBOARD INSTITUTE AND FESTIVAL (Sunday through Thursday) This expansive festival of master classes and concerts runs through the rest of July, and tends to draw the biggest crowds of all the Mannes College of Music's summer series. Jerome Rose, the institute's director, plays the first faculty concert on Sunday, with works by Mozart, Schumann, Chopin (the four Ballades) and Paul Schoenfield. On Monday Fabio Bidini plays Schumann's ''Carnaval'' and Beethoven's ''Waldstein'' and ''Appassionata'' Sonatas. On Tuesday Steven Mayer offers a virtuoso program that moves from Weber and Schumann through Ives, Gottschalk and James P. Johnson into jazz pieces by Jelly Roll Morton and Art Tatum. On Wednesday Nikolai Demidenko plays Schubert, Liszt and Bach. On Thursday Jeffrey Swann offers a lecture-recital, ''In Search of Lost Time: Music in the World of Marcel Proust,'' that includes works by Franck, Fauré, Saint-Saëns, Debussy, Reynaldo Hahn and Wagner. At 8 p.m., Mannes College, 150 West 85th Street, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, Ext. 4858; $25. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC'S CONCERTS IN THE PARKS (Tonight, tomorrow, Monday and Tuesday) The Philharmonic has left the air-conditioned confines of Avery Fisher Hall for its annual series of free concerts in the parks. Notably, the conductors and soloists for both programs this summer are dynamic women. The orchestra's impressive associate conductor, Xian Zhang, offers two Tchaikovsky works, the ''Coronation March'' and the Violin Concerto (with the charismatic violinist Jennifer Koh as soloist), and Dvorak's exuberant Symphony No. 8. The series ends on Tuesday with the adventurous Marin Alsop conducting John Adams's ''Chairman Dances,'' Prokofiev's Violin Concerto No. 1, with the virtuosic Leila Josefowicz as soloist, and Beethoven's always-popular Fifth Symphony. Expect these concerts, as usual, to draws tens of thousands of people for picnics in the parks and music under the stars (if nature cooperates). There will be fireworks after each performance. Tonight at 8, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Staten Island; tomorrow at 8 p.m., Heckscher State Park, East Islip, N.Y.; Monday at 8 p.m., Van Cortlandt Park, Broadway and West 246th Street, the Bronx; Tuesday at 8 p.m., Great Lawn, Central Park; (212) 875-5709. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight) A host of chamber musicians play an all-Russian evening. At 8, Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000; $15 to $45. (Holland)</p>
        <p>SVET STOYANOV (Monday) The River to River Festival this week includes a performance by Mr. Stoyanov, a Bulgarian percussionist. At 7:30 p.m., Schimmel Center for the Arts, 3 Spruce Street, near Park Row, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789; free tickets available after 4 p.m. (Holland)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tonight through Sunday) James Levine's return to action with the Boston Symphony Orchestra includes Schoenberg's gigantic oratorio ''Gurrelieder'' tonight, and Strauss's equally large opera ''Elektra,'' performed in concert tomorrow. Andrew Davis conducts a mixed program on Sunday afternoon. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30, Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200; $18 to $87 tonight, with $8.50 lawn tickets; $18 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, with $17 lawn tickets. (Holland)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>* AMERICAN BALLET THEATER (Tonight and tomorrow) The company's spring season ends with three performances of Kenneth MacMillan's highly theatrical ''Romeo and Juliet,'' to Prokofiev's haunting score. Julie Kent (celebrating her 20th anniversary with Ballet Theater) and Marcelo Gomes take the lead roles tonight, Paloma Herrera and David Hallberg tomorrow afternoon, and Alessandra Ferri and José Manuel Carreño tomorrow night. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000 or abt.org; $23 to $100. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>CAPACITOR (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) From San Francisco, Capacitor creates pieces based on science. In ''Digging in the Dark'' the focus is on modern geophysics and acrobatic, virtuosic movement. Through July 30. Tonight through Sunday, Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8, American Theater of Actors, 314 West 54th Street, Clinton, (212) 352-3101 or capacitor.org; $35. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK SUMMERSTAGE (Tonight) The Stephen Petronio Company, known for its stylish, cheeky, high-energy dance, will perform a program featuring two pieces set to music by Rufus Wainwright that will be sung live in part by the Young People's Chorus of New York City. At 8 p.m. Rumsey Playfield, Central Park, enter at Fifth Avenue and 69th Street or Central Park West and 72nd Street, (212) 360-1399 or summerstage.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHASHAMA OASIS FESTIVAL 2006 (Today and Monday through Thursday) Artists of all disciplines -- some, we suspect, wildly undisciplined, in the grand tradition of Chashama productions -- will perform in a Midtown window. Today, and Monday through next Friday from noon to 1:30 p.m. and 5:30 to 7 p.m., 217 East 42nd Street, between Second and Third Avenues, chashama.org; free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Chunky Move (Tonight and tomorrow) Australian men apparently have dancing difficulties too; perhaps not these particular men, though. Using video montages and interviews, the members of the physical Australian troupe Chunky Move channel their inner wallflowers in ''I Want to Dance Better at Parties.'' Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $36. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>COMPANY C CONTEMPORARY BALLET (Opens Thursday). A 12-member ballet troupe from San Francisco with an eclectic repertory presents works by Twyla Tharp, Patrick Corbin, Alexander Proia and its director, Charles Anderson. Through July 23. At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, SoHo, (212) 334-7479; $25, $20 students and 65+. (Jack Anderson)</p>
        <p>PAULA HUNTER (Today through Thursday) Ms. Hunter will perform ''I Am Karen Finley,'' an absurdist performance solo, as a free dance installation in a window in the Theater District. Through July 22. Today through Thursday at 5 and 7:30 p.m., Chashama, 112 West 44th Street, (212) 391-8151 or chashama.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL 2006 (Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) The Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company examines issues relating to patriotism in ''Blind Date.'' At 8 p.m., LaGuardia Concert Hall, Amsterdam Avenue and 65th Street, (212) 721-6500 or lincolncenter.org; $50. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tomorrow, Sunday and Wednesday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, has settled into the intimate Theater 80 until the end of the month. Tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m., Sunday at 2 and 5 p.m., Wednesday at 8 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Mark's Place, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, maybe, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Monday is a special opening event combining parts of the two programs that will alternate for the rest of the run. Through Aug. 12. Monday through Thursday nights at 8, Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org. $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'RIVER DEEP, A TRIBUTE TO TINA TURNER'  (Tonight, tomorrow and Tuesday through Thursday) Gabrielle Lansner pays tribute to this singer, who is played by Pat Hall, in a multimedia production set to music by Philip Hamilton. Through July 29. Tonight, and Tuesday through Thursday nights at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 p.m. Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, between Ninth and Tenth Avenues, (212) 279-4200 or gabriellelansner.com; $35. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SUMMER IN THE SQUARE (Wednesday). A series of Wednesday events featuring music, storytelling, yoga and dance, this week includes modern dance by the Battery Dance Company. Through Aug. 16. At 6 p.m., Union Square Park, Broadway and 14th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 460-1208 or unionsquarenyc.org; free. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>* TAP CITY 2006 (Tonight through Sunday, and Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday) The festivities continue with performances of ''Tap Internationals'' tonight; ''Tap Forward,'' a program of contemporary choreography, tomorrow, Tuesday and Thursday nights; and ''Tap and Song,'' whose performers include Mable Lee and the festival director, Tony Waag, on Sunday and Wednesday nights. Tonight at 7 and 9:30; tomorrow and Sunday at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; Wednesday at 7 and 9:30 p.m.; and Tuesday and Thursday at 7 and 9:30 p.m. The Duke on 42nd Street, 229 West 42nd Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues, (212) 239-6200 and atdf.org; $40. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>THOMAS/ORTIZ DANCE (Wednesday through Thursday) Ted Thomas and Frances Ortiz combine urban athleticism and Latin sensuality in choreographic explorations of socially relevant themes. Through July 22. At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077; $15, $25. (Anderson)</p>
        <p>DUSAN TYNEK DANCE THEATER  (Tonight through Sunday) Dusan Tynek, from Czechoslovakia, trained with Aileen Passloff at Bard College. He will present two premieres, one inspired by sinister 19th-century Czech ballads and set to string music by classical and contemporary composers, and the other set to music by Michael Galasso. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for students, artists and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>VON USSAR DANCEWORKS (Tonight through Sunday) Astrid von Ussar, a Slovenian modern-dance choreographer now based in New York City, will present four new and recent pieces, including her new ''23 hours,'' set to music by Graeme Ravell. The program features a dance by Mojca Ussar, her sister. Tonight through Sunday at 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $20; $15, students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Bruce Museum: 'Best in Show: Dogs in Art From the Renaissance to the Present,' through Aug. 27. This show is a dog lover's picnic, with paintings that celebrate canis lupus familiaris and its wayward ways. 1 Museum Drive, Greenwich, Conn.; (203) 869-0376. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,'  through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedekers, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Sept. 3. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including the young Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. Tirelessly invasive, he lived by night. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM: 'EVA HESSE: SCULPTURE,' through Sept. 17. Assembled by Elizabeth Sussman, curator at the Whitney Museum of American Art, and Fred Wasserman, a curator at the Jewish Museum, this show focuses on a pivotal Hesse exhibition, ''Chain Polymers,'' at the Fischbach Gallery -- known for promoting Minimalist painters -- in 1968. Arguably a compilation of her best work, it was her first and only solo show of sculpture during her lifetime, and most of the objects in it -- along with some earlier and later pieces -- are here. One of the earliest is ''Compart'' (1966), a four-panel vertical that starts at the top with a fully formed, round, breastlike image of neatly wound cord that mysteriously breaks up into part of the same image on each of the three panels beneath. The last, most startling and most impressive work is ''Untitled (Rope Piece),'' of 1970, made as Ms. Hesse was dying, finished with the help of friends. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Metropolitan museum of art: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. Further sharpness comes from the placement of all parts of the altarpiece at eye level, creating a viewing intensity that more than compensates for the fact that they have not been reassembled. (212) 535-7710. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. And wait till you see the painted ceramic vessel known as the ''Dazzler Vase,'' with its red and green patterns like jade on fire, you'll understand its name. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* Morgan Library and Museum: 'Masterworks from the Morgan,'  through Sept. 10. Almost three years after closing to build an expansion, the Morgan is back and brilliant. What's new: Renzo Piano's splendid four-story glass-and-steel court, a sort of giant solarium with see-through elevators; two good-size second-floor galleries; and a neat little strongbox of an enclosure, called the Cube, for reliquaries and altar vessels, medieval objects made with so much silver and gold that they seem to give off heat. What's not new: almost everything in this exhibition, which fills every gallery with mini-exhibitions of master drawings and musical manuscripts, as well as illuminated gospels, devotional sculptures and historical and literary autograph manuscripts from the Brontës to Bob Dylan. 225 Madison Avenue, at East 36th Street, (212) 685-0008 or www.themorgan.org. (Individual show closings can be checked by telephone or through the Web site.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Arts AND Design: 'THE EAMES LOUNGE CHAIR: AN ICON OF MODERN DESIGN,' through Sept. 3. Celebrating the 50th anniversary of a chair whose combination of declarative modernist structure and sheer creature comfort was both innovative and a bit alien, this exhibition is a successful design object in its own right. It pays homage with drawings, advertising ephemera, precursors, vintage television clips, a wonderful documentary and three versions of the chair itself, enshrined, exploded and useable. 40 West 53rd Street, (212) 956-3535. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 170 Central Park West, (212) 873-3400. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/ Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, (718) 784-2084. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art : 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. If ''Full House'' is about one thing, it is about discord, about how harmonious America never was. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West Second Street, (212) 243-0200, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Small Wonders' Bucking the big-picture trend, this absorbing show presents 45 black-and-white photographs ranging from palm to postage-stamp size. They include classic portraits by Edward Weston and Berenice Abbott; André Kertesz's William-Blake-like image of a naked man walking into a field of tall grass; and Walter Auerbach's picture of Willem de Kooning's studio circa 1950. Robert Mann, 210 11th Avenue, (212) 989-7600, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>'About Light' Some works in this show, like Sean Scully's blocky grid painting and Philip Guston's smudgy gray abstraction, absorb more than emit light. Others, including Thomas Pihl's smooth, pink monochromes; Alex Katz's small nocturnal pictures of lighted apartment-building windows; and Richard Pousette-Dart's pulsating, pointillist field, seem to glow from within. Galerie Lelong, 528 West 26th Street, (212) 315-0470, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Air' This appealing, understated show organized by the painter Amy Sillman includes Benjamin Butler's lush, Mondrian-style painting of trees; Pat Palermo's semi-abstract drawings of wrecked cars and other curious subjects; John White Cerasulo's watercolor of a bare-chested wilderness giant; Pamela Wilson-Ryckman's flickering picture of a scattering crowd of people; and abstractions in various styles by Robert Bordo, Jenny Monick, Howard Smith, Laura Newman and Patricia Treib. Monya Rowe, 526 West 26th Street, (646) 234-8645, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 East 22nd Street, (212) 229-2766, through July 28. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Everywhichway' This lively show of artists working inventively between abstraction and representation includes Katherine Bradford's whimsical images of ships and the sea; Chris Martin's updated Tantric art; Sigrid Sandström's Arctic icescapes; suave, retro-Modernist pattern paintings by Jennifer Riley and Colin Thomson; Harvey Tulcensky's finely textured ballpoint-pen fields; and compact, sensuous ceramic slabs by Joyce Robins. Edward Thorp, 210 11th Avenue, at 24th Street, (212) 691-6565, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'I'm not here. This isn't happening' With possibly the best title of the summer season, this group show includes Michelle Lopez's canny, neo-Surrealistic sculptures; Ronnie Bass's incantatory sound-and-video installation in a simulated old ship's cabin; Terry Haggerty's mesmerizing pattern paintings; Katarina Burin's noirish combinations of watercolor and found photography; Damien Cadio's enigmatic, painterly narratives; and Jim Gaylord's explosive, loosely Cubist paintings of natural and artificial fragments. Grimm/Rosenfeld, 530 West 25th Street, (212) 352-2388, through Aug. 4. (Johnson)Smith)</p>
        <p>* THE NAME OF THIS SHOW IS NOT GAY ART NOW Characterized by its organizer, the artist Jack Pierson, as an ode to the passing of ''the notion of Gay Art,'' this exhibition embraces the work of about 60 artists (gay, straight and otherwise) to create a cacophonous celebration and suggest that everyone is a little bit gay, if they are lucky. Paul Kasmin Gallery, 293 10th Avenue, at 27th Street, (212) 563-4474, through tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'The Sanctuary and the Scrum' A diverting, pluralistic show inaugurates a new Northwest Chelsea exhibition space. It includes good abstract and semi-abstract paintings by Jessica Dickinson and Andrew Guenther; a stuffed swan shorn of its feathers from the head down by Jane Benson; a gleaming crutch covered by tiny mirror facets by Kristian Kozul; and a funny photo-conceptual project about grocery store shopping carts by Julian Montague. Black &amp; White, 636 West 28th Street, (212) 244-3007, through July 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Martin Schoeller: 'Close Up' Extraordinarily large and detailed mug-shot-like portraits of celebrities like Jack Nicholson, Angelina Jolie and Bill Clinton. Hasted Hunt, 529 West 20th Street, (212) 627-0006, through Sept. 1. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Vivan Sundaram: 'Re-Take of Amrita' The photographs in this beautiful, time-haunted show are all of past generations of the Indian artist Vivan Sundaram's family, and include images of his aunt, the famed modernist painter Amrita Sher-Gil (1913-1941). Thanks to digital technology, those generations mix in logically impossible combinations. The resulting pictures embody the past the way it survives in the mind: edited, layered, compressed, as if in a dream. Sepia International, 148 West 24th Street, 11th floor, (212) 645-9444, through July 28. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'How I Finally Accepted Fate' The memoir is the loosely defined theme of this interesting 10-person show. It includes Matt Keegan's video of cheerleaders celebrating his grandmother's 90th birthday; Angela Dufresne's vivid painting of a shirtless man called ''Me as a Communist Male in 'The Red and the White' ''; Carolee Schneemann's patchwork tale about modern love in photographs and typewritten words; and Maureen Duncan's three-and-a-half-hour monologue about her CD collection. EFA Gallery, 323 West 39th Street, (212) 563-5855, through July 28. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Christine Osinski: 'Notes From West Brighton' Ms. Osinski took the visually and sociologically gripping photographs in this exhibition on Staten Island, where she lives, in the early 1980's and the early 90's. These exceptionally lucid black-and-white pictures of nondescript neighborhoods, grocery store customers, small-town parades, self-consciously posing teenagers and abandoned wrecked cars were made with an affectionately cool, clear eye for the beauty and weirdness of ordinary people and places. Silo, 1 Freeman Alley, East Village, (212) 505-9156, through July 30. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>Philippe Decrauzat: 'Plate 28' A conceptually perplexing but visually striking installation by this young Swiss artist includes a black-and-white grid painted on the walls, a sculpture based on a Russian Constructivist design, and a grainy, flickering black-and-white film showing glimpses of ominous landscapes from ''The Twilight Zone.'' Swiss Institute, 495 Broadway, at Broome Street, (212) 925-2035, closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'VERONESE'S ALLEGORIES: VIRTUE, LOVE AND EXPLORATION IN RENAISSANCE VENICE,' Paolo Veronese (1528-88), a superb colorist and one of the most suavely sensuous of Renaissance Venetian painters, used the age-old device of allegory to make abstract concepts visual, often by means of human or mythological figures. In this five-painting show, the first to include all of his large-scale allegories from American collections, high ideals mingle with earthy and sometimes erotic physicality, as in the painting ''Venus and Mars United by Love,'' depicting the goddess of love and the god of war in an intimate moment brokered by Cupid, as Mars's sexy horse looks on. The other works are a little more staid, but the painting in them is equally gorgeous. (See above.) 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, closes Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>EVA HESSE: 'DRAWING'  This show deals in depth with Ms. Hesse's works on paper, ranging from rough sketches or notes, to test pieces made from various materials that function as drawings, to finished projects that stand on their own. A zealous researcher, Ms. Hesse made all kinds of thumbnail notations and calculations to explore the properties of her malleable materials. Many of these sheets, perhaps too many, are shown, too. Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, (212) 219-2166; closes tomorrow. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Cosima von Bonin: 'Relax, It's Only a Ghost' Various two- and three-dimensional objects -- including stuffed animals like the ones you might find in a high-end toy store -- and Rorschach test patterns stitched to colorful bedspreads add up to a familiar critique of consumerism. Friedrich Petzel, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 680-9467; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Invisible Might: Works from 1965-1971' This luminous group show about the euphoric convergence of Minimalism and new technologies in the late 1960's and early 70's includes a smoky glass cube by Larry Bell; a solid black plastic cube by John McCracken; a tall, clear acrylic prism by Robert Irwin; a beautiful aqua-green light projection by James Turrell; a yellow molded plastic relief by Craig Kauffman; and a corner composition of elastic cords and bent metal rods by Fred Sandback. Nyehaus, 15 Gramercy Park South, (212) 995-1785; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 18, 2006, Tuesday  A pop music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday for a performance tomorrow by Bravo Silva and Raising the Fawn has become outdated. After the section went to press, the show was moved from Pianos on the Lower East Side to the Syrup Room, 100 Ingraham Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, at 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 25, 2006, Tuesday  A dance review on Wednesday about the opening night of the Pilobolus season at the Joyce Theater, which continues through Aug. 12, misstated the number of programs being performed during the season. It is three, not two. The error also appeared in a dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 27, 2006, Thursday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 about the exhibition ''CRG Presents: Klaus Von Nichtssagend Gallery,'' at the CRG Gallery through tomorrow, misstated the address. It is 535 West 22nd Street, not East 22nd.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 31, 2006, Monday  An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 for the exhibition ''A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field With Sculptures'' at the Matthew Marks Gallery misstated the address. It is 522 West 22nd Street, not West Second Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 18, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A pop music entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on Friday for a performance tomorrow by Bravo Silva and Raising the Fawn has become outdated. After the section went to press, the show was moved from Pianos on the Lower East Side to the Syrup Room, 100 Ingraham Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, at 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: July 25, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A dance review on Wednesday about the opening night of the Pilobolus season at the Joyce Theater, which continues through Aug. 12, misstated the number of programs being performed during the season. It is three, not two. The error also appeared in a dance entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: July 27, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 about the exhibition ''CRG Presents: Klaus Von Nichtssagend Gallery,'' at the CRG Gallery through tomorrow, misstated the address. It is 535 West 22nd Street, not East 22nd.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: July 31, 2006, Monday</p>
        <p>An art entry in the Listings pages of Weekend on July 14 and July 21 for the exhibition ''A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field With Sculptures'' at the Matthew Marks Gallery misstated the address. It is 522 West 22nd Street, not West Second Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
