<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Laugh Lines</title>
    <meta content="23jokes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1756528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA153FF930A15757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Laugh Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jay Leno</p>
        <p>As I'm sure you have heard, there have been resignations in Washington. Yesterday, Press Secretary Scott McClellan resigned. People at the White House are dropping faster than old guys hunting with Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>Al Gore's coming out with a movie about global warming called ''An Inconvenient Truth.'' It's described as a detailed scientific view of global warming. President Bush said he just saw a film about global warming, ''Ice Age 2: The Meltdown.'' He said, ''It's so much better than that boring Al Gore movie.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jay Leno</p>
        <p>As I'm sure you have heard, there have been resignations in Washington. Yesterday, Press Secretary Scott McClellan resigned. People at the White House are dropping faster than old guys hunting with Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>Al Gore's coming out with a movie about global warming called ''An Inconvenient Truth.'' It's described as a detailed scientific view of global warming. President Bush said he just saw a film about global warming, ''Ice Age 2: The Meltdown.'' He said, ''It's so much better than that boring Al Gore movie.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the White House sponsored the annual Easter egg roll on the South Lawn. The winning child found 6 eggs and 14 lobbyists hiding in the bushes.</p>
        <p>President Bush had to ask for an extension on his taxes. He's still trying to decide whether or not to write off Donald Rumsfeld.</p>
        <p>I don't want to say that Donald Rumsfeld is in trouble, but this morning they found him hiding in a spider hole.</p>
        <p>The president of China, Hu Jintao, arrived in the United States today. His first stop is Seattle. He stopped into a store to buy some souvenirs to bring home. He was a little frustrated. He said, ''Do you guys have anything that wasn't made in China?''</p>
        <p>So China's president meets America's president. It will be President Hu meeting President Huh.</p>
        <p>David Letterman</p>
        <p>In Washington, D.C., today is the annual White House front lawn Easter egg hunt. It's a big, big annual event and the kids found so many eggs, it was unbelievable, and I'm thinking, ''Well, maybe they should send the kids to look for Osama Bin Laden.''</p>
        <p>This is the 100th anniversary of the devastating San Francisco earthquake. The devastating earthquake happened today, 100 years ago. FEMA is on the way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
