<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nonfiction Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="09williams" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/books/review/09williams.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1774593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Pearson, T R</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chadwick, Douglas H</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DB1430F93AA35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nonfiction Chronicle</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nonfiction Chronicle</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Florence Williams</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEX, ROCK &amp; OPTICAL ILLUSIONS. By Victor Moscoso. Preface by Milton Glaser. Introduction by Steven Heller. (Fantagraphics, $34.95.) A retrospective of the career of Moscoso, whose posters for groups like the Grateful Dead and Big Brother &amp; the Holding Company accomplished what the bands ''did for rock music: They turned up the volume and broke all the rules,'' as Heller, the art director of the Book Review, writes in his introduction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New books by T. R. Pearson, Jason Roberts, Mark and Delia Owens, Gilles Fonteneau and Douglas H. Chadwick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEX, ROCK &amp; OPTICAL ILLUSIONS. By Victor Moscoso. Preface by Milton Glaser. Introduction by Steven Heller. (Fantagraphics, $34.95.) A retrospective of the career of Moscoso, whose posters for groups like the Grateful Dead and Big Brother &amp; the Holding Company accomplished what the bands ''did for rock music: They turned up the volume and broke all the rules,'' as Heller, the art director of the Book Review, writes in his introduction.</p>
        <p>SEAWORTHY: Adrift With William Willis in the Golden Age of Rafting. By T. R. Pearson. (Crown, $24.95.) Armchair adventurers can be forgiven for not remembering William Willis, who was briefly famous for having crossed the Pacific on a balsa raft several months after having been declared lost at sea in 1954. Thor Heyerdahl had already beaten him to the feat by seven years, and unlike the high-profile Norseman, Willis, who was 60 when he set out, had nothing scientific or anthropological to prove. But as T. R. Pearson conjures Willis's many nautical adventures, they are both thrilling and bizarre. Willis was ahead of his time in style (he was a compulsive whole-wheat-eating yogi) and ambition. Pearson describes him as a nearly pathological adrenaline addict, and a careless one to boot. He was the sort of man who didn't think to bring a transmitter, refused to carry an extra set of sails and used corroding paint cans to hold his water supply. At one point he fell out of the swiftly moving raft and was saved only by the vessel's fishing line, which was accidentally hooked to his shirt. The first nonfiction book by Pearson, a novelist, ''Seaworthy'' occasionally suffers from a lack of sourcing, and it could have benefited from a more thorough discussion of relevant topics like the physiology of dehydration. After his fresh water leaked away, Willis discovered that he could survive for months by drinking seawater alone. This was just one of his astounding accomplishments.</p>
        <p>A SENSE OF THE WORLD: How a Blind Man Became History's Greatest Traveler. By Jason Roberts. (HarperCollins, $26.95.) James Holman (1786-1857) was a man with a burning ambition: to be the first person to travel around the world for pleasure by foot and horse, and by boat only when there was no other option. In the 1820's, this was a daunting goal; for a blind Englishman of limited means, it was remarkable. Jason Roberts, a contributor to McSweeney's and The Believer, discovered Holman in an antiquated book about eccentric travelers and was immediately hooked. ''A medical mystery, a modest hero, a series of cloaked affections. How could my fascination not become an obsession?'' he writes. Roberts is only partly successful in conveying his passion. He dutifully traces Holman's wanderings, adding well-researched asides on the Royal Navy, the aftereffects of the Napoleonic wars, the politics of czarist Russia and other topics. Most of these accounts are interesting, but the book suffers a bit from the dated quality of the quest (which, by the way, Holman achieved in 1832). Walking through Italy may have been mildly hazardous and exotic to Holman, but the recounting here doesn't read with much suspense. Other adventures are somewhat more exciting, as when he joins an anti-slavery expedition to West Africa or is roughly escorted out of Siberia. Roberts only touches on Holman's apparent interest in sex tourism. Still, ''A Sense of the World'' gives us a man who embraced wanderlust at a time when the continents and oceans were much, much bigger.</p>
        <p>SECRETS OF THE SAVANNA: Twenty-Three Years in the African Wilderness Unraveling the Mysteries of Elephants and People. By Mark and Delia Owens. (Houghton Mifflin, $26.) In the early 1990's, Mark and Delia Owens, the authors of ''Cry of the Kalahari,'' homed in on Zambia as a good place to conduct research. When they arrived at the vast wilderness of North Luangwa National Park, however, they found that the elephant population had plummeted from 17,000 to 1,500. Driven by poverty and corrupt officials, villagers were illegally slaughtering the animals for the ivory trade. If the critical question was how to stop poaching, the answer was in finding stable, alternative employment for the people surrounding the park. The Owenses put down their binoculars to become pioneers in the field of community conservation. They set up a microloan program to finance local businesses like beekeeping and fish farming, helped build schools and wrote a conservation curriculum. ''Secrets of the Savanna'' is less about elephant mysteries (although we do learn how stressed-out adolescent elephants behave in the absence of parents) than about successful conservation. Saving wilderness, it turns out, is all about improving civilization. Writing about your achievements can be tricky, though, and parts of the narrative read like grant proposals, with separate sections written by either Mark or Delia. But the book is filled with some remarkable characters, including the local leaders, as well as the inspiring core of it all, the animals. ''Many late afternoons found us waiting with the lions in some isolated spot, sharing the same lean shade of a twisted thorn tree, all of us lethargic, torpid, lightheaded, comatose,'' Delia Owens recalls of her early work in Africa. ''The Kalahari heat is a great equalizer, reducing all creatures to a sluggish heap.''</p>
        <p>MURMURS FROM THE DEEP: Scientific Adventure in the Caribbean. By Gilles Fonteneau. Translated by George Holoch. (Arcade, $25.) Fonteneau, a former executive for a French perfume company, yearned to combine his flair for fun and his desire to advance marine science. With backing from the Bacardi Family Foundation, he outfitted a catamaran with plenty of technological equipment and, it seems, bottles of rum. For most of two years beginning in 2000, he and his crew trolled the Caribbean, recording the underwater sounds of fish like groupers and porgies, helping set up global-positioning devices on volcanic slopes and hunting for prehistoric carvings in marine caves. Billed as a ''scientific adventure,'' ''Murmurs From the Deep'' falls short on both counts. Several of Fonteneau's adventures have to do with waiting for paperwork or working out. The biggest drama involves a couple of armed guards forcing his boat out of harbor. His explanations of the science behind his exploits are tantalizing, but frustratingly brief. ''Unfortunately, I knew nothing of ethology, the study of animal behavior,'' he writes. ''Nonetheless, I was able to observe many things that I found extraordinarily interesting, for example, detecting the fishes' territory and guessing at their various defensive reactions.'' He tells us what he did on a given day, but rarely engages us.</p>
        <p>THE GRANDEST OF LIVES: Eye to Eye With Whales. By Douglas H. Chadwick. (Sierra Club, $24.95.) Once upon a time, men speared baby gray whales in order to lure in their mammoth mothers to slaughter. Nowadays, tourists pay millions of dollars annually to coo over the calves and applaud the giants of the sea. What happened in between was the near demise of many species of whale, followed by gee-whiz research into their social and physiological complexity. Some of the science is ''woo-woo,'' says Chadwick, a journalist who has written extensively on the subject for National Geographic and other magazines, but the legitimate work is revelatory.</p>
        <p>Observing five species across the world -- even swimming among them -- Chadwick tallies up fact after fact in a breezy and straightforward style. Minke whale breath smells like over-steamed broccoli. Orca whales have overtaken polar bears as ''the most toxified mammals in the Arctic,'' and possibly the world. In Vancouver, you can tune in to live whale recordings on ORCA-FM. An infant blue whale gains 9 to 10 pounds an hour. The blue whale's major food source, krill, has declined 80 percent in the Southern Ocean, probably a direct effect of global warming. Chadwick found that the whales seemed to be observing him as much as the other way around, and writes at length about their legendary intelligence. ''No matter how much of what we think passes back and forth during such meetings turns out to be yet another example of humans' boundless capacity for fooling themselves, the chance to visit whales that go out of their way to visit you is still a tremendous privilege.''</p>
        <p>Florence Williams is a contributing editor for Outside magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Florence Williams is a contributing editor for Outside magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
