<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecting to Nature (and Not by Google)</title>
    <meta content="09ctoutdoor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1753399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Department (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rell, M Jodi (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braccidiferro, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4DD1E30F93AA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecting to Nature (and Not by Google)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL BRACCIDIFERRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Braccidiferro, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Gov M Jodi Rell, in effort to encourage children and their families to head outdoors to enjoy unorganized play, has launched campaign called No Child Left Inside; campaign, led by State Department of Environmental Protection, includes hiring of more park and forest workers, having state-park passes available at public libraries and sponsoring programs at eight state parks; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARCY KLATTENBERG recalled a class in which she introduced kindergartners to live snakes and turtles, and one child then asked a question about the animals.</p>
        <p>''I can't remember exactly what the child's question was, but I remember that the teacher gasped,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARCY KLATTENBERG recalled a class in which she introduced kindergartners to live snakes and turtles, and one child then asked a question about the animals.</p>
        <p>''I can't remember exactly what the child's question was, but I remember that the teacher gasped,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The teacher later told Ms. Klattenberg that the child, who was autistic, had never previously asked a teacher a question directly related to the lesson being taught at the time.</p>
        <p>''That's what nature can do,'' said Ms. Klattenberg, a naturalist who works for Regional School District 13's Outdoor Education Center. The district encompasses Durham and Middlefield.</p>
        <p>Ms. Klattenberg said that in her classes she sees examples of the inspiration children get from nature. Environmentalists and educators throughout the state are now working to extend such experiences to more children.</p>
        <p>The increasing affinity of children for the Internet, iPods, video games and television -- combined with adults' rising fears about traffic, diseases and strangers -- have caused some children to disconnect from nature, they said. This in turn contributes to problems such as childhood obesity, behavioral conditions and mental illnesses.</p>
        <p>In an effort to encourage children and their families to head outdoors to enjoy unorganized play, Gov. M. Jodi Rell last month launched a state campaign called No Child Left Inside.</p>
        <p>Led by the State Department of Environmental Protection, the campaign encourages families to go outdoors. It includes the hiring of more park and forest workers, having state-park passes available at public libraries and sponsoring a game called ''The Great Park Pursuit'' that will include programs at eight state parks.</p>
        <p>''Our effort is to build the next generation of environmental stewards,'' Gina McCarthy, D.E.P. commissioner, said. ''This is not just about the parks. This is about what kind of generation we're bringing up.''</p>
        <p>While No Child Left Inside incorporates specific games and activities, Ms. McCarthy said she hoped it also touches off deeper environmental discussions and helps re-establish connections to nature.</p>
        <p>''Anti-litter and other big environmental programs largely grew from college campuses,'' she said, referring to environmental campaigns in the 1970's. ''Now, the environment is not on the list of cool things to do as a college student. If we don't have kids who really care and understand about the natural world, we'll have a hard time getting them to consider problems such as global warming.''</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Outdoor and Environmental Education Association annual conference that was held last month at Quinnipiac University in Hamden also was called No Child Left Inside and explored the importance of connecting children with nature. Richard Louv, who wrote the book, ''Last Child in the Woods: Saving Our Children from Nature-Deficit Disorder,'' is keynote speaker for the conference.</p>
        <p>''I'm not declaring nature-deficit as a known medical condition,'' he said about the term used in his book. ''For all of human history, kids went outdoors and played or worked outdoors. The change is happening now so quickly, it needs to be examined.''</p>
        <p>He said some researchers found that test scores improved when children were encouraged to write in outdoor classrooms and other researchers found that children played more cooperatively in natural settings than on artificial playgrounds, he said.</p>
        <p>''If we really want to help kids, we need to get them out into nature,'' he said. ''I read this huge newspaper insert on childhood obesity and it never recommended getting kids outside to play.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Louv loosely defines nature: It can be as simple as a clump of bushes near an apartment complex driveway, a vacant urban lot, a city park or a small group of trees bordering a suburban subdivision. The most beneficial outdoor play is spontaneous, rather than the organized sports that take up many children's outdoor time, he said.</p>
        <p>A prime emphasis of the state's No Child Left Inside campaign is simple outdoor activities. Thomas Morrissey, D.E.P. bureau chief for outdoor recreation, said the Great Park Pursuit game promotes activities such as nature walks, scavenger hunts and fishing contests at eight state parks.</p>
        <p>The first day of Great Park Pursuit is at Dinosaur State Park in Rocky Hill on May 6. Families can follow the game in other parks at www.nochildleftinside.org, he said.</p>
        <p>''Kids need to get pushed outdoors a little bit now,'' he said. ''My own kids prefer to play with computers.''</p>
        <p>Those who work at keeping kids connected to nature said they witness more and more children who do not regularly play and explore outdoors.</p>
        <p>''I was talking to third graders today about spring peepers,'' said Kim Hargrave, education director of the Denison nature center in Mystic, referring to the tree frogs. ''I could tell there were some children who had experienced the sound of peepers and others who looked at me like I had four heads.''</p>
        <p>Melissa Hammel of New London and her son, Ben, 10, have long participated in outdoor programs at the Denison nature center. She said they volunteer at the center and sometimes he invites a friend. Some of his friends have expressed trepidation about being outdoors at the center.</p>
        <p>''But once you get them out there, before you know it, they are running around enjoying themselves, too,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCarthy of the D.E.P. said her daughter once invited a friend to join their family on a hike, and the friend's mother would not let her daughter go.</p>
        <p>''I asked the mother why and she said she had heard there were snakes at the park,'' Ms. McCarthy said. ''I told her that was one of the reasons we went there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
