<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Snows of Yesteryear? Today They're in Machinery</title>
    <meta content="06towns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/06/nyregion/06towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont/Killington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Killington (Vt)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DB1631F935A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Snows of Yesteryear? Today They're in Machinery</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Snows of Yesteryear? Today They’re in Machinery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>WINDHAM, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was sort of like the good old days as Nelson Armlin, mountain manager at the Windham Mountain ski resort in the Catskills, plowed his way toward the top of the 1,600-foot hill in a 15-ton Pisten Bully snow groomer.</p>
        <p>A blizzard pelted the windshield, and here and there were snow piles six feet high, which will be spread into two feet of eminently skiable base and powder when Windham reopens today. The ski center opened 10 days later than scheduled last month because of warm weather, then had to shut back down during last week's grand finale to our preternaturally warm, endless autumn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those who depend on cold weather and snow for their livelihood, the weather-watching is a good deal less casual than it is for the rest of us.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was sort of like the good old days as Nelson Armlin, mountain manager at the Windham Mountain ski resort in the Catskills, plowed his way toward the top of the 1,600-foot hill in a 15-ton Pisten Bully snow groomer.</p>
        <p>A blizzard pelted the windshield, and here and there were snow piles six feet high, which will be spread into two feet of eminently skiable base and powder when Windham reopens today. The ski center opened 10 days later than scheduled last month because of warm weather, then had to shut back down during last week's grand finale to our preternaturally warm, endless autumn.</p>
        <p>Of course all the snow was machine-made, its blizzard the result of an incessant frigid hiss from three kinds of blowers going full tilt on 11 of Windham's 46 trails. The other 35 had grass poking out from a dainty white frosting. And the good old days doesn't mean a time when a resort like Windham could depend on real blizzards. ''Natural snow for us is icing on the cake,'' said Tim Woods, Windham's general manager. ''It's great when we get it, but we don't rely on it.''</p>
        <p>No, the good old days redefined is when it's cold enough to make snow in December, not last week's nightmare -- 60 degrees, torrential rain, thunder, lightning -- a ski resort catastrophe that shut down virtually everything in the Northeast, even mighty Killington in Vermont, where people assume they can ski from early November well into May.</p>
        <p>People have their own informal index of climate change, but for those who depend on cold weather and snow for their livelihood, the weather-watching is a good deal less casual than it is for the rest of us. So it turns out there will be good early-December skiing at Windham, at least on the trails that will open today. But of the many canaries in the mineshaft of climate change, some of the most attentive are people like Mr. Armlin and Mr. Woods, who watch the skies from October to March and are increasingly worried by what they see.</p>
        <p>Consider Mr. Woods, 41, who virtually grew up on snow -- the Woods Valley ski area that his parents owned in Westernville, north of Rome, N.Y. The center operated on natural snow from 1964 to 1980, but a few disastrous winters made it clear that something more reliable was needed. The center has had snow made by machine ever since, and could not have survived otherwise. Mr. Woods watches each too-mild winter at Windham and gets the same queasy feeling.</p>
        <p>''The weather's definitely changed,'' he said. ''Every year now when we sit down at budget time, instead of planning cash flow for what would have been a typical year 10 years ago, we basically plan for having a couple of thaws at the very worst possible moments. In the past, the law of averages might say that 3 of 10 years would be lousy. Now our challenge is to remain profitable, figuring that possibly 6 or 7 of 10 will be.''</p>
        <p>For Windham and other ski areas that means, first of all, investing in the best snowmaking equipment possible, and upgrading it every year to make more snow than ever, as quickly as possible in warmer temperatures. It means diversifying -- a new skating rink, snowboard attractions that can operate on less snow, a fancy new restaurant. There's consideration of a spa. ''We're trying to hedge our bets against winter being milder and shorter,'' Mr. Woods said, ''looking to give people things to do if the skiing isn't great.''</p>
        <p>Of course, making snow on a mountain doesn't make one an expert on climate change. Mr. Armlin, who has the challenge of providing what nature doesn't, would like to think that it's part of a long natural cycle that will swing back the other way. ''Maybe I'm just being optimistic,'' he said. ''Optimism can get you a long way in the ski industry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Woods, who cites oxygen isotope levels and core samples from the polar ice caps, and what is happening with glaciers, is less sanguine. ''There's no question the general trend'' is higher temperatures, he said. ''It's pretty terrifying stuff.''</p>
        <p>So will there be skiing in the Catskills in 50 years? And 100 years?</p>
        <p>Sure, he figures. There are places that now make snow, or ice that's sort of like snow, in June and July. Indoor ski attractions are cropping up in Los Angeles, England, Scotland and Dubai.</p>
        <p>That might not be winter as we know it. But our recent winters haven't been, either.</p>
        <p>So the skiing will be in pretty good shape today at Windham, five days after the temperature hit 60 degrees. Whether the planet is doing as well is a much more complicated discussion.</p>
        <p>OUR TOWNS E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
