<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Nimby Extends Offshore</title>
    <meta content="29liwind" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/29/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/29liwind.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDA103FF93AA15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Nimby Extends Offshore</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When Nimby Extends Offshore</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO they have to be there?</p>
        <p>The mounting opposition to proposals for an offshore ''wind farm'' of 40 giant turbines to supplement Long Island's electricity supply has less to do with the technology itself than with the planned location: a few miles off Jones Beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A planned wind farm is generating opposition along the South Shore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO they have to be there?</p>
        <p>The mounting opposition to proposals for an offshore ''wind farm'' of 40 giant turbines to supplement Long Island's electricity supply has less to do with the technology itself than with the planned location: a few miles off Jones Beach.</p>
        <p>In fact, many critics of the plan agree with its proponents that Long Island needs renewable sources of electricity to reduce its dependence on power plants burning fossil fuels, and that with oil and gas prices so high, wind turbines may yet become economically viable and environmentally benign.</p>
        <p>But they're ugly, say opponents, led by a group called the Jones Beach Ad Hoc Committee. The turbines, with fan blades that would sweep to 443 feet above sea level at their highest point, would be an intrusive blight on the jewels of the Island's recreational and tourist attractions, its ocean beaches, where millions of people flock for sun, surf and unfettered ocean views, they say.</p>
        <p>Sentiment among South Shore residents ran heavily against the project at two public forums attended by representatives of the project's sponsors, the Long Island Power Authority and FPL Energy, a major developer of wind energy projects that is part of an energy conglomerate once known as Florida Power and Light.</p>
        <p>More than 300 people turned out for the most recent forum, held in Massapequa on Jan. 19. Opposition leaders said they hoped to organize more forums in other South Shore towns in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>A similar story is playing out in Massachusetts, where a large offshore wind farm proposed for Nantucket Sound has attracted growing opposition, much of it from people who ordinarily favor development of renewable energy, like the Kennedy family. By all means develop wind energy, these opponents say, but do it somewhere else.</p>
        <p>The question then becomes, where?</p>
        <p>Could Long Island's wind project be built someplace less aesthetically objectionable -- say, the Babylon town landfill, or Plum Island, or someplace far enough out to sea to be invisible from shore?</p>
        <p>The first thing a wind energy project needs is wind, steady and moderately strong. The turbines provide no power in a calm, of course, or when winds exceed about 50 miles an hour, for safety reasons. They need average winds of at least 18 miles an hour to be productive enough to be worth building, LIPA officials say, and reach peak output at about 30 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>The winds on the Long Island Sound are too light and variable, they say, and many suggested sites on land do not make the meteorological cut, either, including most of Plum Island.</p>
        <p>Wind turbines also need a lot of room. The blades are almost 180 feet long and sweep around a central mechanism 260 feet above the ground or water. They must be placed far enough apart not to interfere with one another. Daniel Zaweski, the power authority's wind-turbine project manager, said that building the proposed 40-turbine project on land would require about 1,600 open, contiguous acres of land.</p>
        <p>No such site is available on the Island, he said, except in the protected core of the Long Island pine barrens, a state preserve.</p>
        <p>The spinning turbine blades are a potential hazard to anything in flight, so they must be kept away from the approaches to airports and from flyways of migratory birds.</p>
        <p>That factor has kept wind turbines off Plum Island before. According to Larry Orluskie, a spokesman for the Department of Homeland Security, which now controls the 740-acre island, the government considered placing several smaller wind turbines on the island in 1998 to help power the animal disease laboratory there. The plan was abandoned because of the threat to migratory birds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orluskie said that any talk of a commercial-scale wind farm on Plum Island was premature and that it remained closed to the public and to any development other than the lab.</p>
        <p>The 212-foot-high Babylon town landfill, another alternative site some opponents mention, also appears to be ruled out. Vanessa Baird-Streeter, a spokeswoman for the town, said that the Federal Aviation Administration found the landfill to be too close to Republic Airport for tall structures like the turbines to be built there.</p>
        <p>Getting the wind power to customers is another issue, with distance an important factor in the cost. Mr. Zaweski of the power authority said that dozens of miles of major transmission line upgrades would be needed to connect turbines on, say, Plum Island or Gardiners Island with Long Island's power grid.</p>
        <p>Attaching wind turbines to existing tall structures on the Island, like cellular phone towers or the Jones Beach tower, would also run afoul of engineering or aesthetic constraints, engineers and utility executives said.</p>
        <p>That leaves the waters off the South Shore as the only practical place to put the turbines, power authority officials say.</p>
        <p>Under the LIPA-FPL proposal, the nearest turbine to shore would be 3.6 miles out in the ocean, visible from the beach in much of Nassau and western Suffolk. Each turbine tower would rest on a single piling about 18 feet in diameter, sunk between 70 and 120 feet into the ocean floor. A nine-mile transmission line would connect the wind farm to a substation in the Amityville-Massapequa area.</p>
        <p>Moving the turbines farther offshore would diminish their visual impact and give them even better wind conditions. But Mr. Zaweski said that it would also put them in major shipping lanes, where they are not allowed for safety reasons, or in water deeper than 100 feet, where the cost to build them and connect them to shore would be prohibitively high.</p>
        <p>Still, project opponents said the power authority was rushing ahead with the project, which would be the nation's first offshore wind farm, even as new technology that would make it economically feasible to place the turbines out of sight of land was advancing.</p>
        <p>FPL, which is completing its design for the project, would build the turbines and sell their output, up to about 3.6 megawatts per turbine in ideal weather, to the power authority under a 20-year contract. The average output of 140 megawatts would be enough to power about 44,000 homes.</p>
        <p>The power authority and FPL hope to complete construction in 2008; the cost has yet to be determined, but is sure to run into the hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>A federal law enacted in August shifted responsibility for licensing offshore wind turbines to the Minerals Management Service, an agency of the Interior Department, from the Army Corps of Engineers. The agency also reviews applications for offshore oil platforms.</p>
        <p>Though the agency is expected to speed up the approval process, it is still devising guidelines for evaluating wind turbine projects, including the LIPA-FPL project and the other major proposal before it, the 130-turbine complex planned for a 24-square-mile area of Nantucket Sound and known as Cape Wind.</p>
        <p>LIPA said its project would also require state permits.</p>
        <p>In Massachusetts, Senator Edward M. Kennedy; his nephew Robert F. Kennedy Jr., who is an environmental lawyer and professor at Pace University Law School; and many Cape Cod residents have spoken out against Cape Wind.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Kennedy has said that private energy companies should no more put wind turbines in Nantucket Sound than in Yosemite National Park. Mr. Kennedy said he had no position on wind turbines off Jones Beach.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the Long Island project say the same logic Mr. Kennedy applied to Cape Wind should apply to Jones Beach. They argue that the cost would be too high and the power yield too small to justify the visual desecration of a national treasure.</p>
        <p>They also say the computer images LIPA and FPL have displayed understate how large the turbines will loom in the view from shore.</p>
        <p>Philip Healey of Massapequa, a co-chairman of Save Jones Beach, said LIPA was ''playing on the fact that people don't really understand distance over the open water.'' Though the turbines would be more than three miles out, ''the horizon is 11 to 12 miles,'' he said. ''People think three miles is far away, but over the open ocean, it's right in front of you.''</p>
        <p>Still, the project has broad support among environmental groups, and adamant backing from LIPA's chairman, Richard M. Kessel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel, who lives in Merrick, said he believed there was strong public support, even on the South Shore, for a project that would begin to wean Long Island off fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>''We have got to start somewhere,'' Mr. Kessel said. ''And if we can't put these up, it signals we are going to continue to be captives to the oil barons. I understand that there is an aesthetic issue, but there are pros and cons to whatever we do.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of the turbines said it was inconsistent for environmental groups to oppose the Broadwater Energy plan for a $700 million floating natural gas plant in the Long Island Sound but support the wind turbines.</p>
        <p>''They don't want to industrialize the sound, but they're in favor of industrializing the ocean,'' said Richard Schary of North Bellmore, who is opposed to the turbines. ''And if they were trying to pick the worst place on Long Island to site these things, they've done it. You are ruining Jones Beach and it's known all over the world, it's our most famous landmark.''</p>
        <p>Wendy Gibson, a spokeswoman for the New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation, which operates Jones Beach, said in an e-mail message that the state would ''certainly assess the potential impact'' of the project on the beach, which was added last year to the National Register of Historic Places. But she said that her office supported development of renewable energy and had not joined in objections to the plan.</p>
        <p>Adrienne Esposito, the executive director of Citizens Campaign for the Environment in Farmingdale, rejected the comparison between the Broadwater project and the wind turbines.</p>
        <p>''One blows up, one doesn't,'' she said. ''One is a terrorist risk, and the other isn't. One gives us clean, safe, domestically produced energy, the other gives us dirty, dangerous foreign energy once again.''</p>
        <p>The wind project faces opposition on other grounds besides the view from the beach. Wally D'Amato, the president of the Nassau Shores Association in Massapequa and an opponent of the turbines, questioned whether they were a wise energy investment given their cost.</p>
        <p>''They don't make sense,'' Mr. D'Amato said. ''If anything, we have to get started with the solar again.''</p>
        <p>But Gordian Raacke, the executive director of Renewable Energy Long Island, a Bridgehampton advocacy group, said solar energy, while promising, held little immediate prospect of matching wind power on a large scale.</p>
        <p>''Solar panels are great,'' he said, adding that his home was one of about 600 on the Island equipped with solar installations. ''But given their relatively high cost, we won't see 44,000 homes equipped with solar panels by 2008.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Raacke noted that use of wind energy was growing rapidly around the world, and that several European nations had made great strides in using it. Denmark gets almost one-fifth of its national electricity supply from wind, and turbines have become a common sight in Mr. Raacke's native Germany, which produces more than 16,000 megawatts of wind power, one-third of the world total.</p>
        <p>Opponents warn that the 40-turbine LIPA-FPL project may be just the first of many that would eventually line the whole South Shore. ''This could be the beginning of the end for our shoreline,'' said Mr. Schary of North Bellmore.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kessel said LIPA had no plans now for more turbines. ''That's for a future LIPA to look at,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
