<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Outlines Plan to Cut Oil Consumption</title>
    <meta content="24hillary" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/24/nyregion/24hillary.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1764079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Press Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DE113EF937A15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Outlines Plan to Cut Oil Consumption</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clinton Outlines Proposal to Cut Oil Consumption</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States Sen Hillary Rodham Clinton, who is running for re-election in New York State, addresses National Press Club; proposes series of measures designed to cut nation's foreign oil dependence; holds that proposals would cut US comsumption of foreign oil in half by 2025; describes plan component that would encourage oil companies to create $50 billion fund to support alternate fuels research; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton proposed a series of measures on Tuesday to cut the nation's consumption of foreign oil in half by 2025, including encouraging the development of alternative forms of energy.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who is up for re-election in New York this year and who is viewed as a likely presidential candidate in 2008, also said that America's dependence on foreign oil was posing a grave threat to the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton proposed a series of measures to cut the nation's consumption of foreign oil in half by 2025.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton proposed a series of measures on Tuesday to cut the nation's consumption of foreign oil in half by 2025, including encouraging the development of alternative forms of energy.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who is up for re-election in New York this year and who is viewed as a likely presidential candidate in 2008, also said that America's dependence on foreign oil was posing a grave threat to the nation.</p>
        <p>''Our present system of energy is weakening our national security, hurting our pocketbooks, violating our common values and threatening our children's future,'' she said in a speech at the National Press Club. ''Right now, instead of national security dictating our energy policy, our failed energy policy dictates our national security.''</p>
        <p>With the energy sector under fire as soaring prices for crude oil and natural gas push industry profits to record highs, Mrs. Clinton proposed imposing a two-year fee on oil companies to create a $50 billion fund to help spur research into new conservation approaches and alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>''Now, the oil companies would have the option,'' she said, referring to the fees companies would be required to pay. ''They wouldn't have to invest if they did this themselves, if they began making investments in bio-fuels, in other forms of renewable energy, in new, cleaner refining capacity, solar, wind. If they did it themselves, then they wouldn't have to pay into the fund.''</p>
        <p>Republicans quickly criticized Mrs. Clinton, seizing on one aspect of her proposal: a call for expanding the use of ethanol. Republicans noted that she has frequently opposed measures that would have done just that. They accused her of political opportunism, noting that ethanol is a corn-based fuel additive that is popular in Iowa, the state whose caucus plays a crucial role in the presidential race. ''Senator Clinton's energy policy consists of a unique balancing act involving partisanship, political pandering and yesterday's mistakes,'' said Tracey Schmitt, a spokeswoman for the Republican National Committee.</p>
        <p>Philippe Reines, a spokesman for Mrs. Clinton, said in response, ''If unfounded partisan attacks could somehow be harnessed as an energy source, then this White House could claim to actually have a plan to address our country's energy needs.''</p>
        <p>During her appearance, Mrs. Clinton also addressed the war in Iraq. Asked whether she regretted voting to authorize President Bush to use military force in Iraq, she said, ''I regret the way the president used the authority he was given.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, whose support for the war has caused her problems with the liberal wing of her party, also suggested that the time was nearing for Iraq to take a larger role in its own security.</p>
        <p>But the senator, whose speech was interrupted by two antiwar protesters, stopped short of calling for a troop withdrawal.</p>
        <p>''I think that once there is a fully established Iraqi government,'' she said, ''we have to make it very clear that the Iraqis are responsible for their own security, the Iraqis are responsible for ending the sectarian violence.''</p>
        <p>''I don't think we are there quite yet,'' she added. ''But we should be there soon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
