<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Says Nation Lacks Energy Policy</title>
    <meta content="14rudy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/14/nyregion/14rudy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1768971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4D71331F937A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Says Nation Lacks Energy Policy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani Says Nation Lacks Energy Policy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK HEALY; Conrad Mulcahy contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Healy, Patrick</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Challenging fellow Republicans in Washington, former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that the Bush administration lacked an energy policy and that greater reliance on nuclear power, ethanol-based fuels and hybrid vehicles was more realistic than President Bush's goal of independence from foreign energy sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, who is considering a presidential bid in 2008, did not criticize Mr. Bush by name, and some of his ideas reflected Republican orthodoxy about increasing energy supply. Yet in a speech to conservative thinkers from the Manhattan Institute for Policy Research, Mr. Giuliani implicitly accused the White House of doing little to expand energy sources. Afterward, too, he expressed concern about global warming, saying that ''everyone accepts the fact that it's happening and it has an impact.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said a greater reliance on nuclear power and ethanol-based fuels was more realistic than President Bush's plan of reducing dependence on foreign energy sources.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Challenging fellow Republicans in Washington, former Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that the Bush administration lacked an energy policy and that greater reliance on nuclear power, ethanol-based fuels and hybrid vehicles was more realistic than President Bush's goal of independence from foreign energy sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, who is considering a presidential bid in 2008, did not criticize Mr. Bush by name, and some of his ideas reflected Republican orthodoxy about increasing energy supply. Yet in a speech to conservative thinkers from the Manhattan Institute for Policy Research, Mr. Giuliani implicitly accused the White House of doing little to expand energy sources. Afterward, too, he expressed concern about global warming, saying that ''everyone accepts the fact that it's happening and it has an impact.''</p>
        <p>''I can't imagine how you can achieve anything in government without a plan,'' he said in his remarks at the Princeton Club, referring to the nation's long-range energy needs. ''This is an area where we haven't had a plan in a very, very long time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, whose consulting firm, Giuliani Partners, advises energy companies and a liquefied natural gas project on Long Island Sound, called for easing and hastening permits for more nuclear power plants, natural gas ports and oil refineries. He said the nation could not afford another 30 years without a far-sighted energy policy.</p>
        <p>''We've been sitting there for a generation, just hoping there'll be some magic solution,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His comments come as some of the leading Democratic presidential prospects, including Al Gore and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, have been highlighting environmental issues, particularly the need to move away from dependence on fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Asked by an audience member what his advice to Mr. Bush would be, Mr. Giuliani called for fixed numerical goals and deadlines to build more nuclear power plants, encourage use of hybrid cars, and increase the supply of ethanol and other resources. Ethanol is an economic priority in Iowa, which has the nation's first presidential caucuses.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Giuliani has spoken recently on immigration and terrorism, he has mostly avoided giving presidential-style addresses this year. He said yesterday he would make a decision about a presidential bid after the 2006 elections.</p>
        <p>Yet he also did not fuss yesterday when an audience member asked how he would approach education as president. He spoke forcefully in favor of school choice and vouchers, saying education was ''a major civil rights issue'' in cities that had failing public schools.</p>
        <p>He did not explicitly propose a program of federal vouchers, but he said he would emphasize the idea in office and urge local districts to ''go to a choice system and break up the monopoly'' of public school education.</p>
        <p>Many political analysts regard Mr. Giuliani as a popular national political figure who would nevertheless be a long shot for the presidency, because he would face real challenges winning the Republican Party nomination. He supports abortion rights, gay civil unions and gun control measures, three positions that are unacceptable to many Republican primary voters.</p>
        <p>Political advisers to Mr. Giuliani say they believe that national security, terrorism, the economy, and perhaps Iraq will dominate the 2008 race, and that Mr. Giuliani is in the Republican mainstream on those issues. They also note that, in large part because of leadership after the 9/11 attacks, Mr. Giuliani is in first or second place in most public opinion polls surveying the 2008 race; only Senator John McCain tends to do as well.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Giuliani has applied his political muscle to raising money for Republican candidates for state and federal office, as well as defending President Bush's Iraq strategy and tax cuts.</p>
        <p>Given how rarely he has publicly disagreed with the White House, Mr. Giuliani's complaints about federal energy policy were intriguing.</p>
        <p>During the speech -- in which he relied on a slide show instead of prepared remarks and rambled at times -- Mr. Giuliani was relentlessly skeptical while also being short on specific solutions. He questioned the notion of energy independence that Mr. Bush and many Democrats have floated, yet his own alternatives were fairly general.</p>
        <p>''The idea of energy independence for the United States is maybe the wrong paradigm -- I don't know if we can ever be independent,'' he said. But he added, ''I think you can be independent by being diversified,'' arguing that Americans needed to depend more on home-grown fuels and energy resources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani repeatedly touted hybrid cars and said they needed ''to be heavily supported and effectively moved forward.'' (It did not escape reporters' attention, however, that a large Escalade was idling outside for him.)</p>
        <p>At the same time, he sounded a skeptical note about energy conservation, saying it was ''helpful but not really very, very effective'' in dealing with energy. He said decreasing demand could harm the economy, though he did not go into detail.</p>
        <p>Energy analysts said that while his remarks had a theatrical call-to-arms quality, many of his ideas were familiar.</p>
        <p>''There's not a lot here that's different from what Dick Cheney would say,'' said Ashok Gupta, director of the air and energy program at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group in New York.</p>
        <p>''Giuliani is focused so much on supply, instead of dealing with demand and energy efficiency and conservation,'' Mr. Gupta said. ''To pass anything through Congress, you need a balanced message.''</p>
        <p>Yet Myron Magnet, an audience member and the editor of City Journal, a Manhattan Institute publication, praised Mr. Giuliani's plan as ''absolutely coherent.''</p>
        <p>Later yesterday, Mr. Giuliani was host of a reception at the Four Seasons to raise $2 million for his political action committee, Solutions America.</p>
        <p>It drew 200 donors and friends, as well as Ken Mehlman, chairman of the Republican National Committee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
