<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: Sept. 15 - Sept. 21</title>
    <meta content="15thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6DB1231F936A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="14444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: Sept. 15 - Sept. 21</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' Previews start on Monday. Opens on Oct. 5. The legendary musical about Broadway gypsies returns with Charlotte d'Amboise and Michael Berresse (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JOHN FERGUSON' In previews; opens on Sept. 25. The Mint Theater unearths St. John Ervine's gritty piece of realism from 1919 about a pious farmer who can't make his mortgage payments (2:20). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 315-0231.</p>
        <p>'FRINGE NYC ENCORES' Through Sept. 24. Ten hits from the New York International Fringe Festival return for a second run at two theaters. Shows include ''Billy the Mime,'' ''Walmartopia,'' ''Broken Hands,'' ''Danny Boy,'' ''Open House'' and others. The 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street, East Village; Lion Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'HEARTBREAK HOUSE' Previews start today. Opens on Oct 11. Roundabout revives Shaw's drama with a superb cast of theater pros, including Swoosie Kurtz, Philip Bosco and the always elegant Byron Jennings (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'JAY JOHNSON: THE TWO AND ONLY' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Sept 28. The ventriloquist, whose solo show ran at the Atlantic in 2004, talks about his mentor and career (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LOSING LOUIE' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on Oct. 12. Mark Linn-Baker and Matthew Arkin star in Simon Mendes da Costa's family comedy, which spans 50 years. Jerry Zaks directs this West End transfer. (2:10). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'NIXON'S NIXON' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Oct 4. In this revival Russell Lees imagines the conversation between Nixon and Kissinger the night before Nixon resigned. Jim Simpson directs (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE PAIN AND THE ITCH' In previews; opens on Thursday. Bruce Norris's drama about a dysfunctional family arrives in New York after a successful run at the Steppenwolf Theater in Chicago. Jayne Houdyshell and Reg Rogers star (2:15). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE PERSIANS' Runs tomorrow through Wednesday. Politics have made this relatively obscure ancient drama, about an arrogant ruler who rushes to war, suddenly popular. This latest production is by the National Theater of Greece (2:00). City Center, 100 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212.</p>
        <p>'RICHARD II' In previews; opens on Sunday. Michael Cumpsty, who played Hamlet at the Classic Stage Company last season, returns to that downtown theater to headline Shakespeare's history play about a deeply flawed king (2:15). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'SUBURBIA' In previews; opens on Sept. 28. Eric Bogosian revamps his tale of youthful angst and alienation for the new millennium. Jo Bonney directs (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'SISTERS' In previews; opens on Sunday. Anna Manahan, who won a Tony in 1998 for her performance in ''The Beauty Queen of Leenane,'' portrays two sisters in Declan Hassett's play set in the rural Ireland of the 1950's (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SOUTHERN COMFORTS' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Oct. 4. Judith Ivey directs this drama about a widow and a widower who meet late in life. Presented by Primary Stages (2:00). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' This eager and amiably scattershot satire of celebrity memoirs and Broadway musicals, starring the immodestly modest Mr. Short, arrives a little late to the table for such parody to taste fresh. With serviceably tuneful songs by Scott Wittman and Marc Shaiman (of ''Hairspray'' fame) (1:45). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Constantine Maroulis, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FOGGY BOTTOM' James Armstrong's comedy about a Washingtonian who seduces women by promising them green cards has a nice sense of the ridiculous, but sometimes the action is unbelievable, even by the standards of farce (2:00). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444.(Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GARDEL: THE MUSICAL' A standard-issue bio-musical about the tango legend Carlos Gardel that wallows in melodrama (1:30). Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, (212) 225-9920. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'IT GOES WITHOUT SAYING' Bill Bowers's zestful, endearing one-man show is about his life as a mime, an actor and a gay boy growing up in Montana (1:15). Rattlestick Playwrights Theater, 224 Waverly Place, off Seventh Avenue South, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SEVEN GUITARS' (2:45). Life and death dance cheek to cheek in this fine new revival of August Wilson's drama from 1996. Directed by Ruben Santiago-Hudson, and acted with absorbing restraint and immediacy, this is a truly life-size production, which means it is big indeed (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A miniskirted, go-go-booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the showroom of a Carnival cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'I  3/5sheart 4/5 KANT' Keith Urban's nimble, knowing one-act is about four women (a graduate student, a heroin addict, a depressive and a bombing victim), the men in their lives and the little humiliations and unexpected certainties of daily existence (1:10). Linhart Theater at 440 Studios, 440 Lafayette Street, near Astor Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'ABSINTHE' Think Cirque du Soleil as channeled through ''Rocky Horror'' and painted by George Grosz. Part cabaret, part circus, ''Absinthe'' aims for a kind of seedy decadence that's mingled with the simple, aw-shucks wonder of knife-jugglers, sword-swallowers and a man creating constructions out of soap bubbles. It's the main event at the Spiegeltent, a vintage European tradition visiting South Street Seaport this summer (1:30). Spiegeltent, at the former Fulton Fish Market site, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'REVEREND BILLY AND THE CHURCH OF STOP-SHOPPING' Reverend Billy (a k a the performance artist Bill Talen) struts and preaches his way across the Spiegeltent stage accompanied by a choir and a fine seven-piece band. Radical political theater has rarely been more thoughtful or fun (1:30). Spiegeltent, at the former Fulton Fish Market site, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). 2005 New World Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans. (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY OF VALENTYNE AND ORSON' The director and puppet maker Ralph Lee makes a royal steed out of a hobby horse and a ferocious bear from cardboard and baseball mitts in this enchanting tale of a young prince and the ''wild man'' he befriends (1:05). The outdoor garden of the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 929-4777; closes on Sunday. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'ACCEPTED' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A clever slacker and his oddball crew invent a phony college in this passable example of that oxymoronic genre, the Hollywood comedy about sticking it to the man. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 (2:20)minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BARNYARD' (PG, 88 minutes) The barnyard animals in this crude 3-D animation walk, talk and party down like human beings. Way too often the male ''cows,'' as the film calls them, also flash their udders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEERFEST' (R, 110 minutes) In ''Beerfest,'' a gaseous celebration of binge drinking and family honor, the five comedians known collectively as Broken Lizard head for Munich and an underground beer-guzzling contest. Best viewed while sloshed, the movie is idiotic, tasteless and irrepressibly good-natured: in other words, a frat-house classic. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BOYNTON BEACH CLUB' (No rating, 104 minutes) A fast-paced romantic comedy about frisky 60-something residents of a Florida ''active adult'' community, ''Boynton Beach Club'' is a rose-colored fantasy about aging that has just enough credibility to make you care about its characters and wish them merrily on their way. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'A CANTOR'S TALE' (No rating, 95 minutes) Jovial, rotund and prone to impromptu bursts of song, Cantor Jacob Mendelson has dedicated his life to preserving the Jewish liturgical music known as chazzanut. Erik Greenberg Anjou's charming documentary is more concerned with singing praises than arguing over orthodoxies, while interviews with an uncharacteristically subdued Jackie Mason and Alan Dershowitz suggest an awareness that they're in the presence of greater voices. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt-putt-putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Celestine Prophecy' (PG, 100 minutes) A delectable fusion of New Age babble and luridly bad filmmaking based on the best-selling book by James Redfield. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE COVENANT' (PG-13, 97 minutes) The director Renny Harlin proves that ''Exorcist: The Beginning'' was not the nadir of his career with this thriller about boy witches fending off a nefarious transfer student. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'CRANK' (R, 83 minutes) A poisoned hit man rampages in Los Angeles, doling revenge on his nemesis and misanthropy on all. Basically a broken-down retread of ''Speed,'' with Jason Stratham as the bus. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'CROSSOVER' (PG-13, 95 minutes) Bling is bad, and friends are good in this story of temptation, rivalry and cheerleaders, set in the world of Detroit street basketball. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DESCENT' (R, 99 minutes) A total horror freakout from the British writer and director Neil Marshall about six women on a caving expedition who meet their fears and some scary monsters, too. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'FACTOTUM' (R, 94 minutes) Matt Dillon goes deep to play Henry Chinaski, the familiar alter ego of the great Charles Bukowski, who survived countless benders, brawls, rejection slips, crazy women and soul-killing jobs. The Norwegian filmmaker Bent Hamer directed. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'Half Nelson' (R, 107 minutes) In their beautiful bummer about the relationship between a white teacher (Ryan Gosling) and a black student (Shareeka Epps), the gifted young director Ryan Fleck and his writing partner, Anna Boden, offer a lament for the radical fires of the 1960's and a suggestion for life and politics after the new left. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'HOLLYWOODLAND' (R, 126 minutes) A fictional look at the life and downward-spiraling times of George Reeves, the man who played Superman on television and is here played by a fine Ben Affleck. Allen Coulter directs Paul Bernbaum's screenplay, which features a dead-end parallel plot about a detective (Adrien Brody). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HOW TO EAT FRIED WORMS' (PG, 98 minutes) The worms go in, the worms go out, but mostly the worms go into the frying pan in Bob Dolman's engaging and yucky adaptation of the Thomas Rockwell book. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HOUSE OF SAND' (R, 115 minutes, in Portuguese) Beautifully shot in a sandy, remote corner of northern Brazil, this film tells the story of three generations of women, all of them played by Fernanda Montenegro and Fernanda Torres, mother and daughter in real life and two of the national treasures of Brazilian cinema. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'IDLEWILD' (R, 120 minutes) André Benjamin and Antwan A. Patton, a k a André 3000 and Big Boi of OutKast, play friends living and sometimes singing in Depression-era Georgia. The joint doesn't jump; it twitches and stumbles. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE ILLUSIONIST' (PG-13, 109 minutes) This film tells the story of Eisenheim (Edward Norton), a fictional conjurer who enraptured Viennese audiences in 1900 with his supernatural magic shows. A terrific yarn, it rouses your slumbering belief in the miraculous. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'INVINCIBLE' (PG, 99 minutes) The latest addition to the Disney stable of sports-underdog movies, ''Invincible'' is the true story of Vince Papale (Mark Wahlberg), a substitute teacher and part-time bartender, who in 1976 realizes his dream of playing for the Philadelphia Eagles. While Disney piles on the uplift, the director and cinematographer, Ericson Core, counters the story's predictably inspirational trajectory with close attention to historical detail and blue-collar hardship. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'LASSIE' (PG, 100 minutes) Everything old is new again in the 11th film about the beloved pooch with the I.Q. of a grad student and the instincts of a boomerang. Blissfully restored to the period and location of Eric Knight's original novel -- pre-World War Britain -- the movie balances humor and pathos with old-fashioned charm and not a trace of satire. Progressive adults may balk at the film's ultimate capitulation to the power of patronage, but tykes will just be happy that Lassie has come home once more to the multiplex where she belongs. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LE PETIT LIEUTENANT' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) A tough, satisfying drama from Xavier Beauvois about an alcoholic Parisian detective (Nathalie Baye) and the young lieutenant (Jalil Lespert) who comes under her wing. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MAN PUSH CART' (No rating, 87 minutes) The Sisyphean daily grind of a Pakistani immigrant who sells coffee, doughnuts and bagels from a cart in Midtown Manhattan is an exemplary work of independent filmmaking carried out on a shoestring. At its best, it suggests an American ''Bicycle Thief.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. Three intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MUTUAL APPRECIATION' (No rating, 110 minutes)Andrew Bujalski's wonderful independent film about friendship in the modern world looks like something that came out of a time capsule, but there's nothing dusty about it. Shot on expressively grainy black-and-white celluloid, it is the sort of unassuming discovery that could suffer from too much big love, and while it won't save or change your life, it may make your heart swell. Its aim is modest and true. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PAPER DOLLS' (No rating, 80 minutes, in Hebrew, English and Tagalog) A small, touching documentary about Phillipine transexuals living in Israel. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PROTECTOR' (R, 84 minutes, in Thai) A provincial Thai warrior rampages through Australia, busting skulls and shouting, ''You stole my elephants!'' in this infectious B-movie smackdown. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'QUEENS' (No rating, 107 minutes, in Spanish) A dithering but generous Spanish farce, ''Queens'' follows the forthcoming nuptials of three gay couples by focusing on their overbearing mothers. While the sons dance, bicker and fret over antiques, the mamas express their discomfort with the wedding plans by seducing inappropriate men. Despite obvious nods to Pedro Almodóvar, ''Queens'' is notable only for its unadulterated worship of middle-aged women. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'QUINCEAÑERA' (R, 90 minutes) This portrait of a Mexican-American family living in a Latino neighborhood of Los Angeles is as smart and warm-hearted an exploration of an upwardly mobile immigrant culture as American independent cinema has produced. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'RED DOORS' (No rating, 90 minutes) This agreeable, lightweight movie, written and directed by Georgia Lee, turns the malaises of a dysfunctional suburban Chinese-American family into a bittersweet farce that teeters between cheeky humor and surface pathos. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'RIDING ALONE FOR THOUSANDS OF MILES' (PG, 108 minutes, in Mandarin) Zhang Yimou takes a pause between marital-arts extravaganzas with this simple, affecting melodrama about a mournful Japanese patriarch on an odyssey through rural China. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Satellite' (No rating, 100 minutes) In this captivating romantic fairy tale for grown-ups, made on a shoestring, two young lovers in New York flee yuppie hell into a life of petty theft. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Scoop' (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SHERRYBABY' (No rating, 96 minutes) This story of a young woman, just released from prison, trying to put her life back together, is somewhat predictable, but well observed by Laurie Collyer, the writer and director, and beautifully realized by Maggie Gyllenhaal in the principal role. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SNAKES ON A PLANE' (R, 105 minutes) Snakes + plane + Samuel L. Jackson. David R. Ellis provides the fine B-movie-style direction, while Mr. Jackson supplies the cool and his trademark epithet. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STEP UP' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Ever since Kevin Bacon's rebellious hips ignited a small-town uproar in ''Footloose,'' the modern high school romance has placed a premium on rhythm. In ''Step Up'' a rough Baltimore kid (Channing Tatum), armed only with a killer smile and hip-hop moves, falls for a classically trained dancer (Jenna Dewan). Bland but likable, the movie fashions social equality from big musical numbers. If ballet and hip-hop can coexist, it asks, why can't we all be friends? (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'TALLADEGA NIGHTS: THE BALLAD OF RICKY BOBBY' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Fast, fun and silly, with Will Ferrell as a Nascar driver, Sacha Baron Cohen as his nemesis, and a new course record for product placements per gallon. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French New Wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THIS FILM IS NOT YET RATED' (No rating, 97 minutes) Kirby Dick, with the help of a private detective, investigates the mysterious workings of the Motion Picture Association of America, a highly secretive, deeply irrational organization with enormous influence over what we see -- and don't see -- on movie screens. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'TRUST THE MAN' (R, 101 minutes) A strained, flatulent relationship comedy about two couples, from the writer and director Bart Freundlich. With Julianne Moore, David Duchovny, Maggie Gyllenhaal and Billy Crudup. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'ANDY WARHOL: A DOCUMENTARY FILM' (No rating, 4 hours with an intermission) Ric Burns's absorbing four-hour critical biography of this seminal Pop artist is devoted to the proposition that Warhol was the greatest artist of the second half of the 20th century, as Picasso was in the first. It makes a mostly persuasive, highly entertaining case for that claim. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'the WICKER MAN' (PG-13, 106 minutes) In remaking a 1973 British horror classic, Neil LaBute once again demonstrates his misogyny and, worse, his technical incompetence. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'WORLD TRADE CENTER' (PG-13, 129 minutes) From Oliver Stone, a return to the emotions of 9/11. Powerful and almost unbearably moving. (Scott)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ANOTHER WAVE: GLOBAL QUEER CINEMA (Through tomorrow) The Museum of Modern Art's festival of gay films and shorts from more than two dozen countries ends this weekend with one feature and a series of five short films. ''Memento Mori: Films by Jim Hubbard'' includes a work in progress about the history of Act Up; Anahi Berneri's drama ''A Year Without Love'' (2005), from Argentina, is the story of a young writer with AIDS who learns to eroticize his pain. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>THE FABULOUS ART OF SURVIVAL: LECH KOWALSKI (Through Sept. 26) BAMcinématek's two-week tribute to the punk filmmaker Mr. Kowalski, which began on Tuesday, continues next week with two films. ''Gringo'' (1985) is a gritty, partly documentary portrait of a New York heroin addict. ''On Hitler's Highway'' (2002), a documentary road movie, includes a side trip to Auschwitz. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, www.bam.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE'S LANGUAGE OF FILM  (Through Sept. 27) BAMcinématek's series honoring Mr. Carrière, the prolific French screenwriter, continues this weekend with three films. ''The Outside Man'' (1972) stars Jean-Louis Trintignant as a French hit man on a job in Los Angeles. ''Belle de Jour'' (1967) stars Catherine Deneuve as a bored newlywed who takes a day job at a tasteful brothel. Volker Schlöndorff's Oscar-winning allegory ''The Tin Drum'' (1979) was adapted by Mr. Carrière (and a few co-writers) from Günter Grass's novel. BAM Rose Cinemas (see above); $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Monday) The IFC Center's five-month series honoring Akira Kurosawa comes to a close with ''High and Low'' (1963), a drama about a businessman in a devastating moral quandary over the kidnapping of a child. Toshiro Mifune stars, of course. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, www.ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>MIZOGUCHI (Through Sept. 21) Film Forum's two-week series honoring the Japanese master director Kenzi Mizoguchi (1898-1956) continues this weekend with two features. ''Sansho the Bailiff'' (1954) is his acclaimed drama about an exiled governor whose children are sold into slavery. ''The Life of Oharu'' (1952), about a samurai's daughter in love with a man beneath her class, was Toshiro Mifune's only Mizoguchi film. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8112, www.filmforum.com; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE SUPPORTING CAST: AS BRIGHT AS THE STARS (Through Sept. 26) Symphony Space's series of double features honoring the names well below the title continues this weekend with two 1954 dramas. Hitchcock's ''Rear Window'' features Thelma Ritter, Raymond Burr and Wendell Corey. The supporting cast of Elia Kazan's ''On the Waterfront'' includes Karl Malden, Lee J. Cobb and Rod Steiger. 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* NATACHA ATLAS (Tonight) Musical globalism often works best on the dance floor, where traditions from anywhere, new or old, can mingle and flirt as long as the beat is good. Ms. Atlas, born in Belgium to Jewish and Muslim parents, with family ties to Morocco and Egypt, is a natural multiculturalist. In a strong, sensuous voice, and with the help of bubbly electronic beats, she brings North African, Middle Eastern and Indian styles together; her newest album, ''Mish Maoul'' (Mantra), throws in some rap too. She opens the World Music Institute's season with an all-acoustic ensemble. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536, symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $32; $15 for students. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES AZNAVOUR (Monday and Tuesday) This legendary French-Armenian music hall entertainer, now 82, is an ageless, sad-faced everyman who brings the skills of a great character actor and mime to his spellbinding performance. This is his farewell tour. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $44.50 to $154.50. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BALKAN BEAT BOX (Tomorrow) Suddenly Balkan brass bands are the hottest sound in dance music. This New York group plays a combustible mix of big, bright horns and high-energy electronic beats. With Sway Machinery. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAN BERN, HAMELL ON TRIAL (Tomorrow night) With a nasal sing-speak that recalls the young Bob Dylan, Dan Bern offers smooth folk-rock and a world-weary cynicism. (''There's nothing innocent about a newborn babe,'' he sings, ''that a few years here can't cure.'') Ed Hamell, a k a Hamell on Trial, is a manic and sharp-tongued comedian-raconteur who is merciless toward his acoustic guitar. At 7, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $18.50 in advance, $20 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CITIZEN COPE (Tonight) Clarence Greenwood, a k a Citizen Cope, is the umpteenth singer-songwriter to use hip-hop beats and drawled, rap-sung vocals in search of novelty. At 6:30, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRUCE COCKBURN (Tomorrow) One of Canada's most revered songwriters since the 1970's, Bruce Cockburn sings about love, politics and spiritual yearning, all tied together by his thoughtful, sympathetic voice and guitar playing that's a quietly virtuosic melding of folk and jazz. At 8 p.m., the Concert Hall at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $30 and $35. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DASTAN ENSEMBLE WITH PARISSA (Tomorrow) Parissa, a leading traditional singer from Iran, has a repertory that includes both classical Persian music and Sufi songs; she is one of very few female performers from Iran who tour internationally. She will be joining the Dastan Ensemble, which plays classical Persian music: an improvisatory tradition that builds from meditative melodies to dazzling virtuosity. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536, symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $35 and $40; $15 for students. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ELYSIAN FIELDS (Thursday) Elysian Fields plays languid songs that sound best in a late-night haze, as Jennifer Charles's breathy voice hints at decadence and vulnerability, while Oren Bloedow wraps the songs in slinky, deadpan guitar. At 8:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503, tonicnyc.com; $12 in advance, $15 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>GOLDEN SMOG (Sunday) Even heartsick alt-country has its celebrity supergroups. Golden Smog includes Jeff Tweedy of Wilco, Dan Murphy of Soul Asylum, Gary Louris and Marc Perlman of the Jayhawks, and Kraig Johnson of Run Westy Run. With Tim O'Reagan. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE KILLS (Tonight) Part White Stripes and part Sonic Youth, the Kills play a barbed and bluesy garage rock that sounds always on the brink of collapse. With Effi Priest and Mr. J. Carpenter. At 8, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOHN LEGEND (Monday) This 27-year-old singer of passionate and stylish R&amp;B, who won three Grammys this year, offers a preview of songs from his new album, due next month. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAN MAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) Man Man, from Philadelphia, follows the expressive gutter cabaret of Tom Waits into a kinetic chaos that has more than a little Captain Beefheart in it. Formed three years ago, the band quickly acquired a high profile for its energetic live shows. Tonight at 9:30, with Coyote and Tiny Masters of Today, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. Tomorrow at midnight, Spiegeltent, Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK SALSA FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) The 31st annual installment of this essential Latin concert features Willie Colón, Cheo Feliciano, Tito Rojas, Lalo Rodríguez, Ismael Miranda, Tito Nieves, Cano Estremera, Tony Vega, Michael Stuart, Jose Alberto (El Canario), Adalberto Santiago, Yomo Toro and the return of Domingo Quiñones. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $45 to $110. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PINK MARTINI (Monday and Tuesday) The Hollywood lounge band gone global, this 12-or-so-piece ensemble from Portland, Ore., follows a glamour jet stream from Rio to Havana to Paris. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, the-townhall-nyc.org; $25 and $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SANTANA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Using rock instruments to supercharge a salsa band -- or is it vice versa? -- the guitarist Carlos Santana came up with a prototype three decades ago for Latin rock, jazz rock, world music and far-reaching jam bands. He clutters his albums with guest singers to make a run at the pop charts, but on tour the guests are out of the way, and the music soars. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; Sunday at 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; $20 to $75. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TORTOISE (Sunday) After 16 years as the one followed by all other post-rock, neo-jazz-fusion bands (and there are quite a few), Tortoise, from Chicago, still has some surprises. This year it released an album with Bonnie (Prince) Billy that includes truly idiosyncratic versions of songs by Elton John, Devo and Bruce Springsteen, as well as a retrospective box set that remains entrancing through all four discs. With the Notekillers. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE WHO (Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Down to just Pete Townshend and Roger Daltrey (with hired guns), the Who has made an ambitious play by recording its first new album in 24 years, to be released next month. But the real surprise is just how good it is; based on ''Wire &amp; Glass,'' the teaser EP released in Britain this summer, it is a throwback to the expansive, rock-opera brilliance of ''Quadrophenia.'' With Peeping Tom. Monday and Tuesday at 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $56.50 to $256.50. Thursday at 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; $48.75 to $258.75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WIDESPREAD PANIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) Widespread Panic, from Georgia, leans toward the Southern-rock side of the Allman Brothers-Grateful Dead axis, but like any good jam band, it's flexible and then some. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>HORACEE ARNOLD QUARTET/TRINITY (Tonight) The New York chapter of the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians presents one of its sporadic concerts, featuring a quartet led by the drummer Horacee Arnold, with Marcus Strickland on saxophones, Orrin Evans on piano and Buster Williams on bass; and Trinity, a collective consisting of the saxophonist Patience Higgins, the Hammond B-3 organist Lonnie Gasparini, the percussionist Thurman Baker and the poet Mikhail Horowitz. At 8, Community Church of New York, 40 East 35th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-4988, aacm-newyork.com; $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>OMER AVITAL GROUP (Wednesday) The bassist Omer Avital has a new live album, ''The Ancient Art of Giving,'' on Smalls Records, which delivers the compact jolt of his chamberlike compositions. For this one-night stand at Smalls, he leads a group including the trumpeter Avishai Cohen, the tenor and soprano saxophonist Joel Frahm, the pianist Jason Lindner and the drummer Johnathan Blake. At 10:30 p.m. and midnight, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, fatcatjazz.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE BAD PLUS/JASON MORAN AND THE BANDWAGON (Through Sunday) Two trios, both plumbing the territory between melodic abstraction and gut-level groove, both featuring an erudite pianist and both involving a turbulent and unconventional drummer. This may turn out to be the most thought-provoking double bill to come under a mainstream banner this fall. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY BANG (Tonight and tomorrow night) As a violinist and composer, Mr. Bang favors astringency and formal tension, qualities that come naturally to the musicians he has assembled here: the trumpeter Ted Daniels, the saxophonist and flutist James Spaulding, the pianist Andrew Bemkey, the bassist Todd Nicholson and the drummer Newman Taylor Baker. At 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE'S HARD CELL (Tonight) With his recent album ''Feign'' (Screwgun), the alto saxophonist and composer Tim Berne advanced a volatile yet groove-oriented approach to experimental chamber music. Here he reconvenes Hard Cell, the fine ensemble from that album: David Torn on guitar and electronics, Craig Taborn on keyboards and Tom Rainey on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN COLTRANE 80TH-BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Wednesday and Thursday) Countless tenor saxophonists have adapted John Coltrane's sound and style over the years, but few have personalized it more effectively than Joe Lovano, who headlines here with the pianist Steve Kuhn, who briefly worked with Coltrane, and the serious-minded rhythm section of Lonnie Plaxico, bassist, and Andrew Cyrille, drummer. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* COLTRANE FESTIVAL (Through tomorrow) John Coltrane would have turned 80 this month, and Jazz at Lincoln Center has decided to open its new season with a celebration of his music. At the Rose Theater Wynton Marsalis is leading the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra in a concert featuring arrangements of Coltrane themes. In the Allen Room the vocalist Kevin Mahogany and the saxophonist Todd Williams will pay tribute to Coltrane's album with the baritone Johnny Hartman, with Eric Reed on piano, Reginald Veal on bass and Herlin Riley on drums. The Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra performs at 8 p.m., and Kevin Mahogany performs at 7:30 and 9:30, at Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50 for the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra; $67.50 for Kevin Mahogany. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIET COKE WOMEN IN JAZZ FESTIVAL (Through Thursday) This monthlong festival of female jazz artists continues with the beloved pianist and radio personality Marian McPartland, with her trio (through Sunday); the singer Datevik Hovanesian (7:30 p.m. on Monday) and the saxophonist Tia Fuller, with her quintet (9:30 p.m. on Monday); and the pianist and vocalist Eliane Elias, performing music from her recent RCA Victor album, ''Around the City'' (Tuesday through Thursday). There are also good offerings during the club's after-hours sets, including the singers Andrea Wolper (tonight) and Kate McGarry (tomorrow). At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, or $10 for after-hours sets, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARK DRESSER AND RAZ MESINAI (Thursday) Mr. Dresser is a bassist with a full range of experimental techniques; Mr. Mesinai is a composer with a broad palette of electronic devices. Their duo performance should be a study in texture, but not without a sense of pulse. At 8:30 p.m., Roulette at Location One, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FATBLASTER (Thursday) A confab of adventurous trumpeters, representing three overlapping levels of experience: Ralph Alessi, an accomplished leader and educator; Shane Endsley, a prominent up-and-comer; and Eric Biondo, who seems most likely to have been behind the band's prankish name. The saxophonist Alex Hamlin and the guitarist Ryan Ferreira round out the group, without adding an ounce of flab. At 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FESTIVAL OF NEW TRUMPET MUSIC (Through Thursday) This laudably expansive survey of contemporary trumpeters, organized by Dave Douglas, begins its fourth season this weekend, and one of its most promising events happens early. Tomorrow night at Merkin Concert Hall, Mr. Douglas and another trumpeter, Roy Campbell, revisit the music of Don Cherry, notably including the 1966 album ''Symphony for Improvisers.'' Next week the action moves to the Jazz Standard, with a parade of players including Avishai Cohen, Jeremy Pelt and Keyon Harrold (on Tuesday); Taylor Ho Bynum and Stephen Haynes (Wednesday); and Ingrid Jensen and Lina Allemano (Thursday). Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 ($30 in advance). The festival continues on Tuesday at the Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. For a full festival schedule, visit fontmusic.org. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FULTON STREET BEAT FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) This free outdoor concert features three different perspectives on New Orleans rhythm, each compelling in its own fashion. Second-line groove drives the Jambalaya Brass Band, which plays at 1 p.m., while funk and soul provide the steam for a quintet led by the trumpeter Maurice Brown, at 2:30. New Orleans jazz, in both modern and traditional iterations, animates the final group, led by the saxophonist and clarinetist Victor Goines. At 1 p.m., Fulton Street Mall, DeKalb Avenue at Albee Square West, Downtown Brooklyn, (718) 488-8200, fultonstreet.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GAME PIECE FOR STRING INSTRUMENTS (Tomorrow) Suzanne Fiol, the artistic director of the Issue Project Room on the Gowanus Canal in Brooklyn, conducts this experimental happening for more than a dozen improvisers, including Miya Masaoka on koto, Jane Scarpantoni on cello and Lucian Buscemi on bass. At 8 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TOM HARRELL-VINCENT HERRING QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Tom Harrell, a tersely lyrical trumpeter, and Vincent Herring, a voluble alto saxophonist, share a preference for high-octane post-bop. Their ensemble includes Nat Adderley Jr. on piano, Richie Goods on bass and Quincy Davis on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRED HERSCH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Fred Hersch is a pianist associated with solo piano recitals, including a week's worth at the Village Vanguard early this year. He returns to the Vanguard with the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Nasheet Waits, his regular rhythm partners; together they apply a rigorous yet elastic interpretative style to originals and standards alike. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GLENN KOTCHE AND NELS CLINE/JENNY LIN (Monday) Mr. Kotche, who plays drums with the rock band Wilco, has an engrossing new solo percussion album (''Mobile,'' on Nonesuch) that reinforces his new-music credentials. Mr. Cline, Wilco's lead guitarist, also has a new album (''New Monastery,'' on Cryptogramophone), which thoughtfully investigates the compositions of the jazz pianist Andrew Hill. Performing as a duo here, Mr. Kotche and Mr. Cline are likely to incorporate extended techniques and artful atonality; it makes a certain sense that they will follow a piano recital by Jenny Lin, with a repertory including Ligeti, Shostakovich and Elliott Sharp, who will join her on electronics. At 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 877-0685, wordlessmusic.org; $19.99. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN 60TH-BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Liebman, an incantatory saxophonist and flutist working in the idiom established by John Coltrane, caps off his birthday celebration at Birdland with a big band directed by the saxophonist and educator Gunnar Mossblad (tonight) and a tribute to the music of Coltrane and Miles Davis, featuring Ravi Coltrane on tenor and soprano saxophone, Randy Brecker on trumpet, Phil Markowitz on piano, Cecil McBee on bass and Adam Nussbaum on drums (tomorrow). At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEN PEPLOWSKI (Tonight) Mr. Peplowski is a clarinetist dedicated to traditional jazz, a preference that should not be mistaken for a limitation. He also plays tenor saxophone and surrounds himself with other accomplished musicians, like the bassist Sean Smith and the percussionist Chuck Reed, who play here. At 7 p.m., Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NED ROTHENBERG (Tonight) Mr. Rothenberg is a saxophonist, clarinetist, flutist and composer with a penchant for insistent frictions, as he demonstrates on a strong new album, ''The Fell Clutch'' (Animul). Tonight he celebrates his 50th birthday with a roll call of more than a dozen fellow experimentalists, including the saxophonists John Zorn and Marty Ehrlich, the guitarist Marc Ribot and the bassists Jerome Harris and Stomu Takeishi. On Tuesday Mr. Rothenberg leads a smaller coterie: Mark Dresser on bass, Kazu Uchihashi on guitar and Susie Ibarra on drums. Tonight at 8, Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; sold out. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KERMIT RUFFINS AND THE BARBECUE SWINGERS (Sunday) The tradition of New Orleans-bred trumpeter-entertainers has an especially robust representative in Mr. Ruffins, who appears here with his celebrated working band. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY SCOTT (Through Sunday) Mr. Scott's piercing voice and achingly emotional style are rightfully enshrined in the annals of songbook interpretation. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUCIANA SOUZA: BRAZILIAN DUOS (Through Sunday) Luciana Souza, a vocalist raised in São Paolo, has made some of her most beguiling music in this format, joined by a lone acoustic guitar. Romero Lubambo, the guitarist, is more than an accompanist; providing intricate counterpoint and rhythmic undertow, he is Ms. Souza's equal. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* MCCOY TYNER TRIO WITH PHAROAH SANDERS (Tuesday through Thursday) The pianist McCoy Tyner and the tenor saxophonist Pharoah Sanders are indelibly associated with the 1960's output of John Coltrane, though each enjoyed a productive period as a solo artist in the 70's and beyond. They combine their searching energies here in a quartet with Charnett Moffett on bass and Eric Kamau Gravatt on drums. (Through Sept. 24.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WILLIAMSBURG JAZZ FESTIVAL (Through Sunday) This grass-roots affair, which briefly subsumes a small swatch of Brooklyn with modern jazz, hits full stride this weekend, with notable performances at Laila Lounge (the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, tonight at 11); Galapagos (the cellist Dana Leong, tomorrow night at 8, and the trumpeter Maurice Brown, tomorrow night at 10); and Rose Live Music (the singer Gretchen Parlato, tomorrow night at 10, and the pianist Jason Lindner, tomorrow night at midnight). The festival closes, oddly enough, on the Lower East Side, at Tonic (the saxophonist Sabir Mateen with the festival's organizer, the trumpeter Jesse Selengut, Sunday at 8 p.m.). Times and locations vary; full schedule, fullcircledrumming.com/wjazzfestival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON/CHRISTIAN SCOTT  (Wednesday) A jazz singer by training and temperament, Ms. Wilson takes obvious pleasure in a boundless, genre-blind repertory, a tendency borne out vividly on her most recent album, ''Thunderbird'' (Blue Note). It's a recording with the seamless sensibility of a modern studio concoction, but Ms. Wilson, often a deeply magnetic performer, should be able to carry it off in concert. The opener is Christian Scott, an excellent young trumpeter whose recent debut, ''Rewind That'' (Concord), signaled his intention to explore a modern funk-based sound. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $45 and $35. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEPHANE WREMBEL (Sunday) Virtually every Sunday night for the last three years, Mr. Wrembel, a French guitarist, has been playing the music of the Gypsy guitar hero Django Reinhardt at Barbès. This Sunday Mr. Wrembel marks his anniversary at the club with three sets, loosely tracing the chronological arc of Mr. Reinhardt's career. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Updated to the years around World War I, this is one of New York City Opera's best productions, and some fine young talents should make this run of it worth hearing. Shu-Ying Li, the Mimi, has shown a really striking soprano on past occasions; James Valenti, her Rodolfo, was a promising Met Council winner in 2002; Elisabeth Caballero, the Musetta, made a very good City Opera debut last season; and Daniel Mobbs, the Marcello, has been proving himself reliably at Caramoor and elsewhere for several years. George Manahan, the company's music director, conducts. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'CARMEN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Rinat Shaham, who made her company debut as Zerlina, is a small singer for Carmen; but worse, City Opera's production seems to have veiled her spark, rendering her a mere stereotype in a stiff performance. Her Don José, Mark Duffin, has warm lower notes and a pressed, often flat sound on top; the Escamillo is Adrian Gans, who was too nervous to be judged at his company debut in the role. The high point is Latonia Moore, a radiant-voiced Micaëla who seems to belong to a world apart from this rather pedestrian production. Ari Pelto conducts, a little woodenly but competently enough. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $130. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE MARRIAGE OF FIGARO' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Diminutive and beloved, the sexaguanarian Amato Opera proves that, in opera, tradition and devotion can prevail over quality. It's remarkable that all of Mozart's characters can fit on the theater's tiny stage. Saturday at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Solo piano recitals frame the week's offerings at New York's favorite floating concert hall. Tonight Steven Lubin offers three Beethoven sonatas (including the ''Waldstein'' and ''Appassionata''); next Thursday Steven Beck juxtaposes Bach and Shostakovich preludes and fugues, then plays some Mozart sonatas. In between, the Quartetto di Cremona shows its stuff in two varied programs tomorrow and Sunday, featuring Shostakovich, Schubert, Mozart, Schumann and Vacchi. Tonight, tomorrow night and Thursday night at 7:30; Sunday afternoon at 4; Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65 tonight and Thursday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Thursday) The season begins with a generous program ranging as far back as Vivaldi and Mendelssohn and as far forward as Bright Sheng, Leon Kirchner and Nicholas Maw. Pieces by John Ireland and Arthur Bliss will also show up. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788; $28 to $70. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'THE CONSTITUTION: A SECULAR ORATORIO' (Tonight and Thursday) Those who celebrate Constitution Day should not miss the composer Ben Yarmolinsky's word-for-word setting of large swatches of the Constitution, modeled on a Handelian oratorio but with echoes of musical styles from classical to American folk. This being Constitution Week, it will have two separate performances. Tonight at 8, General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen, 20 West 44th Street, (212) 921-1767; $15; $10 for members; $5 for students. Thursday afternoon at 12:15, Gould Memorial Library Auditorium, Bronx Community College, University Avenue and 181st Street, (718) 289-5100; free. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* ENSEMBLE XX.JAHRHUNDERT (Monday through Wednesday) Call it old new music: the 20th-Century Ensemble has been devoted to contemporary and modern works since the conductor Peter Burwik founded it in 1971. At the Austrian Cultural Forum's continuing ''Mostly Modern'' festival, the ensemble brackets its three performances next week with works of the Second Viennese School (Webern and Berg) and émigré composers (Eisler and Krenek); these surround a range of works by living composers, many Austrian, and many unfamiliar to New York audiences. At 8 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, Ext. 222; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TAKA KIGAWA (Tonight) This enterprising young Japanese pianist tackles another tough program, this time with Bach, Beethoven and Boulez. At 8, Greenwich House Music School, 46 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 242-4770; $10. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'A NIGHT AT THE OPERA' (Tuesday) A host of singers from the New York City Opera's past and present, including Samuel Ramey and Carol Vaness, will parade their vocal talents across the stage of the New York State Theater. At 7:30 p.m., Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $27 to $135. (Holland)</p>
        <p>ORPHEUS CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Monday) The Metropolitan Museum opens its music season with hearty, traditional fare in the Great Hall. Janine Jansen and Eriko Sato are violinists in Bach's D-minor Double Concerto and will also be busy in excerpts from Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons.'' At 7 p.m., (212) 570-3949; $60. (Holland)</p>
        <p>St. LUKE'S CHAMBER ENSEMBLE (Wednesday) In its first full season of concert programs after the impressive expansion of its campus, the Morgan Library and Museum gets things going at its intimate new Gilder Lehrman Hall with the St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble. Booking this popular ensemble into this 280-seat hall has proved a smart move. There are two series with three programs each; the first is officially sold out, and there is limited availability for the second. The programs begin with a concert of Baroque works by Bach, Vivaldi and Handel. At 7:30 p.m., 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 594-6100; $35; $25 for members.(Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* SILK ROAD ENSEMBLE YOUNG ARTISTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) As part of the continuing Silk Road Project, Yo-Yo Ma's mission to bring together musicians of diverse cultures from the ancient international Silk Road trade routes, Carnegie Hall and the Weill Music Institute present four programs this weekend that grew out of a ''Tradition and Innovation'' workshop for composers and young artists. The concerts offer works by emerging composers like the 28-year-old Angel Lam, who was born in Hong Kong and now lives in Baltimore, and by established figures like Dmitri Yanov-Yanovsky, one of the leading voices in Uzbekistan, as well as the acclaimed Argentine composer of Eastern European Jewish heritage, Osvaldo Golijov. The specific works on each of the four programs will be announced at the concerts, chosen from composers including Gabriela Lena Frank, Christopher Adler, Kayhan Kalhor, Jeeyoung Kim, Evan Ziporyn and others. Tomorrow and Sunday at 4 and 8 p.m., Zankel Hall, (212) 247-7800; $15. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ARTICHOKE DANCE COMPANY (Tonight through Sunday) The company will perform Lynn Neumann's new ''I Am Nothing (Without You): Rounds 1-6,'' which involves the audience in determining the structure of each performance of the piece, which can be seen from perspectives that include the sidewalk outside. Through Sept. 24. At 8 p.m., Center for Remembering and Sharing, 123 Fourth Avenue, between 12th and 13th Streets, East Village, (212) 352-3101; $15; $12 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARIANA BEKERMAN DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Created by Mariana Bekerman and the guest choreographers Keiko Fujii and Rebekah J. Kennedy, ''Taro'' tells the story of a woman whose world is transformed when she encounters an evil spirit. (Through Sept. 24.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN ADULT RECORDER CHOIR (Tonight and tomorrow night) The name of this group turns out to be literal description rather than whimsy: a self-described ad hoc group of some 60 performers trying to recapture the joys of those painful recorder lessons at school during ''In the Closet, Again, Again.'' The choreographer Beth Gill and the composer Chris Peck thought this up. From 7 to 10, the Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $15, or pay what you will for Queens residents. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT MILLER: NEW BALLET CHOREOGRAPHERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ashley Bouder, Maria Kowrowski and Wendy Whelan are among the wonderful dancers from the New York City Ballet and American Ballet Theater Studio Company who will perform in this enticing program of new ballets to live music by the Masada String Trio. The choreographers are the City Ballet soloists Edwaard Liang and Tom Gold, and the former Ballet Theater dancer Brian Reeder. Mr. Gold is the wild card here -- the other two have budding reputations as promising ballet choreographers -- but he is in very good company. At 8, Miller Theater at Columbia University, 116th Street and Broadway, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799; $35; Columbia students, $7; non-Columbia students and Guggenheim Museum members, $21. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>DANCENOW/NYC FESTIVAL: DANCEMOPOLITAN @ JOE'S PUB (Tonight and tomorrow night) In the festival's closing performances, Leigh Garrett serves as host for two different programs featuring 19 choreographers and companies. At 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200 or joespub.org. Information about participants: dancenownyc.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BILL T. JONES/ARNIE ZANE DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) Bill T. Jones's ''Another Evening: I Bow Down,'' which had its premiere earlier this year, is back in the New York area forone night. The music is by Mr. Jones's regular collaborator Daniel Bernard Roumain, performing with the Bronx hard-core band Regain the Heart Condemned. An actor, Andrea Smith, performs alongside 10 dancers. Mr. Jones appears too -- always worth the trip. At 8 p.m., Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Rutgers University, 85 George Street, New Brunswick, N.J., (732) 932-7511, masongross.rutgers.edu; $15 to $25. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* LARRY KEIGWIN (Sunday and Tuesday) An expanded version of Mr. Keigwin's amusing contribution to the first (2005) installment of Dancing in the Streets's ''Dance Charrette,'' complete with dancers gabbing into cellphones and walking on walls. Sunday at 1:30 and 5 p.m., and Tuesday at 6 p.m., rain or shine, Tobacco Warehouse, Empire-Fulton Ferry State Park section of the Brooklyn Bridge Park, Dumbo, Brooklyn, (212) 635-3505 or dancinginthestreets.org; free. The Sunday performances will flank a walking tour of the Brooklyn Bridge Park area at 2:30 p.m., sponsored by the Municipal Art Society, (212) 935-2075; $15. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NOÉMIE LAFRANCE'S 'AGORA II' (Tonight, tomorrow, Wedneday and Thursday) Apparently Ms. LaFrance, a tireless artistic explorer of public space, is a glutton for punishment. Having moved bureaucratic mountains last year to stage ''Agora'' in the enormous (and empty) McCarren Park pool in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, she now has a sequel, ''Agora II,'' which incorporates a number of guest companies and is described in the publicity materials as ''a choreographic game for 1,000 bodies.'' Good luck to them all. At 8 p.m. (arrive by 7:30), McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs and Bayard Streets, (718) 388-6309 or sensproduction.org; $20 and $30. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>LIVE ARTS FESTIVAL AND PHILLY FRINGE (Tonight and tomorrow night) These festivals wind to an end this weekend at theater spaces throughout downtown Philadelphia with several intriguing-sounding events, among them Jeb Kreager's ''Contest,'' which explores an American cultural preoccupation with competition and victory in choreography that draws on marching bands, platoon drilling and group singing. Information and reservations: (215) 413-1318 or livearts-fringe.org; $10, $15 and $20, depending on the event, with some shows free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CONSTANZA MACRAS (Thursday) This choreographer, born in Argentina, trained in New York and Amsterdam and based in Berlin, will perform with her 18-member international company, Dorky Park, in the United States premiere of ''Back to the Present,'' originally presented over four hours in 2003 in an abandoned Berlin department store. (Through Sept. 23.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for artists, members, students and 65+. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>MÉXICO NOW @ DNA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mexican choreographers living in New York City will present their work. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MÉXICO NOW: Danscores by OFELIA LORET DE MOLA (Tonight and tomorrow night) Although ''Aktun Spukil,'' the title of a work by the choreographer Ofelia Loret de Mola, sounds like one of the crew on the Starship Enterprise, it is, according to Mexican lore, the name of a group of caves in which the Maya took shelter during battles. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; students, $12. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>ELISA MONTE DANCE (Tuesday through Thursday) This company, well known to New Yorkers, opens the Joyce's fall season with a weeklong celebration of its 25th anniversary. Elisa Monte has created a new piece, ''Hardwood,'' and has revived some older works for the occasion. At 7.30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $40; Joyce members, $30. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>JEREMY NELSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson will continue his investigation into physical turbulence in his new ''Mean Piece,'' a work for six dancers, with sets and costumes by Luis Lara Malvacias. At 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BAROQUE DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Last month Mark Morris offered a new piece called ''Mozart Dances,'' set to Mozart piano music, none composed for dance. Now Catherine Turocky's historical-dance company and its affiliated early-music group Concert Royal will present their own program, ''Mozart Dances!'' Here the music will again include a piano concerto, but also Mozart's actual dance music for ''Les Petits Riens'' and the opera ''Idomeneo.'' At 8 p.m., Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, (212) 307-4100 or (212) 355-6160 or nybaroquedance.org; $30. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>ELKA RINDFLEISCH (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) In Ms. Rindfleisch's new ''Damage,'' six dancers will struggle through a spreading inner disturbance to rock music by Chris Woltmann, performed live. They end up nowhere, the choreographer says, or in places of unexpected tenderness in a set that fills the performance space with small alternative spaces. At 8 p.m., Wallabout Studio, 50 Taaffe Place, between Flushing and Park Avenues, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (917) 251-4561 or rindfleischdance.com; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>T E A DANCE COMPANY (Tonight through Sunday night) Sahar Javedani and Ella Ben-Aharon, the troupe's resident choreographers, will present their new ''Gardens,'' which probes the notion of the pre-apple Eden as a metaphor for purity. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or www.danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YUBIWA HOTEL (Tonight and tomorrow night) In its American debut, this all-female modern-dance and performance company will examine the Japanese woman today, focusing on girlhood in ''Candies: girlish hardcore.'' At 7:30, Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258 or japansociety.org; $28. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BARD GRADUATE CENTER: ' LIONS, DRAGONS AND OTHER BEASTS: AQUAMANILIA OF THE MIDDLE AGES, VESSELS FOR CHURCH AND TABLE,' through Oct. 15. Aquamanilia sounds like the latest perfume or sorbet, but actually refers to the small, cunningly figurative medieval vessels used for ritual hand-washing. Cast in sturdy, glowing copper-alloy, most often in the form of lions with serpents on their backs, aquamanilia are now having their first exhibition, complete with lavish catalog. The show has been drawn mostly from the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and overseen by the head of the museum's medieval department and its object conservator in collaboration with Bard graduate students. But don't worry about dryness. The aquamanile's triple function as totem, prestige object and pitcher lends it an undeniable energy. (The serpents are handles.) The show feels like a walk-in bestiary and is enhanced by striking abbreviations reminiscent of folk art; a versatile repertory of incised details and patterns; and a continuing, rarely resolved struggle between form and function. Bard Graduate Center for Studies in the Decorative Arts, Design and Culture, 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000, www.bgc.bard.edu. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Looking Back from Ground Zero: Images from the Brooklyn Museum Collection,' through Dec. 27. This show, drawn entirely from the Brooklyn Museum's collection, presents a historical picture of Lower Manhattan from early on to the present, with the building of the World Trade Center as the pivotal point. A short film, ''Building the World Trade Center,'' produced by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey in 1983, is an invaluable document of the triumphalist spin surrounding the construction of the complex. A small selection of artworks produced in or just after 2001 hints at the profound and conflicted feelings the destruction of the twin towers has evoked. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, New York, (718) 638-5000, www.brooklynmuseum.org.(Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedeker's guides, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. And Church's oil sketches alone are worth the price of admission: exquisite, plainspoken Emersonian love poems to New York and New England. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400 or ndm.si.edu. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this engrossing if somewhat strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606, daheshmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Dia:Beacon: 'Agnes Martin: A Field of Vision: Paintings from the 1980's,'  through March. Dia:Beacon, a bulwark of Minimalism on the banks of the Hudson River north of Manhattan, has three permanent galleries devoted to the artist Agnes Martin. Over the last two years they have been used for a retrospective of her paintings, installed in decade-long increments. The fourth installment is now in place. If Martin's spare, lucid compositions of drawn lines and painted bands feel different from much of the art around them here, that is because she was not a Minimalist. In fact, she called herself an Abstract Expressionist, and she was adamant on this point. The 18 paintings here confirm her conviction, in a show as deep, light-glinting, restless and purposeful as the river flowing nearby. Dia:Beacon, Riggio Galleries, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, www.diacenter.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Guild Hall Museum: 'Elizabeth Peyton,'  through Oct. 22. Most of the 43 works in this exhibition portray beautiful people, some famous, some less so. Most immediately engaging is the tension between the painterly abstraction and the human subject matter. Images are realized in drippy swatches, squiggly lines and feathery dabs, and colors range from incandescent reds and oranges to pale lavenders and grays to dark velvety browns, blacks and purples. Yet for all that expressionistic action, likenesses are exacting. People like Nicole Kidman and Queen Elizabeth are rendered with seemingly effortless precision. Romantic feeling connects the form and content in Ms. Peyton's work. A kind of erotic yearning animates how Ms. Peyton sees her subjects and how she makes her pictures. To paint, her works imply, is to be in love: to be in love with certain people and with painting itself. 158 Main Street, East Hampton, N.Y., (631) 324-0806, www.guildhall.org/museum.ihtml. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* Metropolitan Museum of Art: 'Brush and Ink: The Chinese Art of Writing,' through Jan. 21. If painting and writing can be seen as modes of thinking, and they can, then ''Brush and Ink: The Chinese Art of Writing'' at the Metropolitan Museum is as much a brainstorming session as an art exhibition, crackling with ideas and arguments every step of the way. It is also a sequence of moods, with impassioned voices calling out from the 80 scrolls and inscribed fans that line the galleries, which include colossal examples of contemporary 21st-century art that both depart from and preserve a tradition, (212) 535-7710, www.metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Morgan Library &amp; Museum: CELEBRATING REMBRANDT: ETCHINGS FROM THE MORGAN, through Oct. 1. On the occasion of the opening of its newly rethought home, the Morgan Library has mounted a show of 50 of its greatest Rembrandt etchings. The selection demonstrates the range of the master's subjects (from the heights of biblical tragedy to the casually erotic) and also his amazingly expressive technique. It serves as reminder that Rembrandt's prints represent genius of the plainest, most accessible sort: sustaining classics that encompass the earthy and the exalted and offer fresh meanings with each encounter. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, www.themorgan.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer,  through Oct 9. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Las Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle-shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: Had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, www.neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400, www.nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Nadine Robinson: Alles Grau,' 'Quid Pro Quo: Rashawn Griffin, Karyn Olivier and Clifford Owen: 2005-06 Artists-in-Residence,' and 'Beyond Sight,' through Oct. 22. The Studio Museum in Harlem is looking sharp with three concurrent shows, the outstanding one being a single big sound-sculpture by Nadine Robinson. It expands her political purview from imperialism to Armageddon with hundreds of speakers embedded in an 11-foot-high gray-black wall unit that generate a sampling of satanic film scores (''The Omen,'' ''The Matrix''), mixed with funeral chants and Rastafarian dance music. ''Quid Pro Quo'' is a showcase for the 2005-6 artists in residence, all interdisciplinarians with a sweet-and-sour Dadaist touch. Mr. Owens, with performance, looks intriguingly volatile; he will give a live performance at the museum tonight (reservations suggested). And you won't want to leave the museum without checking out ''Beyond Sight,'' the work of the 14 teenage participants in the program called ''Expanding the Walls: Making Connections Between Photography, History and Community,'' 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, www.studiomuseuminharlem.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Wadsworth Atheneum: 'American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum,' through Dec. 31. Back from a two-and-a-half-year tour at six other American museums, the Wadsworth's formidable collection of 19th-century Hudson River School paintings is on display in this homecoming show. Not every Hudson River collection can boast 11 works by Frederic Edwin Church, 13 by Thomas Cole and 5 by Albert Bierstadt,, a leading painter of the American West, along with powerful examples by other artists of the school. They are among the more than 60 paintings on display here. It's rare that you see these ultrafamiliar paintings in such concentration; their combined presence gives the show a synergistic sparkle and energy that you don't get when you see them in smaller groupings. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, www.wadsworthatheneum.org.(Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* ONE WAY OR ANOTHER: ASIAN AMERICAN ART NOW,  through Dec. 10. Taking its name from a 1978 hit by the punk band Blondie, this lively exhibition finds a new vitality and freedom, especially where identity is involved, in Asian-American art. The artists' roots range from Iran to Korea; their mediums include painting, drawing, sculpture, video, photography and performance. Keep a special eye out for Mari Eastman's wryly beautiful paintings; Mika Tajima's glamorous deconstruction of Minimalism; and the video-performance efforts of Patty Chang, Laurel Nakadate and Xavier Cha. An added bonus: 12, or 71 percent, of the show's 17 artists are women. Asia Society, 725 Park Avenue, at 70th Street, (212) 517-2742, www.asiasociety.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* STUART HAWKINS: CUSTOMS The latest series of daffy photographs by this American artist working in Nepal rarely reflects well on Western tourists. Too stagy to be snapshots and too haphazard to be completely planned, they parlay familiar travel terms like ''Day Driver,'' ''Field Notes,'' ''Welcome Drink'' and ''Medicine Kit'' into bizarre sitcoms. In ''Souvenir,'' a short video about the search for indigenous authenticity, the ensemble performance that is generated in the photographs becomes openly antic and wonderfully pointed. Zach Feuer Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, (212) 989-7700, www.zachfeuer.com, through Sept. 23. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'Zoo Story' A clay gorilla by Daisy Youngblood, a bronze she-wolf by Kiki Smith, a flock of concrete sheep by Françoise-Xavier Lalanne and works about animals by more than 20 other artists, including John Baldessari, Katharina Fritsch, Ross Bleckner and Rebecca Horn, turn the first floor of this sleek, three-story private museum into a diverting menagerie. Fisher Landau Center for Art, 38-27 30th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-0727, www.flcart.org through Oct. 16. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, www.folkartmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, www.frick.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES This well-known Cologne gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-7100, www.metropicturesgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM: 'EVA HESSE: SCULPTURE,' Assembled by Elizabeth Sussman, curator at the Whitney Museum of American Art, and Fred Wasserman, a curator at the Jewish Museum, this show focuses on a pivotal Hesse exhibition, ''Chain Polymers,'' at the Fischbach Gallery -- known for promoting Minimalist painters -- in 1968. Arguably a compilation of her best work, it was her first and only solo show of sculpture during her lifetime, and most of the objects in it -- along with some earlier and later pieces -- are here. One of the earliest is ''Compart'' (1966), a four-panel vertical that starts at the top with a fully formed, round, breastlike image of neatly wound cord that mysteriously breaks up into part of the same image on each of the three panels beneath. The last, most startling and most impressive work is ''Untitled (Rope Piece),'' of 1970, made as Ms. Hesse was dying, finished with the help of friends. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200 or www.jewishmuseum.org, closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Katonah Museum of Art: 'Andromeda Hotel, the Art of Joseph Cornell,'  Although Cornell never left the United States, he translated his dreams of faraway places into delicate, sometimes overly precious works that have a sense of longing. In this show the white-painted, weathered interior of a box titled ''Grand Hotel -- Hotel Taglioni'' (1954) contains incongruous elements of collage, among them an old ad for a French bakery topped by a color cutout of the ballerina Marie Taglioni, an object of the artist's adoration. Even simpler, but equally dreamy, is another weathered box, ''Hotel de l'Étoile'' (1950), which holds only a long, vertical image of a deep blue sky rife with thousands of tiny pinpoints of light. One of the show's most striking images is a surreal photograph of Cornell by Lee Miller in which he is seen gazing upward, entranced, his shoulder adorned with a miniature sailboat (around 1935). Route 22 at Jay Street, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-9555, www.katonahmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>HANS RICHTER (1888-1976), DADA; ART AND ANTI-ART This daunting yet partial survey is clogged with late paintings and reliefs that are for the most part elegant pastiches of Constructivism, Cubism and Abstract Expressionism. But it should be seen for the four short films from the 1920's, in which Richter's formalist and Dada sides balance beautifully, with elegantly Surrealist results. This is especially the case in the luminous ''Ghosts Before Breakfast,'' from 1927, which explores most of film's structural possibilities and segues briskly between abstraction and Hollywood narrative, while three skittering bowler hats provide continuity. Maya Stendhal Gallery, 545 West 20th Street, (212) 366-1549, www.mayastendhalgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* STRANGE POWERS This exhibition vacillates between the hokiness of spirit photography and the immateriality of Conceptual Art with just enough agility to keep you guessing about whether ghosts, ESP and other paranormal phenomena are matters of fact or faith. Among the more convincing indications are Anne Collier's small color photographs of the auras of her friends; Sophie Calle's video documentary (made with Fabio Balducci) of a psychic-guided journey; and the Center for Tactical Magic's ''Vital Psigns,'' which demonstrates the power of positive thought on plants. But the efforts of nearly 20 other artists round out the argument, often to unsettling effect. Creative Time, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 206-6674, www.creativetime.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'A CHORUS LINE' Previews start on Monday. Opens on Oct. 5. The legendary musical about Broadway gypsies returns with Charlotte d'Amboise and Michael Berresse (2:00). Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'JOHN FERGUSON' In previews; opens on Sept. 25. The Mint Theater unearths St. John Ervine's gritty piece of realism from 1919 about a pious farmer who can't make his mortgage payments (2:20). Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 315-0231.</p>
        <p>'FRINGE NYC ENCORES' Through Sept. 24. Ten hits from the New York International Fringe Festival return for a second run at two theaters. Shows include ''Billy the Mime,'' ''Walmartopia,'' ''Broken Hands,'' ''Danny Boy,'' ''Open House'' and others. The 14th Street Y, 344 East 14th Street, East Village; Lion Theater, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'HEARTBREAK HOUSE' Previews start today. Opens on Oct 11. Roundabout revives Shaw's drama with a superb cast of theater pros, including Swoosie Kurtz, Philip Bosco and the always elegant Byron Jennings (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'JAY JOHNSON: THE TWO AND ONLY' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Sept 28. The ventriloquist, whose solo show ran at the Atlantic in 2004, talks about his mentor and career (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'LOSING LOUIE' Previews start on Thursday. Opens on Oct. 12. Mark Linn-Baker and Matthew Arkin star in Simon Mendes da Costa's family comedy, which spans 50 years. Jerry Zaks directs this West End transfer. (2:10). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'NIXON'S NIXON' Previews start on Wednesday. Opens on Oct 4. In this revival Russell Lees imagines the conversation between Nixon and Kissinger the night before Nixon resigned. Jim Simpson directs (1:30). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE PAIN AND THE ITCH' In previews; opens on Thursday. Bruce Norris's drama about a dysfunctional family arrives in New York after a successful run at the Steppenwolf Theater in Chicago. Jayne Houdyshell and Reg Rogers star (2:15). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'THE PERSIANS' Runs tomorrow through Wednesday. Politics have made this relatively obscure ancient drama, about an arrogant ruler who rushes to war, suddenly popular. This latest production is by the National Theater of Greece (2:00). City Center, 100 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212.</p>
        <p>'RICHARD II' In previews; opens on Sunday. Michael Cumpsty, who played Hamlet at the Classic Stage Company last season, returns to that downtown theater to headline Shakespeare's history play about a deeply flawed king (2:15). Classic Stage Company, 136 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101.</p>
        <p>'SUBURBIA' In previews; opens on Sept. 28. Eric Bogosian revamps his tale of youthful angst and alienation for the new millennium. Jo Bonney directs (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422.</p>
        <p>'SISTERS' In previews; opens on Sunday. Anna Manahan, who won a Tony in 1998 for her performance in ''The Beauty Queen of Leenane,'' portrays two sisters in Declan Hassett's play set in the rural Ireland of the 1950's (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'SOUTHERN COMFORTS' Previews start on Tuesday. Opens on Oct. 4. Judith Ivey directs this drama about a widow and a widower who meet late in life. Presented by Primary Stages (2:00). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering houseplants finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the avid, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' This eager and amiably scattershot satire of celebrity memoirs and Broadway musicals, starring the immodestly modest Mr. Short, arrives a little late to the table for such parody to taste fresh. With serviceably tuneful songs by Scott Wittman and Marc Shaiman (of ''Hairspray'' fame) (1:45). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a superdeluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Constantine Maroulis, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' A revival -- well, more like a resuscitation -- of the Little Musical That Wouldn't Die. This sweet-as-ever production of Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt's commedia-dell'arte-style confection is most notable for Mr. Jones's touching performance (under the pseudonym Thomas Bruce) as the Old Actor, a role he created when the show opened in 1960. Mr. Jones also directs (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FOGGY BOTTOM' James Armstrong's comedy about a Washingtonian who seduces women by promising them green cards has a nice sense of the ridiculous, but sometimes the action is unbelievable, even by the standards of farce (2:00). Abingdon Theater Arts Complex, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444.(Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GARDEL: THE MUSICAL' A standard-issue bio-musical about the tango legend Carlos Gardel that wallows in melodrama (1:30). Gramercy Arts Theater, 138 East 27th Street, (212) 225-9920. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'IT GOES WITHOUT SAYING' Bill Bowers's zestful, endearing one-man show is about his life as a mime, an actor and a gay boy growing up in Montana (1:15). Rattlestick Playwrights Theater, 224 Waverly Place, off Seventh Avenue South, Greenwich Village, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School (1:10). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* 'SEVEN GUITARS' (2:45). Life and death dance cheek to cheek in this fine new revival of August Wilson's drama from 1996. Directed by Ruben Santiago-Hudson, and acted with absorbing restraint and immediacy, this is a truly life-size production, which means it is big indeed (2:45). Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SHOUT!' A miniskirted, go-go-booted zombie of a musical about women searching for love in London in the 1960's. You won't see anything this groovy, this far-out, this with-it outside of, oh, maybe the showroom of a Carnival cruise ship (1:30). Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'I  3/5sheart 4/5 KANT' Keith Urban's nimble, knowing one-act is about four women (a graduate student, a heroin addict, a depressive and a bombing victim), the men in their lives and the little humiliations and unexpected certainties of daily existence (1:10). Linhart Theater at 440 Studios, 440 Lafayette Street, near Astor Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Spectacles</p>
        <p>'ABSINTHE' Think Cirque du Soleil as channeled through ''Rocky Horror'' and painted by George Grosz. Part cabaret, part circus, ''Absinthe'' aims for a kind of seedy decadence that's mingled with the simple, aw-shucks wonder of knife-jugglers, sword-swallowers and a man creating constructions out of soap bubbles. It's the main event at the Spiegeltent, a vintage European tradition visiting South Street Seaport this summer (1:30). Spiegeltent, at the former Fulton Fish Market site, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'REVEREND BILLY AND THE CHURCH OF STOP-SHOPPING' Reverend Billy (a k a the performance artist Bill Talen) struts and preaches his way across the Spiegeltent stage accompanied by a choir and a fine seven-piece band. Radical political theater has rarely been more thoughtful or fun (1:30). Spiegeltent, at the former Fulton Fish Market site, Pier 17, South Street, under the Brooklyn Bridge, (212) 279-4200. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden Theater, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30). 2005 New World Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SLAVA'S SNOWSHOW' Clowns chosen by the Russian master Slava Polunin stir up laughter and enjoyment. A show that touches the heart as well as tickles the funny bone (1:30). Union Square Theater, 100 East 17th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT'  A singing scrapbook for Monty Python fans. (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY OF VALENTYNE AND ORSON' The director and puppet maker Ralph Lee makes a royal steed out of a hobby horse and a ferocious bear from cardboard and baseball mitts in this enchanting tale of a young prince and the ''wild man'' he befriends (1:05). The outdoor garden of the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 929-4777; closes on Sunday. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'ACCEPTED' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A clever slacker and his oddball crew invent a phony college in this passable example of that oxymoronic genre, the Hollywood comedy about sticking it to the man. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'THE ANT BULLY' (PG, 90 minutes) A young boy goes to live among the ants, who talk remarkably like Academy Award-winning actors. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 (2:20)minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BARNYARD' (PG, 88 minutes) The barnyard animals in this crude 3-D animation walk, talk and party down like human beings. Way too often the male ''cows,'' as the film calls them, also flash their udders. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEERFEST' (R, 110 minutes) In ''Beerfest,'' a gaseous celebration of binge drinking and family honor, the five comedians known collectively as Broken Lizard head for Munich and an underground beer-guzzling contest. Best viewed while sloshed, the movie is idiotic, tasteless and irrepressibly good-natured: in other words, a frat-house classic. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'BOYNTON BEACH CLUB' (No rating, 104 minutes) A fast-paced romantic comedy about frisky 60-something residents of a Florida ''active adult'' community, ''Boynton Beach Club'' is a rose-colored fantasy about aging that has just enough credibility to make you care about its characters and wish them merrily on their way. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'A CANTOR'S TALE' (No rating, 95 minutes) Jovial, rotund and prone to impromptu bursts of song, Cantor Jacob Mendelson has dedicated his life to preserving the Jewish liturgical music known as chazzanut. Erik Greenberg Anjou's charming documentary is more concerned with singing praises than arguing over orthodoxies, while interviews with an uncharacteristically subdued Jackie Mason and Alan Dershowitz suggest an awareness that they're in the presence of greater voices. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt-putt-putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'The Celestine Prophecy' (PG, 100 minutes) A delectable fusion of New Age babble and luridly bad filmmaking based on the best-selling book by James Redfield. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE COVENANT' (PG-13, 97 minutes) The director Renny Harlin proves that ''Exorcist: The Beginning'' was not the nadir of his career with this thriller about boy witches fending off a nefarious transfer student. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'CRANK' (R, 83 minutes) A poisoned hit man rampages in Los Angeles, doling revenge on his nemesis and misanthropy on all. Basically a broken-down retread of ''Speed,'' with Jason Stratham as the bus. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'CROSSOVER' (PG-13, 95 minutes) Bling is bad, and friends are good in this story of temptation, rivalry and cheerleaders, set in the world of Detroit street basketball. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'THE DESCENT' (R, 99 minutes) A total horror freakout from the British writer and director Neil Marshall about six women on a caving expedition who meet their fears and some scary monsters, too. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'FACTOTUM' (R, 94 minutes) Matt Dillon goes deep to play Henry Chinaski, the familiar alter ego of the great Charles Bukowski, who survived countless benders, brawls, rejection slips, crazy women and soul-killing jobs. The Norwegian filmmaker Bent Hamer directed. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'Half Nelson' (R, 107 minutes) In their beautiful bummer about the relationship between a white teacher (Ryan Gosling) and a black student (Shareeka Epps), the gifted young director Ryan Fleck and his writing partner, Anna Boden, offer a lament for the radical fires of the 1960's and a suggestion for life and politics after the new left. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'HOLLYWOODLAND' (R, 126 minutes) A fictional look at the life and downward-spiraling times of George Reeves, the man who played Superman on television and is here played by a fine Ben Affleck. Allen Coulter directs Paul Bernbaum's screenplay, which features a dead-end parallel plot about a detective (Adrien Brody). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'HOW TO EAT FRIED WORMS' (PG, 98 minutes) The worms go in, the worms go out, but mostly the worms go into the frying pan in Bob Dolman's engaging and yucky adaptation of the Thomas Rockwell book. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'HOUSE OF SAND' (R, 115 minutes, in Portuguese) Beautifully shot in a sandy, remote corner of northern Brazil, this film tells the story of three generations of women, all of them played by Fernanda Montenegro and Fernanda Torres, mother and daughter in real life and two of the national treasures of Brazilian cinema. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'IDLEWILD' (R, 120 minutes) André Benjamin and Antwan A. Patton, a k a André 3000 and Big Boi of OutKast, play friends living and sometimes singing in Depression-era Georgia. The joint doesn't jump; it twitches and stumbles. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE ILLUSIONIST' (PG-13, 109 minutes) This film tells the story of Eisenheim (Edward Norton), a fictional conjurer who enraptured Viennese audiences in 1900 with his supernatural magic shows. A terrific yarn, it rouses your slumbering belief in the miraculous. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'INVINCIBLE' (PG, 99 minutes) The latest addition to the Disney stable of sports-underdog movies, ''Invincible'' is the true story of Vince Papale (Mark Wahlberg), a substitute teacher and part-time bartender, who in 1976 realizes his dream of playing for the Philadelphia Eagles. While Disney piles on the uplift, the director and cinematographer, Ericson Core, counters the story's predictably inspirational trajectory with close attention to historical detail and blue-collar hardship. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'LASSIE' (PG, 100 minutes) Everything old is new again in the 11th film about the beloved pooch with the I.Q. of a grad student and the instincts of a boomerang. Blissfully restored to the period and location of Eric Knight's original novel -- pre-World War Britain -- the movie balances humor and pathos with old-fashioned charm and not a trace of satire. Progressive adults may balk at the film's ultimate capitulation to the power of patronage, but tykes will just be happy that Lassie has come home once more to the multiplex where she belongs. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LE PETIT LIEUTENANT' (No rating, 110 minutes, in French) A tough, satisfying drama from Xavier Beauvois about an alcoholic Parisian detective (Nathalie Baye) and the young lieutenant (Jalil Lespert) who comes under her wing. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'Little Miss Sunshine' (R, 101 minutes) A bittersweet comedy of dysfunction that takes place at the terminus of the American dream. The excellent cast includes Greg Kinnear, Steve Carell, Toni Collette, Paul Dano and that national treasure, Alan Arkin. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MAN PUSH CART' (No rating, 87 minutes) The Sisyphean daily grind of a Pakistani immigrant who sells coffee, doughnuts and bagels from a cart in Midtown Manhattan is an exemplary work of independent filmmaking carried out on a shoestring. At its best, it suggests an American ''Bicycle Thief.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. Three intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MUTUAL APPRECIATION' (No rating, 110 minutes)Andrew Bujalski's wonderful independent film about friendship in the modern world looks like something that came out of a time capsule, but there's nothing dusty about it. Shot on expressively grainy black-and-white celluloid, it is the sort of unassuming discovery that could suffer from too much big love, and while it won't save or change your life, it may make your heart swell. Its aim is modest and true. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PAPER DOLLS' (No rating, 80 minutes, in Hebrew, English and Tagalog) A small, touching documentary about Phillipine transexuals living in Israel. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE PROTECTOR' (R, 84 minutes, in Thai) A provincial Thai warrior rampages through Australia, busting skulls and shouting, ''You stole my elephants!'' in this infectious B-movie smackdown. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'QUEENS' (No rating, 107 minutes, in Spanish) A dithering but generous Spanish farce, ''Queens'' follows the forthcoming nuptials of three gay couples by focusing on their overbearing mothers. While the sons dance, bicker and fret over antiques, the mamas express their discomfort with the wedding plans by seducing inappropriate men. Despite obvious nods to Pedro Almodóvar, ''Queens'' is notable only for its unadulterated worship of middle-aged women. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'QUINCEAÑERA' (R, 90 minutes) This portrait of a Mexican-American family living in a Latino neighborhood of Los Angeles is as smart and warm-hearted an exploration of an upwardly mobile immigrant culture as American independent cinema has produced. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'RED DOORS' (No rating, 90 minutes) This agreeable, lightweight movie, written and directed by Georgia Lee, turns the malaises of a dysfunctional suburban Chinese-American family into a bittersweet farce that teeters between cheeky humor and surface pathos. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'RIDING ALONE FOR THOUSANDS OF MILES' (PG, 108 minutes, in Mandarin) Zhang Yimou takes a pause between marital-arts extravaganzas with this simple, affecting melodrama about a mournful Japanese patriarch on an odyssey through rural China. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Satellite' (No rating, 100 minutes) In this captivating romantic fairy tale for grown-ups, made on a shoestring, two young lovers in New York flee yuppie hell into a life of petty theft. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'Scoop' (PG-13, 96 minutes) A not especially funny yet oddly appealing comedy in which Woody Allen and Scarlett Johansson make like Nick and Nora, but with more shtick and no martinis (or Asta). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SHERRYBABY' (No rating, 96 minutes) This story of a young woman, just released from prison, trying to put her life back together, is somewhat predictable, but well observed by Laurie Collyer, the writer and director, and beautifully realized by Maggie Gyllenhaal in the principal role. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SNAKES ON A PLANE' (R, 105 minutes) Snakes + plane + Samuel L. Jackson. David R. Ellis provides the fine B-movie-style direction, while Mr. Jackson supplies the cool and his trademark epithet. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STEP UP' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Ever since Kevin Bacon's rebellious hips ignited a small-town uproar in ''Footloose,'' the modern high school romance has placed a premium on rhythm. In ''Step Up'' a rough Baltimore kid (Channing Tatum), armed only with a killer smile and hip-hop moves, falls for a classically trained dancer (Jenna Dewan). Bland but likable, the movie fashions social equality from big musical numbers. If ballet and hip-hop can coexist, it asks, why can't we all be friends? (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'TALLADEGA NIGHTS: THE BALLAD OF RICKY BOBBY' (PG-13, 110 minutes) Fast, fun and silly, with Will Ferrell as a Nascar driver, Sacha Baron Cohen as his nemesis, and a new course record for product placements per gallon. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'13 Tzameti'  (No rating, 90 minutes) The flashy black-and-white directorial debut of the Georgian filmmaker Gela Babluani is a sadistic, arty thriller that suggests a French New Wave film infected by a virulent strain of Eastern European nihilism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'THIS FILM IS NOT YET RATED' (No rating, 97 minutes) Kirby Dick, with the help of a private detective, investigates the mysterious workings of the Motion Picture Association of America, a highly secretive, deeply irrational organization with enormous influence over what we see -- and don't see -- on movie screens. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'TRUST THE MAN' (R, 101 minutes) A strained, flatulent relationship comedy about two couples, from the writer and director Bart Freundlich. With Julianne Moore, David Duchovny, Maggie Gyllenhaal and Billy Crudup. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'ANDY WARHOL: A DOCUMENTARY FILM' (No rating, 4 hours with an intermission) Ric Burns's absorbing four-hour critical biography of this seminal Pop artist is devoted to the proposition that Warhol was the greatest artist of the second half of the 20th century, as Picasso was in the first. It makes a mostly persuasive, highly entertaining case for that claim. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'the WICKER MAN' (PG-13, 106 minutes) In remaking a 1973 British horror classic, Neil LaBute once again demonstrates his misogyny and, worse, his technical incompetence. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'WORLD TRADE CENTER' (PG-13, 129 minutes) From Oliver Stone, a return to the emotions of 9/11. Powerful and almost unbearably moving. (Scott)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>ANOTHER WAVE: GLOBAL QUEER CINEMA (Through tomorrow) The Museum of Modern Art's festival of gay films and shorts from more than two dozen countries ends this weekend with one feature and a series of five short films. ''Memento Mori: Films by Jim Hubbard'' includes a work in progress about the history of Act Up; Anahi Berneri's drama ''A Year Without Love'' (2005), from Argentina, is the story of a young writer with AIDS who learns to eroticize his pain. Roy and Niuta Titus Theaters, 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>THE FABULOUS ART OF SURVIVAL: LECH KOWALSKI (Through Sept. 26) BAMcinématek's two-week tribute to the punk filmmaker Mr. Kowalski, which began on Tuesday, continues next week with two films. ''Gringo'' (1985) is a gritty, partly documentary portrait of a New York heroin addict. ''On Hitler's Highway'' (2002), a documentary road movie, includes a side trip to Auschwitz. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100, www.bam.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>JEAN-CLAUDE CARRIÈRE'S LANGUAGE OF FILM  (Through Sept. 27) BAMcinématek's series honoring Mr. Carrière, the prolific French screenwriter, continues this weekend with three films. ''The Outside Man'' (1972) stars Jean-Louis Trintignant as a French hit man on a job in Los Angeles. ''Belle de Jour'' (1967) stars Catherine Deneuve as a bored newlywed who takes a day job at a tasteful brothel. Volker Schlöndorff's Oscar-winning allegory ''The Tin Drum'' (1979) was adapted by Mr. Carrière (and a few co-writers) from Günter Grass's novel. BAM Rose Cinemas (see above); $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Monday) The IFC Center's five-month series honoring Akira Kurosawa comes to a close with ''High and Low'' (1963), a drama about a businessman in a devastating moral quandary over the kidnapping of a child. Toshiro Mifune stars, of course. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771, www.ifccenter.com; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>MIZOGUCHI (Through Sept. 21) Film Forum's two-week series honoring the Japanese master director Kenzi Mizoguchi (1898-1956) continues this weekend with two features. ''Sansho the Bailiff'' (1954) is his acclaimed drama about an exiled governor whose children are sold into slavery. ''The Life of Oharu'' (1952), about a samurai's daughter in love with a man beneath her class, was Toshiro Mifune's only Mizoguchi film. 209 West Houston Street, west of Avenue of the Americas, South Village, (212) 727-8112, www.filmforum.com; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE SUPPORTING CAST: AS BRIGHT AS THE STARS (Through Sept. 26) Symphony Space's series of double features honoring the names well below the title continues this weekend with two 1954 dramas. Hitchcock's ''Rear Window'' features Thelma Ritter, Raymond Burr and Wendell Corey. The supporting cast of Elia Kazan's ''On the Waterfront'' includes Karl Malden, Lee J. Cobb and Rod Steiger. 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, www.symphonyspace.org; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* NATACHA ATLAS (Tonight) Musical globalism often works best on the dance floor, where traditions from anywhere, new or old, can mingle and flirt as long as the beat is good. Ms. Atlas, born in Belgium to Jewish and Muslim parents, with family ties to Morocco and Egypt, is a natural multiculturalist. In a strong, sensuous voice, and with the help of bubbly electronic beats, she brings North African, Middle Eastern and Indian styles together; her newest album, ''Mish Maoul'' (Mantra), throws in some rap too. She opens the World Music Institute's season with an all-acoustic ensemble. At 8, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536, symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $32; $15 for students. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>* CHARLES AZNAVOUR (Monday and Tuesday) This legendary French-Armenian music hall entertainer, now 82, is an ageless, sad-faced everyman who brings the skills of a great character actor and mime to his spellbinding performance. This is his farewell tour. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $44.50 to $154.50. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BALKAN BEAT BOX (Tomorrow) Suddenly Balkan brass bands are the hottest sound in dance music. This New York group plays a combustible mix of big, bright horns and high-energy electronic beats. With Sway Machinery. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15 in advance, $17 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAN BERN, HAMELL ON TRIAL (Tomorrow night) With a nasal sing-speak that recalls the young Bob Dylan, Dan Bern offers smooth folk-rock and a world-weary cynicism. (''There's nothing innocent about a newborn babe,'' he sings, ''that a few years here can't cure.'') Ed Hamell, a k a Hamell on Trial, is a manic and sharp-tongued comedian-raconteur who is merciless toward his acoustic guitar. At 7, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $18.50 in advance, $20 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>CITIZEN COPE (Tonight) Clarence Greenwood, a k a Citizen Cope, is the umpteenth singer-songwriter to use hip-hop beats and drawled, rap-sung vocals in search of novelty. At 6:30, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, mcstudios.com; $30. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRUCE COCKBURN (Tomorrow) One of Canada's most revered songwriters since the 1970's, Bruce Cockburn sings about love, politics and spiritual yearning, all tied together by his thoughtful, sympathetic voice and guitar playing that's a quietly virtuosic melding of folk and jazz. At 8 p.m., the Concert Hall at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, concertstonight.com; $30 and $35. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>DASTAN ENSEMBLE WITH PARISSA (Tomorrow) Parissa, a leading traditional singer from Iran, has a repertory that includes both classical Persian music and Sufi songs; she is one of very few female performers from Iran who tour internationally. She will be joining the Dastan Ensemble, which plays classical Persian music: an improvisatory tradition that builds from meditative melodies to dazzling virtuosity. At 8 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 545-7536, symphonyspace.org or worldmusicinstitute.org; $35 and $40; $15 for students. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>ELYSIAN FIELDS (Thursday) Elysian Fields plays languid songs that sound best in a late-night haze, as Jennifer Charles's breathy voice hints at decadence and vulnerability, while Oren Bloedow wraps the songs in slinky, deadpan guitar. At 8:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503, tonicnyc.com; $12 in advance, $15 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>GOLDEN SMOG (Sunday) Even heartsick alt-country has its celebrity supergroups. Golden Smog includes Jeff Tweedy of Wilco, Dan Murphy of Soul Asylum, Gary Louris and Marc Perlman of the Jayhawks, and Kraig Johnson of Run Westy Run. With Tim O'Reagan. At 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE KILLS (Tonight) Part White Stripes and part Sonic Youth, the Kills play a barbed and bluesy garage rock that sounds always on the brink of collapse. With Effi Priest and Mr. J. Carpenter. At 8, Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JOHN LEGEND (Monday) This 27-year-old singer of passionate and stylish R&amp;B, who won three Grammys this year, offers a preview of songs from his new album, due next month. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MAN MAN (Tonight and tomorrow night) Man Man, from Philadelphia, follows the expressive gutter cabaret of Tom Waits into a kinetic chaos that has more than a little Captain Beefheart in it. Formed three years ago, the band quickly acquired a high profile for its energetic live shows. Tonight at 9:30, with Coyote and Tiny Masters of Today, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. Tomorrow at midnight, Spiegeltent, Fulton Fish Market, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 279-4200, spiegelworld.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK SALSA FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) The 31st annual installment of this essential Latin concert features Willie Colón, Cheo Feliciano, Tito Rojas, Lalo Rodríguez, Ismael Miranda, Tito Nieves, Cano Estremera, Tony Vega, Michael Stuart, Jose Alberto (El Canario), Adalberto Santiago, Yomo Toro and the return of Domingo Quiñones. At 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $45 to $110. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>PINK MARTINI (Monday and Tuesday) The Hollywood lounge band gone global, this 12-or-so-piece ensemble from Portland, Ore., follows a glamour jet stream from Rio to Havana to Paris. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 307-7171, the-townhall-nyc.org; $25 and $35. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SANTANA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Using rock instruments to supercharge a salsa band -- or is it vice versa? -- the guitarist Carlos Santana came up with a prototype three decades ago for Latin rock, jazz rock, world music and far-reaching jam bands. He clutters his albums with guest singers to make a run at the pop charts, but on tour the guests are out of the way, and the music soars. Tomorrow at 7:30 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; Sunday at 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; $20 to $75. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>TORTOISE (Sunday) After 16 years as the one followed by all other post-rock, neo-jazz-fusion bands (and there are quite a few), Tortoise, from Chicago, still has some surprises. This year it released an album with Bonnie (Prince) Billy that includes truly idiosyncratic versions of songs by Elton John, Devo and Bruce Springsteen, as well as a retrospective box set that remains entrancing through all four discs. With the Notekillers. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>THE WHO (Monday, Tuesday and Thursday) Down to just Pete Townshend and Roger Daltrey (with hired guns), the Who has made an ambitious play by recording its first new album in 24 years, to be released next month. But the real surprise is just how good it is; based on ''Wire &amp; Glass,'' the teaser EP released in Britain this summer, it is a throwback to the expansive, rock-opera brilliance of ''Quadrophenia.'' With Peeping Tom. Monday and Tuesday at 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $56.50 to $256.50. Thursday at 7:30 p.m., PNC Bank Arts Center, Holmdel, N.J., (732) 335-8698, artscenter.com; $48.75 to $258.75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>WIDESPREAD PANIC (Tonight and tomorrow night) Widespread Panic, from Georgia, leans toward the Southern-rock side of the Allman Brothers-Grateful Dead axis, but like any good jam band, it's flexible and then some. At 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 307-7171, radiocity.com; $50. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>HORACEE ARNOLD QUARTET/TRINITY (Tonight) The New York chapter of the Association for the Advancement of Creative Musicians presents one of its sporadic concerts, featuring a quartet led by the drummer Horacee Arnold, with Marcus Strickland on saxophones, Orrin Evans on piano and Buster Williams on bass; and Trinity, a collective consisting of the saxophonist Patience Higgins, the Hammond B-3 organist Lonnie Gasparini, the percussionist Thurman Baker and the poet Mikhail Horowitz. At 8, Community Church of New York, 40 East 35th Street, Manhattan, (212) 683-4988, aacm-newyork.com; $25. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>OMER AVITAL GROUP (Wednesday) The bassist Omer Avital has a new live album, ''The Ancient Art of Giving,'' on Smalls Records, which delivers the compact jolt of his chamberlike compositions. For this one-night stand at Smalls, he leads a group including the trumpeter Avishai Cohen, the tenor and soprano saxophonist Joel Frahm, the pianist Jason Lindner and the drummer Johnathan Blake. At 10:30 p.m. and midnight, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369, fatcatjazz.com; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE BAD PLUS/JASON MORAN AND THE BANDWAGON (Through Sunday) Two trios, both plumbing the territory between melodic abstraction and gut-level groove, both featuring an erudite pianist and both involving a turbulent and unconventional drummer. This may turn out to be the most thought-provoking double bill to come under a mainstream banner this fall. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY BANG (Tonight and tomorrow night) As a violinist and composer, Mr. Bang favors astringency and formal tension, qualities that come naturally to the musicians he has assembled here: the trumpeter Ted Daniels, the saxophonist and flutist James Spaulding, the pianist Andrew Bemkey, the bassist Todd Nicholson and the drummer Newman Taylor Baker. At 8 and 10, Sweet Rhythm, 88 Seventh Avenue South, at Bleecker Street, West Village, (212) 255-3626, sweetrhythmny.com; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE'S HARD CELL (Tonight) With his recent album ''Feign'' (Screwgun), the alto saxophonist and composer Tim Berne advanced a volatile yet groove-oriented approach to experimental chamber music. Here he reconvenes Hard Cell, the fine ensemble from that album: David Torn on guitar and electronics, Craig Taborn on keyboards and Tom Rainey on drums. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN COLTRANE 80TH-BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Wednesday and Thursday) Countless tenor saxophonists have adapted John Coltrane's sound and style over the years, but few have personalized it more effectively than Joe Lovano, who headlines here with the pianist Steve Kuhn, who briefly worked with Coltrane, and the serious-minded rhythm section of Lonnie Plaxico, bassist, and Andrew Cyrille, drummer. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $40, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* COLTRANE FESTIVAL (Through tomorrow) John Coltrane would have turned 80 this month, and Jazz at Lincoln Center has decided to open its new season with a celebration of his music. At the Rose Theater Wynton Marsalis is leading the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra in a concert featuring arrangements of Coltrane themes. In the Allen Room the vocalist Kevin Mahogany and the saxophonist Todd Williams will pay tribute to Coltrane's album with the baritone Johnny Hartman, with Eric Reed on piano, Reginald Veal on bass and Herlin Riley on drums. The Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra performs at 8 p.m., and Kevin Mahogany performs at 7:30 and 9:30, at Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37.50 to $127.50 for the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra; $67.50 for Kevin Mahogany. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DIET COKE WOMEN IN JAZZ FESTIVAL (Through Thursday) This monthlong festival of female jazz artists continues with the beloved pianist and radio personality Marian McPartland, with her trio (through Sunday); the singer Datevik Hovanesian (7:30 p.m. on Monday) and the saxophonist Tia Fuller, with her quintet (9:30 p.m. on Monday); and the pianist and vocalist Eliane Elias, performing music from her recent RCA Victor album, ''Around the City'' (Tuesday through Thursday). There are also good offerings during the club's after-hours sets, including the singers Andrea Wolper (tonight) and Kate McGarry (tomorrow). At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, or $10 for after-hours sets, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARK DRESSER AND RAZ MESINAI (Thursday) Mr. Dresser is a bassist with a full range of experimental techniques; Mr. Mesinai is a composer with a broad palette of electronic devices. Their duo performance should be a study in texture, but not without a sense of pulse. At 8:30 p.m., Roulette at Location One, 20 Greene Street, at Grand Street, SoHo, (212) 219-8242, roulette.org; $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FATBLASTER (Thursday) A confab of adventurous trumpeters, representing three overlapping levels of experience: Ralph Alessi, an accomplished leader and educator; Shane Endsley, a prominent up-and-comer; and Eric Biondo, who seems most likely to have been behind the band's prankish name. The saxophonist Alex Hamlin and the guitarist Ryan Ferreira round out the group, without adding an ounce of flab. At 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* FESTIVAL OF NEW TRUMPET MUSIC (Through Thursday) This laudably expansive survey of contemporary trumpeters, organized by Dave Douglas, begins its fourth season this weekend, and one of its most promising events happens early. Tomorrow night at Merkin Concert Hall, Mr. Douglas and another trumpeter, Roy Campbell, revisit the music of Don Cherry, notably including the 1966 album ''Symphony for Improvisers.'' Next week the action moves to the Jazz Standard, with a parade of players including Avishai Cohen, Jeremy Pelt and Keyon Harrold (on Tuesday); Taylor Ho Bynum and Stephen Haynes (Wednesday); and Ingrid Jensen and Lina Allemano (Thursday). Tomorrow at 8:30 p.m., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, (212) 501-3330, kaufman-center.org; $35 ($30 in advance). The festival continues on Tuesday at the Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25. For a full festival schedule, visit fontmusic.org. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FULTON STREET BEAT FESTIVAL (Tomorrow) This free outdoor concert features three different perspectives on New Orleans rhythm, each compelling in its own fashion. Second-line groove drives the Jambalaya Brass Band, which plays at 1 p.m., while funk and soul provide the steam for a quintet led by the trumpeter Maurice Brown, at 2:30. New Orleans jazz, in both modern and traditional iterations, animates the final group, led by the saxophonist and clarinetist Victor Goines. At 1 p.m., Fulton Street Mall, DeKalb Avenue at Albee Square West, Downtown Brooklyn, (718) 488-8200, fultonstreet.org; free. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GAME PIECE FOR STRING INSTRUMENTS (Tomorrow) Suzanne Fiol, the artistic director of the Issue Project Room on the Gowanus Canal in Brooklyn, conducts this experimental happening for more than a dozen improvisers, including Miya Masaoka on koto, Jane Scarpantoni on cello and Lucian Buscemi on bass. At 8 p.m., Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Carroll Gardens, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TOM HARRELL-VINCENT HERRING QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Tom Harrell, a tersely lyrical trumpeter, and Vincent Herring, a voluble alto saxophonist, share a preference for high-octane post-bop. Their ensemble includes Nat Adderley Jr. on piano, Richie Goods on bass and Quincy Davis on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRED HERSCH TRIO (Tuesday through Thursday) Fred Hersch is a pianist associated with solo piano recitals, including a week's worth at the Village Vanguard early this year. He returns to the Vanguard with the bassist Drew Gress and the drummer Nasheet Waits, his regular rhythm partners; together they apply a rigorous yet elastic interpretative style to originals and standards alike. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GLENN KOTCHE AND NELS CLINE/JENNY LIN (Monday) Mr. Kotche, who plays drums with the rock band Wilco, has an engrossing new solo percussion album (''Mobile,'' on Nonesuch) that reinforces his new-music credentials. Mr. Cline, Wilco's lead guitarist, also has a new album (''New Monastery,'' on Cryptogramophone), which thoughtfully investigates the compositions of the jazz pianist Andrew Hill. Performing as a duo here, Mr. Kotche and Mr. Cline are likely to incorporate extended techniques and artful atonality; it makes a certain sense that they will follow a piano recital by Jenny Lin, with a repertory including Ligeti, Shostakovich and Elliott Sharp, who will join her on electronics. At 7:30 p.m., Good Shepherd-Faith Presbyterian Church, 152 West 66th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 877-0685, wordlessmusic.org; $19.99. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN 60TH-BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Liebman, an incantatory saxophonist and flutist working in the idiom established by John Coltrane, caps off his birthday celebration at Birdland with a big band directed by the saxophonist and educator Gunnar Mossblad (tonight) and a tribute to the music of Coltrane and Miles Davis, featuring Ravi Coltrane on tenor and soprano saxophone, Randy Brecker on trumpet, Phil Markowitz on piano, Cecil McBee on bass and Adam Nussbaum on drums (tomorrow). At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEN PEPLOWSKI (Tonight) Mr. Peplowski is a clarinetist dedicated to traditional jazz, a preference that should not be mistaken for a limitation. He also plays tenor saxophone and surrounds himself with other accomplished musicians, like the bassist Sean Smith and the percussionist Chuck Reed, who play here. At 7 p.m., Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>NED ROTHENBERG (Tonight) Mr. Rothenberg is a saxophonist, clarinetist, flutist and composer with a penchant for insistent frictions, as he demonstrates on a strong new album, ''The Fell Clutch'' (Animul). Tonight he celebrates his 50th birthday with a roll call of more than a dozen fellow experimentalists, including the saxophonists John Zorn and Marty Ehrlich, the guitarist Marc Ribot and the bassists Jerome Harris and Stomu Takeishi. On Tuesday Mr. Rothenberg leads a smaller coterie: Mark Dresser on bass, Kazu Uchihashi on guitar and Susie Ibarra on drums. Tonight at 8, Issue Project Room, 400 Carroll Street, between Bond and Nevins Streets, Brooklyn, (718) 330-0313, issueprojectroom.org; sold out. Tuesday at 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KERMIT RUFFINS AND THE BARBECUE SWINGERS (Sunday) The tradition of New Orleans-bred trumpeter-entertainers has an especially robust representative in Mr. Ruffins, who appears here with his celebrated working band. At 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 539-8778, joespub.com; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JIMMY SCOTT (Through Sunday) Mr. Scott's piercing voice and achingly emotional style are rightfully enshrined in the annals of songbook interpretation. At 8:30 and 10:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LUCIANA SOUZA: BRAZILIAN DUOS (Through Sunday) Luciana Souza, a vocalist raised in São Paolo, has made some of her most beguiling music in this format, joined by a lone acoustic guitar. Romero Lubambo, the guitarist, is more than an accompanist; providing intricate counterpoint and rhythmic undertow, he is Ms. Souza's equal. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* MCCOY TYNER TRIO WITH PHAROAH SANDERS (Tuesday through Thursday) The pianist McCoy Tyner and the tenor saxophonist Pharoah Sanders are indelibly associated with the 1960's output of John Coltrane, though each enjoyed a productive period as a solo artist in the 70's and beyond. They combine their searching energies here in a quartet with Charnett Moffett on bass and Eric Kamau Gravatt on drums. (Through Sept. 24.) At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $45 at tables, $30 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WILLIAMSBURG JAZZ FESTIVAL (Through Sunday) This grass-roots affair, which briefly subsumes a small swatch of Brooklyn with modern jazz, hits full stride this weekend, with notable performances at Laila Lounge (the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, tonight at 11); Galapagos (the cellist Dana Leong, tomorrow night at 8, and the trumpeter Maurice Brown, tomorrow night at 10); and Rose Live Music (the singer Gretchen Parlato, tomorrow night at 10, and the pianist Jason Lindner, tomorrow night at midnight). The festival closes, oddly enough, on the Lower East Side, at Tonic (the saxophonist Sabir Mateen with the festival's organizer, the trumpeter Jesse Selengut, Sunday at 8 p.m.). Times and locations vary; full schedule, fullcircledrumming.com/wjazzfestival. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* CASSANDRA WILSON/CHRISTIAN SCOTT  (Wednesday) A jazz singer by training and temperament, Ms. Wilson takes obvious pleasure in a boundless, genre-blind repertory, a tendency borne out vividly on her most recent album, ''Thunderbird'' (Blue Note). It's a recording with the seamless sensibility of a modern studio concoction, but Ms. Wilson, often a deeply magnetic performer, should be able to carry it off in concert. The opener is Christian Scott, an excellent young trumpeter whose recent debut, ''Rewind That'' (Concord), signaled his intention to explore a modern funk-based sound. At 8 p.m., Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824, the-townhall-nyc.org; $45 and $35. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEPHANE WREMBEL (Sunday) Virtually every Sunday night for the last three years, Mr. Wrembel, a French guitarist, has been playing the music of the Gypsy guitar hero Django Reinhardt at Barbès. This Sunday Mr. Wrembel marks his anniversary at the club with three sets, loosely tracing the chronological arc of Mr. Reinhardt's career. At 8 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'LA BOHÈME' (Tomorrow and Thursday) Updated to the years around World War I, this is one of New York City Opera's best productions, and some fine young talents should make this run of it worth hearing. Shu-Ying Li, the Mimi, has shown a really striking soprano on past occasions; James Valenti, her Rodolfo, was a promising Met Council winner in 2002; Elisabeth Caballero, the Musetta, made a very good City Opera debut last season; and Daniel Mobbs, the Marcello, has been proving himself reliably at Caramoor and elsewhere for several years. George Manahan, the company's music director, conducts. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $125. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'CARMEN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Rinat Shaham, who made her company debut as Zerlina, is a small singer for Carmen; but worse, City Opera's production seems to have veiled her spark, rendering her a mere stereotype in a stiff performance. Her Don José, Mark Duffin, has warm lower notes and a pressed, often flat sound on top; the Escamillo is Adrian Gans, who was too nervous to be judged at his company debut in the role. The high point is Latonia Moore, a radiant-voiced Micaëla who seems to belong to a world apart from this rather pedestrian production. Ari Pelto conducts, a little woodenly but competently enough. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $130. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'THE MARRIAGE OF FIGARO' (Tomorrow and Sunday) Diminutive and beloved, the sexaguanarian Amato Opera proves that, in opera, tradition and devotion can prevail over quality. It's remarkable that all of Mozart's characters can fit on the theater's tiny stage. Saturday at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m., Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200; $35; $28 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Sunday, and Thursday) Solo piano recitals frame the week's offerings at New York's favorite floating concert hall. Tonight Steven Lubin offers three Beethoven sonatas (including the ''Waldstein'' and ''Appassionata''); next Thursday Steven Beck juxtaposes Bach and Shostakovich preludes and fugues, then plays some Mozart sonatas. In between, the Quartetto di Cremona shows its stuff in two varied programs tomorrow and Sunday, featuring Shostakovich, Schubert, Mozart, Schumann and Vacchi. Tonight, tomorrow night and Thursday night at 7:30; Sunday afternoon at 4; Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35; $20 for students; $30 for 65 tonight and Thursday. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Thursday) The season begins with a generous program ranging as far back as Vivaldi and Mendelssohn and as far forward as Bright Sheng, Leon Kirchner and Nicholas Maw. Pieces by John Ireland and Arthur Bliss will also show up. At 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788; $28 to $70. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>'THE CONSTITUTION: A SECULAR ORATORIO' (Tonight and Thursday) Those who celebrate Constitution Day should not miss the composer Ben Yarmolinsky's word-for-word setting of large swatches of the Constitution, modeled on a Handelian oratorio but with echoes of musical styles from classical to American folk. This being Constitution Week, it will have two separate performances. Tonight at 8, General Society of Mechanics and Tradesmen, 20 West 44th Street, (212) 921-1767; $15; $10 for members; $5 for students. Thursday afternoon at 12:15, Gould Memorial Library Auditorium, Bronx Community College, University Avenue and 181st Street, (718) 289-5100; free. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* ENSEMBLE XX.JAHRHUNDERT (Monday through Wednesday) Call it old new music: the 20th-Century Ensemble has been devoted to contemporary and modern works since the conductor Peter Burwik founded it in 1971. At the Austrian Cultural Forum's continuing ''Mostly Modern'' festival, the ensemble brackets its three performances next week with works of the Second Viennese School (Webern and Berg) and émigré composers (Eisler and Krenek); these surround a range of works by living composers, many Austrian, and many unfamiliar to New York audiences. At 8 p.m., 11 East 52nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 319-5300, Ext. 222; free, but reservations are required. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>TAKA KIGAWA (Tonight) This enterprising young Japanese pianist tackles another tough program, this time with Bach, Beethoven and Boulez. At 8, Greenwich House Music School, 46 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 242-4770; $10. (Holland)</p>
        <p>'A NIGHT AT THE OPERA' (Tuesday) A host of singers from the New York City Opera's past and present, including Samuel Ramey and Carol Vaness, will parade their vocal talents across the stage of the New York State Theater. At 7:30 p.m., Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $27 to $135. (Holland)</p>
        <p>ORPHEUS CHAMBER ORCHESTRA (Monday) The Metropolitan Museum opens its music season with hearty, traditional fare in the Great Hall. Janine Jansen and Eriko Sato are violinists in Bach's D-minor Double Concerto and will also be busy in excerpts from Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons.'' At 7 p.m., (212) 570-3949; $60. (Holland)</p>
        <p>St. LUKE'S CHAMBER ENSEMBLE (Wednesday) In its first full season of concert programs after the impressive expansion of its campus, the Morgan Library and Museum gets things going at its intimate new Gilder Lehrman Hall with the St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble. Booking this popular ensemble into this 280-seat hall has proved a smart move. There are two series with three programs each; the first is officially sold out, and there is limited availability for the second. The programs begin with a concert of Baroque works by Bach, Vivaldi and Handel. At 7:30 p.m., 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 594-6100; $35; $25 for members.(Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* SILK ROAD ENSEMBLE YOUNG ARTISTS (Tomorrow and Sunday) As part of the continuing Silk Road Project, Yo-Yo Ma's mission to bring together musicians of diverse cultures from the ancient international Silk Road trade routes, Carnegie Hall and the Weill Music Institute present four programs this weekend that grew out of a ''Tradition and Innovation'' workshop for composers and young artists. The concerts offer works by emerging composers like the 28-year-old Angel Lam, who was born in Hong Kong and now lives in Baltimore, and by established figures like Dmitri Yanov-Yanovsky, one of the leading voices in Uzbekistan, as well as the acclaimed Argentine composer of Eastern European Jewish heritage, Osvaldo Golijov. The specific works on each of the four programs will be announced at the concerts, chosen from composers including Gabriela Lena Frank, Christopher Adler, Kayhan Kalhor, Jeeyoung Kim, Evan Ziporyn and others. Tomorrow and Sunday at 4 and 8 p.m., Zankel Hall, (212) 247-7800; $15. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ARTICHOKE DANCE COMPANY (Tonight through Sunday) The company will perform Lynn Neumann's new ''I Am Nothing (Without You): Rounds 1-6,'' which involves the audience in determining the structure of each performance of the piece, which can be seen from perspectives that include the sidewalk outside. Through Sept. 24. At 8 p.m., Center for Remembering and Sharing, 123 Fourth Avenue, between 12th and 13th Streets, East Village, (212) 352-3101; $15; $12 for students and 65+. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARIANA BEKERMAN DANCE COMPANY (Thursday) Created by Mariana Bekerman and the guest choreographers Keiko Fujii and Rebekah J. Kennedy, ''Taro'' tells the story of a woman whose world is transformed when she encounters an evil spirit. (Through Sept. 24.) At 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, (212) 334-7479; $15; $10 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN ADULT RECORDER CHOIR (Tonight and tomorrow night) The name of this group turns out to be literal description rather than whimsy: a self-described ad hoc group of some 60 performers trying to recapture the joys of those painful recorder lessons at school during ''In the Closet, Again, Again.'' The choreographer Beth Gill and the composer Chris Peck thought this up. From 7 to 10, the Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $15, or pay what you will for Queens residents. (Roslyn Sulcas)</p>
        <p>DANCE AT MILLER: NEW BALLET CHOREOGRAPHERS (Tonight and tomorrow night) Ashley Bouder, Maria Kowrowski and Wendy Whelan are among the wonderful dancers from the New York City Ballet and American Ballet Theater Studio Company who will perform in this enticing program of new ballets to live music by the Masada String Trio. The choreographers are the City Ballet soloists Edwaard Liang and Tom Gold, and the former Ballet Theater dancer Brian Reeder. Mr. Gold is the wild card here -- the other two have budding reputations as promising ballet choreographers -- but he is in very good company. At 8, Miller Theater at Columbia University, 116th Street and Broadway, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799; $35; Columbia students, $7; non-Columbia students and Guggenheim Museum members, $21. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>DANCENOW/NYC FESTIVAL: DANCEMOPOLITAN @ JOE'S PUB (Tonight and tomorrow night) In the festival's closing performances, Leigh Garrett serves as host for two different programs featuring 19 choreographers and companies. At 9:30, Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200 or joespub.org. Information about participants: dancenownyc.org; $20. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BILL T. JONES/ARNIE ZANE DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) Bill T. Jones's ''Another Evening: I Bow Down,'' which had its premiere earlier this year, is back in the New York area forone night. The music is by Mr. Jones's regular collaborator Daniel Bernard Roumain, performing with the Bronx hard-core band Regain the Heart Condemned. An actor, Andrea Smith, performs alongside 10 dancers. Mr. Jones appears too -- always worth the trip. At 8 p.m., Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, Rutgers University, 85 George Street, New Brunswick, N.J., (732) 932-7511, masongross.rutgers.edu; $15 to $25. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>* LARRY KEIGWIN (Sunday and Tuesday) An expanded version of Mr. Keigwin's amusing contribution to the first (2005) installment of Dancing in the Streets's ''Dance Charrette,'' complete with dancers gabbing into cellphones and walking on walls. Sunday at 1:30 and 5 p.m., and Tuesday at 6 p.m., rain or shine, Tobacco Warehouse, Empire-Fulton Ferry State Park section of the Brooklyn Bridge Park, Dumbo, Brooklyn, (212) 635-3505 or dancinginthestreets.org; free. The Sunday performances will flank a walking tour of the Brooklyn Bridge Park area at 2:30 p.m., sponsored by the Municipal Art Society, (212) 935-2075; $15. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>NOÉMIE LAFRANCE'S 'AGORA II' (Tonight, tomorrow, Wedneday and Thursday) Apparently Ms. LaFrance, a tireless artistic explorer of public space, is a glutton for punishment. Having moved bureaucratic mountains last year to stage ''Agora'' in the enormous (and empty) McCarren Park pool in Greenpoint, Brooklyn, she now has a sequel, ''Agora II,'' which incorporates a number of guest companies and is described in the publicity materials as ''a choreographic game for 1,000 bodies.'' Good luck to them all. At 8 p.m. (arrive by 7:30), McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs and Bayard Streets, (718) 388-6309 or sensproduction.org; $20 and $30. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>LIVE ARTS FESTIVAL AND PHILLY FRINGE (Tonight and tomorrow night) These festivals wind to an end this weekend at theater spaces throughout downtown Philadelphia with several intriguing-sounding events, among them Jeb Kreager's ''Contest,'' which explores an American cultural preoccupation with competition and victory in choreography that draws on marching bands, platoon drilling and group singing. Information and reservations: (215) 413-1318 or livearts-fringe.org; $10, $15 and $20, depending on the event, with some shows free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* CONSTANZA MACRAS (Thursday) This choreographer, born in Argentina, trained in New York and Amsterdam and based in Berlin, will perform with her 18-member international company, Dorky Park, in the United States premiere of ''Back to the Present,'' originally presented over four hours in 2003 in an abandoned Berlin department store. (Through Sept. 23.) At 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $20; $12 for artists, members, students and 65+. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>MÉXICO NOW @ DNA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Mexican choreographers living in New York City will present their work. Tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 3 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, TriBeCa, ticketcentral.com; $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MÉXICO NOW: Danscores by OFELIA LORET DE MOLA (Tonight and tomorrow night) Although ''Aktun Spukil,'' the title of a work by the choreographer Ofelia Loret de Mola, sounds like one of the crew on the Starship Enterprise, it is, according to Mexican lore, the name of a group of caves in which the Maya took shelter during battles. At 8, Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, (212) 334-7479; $15; students, $12. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>ELISA MONTE DANCE (Tuesday through Thursday) This company, well known to New Yorkers, opens the Joyce's fall season with a weeklong celebration of its 25th anniversary. Elisa Monte has created a new piece, ''Hardwood,'' and has revived some older works for the occasion. At 7.30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800; $40; Joyce members, $30. (Sulcas)</p>
        <p>JEREMY NELSON (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson will continue his investigation into physical turbulence in his new ''Mean Piece,'' a work for six dancers, with sets and costumes by Luis Lara Malvacias. At 7:30, Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org; $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BAROQUE DANCE COMPANY (Tonight and tomorrow night) Last month Mark Morris offered a new piece called ''Mozart Dances,'' set to Mozart piano music, none composed for dance. Now Catherine Turocky's historical-dance company and its affiliated early-music group Concert Royal will present their own program, ''Mozart Dances!'' Here the music will again include a piano concerto, but also Mozart's actual dance music for ''Les Petits Riens'' and the opera ''Idomeneo.'' At 8 p.m., Florence Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, (212) 307-4100 or (212) 355-6160 or nybaroquedance.org; $30. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>ELKA RINDFLEISCH (Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday) In Ms. Rindfleisch's new ''Damage,'' six dancers will struggle through a spreading inner disturbance to rock music by Chris Woltmann, performed live. They end up nowhere, the choreographer says, or in places of unexpected tenderness in a set that fills the performance space with small alternative spaces. At 8 p.m., Wallabout Studio, 50 Taaffe Place, between Flushing and Park Avenues, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (917) 251-4561 or rindfleischdance.com; $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>T E A DANCE COMPANY (Tonight through Sunday night) Sahar Javedani and Ella Ben-Aharon, the troupe's resident choreographers, will present their new ''Gardens,'' which probes the notion of the pre-apple Eden as a metaphor for purity. At 8:30, Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or www.danspaceproject.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YUBIWA HOTEL (Tonight and tomorrow night) In its American debut, this all-female modern-dance and performance company will examine the Japanese woman today, focusing on girlhood in ''Candies: girlish hardcore.'' At 7:30, Japan Society, 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258 or japansociety.org; $28. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>BARD GRADUATE CENTER: ' LIONS, DRAGONS AND OTHER BEASTS: AQUAMANILIA OF THE MIDDLE AGES, VESSELS FOR CHURCH AND TABLE,' through Oct. 15. Aquamanilia sounds like the latest perfume or sorbet, but actually refers to the small, cunningly figurative medieval vessels used for ritual hand-washing. Cast in sturdy, glowing copper-alloy, most often in the form of lions with serpents on their backs, aquamanilia are now having their first exhibition, complete with lavish catalog. The show has been drawn mostly from the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and overseen by the head of the museum's medieval department and its object conservator in collaboration with Bard graduate students. But don't worry about dryness. The aquamanile's triple function as totem, prestige object and pitcher lends it an undeniable energy. (The serpents are handles.) The show feels like a walk-in bestiary and is enhanced by striking abbreviations reminiscent of folk art; a versatile repertory of incised details and patterns; and a continuing, rarely resolved struggle between form and function. Bard Graduate Center for Studies in the Decorative Arts, Design and Culture, 18 West 86th Street, (212) 501-3000, www.bgc.bard.edu. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Looking Back from Ground Zero: Images from the Brooklyn Museum Collection,' through Dec. 27. This show, drawn entirely from the Brooklyn Museum's collection, presents a historical picture of Lower Manhattan from early on to the present, with the building of the World Trade Center as the pivotal point. A short film, ''Building the World Trade Center,'' produced by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey in 1983, is an invaluable document of the triumphalist spin surrounding the construction of the complex. A small selection of artworks produced in or just after 2001 hints at the profound and conflicted feelings the destruction of the twin towers has evoked. 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn, New York, (718) 638-5000, www.brooklynmuseum.org.(Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>COOPER-HEWITT NATIONAL DESIGN MUSEUM: 'FREDERIC CHURCH, WINSLOW HOMER AND THOMAS MORAN: TOURISM AND THE AMERICAN LANDSCAPE,' through Oct. 22. It turns out that the Cooper-Hewitt owns thousands of rarely seen paintings, prints and sketches by Church, Homer and Moran. Studies of the countryside, mostly, they revere unspoiled nature and record tourism, a booming industry in 19th-century America. Here they're combined with antique postcards, old Baedeker's guides, stereoscopic photographs, playing cards with pictures of Yellowstone on them and souvenir platters, all to trace the nation's transformation from primeval wilderness to Catskills resort. The show is extremely entertaining. And Church's oil sketches alone are worth the price of admission: exquisite, plainspoken Emersonian love poems to New York and New England. 2 East 91st Street, (212) 849-8400 or ndm.si.edu. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the 23-volume ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this engrossing if somewhat strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606, daheshmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Dia:Beacon: 'Agnes Martin: A Field of Vision: Paintings from the 1980's,'  through March. Dia:Beacon, a bulwark of Minimalism on the banks of the Hudson River north of Manhattan, has three permanent galleries devoted to the artist Agnes Martin. Over the last two years they have been used for a retrospective of her paintings, installed in decade-long increments. The fourth installment is now in place. If Martin's spare, lucid compositions of drawn lines and painted bands feel different from much of the art around them here, that is because she was not a Minimalist. In fact, she called herself an Abstract Expressionist, and she was adamant on this point. The 18 paintings here confirm her conviction, in a show as deep, light-glinting, restless and purposeful as the river flowing nearby. Dia:Beacon, Riggio Galleries, 3 Beekman Street, Beacon, N.Y., (845) 440-0100, www.diacenter.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Guild Hall Museum: 'Elizabeth Peyton,'  through Oct. 22. Most of the 43 works in this exhibition portray beautiful people, some famous, some less so. Most immediately engaging is the tension between the painterly abstraction and the human subject matter. Images are realized in drippy swatches, squiggly lines and feathery dabs, and colors range from incandescent reds and oranges to pale lavenders and grays to dark velvety browns, blacks and purples. Yet for all that expressionistic action, likenesses are exacting. People like Nicole Kidman and Queen Elizabeth are rendered with seemingly effortless precision. Romantic feeling connects the form and content in Ms. Peyton's work. A kind of erotic yearning animates how Ms. Peyton sees her subjects and how she makes her pictures. To paint, her works imply, is to be in love: to be in love with certain people and with painting itself. 158 Main Street, East Hampton, N.Y., (631) 324-0806, www.guildhall.org/museum.ihtml. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestoes and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500, guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* Metropolitan Museum of Art: 'Brush and Ink: The Chinese Art of Writing,' through Jan. 21. If painting and writing can be seen as modes of thinking, and they can, then ''Brush and Ink: The Chinese Art of Writing'' at the Metropolitan Museum is as much a brainstorming session as an art exhibition, crackling with ideas and arguments every step of the way. It is also a sequence of moods, with impassioned voices calling out from the 80 scrolls and inscribed fans that line the galleries, which include colossal examples of contemporary 21st-century art that both depart from and preserve a tradition, (212) 535-7710, www.metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Morgan Library &amp; Museum: CELEBRATING REMBRANDT: ETCHINGS FROM THE MORGAN, through Oct. 1. On the occasion of the opening of its newly rethought home, the Morgan Library has mounted a show of 50 of its greatest Rembrandt etchings. The selection demonstrates the range of the master's subjects (from the heights of biblical tragedy to the casually erotic) and also his amazingly expressive technique. It serves as reminder that Rembrandt's prints represent genius of the plainest, most accessible sort: sustaining classics that encompass the earthy and the exalted and offer fresh meanings with each encounter. 225 Madison Avenue, at 36th Street, (212) 685-0008, www.themorgan.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer, and it makes some interesting points about the spectacle of the museum, the Modern included. (212) 708-9400, www.moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer,  through Oct 9. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Las Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle-shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: Had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200, www.neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, (212) 873-3400, www.nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Studio Museum in Harlem: 'Nadine Robinson: Alles Grau,' 'Quid Pro Quo: Rashawn Griffin, Karyn Olivier and Clifford Owen: 2005-06 Artists-in-Residence,' and 'Beyond Sight,' through Oct. 22. The Studio Museum in Harlem is looking sharp with three concurrent shows, the outstanding one being a single big sound-sculpture by Nadine Robinson. It expands her political purview from imperialism to Armageddon with hundreds of speakers embedded in an 11-foot-high gray-black wall unit that generate a sampling of satanic film scores (''The Omen,'' ''The Matrix''), mixed with funeral chants and Rastafarian dance music. ''Quid Pro Quo'' is a showcase for the 2005-6 artists in residence, all interdisciplinarians with a sweet-and-sour Dadaist touch. Mr. Owens, with performance, looks intriguingly volatile; he will give a live performance at the museum tonight (reservations suggested). And you won't want to leave the museum without checking out ''Beyond Sight,'' the work of the 14 teenage participants in the program called ''Expanding the Walls: Making Connections Between Photography, History and Community,'' 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500, www.studiomuseuminharlem.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Wadsworth Atheneum: 'American Splendor: Hudson River School Masterworks From the Wadsworth Atheneum,' through Dec. 31. Back from a two-and-a-half-year tour at six other American museums, the Wadsworth's formidable collection of 19th-century Hudson River School paintings is on display in this homecoming show. Not every Hudson River collection can boast 11 works by Frederic Edwin Church, 13 by Thomas Cole and 5 by Albert Bierstadt,, a leading painter of the American West, along with powerful examples by other artists of the school. They are among the more than 60 paintings on display here. It's rare that you see these ultrafamiliar paintings in such concentration; their combined presence gives the show a synergistic sparkle and energy that you don't get when you see them in smaller groupings. 600 Main Street, Hartford, (860) 278-2670, www.wadsworthatheneum.org.(Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* ONE WAY OR ANOTHER: ASIAN AMERICAN ART NOW,  through Dec. 10. Taking its name from a 1978 hit by the punk band Blondie, this lively exhibition finds a new vitality and freedom, especially where identity is involved, in Asian-American art. The artists' roots range from Iran to Korea; their mediums include painting, drawing, sculpture, video, photography and performance. Keep a special eye out for Mari Eastman's wryly beautiful paintings; Mika Tajima's glamorous deconstruction of Minimalism; and the video-performance efforts of Patty Chang, Laurel Nakadate and Xavier Cha. An added bonus: 12, or 71 percent, of the show's 17 artists are women. Asia Society, 725 Park Avenue, at 70th Street, (212) 517-2742, www.asiasociety.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>* STUART HAWKINS: CUSTOMS The latest series of daffy photographs by this American artist working in Nepal rarely reflects well on Western tourists. Too stagy to be snapshots and too haphazard to be completely planned, they parlay familiar travel terms like ''Day Driver,'' ''Field Notes,'' ''Welcome Drink'' and ''Medicine Kit'' into bizarre sitcoms. In ''Souvenir,'' a short video about the search for indigenous authenticity, the ensemble performance that is generated in the photographs becomes openly antic and wonderfully pointed. Zach Feuer Gallery, 530 West 24th Street, (212) 989-7700, www.zachfeuer.com, through Sept. 23. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'Zoo Story' A clay gorilla by Daisy Youngblood, a bronze she-wolf by Kiki Smith, a flock of concrete sheep by Françoise-Xavier Lalanne and works about animals by more than 20 other artists, including John Baldessari, Katharina Fritsch, Ross Bleckner and Rebecca Horn, turn the first floor of this sleek, three-story private museum into a diverting menagerie. Fisher Landau Center for Art, 38-27 30th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-0727, www.flcart.org through Oct. 16. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* American Folk Art Museum: 'WHITE ON WHITE (AND A LITTLE GRAY),' The importance of neo-Classicism to early American architecture, silver and fine furniture is not exactly news. This small, beautiful show follows its spread into more personal corners of visual culture: often exquisite, strikingly dimensional white-work bedcovers; luminously grisaille, sometimes wacky marble-dust drawings; and print-work embroidery mourning pictures. 45 West 53rd Street, (212) 265-1040, www.folkartmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700, www.frick.org; closes on Sunday. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* GALERIE DANIEL BUCHHOLZ AT METRO PICTURES This well-known Cologne gallery presents a surprisingly sweeping view of current art that includes Americans and Europeans and, despite its Conceptual slant, an impressive range of mediums and sensibilities. Metro Pictures, 519 West 24th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-7100, www.metropicturesgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM: 'EVA HESSE: SCULPTURE,' Assembled by Elizabeth Sussman, curator at the Whitney Museum of American Art, and Fred Wasserman, a curator at the Jewish Museum, this show focuses on a pivotal Hesse exhibition, ''Chain Polymers,'' at the Fischbach Gallery -- known for promoting Minimalist painters -- in 1968. Arguably a compilation of her best work, it was her first and only solo show of sculpture during her lifetime, and most of the objects in it -- along with some earlier and later pieces -- are here. One of the earliest is ''Compart'' (1966), a four-panel vertical that starts at the top with a fully formed, round, breastlike image of neatly wound cord that mysteriously breaks up into part of the same image on each of the three panels beneath. The last, most startling and most impressive work is ''Untitled (Rope Piece),'' of 1970, made as Ms. Hesse was dying, finished with the help of friends. 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200 or www.jewishmuseum.org, closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Katonah Museum of Art: 'Andromeda Hotel, the Art of Joseph Cornell,'  Although Cornell never left the United States, he translated his dreams of faraway places into delicate, sometimes overly precious works that have a sense of longing. In this show the white-painted, weathered interior of a box titled ''Grand Hotel -- Hotel Taglioni'' (1954) contains incongruous elements of collage, among them an old ad for a French bakery topped by a color cutout of the ballerina Marie Taglioni, an object of the artist's adoration. Even simpler, but equally dreamy, is another weathered box, ''Hotel de l'Étoile'' (1950), which holds only a long, vertical image of a deep blue sky rife with thousands of tiny pinpoints of light. One of the show's most striking images is a surreal photograph of Cornell by Lee Miller in which he is seen gazing upward, entranced, his shoulder adorned with a miniature sailboat (around 1935). Route 22 at Jay Street, Katonah, N.Y., (914) 232-9555, www.katonahmuseum.org; closes on Sunday. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>HANS RICHTER (1888-1976), DADA; ART AND ANTI-ART This daunting yet partial survey is clogged with late paintings and reliefs that are for the most part elegant pastiches of Constructivism, Cubism and Abstract Expressionism. But it should be seen for the four short films from the 1920's, in which Richter's formalist and Dada sides balance beautifully, with elegantly Surrealist results. This is especially the case in the luminous ''Ghosts Before Breakfast,'' from 1927, which explores most of film's structural possibilities and segues briskly between abstraction and Hollywood narrative, while three skittering bowler hats provide continuity. Maya Stendhal Gallery, 545 West 20th Street, (212) 366-1549, www.mayastendhalgallery.com; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* STRANGE POWERS This exhibition vacillates between the hokiness of spirit photography and the immateriality of Conceptual Art with just enough agility to keep you guessing about whether ghosts, ESP and other paranormal phenomena are matters of fact or faith. Among the more convincing indications are Anne Collier's small color photographs of the auras of her friends; Sophie Calle's video documentary (made with Fabio Balducci) of a psychic-guided journey; and the Center for Tactical Magic's ''Vital Psigns,'' which demonstrates the power of positive thought on plants. But the efforts of nearly 20 other artists round out the argument, often to unsettling effect. Creative Time, 64 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 206-6674, www.creativetime.org; closes on Sunday. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
