<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jeter Unable to Make It Easier for Rodriguez</title>
    <meta content="26base" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061101T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA143FF935A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jeter Unable to Make It Easier for Rodriguez</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Derek Jeter has been traveling in Europe, and he said Wednesday that he had not seen any of this year's World Series. This is the time of year when Jeter, the Yankees' shortstop, would rather be playing than watching.</p>
        <p>Jeter was at Busch Stadium before Game 4, which was rained out, to receive the Hank Aaron Award, voted on by fans to represent the best offensive player in the American League. Alex Rodriguez, a three-time winner, was not nominated this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Derek Jeter has been traveling in Europe, and he said Wednesday that he had not seen any of this year's World Series. This is the time of year when Jeter, the Yankees' shortstop, would rather be playing than watching.</p>
        <p>Jeter was at Busch Stadium before Game 4, which was rained out, to receive the Hank Aaron Award, voted on by fans to represent the best offensive player in the American League. Alex Rodriguez, a three-time winner, was not nominated this year.</p>
        <p>It was a trying year for Rodriguez, whose numbers and popularity declined sharply since he won the 2005 American League Most Valuable Player award. Rodriguez, his agent, Scott Boras, Manager Joe Torre and General Manager Brian Cashman have insisted Rodriguez would not be traded.</p>
        <p>Yet the issue persists, and Jeter was asked about it Wednesday. Jeter said he expected Rodriguez to be back, but he did not have any ideas on how he could make life easier for his teammate. Jeter, the Yankees' captain, has been criticized for his seemingly lukewarm support of Rodriguez.</p>
        <p>''What would you like me to do?'' Jeter said. ''You're there and you support him. Everybody supports all your teammates at all times. I don't really know if there's anything else I can do. Maybe I'm not that smart; maybe you can help me out.''</p>
        <p>Jeter said he had spoken to Rodriguez since the season ended -- ''Briefly,'' he added -- and he said he saw no reason that Torre and Rodriguez would have to clear the air. Torre batted Rodriguez eighth in the Yankees' final playoff game; Rodriguez had not hit that low in more than 10 years.</p>
        <p>''Clear what air?'' Jeter said. ''I don't have anything to do with that. From what I've heard, I haven't heard there's any air that needed to be cleared. I'm not speaking on his behalf or Mr. T's behalf, but that's not something I've heard.''</p>
        <p>Jeter also disputed the notion that there was tension in the Yankees' clubhouse, saying that members of the news media were not around enough to make that judgment. As for the pressure on Torre, who enters the last year of his contract, Jeter said it would be a nonissue.</p>
        <p>''In New York, it doesn't make a difference if you have a contract or not,'' Jeter said. ''There are expectations every season. I don't think because it's the last year of his deal, the focus is going to be any more on that. It's always on us to win.''</p>
        <p>This year, of course, the Yankees did not win enough. But Jeter's standout season brought him here anyway, sharing a stage with the National League winner, Ryan Howard of the Phillies, and with Aaron.</p>
        <p>Next month, Jeter and Howard could win the M.V.P. awards, based on voting by the Baseball Writers' Association of America.</p>
        <p>Asked if that would surprise him, Jeter said, ''I'm surprised I'm here right now.''</p>
        <p>KEEPING A TRADITION -- With a steady rain falling over Busch Stadium on Wednesday, the fourth game of the World Series was postponed. The game was the fourth rainout of the baseball postseason, but do not suggest to Jim Leyland the possibility of moving the games to a warm-weather site.</p>
        <p>''I would never go for that,'' said Leyland, the Tigers' manager. ''I love this. I don't care how miserable it is. I think it would be a crying shame to take something like this away from the fans of St. Louis or the fans of Detroit.''</p>
        <p>Leyland's center fielder, Curtis Granderson, did not seem so sure it was a bad idea, although he said there was no way it would happen.</p>
        <p>''It's tradition, and it's hard to break tradition,'' he said. ''Just look at our jerseys. We've been using these for so many years. It would definitely be something to present, but I don't think it will happen.''</p>
        <p>It was 43 degrees at game time Tuesday, the coldest at the start of a World Series game since the Marlins and the Indians played in snow in Cleveland in 1997. Tigers reliever Todd Jones said the Cardinals did little to keep the bullpen warm.</p>
        <p>''The Chicago White Sox have this big industrial jet engine that will cook you if you're not careful,'' Jones said. ''Here, I'm telling you, it's like a toaster. We could grill marshmallows like there's nothing to it.''</p>
        <p>Jones said the relievers huddled over the small heater like people singing around a fire in a trash can on a street corner.</p>
        <p>''I thought there was global warming going on,'' Jones said. ''But apparently, there's not.''</p>
        <p>ALL IN THE FAMILY -- Displayed on a shelf of Scott Spiezio's locker is Card 349 of the 1968 Topps baseball set. The man in a Cardinals jersey holding a bat is his father, Ed, a reserve infielder on the Cardinals' World Series teams of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>''When I was growing up, that's all he taught me,'' said Spiezio, who was 0 for 3 for St. Louis in Game 2. ''That's what I prepared for was to play in the World Series. I got to do it in 2002, and I get to do it again now. It's pretty cool.''</p>
        <p>Spiezio won a championship with the Angels in 2002, when he and the Cardinals' current shortstop, David Eckstein, played in the same infield. The catchers on that team were Bengie and José Molina. Their younger brother Yadier catches for the Cardinals.</p>
        <p>FASTBALL NOT AS FAST -- The radar gun readings for Tigers setup man Joel Zumaya were suspiciously slow on the Busch Stadium scoreboard in Game 3. Zumaya, whose pitches were timed as fast as 103 miles an hour in earlier playoff rounds, was down to around 95 here.</p>
        <p>''It's 102, and if you don't believe it, get a batting helmet and stand in the box, because I've seen it too many times to doubt his fastball,'' Todd Jones said. ''Maybe it was 95 Canadian, I don't know. Maybe it was metric or Celsius.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 1, 2006, Wednesday  A brief sports report in some copies on Thursday about Scott Spiezio of the St. Louis Cardinals misidentified a Topps baseball card of Spiezio's father, Ed, in a Cardinals jersey and holding a bat. It was Card 128 from the 1967 set, not Card 349 from 1968.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 1, 2006, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A brief sports report in some copies on Thursday about Scott Spiezio of the St. Louis Cardinals misidentified a Topps baseball card of Spiezio's father, Ed, in a Cardinals jersey and holding a bat. It was Card 128 from the 1967 set, not Card 349 from 1968.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
