<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Science Show Courts 'Blue-Collar Intellectuals'</title>
    <meta content="03tyso" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/03/arts/television/03tyso.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1794433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hayden Planetarium</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Tyson, Neil DeGrasse</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DC1430F930A35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Science Show Courts 'Blue-Collar Intellectuals'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Science Show Courts ‘Blue-Collar Intellectuals’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Felicia R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Imagine Andy Rooney's knack for the offbeat and the comic in the person of a tall, dark and telegenic scientist with a booming voice.</p>
        <p>Neil deGrasse Tyson would be your guy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neil deGrasse Tyson, director of the Hayden Planetarium and host of “Nova Science Now,” is looking to bring science to the people  the regular people, that is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Imagine Andy Rooney's knack for the offbeat and the comic in the person of a tall, dark and telegenic scientist with a booming voice.</p>
        <p>Neil deGrasse Tyson would be your guy.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tyson, an astrophysicist and the director of the Hayden Planetarium in Manhattan, is the new host of ''Nova Science Now,'' the PBS newsmagazine that begins its second season tonight.</p>
        <p>In the same way that Mr. Rooney explores the mundane, Dr. Tyson said he would use the program to offer what he called a ''cosmic perspective'' on things like the demise of the dinosaurs or the number of molecules in a glass of water. ''There are more molecules in a single glass of water than there are glasses of water in all the oceans of the world,'' he said. That kind of quick ''cosmic biscuit'' (his term) will be only part of a one-hour program that will divvy the cosmos into four snappy segments, including profiles of scientists.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tyson, who delights in noting that he was born the same week that NASA was founded in 1958, said he also hoped the show would capitalize on what he calls underserved ''blue-collar intellectuals.'' They are people who do not necessarily have college degrees but are fascinated by science, he said. Some have seen him on the screen at shows at the Hayden or watched him on television.</p>
        <p>''Most people who stop me in the street and say, 'Dr. Tyson, I saw you on TV,' are in blue-collar jobs. The U.P.S. guy, the sanitation truck driver,'' Dr. Tyson said during an interview in his office at the American Museum of Natural History, where a print of van Gogh's ''Starry Night'' dominates one wall. The advertising campaign for the series -- which shows ordinary people asking Dr. Tyson science questions -- came from those real-life examples. ''We got the idea for the promotion for the show,'' he added, ''when a guy driving a truck stopped me as I took my kids to school and said, 'Dr. Tyson, how are the planets today?' ''</p>
        <p>''It's easy to become curious because there is access to good science today,'' said Dr. Tyson, who lives with his wife and two children in downtown Manhattan. His role as host is to walk the viewer from subject to subject. ''I'll provide the connective tissue between the show segments,'' he added. ''We'll concentrate on things that work thematically, that work visually. What will show up in the news later on?''</p>
        <p>The season premiere -- there are five one-hour shows this season -- has reports on doomsday asteroids, the biology behind the compulsion to eat and the creation of a new element for the periodic table. He can tell what's intriguing, Dr. Tyson said, just by watching faces. ''I've spent enough time bringing the universe to the public that I've become a repository of facial reactions to draw from,'' he said. ''What created the brightest eyes and the most astonished looks.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Tyson thinks science is fun, he says, and he plays against the nerdy scientist stereotype. He is 6-foot-4, well dressed and an agile speaker. He also happens to be athletic and African-American. Reared in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, he attended the Bronx High School of Science before earning degrees in physics from Harvard and a Ph.D. in astrophysics from Columbia.</p>
        <p>He jokes that he was ''star struck'' by his first trip to Hayden, at 9, and after that delighted in looking at the sky through a telescope. But on his third-grade report card his teacher commented, ''Neil should cultivate a more serious attitude toward his school work.'' Dr. Tyson related that story as a visitor perused his 2004 book, ''The Sky Is Not the Limit: Adventures of an Urban Astrophysicist.''</p>
        <p>''Nova'' has been around for 34 years, and its programs attract more than five million viewers each week, said Paula S. Apsell, the senior executive producer for ''Nova.'' ''Science Now'' is a chance to nab viewers who were getting their science news from the Internet, she said (all the ''Science Now'' stories will be streamed on the Web), and Dr. Tyson was their top choice for the second season after the host of the first season, Robert Krulwich, left for NPR.</p>
        <p>''He can talk about the most detailed elements of science in an inviting way,'' she said of Dr. Tyson.</p>
        <p>He also helped bring in high ratings as host of the 2004 ''Origins'' series on ''Nova,'' she said, and science-program viewers who contacted the show said that they wanted to see real scientists. '' 'Nova Science Now' focuses on current research,'' Ms. Apsell said. ''The U.S. funds $250 billion annually in science research and most Americans have no idea of what goes on in the labs.''</p>
        <p>Recalling his own delight in peering at the cosmos from a perch in the Bronx, Dr. Tyson said he was also keen on the notion of making science more accessible. ''You take it out of this priesthood and bring it to the people who are funding it,'' he said, meaning taxpayers whose money is used for scientific research. Those taxpayers, after all, are involved in many debates with science at their core -- abortion, global warming, stem cell research, gender differences, Dr. Tyson said.</p>
        <p>''What you want is a debate with people with different opinions who are scientifically literate,'' he added. ''The scientist won't say 'I know this with certainty.' We don't speak that way. We present evidence that supports an idea. When the evidence is overwhelming, we go on to the next problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
