<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At This Party, The Small Talk Seemed to Be Anything But</title>
    <meta content="21party" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1791690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DB1131F932A1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At This Party, The Small Talk Seemed to Be Anything But</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cocktail party conversation is usually restricted to the witty and the batty: insubstantial, gossip-laden, aphoristic, blithe.</p>
        <p>An authority no less than Oscar Wilde once remarked upon its tendency toward fluff: ''Conversation should touch on everything, but should concentrate on nothing,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cocktail party conversation is usually restricted to the witty and the batty: insubstantial, gossip-laden, aphoristic, blithe.</p>
        <p>An authority no less than Oscar Wilde once remarked upon its tendency toward fluff: ''Conversation should touch on everything, but should concentrate on nothing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then there was the conversation at the Museum of Modern Art last night in which one heard bons mots like, ''John Ashcroft's Justice Department was a fascinating place, truly complex.'' These were tossed off blithely, like crumbs from a cuff, heady stuff for soiree chatter. Even the small talk was as heavy as a horse.</p>
        <p>The occasion was the opening reception for Bill Clinton's world issues conference, a two-day symposium on climate change, ethnic conflict, poverty and global health. With topics like that, it was not surprising that the potentates and business titans there moved in quickly for a drink.</p>
        <p>Shimon Peres, the former prime minister of Israel, rushed off for a tête-à-tête with a mystery man, protected by his guards. Cory A. Booker, the mayor of Newark, might have sprained his wrist he shook so many hands. Madeleine K. Albright, the former secretary of state, was deep in conversation in close vicinity to Russell Simmons, the hip-hop impresario. The president of Chile, Michelle Bachelet, was there, but no one seemed to know which one she was.</p>
        <p>Amid the Twomblys and passed hors d'oeuvres, the crowd was rich, well-dressed and heavy on men. They were deal-makers, risk-takers, money men and software kings. They mentioned that Uzbekistan was a landlocked country surrounded by other landlocked countries. They discussed Central Asian hangover cures.</p>
        <p>When the Rev. Jesse Jackson strolled in, he found himself in the wrong line: the one without the cameras. A word to a staff member rectified that, and soon enough he was again comfortably in front of a lens.</p>
        <p>In the middle of the throng, Mr. Simmons ran into the Rev. Al Sharpton and asked if in the next few days the two could meet. ''I'll text you,'' Mr. Simmons said, growing suddenly concerned. Did the reverend knowing what texting was? (He did.)</p>
        <p>From rum and Coke (one of Richard Nixon's favorites) to lukewarm shots of bourbon (Harry Truman's drink), presidential beverages have always held a fascination with the masses, who crave, with understandable curiosity, to know what their leaders like to drink.</p>
        <p>It was impossible to know what Mr. Clinton likes for the simple reason he was far too busy for the bar. As host, he was the hero of the evening, surrounded by a constant battlement of flesh.</p>
        <p>He arrived at 8 or so with his daughter, Chelsea, for the ritual of photographs and greetings. Mr. Clinton saved a special shake for Jimmy Carter: two white-haired men who used to run the world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has specific gravity and hardly moved from his spot all night. The mountain, as the saying goes, went to Muhammad.</p>
        <p>''It's murder getting in and worse getting out,'' one survivor of the crowd around the president said.</p>
        <p>It was not possible to eavesdrop on his conversations, though one could read reactions to Mr. Clinton's presence by the faces in his midst.</p>
        <p>Among them were The Laugher (giddy and familiar), The Beamer (awestruck and inert), The Confidant (nonchalant and knowing), The Gusher (loose-lipped and ridiculous) and then, of course, The Staffer (agitated and studying a watch).</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there were canapés and bite-sized ravioli and brown stuff in glasses that may have been chocolate mousse. There was also Topsy Chapman in the atrium singing ''Let the Good Times Roll'' while a Sikh in a turban clapped his hands.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chapman's drummer is a young man from New Orleans named Jonathan Batiste. He has played for the swank before, but never a crowd like this.</p>
        <p>He was asked a prying question: Do the leaders of the free world tip the piano man?</p>
        <p>''Hopefully,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
