<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="05obse" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/05/science/05observ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Observatory"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Alberta/Jasper National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mammals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DF1631F936A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After a Fire, Mercury Rises in a Lake’s Food Chain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Fountain</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Snap!</p>
        <p>By most measures, Dunkleosteus terrelli was a monster. An armored prehistoric fish from the Devonian Period about 400 million years ago, it reached lengths of 15 feet or more and a weight approaching a couple of tons. And it didn't fool around. It was a predator, at or near the top of the food chain.</p>
        <p>To be a top predator you've got to have a good bite. Now Philip S. L. Anderson of the University of Chicago and Mark W. Westneat of the Field Museum of Natural History have determined just how good. Dunkleosteus was the most powerful of any fish, living or extinct, they report in Biology Letters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mercury’s rise up the food chain, the most powerful fish ever and another look at the Tagish Lake meteorite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Snap!</p>
        <p>By most measures, Dunkleosteus terrelli was a monster. An armored prehistoric fish from the Devonian Period about 400 million years ago, it reached lengths of 15 feet or more and a weight approaching a couple of tons. And it didn't fool around. It was a predator, at or near the top of the food chain.</p>
        <p>To be a top predator you've got to have a good bite. Now Philip S. L. Anderson of the University of Chicago and Mark W. Westneat of the Field Museum of Natural History have determined just how good. Dunkleosteus was the most powerful of any fish, living or extinct, they report in Biology Letters.</p>
        <p>The scientists developed a biomechanical model of the forces and motion involved in the bite, basing it on five specimens from the Cleveland Museum of Natural History (the fish is named for David Dunkle, a former curator there). In addition to a jaw joint, Dunkleosteus had a joint at the back of its skull. These and other anatomical elements created a linkage system that let the fish open its jaw very rapidly, on the order of 20 milliseconds.</p>
        <p>The fish could close its jaw almost as fast, and the researchers' simulations showed that in doing so very powerful forces were created -- more than 5,000 Newtons on certain parts of the jaw. This is even more powerful than the bite of most land mammals, including the spotted hyena, which has been known to break bones with its jaws.</p>
        <p>The quick powerful bite, combined with teeth that were more like fangs or knife blades, enabled Dunkleosteus to chomp and tear up almost anything, particularly smaller armored fishes.</p>
        <p>Organic Meteorite</p>
        <p>It's been a bit of a roller-coaster ride for the Tagish Lake meteorite, which blazed across the northern Canadian sky nearly seven years ago before fragments fell to Earth on a frozen lake in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>Hailed as potentially the most important meteoritic find in years -- for many reasons, not the least of which is that the fragments were quickly retrieved and kept frozen, preserving any volatile organic compounds within -- Tagish Lake at first seemed something of a disappointment. It's what is known as a carbonaceous chondrite meteorite. But early tests showed few signs that it contained amino acids or other organic acids, as some other carbonaceous chondrites do.</p>
        <p>Now, though, Tagish Lake is starting to live up to its billing. In a study published in Science, NASA researchers report that the meteorite contains organic globules that probably predate the Sun.</p>
        <p>Keiko Nakamura-Messenger and colleagues found evidence of the globules, about a micron in diameter or smaller, in extremely thin slices of the meteorite. Similar globules were first noticed in a meteorite in 1961 and have since been seen in a few other carbonaceous chondrites. But until now there has been no way to adequately analyze them.</p>
        <p>The NASA scientists used a mass spectrometer with a tiny probe and found that the globules contained carbon, nitrogen and hydrogen. Isotopic analysis of the nitrogen and hydrogen determined that the globules had probably formed at temperatures approaching absolute zero.</p>
        <p>That finding, the researchers say, means that the globules probably were created in the outer reaches of the developing solar system or in the molecular cloud that became the Sun. The researchers suggest that if, as is thought, Earth was bombarded by these kinds of meteorites early in its history, such globules may have helped ''seed'' the planet with organic compounds that led to life.</p>
        <p>After a Fire, Mercury Rises in a Lake's Food Chain</p>
        <p>Scientific studies seldom go completely as planned. There can be twists and turns along the way. Or fires, in Erin N. Kelly's case.</p>
        <p>In 2000, Ms. Kelly, a doctoral student at the University of Alberta, was working on her thesis, a study of how mercury in water, invertebrates and fish in the Canadian Rockies varies with elevation. The question has large implications: mercury accumulates through the food chain and can harm people if they eat fish containing too much of it.</p>
        <p>''I went to go and sample my lakes over the elevation gradient,'' Ms. Kelly said, ''and there was this fire.'' A forest fire that summer burned nearly three-quarters of the watershed of Moab Lake in Jasper National Park. So with her adviser, David W. Schindler, she decided to add another facet to her research. ''Dave and I came up with the idea that it might be interesting to see what happened with mercury concentrations in the lake,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Their findings are now in: the fire resulted in a fivefold increase in the concentration of mercury in rainbow trout. But what was even more interesting was the mechanism by which the mercury levels increased, Ms. Kelly, Dr. Schindler and others report in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. The forest fire altered the lake's food chain.</p>
        <p>Ordinarily, one might expect that after a fire, erosion caused by loss of vegetation would result in a rush of mercury (bound in the soil) into the water. And the researchers did find a spike in mercury concentration in the lake after the fire.</p>
        <p>But their experiments showed that the real culprits in increasing the mercury levels in fish were nutrients like nitrogen and phosphorus that washed into the lake. The nutrients increased algal productivity, which in turn led to more young fish, particularly rainbow trout. That caused the adult fish to shift from a largely invertebrate diet to one that consisted of young fish, which had accumulated a great deal of mercury in their own diet.</p>
        <p>This ''lengthening'' of the food chain resulted in a greater accumulation of mercury in the adult fish. ''It's possible that forest fires could cause concentrations in fishes to go over consumption guidelines,'' Ms. Kelly said. Because global climate change is expected to increase the number of forest fires, the findings could have longer-term significance for mercury levels in freshwater fish, she said.</p>
        <p>Observatory</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
