<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Steep Learning Curve</title>
    <meta content="12njcover" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D61231F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Steep Learning Curve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BENSON</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE questions should have been softballs.</p>
        <p>After all, the moderator at a small roundtable held recently by several North Jersey business leaders -- a friendly gathering for a Republican candidate if there ever was one -- wanted to know how State Senator Thomas H. Kean Jr. planned to sell himself to Democratic voters in this year's United States Senate race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE questions should have been softballs.</p>
        <p>After all, the moderator at a small roundtable held recently by several North Jersey business leaders -- a friendly gathering for a Republican candidate if there ever was one -- wanted to know how State Senator Thomas H. Kean Jr. planned to sell himself to Democratic voters in this year's United States Senate race.</p>
        <p>Cautiously and deliberately, as Mr. Kean usually comports himself, he answered, ''I am going to call myself a senator who is going to work in the best interests of New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Asked by a black official about how he would reach out to African-American voters, Mr. Kean again demurred, saying only that he planned to ''continue traveling up and down the state'' and promised to create ''opportunities for everyone.''</p>
        <p>And in response to a question from an executive at a company that finances clean-energy projects on how the state senator felt about the Kyoto Protocols that limit the emission of greenhouse gases, Mr. Kean spoke for nearly five minutes on the relative merits of voluntary limits on emissions without once mentioning the word ''Kyoto,'' or, for that matter, answering the question.</p>
        <p>For someone who is planning to take on Senator Robert Menendez, one of the more experienced and crafty politicians in New Jersey, it was indeed a head-scratching experience. After Mr. Kean left, the people in attendance largely revealed themselves to be sympathetic toward their guest, but not overwhelmed by his delivery.</p>
        <p>Robert De Mers, a Republican official from Passaic County who led the discussion on behalf of the business group, the North Jersey Chamber Consortium, tried to be as diplomatic as possible about the 37-year-old candidate, son of one of the party's icons, former Gov. Thomas H. Kean.</p>
        <p>''Senator Kean is in the process of determining which parts of his message are going to resonate with New Jersey voters,'' Mr. De Mers said.</p>
        <p>Christine Eibs Singer, a registered Democrat who had asked about global warming, was less measured in her assessment: ''I respected his eagerness to tackle different issues, but he seemed to be short on specifics. Frankly, I think there were a few people who asked questions who didn't feel they got answers.''</p>
        <p>It was typical stuff for the opening stages of a campaign in which Mr. Kean has begun in earnest the business of introducing himself to New Jersey, but has at times labored to make an impression.</p>
        <p>It is not as if there haven't been any positive developments for the Kean campaign in recent days. The work of raising money to pay for his statewide political debut began strongly with a fund-raising event featuring Senator John McCain of Arizona -- at which about 250 guests donated $400,000 -- one of several marquee Republicans who have committed themselves to appear on Mr. Kean's behalf.</p>
        <p>And with a primary election filing deadline of April 10 less than a month away, Mr. Kean looks increasingly sure of avoiding a potentially damaging intra-party fight.</p>
        <p>Smoothing the Edges</p>
        <p>But at the same time, the campaign and the candidate are very clearly works in progress.</p>
        <p>As Ross K. Baker, a professor of political science at Rutgers University, put it: ''He's got the reputation for being a very mannerly guy, and that's certainly a nice quality in some areas of life, but in politics, sometimes even at the risk of oversimplifying issues, you really just have to tell people where you stand. Right now, he looks like he's very much in need of a good shot of ectoplasm.''</p>
        <p>There is the matter of Mr. Kean's cautious style: faced with even the softest of softball questions lobbed his way, too often the senator's default reaction is to send himself diving for the dirt. ''He's got to become a bolder candidate than he seems to be at the moment,'' Mr. Baker said.</p>
        <p>Then there is the broader question of his political instincts, found wanting this month as Mr. Kean missed his first political opportunity of the race on the issue of foreign ownership of the Port of Newark. He spoke out too late against the Bush administration's proposed deal giving a Dubai company control of some major seaport operations, handing a glut of favorable and invaluable publicity to Mr. Menendez -- a veteran legislator who spent 14 years in the House and served on the International Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>It was the sort of trepidatious reaction that Mr. Kean, who Republicans consider their strongest hope in a decade for a statewide victory, will have to improve upon in a competitive race against a seasoned and sharp-elbowed opponent.</p>
        <p>''It's a question of poise, it's a question of strategic vision, it's a question of self-confidence and so on,'' Mr. Baker said, ''and I think there is necessarily a very considerable gap.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it led Jennifer Duffy, a political analyst for the Cook Political Report, to marvel a bit at Mr. Kean's anemic start. ''It's interesting because Kean is probably the best statewide candidate the New Jersey Republicans have recruited in a while, but he's saddled with a bad environment in a blue state and it's already tough,'' Ms. Duffy said. ''If he's being timid and not being aggressive enough, that goes to a whole other set of problems -- candidate skills -- and in that case, nothing else even matters.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Kean said that the focus on scoring political points was just a distraction from the issues that are important to the people of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''I personally believe that national security is not about who gets to the microphones first,'' Mr. Kean said over a late dinner of chicken fingers and French fries at Paul's Family Diner on Route 46 in Morris County. ''It's about proposing real solutions.''</p>
        <p>Asked about the notion that he was somewhat less than clear in the way that he presented his ideas, Mr. Kean said, ''I think that anyone who has followed my career knows that I will stand up firmly for what is right, not only on the campaign trail but in Washington, D.C.''</p>
        <p>During his five years in the State Assembly and Senate, Mr. Kean has taken stands on a limited range of such safe issues as governmental ethics and reform of the practice known as pay-to-play. But the problem is that relatively few people in the state -- and almost no one outside his Union County-based legislative district -- know much about him other than his name.</p>
        <p>A Need to Be More Vocal</p>
        <p>Nor will the campaign get any easier. So far, Mr. Kean has talked about paying for homeland security measures, ethics reform and federal tax relief, but has yet to establish a strong identity for himself among statewide voters on any one issue.</p>
        <p>''We certainly need to be more vocal and more repetitive about our solutions to the problems that face the people of this state,'' Mr. Kean eventually allowed.</p>
        <p>For now, the onus is very much on Mr. Kean to break through to voters with a compelling message because as the port controversy showed, Mr. Menendez will be able to use his office -- to which he was appointed in January by Gov. Jon S. Corzine -- to command national attention, such as when he appeared next to fellow Senator Hillary Clinton to denounce the agreement.</p>
        <p>And despite being in favor of cleaning the environment and supporting abortion rights -- in other words, a Republican who is firmly identified with the more moderate wing of the party -- Mr. Kean will have to tread carefully to avoid being tied by his opponent to the conservative policies of President Bush, not an easy maneuver for a man who is also planning to be host to a fund-raising event with Vice President Dick Cheney in Newark on March 20.</p>
        <p>After all, the president's approval rating in New Jersey, according to a recent Fairleigh Dickinson University poll, has fallen below 30 percent. Another Fairleigh Dickinson poll showed Mr. Kean trailing by 5 percentage points among registered voters, and that his name recognition and approval ratings had remained flat since January, while Mr. Menendez's numbers had significantly improved.</p>
        <p>''I think I will continue to focus, and make my primary focus, on what's in the best interest of the people of New Jersey,'' Mr. Kean said. ''That means when I agree with the administration I'll say so, and when I disagree with the administration I will say that as well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kean supports the president's Iraq policy and tax cuts, but said that there were other areas he planned to address in which he clearly differed with the administration, including on environmental policy and, in particular, budget priorities.</p>
        <p>''We have to make sure the government is making these decisions based on merit,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some Built-In Advantages</p>
        <p>Fortunately for him, Mr. Kean also has a number of inherent advantages in the contest against Mr. Menendez. He has, of course, a popular name, giving him the equivalent of millions of dollars' worth of introductory ads he would otherwise have to pay to put on television.</p>
        <p>And he is engaging to the point that he is almost universally liked among his colleagues in Trenton.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in Mr. Menendez, Mr. Kean has an opponent with some potentially serious political liabilities. Mr. Menendez is a leader of the notoriously rough Hudson County Democratic machine -- no great selling point elsewhere in the state -- and he has earned himself the undying enmity of the people he climbed over on his way to power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menendez has also raised a few eyebrows because of reports that he had a romantic relationship with a congressional staff aide and then helped her with a new job as a highly paid consultant. In addition, just last week, the Web site politicsnj.com posted a letter of recommendation for a government contract that Mr. Menendez wrote on behalf of a company whose owner five days later contributed $4,000 to his congressional campaign account.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kean declined to say whether he would raise Mr. Menendez's personal ethics as an issue, offering instead that he would try to highlight what he contends is a poor record of accomplishment during his opponent's tenure in Congress. For instance, Mr. Kean's campaign recently started sending out daily e-mail releases criticizing Mr. Menendez on his voting record on taxes and homeland security.</p>
        <p>But perhaps most importantly for Mr. Kean, with the election nine months away and both candidates still vaguely defined for most New Jerseyans, he still has time to improve as a candidate in what he hopes will be his first successful bid for office outside of his heavily Republican district.</p>
        <p>''The best use of his time right now is just meeting people, talking to everyone he can, hitting every rubber-chicken circuit in the state,'' Ms. Duffy said. ''I would say he's got until around June to really settle on what his message is.''</p>
        <p>Meet and Greet Around the State</p>
        <p>So Mr. Kean has been, as he is fond of saying, ''traveling up and down the state'' to introduce himself to voters and drum up support, as he did late last month in Cape May, Ocean and Camden counties as well as at several meet-and-greet occasions closer to home.</p>
        <p>Last Monday, the senator headed to a well-attended annual St. Patrick's Day fund-raising event in Mountain Lakes organized by Morris County Sheriff Ed Rochford, where he promptly set himself up by the front door to greet guests as they funneled in.</p>
        <p>''Hi, Tom Kean Jr.,'' he said again and again, responding to good luck wishes with a succinct ''with your help.''</p>
        <p>He was greeted with universally good cheer by the guests as he wandered around the affair, and received warm applause from the crowd when a freeholder, John Murphy, toasted him as ''a man I hope will be our next senator.''</p>
        <p>Afterward, at the diner just down the road, Mr. Kean had more well-wishers in a middle-aged couple who stopped by the table to wish the senator luck and offer him some counsel.</p>
        <p>''I've got two pieces of advice for you,'' said the man, Larry Winer of nearby Boonton Township. ''Get your father involved with the campaign, and keep that idiot president away from it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
