<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Many Wasps Make a Pound?</title>
    <meta content="28ctbees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Allergies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wasps (Insects)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hartford (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patterson, Norman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Patterson, Debbie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ahles, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Allergies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/Hartford</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7D61E3EF93BA15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Many Wasps Make a Pound?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DICK AHLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ahles, Dick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Norman Patterson, minister of Covenant of Grace Church, and his wife, Debbie, who live in New Hartford, Conn, and harvest bees and wasps for medical labs that use venom for allergy immunization purposes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESIDENTS of some northwestern Connecticut towns know summer is coming when they see signs along the road informing them they can have bees removed from their property free by checking out www.freeyellowjacketremoval.com.</p>
        <p>Norman Patterson of New Hartford, a beekeeper since childhood and now pastor of the Covenant of Grace Church in New Hartford, removes the hives because he enjoys doing it and because it provides a little extra income for his family of six. He sells the bees by the pound to a medical lab that uses their venom in injections that help immunize people allergic to bee stings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESIDENTS of some northwestern Connecticut towns know summer is coming when they see signs along the road informing them they can have bees removed from their property free by checking out www.freeyellowjacketremoval.com.</p>
        <p>Norman Patterson of New Hartford, a beekeeper since childhood and now pastor of the Covenant of Grace Church in New Hartford, removes the hives because he enjoys doing it and because it provides a little extra income for his family of six. He sells the bees by the pound to a medical lab that uses their venom in injections that help immunize people allergic to bee stings.</p>
        <p>Such allergies can cause reactions that range from itching and swelling to sharp drops in blood pressure or even cardiac arrest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson, who is an ordained Methodist minister, calculates that he needs 6,960 yellow jackets, or the population of 8 to 10 hives, before he has captured a pound. Hornets take less effort with only 4,640 of them to the pound.</p>
        <p>''It takes 15 yellow jackets to make a gram,'' Mr. Patterson said, and there are about 454 grams to a pound. In an average season, Mr. Patterson and his wife, Debbie, collect about 300 nests, which represent about 20 pounds of bees. They do not remove nests that have been treated with pesticides.</p>
        <p>The bee removal season peaks in late summer and early fall. This time of year, Mr. Patterson is looking for beginning hives of the hard-to-find dominulus wasp species, which is relatively new to Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''Bees sell for about $500 a pound on average,'' Mr. Patterson said, ''but the dominulus, which is in great demand in Europe, is worth $2,000 a pound.''</p>
        <p>This spring, Mr. Patterson is bringing the small dominulus hives home and tacking them under his deck. ''Only the queen is in the hives now,'' he said. ''We'll watch the hives grow until they reach their peak in July and then we'll harvest them.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Patterson did the job alone when Mr. Patterson was chaplain of the Master's School, a Christian private school in West Simsbury, from 2000 to 2004. He was also assistant pastor of the Bakerville United Methodist Church in New Hartford for seven years.</p>
        <p>In 2004, he founded the Covenant of Grace Church, a small Presbyterian denomination. The Pattersons have two boys and two girls, ages 8 to 16.</p>
        <p>In addition to the dominulus wasps, the Pattersons collect the more common yellow jackets and hornets for Vespa Laboratories Inc. in Spring Valley, Pa., one of only three labs producing venom for the treatment of insect sting allergies in the country, according to its president, Miles Guralnick.</p>
        <p>To collect white-faced hornets or the dominulus wasps, Mr. Patterson puts the end of a nozzle attached to a plastic container through an opening in the hive. ''Then I pound the hive until the bees fall into the container,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He does not kill the bees, but puts them to sleep with carbon dioxide. He then places them in plastic bags, which he puts into a chest with dry ice. ''The bees are shipped frozen to the lab where each bee's stinger is removed and the venom is taken and processed,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The process kills the bees, but Mr. Patterson said it was for the greater good. He said he ''provides help for many people who would otherwise be suffering from sting-inflicted allergies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson said he and his wife do get stung, but not a lot. ''My wife went through the entire season in 2003 without getting stung once,'' he said. They are protected by hooded one-piece cotton suits with netting over their faces.</p>
        <p>But Debbie Patterson has been stung enough times to develop a recently discovered allergy of her own and she will be receiving injections of the venom, which the lab is providing at no cost to its supplier. Mr. Guralnick said Mr. Patterson is one of about 40 suppliers.</p>
        <p>''He's the only clergyman, but we've had a doctor and a lawyer who do this just because they like it,'' Mr. Guralnick said.</p>
        <p>Dan Palladino remembered that the Pattersons not only removed bees free from his restaurant in downtown Torrington, but also saved him a lot of money.</p>
        <p>''The summer before last, were putting a pitched roof on a flat roof in back of the restaurant and the roof had an old air-conditioner and other equipment that were full of bees,'' Mr. Palladino said.</p>
        <p>''All of a sudden, the guys I was paying big bucks were being bombarded and had to stop work. I called the Pattersons and they were able to get the bees in no time. They're great people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
