<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>There's a New Bad Guy in Town</title>
    <meta content="Stasio.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/17/books/review/Stasio.t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1790417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">LaPierre, Janet</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hamilton, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Grabenstein, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hillerman, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Walter, Jess</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rozan, S J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nadelson, Reggie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E7DD1731F934A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>There's a New Bad Guy in Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">There’s a New Bad Guy in Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stasio, Marilyn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes it seems as if writers of escapist fiction are themselves in need of escape. How else to explain the recent drift of hometown mysteries -- as one might call those locally based whodunits that normally take a stern but essentially benign view of their neighbors' criminal eccentricities?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Small-town gumshoes are increasingly beating the bushes for gun runners and terrorist cells.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes it seems as if writers of escapist fiction are themselves in need of escape. How else to explain the recent drift of hometown mysteries -- as one might call those locally based whodunits that normally take a stern but essentially benign view of their neighbors' criminal eccentricities?</p>
        <p>Not too long ago, the amateur sleuths and professional lawmen who police these regional mysteries were mainly engaged in rooting out individuals who threatened the collective good of the community. Wife-beaters, child abusers and other domestic tyrants could always be counted on to stir up homicidal outrage. Corrupt politicians and rapacious real estate developers also meant trouble, especially when they had their hooks into fragile environments like the Florida Everglades or the majestic forests of the Northwest.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, the forces destabilizing the small towns in these books are the same ones bedeviling big cities -- organized crime, foreign drug cartels, illegal immigration and a host of new ills perceived as threats to national security. Detectives who once applied their ratiocinative skills to the Mystery of Who Fiddled With Grandfather's Will are now beating the bushes for international gun runners and terrorist cells.</p>
        <p>The anxiety levels in current mysteries are so off-the-charts that even a placid community like Port Silva, the picturesque coastal town in Northern California where Janet LaPierre sets her cozy whodunits, is thrown into a state of civil war over a peace march. ''Family Business'' (2006), the latest novel in LaPierre's series, opens on the first anniversary of the Sept. 11 attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon to find Port Silva deeply divided over the impending invasion of Iraq. Antiwar sentiments have been building for months, setting off counterdemonstrations, and on the night of a memorial service for the victims of 9/11 some teenagers are arrested for vandalizing a mosque. Hostilities escalate at an antiwar demonstration at South Bluffs Park, with angry counterprotesters facing down ''Grannies Against War'' and young peaceniks playing guitars and flutes. The peace march ends in the worst possible way when rioting breaks out and two demonstrators fall -- or are pushed -- off the bluff into the sea. No hometown, it seems, is too remote to remain untouched by the tensions of a nation -- and a popular literature -- divided within itself.</p>
        <p>Just try looking on a map for Brimley and Hessel and Paradise, little burgs that figure in ''A Stolen Season'' (2006) and other rugged mysteries that Steve Hamilton sets in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan, on the shores of Lake Superior. But even up here, ''as far away from civilization as you can get without leaving the country,'' people are uneasy about a new breed of criminal who knows no loyalty to clan or country. Unlike the local Indians trafficking in prescription drugs and the biker gangs peddling home-made meth, the gang smuggling assault weapons across the porous Canadian border doesn't care who buys its lethal wares or what wars they start with them.</p>
        <p>The rawboned men (and equally hardy women) who thrive in the harsh and lonely environment of Hamilton's novels don't have much to say about global warming -- not when the weather is so foggy and fierce they can barely send up a few fireworks over Waishkey Bay on the Fourth of July. But even the laid-back hippie proprietor of the only inn and taproom in Paradise senses some freakish disturbance in the air. ''It just feels strange,'' he says. ''Did you see that sky out there? It looks like the world's gonna end soon. ... It's just ... wrong,'' he concludes. ''Something in the air is just plain broken.''</p>
        <p>That premonition of a ''broken'' world at the end of days is something that has been making its way into popular crime fiction ever since 9/11. International thrillers responded fairly quickly, moving their operational theaters to the Middle East and retooling their plots for Islamic terrorists. Other shifts in the genre have been more subtle: an uptick in historical detective fiction, a trendy turn to metaphysical religious themes and supernatural subject matter, and a wave of nostalgia-based plots.</p>
        <p>But traditional detective stories are not built for far-flung action or retreats into fantasy. However romanticized, the small suburban towns and rural hamlets depicted in regional whodunits are grounded in reality. Their amateur sleuths and local police officers, charged with keeping the peace at home, are compelled to process even the gravest of national events through the prism of that hometown perspective.</p>
        <p>This is not at all to say that authors of regional crime novels must keep their distance from world events. But it does mean that writers who want their mysteries to reflect these new realities -- without going outside the genre conventions -- must make new use of the mystery's highly flexible form. ''Tilt a Whirl'' (2005), a first novel by Chris Grabenstein, seemed a promising start to a light-hearted series about a young beach cop who teams up with an older officer to police the colorful crimes that residents of their New Jersey shore community try to get away with. But while the humor of the situation holds up in the sequel, ''Mad Mouse'' (2006), the relationship between the kiddie cop and his mentor, a combat-seasoned veteran of the war in Iraq, has deepened into something more substantial than a comic buddy routine. In an author interview, Grabenstein said he based his fictional vet on some soldiers he once met who had served in Bosnia, and took the character's ''code of chivalry'' from the ''firefighters and cops who ran up the staircases of the World Trade Center when everybody else was running down.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after 9/11, Tony Hillerman brought out a novel, ''The Sinister Pig'' (2003), in which the Navajo cops who normally deal with internal tribal affairs in his Southwestern mysteries put themselves on border patrol. On the watch for illegal aliens, they discover a plot to sabotage oil pipelines in the San Juan Basin of New Mexico (''the very heart of America's version of the Persian Gulf'') and find themselves in the middle of a jurisdictional power struggle among the F.B.I., the D.E.A., the Border Patrol and the Bureau of Land Management -- which escalates into open warfare when Homeland Security gets into the act.</p>
        <p>Jess Walter, who started out writing muscular procedural thrillers based on real-life serial murder cases in Spokane, Wash. (''the trailer park of the Pacific Northwest''), detoured into historical fiction with last year's ''Citizen Vince.'' His latest novel, ''The Zero,'' is a black comedy that takes a bizarre view of the aftermath of 9/11 by creating a sinister Office of Liberty and Recovery whose official job is to analyze every scrap of paper blown from the twin towers.</p>
        <p>New York authors (and yes, New York is just as much somebody's hometown as Spokane or Port Silva) have hesitated to re-structure the formulas of their series novels, although just about every cop, private eye and amateur sleuth has clearly been changed by the events of 9/11. S. J. Rozan, who maintains a smart series about sleuthing partners who work out of Chinatown, wrote a stand-alone crime novel, ''Absent Friends'' (2004), about a group of Staten Island friends who lost one of their own when the twin towers fell. But that was as unusual as finding a New Orleans novelist ready to incorporate the horrific disaster of Hurricane Katrina into the plot of a conventional whodunit.</p>
        <p>More characteristic of what's happening in the genre can be seen in Reggie Nadelson's procedural series about a Russian-born cop named Artie Cohen who works a beat in Brooklyn. In ''Disturbed Earth'' (2005), the traumatized city serves as the dramatic backdrop for a missing-child case that Artie is investigating. But in his new book, ''Red Hook,'' which finds him assigned to the 2004 Republican Convention, the political fallout from the administration's ''war on terror'' has become the heart of the story.</p>
        <p>In truth, hometown mysteries have never been mindless flights from reality. Because every detective story both reflects and corrects the collective fears of a community, foiling the crooked lawyer who doctored grandfather's will or running that real estate raider off the family farm is simply an imaginative way to reassure readers that there is still justice in the world. So far, that comforting formula seems to be adapting itself to more heightened threats, from drug cartels in New England and schoolyard shootings in the Midwest to arson attacks on the Pacific Coast. The question now is what it might take for the decent detectives in hometown mysteries to throw up their hands and say: ''This one beats me. This is one atrocity that I just can't solve.''</p>
        <p>ESSAY Marilyn Stasio writes the Crime column for the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marilyn Stasio writes the Crime column for the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
