<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tending the Fire, and the Woodpile</title>
    <meta content="10RhomeWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1810827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="HOME WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fireplaces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDF1731F933A25751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tending the Fire, and the Woodpile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES McGRATH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE burn a lot of wood at our place. We do it mostly for the same reason they burn wood at genteel old clubs and expensive hotels -- for atmosphere -- but occasionally we do it for warmth. Two winters ago, when we were renovating the second floor of our house, the plumber who was supposed to be working on the heating system went AWOL, and for a couple of months we lived a suburban version of ''Little House on the Prairie.'' Dinner in front of the downstairs fireplace; then quickly to bed, in down vests and stocking hats, before the bedroom fire burned out.</p>
        <p>Romantic at first, the whole drill -- lugging the logs upstairs, hauling the ashes down, waking in the morning to see your breath in front of you -- quickly grew old, and we rediscovered what people have known for centuries: that the fireplace is not, in truth, a very efficient heating device. In a house as old and drafty as ours, it's essentially an engine for sucking in cold air, warming it up and then quickly shooting it out the chimney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE burn a lot of wood at our place. We do it mostly for the same reason they burn wood at genteel old clubs and expensive hotels -- for atmosphere -- but occasionally we do it for warmth. Two winters ago, when we were renovating the second floor of our house, the plumber who was supposed to be working on the heating system went AWOL, and for a couple of months we lived a suburban version of ''Little House on the Prairie.'' Dinner in front of the downstairs fireplace; then quickly to bed, in down vests and stocking hats, before the bedroom fire burned out.</p>
        <p>Romantic at first, the whole drill -- lugging the logs upstairs, hauling the ashes down, waking in the morning to see your breath in front of you -- quickly grew old, and we rediscovered what people have known for centuries: that the fireplace is not, in truth, a very efficient heating device. In a house as old and drafty as ours, it's essentially an engine for sucking in cold air, warming it up and then quickly shooting it out the chimney.</p>
        <p>Few domestic events are as pleasing as a fire, however, and so at the slightest hint of a chill, even on a summer evening, we will happily light up. How much wood we go through in a year is hard to say, because the official measurement for firewood, the cord, is in fact highly arbitrary. Strictly speaking, a cord is a pile 8 feet long, 4 feet high and 4 feet deep, but that has long since been devalued into the so-called ''face cord,'' a pile 8 feet long, 4 feet high and 1 log wide, and even the face cord is just a metaphor these days. A genuine cord of wood is however much the wood guy decides to give you, and corresponds roughly to the size of his dump-truck bed, unless he has a really big dump truck, in which case he eyeballs it.</p>
        <p>The wood guy pours your wood out on the driveway, you look at the pile, which appears considerably smaller than last year's, and say, ''You sure that's a cord?''</p>
        <p>''Oh, yeah, that's a cord,'' he replies, and you hand him his check.</p>
        <p>The logs in your pile are supposed to be ''seasoned hardwood,'' which is the only kind that wood guys advertise. (You never see signs for ''Fresh-cut softwood.'') But these terms, too, are metaphorical woodspeak. Poking around in the pile, you will almost certainly find a fair amount of pine, maybe even some birch, which burns so fast and with so much residue that it's the firewood equivalent of the rolled-up newspaper. This is not necessarily the end of the world, if you figure that if you didn't have this particular load of wood, rolled-up newspapers are exactly what you would be tossing into the fireplace.</p>
        <p>More worrisome is that those pine logs are dripping pitch and the others still smell fresh and sappy. If you clink two together, they don't ring the way properly aged firewood does; they thud. To burn well, firewood ought to dry for at least six months, but as often as not ''seasoned'' firewood is wood that was cut a few weeks ago. This is because in the suburbs the wood guys are actually landscapers, who don't have woodlots. They need all their open space for the shrubs and saplings they want to sell you, so that these can thrive and eventually grow so large and unruly that you will require the landscaper's services once again. This is why we live in the suburbs, of course: to be part of nature's mysterious and eternal cycle, the growing up, the cutting down, the buying back of the very trees, now neatly sawn into logs, we once paid to have removed.</p>
        <p>The problem with unseasoned wood is that it won't burn, and then when it finally does (goosed, perhaps, by one of those artificial, pressed-wax log-substitutes), it leaves creosote deposits in the chimney, and these, if not regularly removed, can cause 20-foot plumes of flame to shoot from your chimney top. More times than I am comfortable admitting, we have had to summon the local fire department to deal with a chimney blaze -- an experience that is always extremely embarrassing, and was once quite expensive as well, because for some reason, after shooting carbon dioxide up the chimney, the firefighters then dug up the hearth.</p>
        <p>Another time, a familial post-Christmas evening was interrupted by a complete stranger pounding on the door and shouting: ''Everybody out! Everybody out!'' He was overreacting, I thought, but I did see his point when he made me step outside with him to where the night sky was brightly illuminated by flame emanating from my own chimney flue. Pizza boxes this time, and though I no longer use them as fuel, they are, fortunately, a fairly quick burn.</p>
        <p>The latest thing in upscale suburban construction are gas fireplaces that can be lighted and extinguished by remote control. They are more convincing than you may imagine, though gas burns much bluer than wood. They are also so effortless as to make the whole hearthside experience not much different from watching a fire on TV. No mess; no logs, damp, moldy and hard to light; no sparks popping out and charring the living room rug so that it gives off an acrid whiff of burning wool. No yearly conversation with the wood guy. No making coffee for the firefighters.</p>
        <p>It used to be a country truism that wood warms you twice, once when you cut it and again when you burn it. That no longer applies in the age of the chain saw, though when I do cut my own wood these days, I experience a pulse-quickening frisson: the fear of wounding myself. Still, a certain effortfulness -- fussing and worrying, even -- is an essential part of the wood-gathering and burning experience. Fire came to our cave-dwelling ancestors as a great gift but also as a bother. Part of what makes sitting in front of the fireplace so sweet is the ancient awareness that eventually the fire will go out and if you don't do something about the next one, you will wind up in the cold.</p>
        <p>HOME WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
