<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Blair-Brown Dance: Can Britain Follow Their Steps?</title>
    <meta content="21britain" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/21/international/europe/21britain.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1741347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Tony</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Gordon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2D9113EF932A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Blair-Brown Dance: Can Britain Follow Their Steps?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Blair-Brown Dance: Can Britain Follow Their Steps?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of talk and rumor, denial and debate, Tony Blair's transfer of power to Gordon Brown may actually have begun, but stealthily.</p>
        <p>In a relationship conducted through the signs and whispers of deniability rather than public debate, nothing has been formally declared. But last week, Mr. Brown, the chancellor of the exchequer, made a long-heralded and quasi-Churchillian speech about the effort to curb terrorism -- a distinct expansion of the topics he usually covers as finance minister to cover ground usually reserved for the prime minister. The same day, he went on to steward major legislation through the House of Commons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of rumor, Tony Blair's transfer of power to Gordon Brown may have begun, but stealthily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years of talk and rumor, denial and debate, Tony Blair's transfer of power to Gordon Brown may actually have begun, but stealthily.</p>
        <p>In a relationship conducted through the signs and whispers of deniability rather than public debate, nothing has been formally declared. But last week, Mr. Brown, the chancellor of the exchequer, made a long-heralded and quasi-Churchillian speech about the effort to curb terrorism -- a distinct expansion of the topics he usually covers as finance minister to cover ground usually reserved for the prime minister. The same day, he went on to steward major legislation through the House of Commons.</p>
        <p>Spreading his political wings last month, he mused in a speech on the nature of Britishness. In the same vein, he plans to discuss the environment, education, transportation, science and technology and foreign affairs in a series of speeches offering a political overview well beyond his formal responsibilities. Television reporters have taken to analyzing his attire, seeking clues about his political intentions in the switch from his hallmark red tie (Socialist!) to a pink tie (more moderate).</p>
        <p>One reason for the burst of coded messages may be that Mr. Brown and Mr. Blair are positioning themselves for the next election, possibly in 2009, in which Mr. Brown is widely expected to be the Labor candidate to face David Cameron, the Conservative leader. Another may be that Mr. Blair and Mr. Brown are now co-leaders in an undeclared shared premiership. Some see a mix of both.</p>
        <p>''It is part of a strategy intended not so much (though widely interpreted) as a dual prime ministership, but an early attempt to define Mr. Brown as the weighty, reliable figure and Mr. Cameron as a gadfly who is energetic but fundamentally unfocused,'' the columnist Anne McElvoy wrote in The Evening Standard.</p>
        <p>Does it matter? Yes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown is almost sure to be Labor's next candidate. But his likely behavior as prime minister remains a matter of speculation, even though he has been a prominent figure for years and was a major player in the election victory in 1997 that ended Labor's 18 years in opposition.</p>
        <p>Will he scare the middle class by abandoning Mr. Blair's center ground for the old-left values of higher taxation and more public spending? Or will he disappoint Labor's socialist stalwarts by shifting more to the center -- the area Mr. Cameron wishes to occupy? The answer to those questions will determine how Britons are educated, how they finance their health care, where they deploy their armed forces and the degree to which the middle class bears a greater burden of taxes.</p>
        <p>The issues come to the fore because of Mr. Blair's fretfulness about his legacy. True, in a series of parliamentary votes last week (one taken while he was in South Africa), Mr. Blair's party won victories that will remodel Britain in noticeable ways, moving closer the introduction of mandatory identity cards and banning smoking in enclosed places, including the traditionally hazy British pub.</p>
        <p>But from a broader perspective, Mr. Blair's global ambitions seem petrified. He has not, as he promised when he came to power in 1997, placed Britain at the heart of European decision making, in part because of his alliance with the White House over Iraq. Iraq itself is as messy, if not quite so deadly, for Britain as for the United States. Enduring changes on the big domestic themes of health, crime and education remain elusive.</p>
        <p>The current rash of signals from the inscrutable Mr. Brown -- most of them supportive of Mr. Blair -- ''tells us very little of what to expect when Brown's day finally comes,'' said Polly Toynbee, a columnist in The Guardian. ''Expect no more than a tiny flash of the cardinal's red lining in what he says now.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, talk of his succession is everywhere.</p>
        <p>In Parliament this week, for instance, the former Conservative leader William Hague stood in as deputy for Mr. Cameron, who was on paternity leave after the birth of his third child. Standing opposite the prime minister, Mr. Hague told Mr. Blair, with cruel wit and to raucous laughter, that it was probably the first time in history that all three main parties were being represented by ''stand-in leaders'' -- implying that Mr. Blair had somehow become Mr. Brown's junior. (The third stand-in was Sir Menzies Campbell, acting head of the Liberal Democrats during a protracted and continuing leadership contest.)</p>
        <p>The newspapers routinely run articles quoting ''Brownites'' or ''Blairites'' to offer a running commentary on the state of the rivalry, though there is one theory being offered that the threat posed by Mr. Cameron as Conservative leader has forced both men into a truce.</p>
        <p>And, since a crushing by-election defeat for Labor in a Scottish stronghold, in Mr. Brown's home district, no less, Labor has also had to ponder its own popularity.</p>
        <p>The satirical magazine Private Eye made a point of that with its Valentine's Day cover. ''Together again,'' it said of the two men, whose rivalry has often burst into dispute. A heart-shaped photograph showed Mr. Brown and Mr. Blair reciting a poem: ''Roses are red, violets are blue. No one loves me, and no one loves you!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has denied that he has made an arrangement with Mr. Blair to run the country jointly. Indeed, some people challenge the very idea that Mr. Brown's premiership should be automatic.</p>
        <p>Charles Clarke, the home secretary and a senior member of Mr. Blair's government, said he ''would be very surprised if there weren't a leadership contest'' to replace Mr. Blair, who has said he will not run in a fourth election but will serve a ''full'' third term.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has acknowledged only that ''Tony Blair and I are talking about the long-term challenges ahead'' in areas as varied as climate change and child care. ''We get on with the job of running the country,'' he said, ''and taking the decisions that matter.''</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
