<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Detroit Calls, U.S. May Not Replay the Bailout Role</title>
    <meta content="14bailout" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/14/automobiles/14bailout.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Ford Motor Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDD163FF937A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Detroit Calls, U.S. May Not Replay the Bailout Role</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Auto Bailout Seems Unlikely</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDUARDO PORTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gasoline prices are rising. Sales of Detroit's carmakers suffer as Japanese brands carve out a growing share of the American market. One of the nation's largest automobile manufacturers flirts with bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Sound familiar?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The government shows no signs of hurrying to the auto industry's rescue and the reasons are telling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gasoline prices are rising. Sales of Detroit's carmakers suffer as Japanese brands carve out a growing share of the American market. One of the nation's largest automobile manufacturers flirts with bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Sound familiar?</p>
        <p>Just over a quarter of a century ago, the Chrysler Corporation teetered on the brink of bankruptcy, hobbled by falling sales, heavy payroll costs and bloated debt.</p>
        <p>Today General Motors and Ford, staggering under the costs of providing health benefits for workers and retirees and with few cars that excite consumers, are still struggling to compete against their Japanese (and Korean) rivals. And now it is G.M. that is skirting the edge of financial disaster.</p>
        <p>But don't expect a rerun of Detroit's earlier drama. In the late 1970's, car companies were considered too big and too important to fail. Washington not only put up trade barriers to Japanese cars and trucks, it also agreed to bail out Chrysler with government-backed loans aimed at preserving the company and its jobs.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the government today shows no signs of hurrying to the auto industry's rescue. The reasons are telling. American car companies and the United Automobile Workers have lost much of their political influence as their share of the nation's output and employment has shrunk. The industry's composition has changed too.</p>
        <p>Back then, the Big Three, which had their headquarters in Detroit, were the national auto industry. Today the industry includes the American manufacturing plants of Japanese and Korean companies, which are doing just fine at providing popular vehicles and have created tens of thousands of good jobs for Americans.</p>
        <p>And it is less obvious what Washington could do to help.</p>
        <p>''In the current climate, the government would be very reluctant to step in and protect one company in a much larger industry,'' said Stewart J. Schwab, an expert in labor law and dean of Cornell Law School. ''They would have to wonder whether they are just helping the inefficient; that's not a good long-term strategy.''</p>
        <p>As Chrysler was tottering in 1979, President Jimmy Carter and the Democratic-controlled Congress cobbled together a rescue plan that included $1.5 billion in federal loan guarantees and a package of concessions worth several billion dollars more from others interested in Chrysler's survival, including its union, its bankers and its dealers.</p>
        <p>The Carter administration also made a 25 percent tariff on imports of Japanese light trucks unavoidable -- building a protective wall around what were to become Detroit's hottest products: sport utility vehicles and minivans.</p>
        <p>The effort was bipartisan and it continued into the 1980's. One of the first things the Reagan administration did upon taking office in 1981 was to press Japan to agree to so-called voluntary export restraints by its carmakers.</p>
        <p>Today, the automakers' troubles are arguably on an even greater scale. General Motors lost more than $10 billion last year as the high cost of gasoline made consumers shun its large S.U.V.'s., further eroding its market share. This only added to G.M.'s structural problems, associated with the cost of providing pensions and health care to its army of retired workers.</p>
        <p>G.M. said last year that it would cut 30,000 jobs and close all or parts of 12 plants by 2008. Last month, it offered a buyout program to all 113,000 unionized workers. The company's debt has been downgraded to junk bond status. Ford is facing similar troubles. Delphi, the nation's largest auto parts maker, is in bankruptcy and wants to shed about two-thirds of its work force in the United States.</p>
        <p>Yet despite the long list of woes, neither the White House nor Congress is rushing to the rescue.</p>
        <p>''We might be coming to a crisis faster than we thought,'' said Senator Richard G. Lugar, Republican of Indiana, who with Paul E. Tsongas, then a Democratic senator from Massachusetts, hammered out the Senate version of the bill that led to Chrysler's rescue. ''It's not that people are dismissive but they just haven't given it that much thought.''</p>
        <p>At a news conference in 1980, Mr. Carter justified the government's involvement in the Chrysler bailout as necessary ''to avoid the loss of hundreds of thousands of American jobs among automobile workers and to keep a highly competitive automobile industry in our country.''</p>
        <p>In January, President Bush suggested that carmakers solve their own problems by making cars that are ''relevant.'' Referring to President Carter's decision to help Chrysler, he noted, ''I would hope I wouldn't be asked to make that decision.''</p>
        <p>Washington's change of tune is, perhaps, understandable: in the 1970's, not only was the economy sliding into a recession, the United States still understood itself as a strong manufacturing nation -- and cars represented one of its most important industries.</p>
        <p>''It's a much smaller part of the U.S. economy than it was then,'' said Robert J. Barbera, chief economist of ITG/Hoenig, who as an economist on the staff of Senator Tsongas helped devise the Chrysler bailout in 1979. ''Today 9 out of 10 jobs in the United States are not in manufacturing.''</p>
        <p>The share of gross domestic product from motor vehicle output is down by about a third since the late 1970's, to 3.2 percent. In 1978, makers of cars and auto parts employed 1.4 percent of all private sector workers; the figure today is less than 1 percent.</p>
        <p>Even in Michigan, the automotive sector's share of employment has fallen by about half, to some 6 percent of all nonfarm jobs.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress who voted for the Chrysler bill ''worried that thousands of people would lose their jobs needlessly,'' said James J. Blanchard, a former Michigan governor who led negotiations for the Chrysler bill as a House representative from the state. ''The cost in welfare and pension guarantees would be astronomical. It would have been a serious blow to a precarious national economy.''</p>
        <p>Today, General Motors is insistent that it does not want a direct government bailout. ''One thing we haven't done is go to the federal government and enlist their aid in respect to our current situation,'' said Christopher Preuss, a G.M. spokesman.</p>
        <p>Yet Detroit is certainly interested in other forms of help from Washington. The Big Three, with their older, heavily unionized work forces, are competing against imports and transplants built without the burden of ''legacy costs'' accumulated through decades of increasingly elaborate contracts. They would love a hand from the government to remove the health care expenses of retirees from their books.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they complain bitterly that Japan keeps the value of the yen artificially low, lowering the cost of Japanese carmakers' imports of cars and parts from Japan.</p>
        <p>But these days Detroit no longer has a near monopoly on domestic production. Having started building plants in the United States in the early 1980's, foreign carmakers like Toyota and Honda now account for over a quarter of the output of vehicles built for consumers. They employ about a fifth of workers engaged in making cars and trucks. Many more Americans are involved in designing, marketing and repairing foreign brands.</p>
        <p>And the cars are selling well: the United States market share of brands from Asia jumped to 37 percent last year from 35 percent in 2004, according to Thomas W. LaSorda, chief executive of the Chrysler Group of DaimlerChrysler.</p>
        <p>Other factors are also staying the government's hand. More than a quarter of a century since the Chrysler bailout, there is a much firmer belief in the ability of market forces to deal with the problems facing the big car companies.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Chrysler is today much healthier than General Motors and Ford, in part because it was bought by Daimler-Benz of Germany, creating DaimlerChrysler. And bankruptcy, which would allow G.M. to rewrite union contracts, is not necessarily regarded as a death sentence.</p>
        <p>Even if Washington were willing to step up to bat for Detroit, it is not clear that it has the necessary firepower. The total Chrysler rescue package of 1979 was worth less than $5 billion -- somewhat less than $15 billion in today's money -- and the government ended up guaranteeing only $1.2 billion worth of loans.</p>
        <p>At the end of last year, General Motors estimated that its overall unfunded liabilities to cover retiree health care and life insurance amounted to $62 billion. Ford's added up to about $33 billion.</p>
        <p>More far-reaching legislation -- to create a national health care system, for example -- might pull the car companies out of their hole. But nobody is counting on that kind of help.</p>
        <p>''While spiraling health care costs are a monumental issue for the entire economy,'' Mr. Preuss of G.M. said, ''we're not counting on any immediate legislative relief that would change the current situation.''</p>
        <p>In some areas, the politics are going against Detroit's interests. California and a number of other states, mostly in the Northeast (where foreign cars are often more popular than domestic vehicles), are pressing the industry for drastic reductions in the level of greenhouse gases coming out of car and truck tailpipes.</p>
        <p>To reverse the industry's decline, even Detroit's most ardent supporters in Congress have come up with only modest ideas.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, a Democrat from Michigan, introduced a bill in the House last year that would force the administration to seek redress at the World Trade Organization over currency manipulation by Japan and other countries. It has little chance in Congress.</p>
        <p>Bills have been introduced in the House and Senate to give tax breaks for car companies' investments in alternative fuel technologies and other energy-saving initiatives. Their prospects are somewhat brighter.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration has also tried to help via regulation. The new fuel efficiency rules issued last month, which set relatively modest targets for large sport utility vehicles, were seen as a victory for the Big Three, which have the heaviest S.U.V. fleets.</p>
        <p>''There's no grand solution,'' said Dennis Fitzgibbons, director for public policy at DaimlerChrysler in Washington. ''But there are a number of smaller things that could be done.''</p>
        <p>It is still possible, of course, that Washington might be moved to respond. In 1980, Chrysler was only weeks from filing for bankruptcy by the time the government acted. If G.M. were to be pulled even further into trouble by a strike at Delphi, its biggest supplier, that shut G.M.'s own assembly lines and if it were truly tottering on the brink, the urge to keep it from tipping over might prove too great to resist.</p>
        <p>''This type of event could really galvanize people,'' Mr. Fitzgibbons said. ''But do I know which way they would go? No.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
