<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expected Ban on Primatene Mist Raises Some Concerns</title>
    <meta content="12asthma" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/12/business/12asthma.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1761057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Epinephrine (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Albuterol (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wyeth</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7D7173EF931A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expected Ban on Primatene Mist Raises Some Concerns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Expected Ban on Primatene Mist Raises Some Concerns</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Asthmatics, their families and advocates for minority groups and poor oppose decision by advisory committee of Food and Drug Administration to ban Primatene Mist; epinephrine inhaler, on market for about 40 years, contains propellant harmful to earth's ozone layer and is only over-the-counter method of quelling asthma attack; advocates say it is often only remedy available to those who do not see doctors and cannot afford or otherwise obtain prescription drugs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The situation looked dire. While Jay Kraeszig of Zionsville, Ind., was on vacation in Florida a few years ago, he had a severe asthma attack and realized he had left his albuterol inhaler in his hotel room.</p>
        <p>''He was turning gray,'' his wife, Mary D. Kraeszig, recalled in an interview. ''Probably another couple of minutes and he wouldn't have been conscious.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Primatene Mist, on the market for about 40 years, could be the next asthma inhaler banned because it uses a propellant harmful to the ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The situation looked dire. While Jay Kraeszig of Zionsville, Ind., was on vacation in Florida a few years ago, he had a severe asthma attack and realized he had left his albuterol inhaler in his hotel room.</p>
        <p>''He was turning gray,'' his wife, Mary D. Kraeszig, recalled in an interview. ''Probably another couple of minutes and he wouldn't have been conscious.''</p>
        <p>Fortunately, she said, there was a Wal-Mart nearby. She dashed in and bought Primatene Mist, an asthma inhaler available without a prescription. It relieved the attack in minutes.</p>
        <p>But Primatene Mist, on the market for about 40 years, could be the next asthma inhaler banned because it uses a propellant harmful to the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>An advisory committee of the Food and Drug Administration decided by a vote of 11 to 7 in January that the product, which contains the drug epinephrine, is not medically essential and therefore should not be exempt from a global treaty mandating the elimination of ozone-destroying products.</p>
        <p>But people like Ms. Kraeszig say that Primatene, the only over-the-counter method of quelling an asthma attack, is a vital stopgap for people caught without their prescription albuterol inhalers. And some advocates for minority groups and the poor say that Primatene is often the only remedy available to those who do not see doctors and cannot afford or otherwise obtain prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>''These inhalers are all that, in many cases, stand between them, as an asthmatic, and the emergency room or worse,'' Manuel Mirabal, president of the National Puerto Rican Coalition, testified at the January F.D.A. meeting.</p>
        <p>The drug maker Wyeth, which sold $43 million of Primatene Mist last year, estimates that two million to three million people use the product -- two-thirds of them as a backup for albuterol and the other third as their sole medication. Armstrong Pharmaceuticals, which makes the product for Wyeth, also makes epinephrine inhalers sold as store brands, and those, too, would be removed from the market. Armstrong is a unit of Amphastar Pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>Wyeth said it had been unable so far, after years of effort, to develop an epinephrine inhaler that would be effective and acceptable to consumers but would use a propellant that does not harm the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Wyeth, which is now working jointly with Armstrong, urged the F.D.A. to keep Primatene on the market until an alternative is ready, which it estimated would be around 2011.</p>
        <p>But some of the physicians on the F.D.A. advisory committee had little sympathy. They said that despite Primatene's long history of use, there was little evidence of the drug's safety and effectiveness. Epinephrine is a synthetic version of the human hormone adrenaline.</p>
        <p>These doctors said Primatene could even harm patients because of side effects or because users might forgo better treatments. Removing it from the market, they said, could be an opportunity to switch asthma patients to better medications.</p>
        <p>''It is clearly not optimum therapy and I think suboptimal therapy is a disservice to our patients,'' said Dr. Mark L. Brantly, a pulmonary physician at the University of Florida.</p>
        <p>Other committee members countered that even though Primatene was not ideal, it should remain available. ''I think it's naïve on our part to think that if this medication went away that these people would access appropriate care,'' Dr. Mary E. Tinetti of Yale said.</p>
        <p>The F.D.A., which usually follows the recommendations of its advisory committees, has not yet announced its decision. It plans to issue a proposed rule that would still be subject to public comment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kraeszig, a veterinarian, has already commented. After seeing a news report about the committee's decision, she sent an e-mail message to the F.D.A. telling how her husband's life was saved by the over-the-counter product. ''If you ban Primatene Mist without another available O.T.C. substitute,'' she wrote, ''people will undoubtedly die.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
