<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Says Lower Oil Prices Won't Blunt New-Fuel Push</title>
    <meta content="13fuel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/13/business/13fuel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1796797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DF1130F930A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Says Lower Oil Prices Won't Blunt New-Fuel Push</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Says Lower Oil Prices Won’t Blunt New-Fuel Push</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXEI BARRIONUEVO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barrionuevo, Alexei</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a tailwind of strong political support behind them, advocates for renewable fuels declared Thursday that ethanol is here to stay and issued a call for greater research and investment to solve the challenges still preventing broader use.</p>
        <p>At a conference to promote bio-fuels, President Bush suggested that the push to wean America from its oil addiction would be a priority of the last two years of his presidency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush suggested that the push to wean America from its oil addiction would be a priority of the last two years of his presidency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a tailwind of strong political support behind them, advocates for renewable fuels declared Thursday that ethanol is here to stay and issued a call for greater research and investment to solve the challenges still preventing broader use.</p>
        <p>At a conference to promote bio-fuels, President Bush suggested that the push to wean America from its oil addiction would be a priority of the last two years of his presidency.</p>
        <p>''Let me put it bluntly,'' Mr. Bush said. ''We are too dependent on oil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush promised that his administration would continue to pay for research into breakthrough technologies in ethanol, hybrid vehicles and nuclear power, and would uphold tax credits that he said were encouraging private investment to flood into the sector.</p>
        <p>While saying that corn-produced ethanol was good for farmers and good for the country's economy, he also said ethanol from noncorn crops, like wood chips and switchgrass, a tall, drought-resistant prairie grass, would be needed to supply enough of the fuel to substantially blunt America's dependence on oil.</p>
        <p>''The low gas prices,'' he said, ''are not going to dim my enthusiasm to diversify from oil.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's speech capped a two-day conference that featured government and industry leaders, including three members of Mr. Bush's cabinet, chief executives from Fortune 500 companies like Archer Daniels Midland and DuPont, and venture capitalists like Vinod Khosla.</p>
        <p>Industry groups, in particular the National Corn Growers Association, have been holding a series of meetings across the country in recent months to cheerlead for ethanol and biodiesel, which are at the center of broad efforts to overhaul the Midwestern farm economy.</p>
        <p>''We are guided by the need to structure and scale renewable energy projects to be commercially viable and replicable,'' said Alexander Karsner, assistant secretary for energy efficiency and renewable energy at the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>The conference was an unusual collaboration between the Energy and Agriculture Departments, which jointly organized the event.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department described some of its efforts to develop cheaper, more efficient ethanol from noncorn crops, but the central investment appeared to be $250 million over five years to "crack the technological barriers to developing wide-scale and cost-effective biofuels."</p>
        <p>The critical issue is making a breakthrough in the cost of cellulosic ethanol, made from plant waste or nonedible crops. That fuel costs at least twice as much per gallon to produce today as corn-based ethanol.</p>
        <p>The ethanol boom is at the heart of farm state politics these days, and some attendees dismissed the carefully stage-managed celebration, which included rock music, but no opportunity to ask prominent speakers any questions.</p>
        <p>Some major issues were discussed. R. James Woolsey, the former director of the Central Intelligence Agency, said federal subsidies for ethanol should be revised to allow the industry to be more self-supporting. He agreed with a suggestion by Mr. Khosla that subsidies should float according to the price of oil, moving higher when oil prices fall.</p>
        <p>Keith Collins, chief economist at the Agriculture Department, warned that if not carefully managed, the industry's heated rush to produce ethanol threatened to take too much land away from crop production for food. He said ethanol would consume 19 percent of corn production this year, up from 6 percent in 2000.</p>
        <p>That could push up corn prices and cause ripple effects on America's ability to export corn to places like China, where food demand is growing rapidly.</p>
        <p>Only one oil company -- Chevron -- was invited to the conference. The company is involved in several research initiatives with the Energy Department, some of them looking at ethanol and bio-diesel.</p>
        <p>BP, an oil company that invests in biofuels, was snubbed because of concerns that it might not be strong enough in its support of ethanol, said a person at an oil company who had been informed of the decision.</p>
        <p>Donald L. Paul, Chevron's chief technology officer, said in an interview that Chevron saw opportunities to help ''industrialize'' biofuels and ensure that they are sustainable over decades. ''Our view is that fuel diversification will be important,'' Dr. Paul said. ''To meet our fuel needs over the next 25 years we will have to add unconventional fuels, including biofuels. It will take every molecule.''</p>
        <p>But some questioned the oil industry's motives for seeming to support ethanol now when it fought so hard to keep it out of gasoline before. On Wednesday, Mr. Khosla, who helped start Sun Microsystems and has been stumping lately for biofuels and other alternative energy investments, accused the oil industry of trying to slow the effort to incorporate more ethanol into gasoline.</p>
        <p>''Despite nice words from the American Petroleum Institute, make no mistake about it -- they are not interested in a rapid transition,'' Mr. Khosla said after a speech by Red Cavaney, president of the institute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavaney warned that a push to sell more of an 85 percent ethanol/15 percent gasoline blend could prove ''unnecessarily expensive and risky, especially in the earlier years.''</p>
        <p>''If we are to encourage more long-term use of ethanol, we need to avoid surprising consumers with unanticipated problems.''</p>
        <p>He also cautioned against a ''patchwork of state-by-state laws mandating ethanol use,'' which could result in price spikes and fuel shortages similar to the situation when ''boutique fuels'' were introduced with different ingredients in different regions of the country at the end of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khosla accused the oil industry of trying to confine ethanol's role to 10 percent of gasoline at the pump, serving as a supplement to improve performance, which Mr. Cavaney said was the safest way to go.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Samuel W. Bodman said in an interview that he had personally invited Mr. Khosla to speak because ''he has a viewpoint that has to be heard.''</p>
        <p>Patricia A. Woertz, the chief executive of Archer Daniels Midland, the biggest ethanol producer, said partnerships across different industries and heavy investment in research and infrastructure would be needed to transform biofuels from ''visionary to viable.''</p>
        <p>''The question is not whether there will be a sustainable market for biofuels, but how big that market can or should that market become,'' Ms. Woertz said.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Bush promised to push to make the research and development tax credit a permanent part of the tax code. And he said the flood of private investment into biofuels must continue.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot of smart money in America going into energy diversification,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I hope you make a good return, and I think you will.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
