<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seizing Power, And Leaving The Grid Behind</title>
    <meta content="12ctcolCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DF1F3FF931A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seizing Power, And Leaving The Grid Behind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERRI HIRSHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hirshey, Gerri</byline>
      <dateline>FAIRFIELD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN anticipation of January's big chill -- another increase in Connecticut's electricity rates that is expected to approach 50 percent -- let's have a show of waving checkbooks: How many residents would like an amicable separation from the likes of Connecticut Light and Power or United Illuminating? Harder question: How many ratepayers still reeling from last year's approximately 27 percent spike realize that under provisions of the state's 2005 Energy Independence Act, the utilities are now delighted to have some of their biggest customers walk away?</p>
        <p>Consider this revolutionary move by the forward-thinking Jesuits of Fairfield University, whose United Illuminating bill in 2005 was $1.8 million. The university is getting off the grid -- for good. In April, the university, which gobbles 24 million kilowatt-hours a year, expects to flip the switches on its own $9.5 million combined heat and electric plant powered by a natural gas turbine built by Solar, a subsidiary of Caterpillar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN anticipation of January's big chill -- another increase in Connecticut's electricity rates that is expected to approach 50 percent -- let's have a show of waving checkbooks: How many residents would like an amicable separation from the likes of Connecticut Light and Power or United Illuminating? Harder question: How many ratepayers still reeling from last year's approximately 27 percent spike realize that under provisions of the state's 2005 Energy Independence Act, the utilities are now delighted to have some of their biggest customers walk away?</p>
        <p>Consider this revolutionary move by the forward-thinking Jesuits of Fairfield University, whose United Illuminating bill in 2005 was $1.8 million. The university is getting off the grid -- for good. In April, the university, which gobbles 24 million kilowatt-hours a year, expects to flip the switches on its own $9.5 million combined heat and electric plant powered by a natural gas turbine built by Solar, a subsidiary of Caterpillar.</p>
        <p>It will be done with the blessing (and backup) of United Illuminating -- and a $2.3 million state grant for on-site generation. Part of the Energy Independence Act, the grant program aims to reduce the staggering $500 million paid last year by Connecticut residents in federally mandated congestion charges, owing to the state's generation shortcomings and old transmission lines.</p>
        <p>Generating its own electricity, the 3,000-student university will take the equivalent of 4,000 households off the grid, reduce its energy costs and help insure its operating budget against future rate spikes. But what is the upside for the utility in losing one of its 20 biggest customers?</p>
        <p>''The gain in reducing congestion charges will be greater than the revenue loss to U. I.,'' says Tony Marone, United Illuminating's vice president of client services, who has been working on the project. ''Really, it's a net positive value for society.''</p>
        <p>''We'll be something like the 40th campus in the country to purchase a Solar turbine,'' says Richard I. Taylor Jr., the university's associate vice president for campus planning and operations. ''We're definitely on the cutting edge, and taking this to the trustees was a little bit frightening.''</p>
        <p>But as the university tries to limit tuition increases (tuition and board hovers at $30,000), while contending with the expected rate increase and an electric bill that chomped nearly two-thirds of its $3.2 million utility budget, feasibility studies made such a drastic measure look reasonable.</p>
        <p>The trustees liked the numbers: The university expects to generate 99 percent of its own electricity and 67 percent of its hot water that will be pumped campuswide through its existing underground system. Better still, the turbine will run much cleaner. ''There is a huge reduction from our current emissions -- 96 percent reduction of sulfur oxides and 17 percent in nitrogen oxides, both of which contribute to acid rain,'' Mr. Taylor says.</p>
        <p>Faced with this good news, Mr. Taylor says, the town of Fairfield and neighbors did not oppose the power plant. Construction is under way on a 3,000-square-foot addition to the university's heating and cooling plant near North Benson Road. Behind a tasteful noise-abatement wall, it will house a railcar-size turbine that traps and reclaims heat, boasting an efficiency rating twice that of most conventional power plants.</p>
        <p>Lest the average utility customer dream of working such an off-grid wonder in a three-bedroom Cape, Beryl Lyons, a spokeswoman for the Connecticut Department of Public Utility Control, cautioned that the grant program is only feasible for larger users. Frito-Lay just got a $1.7 million grant for its Killingly plant.</p>
        <p>''But we have pending applications for all sizes and types of generation,'' she says. ''We're overwhelmed by the response.'' She read from her list of 35 submissions: ''A banquet hall. A dairy. Blue Cross. Pitney Bowes. A skating rink. Cablevision.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Marone, of United Illuminating, says that most of the applications he is reviewing are not for full on-site generation but for emergency backup. Grantees are required to use their generators to send power back into the grid when called upon.</p>
        <p>''The response to a usage spike on a hot day this past August was tremendous,'' Mr. Marone says. ''When we called all those smaller generators online, we got to 120 percent load capacity right away.''</p>
        <p>Thus, curiouser and curiouser grows the nation's fourth-most-expensive, deregulated and baffling Connecticut energy market. With its unconventional new partnerships, the state's Energy Independence Act may be seen as a Hail Mary pass for increasingly stressed utilities and consumers. Could this jury-rigged mutual aid society restore some balance of power?</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor thinks so. With the university's new plant up and running, and a standby hookup to United Illuminating, he expects the campus will become a bright and warm oasis should the rest of Fairfield suffer a major power failure.</p>
        <p>''Come on down,'' he says. ''The lights will be on. And we'll be cooking.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: conn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
