<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax Incentives for Oil Stand in Way of Push For Alternative Fuels</title>
    <meta content="03fuels" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/03/nyregion/03fuels.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1736842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits, Deductions and Exemptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Petroleum Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDC163EF930A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax Incentives for Oil Stand in Way of Push For Alternative Fuels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oil Habit Is Hard to Break Under New York Tax Code</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Feb. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oil companies and wholesalers of oil and gasoline continue to receive benefits of tax cuts and government incentives, despite record-high profits and call for Americans to reduce their dependence on oil; disconnect between claimed political policy and actual legislation is evident at both national and state levels; American Petroleum Institute says that New York has nation's highest state and local gasoline taxes, but lawmakers continue to pass laws that do not require companies to lower consumer costs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his address to the nation on Tuesday, President Bush said the United States must move to wean itself from foreign oil.</p>
        <p>But New York's energy policies show just how hard that goal may be, with a tax code that offers more than $1 billion worth of breaks for gasoline and diesel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's call for less dependence on oil faces a challenge in New York State, where gasoline and diesel tax breaks total more than $1 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his address to the nation on Tuesday, President Bush said the United States must move to wean itself from foreign oil.</p>
        <p>But New York's energy policies show just how hard that goal may be, with a tax code that offers more than $1 billion worth of breaks for gasoline and diesel.</p>
        <p>And on the day of Mr. Bush's speech, the State Senate passed a bill that would grant a tax cut to giant oil companies, even as they are reporting record profits, as well as to independent distributors that bring oil into the state.</p>
        <p>Such tax breaks not only encourage continued dependence on fossil fuels, but may make it harder to accomplish what Mr. Bush, along with Gov. George E. Pataki, is calling for: the wider development and use of alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>Many of the more than $1 billion in tax breaks that New York grants for conventional fuels -- plain old gasoline and diesel -- have been built up over Mr. Pataki's nearly dozen years in office, sometimes as incentives to keep businesses in the state. State gasoline and diesel taxes are discounted for commercial fishermen, farmers, nonprofit groups, private and parochial schools, private bus companies that have contracts with the state, commuter ferries, manufacturers, mining companies and veterans' groups, among others.</p>
        <p>Republican lawmakers continue to press for more. In addition to the tax cut for oil distributors, which the Senate also passed last year, other recent measures it has passed include a reimbursement of taxes on diesel fuel paid by small businesses that charter boats for sports fishermen. Both ideas have so far stalled in the Democratic Assembly.</p>
        <p>This legislation comes as Mr. Pataki has proposed tens of millions of dollars in tax breaks and other incentives to promote alternative fuels like ethanol and biodiesel. His measures are aimed, as he put it in his State of the State address last month, at ''reducing our dependence on expensive, polluting, terror-promoting foreign oil.'' Mr. Bush appeared to echo that call on Tuesday, saying that ''America is addicted to oil'' and should increase spending on alternatives.</p>
        <p>Seeking to expand tax breaks for both regular and alternative fuels may seem counterproductive. One school of thought among some policymakers, and even Detroit auto executives, is that the surest way to wean America from its oil addiction is to follow the lead of Europe, where high gasoline taxes are a powerful incentive to buy fuel-efficient cars.</p>
        <p>''You have to ask the question in 2006,'' said State Senator Liz Krueger, a Manhattan Democrat, ''when we all agree we should be decreasing our dependence on foreign petroleum and increasing our use of alternative and renewable resources, why we continue to give tax expenditures, exemptions, credits and refunds for the use of petroleum and even have bills coming to the floor that would expand those.''</p>
        <p>''It seems to be a net lose-lose proposition to use the tax code to encourage alternative fuels while also allowing the same tax code to encourage the expanded use of petroleum,'' she added.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Americans -- particularly lower-income Americans -- have been battered by the run-up in oil prices, as have many of their employers, so potential tax breaks for traditional fuels are politically popular. The biggest current tax break is for diesel fuel used in residential heating, costing the state a projected $276.7 million in lost revenue annually.</p>
        <p>''With the price of fuel the way it is, it's killing me,'' said Mike Albronda of Long Island, a captain of the charter boat Montauk. The measure passed by the Senate would help considerably, he said, because fuel taxes typically cost him about $900 a year.</p>
        <p>Michael Marr, a spokesman for Mr. Pataki's budget division, said, ''The governor does not believe that raising taxes is the way to address the need to reduce our dependence on foreign energy sources.</p>
        <p>''The governor has advanced a comprehensive plan to help New York transition out of our current overreliance on foreign energy sources by providing the state with the means to develop the alternative energy sources of tomorrow while also creating a market for those new energy sources,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The governor's budget proposal includes $30 million for projects aimed at promoting the use of alternative fuels, including giving money to gas stations as incentives to offer such fuels to consumers. An additional $20 million would be set aside to support the construction of a new kind of refinery that produces ethanol through a more environmentally efficient process than producing it from corn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki also seeks a $2,000 tax credit for people who buy hybrid gas-and-electric cars, costing the state $10 million when fully phased in, and he wants to waive the modest taxes that exist on some alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>According to the American Petroleum Institute, an oil industry trade group, New York has the nation's highest state and local gasoline taxes, at more than 40 cents a gallon, on top of the 18.4 cents in federal taxes consumers must pay.</p>
        <p>State fuel taxes are generally levied on oil companies or businesses that distribute fuel to gas stations, then passed along to consumers. The bill passed by the State Senate on Tuesday would cut sales taxes on gasoline at prices above $2 a gallon, or by about 4 cents a gallon at current prices. Over all, the measure is projected to cost the state $200 million in lost revenue.</p>
        <p>The bill's sponsor, Senator Joseph E. Robach, a Rochester Republican, said he believed that oil companies would pass the savings to retailers, who would pass them to consumers. ''That is free enterprise,'' he said. ''At least one hungry entrepreneur will use that to lower prices.''</p>
        <p>But the bill does not require that the tax breaks be passed on to consumers, and the industry has not seemed inclined to share its profits. This week, Exxon Mobil reported a $36.1 billion profit for 2005, the largest ever for an American company.</p>
        <p>''To say that is going to translate to the end consumer when you have a lot of people in the distribution chain is hard to anticipate,'' said Cathy Kenny, an associate director at a New York arm of the American Petroleum Institute. ''If you're a retailer, why would you lower your price 4 cents?''</p>
        <p>Democrats contend that tax relief for lower-income families should be accomplished in other ways, like income tax relief.</p>
        <p>Ms. Krueger, who voted against the bill the Senate passed on Tuesday, said, ''This isn't a tax return to consumers; this is a reduction in taxes to the wholesalers with no ability to hold them accountable to pass that savings along to the consumer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
