<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: July 28 - August 3</title>
    <meta content="28theater" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1778908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDE123FF93BA15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="15426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: July 28 - August 3</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' Previews start tomorrow. Opens Aug. 16. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' In previews; opens Aug. 9. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' Previews start tomorrow. Opens Aug. 17. This musical sendup of biographical shows features Martin Short and an ensemble telling the story of his life. Mr. Short's beloved old characters, like Ed Grimley and Jiminy Glick, make appearances (2:15). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street; (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Aug. 6. The seventh annual showcase may get lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information: (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' An elderly carver refuses to make way for a new highway in this drama set in the 1970's. Dan Lauria (''The Wonder Years'') stars (1:40). Soho Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village; (212) 691-1555.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BULLY' William Walsh plays the quotable Theodore Roosevelt in this interesting but not completely polished one-man show (2:00). Irish Arts Center, 553 West 51st Street, (212) 868-4444. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School. Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200 (1:10). Beckett Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANGEL MOUNTAIN' A young soldier, his mentally slow brother and their widowed father react to the new housekeeper in John-Richard Thompson's absorbing if sometimes predictable drama, set in 1946 (1:05). The Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching and beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' A solid rendition of Jose Rivera's thin fable about time, centering on a hitchhiking woman who has been pregnant for two years. Luis Vega is particularly good as the man who gives her a ride and shelter for the night (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE AND OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village; (212) 642-9033. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where conmen are king (see ''The Producers.'') Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James at the mismatched swindlers. (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FRANKENSTEIN, THE MUSICAL' More is not better in Robert Mitchell's show based on Mary Shelley's novel. The too many songs and scenes are confusing and ultimately defeat the cast, while Brian Charles Rooney as the scientist Victor Frankenstein might regain his fire if he switched roles with Timothy Warmen, who, as the lab mistake, seems more like a morose personal trainer out on a hike (2:15). The Wings Theater, 154 Christopher Street, between Washington and Greenwich Streets, West Village, (212) 627-2961; closing on Sunday. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'ORANGE LEMON EGG CANARY' Rinne Groff's deceptive romance about a hard-drinking magician is like a great trick with a bungled payoff (1:30). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing on Sunday. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SECRETS' A clunky relationship drama about shrill, cruel middle-age couples (1:05). The Theater at St. Luke's, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231; closing on Sunday. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, just west of Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 868-4444; closing tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEEN RICH ALL MY LIFE' (No rating, 80 minutes) This admiring documentary portrait of the Silver Belles, an indefatigable troupe of veteran Harlem tap dancers between the ages of 84 and 96, is a valuable historical footnote and a useful how-to movie about making the most of old age. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright and Antony are among the featured performers. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeoisie Parisian marriage, circa 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LADY IN THE WATER' (PG-13, 108 minutes) In this watchable folly, Paul Giamatti plays a building manager who encounters a menagerie of otherworldy creatures, most important Bryce Dallas Howard's water nymph. The writer and director M. Night Shyamalan wants us to believe, mostly in the myth of his own genius. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Mini's First Time' (R, 91 minutes) Yet another poor little rich girl tends to her festering inner wounds by becoming one of Southern California's children of the damned. Nikki Reed stars alongside the slumming likes of Alec Baldwin, Carrie-Anne Moss, Jeff Goldblum and Luke Wilson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband, and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises, yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SHADOWBOXER' (R, 93 minutes) This garish thriller starring Helen Mirren and Cuba Gooding Jr. as contract killers and lovers is an extravagance that leaves you with your mouth hanging open -- partly in admiration of its audacity and partly in disbelief at its preposterousness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE WORLD ACCORDING TO SHORTS' (No rating, 95 minutes total running time) For audiences exhausted by today's bloated extravaganzas, ''The World According to Shorts'' is an eclectic palate cleanser. Addressing topics as diverse as aging, marital sex and the fantasy lives of children, this six-film sampling of world cinema ranges from the traditional to the surreal, the latter brilliantly exemplified by the German animated western ''Ring of Fire.'' As frustrated cowboys trail beckoning women and pulsing vaginas across a Dalíesque landscape, the wonderful world of Disney seems a million miles away. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) continues at the Museum of the Moving Image with two silents starring Janet Gaynor and Charles Farrell. Borzage won the first-ever best-director Oscar for ''Seventh Heaven'' (1927), a love story set in a slum. In ''Street Angel'' (1928), Gaynor plays a Neapolitan prostitute. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through Sunday) BAMcinématek's tribute to movie bad guys comes to a close this weekend with three films. In ''The Manchurian Candidate'' (1962), Angela Lansbury's character sells out her nearest and dearest for political power. In ''The Godfather: Part II'' (1974), Michael Corleone (Al Pacino) turns ruthless. In ''Apocalypse Now Redux'' (1979), Marlon Brando's Colonel Kurtz embraces the horror. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Thursday) This fifth annual outdoor festival concludes next week with two very different features. Wednesday night's film, from Senegal, is ''Hyenas'' (1992), a drama in which a rich woman bribes poor villagers to commit murder. Thursday night's feature is ''All on a Mardi Gras Day'' (2003), Royce Osborne's look at the history of African-American culture in New Orleans. Harlem Meer, Central Park, 110th Street and Lenox Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues Sunday and Tuesday with ''The Lower Depths'' (1957), his adaptation of Maxim Gorky's masterpiece about poor souls in a flophouse. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-84) begins Tuesday night with ''Ride the High Country'' (1962), his second film, which stars Randolph Scott and Joel McCrea as Old West lawmen in a changing world. Thursday night's film is Peckinpah's masterpiece, ''The Wild Bunch'' (1969), a violent western about the nature of morality. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ADOLESCENTS (Sunday) After a painfully drawn-out dispute with its landlord, CBGB will close at the end of October, which means that everybody is rushing to play his last gig there. Sunday features the Adolescents, one of the architects of the early-1980's Southern California hardcore punk sound, who joined the scruffy melodicism of the Ramones with boys-will-be-boys petulance and angry social realism. With the Freeze, Street Dogs and the Vacancies. At 6:30 p.m., 315 Bowery, at Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 982-4052, cbgb.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLOC PARTY (Tomorrow) With spiky but melodic guitars and agitated dance beats, Bloc Party revives the nervous funk of postpunk bands like Gang of Four. With Secret Machines and Mew. At 6:30 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $34. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BON JOVI (Tomorrow) Bon Jovi, the band that titled its 1998 album ''New Jersey,'' is back in its home state. Jon Bon Jovi's band conquered the airwaves in the 1980's and 90's by sticking together everything catchy about 1970's rock: Bruce Springsteen's earnestness, Led Zeppelin's crunch, Boston's harmonies and lyrics that paint romance as nothing less than a titanic adventure. A photogenic lead singer doesn't hurt, either. With Nickelback. At 7 p.m., Giants Stadium, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900, meadowlands.com; $37.50 to $125. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Tonight) This Long Island emo band made a quantum leap with its second album three years ago, from whiny and unchallenging breakup songs to tangles of explosive melody with brooding, sometimes horrific lyrics. What the band will come up with on its as-yet-unscheduled album No. 3 is a subject of intense speculation among fans. With Colour Revolt. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EDIE BRICKELL AND NEW BOHEMIANS (Tonight) Sixteen years after her last studio album with New Bohemians, Edie Brickell has reunited with the group; their new record, ''Stranger Things'' (Fantasy/Concord), was released on Tuesday. With Sonya Kitchell, a teenage singer-songwriter whose debut CD is promoted by Starbucks. At 7, Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777, summerstage.org; free, but a donation is suggested. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JIM CAMPILONGO, MIKE VIOLA (Monday) Just another night at the Living Room, a plain Lower East Side cabaret that puts on one guitar-cradling singer-songwriter after another, some of them world-class. Mr. Campilongo is a well-traveled guitar whiz who plays with Norah Jones in her country band, the Little Willies; here he leads his Electric Trio. Mr. Viola, jumping from piano to guitar, sings strident power-pop with some jagged wit. Also on the bill are Grainne Ryan, Alice Bierhorst, Jim Boggia and the Jason Crigler Band. At 6 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>DILLINGER ESCAPE PLAN (Wednesday) With harsh screams and convoluted guitar riffs that sometimes seem to have been written with the aid of advanced calculus, this New Jersey band plays a cathartic and yet impossibly complex kind of punk-jazz. With God Forbid. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DIXIE CHICKS (Tuesday and Wednesday) After first backing down slightly from their criticism of President Bush in 2003, the Dixie Chicks returned this year with ''Taking the Long Way'' (Columbia), a reflective and defiant album that declares: ''I'm not ready to make nice/I'm not ready to back down.'' Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39.59 to $89.50. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; $39.50 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'DOT DASH YEAR IV' (Tonight and tomorrow) For its minifestival each summer, Dot Dash, a little concert promoter in Brooklyn devoted to punk and garage-rock, presents some big-deal reunions. This year features Rocket From the Tombs, a storied protopunk band from Cleveland that never recorded an album but spawned two influential groups when it broke up in 1975: the arty Pere Ubu and the more conventionally bratty Dead Boys. The band first reunited in 2003 and returns tomorrow with new material on a bill with the Little Killers, DC Snipers, Angry Angles and Imaginary Icons. Tonight's show features the Cynics, the Original Sins, the Hentchmen, the Turpentine Brothers and the Alarm Clocks, a 1960's band from Ohio whose single ''No Reason to Complain'' has been covered by countless shaggy-haired bands. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $17 tonight, $20 tomorrow. Rocket From the Tombs also plays on Sunday at 9 p.m. at Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NICOLAI DUNGER (Tonight) A Swedish balladeer with serious Van Morrison envy, Mr. Dunger makes earnest entreaties for romance and existential relief (''Take away my sadness, wipe away these blues in here'') in a tremulous tenor. With Elvis Perkins and Benjy Ferree. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EDITORS (Tonight) This band from Birmingham, England, chose a fitting name: it stitches together material from other sources with taste and artistry, joining the baritone-of-gloom vocals of Joy Division (''Oh, if fortune favors the brave/I am as poor as they come'') and the early U2's shimmering sheets of guitar. With Lake Trout and the Big Sleep. At 9, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARY GAUTHIER (Wednesday) Ms. Gauthier, who was born in Baton Rouge, La., and worked as a restaurateur before turning to music, writes sparse observations that suggest a modest but penetrating wisdom (''Every living thing could use a little mercy now''). With Eliza Gilkyson. At 7 p.m., Madison Square Park, Madison Avenue at 24th Street, (212) 538-6667; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>METERS (Thursday) Hurricane Katrina could not drown New Orleans syncopation. It lives on with the reunion of the Meters, the definitive New Orleans funk band since 1967. The group has backed others, but saved its snappiest, trickiest grooves for its own tracks. With Art Neville on keyboards, George Porter Jr. on bass, Leo Nocentelli on guitar and Zigaboo Modeliste on drums, they open up nooks and crannies of the beat to carry every hip into irresistible motion. At 9 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $45. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* NEW PORNOGRAPHERS, CALEXICO, FRAMES (Thursday) If the weather holds, this benefit for Central Park SummerStage will be a perfect night of smart, tuneful indie rock. The New Pornographers, from Vancouver, British Columbia, play sharp, elegant pop-rock with a wit that comes down from the Kinks. Calexico, a collective from Tucson, pushes desert-dry alt-country toward surf guitar, mariachi and a folk-flavored psychedelia like that of the 1960's band Love. The Frames are one of the most expressive Irish groups since U2. At 6 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777, summerstage.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the site. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OLLABELLE (Monday through Thursday) Celebrating a new album, ''Riverside Battle Songs'' (Verve Forecast), Ollabelle, a vocal sextet that worships country, bluegrass and gospel with crystalline voices and wide eyes, will play for four nights at Banjo Jim's, an East Village club the group has played many times. At 9 p.m., Avenue C at Ninth Street, (212) 777-0869, banjojims.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OZZFEST (Tomorrow) In its 11th installment, the annual carnival of black cotton T-shirts, guttural heavy metal and nostalgic affection for Ozzy Osbourne features System of a Down, Disturbed, Avenged Sevenfold, Hatebreed, Lacuna Coil, Dragonforce and many others on a smaller stage. Ozzy fans in New York are fortunate: this concert is one of only 8 among the 27 stops on the tour that will feature Mr. Osbourne performing on the main stage. Doors open at 9 a.m., Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, (212) 307-7171, ozzfest.com; $87.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAD PAISLEY (Tonight) A young songwriter who knows the value of terse composition and sly wordplay, Mr. Paisley scored one of country's biggest hits last year with ''Alcohol.'' A droll defense of grog from the drink's point of view (''I've been known to cause a few breakups/And I've been known to cause a few births''), it is one of those rare novelty songs that outlives its novelty. With Eric Church, a rising country singer from North Carolina. At 8, Bethel Woods Center for the Arts, Bethel, N.Y., (845) 454-3388, bethelwoods.us; $46; $30.50 for lawn seats. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'RAMAKIEN: A RAK OPERA' (Tonight through Sunday) The Lincoln Center Festival presents an intriguing ''rock-theater piece'' based on an excerpt from the Ramakien, the Thai national epic. The show features many of Thailand's biggest and most respected rockers, including Sek Loso, who has led his band at the South by Southwest and Glastonbury festivals; the Photo Sticker Machine, an electronic group; and Rik Vachilapun, called a cross between Diamanda Galás and Patti Smith. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday night at 7, La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>The RED KRAYOLA (Wednesday) The first album of the Red Crayola (as it was originally called) appeared in 1967, and Mayo Thompson has held on to its skewed psychedelic perspective ever since; he also spent some years as a member of Pere Ubu. He's fond of dissolving song structures, crypto-Marxist messages and woozy sounds, and when he reconvened the Red Krayola (its name was changed to avoid trademark problems) in 1994, he found fans and collaborators among progressive- and post-rock musicians. With White Magic and Miighty Flashlight. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* SLEATER-KINNEY (Wednesday) After a 12-year reign over indie rock, the three women of Sleater-Kinney are calling it quits: their brief summer tour will find them screaming their last shrill screams and playing their last postpunk deconstructions of thick, meaty guitar riffs. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUL ASYLUM (Thursday) This Minneapolis band lived the story of alternative rock: from loud and scrappy beginnings in the early 1980's, it matured largely out of sight of the mainstream, then found sudden fame in the 90's. The next phase is the reunion with something to prove, and on ''The Silver Lining'' (Legacy), its first new studio album in eight years, Soul Asylum proves that it still has a strong command of burly guitar and yearning vocals. At 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUND TEAM (Tonight through Monday) Recalling Spoon, another indie band from Austin, Tex., Sound Team constructs dense and psychologically rich songs in which elements of white soul hint at a spiritual nourishment denied by the anxious guitars and brooding, aloof vocals. With Cold War Kids and Midlake. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out tonight, $12 tomorrow. Sunday at 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $10. Monday at 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAR WILLIAMS (Wednesday) In bare and tuneful songs that are called folk because they are quiet but could very well be rock, Ms. Williams is sometimes reflective and sometimes topical, as in her recent ''Teen for God,'' which explores religion as a psychological terror on the young: ''Dear Lord, I plan each day/The things I will not do or say.'' She plays an acoustic set. At 7 p.m., Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; $50, including museum admission. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DON BYRON QUARTET (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Byron is justifiably known for his independent-minded concept albums -- his next one will shine a spotlight on the rhythm-and-blues saxophonist Junior Walker -- but he is, first and foremost, a daring clarinetist. He will play with several longtime associates: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the bassist Lonnie Plaxico and the drummer Billy Hart. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>CELEBRATION OF RAY BARRETTO AND HILTON RUIZ (Tonight through Sunday) ''Standards Rican-ditioned,'' recently issued on Zoho Music, was the final studio album of the conga virtuoso Ray Barretto. It also turned out to be the last recorded effort by the pianist Hilton Ruiz. Both were New York-born musicians of Puerto Rican heritage, and both were pillars of the Latin jazz community. This tribute, fittingly programmed as the culmination of a monthlong ''Latin in Manhattan'' festival, includes Mr. Barretto's son Chris Barretto, as well as a couple of more established saxophonists, Sonny Fortune and David Sánchez. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SYLVIE COURVOISIER AND MARK FELDMAN (Tonight) As a pianist and composer, Ms. Courvoisier pursues intricacy and rigor; Mr. Feldman, a violinist, favors plangent intensity. They have worked well as a duo, perhaps most notably on ''Malphas: Book of Angels Vol. 3'' (Tzadik), a volume of John Zorn compositions. At 8, Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EDDIE DURHAM JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) Eddie Durham was an important composer, arranger and bandleader of the prewar era, best known for helping shape the sound of Kansas City swing. He also played trombone and guitar, tasks handled respectively by Fred Wesley and Hiram Bullock in this casual salute. Through Aug. 6. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARTY EHRLICH SEXTET (Sunday) As on his appealing recent album, ''News on the Rail'' (Palmetto), Mr. Ehrlich, a versatile alto saxophonist and virtuoso clarinetist, leads a sextet that includes James Zollar on trumpet, Allison Miller on drums and Howard Johnson on tuba and baritone saxophone. At 8 p.m., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Sculpture Garden at the Museum of Modern Art, 15 West 54th Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9491. moma.org/events/summergarden; free, but tickets, required for entry, will be distributed at 5:30 p.m. on a first-come-first-served basis. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON FADDIS QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Faddis is a highly proficient trumpeter, sometimes to the point of effulgence. But with ''Teranga'' (Koch), his first quartet album in 15 years, he exercises an effective and impressive restraint, with the help of David Hazeltine on piano, Kiyoshi Kitagawa on bass and Dion Parson on drums. Through Aug. 6. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FAUX, FAUX (Tonight) Conceived as a showcase for the veteran avant-garde trumpeter Baikida Carroll, this collective quartet features the convoluted compositions of its other members, mainly Tim Berne, an alto saxophonist, and Michael Formanek, a bassist. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Gordon, a high-spirited trombonist and one of the most authoritative soloists in the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra, leads a swing-minded small group with Dan Nimmer on piano, Thaddeus Expose on bass and Marion Felder on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANNY GRISSETT TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. Grissett is a young pianist with a strong track record as a sideman and a solid debut as a leader: ''Promise,'' on Criss Cross Records. Kendrick Scott plays drums, as on the album; Dwayne Burno is a substitute bassist but a good one. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RANDY JOHNSTON TRIO (Tonight) A proficient guitarist, Mr. Johnston sounds best performing with a trio in an intimate setting, like this one, where he frequently appears. At 9:15, 10:40 and midnight, Puppets Jazz Bar, 294 Fifth Avenue, near Second Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 499-2627, puppetsjazz.com; $5, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KANAN TRIO (Sunday) Mr. Kanan is an articulate pianist, and his trio, with Joseph Lepore on bass and Jeff Williams on drums, adheres to a melodic and unhurried variety of post-bop. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEVIN MAHOGANY (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Mahogany's rich and deep-toned singing voice is worthy of his stately surname. He will use it to pay tribute to the crooner Johnny Hartman, another baritone with an appropriate handle. At 8 and 10 p.m., with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) As on a recent Blue Note album, Mr. Martino pays homage to one of his guitar heroes, Wes Montgomery. The untroubled self-assurance of the emulation and the simple satisfaction of a hard-swinging band make the gesture pay off. Through Aug. 5. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAUL MOTIAN TRIO 2000 + 1 (Tuesday through Thursday) Show tunes and other standards receive loving and slyly imaginative interpretations on ''Paul Motian on Broadway Vol. 4'' (Winter &amp; Winter), scheduled for release just after this weeklong run. Mr. Motian's teasingly suggestive drumming is well matched by the quietly abstruse pianism of Masabumi Kikuchi; Rebecca Martin handles vocals, with a casual sort of purity. The tenor saxophonist Chris Potter and the bassist Larry Grenadier add some welcome ballast and heft. Through Aug. 6. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE NELSON/MULGREW MILLER QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson, on vibraphone, and Mr. Miller, on piano, travel with grace and confidence through the familiar terrain of post-bop, joined by Ivan Taylor on bass and Carl Allen on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY QUARTET (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Osby is an alto saxophonist with a predilection for jagged edges, and yet he's squarely within the jazz tradition. His rhythm section here consists of the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Tommy Crane. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE OTHER HALF (Wednesday) Notwithstanding the title, which is either weakly ironic or oddly dismissive, this concert is a laudable showcase for six female avant-garde composers. In order, they are the cellist Ha-Yang Kim, performing alone; the pianist Angelica Sanchez, with a top-shelf quintet; the vocalist Judith Berkson, self-accompanied on keyboards; the alto saxophonist Matana Roberts, in a solo exertion; and the sympathetic duo of Jessica Pavone, on viola, and Mary Halvorson, on guitar. At 7:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HOUSTON PERSON QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Person's latest album, ''You Taught My Heart to Sing'' (Half Note), features his tenor saxophone and Bill Charlap's piano in a program of tender duets. Performing without Mr. Charlap, he returns to form, applying his robust tone to a more rhythmically assertive purpose. At 9, 10:30 and midnight, Lenox Lounge, 288 Lenox Avenue, near 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 427-0253, lenoxlounge.com; cover, $25, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SPIRIT OF DJANGO REINHARDT (Tuesday) What began as a strict salute to this immortal Manouche Gypsy guitarist has evolved into a smorgasbord of buoyant swing, as well as a New York institution. This year's summer concert features a prominent inheritor of the Reinhardt style, Dorado Schmitt, along with two of his guitar-playing family members: Samson Schmitt, his son, and Tchavolo Schmitt, a cousin. Also on hand are the Romanian violinist Florin Niculescu, the French accordionist Ludovic Beier, the Dutch pianist Peter Beets and a pair of Americans: Joel Frahm, a saxophonist, and Brian Torff, who plays bass and serves as musical director. At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37 to $57. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ROBBINS AND CENTRIC (Tomorrow) ''Waits and Measures'' (Playscape), the new album by the alto saxophonist Pete Robbins, is an intimate sort of jazz-rock hybrid, complete with Fender Rhodes piano and artfully fuzzed-out electric guitar. Mr. Robbins reconvenes the album's cast here: Sam Sadigursky on saxophones, Mike Gamble on guitar, Eliot Cardinaux on keyboards, Thomas Morgan on bass, and Dan Weiss and Tyshawn Sorey on drums. At 10 p.m., Detour, 349 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 533-6212, jazzatdetour.com; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTURO SANDOVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Sandoval is a trumpeter best known for stratospheric bravado, though he occasionally reaches for a subtler aesthetic. His Latin-jazz sextet features Ed Calle on saxophones, Javier Concepcion on piano, Armando Gola on bass, Tomas Cruz on percussion and Alexis Arce on drums. Through Aug. 6 at 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SKERIK'S MAELSTROM TRIO (Tomorrow and Sunday) The tenor and soprano saxophonist known as Skerik brings a hyperactive jam-band mentality to the traditions of soul-jazz organ trios, with Brian Coogan on Hammond B-3 organ and Simon Lott on drums. Tomorrow night at 12:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $15, with a $5 minimum. Sunday at 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN'S TRIO ALTO (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Stillman, a young alto saxophonist with an inquisitive relationship to jazz conventions, joins forces with two exploratory rhythm players, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Take Toriyama. Wednesday at 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK TERRY BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Terry's big-band experience is extensive: starting in the late 1940's, he served successively in the orchestras of Count Basie, Duke Ellington and Quincy Jones. Mr. Terry, an octogenarian trumpet and fluegelhorn player, applies a lifetime of wit and experience to his own swinging ensemble. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ZIMMER QUINTET (Tonight) The hard bop of the 1960's provides thematic sustenance for Mr. Zimmer, a drummer, and his working band, which includes the smartly assertive tenor saxophonist Joel Frahm. At 9, Night and Day, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, nightanddayrestaurant.com; cover, $10, with a $7 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Tonight, Sunday and Wednesday) The conductor Leon Botstein enjoys resuscitating neglected works, some of which have proved to be more worthwhile than others. Tonight he will lead the American Symphony Orchestra in a production of ''Genoveva,'' Robert Schumann's only opera. The work has been infrequently performed or recorded since its premiere in 1850, and this performance is billed as its American stage premiere. Kasper Bech Holten, the dynamic young director of the Royal Danish Opera, is directing a cast that includes the soprano Ylva Kihlberg in the title role of the young wife. Her husband, the crusading knight Siegfried, will be sung by the baritone Johannes Mannov; Golo, whose love for her is unrequited, will be portrayed by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m. and Wednesday at 8 p.m., Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu; $35 to $85. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Tuesday, and Thursday) Four operas are the rotation over the next week: Rossini's ''Barber of Seville'' is scheduled for tonight at 8; Janacek's ''Jenufa'' for tomorrow night at 8 and Monday at 1:30 p.m.; Stephen Hartke's ''Greater Good'' for Sunday at 1:30 p.m. and Thursday at 8 p.m.; and Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' Tuesday at 1:30 p.m. Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; sold out tonight, Monday and Tuesday; $64 to $112 tomorrow and Sunday; $41 to $104 on Thursday, with limited availability. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN ACCORDIONISTS' ASSOCIATION MASTER CLASS AND CONCERT SERIES (Today through Sunday) There is more to accordion music than you may think, or at least there is when the accordionist William Schimmel is in charge of the proceedings. The concerts in Mr. Schimmel's annual series offer everything from works by Alexander Tcherepnin, Eric Salzman and Leonard Feather to daring transcriptions of Paganini and Ravel, freewheeling variations on ''Hava Nagila'' and extended Elvis fantasies. The master classes are wild, too; topics this year include ''Accordion and the Standup Comic,'' ''Accordion and the Stripper,'' ''Hitler, Mengele and Other Repulsive Views Concerning the Accordion,'' and ''The Zen-Accordion Laugh.'' Master classes at 3 p.m., concerts at 7 p.m., Tenri Cultural Center, 43A West 13th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 876-0827; $110 for all three days; $40 for daily passes; $20 for master classes; $25 for concerts. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) The harpsichordist John Gibbons plays Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations at this venerable early-music festival this weekend. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156, astonmagna.org; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BANG ON A CAN FESTIVAL MARATHON (Sunday) This vibrant new-music collective ends its annual summer festival and institute at Mass MoCA with a six-hour marathon mélange of rock, classical, jazz and world music. Students and faculty will perform works by the Bang on a Can artistic directors, Julia Wolfe, David Lang and Michael Gordon; this year's composer in residence, Meredith Monk; as well as Steve Martland, Michael Daugherty and Joan Tower. The enthusiastically unclassifiable event will also include a Balinese gamelan ensemble performing a work with Western instruments and several robots. At 4 p.m., 7 Marshall Street, North Adams, Mass., (413) 662-2111, massmoca.org; $22. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight a program by the Williams Chamber Players, a piano trio, includes Paul Schoenfield's zesty ''Café Music,'' David Kechley's ''Episodes and Soliloquies'' and trios by Haydn and Beethoven. Tomorrow and Sunday, a large ensemble will be on hand for a hefty program that includes two Haydn cello concertos, Bach's ''Brandenburg'' Concerto No. 3, Mozart's Horn Concerto No. 2 and a Vivaldi Double Concerto. And on Thursday, Bargemusic offers two gems of the chamber repertory. The first, Schubert's ''Two Cellos'' Quintet, will be a video recording from 1967 with the cellists Pablo Casals and Gregor Piatigorsky, the violinists Alexander Schneider and Isadore Cohen, and Milton Thomas, the violist. After the intermission Mark Peskanov, a violinist; Maurycy Banaszek, a violist; and Marie-Elisabeth Hecker, a cellist, will perform Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563). Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m.; Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35 tonight and Thursday; $50 tomorrow and Sunday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* FESTIVAL OF CONTEMPORARY MUSIC at Tanglewood (Today through Monday) At this new-music festival, the students of the Tanglewood Music Center and assorted guests usually give polished, energetic performances of an array of modern works. Last night's opening program, to be repeated this afternoon, is a triple opera bill, with Elliott Carter's ''What Next?,'' as well as Stravinsky's ''Mavra'' and Hindemith's ''Hin und Zurück.'' James Levine leads the Carter; the others are to be led by the student conducting fellows. Other highlights include a program tomorrow morning with works by Ron Ford and Johannes Staud; a concert tomorrow evening that includes Pierre Boulez's ''Messagesquisse'' for seven cellos and works by Andrew Norman and Betsy Jolas; a Sunday morning performance with music by David Felder, Stephen Andrew Taylor, Mark Gustavson, Eric Chasalow, Stephen Jaffe and Edmund Campion; and a Sunday evening concert that includes Hans Abrahamsen's Piano Concerto, a solo violin work by Mr. Ford and works by Mr. Staud, Milton Babbitt, Donald Martino and Poul Ruders, with the guitarist David Starobin as the soloist. The finale will be a performance of the English composer Mark Anthony Turnage's powerful ''Blood on the Floor,'' on Monday evening. Today at 2:30; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 6 p.m.; Sunday at 10 a.m. and 8:30 p.m. and Monday at 8:30. Tanglewood, Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $11 and $30 to $50 for the opera triple bill; $50 pass for all performances tomorrow through Monday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EMILY MANZO (Sunday) This pianist, an Oberlin graduate and new-music champion, has given the premieres of works by John Luther Adams, Kyle Gann and Mary Halvrson. A regular performer at the Stone, John Zorn's experimental performance space, she will tackle John Cage's Sonatas and Interludes for Prepared Piano, with video by Paul Rowley and David Phillips. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C at Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10 per set. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL  (Tomorrow and Sunday) Public concerts are the by-product of this intensive-study chamber music retreat. The soprano Junko Watanabe and the pianist Martin Isepp will perform Schubert's ''Gretchen am Spinnrade'' and Brahms's ''An die Nachtigall'' tomorrow night. On Sunday Schubert's ''Trout'' Quintet is on the bill. Tomorrow at 8:30 and Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394, marlboromusic.org; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Holland)</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS (Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. On Sunday the Brentano String Quartet and Hsin-Yun Hwang, a violist, play Mozart's Viola Quintets in B flat (K. 174) and G minor (K. 516). On its own, the quartet plays David Horne's String Quartet No. 4 (2006). At 3 p.m., Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217, maverickconcerts.org; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART Festival (Tonight, and Tuesday through Thursday) Tonight's free preview concert opens with a work by the father of Salzburg's birthday boy. Leopold Mozart's ''Toy Symphony'' will be followed by Wolfgang Mozart's Symphony No. 1 in E flat and the ''Jupiter'' Symphony No. 41 in C. For the official opening night on Tuesday, the music director Louis Langrée and the festival orchestra will perform two celebratory works. The soprano Hei-Kyung Hong, the mezzo-soprano Susanne Mentzer, the tenor Matthew Polenzani and the bass John Relyea will sing Mozart's ''Coronation'' Mass in C with the Concert Chorale of New York, and the pianist Garrick Ohlsson will play the ''Coronation'' Concerto. (The program will be repeated on Wednesday.) On Thursday, Mr. Ohlsson returns to the intimate, candlelit Kaplan Penthouse -- where he performed Beethoven sonatas at the festival last year -- for ''A Little Night Music.'' This time he offers Beethoven's Sonatas Nos. 5, 10 and 13. Tonight and Tuesday and Wednesday nights at 8, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center; Thursday night at 10:30, Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; free tonight; $38 to $65 on Tuesday and Wednesday; $35 on Thursday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow) It's waltz time tonight with Johann Strauss and Brahms's ''Liebeslieder'' Waltzes. Tomorrow an all-day open house celebrates the 100th anniversary of the Norfolk Shed. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000, yale.edu/norfolk; $15 to $45 tonight; free tomorrow. (Holland)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tomorrow through Thursday) The Austrian conductor Hans Graf, music director of the Houston Symphony, will lead the Boston Symphony Orchestra tomorrow in Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' and Beethoven's Violin Concerto, with Gil Shaham as soloist. On Sunday Mr. Graf shares the stage with the violinist Midori in Bruch's Violin Concerto No. 1; the program also includes Mendelssohn's Symphony No. 4 (''Italian'') and Strauss's ''Till Eulenspiegel's Merry Pranks.'' On Wednesday and Thursday Gidon Kremer and the Kremerata Baltica offer their contribution to the Mozart birthday festivities with his complete violin concertos, programmed alongside works that include Michael Nyman's ''Trysting Fields'' and Alfred Schnittke's ''Gratulationsrondo'' on Tuesday, and Alexander Raskatov's ''Five Minutes in the Life of W.A.M.'' and Shostakovich's Prelude and Scherzo (Op. 11) on Wednesday. Tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday at 8:30 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; Lenox, Mass., (866) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $17 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, $17 to $56 on Wednesday and Thursday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tuesday) Now in its 48th season, this festival has focused mostly on Mozart this year, but for its finale, it is presenting Cuartetango. The implications of its name notwithstanding, the group includes not only a string quartet, but also a bandoneon player, and singers and dancers -- 10 performers in all -- who specialize in tango and jazz. At 8 p.m., Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village, (212) 252-3621, washingtonsquaremusicfestival.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN BALLET THEATER'S NEW YORK SUMMER INTENSIVE FINAL PERFORMANCE (Today) The American Ballet Theater picked 255 of the nation's top ballet students to come to New York for six weeks of intensive training, the fruits of which will be on display this afternoon, as students perform excerpts from ''Raymonda,'' ''La Bayadère,'' ''Études,'' ''Sylvia,'' ''Swan Lake'' and ''Theme and Variations.'' They will also perform original choreography by Leslie Browne, Daniel Baudendistel, Hilary Cartwright, Olga Dvorovenko, Tina Fehlandt, Jessica Lang and Brian Reeder. Four gifted goslings from the group -- Aria Alekzander, Joseph Gorak, Devon Teuscher and Faye Hideko -- will join the American Ballet Theater's Studio Company. At 12:30 p.m. and 4:30 p.m, the Performing Arts Center at Purchase College, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (212) 477-3030, Ext. 3416, abt.org/education/summerintensive.asp; $15. (Erika Kinetz)</p>
        <p>DANCING ON THE PLAZA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Produced by Dancing in the Streets, this free mini-festival will feature a shared program by nicholasleichterdance and CorbinDances (tomorrow) and an hourlong performance by Kun-Yang Lin/Dancers. Mr. Leichter's work stands out for its hip club-dancing influences, the Corbin work for its thoughtful high-energy physicality, and Mr. Lin's for its intensely emotional fusion of Chinese traditional and Western modern dance. At 3 p.m., Dag Hammarskjold Plaza, East 47th Street between First and Second Avenues, Manhattan, (212) 625-3505, or dancinginthestreets.org; free. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>EIDOLON BALLET (Tomorrow) This chamber dance group will perform works by the company's director, Melanie Cortier, and Ginger Thatcher, set to music by the Thai Elephant Orchestra, American polkas and Albinoni. At 2:30 and 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 946-1275, www.eidolonballet.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This wide-ranging festival of mostly new dance companies and artists ends this weekend with performances by Tracie Stanfield's Synthesis Dance Project (tonight and tomorrow night); Bimela Oliver Nsah's Sukinang Dance Group of P.C.H.S. Bamenda Cameroon (tomorrow and Sunday afternoons); and Jacqui Young's Push Factor Dance Company (a shared program Sunday afternoon). Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 6 p.m. Dicapo Opera Theater, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 273-0713, internationaldancefestival.org; $20 to $40 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Eva Yerbabuena's Ballet Flamenco from Spain will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by the Trey McIntyre Project, a contemporary ballet company. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, the Danish Dance Theater, billed as Denmark's leading modern-dance ensemble, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is Armitage Gone!, Karole Armitage's new, New York-based contemporary ballet troupe. Yerbabuena tonight and tomorrow night at 8, and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $50; McIntyre on Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., $45; Danish Dance tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m., $24; Armitage on Thursday at 8:15 p.m., $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org, Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL: GRUPO KRAPP (Wednesday and Thursday) This earthy, funny dance and theater troupe from Argentina will present its new ''Project E,'' a festival commission, in which tall, beautiful performers wander out of their dance and find themselves shrunken and unable to get back the power they once had over their audiences. The troupe will also perform ''Rio Seco'' (''Dry River''), a piece about the family vacation from hell. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows Corona Park, ; $20; $15 in advance. The program will be repeated on Thursday at 7:30 p.m. at the LaGuardia Performing Arts Center, 31-10 Thomson Avenue, Long Island City, Queens; $12; $6 for students. Information and reservations for both performances: (718) 750-0064 or QueensTheatre.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, concludes its two-month run at the intimate Theater 80 this weekend. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., Sunday at 5 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday nights at 8, and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org, $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>URBAN BUSH WOMEN 2006 SUMMER INSTITUTE (Tomorrow) In ''Place Matters: A Look at Displacement,'' directed by Jawole Willa Jo Zollar and created by 74 dance artists participating in the institute, notions of home and displacement are examined in light of events that include Hurricane Katrina, the slaughters in Darfur and the fighting in Iraq. At 4 and 7 p.m. Kumble Theater, Long Island University, at Flatbush and DeKalb Avenues, Downtown Brooklyn, (718) 488-1624 or www.brooklyn.liu.edu/kumbletheater; $10; $2 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOUNG DANCEMAKERS COMPANY CONCERT (Wednesday) A summer ensemble of New York City teenagers will perform an hourlong program directed by Alice Teirstein, with live percussion by William Catanzaro. The show will be followed by some spontaneous dance making, with audience participation. At 3 p.m., Lovinger Theater, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West, at Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 329-7205 or aliceteirstein@aol.com; free. (Kinetz)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 or brooklynmuseum.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States in a garrulous, very personal way. One particularly intense work, based on the belief that Abubakari II, ruler of Mali, crossed the Atlantic nearly 200 years before Columbus to discover the Americas, links the past with the present and Africa with the beloved Columbus of Ms. Robinson's childhood. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606 or daheshmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 or frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500 or guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best-known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000 or icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. History is full of shifty characters, antique visionaries, cusp figures and half-crazy oddball innovators, later overlooked because they're hard to pigeonhole. Their independent cast of mind is the truest expression of how civilization advances. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500 or mobia.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art: Douglas Gordon: 'Timeline,' through Sept 4. This selection of works by the artist known for appropriating and inventively manipulating Hollywood movies includes his projection of Alfred Hitchcock's ''Psycho,'' which runs so slowly that it takes 24 hours to complete, and a large-scale video installation that studies a circus elephant performing in an empty art gallery. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer , through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200 or neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in formal reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700 or nybg.org.(Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 2 West 77th Street, (212) 873-3400 or nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 19. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. The museum entrance is at 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088 or noguchi.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084 or ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art,' This museum is a oasis of calm in the city; you can feel your tension dissolve the minute you walk in the door. At the same time, the place jumps with activities, including lectures, films and exhibitions, many devoted to aspects of Himalayan culture. And for a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this new show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000 or rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676 or whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Mr. Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050 or tibordenagy.com, extended through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Your Beauty's Gold is Clay' This well-selected show of ceramicists includes ruggedly sensuous, Abstract Expressionist-style sculptures by Lynda Benglis; delicate and humorously detailed vessels by Kathy Butterly; surrealistically flamboyant large vases by Nicole Cherubini; comical, demonic heads by William King; a wonderful long-haired cat by Anne Arnold; and sweet faux-juvenile sculptures by Jessica Jackson Hutchins. Alexandre Gallery, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 755-2828 or alexandregallery.com, through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>Joe Biel With an exacting illustrator's touch, Mr. Biel draws large, dreamily perverse images of children, like the one of a girl with rabbit ears and a whip peeking out of a cardboard box, and one of a knife-wielding boy crouching atop a pile of rubble and examining a bone he found. Goff &amp; Rosenthal, 537B West 23rd Street, (212) 675-0461, goffandrosenthal.com, through Aug. 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* J. Bennett Fitts: 'No Lifeguard on Duty' Symbolically resonant photographs of mostly derelict motel swimming pools by a young Californian. Julie Saul, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 627-2410 or saulgallery.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200 or matthewmarks.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Group Show Four interesting Conceptualists: Pierre Bismuth folds a giant reproduction of a Jasper Johns flag painting into a Donald Judd-like box; Ryan Gander makes large photographs of bulletin boards bearing puzzling documents; Karl Haendel covers a wall with his large, handmade graphite copies of consumer-culture ephemera; and T. Kelly Mason constructsa walk-in, padded environment with soft, rain-related sounds and a video. Cohan and Leslie, 138 10th Avenue, near 19th Street, (212) 206-8710 or cohanandleslie.com, through Aug. 18. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Michael Heizer Sculptures in concrete representing prehistoric hand tools much enlarged so that they resemble Modernist sculptures by a follower of Brancusi. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 421-3292 or pacewildenstein.com, through Sept. 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238 or kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 741-4764 or photocollect.com, through Aug. 19. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>Zoe Leonard, Liz Deschenes and Vija Celmins This quietly gripping show of photographs and works derived from photographs includes delicate, hand-drawn images of a spider web, and the ocean's surface in prints by Ms. Celmins; grainy aerial photographs that look as if they were shot from a spy satellite by Ms. Leonard; and Minimalist photograms with silvery surfaces by Ms. Deschenes. Tracy Williams, 313 West Fourth Street, West Village, (212) 229-2757 or tracywilliamsltd.com, through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist, whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444 or ubugallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 229-2766 or crggallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>George Herms Starting out as a beatnik in the 1950's, Mr. Herms has been creating and exhibiting his richly poetic assemblages of grungy found materials in California, his home state, for more than a half century. This show's eight works, from 1965 to 2002, variously call to mind Ernst, Duchamp, Cornell and Rauschenberg, but they have as well their own spiritually generous, heartfelt mix of hermetic imagination and Whitmanesque populism. Franklin Parrasch, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 246-5360 or franklinparrasch.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'How I Finally Accepted Fate' The memoir is the loosely defined theme of this interesting 10-person show. It includes Matt Keegan's video of cheerleaders celebrating his grandmother's 90th birthday; Angela Dufresne's vivid painting of a shirtless man called ''Me as a Communist Male in 'The Red and the White' ''; Carolee Schneemann's patchwork tale about modern love in photographs and typewritten words; and Maureen Duncan's three-and-a-half-hour monologue about her CD collection. EFA Gallery, 323 West 39th Street, (212) 563-5855; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* JUSTIN LOWE: HELTER SWELTER This labor-intensive trompe l'oeil installation passes through the emblematic sites of summer -- an urban bodega, a construction detour and an ice cream truck -- but its chief payoff is a womblike hippie heaven whose floor-of-many-colors is tiled in tightly wound T-shirts. Oliver Kamm/5BE Gallery, 621 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-0979 or 5begallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Money Changes Everything' A show of artworks made at least partly out of actual money: dollar bills, mostly, but Iraqi dinar notes, too. Schroeder Romero, 637 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 630-0722 or schroederromero.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212 or salon94.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the Northeast this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'THE FANTASTICKS' Previews start tomorrow. Opens Aug. 16. If you were one of the people who missed the 17,162 performances of this show the last time around, good news: Harvey Schmidt and Tom Jones's romantic musical, which closed in 2002, is back (2:05). Snapple Theater Center, 210 West 50th Street; (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'INDIAN BLOOD' In previews; opens Aug. 9. Primary Stages presents A. R. Gurney's new comedy about a rebellious boy coming of age in the 1940's. Mark Lamos directs (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street; (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'MARTIN SHORT: FAME BECOMES ME' Previews start tomorrow. Opens Aug. 17. This musical sendup of biographical shows features Martin Short and an ensemble telling the story of his life. Mr. Short's beloved old characters, like Ed Grimley and Jiminy Glick, make appearances (2:15). Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street; (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>MIDTOWN INTERNATIONAL THEATER FESTIVAL Through Aug. 6. The seventh annual showcase may get lost in the shuffle, despite its large and diverse collection of shows. There should be more than 60 productions this season, at four locations on 36th Street. Schedules and information: (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'A STONE CARVER' An elderly carver refuses to make way for a new highway in this drama set in the 1970's. Dan Lauria (''The Wonder Years'') stars (1:40). Soho Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, South Village; (212) 691-1555.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' (Tony Award, special theatrical event, 2006) This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants. Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200.(Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' (Tony Awards, best book of a musical and best original score, 2006) This small and ingratiating spoof of 1920's stage frolics, as imagined by an obsessive show queen, may not be a masterpiece. But in a dry season for musicals, ''The Drowsy Chaperone'' has theatergoers responding as if they were withering house plants, finally being watered after long neglect. Bob Martin and Sutton Foster are the standouts in the eager, energetic cast (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>*'FAITH HEALER' In the title role of Brian Friel's great play, Ralph Fiennes paints a portrait of the artist as dreamer and destroyer that feels both as old as folklore and so fresh that it might be painted in wet blood. Also starring Cherry Jones and the superb Ian McDiarmid, this mesmerizing series of monologues has been directed with poetic starkness by Jonathan Kent (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE HISTORY BOYS' (Tony Awards, best play and best direction of a play, 2006) Madly enjoyable. Alan Bennett's play about a battle for the hearts and minds of a group of university-bound students, imported with the original British cast from the National Theater, moves with a breezy narrative swagger that transcends cultural barriers. Directed by Nicholas Hytner, with a perfectly oiled ensemble led by the superb Richard Griffiths and Stephen Campbell Moore as schoolmasters with opposing views of history and education (2:40). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS'  (Tony Award, best musical, 2006) From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Please turn off your political-correctness monitor along with your cellphone for Martin McDonagh's gleeful, gory and appallingly entertaining play. This blood farce about terrorism in rural Ireland, acutely directed by Wilson Milam, has a carnage factor to rival Quentin Tarantino's. But it is also wildly, absurdly funny and, even more improbably, severely moral (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' (Tony Award, best direction of a musical, 2006) Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'TARZAN'  This writhing green blob with music, adapted by Disney Theatrical Productions from the 1999 animated film, has the feeling of a super-deluxe day care center, equipped with lots of bungee cords and karaoke synthesizers, where children can swing when they get tired of singing, and vice versa. The soda-pop score is by Phil Collins (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER'  An assembly-kit musical that might as well be called ''That 80's Show,'' this stage version of the 1998 film is all winks and nods and quotations from the era of big hair and junk bonds. The cast members, who include Stephen Lynch and Laura Benanti, are personable enough, which is not the same as saying they have personalities (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BULLY' William Walsh plays the quotable Theodore Roosevelt in this interesting but not completely polished one-man show (2:00). Irish Arts Center, 553 West 51st Street, (212) 868-4444. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>'CRAZY FOR THE DOG' Christopher Boal's effective family melodrama about a brother, a sister, a wife and a boyfriend caught in a web of recrimination and confession, touched off by the kidnapping of a shih tzu (2:00). Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, at Bond Street, East Village, (212) 677-0060, Ext. 16. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'THE FIELD'  John B. Keane's portrait of rural life in Ireland in the mid-20th century, both sorrowful and censorious. This sturdy new production, directed by Ciaran O'Reilly, features Marty Maguire as Bull McCabe, a tough farmer who will stop at nothing to preserve his right to raise his cattle on a field about to be auctioned. A little moralistic, but powerful nonetheless (2:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'FORBIDDEN BROADWAY: SPECIAL VICTIMS UNIT' This production features the expected caricatures of ego-driven singing stars. But even more than usual, the show offers an acute list of grievances about the sickly state of the Broadway musical, where, as the lyrics have it, ''everything old is old again'' (1:45). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Drew Sarich) and two women (Natascia Diazand Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best (2:00).Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'NO CHILD'  Teachers will love Nilaja Sun's one-woman show about the challenges of teaching drama at Malcolm X High School. Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, at Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 239-6200 (1:10). Beckett Theater at Theater Row, 410 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'PIG FARM' A gleefully stupid comedy by Greg Kotis about lust and violence in the farm belt, with a few gristly bits of satire aimed at the fat-bellied American electorate thrown in for good measure. Powered by the frenzied commitment of the four skilled actors who make up its cast, the comedy careers around the stage like an interminable improv session for a still-unformulated sketch on ''Saturday Night Live.'' (2:15). Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'ROOM SERVICE' The Peccadillo Theater Company puts a charge into this old comedy from the 1930's, thanks to a brisk pace by the director, Dan Wackerman, and a dozen dandy performances. David Edwards is the would-be producer whose bills threaten to swamp his efforts to put a show on Broadway, and Fred Berman is particularly fine as his director (2:00). Bank Street Theater, 155 Bank Street, West Village, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>* 'SPRING AWAKENING' German schoolboys of the 19th-century frolic like rockers in this adventurous new musical adapted from the 1891 play by Frank Wedekind about sex, death and adolescence. Staged with élan by Michael Mayer, and featuring alluringly melancholy music by the pop singer-songwriter Duncan Sheik, this is a flawed but vibrant show that stretches the stage musical in new directions (2:10). Atlantic Theater, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TEMPEST TOSSED FOOLS' This musical audience-participation children's version of ''The Tempest'' is rowdy, colorful and not all that Shakespearean. Manhattan Ensemble Theater, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo, (212) 239-6200. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'ANGEL MOUNTAIN' A young soldier, his mentally slow brother and their widowed father react to the new housekeeper in John-Richard Thompson's absorbing if sometimes predictable drama, set in 1946 (1:05). The Connelly Theater, 220 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'CHEKHOV &amp; MARIA'  Jovanka Bach's final play is a touching and beautifully acted if sometimes slow-paced study of Anton Chekhov's near-final days and his relationship with his sister, who cared for him (2:00). Barrow Group Theater, 312 West 36th Street, (212) 868-4444. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'CLOUD TECTONICS' A solid rendition of Jose Rivera's thin fable about time, centering on a hitchhiking woman who has been pregnant for two years. Luis Vega is particularly good as the man who gives her a ride and shelter for the night (1:30). Culture Project-45 Below, 45 Bleecker Street, at Lafayette Street, East Village, (212) 868-4444. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'IF YOU GIVE A MOUSE A COOKIE AND OTHER STORY BOOKS' This children's musical, made up of 10 sketches based on 8 books, is diverse, adorable and free. Also, the adults laugh (1:00). Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, West Village; (212) 642-9033. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' Another excavation of what seems to have become Broadway's favorite musical terrain -- call it Scamalot, where conmen are king (see ''The Producers.'') Now starring Keith Carradine and Brian D'Arcy James at the mismatched swindlers. (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DRUMSTRUCK' Lightweight entertainment that stops just short of pulverizing the eardrums (1:30).Dodger Stages, Stage 2, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Lawrence Van Gelder)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street at Broadway, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'FOOD FOR FISH' Adam Szymkowicz's fabulously weird and weirdly fabulous new comedy fools around with cross-dressing, suicidal writers and Chekhovian characters who long for New Jersey (2:00). Kraine Theater, 85 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing tomorrow. (Gates)</p>
        <p>'FRANKENSTEIN, THE MUSICAL' More is not better in Robert Mitchell's show based on Mary Shelley's novel. The too many songs and scenes are confusing and ultimately defeat the cast, while Brian Charles Rooney as the scientist Victor Frankenstein might regain his fire if he switched roles with Timothy Warmen, who, as the lab mistake, seems more like a morose personal trainer out on a hike (2:15). The Wings Theater, 154 Christopher Street, between Washington and Greenwich Streets, West Village, (212) 627-2961; closing on Sunday. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>'THE HOUSE IN TOWN'  A wan new drama by Richard Greenberg about an American marriage slowly imploding in the days before the country's economy did the same, more suddenly and spectacularly, in 1929. A miscast Jessica Hecht stars as Amy Hammer, a well-to-do housewife sliding into despair as her remote husband looks on in frustration. Doug Hughes's production is pretty but desultory, as is Mr. Greenberg's typically eloquent but atypically empty writing (1:30). Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 150 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'ORANGE LEMON EGG CANARY' Rinne Groff's deceptive romance about a hard-drinking magician is like a great trick with a bungled payoff (1:30). Performance Space 122, 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street, East Village, (212) 352-3101; closing on Sunday. (Jason Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SECRETS' A clunky relationship drama about shrill, cruel middle-age couples (1:05). The Theater at St. Luke's, 308 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing on Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'SUSAN AND GOD' The Mint Theater Company's fine revival of Rachel Crothers's 1937 comedy about religion, career and family features Leslie Hendrix of ''Law &amp; Order,'' excellent in the role of Susan. Jonathan Bank directs (2:20). The Mint Theater, 311 West 43rd Street, third floor, Clinton, (212) 315-0231; closing on Sunday. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>'TREASON' The poet Ezra Pound was a repellent fellow, judging from this play by Sallie Bingham: racist, anti-Semitic, eager to exploit the affections of the women who loved him. Just why women were drawn to him is never clear, but the play is thoughtful, and the acting, especially by Philip Pleasants as Pound, is superb (2:10). Perry Street Theater, 31 Perry Street, just west of Seventh Avenue, West Village, (212) 868-4444; closing tomorrow. (Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>* 'AN INCONVENIENT TRUTH' (PG, 96 minutes) Al Gore gives a lecture on climate change. One of the most exciting and necessary movies of the year. Seriously. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'ARMY OF SHADOWS' (No rating, 140 minutes, in French) Dark as pitch and without compromise, Jean-Pierre Melville's 1969 masterpiece centers on the feats of a small band of Resistance fighters during the occupation. Brilliant, harrowing, essential viewing.(Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>'BEEN RICH ALL MY LIFE' (No rating, 80 minutes) This admiring documentary portrait of the Silver Belles, an indefatigable troupe of veteran Harlem tap dancers between the ages of 84 and 96, is a valuable historical footnote and a useful how-to movie about making the most of old age. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE BREAK-UP' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Jennifer Aniston and Vince Vaughn split up and share custody of a Chicago condominium. Dull and cheerless, notwithstanding a handful of funny supporting turns, notably from Judy Davis and Jason Bateman. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CARS' (G, 114 minutes) The latest 3-D toon from Pixar just putt, putt, putts along, a shining model of technological progress and consumer safety. John Lasseter directed, and Owen Wilson provides the voice of the little red race car who learns all the right lessons from, among others, a 1951 Hudson Hornet given voice by Paul Newman. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'CHANGING TIMES' (No rating, 95 minutes, in French and Arabic) Gérard Depardieu and Catherine Deneuve star in André Téchiné's rich, warmhearted exploration of cultural collision in contemporary Tangier. A half-dozen skillfully interwoven subplots create a set of variations on the theme of divided sensibilities tugging one another into states of perpetual unrest and possible happiness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'CLERKS II' (R, 98 minutes) More than a decade later, Kevin Smith's New Jersey underachievers have moved from a convenience store to a fast-food franchise. The humor is reliably filthy and frequently hilarious, and the filmmaking is a few steps above rudimentary, but the movie's poignant sweetness is disarming. It has a dirty mind, but its heart is remarkably pure. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'CLICK' (PG-13, 98 minutes) Adam Sandler stars in this unfunny comedy about a harried family man who uses a universal remote to hop-scotch through time. It's a wonderful life, not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'LEONARD COHEN: I'M YOUR MAN' (PG-13, 104 minutes) This enthralling documentary combines pieces of an extended interview with Mr. Cohen, the Canadian singer-songwriter, poet and author, now 71, with a tribute concert at the Sydney Opera House in January 2005. Nick Cave, Rufus Wainwright, Kate and Anna McGarrigle, Martha Wainwright and Antony are among the featured performers. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'THE DA VINCI CODE' (PG-13, 148 minutes) Theology aside, ''The Da Vinci Code'' is, above all, a murder mystery. And as such, once it gets going, Ron Howard's movie has its pleasures. He and the screenwriter Akiva Goldsman have deftly rearranged some elements of the plot, unkinking a few overelaborate twists and introducing others that keep the action moving along. The movie does, however, take a while to accelerate, popping the clutch and leaving rubber on the road as it tries to establish who is who, what he's doing and why. So I certainly can't support any calls for boycotting or protesting this busy, trivial, inoffensive film. Which is not to say that I'm recommending that you go see it. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA' (PG-13, 106 minutes) Lauren Weisberger's score-settling best seller about a terrible (and famous) boss is reimagined and reversed. Anne Hathaway plays the beleaguered assistant, but she is much less interesting -- and in the end less sympathetic -- than the boss, Miranda Priestly, incarnated by Meryl Streep as a subtle and searching (and very funny) portrait of glamour and power. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE FAST AND THE FURIOUS: TOKYO DRIFT' (PG-13, 98 minutes) The ''Fast and Furious'' formula (dudes + cars + babes = $) is recycled in Tokyo, where the cars are smaller, and the clothes are kookier, but the boys are still boys. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'GARFIELD: A TAIL OF TWO KITTIES'  (PG, 80 minutes) It was the worst of times. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'Gabrielle' (No rating, 90 minutes) A film of eccentric beauty and wild feeling, directed by the consistently inventive Patrice Chéreau and starring the supremely well-matched Pascal Greggory and Isabelle Huppert, about the dissolution of a haute bourgeoisie Parisian marriage, circa 1912. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE GROOMSMEN' (R, 93 minutes) Just when it seems that Edward Burns might have pulled off an American ''I Vitelloni,'' his X-ray vision into life in an Irish-American enclave in New York glazes over, and he resolves his characters' anxiety and despair with tearful hugs and phony reassurances. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'HEADING SOUTH' (No rating, 105 minutes, in English and French) Sex tourism involving middle-aged white women and black beach boys at a Haitian resort in the late 1970's is the subject of Laurent Cantet's third film, one of the most truthful explorations of desire, age and youth ever filmed, with a politically charged subtext about capitalist imperialism. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KEEPING UP WITH THE STEINS' (PG-13, 84 minutes) A rollicking bar mitzvah comedy begins as a growling, razor-toothed satire of carnivorous consumption in Hollywood. But after the first half-hour, those growls subside into whimpers, and the fangs are retracted, and the movie morphs turns into a feel-good family comedy oozing good vibes. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'KILL YOUR IDOLS' (No rating, 71 minutes) S. A. Crary's glib, unfocused music documentary examines the New York No Wave scene of the late 1970's -- an offshoot of punk, the anti-New Wave -- when the music was noisy (and genuinely noncommercial) and the clothes were black (and genuinely secondhand). (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LADY IN THE WATER' (PG-13, 108 minutes) In this watchable folly, Paul Giamatti plays a building manager who encounters a menagerie of otherworldy creatures, most important Bryce Dallas Howard's water nymph. The writer and director M. Night Shyamalan wants us to believe, mostly in the myth of his own genius. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE LAKE HOUSE' (PG, 108 minutes) Keanu Reeves and Sandra Bullock, reunited 12 years after ''Speed,'' play would-be lovers separated by time and yet somehow able to communicate. The absolute preposterousness of this teary romance is inseparable from its charm, which is greater than you might expect. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'LITTLE MAN' (PG-13, 90 minutes) A belligerent midget jewel thief assaults groins and molests women in this infantile comedy from the Wayans brothers. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Mini's First Time' (R, 91 minutes) Yet another poor little rich girl tends to her festering inner wounds by becoming one of Southern California's children of the damned. Nikki Reed stars alongside the slumming likes of Alec Baldwin, Carrie-Anne Moss, Jeff Goldblum and Luke Wilson. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'MONSTER HOUSE' (PG, 86 minutes) This scary movie for kids provides more fun in 86 minutes than all the other would-be summer blockbusters combined. A trio of intrepid youngsters face down a demonic dwelling in a quiet suburb. The motion-capture animation produces an uncanny feeling of realism, while the fantastical effects are spooky, witty and spectacular. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'THE OH IN OHIO' (No rating, 91 minutes) A feel-good movie about feeling good, this fresh and very funny sex comedy stars Parker Posey as a woman in search of an orgasm, Paul Rudd as her frustrated husband, and a delirious supporting cast: Danny DeVito as a swimming pool salesman, Heather Graham as a sex shop clerk and Liza Minnelli as a masturbation guru who encourages frigid women to ''liberate your labia!'' (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'NACHO LIBRE' (PG, 91 minutes) A sweet bliss-out from the writers Mike White, Jerusha Hess and Jared Hess, who also directed, that finds a glorious Jack Black as a half-Mexican, half-Scandinavian monastery cook who aches to belong to another brotherhood, that of the luchadores, or masked wrestlers. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'OVER THE HEDGE' (PG, 83 minutes) This tale about some woodland critters threatened by their new human neighbors has the technical trappings of a worthwhile Saturday matinee, so it's too bad no one paid commensurate attention to the script. The writers, including Karey Kirkpatrick, who directed with Tim Johnson, pad the story with the usual yuks and some glop about family, but there is no poetry here and little thought. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'PEACEFUL WARRIOR' (PG-13, 120 minutes) As ludicrous as the title promises, yet supremely unembarrassed, this New Age enlightenment parable has its heart in the right place, but a mind of corny mush. (Lee)</p>
        <p>'Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man's Chest' (PG-13, 151 minutes) Although there are memorable bits and pieces, this is a movie with no particular interest in coherence, economy or feeling. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'A PRAIRIE HOME COMPANION' (PG-13, 105 minutes) Garrison Keillor's long-running Public Radio hootenanny turns out to be the perfect vehicle for Robert Altman's fluid, chaotic humanism. The performances -- especially by Lily Tomlin and Meryl Streep as a pair of singing sisters -- are so full of relaxed vitality that you almost don't notice that the film is, at heart, a wry, sober contemplation of mortality. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'THE ROAD TO GUANTÁNAMO' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom's powerful, slippery new film mixes documentary and fictional techniques to tell the true story of three British Muslims imprisoned by the United States government in Guantánamo Bay, Cuba. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'SHADOWBOXER' (R, 93 minutes) This garish thriller starring Helen Mirren and Cuba Gooding Jr. as contract killers and lovers is an extravagance that leaves you with your mouth hanging open -- partly in admiration of its audacity and partly in disbelief at its preposterousness. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'A SCANNER DARKLY' (R, 100 minutes) Identities shift and melt like shadows in Richard Linklater's animated adaptation of the Philip K. Dick semispeculative novel ''A Scanner Darkly,'' a look at a future that appears an awful lot like today. With the voices and gestures of Keanu Reeves, Woody Harrelson, Winona Ryder and a wonderful Robert Downey Jr. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'STRANGERS WITH CANDY' (R, 87 minutes) High school high jinks, adapted from the beloved Comedy Central series. The comedy is stretched a little thin by the feature length, but there are still some laughs. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'MY SUPER EX-GIRLFRIEND' (PG-13, 110 minutes) A shaky comedy from the director Ivan Reitman, in which ''Fatal Attraction'' meets ''Wonder Woman,'' by way of Uma Thurman, Luke Wilson and some sexist she-devil clichés, some funny, others not. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SUPERMAN RETURNS' (PG-13, 157 minutes) Last seen larking about on the big screen in the 1987 dud ''Superman IV,'' the Man of Steel has been resurrected in Bryan Singer's leaden new film not only to fight for truth, justice and the American way, but also to give Mel Gibson's passion a run for his box-office money. Where once the superhero flew up, up and away, he now flies down, down, down, sent from above to save mankind from its sins and another bummer summer. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'WAIST DEEP' (R, 97 minutes) Tyrese Gibson plays an ex-convict trying to rescue his son from ruthless criminal kidnappers in this far-from-terrible B movie, directed with style and heart by Vondie Curtis Hall. (Scott)</p>
        <p>* 'WHO KILLED THE ELECTRIC CAR?' (PG, 92 minutes) A murder mystery, a call to arms and an effective inducement to rage, Chris Paine's film about the recent rise and fall of the electric car is the latest and one of the more successful additions to the growing ranks of issue-oriented documentaries. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'THE WORLD ACCORDING TO SHORTS' (No rating, 95 minutes total running time) For audiences exhausted by today's bloated extravaganzas, ''The World According to Shorts'' is an eclectic palate cleanser. Addressing topics as diverse as aging, marital sex and the fantasy lives of children, this six-film sampling of world cinema ranges from the traditional to the surreal, the latter brilliantly exemplified by the German animated western ''Ring of Fire.'' As frustrated cowboys trail beckoning women and pulsing vaginas across a Dalíesque landscape, the wonderful world of Disney seems a million miles away. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'X-MEN: THE LAST STAND' (PG-13, 104 minutes) As expected, the third and presumably last film about the powerful Marvel Comics mutants who walk and often fight among us pretty much looks and plays like the first two, though perhaps with more noise and babes, and a little less glum. The credited writers here are Simon Kinberg and Zak Penn, who, like the director, Brett Ratner, are not mutant enough to fly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>You, Me and Dupree' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Owen Wilson stars as the dude who comes to dinner and stays way past dessert in Joe and Anthony Russo's generally unfunny comedy. A fine Matt Dillon and a decorative Kate Hudson also star, rather more wanly. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>FRANK BORZAGE, HOLLYWOOD ROMANTIC (Through Aug. 20) A 24-film retrospective of Borzage (1893-1962) continues at the Museum of the Moving Image with two silents starring Janet Gaynor and Charles Farrell. Borzage won the first-ever best-director Oscar for ''Seventh Heaven'' (1927), a love story set in a slum. In ''Street Angel'' (1928), Gaynor plays a Neapolitan prostitute. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>GREAT VILLAINS IN CINEMA (Through Sunday) BAMcinématek's tribute to movie bad guys comes to a close this weekend with three films. In ''The Manchurian Candidate'' (1962), Angela Lansbury's character sells out her nearest and dearest for political power. In ''The Godfather: Part II'' (1974), Michael Corleone (Al Pacino) turns ruthless. In ''Apocalypse Now Redux'' (1979), Marlon Brando's Colonel Kurtz embraces the horror. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>HISTORIC HARLEM PARKS FESTIVAL: THROUGH AFRICAN EYES AND PRIZED PIECES (Through Thursday) This fifth annual outdoor festival concludes next week with two very different features. Wednesday night's film, from Senegal, is ''Hyenas'' (1992), a drama in which a rich woman bribes poor villagers to commit murder. Thursday night's feature is ''All on a Mardi Gras Day'' (2003), Royce Osborne's look at the history of African-American culture in New Orleans. Harlem Meer, Central Park, 110th Street and Lenox Avenue, (212) 352-1720; free. (Gates)</p>
        <p>KUROSAWA (Through Sept. 18) The IFC Center's series honoring Akira Kurosawa continues Sunday and Tuesday with ''The Lower Depths'' (1957), his adaptation of Maxim Gorky's masterpiece about poor souls in a flophouse. 323 Avenue of the Americas, at West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 924-7771; $10.75. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RAISING HELL: SAM PECKINPAH (Through Aug. 29) BAMcinématek's monthlong tribute to Peckinpah (1925-84) begins Tuesday night with ''Ride the High Country'' (1962), his second film, which stars Randolph Scott and Joel McCrea as Old West lawmen in a changing world. Thursday night's film is Peckinpah's masterpiece, ''The Wild Bunch'' (1969), a violent western about the nature of morality. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ADOLESCENTS (Sunday) After a painfully drawn-out dispute with its landlord, CBGB will close at the end of October, which means that everybody is rushing to play his last gig there. Sunday features the Adolescents, one of the architects of the early-1980's Southern California hardcore punk sound, who joined the scruffy melodicism of the Ramones with boys-will-be-boys petulance and angry social realism. With the Freeze, Street Dogs and the Vacancies. At 6:30 p.m., 315 Bowery, at Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 982-4052, cbgb.com; $13 in advance, $15 at the door. (Ben Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLOC PARTY (Tomorrow) With spiky but melodic guitars and agitated dance beats, Bloc Party revives the nervous funk of postpunk bands like Gang of Four. With Secret Machines and Mew. At 6:30 p.m., McCarren Park Pool, Lorimer Street, between Driggs Avenue and Bayard Street, Greenpoint, Brooklyn, (212) 307-7171; $34. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BON JOVI (Tomorrow) Bon Jovi, the band that titled its 1998 album ''New Jersey,'' is back in its home state. Jon Bon Jovi's band conquered the airwaves in the 1980's and 90's by sticking together everything catchy about 1970's rock: Bruce Springsteen's earnestness, Led Zeppelin's crunch, Boston's harmonies and lyrics that paint romance as nothing less than a titanic adventure. A photogenic lead singer doesn't hurt, either. With Nickelback. At 7 p.m., Giants Stadium, East Rutherford, N.J., (201) 935-3900, meadowlands.com; $37.50 to $125. (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>* BRAND NEW (Tonight) This Long Island emo band made a quantum leap with its second album three years ago, from whiny and unchallenging breakup songs to tangles of explosive melody with brooding, sometimes horrific lyrics. What the band will come up with on its as-yet-unscheduled album No. 3 is a subject of intense speculation among fans. With Colour Revolt. At 6:30, Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EDIE BRICKELL AND NEW BOHEMIANS (Tonight) Sixteen years after her last studio album with New Bohemians, Edie Brickell has reunited with the group; their new record, ''Stranger Things'' (Fantasy/Concord), was released on Tuesday. With Sonya Kitchell, a teenage singer-songwriter whose debut CD is promoted by Starbucks. At 7, Central Park SummerStage, Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777, summerstage.org; free, but a donation is suggested. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>JIM CAMPILONGO, MIKE VIOLA (Monday) Just another night at the Living Room, a plain Lower East Side cabaret that puts on one guitar-cradling singer-songwriter after another, some of them world-class. Mr. Campilongo is a well-traveled guitar whiz who plays with Norah Jones in her country band, the Little Willies; here he leads his Electric Trio. Mr. Viola, jumping from piano to guitar, sings strident power-pop with some jagged wit. Also on the bill are Grainne Ryan, Alice Bierhorst, Jim Boggia and the Jason Crigler Band. At 6 p.m., 154 Ludlow Street, near Stanton Street, (212) 533-7235, livingroomny.com; no cover. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133, dannysgrandseapalace.com; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>DILLINGER ESCAPE PLAN (Wednesday) With harsh screams and convoluted guitar riffs that sometimes seem to have been written with the aid of advanced calculus, this New Jersey band plays a cathartic and yet impossibly complex kind of punk-jazz. With God Forbid. At 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111, boweryballroom.com; $20. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* DIXIE CHICKS (Tuesday and Wednesday) After first backing down slightly from their criticism of President Bush in 2003, the Dixie Chicks returned this year with ''Taking the Long Way'' (Columbia), a reflective and defiant album that declares: ''I'm not ready to make nice/I'm not ready to back down.'' Tuesday at 7:30 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741, thegarden.com; $39.59 to $89.50. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., Nikon at Jones Beach Theater, Wantagh, N.Y., (516) 221-1000, nikonjonesbeach.com; $39.50 to $75. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'DOT DASH YEAR IV' (Tonight and tomorrow) For its minifestival each summer, Dot Dash, a little concert promoter in Brooklyn devoted to punk and garage-rock, presents some big-deal reunions. This year features Rocket From the Tombs, a storied protopunk band from Cleveland that never recorded an album but spawned two influential groups when it broke up in 1975: the arty Pere Ubu and the more conventionally bratty Dead Boys. The band first reunited in 2003 and returns tomorrow with new material on a bill with the Little Killers, DC Snipers, Angry Angles and Imaginary Icons. Tonight's show features the Cynics, the Original Sins, the Hentchmen, the Turpentine Brothers and the Alarm Clocks, a 1960's band from Ohio whose single ''No Reason to Complain'' has been covered by countless shaggy-haired bands. At 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $17 tonight, $20 tomorrow. Rocket From the Tombs also plays on Sunday at 9 p.m. at Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $15. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>NICOLAI DUNGER (Tonight) A Swedish balladeer with serious Van Morrison envy, Mr. Dunger makes earnest entreaties for romance and existential relief (''Take away my sadness, wipe away these blues in here'') in a tremulous tenor. With Elvis Perkins and Benjy Ferree. At 7, South Street Seaport, Pier 17, Fulton and South Streets, Lower Manhattan, (212) 835-2789, seaportmusicfestival.com; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>EDITORS (Tonight) This band from Birmingham, England, chose a fitting name: it stitches together material from other sources with taste and artistry, joining the baritone-of-gloom vocals of Joy Division (''Oh, if fortune favors the brave/I am as poor as they come'') and the early U2's shimmering sheets of guitar. With Lake Trout and the Big Sleep. At 9, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>MARY GAUTHIER (Wednesday) Ms. Gauthier, who was born in Baton Rouge, La., and worked as a restaurateur before turning to music, writes sparse observations that suggest a modest but penetrating wisdom (''Every living thing could use a little mercy now''). With Eliza Gilkyson. At 7 p.m., Madison Square Park, Madison Avenue at 24th Street, (212) 538-6667; free. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>METERS (Thursday) Hurricane Katrina could not drown New Orleans syncopation. It lives on with the reunion of the Meters, the definitive New Orleans funk band since 1967. The group has backed others, but saved its snappiest, trickiest grooves for its own tracks. With Art Neville on keyboards, George Porter Jr. on bass, Leo Nocentelli on guitar and Zigaboo Modeliste on drums, they open up nooks and crannies of the beat to carry every hip into irresistible motion. At 9 p.m., Nokia Theater, 1515 Broadway, at 44th Street, (212) 307-7171, nokiatheatrenyc.com; $45. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* NEW PORNOGRAPHERS, CALEXICO, FRAMES (Thursday) If the weather holds, this benefit for Central Park SummerStage will be a perfect night of smart, tuneful indie rock. The New Pornographers, from Vancouver, British Columbia, play sharp, elegant pop-rock with a wit that comes down from the Kinks. Calexico, a collective from Tucson, pushes desert-dry alt-country toward surf guitar, mariachi and a folk-flavored psychedelia like that of the 1960's band Love. The Frames are one of the most expressive Irish groups since U2. At 6 p.m., Rumsey Playfield, midpark at 70th Street, (212) 360-2777, summerstage.org; $30 in advance, $35 at the site. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OLLABELLE (Monday through Thursday) Celebrating a new album, ''Riverside Battle Songs'' (Verve Forecast), Ollabelle, a vocal sextet that worships country, bluegrass and gospel with crystalline voices and wide eyes, will play for four nights at Banjo Jim's, an East Village club the group has played many times. At 9 p.m., Avenue C at Ninth Street, (212) 777-0869, banjojims.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>OZZFEST (Tomorrow) In its 11th installment, the annual carnival of black cotton T-shirts, guttural heavy metal and nostalgic affection for Ozzy Osbourne features System of a Down, Disturbed, Avenged Sevenfold, Hatebreed, Lacuna Coil, Dragonforce and many others on a smaller stage. Ozzy fans in New York are fortunate: this concert is one of only 8 among the 27 stops on the tour that will feature Mr. Osbourne performing on the main stage. Doors open at 9 a.m., Randalls Island, near Icahn Stadium, 1 Randalls Island, (212) 307-7171, ozzfest.com; $87.50. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>BRAD PAISLEY (Tonight) A young songwriter who knows the value of terse composition and sly wordplay, Mr. Paisley scored one of country's biggest hits last year with ''Alcohol.'' A droll defense of grog from the drink's point of view (''I've been known to cause a few breakups/And I've been known to cause a few births''), it is one of those rare novelty songs that outlives its novelty. With Eric Church, a rising country singer from North Carolina. At 8, Bethel Woods Center for the Arts, Bethel, N.Y., (845) 454-3388, bethelwoods.us; $46; $30.50 for lawn seats. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>* 'RAMAKIEN: A RAK OPERA' (Tonight through Sunday) The Lincoln Center Festival presents an intriguing ''rock-theater piece'' based on an excerpt from the Ramakien, the Thai national epic. The show features many of Thailand's biggest and most respected rockers, including Sek Loso, who has led his band at the South by Southwest and Glastonbury festivals; the Photo Sticker Machine, an electronic group; and Rik Vachilapun, called a cross between Diamanda Galás and Patti Smith. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, Sunday night at 7, La Guardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts, Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; $40. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>The RED KRAYOLA (Wednesday) The first album of the Red Crayola (as it was originally called) appeared in 1967, and Mayo Thompson has held on to its skewed psychedelic perspective ever since; he also spent some years as a member of Pere Ubu. He's fond of dissolving song structures, crypto-Marxist messages and woozy sounds, and when he reconvened the Red Krayola (its name was changed to avoid trademark problems) in 1994, he found fans and collaborators among progressive- and post-rock musicians. With White Magic and Miighty Flashlight. At 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006, knittingfactory.com; $12 in advance, $14 at the door. (Pareles)</p>
        <p>* SLEATER-KINNEY (Wednesday) After a 12-year reign over indie rock, the three women of Sleater-Kinney are calling it quits: their brief summer tour will find them screaming their last shrill screams and playing their last postpunk deconstructions of thick, meaty guitar riffs. At 8 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 533-2111, bowerypresents.com; sold out. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUL ASYLUM (Thursday) This Minneapolis band lived the story of alternative rock: from loud and scrappy beginnings in the early 1980's, it matured largely out of sight of the mainstream, then found sudden fame in the 90's. The next phase is the reunion with something to prove, and on ''The Silver Lining'' (Legacy), its first new studio album in eight years, Soul Asylum proves that it still has a strong command of burly guitar and yearning vocals. At 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800, irvingplaza.com; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>SOUND TEAM (Tonight through Monday) Recalling Spoon, another indie band from Austin, Tex., Sound Team constructs dense and psychologically rich songs in which elements of white soul hint at a spiritual nourishment denied by the anxious guitars and brooding, aloof vocals. With Cold War Kids and Midlake. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9, Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700, mercuryloungenyc.com; sold out tonight, $12 tomorrow. Sunday at 8 p.m., Southpaw, 125 Fifth Avenue, near Sterling Place, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 230-0236, spsounds.com; $10. Monday at 8:30 p.m., Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 653-1703, maxwellsnj.com; $10. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>DAR WILLIAMS (Wednesday) In bare and tuneful songs that are called folk because they are quiet but could very well be rock, Ms. Williams is sometimes reflective and sometimes topical, as in her recent ''Teen for God,'' which explores religion as a psychological terror on the young: ''Dear Lord, I plan each day/The things I will not do or say.'' She plays an acoustic set. At 7 p.m., Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, rmanyc.org; $50, including museum admission. (Sisario)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DON BYRON QUARTET (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Byron is justifiably known for his independent-minded concept albums -- his next one will shine a spotlight on the rhythm-and-blues saxophonist Junior Walker -- but he is, first and foremost, a daring clarinetist. He will play with several longtime associates: the trumpeter Ralph Alessi, the bassist Lonnie Plaxico and the drummer Billy Hart. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $25; $30 tonight and tomorrow. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>CELEBRATION OF RAY BARRETTO AND HILTON RUIZ (Tonight through Sunday) ''Standards Rican-ditioned,'' recently issued on Zoho Music, was the final studio album of the conga virtuoso Ray Barretto. It also turned out to be the last recorded effort by the pianist Hilton Ruiz. Both were New York-born musicians of Puerto Rican heritage, and both were pillars of the Latin jazz community. This tribute, fittingly programmed as the culmination of a monthlong ''Latin in Manhattan'' festival, includes Mr. Barretto's son Chris Barretto, as well as a couple of more established saxophonists, Sonny Fortune and David Sánchez. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set tonight and tomorrow, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SYLVIE COURVOISIER AND MARK FELDMAN (Tonight) As a pianist and composer, Ms. Courvoisier pursues intricacy and rigor; Mr. Feldman, a violinist, favors plangent intensity. They have worked well as a duo, perhaps most notably on ''Malphas: Book of Angels Vol. 3'' (Tzadik), a volume of John Zorn compositions. At 8, Center for Improvisational Music, 295 Douglass Street, between Third and Fourth Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (212) 631-5882, schoolforimprov.org; cover, $12. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EDDIE DURHAM JAZZ FESTIVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) Eddie Durham was an important composer, arranger and bandleader of the prewar era, best known for helping shape the sound of Kansas City swing. He also played trombone and guitar, tasks handled respectively by Fred Wesley and Hiram Bullock in this casual salute. Through Aug. 6. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595, jalc.org; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARTY EHRLICH SEXTET (Sunday) As on his appealing recent album, ''News on the Rail'' (Palmetto), Mr. Ehrlich, a versatile alto saxophonist and virtuoso clarinetist, leads a sextet that includes James Zollar on trumpet, Allison Miller on drums and Howard Johnson on tuba and baritone saxophone. At 8 p.m., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Sculpture Garden at the Museum of Modern Art, 15 West 54th Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9491. moma.org/events/summergarden; free, but tickets, required for entry, will be distributed at 5:30 p.m. on a first-come-first-served basis. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JON FADDIS QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Faddis is a highly proficient trumpeter, sometimes to the point of effulgence. But with ''Teranga'' (Koch), his first quartet album in 15 years, he exercises an effective and impressive restraint, with the help of David Hazeltine on piano, Kiyoshi Kitagawa on bass and Dion Parson on drums. Through Aug. 6. At 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232, jazzstandard.net; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FAUX, FAUX (Tonight) Conceived as a showcase for the veteran avant-garde trumpeter Baikida Carroll, this collective quartet features the convoluted compositions of its other members, mainly Tim Berne, an alto saxophonist, and Michael Formanek, a bassist. At 10, 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>WYCLIFFE GORDON QUARTET (Tonight) Mr. Gordon, a high-spirited trombonist and one of the most authoritative soloists in the Jazz at Lincoln Center Orchestra, leads a swing-minded small group with Dan Nimmer on piano, Thaddeus Expose on bass and Marion Felder on drums. At 7, Rubin Museum of Art, 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000, Ext. 344, www.rmanyc.org; $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DANNY GRISSETT TRIO (Tomorrow) Mr. Grissett is a young pianist with a strong track record as a sideman and a solid debut as a leader: ''Promise,'' on Criss Cross Records. Kendrick Scott plays drums, as on the album; Dwayne Burno is a substitute bassist but a good one. At 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063, jazzgallery.org; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RANDY JOHNSTON TRIO (Tonight) A proficient guitarist, Mr. Johnston sounds best performing with a trio in an intimate setting, like this one, where he frequently appears. At 9:15, 10:40 and midnight, Puppets Jazz Bar, 294 Fifth Avenue, near Second Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 499-2627, puppetsjazz.com; $5, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL KANAN TRIO (Sunday) Mr. Kanan is an articulate pianist, and his trio, with Joseph Lepore on bass and Jeff Williams on drums, adheres to a melodic and unhurried variety of post-bop. At 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Café, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $8, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>KEVIN MAHOGANY (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Mahogany's rich and deep-toned singing voice is worthy of his stately surname. He will use it to pay tribute to the crooner Johnny Hartman, another baritone with an appropriate handle. At 8 and 10 p.m., with a midnight set tonight and tomorrow, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121, iridiumjazzclub.com; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) As on a recent Blue Note album, Mr. Martino pays homage to one of his guitar heroes, Wes Montgomery. The untroubled self-assurance of the emulation and the simple satisfaction of a hard-swinging band make the gesture pay off. Through Aug. 5. At 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080, birdlandjazz.com; cover, $35, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAUL MOTIAN TRIO 2000 + 1 (Tuesday through Thursday) Show tunes and other standards receive loving and slyly imaginative interpretations on ''Paul Motian on Broadway Vol. 4'' (Winter &amp; Winter), scheduled for release just after this weeklong run. Mr. Motian's teasingly suggestive drumming is well matched by the quietly abstruse pianism of Masabumi Kikuchi; Rebecca Martin handles vocals, with a casual sort of purity. The tenor saxophonist Chris Potter and the bassist Larry Grenadier add some welcome ballast and heft. Through Aug. 6. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE NELSON/MULGREW MILLER QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Nelson, on vibraphone, and Mr. Miller, on piano, travel with grace and confidence through the familiar terrain of post-bop, joined by Ivan Taylor on bass and Carl Allen on drums. At 8, 10 and 11:30, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662, smokejazz.com; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>GREG OSBY QUARTET (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Osby is an alto saxophonist with a predilection for jagged edges, and yet he's squarely within the jazz tradition. His rhythm section here consists of the pianist Frank LoCrasto, the bassist Matt Brewer and the drummer Tommy Crane. At 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037, villagevanguard.com; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE OTHER HALF (Wednesday) Notwithstanding the title, which is either weakly ironic or oddly dismissive, this concert is a laudable showcase for six female avant-garde composers. In order, they are the cellist Ha-Yang Kim, performing alone; the pianist Angelica Sanchez, with a top-shelf quintet; the vocalist Judith Berkson, self-accompanied on keyboards; the alto saxophonist Matana Roberts, in a solo exertion; and the sympathetic duo of Jessica Pavone, on viola, and Mary Halvorson, on guitar. At 7:30 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501, tonicnyc.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>HOUSTON PERSON QUARTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Person's latest album, ''You Taught My Heart to Sing'' (Half Note), features his tenor saxophone and Bill Charlap's piano in a program of tender duets. Performing without Mr. Charlap, he returns to form, applying his robust tone to a more rhythmically assertive purpose. At 9, 10:30 and midnight, Lenox Lounge, 288 Lenox Avenue, near 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 427-0253, lenoxlounge.com; cover, $25, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* SPIRIT OF DJANGO REINHARDT (Tuesday) What began as a strict salute to this immortal Manouche Gypsy guitarist has evolved into a smorgasbord of buoyant swing, as well as a New York institution. This year's summer concert features a prominent inheritor of the Reinhardt style, Dorado Schmitt, along with two of his guitar-playing family members: Samson Schmitt, his son, and Tchavolo Schmitt, a cousin. Also on hand are the Romanian violinist Florin Niculescu, the French accordionist Ludovic Beier, the Dutch pianist Peter Beets and a pair of Americans: Joel Frahm, a saxophonist, and Brian Torff, who plays bass and serves as musical director. At 8 p.m., Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 721-6500, jalc.org; $37 to $57. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ROBBINS AND CENTRIC (Tomorrow) ''Waits and Measures'' (Playscape), the new album by the alto saxophonist Pete Robbins, is an intimate sort of jazz-rock hybrid, complete with Fender Rhodes piano and artfully fuzzed-out electric guitar. Mr. Robbins reconvenes the album's cast here: Sam Sadigursky on saxophones, Mike Gamble on guitar, Eliot Cardinaux on keyboards, Thomas Morgan on bass, and Dan Weiss and Tyshawn Sorey on drums. At 10 p.m., Detour, 349 East 13th Street, East Village, (212) 533-6212, jazzatdetour.com; cover, $5. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>ARTURO SANDOVAL (Tuesday through Thursday) Mr. Sandoval is a trumpeter best known for stratospheric bravado, though he occasionally reaches for a subtler aesthetic. His Latin-jazz sextet features Ed Calle on saxophones, Javier Concepcion on piano, Armando Gola on bass, Tomas Cruz on percussion and Alexis Arce on drums. Through Aug. 6 at 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592 bluenote.net; cover, $30 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>SKERIK'S MAELSTROM TRIO (Tomorrow and Sunday) The tenor and soprano saxophonist known as Skerik brings a hyperactive jam-band mentality to the traditions of soul-jazz organ trios, with Brian Coogan on Hammond B-3 organ and Simon Lott on drums. Tomorrow night at 12:30, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $15, with a $5 minimum. Sunday at 9:30 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, near Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 929-9883, 55bar.com; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LOREN STILLMAN'S TRIO ALTO (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Stillman, a young alto saxophonist with an inquisitive relationship to jazz conventions, joins forces with two exploratory rhythm players, the bassist John Hebert and the drummer Take Toriyama. Wednesday at 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177, barbesbrooklyn.com; cover, $8. Thursday at 9 and 10 p.m., Tea Lounge, 837 Union Street, between Sixth and Seventh Avenues, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 789-2762, tealoungeny.com; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>CLARK TERRY BIG BAND (Tonight through Sunday) Mr. Terry's big-band experience is extensive: starting in the late 1940's, he served successively in the orchestras of Count Basie, Duke Ellington and Quincy Jones. Mr. Terry, an octogenarian trumpet and fluegelhorn player, applies a lifetime of wit and experience to his own swinging ensemble. At 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592, bluenote.net; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PETE ZIMMER QUINTET (Tonight) The hard bop of the 1960's provides thematic sustenance for Mr. Zimmer, a drummer, and his working band, which includes the smartly assertive tenor saxophonist Joel Frahm. At 9, Night and Day, 230 Fifth Avenue, at President Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 399-2161, nightanddayrestaurant.com; cover, $10, with a $7 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>BARD SUMMERSCAPE (Tonight, Sunday and Wednesday) The conductor Leon Botstein enjoys resuscitating neglected works, some of which have proved to be more worthwhile than others. Tonight he will lead the American Symphony Orchestra in a production of ''Genoveva,'' Robert Schumann's only opera. The work has been infrequently performed or recorded since its premiere in 1850, and this performance is billed as its American stage premiere. Kasper Bech Holten, the dynamic young director of the Royal Danish Opera, is directing a cast that includes the soprano Ylva Kihlberg in the title role of the young wife. Her husband, the crusading knight Siegfried, will be sung by the baritone Johannes Mannov; Golo, whose love for her is unrequited, will be portrayed by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Tonight at 8, Sunday at 3 p.m. and Wednesday at 8 p.m., Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7900, summerscape.bard.edu; $35 to $85. (Vivien Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>GLIMMERGLASS OPERA (Tonight through Tuesday, and Thursday) Four operas are the rotation over the next week: Rossini's ''Barber of Seville'' is scheduled for tonight at 8; Janacek's ''Jenufa'' for tomorrow night at 8 and Monday at 1:30 p.m.; Stephen Hartke's ''Greater Good'' for Sunday at 1:30 p.m. and Thursday at 8 p.m.; and Gilbert and Sullivan's ''Pirates of Penzance'' Tuesday at 1:30 p.m. Route 80, north of Cooperstown, N.Y., (607) 547-2255, glimmerglass.org; sold out tonight, Monday and Tuesday; $64 to $112 tomorrow and Sunday; $41 to $104 on Thursday, with limited availability. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN ACCORDIONISTS' ASSOCIATION MASTER CLASS AND CONCERT SERIES (Today through Sunday) There is more to accordion music than you may think, or at least there is when the accordionist William Schimmel is in charge of the proceedings. The concerts in Mr. Schimmel's annual series offer everything from works by Alexander Tcherepnin, Eric Salzman and Leonard Feather to daring transcriptions of Paganini and Ravel, freewheeling variations on ''Hava Nagila'' and extended Elvis fantasies. The master classes are wild, too; topics this year include ''Accordion and the Standup Comic,'' ''Accordion and the Stripper,'' ''Hitler, Mengele and Other Repulsive Views Concerning the Accordion,'' and ''The Zen-Accordion Laugh.'' Master classes at 3 p.m., concerts at 7 p.m., Tenri Cultural Center, 43A West 13th Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 876-0827; $110 for all three days; $40 for daily passes; $20 for master classes; $25 for concerts. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>ASTON MAGNA (Tonight and tomorrow) The harpsichordist John Gibbons plays Bach's ''Goldberg'' Variations at this venerable early-music festival this weekend. Tonight at 8, Olin Humanities Building, Bard College, Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., (845) 758-7425; tomorrow at 5 p.m., Arts Center at Simon's Rock College, Great Barrington, Mass., (800) 875-7156, astonmagna.org; $35. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>BANG ON A CAN FESTIVAL MARATHON (Sunday) This vibrant new-music collective ends its annual summer festival and institute at Mass MoCA with a six-hour marathon mélange of rock, classical, jazz and world music. Students and faculty will perform works by the Bang on a Can artistic directors, Julia Wolfe, David Lang and Michael Gordon; this year's composer in residence, Meredith Monk; as well as Steve Martland, Michael Daugherty and Joan Tower. The enthusiastically unclassifiable event will also include a Balinese gamelan ensemble performing a work with Western instruments and several robots. At 4 p.m., 7 Marshall Street, North Adams, Mass., (413) 662-2111, massmoca.org; $22. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>* BARGEMUSIC (Tonight through Thursday) There are few cozier places to hear chamber music in New York than this floating concert hall (a former coffee barge) on the Brooklyn side of the East River. Tonight a program by the Williams Chamber Players, a piano trio, includes Paul Schoenfield's zesty ''Café Music,'' David Kechley's ''Episodes and Soliloquies'' and trios by Haydn and Beethoven. Tomorrow and Sunday, a large ensemble will be on hand for a hefty program that includes two Haydn cello concertos, Bach's ''Brandenburg'' Concerto No. 3, Mozart's Horn Concerto No. 2 and a Vivaldi Double Concerto. And on Thursday, Bargemusic offers two gems of the chamber repertory. The first, Schubert's ''Two Cellos'' Quintet, will be a video recording from 1967 with the cellists Pablo Casals and Gregor Piatigorsky, the violinists Alexander Schneider and Isadore Cohen, and Milton Thomas, the violist. After the intermission Mark Peskanov, a violinist; Maurycy Banaszek, a violist; and Marie-Elisabeth Hecker, a cellist, will perform Mozart's Divertimento in E flat (K. 563). Tonight, tomorrow and Thursday nights at 7:30; Sunday at 4 p.m.; Fulton Ferry Landing next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083, bargemusic.org; $35 tonight and Thursday; $50 tomorrow and Sunday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* FESTIVAL OF CONTEMPORARY MUSIC at Tanglewood (Today through Monday) At this new-music festival, the students of the Tanglewood Music Center and assorted guests usually give polished, energetic performances of an array of modern works. Last night's opening program, to be repeated this afternoon, is a triple opera bill, with Elliott Carter's ''What Next?,'' as well as Stravinsky's ''Mavra'' and Hindemith's ''Hin und Zurück.'' James Levine leads the Carter; the others are to be led by the student conducting fellows. Other highlights include a program tomorrow morning with works by Ron Ford and Johannes Staud; a concert tomorrow evening that includes Pierre Boulez's ''Messagesquisse'' for seven cellos and works by Andrew Norman and Betsy Jolas; a Sunday morning performance with music by David Felder, Stephen Andrew Taylor, Mark Gustavson, Eric Chasalow, Stephen Jaffe and Edmund Campion; and a Sunday evening concert that includes Hans Abrahamsen's Piano Concerto, a solo violin work by Mr. Ford and works by Mr. Staud, Milton Babbitt, Donald Martino and Poul Ruders, with the guitarist David Starobin as the soloist. The finale will be a performance of the English composer Mark Anthony Turnage's powerful ''Blood on the Floor,'' on Monday evening. Today at 2:30; tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 6 p.m.; Sunday at 10 a.m. and 8:30 p.m. and Monday at 8:30. Tanglewood, Lenox, Mass., (888) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $11 and $30 to $50 for the opera triple bill; $50 pass for all performances tomorrow through Monday. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>EMILY MANZO (Sunday) This pianist, an Oberlin graduate and new-music champion, has given the premieres of works by John Luther Adams, Kyle Gann and Mary Halvrson. A regular performer at the Stone, John Zorn's experimental performance space, she will tackle John Cage's Sonatas and Interludes for Prepared Piano, with video by Paul Rowley and David Phillips. At 8 and 10 p.m., the Stone, Avenue C at Second Street, East Village, thestonenyc.com; $10 per set. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>MARLBORO MUSIC FESTIVAL  (Tomorrow and Sunday) Public concerts are the by-product of this intensive-study chamber music retreat. The soprano Junko Watanabe and the pianist Martin Isepp will perform Schubert's ''Gretchen am Spinnrade'' and Brahms's ''An die Nachtigall'' tomorrow night. On Sunday Schubert's ''Trout'' Quintet is on the bill. Tomorrow at 8:30 and Sunday at 2:30, Marlboro Music School and Festival, Marlboro, Vt., (802) 254-2394, marlboromusic.org; $15 to $30; $5 for canopy areas. (Holland)</p>
        <p>MAVERICK CONCERTS (Sunday) This concert series near Woodstock, N.Y., offers its performances in an open-backed barn that allows the sounds of nature to mingle with the music. On Sunday the Brentano String Quartet and Hsin-Yun Hwang, a violist, play Mozart's Viola Quintets in B flat (K. 174) and G minor (K. 516). On its own, the quartet plays David Horne's String Quartet No. 4 (2006). At 3 p.m., Maverick Concert Hall, Maverick Road, between Routes 28 and 375, West Hurley, N.Y., (845) 679-8217, maverickconcerts.org; $20. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>MOSTLY MOZART Festival (Tonight, and Tuesday through Thursday) Tonight's free preview concert opens with a work by the father of Salzburg's birthday boy. Leopold Mozart's ''Toy Symphony'' will be followed by Wolfgang Mozart's Symphony No. 1 in E flat and the ''Jupiter'' Symphony No. 41 in C. For the official opening night on Tuesday, the music director Louis Langrée and the festival orchestra will perform two celebratory works. The soprano Hei-Kyung Hong, the mezzo-soprano Susanne Mentzer, the tenor Matthew Polenzani and the bass John Relyea will sing Mozart's ''Coronation'' Mass in C with the Concert Chorale of New York, and the pianist Garrick Ohlsson will play the ''Coronation'' Concerto. (The program will be repeated on Wednesday.) On Thursday, Mr. Ohlsson returns to the intimate, candlelit Kaplan Penthouse -- where he performed Beethoven sonatas at the festival last year -- for ''A Little Night Music.'' This time he offers Beethoven's Sonatas Nos. 5, 10 and 13. Tonight and Tuesday and Wednesday nights at 8, Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center; Thursday night at 10:30, Kaplan Penthouse, 165 West 65th Street, (212) 721-6500, lincolncenter.org; free tonight; $38 to $65 on Tuesday and Wednesday; $35 on Thursday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>NORFOLK CHAMBER MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tonight and tomorrow) It's waltz time tonight with Johann Strauss and Brahms's ''Liebeslieder'' Waltzes. Tomorrow an all-day open house celebrates the 100th anniversary of the Norfolk Shed. Tonight at 8, tomorrow at 10:30 a.m., Ellen Battell Stoeckel Estate, Routes 44 and 272, Norfolk, Conn., (860) 542-3000, yale.edu/norfolk; $15 to $45 tonight; free tomorrow. (Holland)</p>
        <p>TANGLEWOOD (Tomorrow through Thursday) The Austrian conductor Hans Graf, music director of the Houston Symphony, will lead the Boston Symphony Orchestra tomorrow in Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' and Beethoven's Violin Concerto, with Gil Shaham as soloist. On Sunday Mr. Graf shares the stage with the violinist Midori in Bruch's Violin Concerto No. 1; the program also includes Mendelssohn's Symphony No. 4 (''Italian'') and Strauss's ''Till Eulenspiegel's Merry Pranks.'' On Wednesday and Thursday Gidon Kremer and the Kremerata Baltica offer their contribution to the Mozart birthday festivities with his complete violin concertos, programmed alongside works that include Michael Nyman's ''Trysting Fields'' and Alfred Schnittke's ''Gratulationsrondo'' on Tuesday, and Alexander Raskatov's ''Five Minutes in the Life of W.A.M.'' and Shostakovich's Prelude and Scherzo (Op. 11) on Wednesday. Tomorrow, Wednesday and Thursday at 8:30 p.m., Sunday at 2:30 p.m.; Lenox, Mass., (866) 266-1200, tanglewood.org; $17 to $87 tomorrow and Sunday, $17 to $56 on Wednesday and Thursday. (Schweitzer)</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE MUSIC FESTIVAL (Tuesday) Now in its 48th season, this festival has focused mostly on Mozart this year, but for its finale, it is presenting Cuartetango. The implications of its name notwithstanding, the group includes not only a string quartet, but also a bandoneon player, and singers and dancers -- 10 performers in all -- who specialize in tango and jazz. At 8 p.m., Washington Square Park, Greenwich Village, (212) 252-3621, washingtonsquaremusicfestival.org; free. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN BALLET THEATER'S NEW YORK SUMMER INTENSIVE FINAL PERFORMANCE (Today) The American Ballet Theater picked 255 of the nation's top ballet students to come to New York for six weeks of intensive training, the fruits of which will be on display this afternoon, as students perform excerpts from ''Raymonda,'' ''La Bayadère,'' ''Études,'' ''Sylvia,'' ''Swan Lake'' and ''Theme and Variations.'' They will also perform original choreography by Leslie Browne, Daniel Baudendistel, Hilary Cartwright, Olga Dvorovenko, Tina Fehlandt, Jessica Lang and Brian Reeder. Four gifted goslings from the group -- Aria Alekzander, Joseph Gorak, Devon Teuscher and Faye Hideko -- will join the American Ballet Theater's Studio Company. At 12:30 p.m. and 4:30 p.m, the Performing Arts Center at Purchase College, 735 Anderson Hill Road, Purchase, N.Y., (212) 477-3030, Ext. 3416, abt.org/education/summerintensive.asp; $15. (Erika Kinetz)</p>
        <p>DANCING ON THE PLAZA (Tomorrow and Sunday) Produced by Dancing in the Streets, this free mini-festival will feature a shared program by nicholasleichterdance and CorbinDances (tomorrow) and an hourlong performance by Kun-Yang Lin/Dancers. Mr. Leichter's work stands out for its hip club-dancing influences, the Corbin work for its thoughtful high-energy physicality, and Mr. Lin's for its intensely emotional fusion of Chinese traditional and Western modern dance. At 3 p.m., Dag Hammarskjold Plaza, East 47th Street between First and Second Avenues, Manhattan, (212) 625-3505, or dancinginthestreets.org; free. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>EIDOLON BALLET (Tomorrow) This chamber dance group will perform works by the company's director, Melanie Cortier, and Ginger Thatcher, set to music by the Thai Elephant Orchestra, American polkas and Albinoni. At 2:30 and 8 p.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 946-1275, www.eidolonballet.org; $20; $15 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday) This wide-ranging festival of mostly new dance companies and artists ends this weekend with performances by Tracie Stanfield's Synthesis Dance Project (tonight and tomorrow night); Bimela Oliver Nsah's Sukinang Dance Group of P.C.H.S. Bamenda Cameroon (tomorrow and Sunday afternoons); and Jacqui Young's Push Factor Dance Company (a shared program Sunday afternoon). Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 6 p.m. Dicapo Opera Theater, 184 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 273-0713, internationaldancefestival.org; $20 to $40 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* JACOB'S PILLOW DANCE FESTIVAL (Tonight through Sunday, and Wednesday and Thursday) Eva Yerbabuena's Ballet Flamenco from Spain will be in the larger Ted Shawn Theater through the weekend, followed there on Wednesday and Thursday (and next weekend) by the Trey McIntyre Project, a contemporary ballet company. In the smaller Doris Duke Studio Theater, the Danish Dance Theater, billed as Denmark's leading modern-dance ensemble, plays through the weekend, and moving in on Thursday through next weekend is Armitage Gone!, Karole Armitage's new, New York-based contemporary ballet troupe. Yerbabuena tonight and tomorrow night at 8, and tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., $50; McIntyre on Wednesday and Thursday at 8 p.m., $45; Danish Dance tonight and tomorrow night at 8:15, tomorrow at 2:15 p.m. and Sunday at 5 p.m., $24; Armitage on Thursday at 8:15 p.m., $24. Ten percent off all tickets for students, ages 65+ and children. Details of the week's free performances and exhibitions can be found at jacobspillow.org, Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, 358 George Carter Road, Becket, Mass., (413) 243-0745. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* JPMORGAN CHASE LATINO CULTURAL FESTIVAL: GRUPO KRAPP (Wednesday and Thursday) This earthy, funny dance and theater troupe from Argentina will present its new ''Project E,'' a festival commission, in which tall, beautiful performers wander out of their dance and find themselves shrunken and unable to get back the power they once had over their audiences. The troupe will also perform ''Rio Seco'' (''Dry River''), a piece about the family vacation from hell. Wednesday at 8 p.m., Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows Corona Park, ; $20; $15 in advance. The program will be repeated on Thursday at 7:30 p.m. at the LaGuardia Performing Arts Center, 31-10 Thomson Avenue, Long Island City, Queens; $12; $6 for students. Information and reservations for both performances: (718) 750-0064 or QueensTheatre.org. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* NOCHE FLAMENCA WITH SOLEDAD BARRIO (Tonight through Sunday) Ms. Barrio is a remarkable dancer, serious and impassioned, and the hit of this winter's Flamenco Gala at City Center. Her Spanish company, founded with her husband, Martin Santangelo, concludes its two-month run at the intimate Theater 80 this weekend. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8, tomorrow and Sunday at 2 p.m., Sunday at 5 p.m., Theater 80, 80 St. Marks Place, East Village, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com; $45. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* PILOBOLUS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Monday through Thursday) The grandfather of the current crop of Nikolais-inspired, Cirque du Soleil-like acrobatic dance troupes with spectacular visual effects. A little mindless, but enormously popular for people of all ages. Three programs alternate for the run ending Aug. 12. Tonight, tomorrow and Monday through Thursday nights at 8, and tomorrow at 2 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800 or joyce.org, $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>URBAN BUSH WOMEN 2006 SUMMER INSTITUTE (Tomorrow) In ''Place Matters: A Look at Displacement,'' directed by Jawole Willa Jo Zollar and created by 74 dance artists participating in the institute, notions of home and displacement are examined in light of events that include Hurricane Katrina, the slaughters in Darfur and the fighting in Iraq. At 4 and 7 p.m. Kumble Theater, Long Island University, at Flatbush and DeKalb Avenues, Downtown Brooklyn, (718) 488-1624 or www.brooklyn.liu.edu/kumbletheater; $10; $2 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>YOUNG DANCEMAKERS COMPANY CONCERT (Wednesday) A summer ensemble of New York City teenagers will perform an hourlong program directed by Alice Teirstein, with live percussion by William Catanzaro. The show will be followed by some spontaneous dance making, with audience participation. At 3 p.m., Lovinger Theater, Lehman College, 250 Bedford Park Boulevard West, at Goulden Avenue, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 329-7205 or aliceteirstein@aol.com; free. (Kinetz)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum: 'Graffiti,' through Sept. 3. Twenty paintings on canvas from the early 1980's by formerly famous subway graffiti artists who went by names like Crash, Daze and Lady Pink. Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, (718) 638-5000 or brooklynmuseum.org. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 13. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and castoff clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to and settlement in the United States in a garrulous, very personal way. One particularly intense work, based on the belief that Abubakari II, ruler of Mali, crossed the Atlantic nearly 200 years before Columbus to discover the Americas, links the past with the present and Africa with the beloved Columbus of Ms. Robinson's childhood. (See above.) (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>Dahesh Museum of Art: 'NAPOLEON ON THE NILE: SOLDIERS, ARTISTS AND THE REDISCOVERY OF EGYPT,' through Dec. 31. Napoleon's invasion of Egypt was a military disaster, but the squadron of scholars and scientists that went with him lay the foundation for Egyptology and Egyptomania, gave Orientalism a big boost and was commemorated by the 1,000 engravings of the ''Description de l'Égypte.'' Examples of the book's prints form the backbone of this strange and sometimes piecemeal show, which includes Orientalist paintings and a cache of fascinating ephemera. 580 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, (212) 759-0606 or daheshmuseum.org. (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* Frick Collection : 'Jean-Étienne Liotard (1702-1789): Swiss MasteR,' through Sept. 17. Liotard is something of a specialty item now, but he was widely known in the Enlightenment Europe of his day. And even then he was seen as a maverick, a figure of contradictions. He was a stone-cold realist in an age of rococo frills. In a great age of oil painting, he favored pastel. He had ultrafancy sitters for his portraits, including Marie Antoinette. But his most vivid likenesses are of himself and his family. The Frick's perfectly proportioned sweetheart of a solo show is the artist's first in North America. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700 or frick.org. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>SOLOMON R. GUGGENHEIM MUSEUM: 'ZAHA HADID: THIRTY YEARS IN ARCHITECTURE,' through Oct. 25. This exhibition, Ms. Hadid's first major retrospective in the United States, gives New Yorkers a chance to see what they've been missing. The show, in the Guggenheim's rotunda, spirals through Ms. Hadid's career, from her early enchantment with Soviet Constructivism to the sensuous and fluid cityscapes of her more recent commissions. It illuminates her capacity for bridging different worlds: traditional perspective drawing and slick computer-generated imagery; the era of utopian manifestos and the ambiguous values of the information age. (212) 423-3500 or guggenheim.org. (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'UNKNOWN WEEGEE,' through Aug. 27. From the 1930's through the 50's, Weegee -- real name, Arthur Fellig (1899-1968) -- was one of the best-known news photographers in the country. He specialized in capturing the sensational side of urban life: crime, disaster, demimonde nightlife. For him, the city was a 24-hour emergency room, an amphetamine drip. This show of 95 pictures gives a good sense of his range and calls particular attention to his awareness of social problems related to class and race. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000 or icp.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* metropolitan museum of art: 'GIRODET: ROMANTIC REBEL,' through Aug. 27. Hugely famous in the early 19th century, Girodet dropped down the memory chute. His ''Ossian Receiving the Ghosts of French Heroes,'' painted for Napoleon, is one of the most deranged pictures in art history. It's so unhinged that it's almost lovable, which is otherwise the last word to come to mind for an artist who, in his uptight, smarty-pants mode, could be a bore. But give the show a shot. It's sometimes brilliant, and Girodet's strangeness and fairly repellent character make him at least fascinating to contemplate and heroic in his immoderation. History is full of shifty characters, antique visionaries, cusp figures and half-crazy oddball innovators, later overlooked because they're hard to pigeonhole. Their independent cast of mind is the truest expression of how civilization advances. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'RAPHAEL AT THE METROPOLITAN: THE COLONNA ALTARPIECE,' through Sept. 3 This exhilarating show reunites the central panel and lunette of Raphael's Colonna Altarpiece (owned by the Met) with all five panels of the predella. Additional works by Raphael, Perugino, Fra Bartolommeo and Leonardo place the work in context and sharpen the understanding of Raphael's budding genius. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Met: 'Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings,' through Sept. 10. ''Treasures of Sacred Maya Kings'' gets a huge gold A for truth in advertising. The treasures are plentiful, rare and splendid. A carved wood figure of kneeling shaman, arms extended, time-raked face entranced, is simply one of the greatest sculptures in the museum. Much of the work has never traveled before; many objects have only recently come to light in Mexico, Guatemala and Honduras. They add up to an exhibition as a think-piece essay on how a culture saw itself in the world. (212) 535-7710 or metmuseum.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Museum of Biblical Art: 'The Word on the Street: the photographs of Larry Racioppo,' through Aug. 20. Photographs documenting vernacular expressions of religious devotion in New York, including spray-painted murals, private shrines and tattoos. Museum of Biblical Art, 1865 Broadway, at 61st Street, (212) 408-1500 or mobia.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MUseum of modern art: 'ARTIST'S CHOICE: Herzog &amp; DE MEURON, PERCEPTION RESTRAINED,' through Sept. 25. In an unusually accessible bit of institutional critique, the architects who failed to win the commission to design the new Museum of Modern Art bite the hand that didn't feed them. They create a kind of deprivation chamber with a black gallery, where excerpts from American movies play on video screens on the ceiling and 110 works of art and design are crammed into enormous niches that are all but sealed from view. Perverse and cerebral, it may be the best one-liner you'll encounter this summer. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'DADA,' through Sept. 11. This is pretty much Dada's official survey (an oxymoron), and it makes nearly all 450 or so objects in it look elegant. That hat rack looks awfully stylish now. It's good to be reacquainted with a generation of artists who had no market to speak of and for whom society's corruption and exhaustion seemed golden opportunities to make themselves useful. Cynical and traumatized, the Dadaists were tireless young optimists at heart. They discovered a world full of wonders, and we are, on the whole, their beneficiaries. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Museum of Modern Art: Douglas Gordon: 'Timeline,' through Sept 4. This selection of works by the artist known for appropriating and inventively manipulating Hollywood movies includes his projection of Alfred Hitchcock's ''Psycho,'' which runs so slowly that it takes 24 hours to complete, and a large-scale video installation that studies a circus elephant performing in an empty art gallery. (212) 708-9400 or moma.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE Galerie: Gustav Klimt: Five Paintings From the Collection of Ferdinand and Adele Bloch-Bauer , through Sept. 18. Klimt's 1907 gold portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer, lately acquired by the billionaire collector Ronald S. Lauder, reportedly for $135 million, is now aptly installed like a trophy head above the mantelpiece. She's half queen, half Vegas showgirl. A perfect New Yorker. She temporarily hangs with four other Klimts, including a second Adele, painted in 1912: a slender, sinuous Coke-bottle shaped figure, more chaste than carnal. A painting of a birch forest is an archetypal Klimt mix of uncanny naturalism and geometric abstraction. Two other landscapes, of an apple tree and an unfinished jigsaw-puzzle view of houses on the shore of the Attersee, raise the question: had Klimt not died at 55 in 1918, would he have ended up a pure abstractionist like Mondrian? 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200 or neuegalerie.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden: Chihuly at the New York Botanical Garden, through Oct. 29. Dale Chihuly, the world's most famous contemporary glass artist, has created ambitious installations of his large-scale, technically virtuosic and materially extravagant works inside the spectacular Haupt Conservatory and outside in formal reflecting pools and smaller gardens. New York Botanical Garden, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Bedford Park, the Bronx, (718) 817-8700 or nybg.org.(Johnson)</p>
        <p>* New-York Historical Society: Legacies: Contemporary Artists Reflect on Slavery, through Jan. 7. Slavery, some would say, didn't really end in the United States until the civil rights legislation of the 1960's. That was a full century after the Emancipation Proclamation. Or the ''Emancipation Approximation,'' as the artist Kara Walker calls it in a series of hallucinatory silkscreen prints. They are among the high points of this large, powerful, subtle group show, the second of three exhibitions on American slavery organized by the New-York Historical Society. 2 West 77th Street, (212) 873-3400 or nyhistory.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>New York Public Library: 'FRENCH BOOK ART/LIVRES D'ARTISTES: ARTISTS AND POETS IN DIALOGUE,' through Aug. 19. Organized with the Bibliothèque Littéraire Jacques Doucet in Paris, this lavish exhibition surveys some of the experimental ferment brought on by the combination of free verse, visionary publishers and the high rate of talent among French artists and poets, especially in the early years of the 20th century. Concentrating on books, but also including prints and drawings, it retells the tale of the French avant-garde on a relatively egalitarian playing field. New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, (212) 869-8089 or nypl.org. (Smith)</p>
        <p>NOGUCHI MUSEUM: 'BEST OF FRIENDS: BUCKMINSTER FULLER AND ISAMU NOGUCHI,' through Oct. 15. Great, lasting friendships are rare, but friendships that enlarge the spirit through ideas, ideals and new insights are in a class by themselves. Over a stretch of more than 50 years the sculptor Isamu Noguchi and the visionary designer R. Buckminster Fuller enjoyed such a friendship, which led to aesthetic and practical achievements that left their mark. The course of their varied collaborations is traced in this exhibition, which includes models, sculptures, drawings, photographs and films. The museum entrance is at 9-01 33rd Road, between Vernon Boulevard and 10th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 204-7088 or noguchi.org. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'Into Me/Out of Me,' through Sept. 25. Often with repulsive immediacy and occasionally with wit and subtlety, works by more than 130 artists in this ambitious exhibition explore the body and all its possible experiences along the pleasure-pain continuum. P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center, 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084 or ps1.org. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* Rubin Museum of Art : 'What is it? HimalAyan Art,' This museum is a oasis of calm in the city; you can feel your tension dissolve the minute you walk in the door. At the same time, the place jumps with activities, including lectures, films and exhibitions, many devoted to aspects of Himalayan culture. And for a basic guide to the art of Tibet and Nepal, you will do no better than to take a slow walk through this new show, which, using an array of gorgeous objects, distills knotty visual and spiritual systems to a soothing but stimulating entry-level form. 150 West 17th Street, Chelsea, (212) 620-5000 or rmanyc.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Whitney Museum of American Art: 'Full House: Views of the Whitney's Collection at 75,' through Sept. 3. The Whitney celebrates a significant birthday this summer with an attic-to-basement display of hundreds of pieces of art from its permanent collection. There are terrific things, arranged mostly by loose theme rather than date. And as an ensemble, they deliver an impressionistic story, through art, of a staggeringly contradictory American 20th-century culture, diverse and narrow-souled, with a devotion to the idea of power so ingrained as to make conflict inevitable and chronic. 945 Madison Avenue, at 75th Street, (212) 570-3676 or whitney.org. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>* Sarah Sze: 'Corner Plot' The upper corner of an apartment building protrudes from the Doris C. Freedman Plaza's pavement as if the whole edifice had toppled and sunk into the ground. Through the window's of Ms. Sze's magical outdoor sculpture you can see a complicated interior that looks as if it were created by a mad architect. Doris C. Freedman Plaza, 60th Street and Fifth Avenue, (212) 980-4575, through Oct. 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>* Rudy Burckhardt: 'New York Paintings' Known as a photographer and filmmaker, Mr. Burckhardt (1914-1999) also painted all through his career. His Manhattan cityscapes, mostly rooftop views of other buildings, have a fresh, almost naïve immediacy and a sophisticated way with relations between surface and depth and complexity and simplicity. Tibor de Nagy, 724 Fifth Avenue, (212) 262-5050 or tibordenagy.com, extended through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Your Beauty's Gold is Clay' This well-selected show of ceramicists includes ruggedly sensuous, Abstract Expressionist-style sculptures by Lynda Benglis; delicate and humorously detailed vessels by Kathy Butterly; surrealistically flamboyant large vases by Nicole Cherubini; comical, demonic heads by William King; a wonderful long-haired cat by Anne Arnold; and sweet faux-juvenile sculptures by Jessica Jackson Hutchins. Alexandre Gallery, 41 East 57th Street, (212) 755-2828 or alexandregallery.com, through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>Joe Biel With an exacting illustrator's touch, Mr. Biel draws large, dreamily perverse images of children, like the one of a girl with rabbit ears and a whip peeking out of a cardboard box, and one of a knife-wielding boy crouching atop a pile of rubble and examining a bone he found. Goff &amp; Rosenthal, 537B West 23rd Street, (212) 675-0461, goffandrosenthal.com, through Aug. 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* J. Bennett Fitts: 'No Lifeguard on Duty' Symbolically resonant photographs of mostly derelict motel swimming pools by a young Californian. Julie Saul, 535 West 22nd Street, (212) 627-2410 or saulgallery.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* 'A Four-Dimensional Being Writes Poetry on a Field with Sculptures' Organized by the sculptor Charles Ray, this beautiful, spare and mysterious exhibition presents sculptures by Alberto Giacometti, Mark di Suvero and the folk artist Edgar Tolson, and a giant photograph by Jeff Wall. Matthew Marks, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200 or matthewmarks.com, through Aug. 11. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Group Show Four interesting Conceptualists: Pierre Bismuth folds a giant reproduction of a Jasper Johns flag painting into a Donald Judd-like box; Ryan Gander makes large photographs of bulletin boards bearing puzzling documents; Karl Haendel covers a wall with his large, handmade graphite copies of consumer-culture ephemera; and T. Kelly Mason constructsa walk-in, padded environment with soft, rain-related sounds and a video. Cohan and Leslie, 138 10th Avenue, near 19th Street, (212) 206-8710 or cohanandleslie.com, through Aug. 18. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Michael Heizer Sculptures in concrete representing prehistoric hand tools much enlarged so that they resemble Modernist sculptures by a follower of Brancusi. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 421-3292 or pacewildenstein.com, through Sept. 23. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Materiality' Inventive works made of all sorts of materials in this show include a stuffed leather-and-plywood tree by Carolyn Salas; a geometric landscape with a slowing-moving, wartlike kinetic element, covered in reflective Mylar, by Charlotte Becket; a neat display of more than 200 pieces of breakfast cereal by Tom Friedman; and a sumptuous stuffed object resembling a much-enlarged amoeba by Ernesto Neto. Kravets/Wehby, 521 West 21st Street, (212) 352-2238 or kravetswehbygallery.com, through Aug. 25. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Photography Is Not An Art!' More than 100 examples of vernacular, often anonymous photographs from fields of medicine, forensics, space exploration and advertising prove that nonart photography is often as interesting as the fine-art variety. Alan Klotz, 511 West 25th Street, (212) 741-4764 or photocollect.com, through Aug. 19. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>Zoe Leonard, Liz Deschenes and Vija Celmins This quietly gripping show of photographs and works derived from photographs includes delicate, hand-drawn images of a spider web, and the ocean's surface in prints by Ms. Celmins; grainy aerial photographs that look as if they were shot from a spy satellite by Ms. Leonard; and Minimalist photograms with silvery surfaces by Ms. Deschenes. Tracy Williams, 313 West Fourth Street, West Village, (212) 229-2757 or tracywilliamsltd.com, through next Friday. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>* HANS BELLMER: ' PETITES ANATOMIES, PETITES IMAGES.'  This extraordinary show of more than 70 images takes you beyond the surface obsessions of Bellmer's girl-crazed art to unveil some of his working processes as a sculptor, installation artist, photographer, editor and hand-colorist, whose preference for small scale intensifies the voyeuristic nature of his art. Ubu Gallery, 416 East 59th Street, (212) 753-4444 or ubugallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* CRG PRESENTS: KLAUS VON NICHTSSAGEND GALLERY Including works by Liz Luisada, Samuel Lopes and Thomas Ovilsen, this group show of work by 17 emerging artists definitely has its moments, but the strongest impression is made by the gallery-within-a-gallery effect resulting from the re-creation of the storefront facade and reception desk of the small Von Nichtssagend Gallery in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. CRG Gallery, 535 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 229-2766 or crggallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>George Herms Starting out as a beatnik in the 1950's, Mr. Herms has been creating and exhibiting his richly poetic assemblages of grungy found materials in California, his home state, for more than a half century. This show's eight works, from 1965 to 2002, variously call to mind Ernst, Duchamp, Cornell and Rauschenberg, but they have as well their own spiritually generous, heartfelt mix of hermetic imagination and Whitmanesque populism. Franklin Parrasch, 20 West 57th Street, (212) 246-5360 or franklinparrasch.com; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'How I Finally Accepted Fate' The memoir is the loosely defined theme of this interesting 10-person show. It includes Matt Keegan's video of cheerleaders celebrating his grandmother's 90th birthday; Angela Dufresne's vivid painting of a shirtless man called ''Me as a Communist Male in 'The Red and the White' ''; Carolee Schneemann's patchwork tale about modern love in photographs and typewritten words; and Maureen Duncan's three-and-a-half-hour monologue about her CD collection. EFA Gallery, 323 West 39th Street, (212) 563-5855; closes today. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* JUSTIN LOWE: HELTER SWELTER This labor-intensive trompe l'oeil installation passes through the emblematic sites of summer -- an urban bodega, a construction detour and an ice cream truck -- but its chief payoff is a womblike hippie heaven whose floor-of-many-colors is tiled in tightly wound T-shirts. Oliver Kamm/5BE Gallery, 621 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-0979 or 5begallery.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
        <p>'Money Changes Everything' A show of artworks made at least partly out of actual money: dollar bills, mostly, but Iraqi dinar notes, too. Schroeder Romero, 637 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 630-0722 or schroederromero.com; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* WANGECHI MUTU: EXHUMING GLUTTONY: A LOVER'S REQUIEM In tandem with this artist's Chelsea debut, an over-the-top installation made with the British architect David Adjaye includes fur-trimmed wine bottles dripping wine, animal skins and an enormous raw wood table. Conflating morgue, tannery and banquet hall, it brings the excess and color of paintings on Mylar into real space, but its main message seems to be: I built this because I can. Salon 94, 12 East 94th Street, (646) 672-9212 or salon94.com; closes today. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
