<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="30biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4DB1F3EF933A05756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OFFER FOR KINDER MORGAN -- A group led by Richard D. Kinder announced a buyout offer valued at $22 billion for Kinder Morgan Inc., the parent of the pipeline giant he founded in 1997. The deal, which includes the assumption of about $8 billion in debt, would be the largest leveraged buyout since Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company bought RJR Nabisco in 1989 for $25 billion. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>TWO IN NEWS CREW KILLED -- Two Britons working as members of a CBS News television crew were killed on Monday and an American correspondent for the network, Kimberly Dozier, was critically wounded when a military patrol they were accompanying was hit by a roadside bomb. [A1.]</p>
        <p>THE BATTLE FOR AIR -- Americans are increasingly recognizing that the effects of carbon emissions on global warming are a serious problem, but there are no rules in the United States regulating heat-trapping gases comparable to those that most other developed countries have adopted under the Kyoto Protocol. Some United States businesses, though, are responding for a variety of reasons anyway: to satisfy customers or shareholders who worry about the environment, to improve their public image or to drive down their energy costs. In addition, some states and local authorities have stepped in to try to curb their contributions to global warming. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A STEEL WAR -- When it came to repelling a hostile takeover bid from Mittal Steel, Arcelor left no stone unturned as it searched for a poison-pill partner. But some critics say that the solution -- a deal that gives more than a third of Arcelor to a Russian billionaire, Aleksei Mordashov, left, may leave a bitter aftertaste. If it is approved by the shareholders, the agreement will put Russian executives in crucial management positions at Arcelor, raising questions about integration between the two corporate cultures, and concerns among some shareholders about what role the Russian government may want to play. [C3.]</p>
        <p>HISPANIC CALLERS -- Now that nearly three out of four people in this country have mobile phone service, cellphone companies are chasing new customers by marketing to ever more specific slices of the population. But one group is getting extra attention: Hispanics. And there is ample reason for the carriers' attention. One of the country's fastest growing demographic groups, Hispanics often have large families that span international borders, making for larger phone bills. [C1.]</p>
        <p>THAT 60'S SHOW -- AMC cable television network is considering a series that would explore how Madison Avenue remakes itself to meet the changing needs of clients as consumers and the media undergo transformation. So the show would be a reality series, right? Not exactly. It is fictional, a drama about the advertising industry circa 1960. In another example of how the more things change the more they remain the same, if AMC decides to pick up the series, each episode may be sponsored by a single advertiser -- just as was done in 1960. Stuart Elliott, Advertising. [C7.]</p>
        <p>A SUMMER OF HIGH GAS PRICES -- As the summer travel season began in earnest this past weekend, Americans were indulging their wanderlust, jamming highways, and filling airports, motels and eateries. But in some small ways, with possibly large consequences for the health of the economy, travelers interviewed across the country over the weekend said they were cutting their spending and downsizing their plans for summer trips. [A1.]</p>
        <p>A MOVE IN EUROPE -- When BAE Systems, the British military contractor, announced that it was bowing out of its nearly 30-year relationship with Airbus, the split was greeted in Britain with shock at first, followed by recognition that the companies had grown apart. BAE's departure now could be transformational not only for it, but also for Airbus, whose ownership -- and decision-making -- structure is evolving. [C4.]</p>
        <p>BRIGHT SPOT FOR G.M. -- Four years ago, Daewoo Motor was the biggest and ugliest addition to South Korea's junkyard of bankrupt companies. Its parent conglomerate had collapsed, and most potential investors were intimidated by its militant labor union. Its founder, Kim Woo Choong, left, is on trial on corruption charges linked to the disintegration of his conglomerate in 1998. But Mr. Kim is gone, and Daewoo has become a bright spot for G.M. [C4.]</p>
        <p>AIRLINE APOLOGIZES -- WestJet Airlines agreed on Monday to pay 15.5 million Canadian dollars ($14 million) to settle accusations of spying on an internal Web site of its rival, Air Canada. The settlement, which came with an apology, brought to an end two years of litigation. [C9.]</p>
        <p>THE OPEC MEETING -- Most delegates at this week's meeting of OPEC are expected to nod politely to Venezuela's calls for output cuts that could drive prices even higher, while doing the opposite by reaping all they can from the current bonanza of high prices. The oil minister of the United Arab Emirates rejected talk of a possible cut in the cartel's output quotas of 28 million barrels a day. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A SOFTWARE BATTLE IN CHINA -- Responding to years of intensive international lobbying, the Chinese government has introduced measures offering the potential to curb widespread piracy and increase revenue for software companies. The Business Software Alliance estimates that more than 90 percent of the software in China is unlicensed. [C3.]</p>
        <p>A NEW TAX COMPLAINT -- In an effort to raise revenues, tax writers in Congress added a last-minute provision that increased taxes for Americans living abroad. But the sudden imposition of taxes has surprised overseas taxpayers, and it has employers concerned about the added cost. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PAYING WITH ATTENTION -- With the cost of mobile phone calls already dropping sharply, Virgin Mobile USA plans to announce a way that people can talk for no money at all. They will, however, have to pay with a chunk of their attention. [C4.]</p>
        <p>FROG POWER -- A tribal cure in Brazil, derived from the secretions of a poisonous tree frog, raises hope of a wonder drug that might benefit the country's indigenous people as well as its drug industry [C1.]</p>
        <p>GLOBAL SECURITY -- In an increasingly global economy, more business travelers find themselves visiting places that, if not as obviously dangerous as Baghdad or Kabul, are unfamiliar and possibly treacherous. And a number of risk management and security firms are providing services to help them, and say their business is growing. [C8.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OFFER FOR KINDER MORGAN -- A group led by Richard D. Kinder announced a buyout offer valued at $22 billion for Kinder Morgan Inc., the parent of the pipeline giant he founded in 1997. The deal, which includes the assumption of about $8 billion in debt, would be the largest leveraged buyout since Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company bought RJR Nabisco in 1989 for $25 billion. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>TWO IN NEWS CREW KILLED -- Two Britons working as members of a CBS News television crew were killed on Monday and an American correspondent for the network, Kimberly Dozier, was critically wounded when a military patrol they were accompanying was hit by a roadside bomb. [A1.]</p>
        <p>THE BATTLE FOR AIR -- Americans are increasingly recognizing that the effects of carbon emissions on global warming are a serious problem, but there are no rules in the United States regulating heat-trapping gases comparable to those that most other developed countries have adopted under the Kyoto Protocol. Some United States businesses, though, are responding for a variety of reasons anyway: to satisfy customers or shareholders who worry about the environment, to improve their public image or to drive down their energy costs. In addition, some states and local authorities have stepped in to try to curb their contributions to global warming. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A STEEL WAR -- When it came to repelling a hostile takeover bid from Mittal Steel, Arcelor left no stone unturned as it searched for a poison-pill partner. But some critics say that the solution -- a deal that gives more than a third of Arcelor to a Russian billionaire, Aleksei Mordashov, left, may leave a bitter aftertaste. If it is approved by the shareholders, the agreement will put Russian executives in crucial management positions at Arcelor, raising questions about integration between the two corporate cultures, and concerns among some shareholders about what role the Russian government may want to play. [C3.]</p>
        <p>HISPANIC CALLERS -- Now that nearly three out of four people in this country have mobile phone service, cellphone companies are chasing new customers by marketing to ever more specific slices of the population. But one group is getting extra attention: Hispanics. And there is ample reason for the carriers' attention. One of the country's fastest growing demographic groups, Hispanics often have large families that span international borders, making for larger phone bills. [C1.]</p>
        <p>THAT 60'S SHOW -- AMC cable television network is considering a series that would explore how Madison Avenue remakes itself to meet the changing needs of clients as consumers and the media undergo transformation. So the show would be a reality series, right? Not exactly. It is fictional, a drama about the advertising industry circa 1960. In another example of how the more things change the more they remain the same, if AMC decides to pick up the series, each episode may be sponsored by a single advertiser -- just as was done in 1960. Stuart Elliott, Advertising. [C7.]</p>
        <p>A SUMMER OF HIGH GAS PRICES -- As the summer travel season began in earnest this past weekend, Americans were indulging their wanderlust, jamming highways, and filling airports, motels and eateries. But in some small ways, with possibly large consequences for the health of the economy, travelers interviewed across the country over the weekend said they were cutting their spending and downsizing their plans for summer trips. [A1.]</p>
        <p>A MOVE IN EUROPE -- When BAE Systems, the British military contractor, announced that it was bowing out of its nearly 30-year relationship with Airbus, the split was greeted in Britain with shock at first, followed by recognition that the companies had grown apart. BAE's departure now could be transformational not only for it, but also for Airbus, whose ownership -- and decision-making -- structure is evolving. [C4.]</p>
        <p>BRIGHT SPOT FOR G.M. -- Four years ago, Daewoo Motor was the biggest and ugliest addition to South Korea's junkyard of bankrupt companies. Its parent conglomerate had collapsed, and most potential investors were intimidated by its militant labor union. Its founder, Kim Woo Choong, left, is on trial on corruption charges linked to the disintegration of his conglomerate in 1998. But Mr. Kim is gone, and Daewoo has become a bright spot for G.M. [C4.]</p>
        <p>AIRLINE APOLOGIZES -- WestJet Airlines agreed on Monday to pay 15.5 million Canadian dollars ($14 million) to settle accusations of spying on an internal Web site of its rival, Air Canada. The settlement, which came with an apology, brought to an end two years of litigation. [C9.]</p>
        <p>THE OPEC MEETING -- Most delegates at this week's meeting of OPEC are expected to nod politely to Venezuela's calls for output cuts that could drive prices even higher, while doing the opposite by reaping all they can from the current bonanza of high prices. The oil minister of the United Arab Emirates rejected talk of a possible cut in the cartel's output quotas of 28 million barrels a day. [C1.]</p>
        <p>A SOFTWARE BATTLE IN CHINA -- Responding to years of intensive international lobbying, the Chinese government has introduced measures offering the potential to curb widespread piracy and increase revenue for software companies. The Business Software Alliance estimates that more than 90 percent of the software in China is unlicensed. [C3.]</p>
        <p>A NEW TAX COMPLAINT -- In an effort to raise revenues, tax writers in Congress added a last-minute provision that increased taxes for Americans living abroad. But the sudden imposition of taxes has surprised overseas taxpayers, and it has employers concerned about the added cost. [C3.]</p>
        <p>PAYING WITH ATTENTION -- With the cost of mobile phone calls already dropping sharply, Virgin Mobile USA plans to announce a way that people can talk for no money at all. They will, however, have to pay with a chunk of their attention. [C4.]</p>
        <p>FROG POWER -- A tribal cure in Brazil, derived from the secretions of a poisonous tree frog, raises hope of a wonder drug that might benefit the country's indigenous people as well as its drug industry [C1.]</p>
        <p>GLOBAL SECURITY -- In an increasingly global economy, more business travelers find themselves visiting places that, if not as obviously dangerous as Baghdad or Kabul, are unfamiliar and possibly treacherous. And a number of risk management and security firms are providing services to help them, and say their business is growing. [C8.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
