<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving the Republican Party</title>
    <meta content="NJrepubs" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/12/opinion/nyregionopinions/NJrepubs.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kean, Thomas H Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Christine Todd</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDE1F3FF931A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving the Republican Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Saving the Republican Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week's elections drove home the fact that New Jersey is on the brink of becoming a one-party state for the Democrats. And that's ominous, because one-party dominance in government leads to arrogance, corruption and a lack of concern for the needs of citizens.</p>
        <p>Republicans have not won the governor's office since Christie Whitman left the scene. Worse, they have not come up with many attractive new faces who seem likely to do the job in the near future. And there has not been a Republican victory in a United States Senate race since Clifford Case won election to a fourth term in 1972.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The big challenge now for New Jersey Republicans is to face the fact that the brand is going to have to be moderate if they want to win statewide elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week's elections drove home the fact that New Jersey is on the brink of becoming a one-party state for the Democrats. And that's ominous, because one-party dominance in government leads to arrogance, corruption and a lack of concern for the needs of citizens.</p>
        <p>Republicans have not won the governor's office since Christie Whitman left the scene. Worse, they have not come up with many attractive new faces who seem likely to do the job in the near future. And there has not been a Republican victory in a United States Senate race since Clifford Case won election to a fourth term in 1972.</p>
        <p>With Thomas Kean Jr.'s loss last week, party stalwarts are demoralized. If Mr. Kean with his famous last name could not win, what Republican can?</p>
        <p>Mr. Kean, of course, had particularly long odds, running against a tidal wave of resentment against his national party and President Bush. Northeast voters tossed out a number of veteran Republican lawmakers in retaliation for the Iraq mess and the scandals in the Republican-dominated House of Representatives. In Rhode Island, to take one prominent example, Senator Lincoln Chafee, a party moderate, received positive ratings of 60 percent in exit polls on Tuesday, even as he was being decisively ousted from office.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, there was little to turn over. The Republicans hold 6 of the state's 13 Congressional seats, mainly in conservative strongholds. But that does little to create a healthy statewide two-party competition.</p>
        <p>Republican survivors should look to the Kean campaign for some clues about what they need to change. Even in a less anti-Republican year, Mr. Kean would not have been a very good candidate. Despite his father's legacy, he did not really run as a moderate.</p>
        <p>On immigration, he took a hard-line, punitive approach rather than the balanced, bipartisan Senate position that offered illegal immigrants some hope of becoming citizens.</p>
        <p>On the Iraq war, he stopped short of any tough criticism of Mr. Bush, saying only that mistakes were made in the way the war was pursued and that Secretary of Defense Donald Rumsfeld should go.</p>
        <p>And for a couple of days late in the campaign, he hedged on his prior support for strong gun controls, and his position on abortion was nuanced enough to win him support from the National Right to Life Committee.</p>
        <p>In short, Mr. Kean pandered to conservatives even as he depended on his father to campaign at his side. Instead of relying on advice from strategists who helped Christie Whitman win the governorship in the '90s and his father win before that, he surrounded himself with advisers from the right. Many moderate Republicans and political independents lost faith in him.</p>
        <p>The Republican Party in New Jersey has run into the same problem that bedevils minority parties in other states: as its constituency shrinks, it becomes dominated by loyalists whose ideology is out of kilter with the electorate in general. Extreme conservatives have a grip on the party machinery in many regions and are able to turn out enough voters to win primaries with their own candidates or, at a minimum, persuade contenders like Mr. Kean to defer to their positions.</p>
        <p>They are also masters of negative campaign advertising, offering little to voters in the way of hope or positive proposals for solving complex problems like global warming, air and water pollution, or bad schools in the cities.</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitman, whose 2005 book, ''It's My Party Too'' called for moderate Republicans everywhere to stand up for their beliefs, is right on the mark when she says that to win in New Jersey, Republicans must offer positive positions, rather than just attack the Democrats. Ingrid Reed, a policy analyst at the Eagleton Institute of Politics at Rutgers University, says it is very unusual for any candidate to win election by relying on the negative as much as Mr. Kean did in his ethics attacks against Mr. Menendez.</p>
        <p>History has shown that New Jersey voters, whatever their registration, like the Republican message of fiscal restraint and lower taxes, combined with a moderate-to-liberal stance on social issues and a clear understanding that largely urban states cannot be run without extensive government services. But the old generation of Republican politicians who championed that philosophy is growing thin, and the party is not doing enough to cultivate replacements.</p>
        <p>There will undoubtedly be future elections in which voters are not irate about the national Republican Party and are willing to look more favorably on the local brand of Republicanism. The big challenge now for New Jersey Republicans is to face the fact that the brand is going to have to be moderate if they want to win statewide elections. If they do not, they will assure the state of continued one-party domination with all the bad baggage that is almost certain to follow.</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
