<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Saturn Vue Green Line and Mercury Mariner Hybrid; Hybrids, Mild or Seasoned, From the Motor City</title>
    <meta content="19AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/19/automobiles/autosreviews/19AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Behind the Wheel"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric and Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Saturn Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mercury Division of Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berman, Bradley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hybrid Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Saturn Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DC143EF93AA25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/Saturn Vue Green Line and Mercury Mariner Hybrid; Hybrids, Mild or Seasoned, From the Motor City</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Saturn Vue and Mercury Mariner: Hybrids, Mild or Seasoned, From the Motor City</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRADLEY BERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berman, Bradley</byline>
      <dateline>BERKELEY, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Behind the Wheel reviews of Saturn Vue Green Line and Mercury Mariner Hybrid; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUCH has changed since the advent of the automobile. Newton's mechanistic view of the universe yielded to Einstein's relativity. Commerce shifted from heavy machinery to packets of ones and zeroes zipping through the air.</p>
        <p>But one thing remains the same. More than a century after the car kicked the horse to the curb, the most popular measure of a vehicle's prowess is still horsepower. The postmodern digital age has not caught up to cars, with one notable exception: the hybrid gas-electric vehicle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hybrid sport utility represents a double-whammy American automotive fantasy: the go-anywhere image of an S.U.V. that's green to boot. But do these hybrids really deliver?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUCH has changed since the advent of the automobile. Newton's mechanistic view of the universe yielded to Einstein's relativity. Commerce shifted from heavy machinery to packets of ones and zeroes zipping through the air.</p>
        <p>But one thing remains the same. More than a century after the car kicked the horse to the curb, the most popular measure of a vehicle's prowess is still horsepower. The postmodern digital age has not caught up to cars, with one notable exception: the hybrid gas-electric vehicle.</p>
        <p>With hybrids, auto engineers have finally harnessed the internal combustion engine, placing it in a secondary position behind computer control systems, electronic transmissions, power-splitting devices and dashboard video monitors that provide X-ray vision into the inner workings of complex systems.</p>
        <p>The best hybrids show their owners, every running moment, just how much energy they are using, and from what source, and why. Can a hybrid play a significant role in solving the problems of oil dependency, auto emissions and climate change? Hybrid drivers don't need a definitive answer. They just need to see -- right now on their dashboards -- that their mileage represents a break from the past and a step toward a potential breakthrough.</p>
        <p>This feedback is what made my test-drives of two hybrids from Detroit-based automakers -- the Mercury Mariner Hybrid (which differs little from the Ford Escape Hybrid) and the Saturn Vue Green Line from General Motors -- so much fun.</p>
        <p>Give me the right tools, and I (or you) can wring truly impressive mileage from cars like these. But if you drive 'em as if you stole 'em, they'll slurp hydrocarbons like any car.</p>
        <p>The hybrid sport utility represents a double-whammy American automotive fantasy: the go-anywhere, do-everything image of an S.U.V. with the potential to preserve the outdoor environment you are rolling over. But do these hybrids really deliver?</p>
        <p>Vue: Going Green for Less</p>
        <p>The mild-hybrid Saturn Vue Green Line is G.M.'s first gas-electric vehicle, unless you count the company's ultramild-hybrid pickup trucks.</p>
        <p>The hybrid field is starting to get crowded -- there are now a dozen to choose from -- so the pitch for the Green Line is ''the most affordable S.U.V. hybrid.'' In other words, this Vue appeals to your inner accountant.</p>
        <p>The numbers would impress any C.P.A. For $22,995, the Green Line delivers an E.P.A. fuel economy rating of 27 m.p.g. in town and 32 in the country, which is the highest highway rating for any sport utility. For comparison's sake, a conventional gas-only Vue with 4-cylinder engine, front drive and automatic transmission is rated 22 in town, 27 on the highway.</p>
        <p>I drove the Green Line on two successive 78-mile highway loops, one well below the speed limit and a second in complete disregard of the 65 m.p.h. signs. As a saint, I achieved an impressive 36 m.p.g. As a sinner, my fuel economy dropped to 24 m.p.g. I have little doubt that a careful foot applied to the Green Line could regularly produce 30 m.p.g. on the highway.</p>
        <p>Instead of a discrete electric motor that can drive the wheels just like a gasoline engine, the Green Line uses a belt alternator-starter; it shuts the engine off when the car comes to a complete stop, eliminating gas consumption at idle. The Green Line's 36-volt battery and motor-generator smartly wake up the engine as soon as the driver's foot comes off the brake pedal.</p>
        <p>Kudos to Saturn's technical team for producing an auto-stop feature that works smoothly and consistently. In contrast, Honda's system requires the car to return to at least 10 m.p.h. before it will shut down again. In the Vue, you can lift and return your foot to the brake as often as you like -- as you would in stop-and-go traffic. Each time, the engine pauses for a few moments at low idle, then drops to a full engine-off stop.</p>
        <p>What you can't do, though, is launch forward in all-electric mode. That feat -- the thing that, in the view of many people, makes a hybrid a hybrid -- belongs, for the moment, only to full hybrid systems from Toyota and Ford.</p>
        <p>Were good mileage the only criterion for likability, this review would be over. The problem, though, is that every auto credit requires a debit, and accountants' fingerprints can be seen all over this Vue.</p>
        <p>Handling is acceptable but not impressive. The 2.4-liter 4-cylinder engine is loud but delivers barely adequate performance.</p>
        <p>Aerodynamics are a crucial factor in fuel economy, and the Vue's was improved -- to a drag coefficient of 0.36, from 0.38 -- by lowering the chassis an inch and leaving off the roof rack. Unfortunately, ridges that remain on the roof call attention to the fact that something is missing. The lower profile also leaves the Green Line feeling more like a portly wagon than a high-riding S.U.V.</p>
        <p>The doors are easy enough to open, but the upright backseat is excruciating; passengers will yearn for the relative comfort of flying cross-country in coach class.</p>
        <p>A 36-volt battery pack, which lets the auto-stop function do its thing, is housed in the cargo area. The rest of that compartment is occupied by what Saturn calls a rear cargo organizer; it is a set of hinged plastic dividers so flimsy that my friends guffawed when I showed it to them.</p>
        <p>The biggest flaw may stem from the cost-containment measures applied to the instruments. The typical hybrid driver needs real-time information to wring the most miles from the fuel, but Saturn provides only silly green lights and a little dial and pointer. A green ''eco'' light is supposed to come on when the Vue matches or beats the E.P.A. economy estimates, but I found the flickering light to be worthless. The dial is supposed to indicate when the battery is charging or providing an assist, but a meter to monitor mileage on a specific trip would be much more useful.</p>
        <p>There is also the Green Line's overall feel of righteous deprivation. While the Green Line is rather Spartan, the Red Line, a higher-performance Vue, has a distinctive front end, sport suspension, 18-inch alloy wheels, leather seats and much more. The not-so-subtle message: You can spend your money on high-quality fun and get a Red Line, or opt for a big green bummer.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, a new Vue is on the way. The 2008 model, which will be previewed at the Los Angeles auto show later this month, will be similar to the new Opel Antara that will be sold in foreign markets. The new Vue will also trade its ding resistant but ill-fitting plastic body panels for sheet-metal, which will perhaps make the crossover utility feel less like a disposable car.</p>
        <p>For now, the Vue Green Line proves that G.M. is capable of improving the fuel efficiency of many of its vehicles at a modest cost. The well-engineered belt alternator-starter could be offered on tens of thousands of G.M. vehicles, virtually eliminating wasted fuel at idle.</p>
        <p>Yet as an overall package, the Green Line is sadly wanting. G.M. started with a laudable goal, to show that it can deliver gas-saving technology at a discount, but it has fallen far short of other hybrid makers on the execution.</p>
        <p>Mariner: Eco Yet Macho</p>
        <p>If the Saturn seems more driven by green-marketing imperatives than by driver satisfaction, G.M.'s crosstown rival has come up with a hybrid S.U.V. that really works, albeit one that costs some $7,000 more.</p>
        <p>The Mercury Mariner Hybrid combines the most robust gas-electric system available today -- it will stay in electric mode longer than any competitor -- with the body of a stylish yet rugged-looking sport utility.</p>
        <p>With its mix of digital-era sophistication and creature comforts, the Mariner Hybrid works so well that one wonders whether, if it had been more aggressively marketed since its debut in late 2004, it could have been the hit that the ailing Ford Motor Company so desperately needs.</p>
        <p>Does the Mariner Hybrid have the rugged sex appeal of other S.U.V.'s? Is that even possible? Until now, hybrids could hardly be considered babe magnets or or hunk attractors.</p>
        <p>The comedic actor Will Ferrell, a Prius owner, has said, ''In addition to being obviously economical and environmentally friendly, they drive great and are just plain sexy.'' Obviously, he tells jokes for a living.</p>
        <p>Consider my brother. Fed up with the cost of feeding a gallon of imported fuel into his Range Rover for every 11 miles driven, he picked up a hybrid crossover utility, a Lexus RX 400h, instead. A year later, the drumbeat of teasing from friends and loved ones -- they accused him of driving a girlie car -- compelled him to ditch the Lexus and get another Range Rover.</p>
        <p>He should have held out for the Mariner Hybrid. Its shape is pugilistic, like the Escape's. It is square and muscular but has flourishes like accent grilles on the taillights and gauges rimmed in chrome.</p>
        <p>The Mariner is technically a crossover, but it seems solid and upright like a real S.U.V. Although the '07 model comes only with all-wheel drive, a front-drive version will be offered for 2008.</p>
        <p>Instrumentation is crucial to the hybrid experience, because the fun of a hybrid is using all available tools to get the maximum mileage. Ford's system beats Toyota's hands-down in its ability to stay in all-electric mode for extended periods.</p>
        <p>The Mariner Hybrid, like the Escape Hybrid, offers an expanded opportunity to use the gas pedal, brake and gears to juggle energy into and out of the rechargeable batteries.</p>
        <p>Want to get a full charge to the batteries? Accelerate to about 30 m.p.h. and slip the shifter into low (not actually a gear, but a tighter engagement of the motor-generator). How long do you want to stay in E.V. (electric) mode? If you use some Astaire footwork to accelerate slowly and evenly, you can nudge the Mariner to 30 m.p.h. without using a drop of gas.</p>
        <p>If you slip out of E.V. mode at speeds as high as 40 m.p.h., and your battery is adequately charged, you can give the brake two quick taps and slip right back into E.V. mode.</p>
        <p>Certainly, few hybrid owners will take the time to learn all the tricks, but even the most absent-minded motorists are constantly reminded that they are piloting some seriously geeky-cool technology.</p>
        <p>When I employed all the advanced techniques of an experienced hybrid driver, I achieved highway and city mileage in the mid-30's -- not bad for an S.U.V. But when I drove like a fool, overall mileage fell to the mid-20s.</p>
        <p>The ultimate benefits of hybrid technology -- savings at the pump, a poke at OPEC, reduced emissions, whatever -- are personal. That gives much more meaning to the Mariner's ability to stay in all-electric mode longer than any other hybrid. Ford's engineers outdid Toyota's in pushing the technology to the limit.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Ford's marketing department overlooked the potential of the Mariner Hybrid as a lean, mean, digital-era machismo machine. It made its debut under the same tired green banners and slipped into obscurity almost immediately. True, the Mariner Hybrid hit its sales target without breaking a sweat, but that is an exceedingly modest 2,000 a year.</p>
        <p>In September, former President Bill Clinton took delivery of a ''Presidential Edition'' Mariner Hybrid, inspiring this flight of fancy: What if Mr. Clinton was Ford's hybrid pitchman rather than Kermit the Frog?</p>
        <p>A suave but serious spokesman might have let the American public see the Mariner Hybrid for what it is: a well-appointed, well-priced S.U.V. with best-in-class fuel economy and groundbreaking technology. It might even have gained recognition as the first great American vehicle of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Behind the Wheel Bradley Berman is the editor of Hybridcars.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bradley Berman is the editor of Hybridcars.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
