<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/TriBeCa; Eco-Conscious Meets Guilty Conscience</title>
    <meta content="12habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/12/realestate/12habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | TriBeCa"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tribeca (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaw, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strand, Ginger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DD1F3FF931A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/TriBeCa; Eco-Conscious Meets Guilty Conscience</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Eco-Conscious Meets Guilty Conscience</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN SHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shaw, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats column on life style choices made by Ginger Strand that, whose her personal ethics on matters like energy efficiency and conspicuous consumption conflict with realities of living in Manhattan, like living in large TriBeCa loft; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S 9 a.m. on a school day, and Ginger Strand has just dropped her car off at the parking lot near her TriBeCa loft. She has already driven to the Upper East Side and back, and she will make the one-hour round trip again in the afternoon to pick up her 12-year-old daughter from school. She feels ashamed of herself.</p>
        <p>''I still think having a car in Manhattan is an act of absurdity,'' said Ms. Strand, an eco-conscious essayist and novelist, who is writing a nonfiction book for Simon &amp; Schuster on the history of Niagara Falls. She considers the falls not a ''natural spectacle'' but a ''triumph of engineering,'' and laments that the falls were manipulated to dazzle tourists instead of producing the maximum amount of renewable energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TriBeCa mother did everything she could to avoid buying a car  to no avail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S 9 a.m. on a school day, and Ginger Strand has just dropped her car off at the parking lot near her TriBeCa loft. She has already driven to the Upper East Side and back, and she will make the one-hour round trip again in the afternoon to pick up her 12-year-old daughter from school. She feels ashamed of herself.</p>
        <p>''I still think having a car in Manhattan is an act of absurdity,'' said Ms. Strand, an eco-conscious essayist and novelist, who is writing a nonfiction book for Simon &amp; Schuster on the history of Niagara Falls. She considers the falls not a ''natural spectacle'' but a ''triumph of engineering,'' and laments that the falls were manipulated to dazzle tourists instead of producing the maximum amount of renewable energy.</p>
        <p>''It is so ironic that I had to buy a car,'' she said. ''I had never owned a car in my entire life. I was very holier than thou. I wanted to go to my grave without owning a car.''</p>
        <p>She did everything she could -- to no avail.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Strand's daughter, who attended Public School 234 down the street from their loft, had to shop around for junior high schools because there isn't one in their neighborhood, she fell in love with a private school on the Upper East Side. ''She begged me to go there,'' said Ms. Strand, who attended a public junior high in Michigan. ''I couldn't say to her, 'You can't go to that school because it is really inconvenient.' So we thought of moving uptown.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Strand and her boyfriend, Robert Brown, who works in the computer industry, started looking at two-bedroom apartments on the Upper East and West Side. ''But it seemed unaffordable,'' she said. ''The maintenances were ridiculous. The cheapest maintenances we would see were $1,500, and we pay just $300 here.''</p>
        <p>So they decided to stay in TriBeCa, and Ms. Strand started taking her daughter to school by subway. They would walk east several blocks and then take the No. 4 or No. 5 train to 86th Street. ''There was a lot of tween misery involved with the subway,'' she said. ''It would be really crowded and these kids have these massive backpacks and it wasn't even convenient to the school once we got off the subway. So then we started taking cabs. And then it occurred to me that if we considered parking fees part of our maintenance, it would still be cheaper to buy a car and park it than to live uptown.''</p>
        <p>To atone for her transgression, Ms. Strand bought a hybrid Prius. ''It doesn't exonerate me, but it does make me feel a little bit better,'' she said. ''It very reliably gets 49.6 miles per gallon, torturing you with its refusal to go over 50.''</p>
        <p>Her daughter adores the car. ''She hugs it,'' said Ms. Strand. ''She has completely anthropomorphized it. It has a personality. It gets jealous when we rent cars. She named it Totoro after Hayao Miyazaki's anime movie about benign forest sprites that sort of look like the car.''</p>
        <p>Most important, the Prius made it possible to continue living happily in TriBeCa. ''Ever since 9/11, we are even more attached to the neighborhood,'' Ms. Strand said. She and Mr. Brown had moved to the loft in 1999. ''The apartment is actually owned by Robert, and I pay him rent and that is our situation,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Before moving to TriBeCa, neither of them had been living as nicely. ''He had a grubby little studio in Brooklyn Heights, and I had a grubby little one-bedroom on the Upper West Side, where I was living with my daughter and sleeping in the living room.'' she said. ''Neither of us had any furniture. We moved in with two futons, bookcases and books and that was pretty much it.''</p>
        <p>The 1,650-square-foot loft is vintage TriBeCa: exposed brick walls, an elevator that opens into the apartment, an airy living room/dining room/kitchen with large windows overlooking the street, and two bedrooms in the back. ''We are a completely self-managed building with a grubby lobby, but we like that,'' she said. ''We were told when we bought it that it was a 'spice warehouse,' but that's what Realtors down here say about every building.''</p>
        <p>Though TriBeCa is rife with home-design stores, they headed to Michigan to furnish the apartment and visit Ms. Strand's family. ''You can't buy furniture in New York because it is ridiculously expensive,'' she said. ''We rented a truck and went to flea markets and antique fairs.''</p>
        <p>They returned with an assortment of low-key midcentury chairs, sofas and tables that look good with their contemporary art.</p>
        <p>The loft is uncluttered and clean, but it was a mess after 9/11. ''It was filled with ash and uninhabitable,'' she recalled. ''We had left our windows open, because another one of my ridiculous little environmental convictions is that I am very opposed to air-conditioning, and I don't use it unless I absolutely have to.''</p>
        <p>They weren't allowed to return to their apartment for nearly two months, though Ms. Strand talked her way past the National Guard on Sept. 12 to rescue her daughter's fish. ''You know how you take on some ridiculous task in such events to assert your control over the situation?'' she said. ''Well, my conviction was that if I could just keep the terrorists from killing my daughter's fish, all would be well. I took them in a Ziploc bag to the nearest pet store and said do whatever you can with them. After that, we were not allowed back without a police escort.''</p>
        <p>As much as she loves the wide open space of her home, Ms. Strand had initially disapproved of loft living. ''I had theorized that in Manhattan, where the rarest, most prized commodity is space, that the loft is the ultimate form of conspicuous consumption because you have all your space on display at once,'' she said. ''It's like wearing all your designer clothing at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Here, you can see all at once the contemporary photographs and paintings she collects, though Ms. Strand refuses to call herself a collector because of the elitist connotations. ''I just buy what I like,'' she said. She grins as she points to a sparkling canvas by the Brooklyn artist Nancy Drew over the sofa. ''She is redoing the great works of Abstract Expressionists in glitter. This one is supposed to be Rauschenberg's 'Erased de Kooning.' It sheds a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Characteristically, she is conflicted about another work of art that she loves, which hangs by the dining table. The colorful mixed-media piece by Charles Spurrier, an artist working in Brooklyn, incorporates multicolored light bulbs. ''It gives off a lot of light, so it is great for dinner parties -- it's like having a fireplace,'' she said, and then makes sure a visitor understands that she feels guilty about the energy it requires. ''We only plug it in for limited amounts of time. It's a little wasteful of watts.''</p>
        <p>Habitats | TriBeCa</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
