<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Water in Two Big River Systems, With Different Approaches to Flood Control</title>
    <meta content="30anatomy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/30/nyregion/30anatomy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D71430F933A05755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Water in Two Big River Systems, With Different Approaches to Flood Control</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">High Water in Two Big River Systems, With Different Approaches to Flood Control</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The flooding that swallowed up communities along the Susquehanna and Delaware Rivers this week was not merely the result of what meteorologists call a striking rain event, three to five inches of rain across large areas in just a few hours. It was also caused by all the rain leading up to the deluge, saturating the ground.</p>
        <p>The storm, which set records in some areas for both rainfall totals and flood levels, was the third in as many years to cause extensive damage in the two river basins, prompting some to wonder whether the extreme weather patterns that scientists say accompany global warming have already arrived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The flooding that swallowed up communities along the Susquehanna and Delaware Rivers this week was not merely the result of what meteorologists call a striking rain event, three to five inches of rain across large areas in just a few hours. It was also caused by all the rain leading up to the deluge, saturating the ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The flooding that swallowed up communities along the Susquehanna and Delaware Rivers this week was not merely the result of what meteorologists call a striking rain event, three to five inches of rain across large areas in just a few hours. It was also caused by all the rain leading up to the deluge, saturating the ground.</p>
        <p>The storm, which set records in some areas for both rainfall totals and flood levels, was the third in as many years to cause extensive damage in the two river basins, prompting some to wonder whether the extreme weather patterns that scientists say accompany global warming have already arrived.</p>
        <p>The Susquehanna travels for 444 miles from its headwaters near Cooperstown, N.Y., south through Pennsylvania to the Chesapeake Bay, and many of the river's tributaries and streams -- there are 48,000 miles of them -- started to flood on Monday. The river itself crested late Wednesday and early yesterday, reaching 26 feet in Danville, Pa., six feet above flood stage.</p>
        <p>Along the Delaware, which flows for 330 miles from the Catskills to the Delaware Bay, the rain also caused swollen creeks and streams, which, in turn, forced up the river levels long after the downpours ended. In Riegelsville, N.J., just south of Easton, Pa., the river rose to 33 feet early yesterday afternoon, 12 feet above flood stage.</p>
        <p>The flooding along the two rivers prompted declarations of emergencies, mass evacuations, rescues and untold property damage claims. Along both rivers, there were scenes of rooftops poking out from a muddy expanse of water.</p>
        <p>The approaches to flood control are markedly different along the two rivers, though.</p>
        <p>The Susquehanna, considered one of the most flood-prone rivers in the country, has an extensive system of levees, walls and flood-control dams, said Susan Obleski, a spokeswoman for the Susquehanna River Basin Commission. The 27,510-square-mile basin -- bigger than Vermont, Massachusetts, New Jersey and Delaware combined -- is laced with shallow streams that flood easily.</p>
        <p>''The river is very shallow as well, so it doesn't take a lot of rain before it starts to overflow its banks,'' she said. ''We're particularly vulnerable to flash flooding.''</p>
        <p>There are a total of 35 flood-control structures maintained by the Army Corps of Engineers along the river basin. On Wednesday, officials in Wilkes-Barre, Pa., held out hope that the towering flood wall there would contain the water. It did, and the water crested 6 or 7 feet below the top of the 41-foot floodwalls.</p>
        <p>While it is too early to say what the flood-control structures up and down the river accomplished in this storm, the commission estimates that in 2004, the bulwark held back 135 billion gallons of floodwater, preventing $1.6 billion of additional damage.</p>
        <p>The Delaware, by contrast, has no concrete flood walls or protection dams, although there are five dams on the tributaries that feed it, said Clarke Rupert, a spokesman for the Delaware River Basin Commission.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, a plan for a major dam project at Tocks Island that would have supplied hydroelectric power, drinking water and flood protection on the Delaware was shelved after a huge outcry. The land that was purchased by the federal government in anticipation of the project later became the Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area.</p>
        <p>Because much of the nontidal portion of the Delaware has a federal designation of ''wild and scenic,'' it is unlikely that anyone will revive attempts to create a new flood-control project any time soon.</p>
        <p>'' 'Wild and scenic' has to do with the free-flowing nature of a river,'' Mr. Rupert said. ''The Delaware is the longest undammed river east of the Mississippi. It's been our experience that the approach to dealing with flood losses has shifted away from constructing new dams and levees to local measures like property acquisition, flood proofing, flood plain regulation and storm water management.''</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates and scientists have long cited the practice of building on flood plains as a cause of the devastation caused by rising rivers, but the recurrence of major floods in the East in recent years is also prompting new worries about global warming.</p>
        <p>Claudia Tebaldi, a project scientist for the National Center for Atmospheric Research, in Colorado, said in a telephone interview that it was impossible to link a specific storm to climate change. ''But we know that in a warm climate, the likelihood of getting intense precipitation events increases,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rupert pointed out that this is not the first time that major floods have occurred within a brief period. Flood crest figures for the Delaware in Trenton show that the highest crest occurred in 1904 and the third-highest in 1903. ''If we were conducting this interview 100 years ago, we would be talking about two tremendous floods that took place in the span of six months,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, he said, the recent floods are right up there. The storm in September 2004 -- remnants of Tropical Storm Ivan -- ranked sixth, while last year's storm in April was fourth. This year's should also make the short list. The water levels had reached 24.97 feet in Trenton as of yesterday evening, which could make it the new No. 5.</p>
        <p>But it was unclear if the river had actually crested. ''The jury is still out, so to speak,'' Mr. Rupert said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
