<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="15biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1790105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1D71231F936A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FORD TO OFFER BUYOUTS -- In the latest sign that Detroit has decided it needs to shrink to survive, the Ford Motor Company agreed to offer buyouts and other incentives worth as much as $140,000 each to all its 75,000 hourly workers in the United States to persuade them to leave their jobs. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>HEDGE FUND MAY GO PUBLIC -- A hedge fund named Fortress Investment Group is considering an initial public offering for later this fall in a deal that could value the company in the range of $5 billion to $7 billion, according to people who have been briefed on the plans. [C1.]</p>
        <p>RUSSIAN REGULATOR IS KILLED -- Andre Kozlov, below, a top Russian bank regulator who had been engaged in an effort to reform Russia's corrupt and risk-laden banking system, died yesterday after being shot on the street the night before. Mr. Kozlov, 41, the first deputy chairman of Russia's central bank, had been leading a drive to combat money laundering and to bring stability to Russia's rapidly expanding banking sector. Among many programs in his portfolio, he had been closing disreputable banks by withdrawing their licenses, a practice his colleagues said had made him enemies in criminal circles. [A3.]</p>
        <p>SETBACK FOR U.S. ON SHELTERS -- A 2004 Internal Revenue Service document indicates that KPMG did not have to register certain questionable tax shelters with the agency, undermining a major claim in the government's case against 18 former tax professionals. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO SELL DIRECTV -- Rupert Murdoch, who spent more than two decades coveting the satellite broadcaster DirecTV before acquiring control of it three years ago, is now in talks to sell it to the financer John C. Malone, people close to the talks said last night. [C1.]</p>
        <p>UTILITY MERGER ABANDONED -- The Public Service Enterprise Group of Newark, the parent company of New Jersey's largest utility, and Exelon of Chicago called off their merger, saying that their differences with New Jersey regulators were ''insurmountable.'' [B5.]</p>
        <p>CHINA AND NEWS SERVICES -- Chinese officials promised that new rules restricting the sale of reports by foreign news agencies would not have an effect on press freedoms. But the officials also strongly defended efforts to control the distribution of financial and economic news inside the country. [A10.]</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA'S EMISSIONS FIGHT -- California is betting that it can succeed in reducing greenhouse gas emissions without wrecking its economy, and therefore inspire other states -- and countries -- to follow its example on slowing climate change. [A1.]</p>
        <p>AOL EXECUTIVE TO LEAVE POST -- Ted Leonsis, who has been a top leader of AOL for 13 years, will give up his jobs as president of what AOL calls its audience business, which creates Web sites and sells advertising on them. He will remain vice chairman of the company. [C4.]</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT'S MUSIC PLAYER -- Hoping to upstage the Apple iPod, Microsoft said that its Zune player, which it plans to release in time for the holiday season, will include wireless technology to allow Zune owners to easily share their favorite songs and playlists with one another. [C3.]</p>
        <p>MEXICO SECURITIES SETTLEMENT -- The billionaire investor Ricardo Salinas Pliego and the United States Securities and Exchange Commission reached a settlement in the first case against a foreign company under the corporate governance rules of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act. [C3.]</p>
        <p>BATTLE OVER JOB CUTS AT PAPER -- The editor of The Los Angeles Times appears to be in a showdown with the paper's owners at the Tribune Company over newsroom job cuts. [C3.]</p>
        <p>RESHAPING RADIO -- Woes in the radio industry have spurred a new wave of deal-making. Clear Channel Communications, the nation's largest radio operator, is considering selling some of its 1,200 stations in smaller markets, according to industry analysts. The CBS Corporation did the same thing recently and now says it is looking at further station sales. Walt Disney recently struck a deal to get out of the radio business altogether, and Susquehanna Broadcasting has been sold to another broadcaster. [C1.]</p>
        <p>INDIA'S CELLPHONE GROWTH  -- India has become the fastest-growing cellular market in the world, adding a net 5.9 million cellular subscribers in August, the Cellular Operators Association of India said. The gain outstripped China's increase of 5.19 million subscribers. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SMALL RISE IN RETAIL SALES -- Retail sales rose 0.2 percent in August after a surge of 1.4 percent in July. Another report showed that weekly first-time claims for jobless benefits fell. [C4.]</p>
        <p>STOCKS END THE DAY MIXED -- Wall Street closed mixed, with blue chips falling and technology stocks managing a slight gain. [C8.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FORD TO OFFER BUYOUTS -- In the latest sign that Detroit has decided it needs to shrink to survive, the Ford Motor Company agreed to offer buyouts and other incentives worth as much as $140,000 each to all its 75,000 hourly workers in the United States to persuade them to leave their jobs. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>HEDGE FUND MAY GO PUBLIC -- A hedge fund named Fortress Investment Group is considering an initial public offering for later this fall in a deal that could value the company in the range of $5 billion to $7 billion, according to people who have been briefed on the plans. [C1.]</p>
        <p>RUSSIAN REGULATOR IS KILLED -- Andre Kozlov, below, a top Russian bank regulator who had been engaged in an effort to reform Russia's corrupt and risk-laden banking system, died yesterday after being shot on the street the night before. Mr. Kozlov, 41, the first deputy chairman of Russia's central bank, had been leading a drive to combat money laundering and to bring stability to Russia's rapidly expanding banking sector. Among many programs in his portfolio, he had been closing disreputable banks by withdrawing their licenses, a practice his colleagues said had made him enemies in criminal circles. [A3.]</p>
        <p>SETBACK FOR U.S. ON SHELTERS -- A 2004 Internal Revenue Service document indicates that KPMG did not have to register certain questionable tax shelters with the agency, undermining a major claim in the government's case against 18 former tax professionals. [C1.]</p>
        <p>TALKS TO SELL DIRECTV -- Rupert Murdoch, who spent more than two decades coveting the satellite broadcaster DirecTV before acquiring control of it three years ago, is now in talks to sell it to the financer John C. Malone, people close to the talks said last night. [C1.]</p>
        <p>UTILITY MERGER ABANDONED -- The Public Service Enterprise Group of Newark, the parent company of New Jersey's largest utility, and Exelon of Chicago called off their merger, saying that their differences with New Jersey regulators were ''insurmountable.'' [B5.]</p>
        <p>CHINA AND NEWS SERVICES -- Chinese officials promised that new rules restricting the sale of reports by foreign news agencies would not have an effect on press freedoms. But the officials also strongly defended efforts to control the distribution of financial and economic news inside the country. [A10.]</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA'S EMISSIONS FIGHT -- California is betting that it can succeed in reducing greenhouse gas emissions without wrecking its economy, and therefore inspire other states -- and countries -- to follow its example on slowing climate change. [A1.]</p>
        <p>AOL EXECUTIVE TO LEAVE POST -- Ted Leonsis, who has been a top leader of AOL for 13 years, will give up his jobs as president of what AOL calls its audience business, which creates Web sites and sells advertising on them. He will remain vice chairman of the company. [C4.]</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT'S MUSIC PLAYER -- Hoping to upstage the Apple iPod, Microsoft said that its Zune player, which it plans to release in time for the holiday season, will include wireless technology to allow Zune owners to easily share their favorite songs and playlists with one another. [C3.]</p>
        <p>MEXICO SECURITIES SETTLEMENT -- The billionaire investor Ricardo Salinas Pliego and the United States Securities and Exchange Commission reached a settlement in the first case against a foreign company under the corporate governance rules of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act. [C3.]</p>
        <p>BATTLE OVER JOB CUTS AT PAPER -- The editor of The Los Angeles Times appears to be in a showdown with the paper's owners at the Tribune Company over newsroom job cuts. [C3.]</p>
        <p>RESHAPING RADIO -- Woes in the radio industry have spurred a new wave of deal-making. Clear Channel Communications, the nation's largest radio operator, is considering selling some of its 1,200 stations in smaller markets, according to industry analysts. The CBS Corporation did the same thing recently and now says it is looking at further station sales. Walt Disney recently struck a deal to get out of the radio business altogether, and Susquehanna Broadcasting has been sold to another broadcaster. [C1.]</p>
        <p>INDIA'S CELLPHONE GROWTH  -- India has become the fastest-growing cellular market in the world, adding a net 5.9 million cellular subscribers in August, the Cellular Operators Association of India said. The gain outstripped China's increase of 5.19 million subscribers. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SMALL RISE IN RETAIL SALES -- Retail sales rose 0.2 percent in August after a surge of 1.4 percent in July. Another report showed that weekly first-time claims for jobless benefits fell. [C4.]</p>
        <p>STOCKS END THE DAY MIXED -- Wall Street closed mixed, with blue chips falling and technology stocks managing a slight gain. [C8.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
