<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="03bizdigest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1736831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DC163EF930A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal Pension Agency to Make a Claim On a Hamptons Estate to Aid Steelworkers  The federal agency that insures pensions appears poised to lay claim to a Hamptons house owned by Ira L. Rennert to make sure he delivers on hundreds of millions of dollars worth of pensions promised to a group of steelworkers in Ohio. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>More Patients Move Away From Traditional Health Care  Feeling misled or even betrayed, millions of people are venturing outside conventional health care by taking herbal medicine or seeking alternative treatments; the government estimates that such measures add up to annual spending of $27 billion. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Drug industry executives are voicing new hope that their companies are past the worst of the scientific, political and legal problems that dogged them through 2005. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Federal spending on the new Medicare drug benefit will be 20 percent lower than expected this year because beneficiaries are choosing prescription drug plans with lower premiums, the Bush administration said. [A20.]</p>
        <p>Executives of Boston Scientific will meet with regulators from the Food and Drug Administration to discuss quality control problems at some of its factories. The agency has already suspended the company's ability to introduce new products, and the meeting could affect its plans to acquire another medical device maker, Guidant. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Study Finds Automakers' Design Changes Save Lives  Design changes that automakers initially resisted and then reluctantly adopted for sport utility vehicles and pickups have sharply reduced the number of deaths among drivers in cars they hit, according to results from the first such study of the standards. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Charges Filed Against Former Insurance Executives  Three former General Re executives and one former American International Group executive have been charged with fraud and conspiracy in connection with a deal that authorities say artificially inflated A.I.G.'s financial position, possibly raising the pressure on other senior executives. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Amazon's Results Come In Below Expectations  Amazon, the online retailer, reported that its profit declined 43 percent during the holiday quarter, in large part because of a decreased tax benefit. A smaller-than-expected increase in revenue, along with high expenses, concerned investors. Amazon's shares declined $3.49, or 8.2 percent, to $39.25 in after-hours trading, after they had fallen in regular trading to close at $42.74. [C2.]</p>
        <p>The iPod Spawns an Industry for Its Accessories  Apple's iPod has given rise to an entire industry in accessories. Sales of cases, docking stations, rechargers and other accessories -- 2,000 at last count -- totaled $850 million last year. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Image Defied Reality, an Enron Executive Testifies  The former Enron chief executives Jeffrey K. Skilling and Kenneth L. Lay continued to publicize the company's retail energy services division as being successful, even as other top executives knew the unit had suffered huge losses from trading and overpriced contracts, Enron's former head of investor relations testified. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Similar Goals but Different Routes on Energy  President Bush supports the development of ethanol, wind power and other forms of renewable energy. So does Congress. But their goals differ in ways that compete for research dollars and are costing some government researchers their jobs. [A17.]</p>
        <p>With a tax code that offers more than $1 billion worth of breaks for gasoline and diesel, New York's energy policies show just how hard it will be for the nation to wean itself from foreign oil. [C19.]</p>
        <p>Retailers Report Their Biggest Sales Gain Since June  Retailers reported their biggest monthly sales gain since June, as shoppers redeemed gift cards and bought spring fashions during one of the warmest Januaries on record. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Workers' Efficiency Increases, but at a Slower Rate  The efficiency of American workers rose in 2005 at the slowest pace since the recession year of 2001 while a major gauge of wage pressures rose at the fastest pace in five years, according to a government report. [C3.]</p>
        <p>General Motors Buys $15 Billion in Technology Services  General Motors said it would spend up to $15 billion over the next five years to contract out information technology services. Electronic Data Systems, its former subsidiary, will remain the biggest supplier but will receive a little less work. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Comcast Posts a Decline in Quarterly Profit  The Comcast Corporation, the nation's largest cable company, said profit slid 69 percent in the fourth quarter as investment losses and a higher tax rate offset gains in its core businesses of selling television, high-speed Internet connections and phone service. [C2.]</p>
        <p>European Bank Paves the Way for a Rate Increase  The European Central Bank laid the groundwork for a rate increase next month, its second in five years, saying that Europe was continuing to grow and that inflation remained a threat. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal Pension Agency to Make a Claim On a Hamptons Estate to Aid Steelworkers  The federal agency that insures pensions appears poised to lay claim to a Hamptons house owned by Ira L. Rennert to make sure he delivers on hundreds of millions of dollars worth of pensions promised to a group of steelworkers in Ohio. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>More Patients Move Away From Traditional Health Care  Feeling misled or even betrayed, millions of people are venturing outside conventional health care by taking herbal medicine or seeking alternative treatments; the government estimates that such measures add up to annual spending of $27 billion. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Drug industry executives are voicing new hope that their companies are past the worst of the scientific, political and legal problems that dogged them through 2005. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Federal spending on the new Medicare drug benefit will be 20 percent lower than expected this year because beneficiaries are choosing prescription drug plans with lower premiums, the Bush administration said. [A20.]</p>
        <p>Executives of Boston Scientific will meet with regulators from the Food and Drug Administration to discuss quality control problems at some of its factories. The agency has already suspended the company's ability to introduce new products, and the meeting could affect its plans to acquire another medical device maker, Guidant. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Study Finds Automakers' Design Changes Save Lives  Design changes that automakers initially resisted and then reluctantly adopted for sport utility vehicles and pickups have sharply reduced the number of deaths among drivers in cars they hit, according to results from the first such study of the standards. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Charges Filed Against Former Insurance Executives  Three former General Re executives and one former American International Group executive have been charged with fraud and conspiracy in connection with a deal that authorities say artificially inflated A.I.G.'s financial position, possibly raising the pressure on other senior executives. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Amazon's Results Come In Below Expectations  Amazon, the online retailer, reported that its profit declined 43 percent during the holiday quarter, in large part because of a decreased tax benefit. A smaller-than-expected increase in revenue, along with high expenses, concerned investors. Amazon's shares declined $3.49, or 8.2 percent, to $39.25 in after-hours trading, after they had fallen in regular trading to close at $42.74. [C2.]</p>
        <p>The iPod Spawns an Industry for Its Accessories  Apple's iPod has given rise to an entire industry in accessories. Sales of cases, docking stations, rechargers and other accessories -- 2,000 at last count -- totaled $850 million last year. [C1.]</p>
        <p>Image Defied Reality, an Enron Executive Testifies  The former Enron chief executives Jeffrey K. Skilling and Kenneth L. Lay continued to publicize the company's retail energy services division as being successful, even as other top executives knew the unit had suffered huge losses from trading and overpriced contracts, Enron's former head of investor relations testified. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Similar Goals but Different Routes on Energy  President Bush supports the development of ethanol, wind power and other forms of renewable energy. So does Congress. But their goals differ in ways that compete for research dollars and are costing some government researchers their jobs. [A17.]</p>
        <p>With a tax code that offers more than $1 billion worth of breaks for gasoline and diesel, New York's energy policies show just how hard it will be for the nation to wean itself from foreign oil. [C19.]</p>
        <p>Retailers Report Their Biggest Sales Gain Since June  Retailers reported their biggest monthly sales gain since June, as shoppers redeemed gift cards and bought spring fashions during one of the warmest Januaries on record. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Workers' Efficiency Increases, but at a Slower Rate  The efficiency of American workers rose in 2005 at the slowest pace since the recession year of 2001 while a major gauge of wage pressures rose at the fastest pace in five years, according to a government report. [C3.]</p>
        <p>General Motors Buys $15 Billion in Technology Services  General Motors said it would spend up to $15 billion over the next five years to contract out information technology services. Electronic Data Systems, its former subsidiary, will remain the biggest supplier but will receive a little less work. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Comcast Posts a Decline in Quarterly Profit  The Comcast Corporation, the nation's largest cable company, said profit slid 69 percent in the fourth quarter as investment losses and a higher tax rate offset gains in its core businesses of selling television, high-speed Internet connections and phone service. [C2.]</p>
        <p>European Bank Paves the Way for a Rate Increase  The European Central Bank laid the groundwork for a rate increase next month, its second in five years, saying that Europe was continuing to grow and that inflation remained a threat. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
