<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are Storm Clouds Massing? These Traders Need to Know</title>
    <meta content="17exchange" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Business of Green" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/17/business/businessspecial2/17exchange.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060525T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1762240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TAKING STOCK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEP Trading Two</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaminer, Curt A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hedge Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFD9153EF934A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are Storm Clouds Massing? These Traders Need to Know</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Are Storm Clouds Massing? These Traders Need to Know</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bajaj, Vikas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trading emission allowances needed by utilities and other industrial users has become established method of improving air quality, as well as profitable investment niche for traders like Curt A Kaminer of hedge fund TEP Trading Two; trading rewards companies and inventors who find way to reduce pollution cheaply while allowing producers with older plants to comply with regulations by buying credits; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CURT A. KAMINER starts his day as any other hedge fund manager would, checking on how his holdings are trading and taking stock of the market forces that are buffeting or bolstering them.</p>
        <p>But unlike standard Wall Street investments, Mr. Kaminer's portfolio does not rise and fall on earnings reports, corporate deals and industry turmoil. His world is swayed by other factors, from weather patterns to delays in coal shipments to the timing of environmental regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An open commodities market allows polluters and traders to figure out the cheapest way toward a common goal: cleaner air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CURT A. KAMINER starts his day as any other hedge fund manager would, checking on how his holdings are trading and taking stock of the market forces that are buffeting or bolstering them.</p>
        <p>But unlike standard Wall Street investments, Mr. Kaminer's portfolio does not rise and fall on earnings reports, corporate deals and industry turmoil. His world is swayed by other factors, from weather patterns to delays in coal shipments to the timing of environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaminer trades in the emission allowances that utilities and other industrial users need so they can pump out sulfur dioxide, nitrous oxide and other pollutants. In this market, prices rally on forecasts of a heat wave on the East Coast, which would mean that power plants need to burn more coal to power air-conditioners. Midsummer rainstorms could have the opposite effect.</p>
        <p>In the last 15 years, regulators have realized a long-debated strategy of turning traditional pollution controls into open commodities markets where polluters and traders can figure out the cheapest way toward a common goal: cleaner air. With some success, the idea has been applied to numerous pollutants, including greenhouse gases in Europe and other industrialized nations as part of the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>Trading in the right to pollute has also become a profitable investment niche drawing professionals like Mr. Kaminer, a former electric utility official who manages a fund with more than $10 million of institutional investors' money.</p>
        <p>''Some days I make money, some days I lose money,'' Mr. Kaminer, 51, said in a phone interview from his home office outside Phoenix. But ''at the end of the day, the air is going to be cleaner because of our efforts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaminer said his hedge fund, TEP Trading Two, had returns of 10 to 20 percent in the last year.</p>
        <p>After false starts beginning in the 1970's, trading in pollution allowances was validated with the Clean Air Act of 1990. That spawned the Environmental Protection Agency's acid rain program to limit sulfur dioxide emissions from power plants in the East and Midwest.</p>
        <p>The pollution-credit system allows utilities that cut emissions more than required to sell their excess reductions as credits to other companies. Or they can bank credits for future use. Credits are bought and sold through electronic trading systems or between two parties through a broker, said Josh Margolis, a managing director for Cantor Fitzgerald Brokerage. Each trade is cleared through an online system maintained by the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>The trading rewards companies and inventors who find a way to reduce pollution cheaply while allowing producers with older plants to comply with regulations by buying credits. Even if some plants do not cut their emissions enough, total pollution is reduced to the desired level.</p>
        <p>''If you can channel greed, for a lack of better term, you are going to clean up the environment a whole lot faster than a government saying thou shalt reduce pollution,'' Mr. Margolis said.</p>
        <p>By 2010, the E.P.A. estimates, the program will generate $120 billion a year in health and visibility benefits at an annual cost of $2 billion. The agency is now working on the Clean Air Interstate Rule, which would require a 70 percent reduction in sulfur dioxide and a 60 percent reduction in nitrous oxide emissions in 28 Eastern states and Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>''It was a real leap of faith in some ways for Congress and the president to say this is a sensible way to manage emissions,'' Bill Wehrum, the E.P.A.'s assistant administrator for air and radiation, said about the first emissions trading programs.</p>
        <p>The agency has expanded trading to other pollutants like nitrous oxide and ozone. Under the Clinton administration, the agency aggressively promoted trading during the negotiations that led to the Kyoto Protocol, the multilateral agreement to reduce greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Although the Bush administration withdrew United States support for Kyoto, partly because it did not impose restrictions on developing countries like China and India, the treaty took effect last year after it was ratified by Europe, Japan, Russia and others. It requires 36 industrial countries to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by varying amounts by 2012.</p>
        <p>The European Union, which must cut its emissions 8 percent under the treaty, began trading in carbon emissions in January 2005, and the market has proved volatile.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the Chicago Climate Exchange is a voluntary greenhouse gas market in which member companies commit to reducing emissions. The exchange has attracted corporations, universities, local governments and even farmers, who can sell credits for keeping carbon buried by not tilling fields after harvests or by using the methane from animal waste as a fuel.</p>
        <p>The creators of the exchange say they are helping to build support for greenhouse gas controls in Congress and in state legislatures.</p>
        <p>Prices and volume on the Climate Exchange are far lower than in Europe because there is no legal requirement for big industrial users to cut emissions in the United States. But some companies, like American Electric Power, a large power producer, have joined the market to get a head start on carbon trading and to push to become more efficient.</p>
        <p>Michael G. Morris, the company's president and chief executive, said that although he opposes Kyoto as it exists, many people wrongly assume utilities have no desire to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>''The question really becomes when and how do we get to the next level of international commitment, and until that time, corporate America can and should continue its commitment on a voluntary basis,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Proponents of emission reductions say Mr. Morris's comments go to the crux of what makes trading work: mandated emissions requirements and a regulatory system that closely monitors compliance and metes out harsh penalties.</p>
        <p>''You will never get there with voluntary measures,'' said David Doniger, a policy director at the Natural Resources Defense Council and a former E.P.A. official. ''The only reason they are trading at a higher price in Europe is that there is a real cap that applies to everyone.''</p>
        <p>TAKING STOCK</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 25, 2006, Thursday  An article about emissions trading in the special Business of Green section on May 17 misstated the costs and benefits of an Environmental Protection Agency program to limit sulfur dioxide emissions. The agency estimates that by 2010 the program will generate $122 billion a year in health and visibility benefits at a cost of $3 billion annually, not $120 billion at $2 billion a year. The article also misstated a type of pollutant that the government regulates. They are nitrogen oxides, not nitrous oxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 25, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article about emissions trading in the special Business of Green section on May 17 misstated the costs and benefits of an Environmental Protection Agency program to limit sulfur dioxide emissions. The agency estimates that by 2010 the program will generate $122 billion a year in health and visibility benefits at a cost of $3 billion annually, not $120 billion at $2 billion a year. The article also misstated a type of pollutant that the government regulates. They are nitrogen oxides, not nitrous oxide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
