<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Listings: April 14 - April 20</title>
    <meta content="14thea" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3D61F30F937A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="15241" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Listings: April 14 - April 20</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'LANDSCAPE OF THE BODY' Opens Sunday. John Guare, never satisfied with an overly tidy play, throws comedy, tragedy, satire and mystery into this cult drama, which first opened almost three decades ago. Lili Taylor and Sherie Rene Scott star (2:15). Signature Theater's Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>'SCREWMACHINE/EYECANDY OR: HOW I LEARNED TO STOP WORRYING AND LOVE BIG BOB' Opens Sunday. C. J. Hopkins's dark drama, a hit at the 2005 Edinburgh Festival, is about a game show host even more bizarre than Bob Barker (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'AWAKE AND SING!' Opens Monday. Lincoln Center Theater revives Clifford Odets's classic fist-shaking drama about a Jewish family struggling to survive during the Depression. The impressive cast includes Mark Ruffalo, Ben Gazzara and Zoë Wanamaker (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE IMPORTANCE OF BEING EARNEST' Opens Tuesday. Closes May 14. Sir Peter Hall stages Oscar Wilde's indestructible comedy. Lynn Redgrave stars as Lady Bracknell (2:25). Brooklyn Academy of Music, Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100.</p>
        <p>'THREE DAYS OF RAIN' Opens Wednesday. Julia Roberts stars in this year's most closely watched star vehicle, a revival of the Richard Greenberg time-traveling drama about how we divide the legacy of our parents. Paul Rudd also stars (2:30). Bernard B. Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Opens Thursday. If any Broadway theater was made for a revival of Brecht's classic, it's the cabaret-style Studio 54, which is host to an intriguing cast that includes Alan Cumming and Cyndi Lauper (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'THE CAINE MUTINY COURT-MARTIAL' Previews start today. Opens May 7. Try not to think of Ross from ''Friends'' when you see David Schwimmer in this revival of Herman Wouk's adaptation of his Pulitzer Prizewinning novel about a lawyer who defends a Navy lieutenant accused of mutiny. Jerry Zaks directs (2:15). The Gerald Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' Opens May 1. This little-musical-that-could about an unscrupulous Broadway producer in the 1920's (some things never change) began at the Toronto Fringe Festival and now makes its unlikely premiere on the Great White Way (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'FAITH HEALER' Previews start Tuesday. Opens May 4. Ralph Fiennes, Cherry Jones and Ian McDiarmid make up the dream cast of this revival of Brian Friel's classic collection of ''Rashomon''-like monologues about a man peddling salvation, his long-suffering wife and his manager (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A FINE AND PRIVATE PLACE' Opens April 27. Redemption is a major theme of this musical fantasy adapted from a Peter S. Beagle novel about a recluse who lives in a Bronx cemetery (2:00). York Theater, St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Lexington Avenue at 54th Street, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY BOYS' Previews start today. Opens April 23. Alan Bennett's acutely observed hit drama about English schoolboys arrives stateside with the best buzz of any new play this year. The National Theater's artistic director Nicholas Hytner directs (2:45). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' Previews start Thursday. Opens April 30. Earth, Wind and Fire get in on the jukebox musical trend with this new show about a woman who dreams of dancing on Broadway. Maurice Hines directs and choreographs (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LESTAT' Opens April 25. Elton John and Bernie Taupin have a good track record for making pop hits, but can they find success in the cursed genre of the vampire musical? Hugh Panaro stars (2:30). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Previews start Wednesday. Opens May 3. The Atlantic Theater Company's acclaimed production of Martin McDonagh's very bloody, exceptionally black comedy about Irish terrorism moves to Broadway (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SHINING CITY' Previews start Thursday. Opens May 9. A guilt-ridden man tells his therapist that he has seen the ghost of his wife in Conor McPherson's new play, which received good reviews at the Royal Court in London. Brian F. O'Byrne, Martha Plimpton and Oliver Platt star (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' Opens May 10. Phil Collins lends his invisible touch to the score of the latest Disney musical. David Henry Hwang wrote the book (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' Opens April 27. Stephen Lynch plays the goofy title character in this musical adaptation of the Adam Sandler film about leg warmers, Billy Idol and other artifacts from the 1980's. John Rando (''Urinetown'') directs (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'BAREFOOT IN THE PARK' For a work that celebrates the liberating force of spontaneity, this revival of Neil Simon's 1963 comedy doesn't have one scene that feels organic, let alone impromptu. Directed by Scott Elliott, and starring Patrick Wilson and a miscast Amanda Peet as newlyweds in Greenwich Village, this ''Barefoot'' has the robotic gait of Frankenstein's monster (2:20). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York City, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FESTEN' An intensely staged, indifferently acted production of David Eldridge's adaptation of a 1998 Danish film about a grim family reunion, which was a big hit in London under the same director, Rufus Norris. While the mise en scène remains unsettlingly stark, the Broadway cast (which includes Michael Hayden, Julianna Margulies, Jeremy Sisto and Ali MacGraw) registers the tension and testiness of people suffering from a collective bad hair day. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Odd is not the word for this couple. How could an adjective suggesting strangeness or surprise apply to a production so calculatedly devoted to the known, the cozy, the conventional? As the title characters in Neil Simon's 1965 comedy, directed as if to a metronome by Joe Mantello, Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick reprise their star performances from ''The Producers,'' and it's not a natural fit. Don't even consider killing yourself because the show is already sold out (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PAJAMA GAME'  Sexual chemistry in a Broadway musical? Isn't that illegal now? If it were, then Harry Connick Jr. and Kelli O'Hara -- the white-hot stars of Kathleen Marshall's delicious revival of this 1954 musical -- would be looking at long jail terms. This intoxicating production, which features a charming supporting cast led by Michael McKean, allows grown-up audiences the rare chance to witness a bona fide adult love affair translated into hummable songs and sprightly dance (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RING OF FIRE'  The man in black turns sunshine yellow in a show that strings songs associated with Johnny Cash into a big, bright candy necklace of a musical revue, created and directed by Richard Maltby Jr. In the current bio-flick ''Walk the Line,'' Cash wrestles demons; ''Ring of Fire'' wrestles with a really bad case of the cutes (2:00). Ethel Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did on Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'WELL' Lisa Kron's sparkling autobiographical play about illness, integration and her mother (portrayed with majestic warmth and weariness by Jayne Houdyshell) helps restore the honor of that tarnished literary form, the memoir. Though it shows the strain of scaling up for Broadway, this singular work, which stars Ms. Kron as herself, opens windows of insight and emotion found in no other show (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BASED ON A TOTALLY TRUE STORY' A chatty, autobiographical comedy by Roberto Aguirre-Sacasa about a writer for comic books who moonlights as a screenwriter and playwright. Juggling his two jobs, the busy writer begins backsliding in his unofficial third, ''being a loving, giving, emotionally available boyfriend.'' Minor-key angst ensues in this perky two hours of comic navel-gazing (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEFIANCE' The second in John Patrick Shanley's cycle of morality plays that began with ''Doubt,'' this ambitious tale of racial relations and the military mindset on a North Carolina marine base feels both overcrowded and oddly diffuse. If ''Doubt'' has an elegant and energy-efficient sprinter's gait, ''Defiance'' progresses with a flustered air of distraction. The excellent Margaret Colin, as an officer's wife, provides a welcome shot of credibility (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club, Theater 1, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ENTERTAINING MR. SLOANE' Miscasting is the mother of invention. Or so it proves to be for Jan Maxwell, who re-tailors an ill-fitting part and makes it as snug as a glove in this underpowered revival of Joe Orton's scandalous 1964 comedy. Scott Ellis's production of Orton's great farce of sexual hypocrisy, which also stars Alec Baldwin, is breezy, often funny and rarely convincing. (2:00). Laura Pels Theater at the Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE M. COHAN TONIGHT!'  The all-singing, all-dancing Jon Peterson summons the spirit of this legendary Broadway entertainer in this engaging one-man musical, devised and directed by Chip Deffaa (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'GREY GARDENS'  As the socialite in limbo called ''Little'' Edie Beale, Christine Ebersole gives one of the most gorgeous performances ever to grace a musical. Unfortunately, she's a pearl of incalculable price in a show that is mostly costume jewelry. Adapted from the Maysles brothers' 1975 cult documentary movie, a camp favorite, and directed by Michael Greif, with the excellent Mary Louise Wilson as Edie's bedridden mother (2:40). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best. (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LOS BIG NAMES'  In the lesbian comic Marga Gomez's friendly new solo show, she measures out affection and mockery in equal doses as she recalls her parents, Willy and Margarita, a comic and a dancer who lived a splashy life on a small scale in the circumscribed world of New York Latino culture in the 1960's. Ms. Gomez pairs stories of their performing careers with comic tales of her own struggles to pursue success in the entertainment industry. A sendup of the movie ''Sphere'' is particularly delicious (1:30). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MACRUNE'S GUEVARA' The Young Mirror arm of Mirror Repertory revives John Spurling's odd 1969 play about an artist who left behind a wall full of drawings of Che Guevara and the man who saw something profound in them. Parts of the play read today like a funny sendup of art critics who see too much brilliance in outsider-art gibberish; other parts seem a bit like gibberish of their own (2:15). St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'RED LIGHT WINTER'  A frank, occasionally graphic story of erotic fixation and the havoc it can wreak on sensitive types. Written and directed by Adam Rapp, this play is both a doomy romantic drama and a morbid comedy about the anxieties of male friendship. Although somewhat contrived, it features a lovely performance by Christopher Denham as a lonely soul starved for intimacy (2:25). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A SAFE HARBOR FOR ELIZABETH BISHOP' The life of a great poet becomes the stuff of stale prose in this one-woman bio-play by Marta Goes, starring Amy Irving (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOW PEOPLE'  Paul Weitz's eyebrow-pencil-thin comedy about a man who hires actors to impersonate his family feels like one long, occasionally amusing party game whose players don't know when to call it a night. The excellent four-member cast, led by Debra Monk and directed by Peter Askin, finds charm and energy amid the vaporous bait-and-switch plot reversals (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TRYST' A suspense drama of a distinctly old-fashioned stamp about the romance between a handsome cad (Maxwell Caulfield) and a lonely spinster (Amelia Campbell). Will the wily predator seduce and abandon the mousy milliner? Karoline Leach's play springs a few twists that lack psychological credibility but keep the plot on the boil (2:00). Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE PRIVATE LIFE OF THE MASTER RACE' Bertolt Brecht's middle-period classic in a robust new translation by Binyamin Shalom and a spare and powerful production by the Roust Theater Company, directed by James Phillip Gates (2:45). Walkerspace, 46 Walker Street, SoHo, (212) 868-4444. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE CATARACT' Though it begins promisingly -- a funny Midwestern noir in the style of the Coen brothers -- Lisa D'Amour's play about Southern drifters unsettling upright Minnesotans soon loses its balance, swamped by a torrent of magical realism and psychobabble (2:15). Women's Project/Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing tomorrow. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>'CONFESSIONS OF A MORMON BOY' Steven Fales, a sixth-generation Mormon, describes leaving his family and becoming a gay escort in this fairly conventional, although admittedly compelling, piece of confessional theater (1:30). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, between Avenue of the Americas and Varick Street, (212) 691-1555; closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'PEN'  David Marshall Grant's sometimes preachy new three-character play is about an unhappy Long Island family in 1969. J. Smith-Cameron is fascinating to watch as she exposes the anguish behind the tough, angry exterior of the wheelchair-bound mother; Dan McCabe is uneven but believable as the troubled teenage son who wants to get away from her; and Reed Birney is less persuasive as the ex-husband who has already left. The title object is a gift from the author to himself: it allows something impossible to happen (2:15). Playwrights Horizons, Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'TRANSATLANTIC LIAISON'  A play fashioned from Simone de Beauvoir's love letters to the American novelist Nelson Algren and scenes from her novel ''The Mandarins'' (which tells the story of their affair). Wonderful performances by Elizabeth Rothan as de Beauvoir in love, and Matthew S. Tompkins as the emotional Algren (1:30). Harold Clurman Theater on Theater Row, 412 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing tomorrow. (Moore)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AQUAMARINE' (PG, 109 minutes) In this sweet comedy for the crowd that has outgrown ''The Little Mermaid,'' two likable pals (Emma Roberts and Joanna Levesque, a k a the singer JoJo) try to help a mermaid (Sara Paxton) find love and learn how to use her feet properly.(Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ATL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) A couple of rap stars make respectable starts on acting careers in this tale of black teenagers in Atlanta, despite a script marred by clichés and predictability. Tip Harris -- the rapper T. I. -- is intriguing as a young man who takes on the responsibility of raising his younger brother when their parents are killed, and Antwan Andre Patton -- Big Boi from OutKast -- makes a terrific drug lord. ( Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BASIC INSTINCT 2' (R, 120 minutes) A joyless calculation, starring Sharon Stone and directed by Michael Caton-Jones, that is also a prime object lesson in the degradation that can face Hollywood actresses, especially those over 40. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BEAUTY ACADEMY OF KABUL' (No rating, 74 minutes, in English and Dari) In the summer of 2004, a group of volunteer American hairstylists arrived in Kabul to open a school. In ''The Beauty Academy of Kabul,'' the director Liz Mermin documents the hilarious, moving and sometimes fractious meeting of diametrically different cultures, one having suffered unimaginable horrors and the other believing a good perm is the answer to everything. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'CAPOTE' (R, 114 minutes) Philip Seymour Hoffman's portrayal of Truman Capote is a tour de force of psychological insight. (Mr. Hoffman won the Academy Award for best actor.) Following the novelist as he works on the magazine assignment that will become ''In Cold Blood,'' the film raises intriguing questions about the ethics of writing. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'CRASH' (Academy Award, Best Picture) (R, 107 minutes) A gaggle of Los Angeles residents from various economic and ethnic backgrounds collide, sometimes literally, within an extremely hectic 36 hours. Well intentioned, impressively acted but ultimately a speechy, ponderous melodrama of liberal superstition masquerading as realism. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DAVE CHAPPELLE'S BLOCK PARTY' (R, 103 minutes) The setup is blissfully simple: a free block party on a dead-end street in Bed-Stuy, with a lineup of musicians, some of whom, like Kanye West and Mos Def, have put in appearances on ''Chappelle's Show.'' The nominal idea, Mr. Chappelle explains on camera, was ''the concert I've always wanted to see.'' The result, which ping-pongs between Brooklyn and Mr. Chappelle's hometown in Ohio, is a tantalizing sketch-portrait of the artist amid an outpouring of hard beats and soul. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DEVIL AND DANIEL JOHNSTON' (PG-13, 110 minutes) The romantic cliché that all artists are a little bit mad is put through its paces (if never seriously questioned) in this documentary about Daniel Johnston, a mentally ill songwriter whom Kurt Cobain, the lead singer for Nirvana, once called the greatest living. Jeff Feuerzeig, who won the best director award at the 2005 Sundance Festival, cobbles together a moving portrait of the artist as his own ghost, using a wealth of material provided by Mr. Johnston, from home movies to audiocassette diaries to dozens of original, and often heartbreakingly beautiful, songs. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'DON'T COME KNOCKING' (R, 122 minutes) The visually majestic but dramatically inert reunion of Sam Shepard (who stars) and the director Wim Wenders, 22 years after their auspicious collaboration on ''Paris, Texas,'' might be described as a magnificent ruin. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'DRAWING RESTRAINT 9' (No rating, 135 minutes) Most of this stately film of few words, conceived and directed by the artist Matthew Barney, who co-stars with his wife, Bjork, takes place on a Japanese whaling ship afloat in Nagasaki Bay. Steeped not only in Japanese seafaring lore but also in centuries-old traditions of Japanese ritual, the film could be described as Mr. Barney's ''Moby-Dick.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>'ICE AGE: THE MELTDOWN' (PG, 93 minutes) Creative exhaustion haunts ''Ice Age: The Meltdown,'' as the characters from 2002's ''Ice Age'' face global warming and the submersion of their valley. While the animals head for safety in a giant, arklike boat, the director, Carlos Saldanha, indulges in biblical imagery and bad science. Over all, a flat and uninspired follow-up to a vastly superior movie. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INSIDE MAN' (R, 128 minutes) The latest from Spike Lee takes a familiar setup -- in this case, a Wall Street bank heist that mutates into a hostage crisis -- and twists it ever so slightly and nicely. Among the film's most sustained pleasures are its holy trinity -- Denzel Washington, Clive Owen and Jodie Foster -- and the best lineup of pusses and mugs outside ''The Sopranos.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LA MUJER DE MI HERMANO' (R, 93 minutes, in Spanish) Zoë (Bárbara Mori) is a gorgeous, vapid wife who longs for children, but her distant spouse (Christian Meier) makes love only on Saturdays. Enter the rebellious brother-in-law (Manolo Cardona), a smoldering artist whose schedule is less regimented. Bubbling with incest, adultery, religion and homosexuality, ''La Mujer de Mi Hermano'' is an overheated telenovela that considers procreation more important than honesty, and what we want more important than who we are. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LOOK BOTH WAYS' (PG-13, 100 minutes) Written and directed by the Australian animator Sarah Watt, ''Look Both Ways'' follows a group of disparate and desperate characters over the course of one of the most depressing weekends in movie history. The principal sufferers are Meryl (Justine Clarke), a morbid illustrator, and Nick (William McInnes), a terminally ill photographer, who discover that a mutual fixation on catastrophe can be quite the aphrodisiac. Bogged down by stylistic gimmickry, ''Look Both Ways'' aims for existential drama but succeeds only in reminding us that misery loves company. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LUCKY NUMBER SLEVIN' (R, 110 minutes) This star-studded jigsaw puzzle of revenge and mistaken identity thinks that it's terribly smart, although it amounts to an empty, self-satisfied imitation of ''Pulp Fiction'' that reputable actors like Morgan Freeman and Ben Kingsley can't salvage. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MARILYN HOTCHKISS BALLROOM DANCING AND CHARM SCHOOL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) John Goodman plays a dying crash victim on his way to a 40-year-old appointment, and Robert Carlyle is the widowed baker entrusted with keeping it. Instead, he meets Marisa Tomei, who teaches him to dance and, more important, throw away his wife's ashes. Toggling back and forth between past and present, ''Marilyn Hotchkiss Ballroom Dancing and Charm School'' is a soggy, endless wallow in nostalgia and the healing power of very bad dancing. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'ON A CLEAR DAY' (PG-13, 99 minutes) Set in and around the dockyards of Glasgow, ''On a Clear Day'' follows Frank (the great Peter Mullan), a laid-off shipbuilder who decides to fix his life by swimming the English Channel. Despite a familiar crop of lovable eccentrics and predictably inspirational thrust, the movie balances the sentimentality with excellent performances and a healthy dose of working-class vulnerability. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SHE'S THE MAN' (PG-13, 105 minutes) ''Twelfth Night'' is recast as a hysterically peppy romantic comedy about a she-jock penetrating the boys' soccer team. Because girls can do anything boys can do, although their ultimate ambition is to put on a nice dress and go steady with a stupid jock. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'16 BLOCKS' (PG-13, 105 minutes) If Richard Donner's presence suggests that his new action flick, ''16 Blocks,'' is a throwback to the 1980's, so does one of the names holding pride of place above the title, Bruce Willis. Mr. Willis has always been an acquired taste, but for those who did acquire that taste, it's a pleasure to see him doing what comes naturally. Which means holding a gun and fending off bad guys with as few words as possible. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SISTERS IN LAW' (No rating, 108 minutes, in English and pidgin) Grass-roots feminism thrives in a Cameroon village, thanks to the pair of warm-hearted, tough-minded women of law profiled in this excellent verité documentary. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'SLITHER' (R, 96 minutes) A horror film about an extraterrestrial monster with a hunger for flesh that slaloms from yucks to yuks, slip-sliding from horror to comedy and back again on its gore-slicked foundation. The writer and director James Gunn knows his icky, scary stuff. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TAKE THE LEAD' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Hip-hop and ballroom dancing styles fuse in a South Bronx high school at which a dance teacher, Antonio Banderas, turns gawky ducklings into gliding swans. It's sloppy but mildly endearing. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'Thank You for Smoking' (R, 92 minutes) The director Jason Reitman has made a glib and funny movie from Christopher Buckley's glib and funny novel about a Big Tobacco lobbyist, but the real attraction here is the hard-working star, Aaron Eckhart. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TORO NEGRO' (No rating, 87 minutes, in Spanish) A disturbed young matador stabs animals, beats his wife and drinks himself to the edge of oblivion in this harrowing, deeply suspect documentary set in rural Mexico. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'TRISTRAM SHANDY: A COCK AND BULL STORY' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom both confirms and refutes the assumption that Laurence Sterne's 18th-century masterpiece of digression could never be made into a movie by making a movie about the making of such a movie. Steve Coogan is wonderful as Tristram, Tristram's father and himself, though Rob Brydon steals more than a few of Mr. Coogan's scenes. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Tsotsi' (R, 94 minutes) (Academy Award winner for best foreign film.) Written and directed by Gavin Hood, from a novel by Athol Fugard, this South African film centers on a 19-year-old thug who steals a baby and finds redemption. You don't have to read crystal balls to see into Tsotsi's future; you just need to have watched a couple of Hollywood chestnuts. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'V for Vendetta' (R, 131 minutes) James McTeigue directs this D-for-dumb future-shock story about a masked avenger (Hugo Weaving) and his pipsqueak sidekick (Natalie Portman) at war against a totalitarian British regime. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'NEIL YOUNG: HEART OF GOLD' (PG, 103 minutes) Filled with country memories, bluesy regret and familiar and piercing sentiment, Jonathan Demme's concert film sounds like quintessential Neil Young, which, depending on your home catalog, will be either an enormous turn-on or a turnoff. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>AGAINST THE TIDE (Through Sunday) The Japan Society's spring film series concludes this weekend. 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>PRIX JEAN VIGO (Through Dec. 30) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Vigo (1905-34), the French filmmaker, with a series of 41 films from directors who have won the prize that bears his name. ''Black Girl'' (1965), Ousmane Sembène's cultural-identity drama about a young African woman living with a French family, will be shown on Thursday. 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RECENT FILMS FROM DENMARK (Through April 22) Scandinavia House continues its overall Scandinavian film series tomorrow. 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE COMPLETE KIESLOWSKI : A ROAD MAP OF THE SOUL (Through April 23) To commemorate the 10th anniversary of Krzysztof Kieslowski's death, the Film Society of Lincoln Center, the Polish National Film Archive and the Polish Cultural Institute in New York are presenting a retrospective of his work. This weekend's films include ''The Double Life of Veronique'' (1991), and all 10 parts of Kieslowski's 1989 Decalogue, inspired by the Ten Commandments. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SHELLEY WINTERS VS. THE WATER (Through April 25) BAMcinématek is honoring Winters, who died in January at 83, with screenings of four of her best-known films. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>ANNA MAY WONG (Through Sunday) Wong, the first Chinese-American movie star, would have turned 100 last year. (She died in 1961.) The Museum of the Moving Image's seven-week retrospective of her work concludes this weekend. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>village voice best of 2005 (Through April 26) This annual series, which opened yesterday, continues this weekend. BAM Rose Cinemas (see above); $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Wednesday) The manic Japanese guitarist Kawabata Makoto leads his long-running band in hard-rocking psychedelic explorations rooted in riffy dirt-rock. 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $15. (Laura Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ALKALINE TRIO, AGAINST ME (Monday) The drummer and bandleader Mike Skiba continues to add 80's brood-pop wrinkles to the straightforward pop punk that made his band's reputation when it began almost a decade ago. 7:30 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>B. B. KING (Monday through Wednesday) The great bluesman B. B. King and his latest guitar called Lucille can, on a good night, summon all the tribulation and joy and resilience of the blues. This show was moved from May 31, and those tickets will be honored. 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; (sold out). (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BRAIN SURGEONS NYC (Monday) With Blue Oyster Cult, Albert Bouchard inspired a generation of metal and punk bands. His current band also features the former Dictator Ross the Boss and the veteran rock critic Deborah Frost. 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $12. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>CHAMILLIONAIRE, LIL' FLIP (Sunday) The Houston rapper Chamillionaire had been lending rhymes to regional records for years. His turns of phrase establish him as an MC, but by singing his own hooks in a deep authoritative voice, he stands out among his peers. Lil' Flip is another Houston luminary with a sing-song flow and class-clown snaps. 9 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ABDULLAH CHHADEH (Wednesday) Abdullah Chhadeh plays the qanun (an 81-string zitherlike instrument) with his ensemble Nara. The group uses jazz double bass and Western percussion, as well as the nay (reed flute), darbuka (hand drum) and Arabic accordion. 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $20. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>CLAP YOUR HANDS SAY YEAH (Tonight and tomorrow) The Brooklyn quintet Clap Your Hands Say Yeah recalls the shamanic whine and thrum of the mid-1990's lo-fi rockers Neutral Milk Hotel, and sometimes the slippery paranoid quirk of the Talking Heads. 8:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE COUP (Tomorrow) The funky, political Coup took flak in 2001 for a pre-9/11 album cover featuring exploding twin towers. But the group's main man, Boots Riley, has lost none of the oppositional fervor. 10 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 992-8484; $25 general admission; $15 for New York University faculty and staff; $7 for N.Y.U. students. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LILY CUSHMAN CULHANE, THE REPUTATION (Monday) Lily Cushman Culhane sings dry, breathy torch songs over rattletrap grooves that recall Tom Waits's early-90's albums. Elizabeth Elmore of the Reputation writes punchy melodic rock anthems about tricky romance. 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $8. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ELBOW, THE CLOUD ROOM (Thursday) Elbow is one of many British bands that have emerged in the wake of Radiohead and Spiritualized, mixing cinematic sonic drift with pointillist emotional disclosure. The new-wave-influenced naïf rockers the Cloud Room garnered wild, though deeply underground, buzz for their best song, ''Hey Hey Now,'' which never broke into the larger indie-pop consciousness. 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 353-1600; $2o in advance, $23 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE FIERY FURNACES (Wednesday) This brother-and-sister art-rock duo's music cuts melodies with carnivalesque keyboard vamps and digressive skronk. 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FIGURINES (Wednesday) The Danish rock band Figurines distinguishes itself from the current glut of post-punk formalists by aping instead the frustrated eeriness of Northwestern indie-rock bands like Modest Mouse. The vocalist Christian Hjelm balances art-song archness and lonely busker frailty. 9 p.m., Rothko, 116 Suffolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 475-7088; $10. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FRANZ FERDINAND, DEATH CAB FOR CUTIE (Tonight) At the vanguard of the post-post-punk trend, the poker-faced Franz Ferdinand plays herky-jerky party music. Death Cab is a decorous diarist-rock band whose sound gets added alternative-rock heft on the recent ''Plans'' (Atlantic). 6, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, (212) 564-4882; $40. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JAMMY AWARDS (Thursday) This is the night when the jam band world proves that its vision extends beyond Grateful Dead approximations. This year's performers include a grab bag of classic rock vets (Little Feat, Peter Frampton); legends of quick-fingered instrumentalism (Bela Fleck, Joe Satriani); and beat scientists (Mad Professor, DJ Logic), as well as the Senegalese great Baaba Maal, the august folkie Richie Havens and the road-tested heroes of the jam scene, Blues Traveler. 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $39.50 to $54.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SHOOTER JENNINGS, DIAMOND NIGHTS (Tuesday) Mr. Jennings follows the outlaw tradition of his legendary father, Waylon, and shares his rough-hewn singing style. But while the younger Mr. Jennings's music is decidedly country, he adds his own classic-rock-informed sensibility. The Diamond Nights of New York play 70's hard-rock with a dollop of new wave. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $17.50 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ROBERT EARL KEEN (Tomorrow) This gravel-voiced Texas songwriter, a contemporary of Lyle Lovett and Nanci Griffith, is a storyteller who can unfurl a sad-luck tale with genuine heart and a sardonic twinge. Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 353-1600; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>R. KELLY (Tuesday) Few artists have turned their personal travails into unique pop music like R. Kelly, whose multi-part R&amp;B saga ''Trapped in the Closet'' is a singularly strange psychosexual ramble. He is billing himself as Mr. Showbiz for this ''Light It Up'' tour, presenting a parade of hits that downplays any voyeuristic weirdness without skimping on the up-front sexuality that has made him famous and dangerous. 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 247-4777; $39.50 to $89.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TALIB KWELI (Tomorrow) The brainy rapper Talib Kweli's agile attack still lacks Jay-Z's precision, 50 Cent's swagger and Nas's anguish. But his thrust can be raw and his struggle beautiful when he laments things like Lauryn Hill's absence from the music scene. 11 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LADYTRON (Tomorrow) Influenced by 1980's synth-pop's great songwriting as well as its style, Ladytron arrived before New York's fleeting electroclash moment, and it has survived it, playing dark, droning dance-pop cut with a romantic sense of alienation. 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ALAN LICHT AND THE PRIX (Monday) For this get-together of indie-rock vets, the experimental guitarist Alan Licht will be backed by the guitarist Chris Brokaw (formerly of Come and Codeine), the bassist Doug McCombs (of Tortoise), and the drummer Elliott Dicks. 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503; $8. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MAPFUMO AND THE BLACKS UNLIMITED (Tuesday) A musical pioneer with a rebel's courage, Thomas Mapfumo made music for the revolutionaries who unseated the white-ruled government from what was Rhodesia and is now Zimbabwe. The music transferred the brisk patterns of traditional thumb-piano music to guitar; the words sometimes sent coded messages. 9 and 11:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JOAN OSBORNE (Tuesday) Best known for her hit song musing on the Almighty, ''One of Us,'' Joan Osborne has since focused on the blues and R&amp;B tradition in which she got her start. Expect lots of classic covers and possibly a display of the Qawwali singing she learned from Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan. 8 p.m., Coda, 34 East 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-3434; $25. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ROBERT POLLARD, RICHARD DAVIES (Thursday) The prolific recording maven Robert Pollard may have disbanded his much beloved band, Guided by Voices, but he continues to record and perform with undeterred gusto. The Australian singer-songwriter Richard Davies has pursued a solo career after playing in the baroque-pop outfit the Cardinal. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Sufi music with AHMET OZHAN AND THE WHIRLING DERVISHES (Tomorrow) Accompanied by the ritual Sufi dancers of the Istanbul Mevlevi Order, the singer Ahmet Ozhan will perform songs in the classical mystic tradition. 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $20 to $100. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TV ON THE RADIO (Tuesday) TV on the Radio tops its jittery rhythms and paranoid guitars with the haunting vocal yelps of Tunde Adebimpe and Kyp Malone. They are soon to release a major-label debut, reportedly even more out-there than their indie releases. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; (sold out) . (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>DAR WILLIAMS (Tuesday) This adorable coffeehouse singer-songwriter augments her sweet voice with that rare quality of seeming like a real person. 7 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or Ticketmaster.com or (212) 307-7171; $30. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) The regal cabaret singer and the brassy songs of Kander and Ebb that she is offering in her new show may not be an obvious fit. But Ms. Akers locates the heart inside the brass and sass. 9 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $60 cover, with a $20 minimum; $60 prix fixe dinner required on Thursdays and at the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. 2 p.m., Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $75, including brunch at noon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER (Tomorrow) This booming pop-blues contralto may not be demure, but she is tasteful in a smart, regal, big-mama way, and she is astute in her choices of often obscure soul, blues and jazz songs that play to her contradictory mixture of the lusty and the philosophical. 7 p.m., Helen's, 169 Eighth Avenue, near 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0609; $20, with a $15 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* MARY CLEERE HARAN  (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) A wonderful no-frills singer with a sophisticated wit, Ms. Haran has a remarkable talent for simultaneously interpreting standards in the spirit in which they were written and looking at them through 21st-century eyes. 8:45 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $60 tonight and tomorrow; $50 Tuesday through Thursday. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DARCY JAMES ARGUE'S SECRET SOCIETY (Tuesday) As the name implies, this 18-piece big band is calibrated for maximum intrigue, with a sound that suggests Steve Reich minimalism as well as orchestral jazz in the lineage of Bob Brookmeyer (one of Mr. Argue's mentors). The ranks of the band include such hale improvisers as the trumpeter Ingrid Jensen, the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin and the trombonist Alan Ferber. 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, between Houston and Bleecker Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 614-0505; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>OMER AVITAL GROUP (Thursday) The bassist Omer Avital, a staple of the West Village club Smalls during its premillennial first run, is back after a spell in his native Israel, with new music and a new stable of bands. This one consists of Joel Frahm on tenor saxophone, Avishai Cohen on trumpet, Omer Klein on piano and Greg Hutchinson on drums. 10 p.m. and midnight, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369; cover, $20; includes two drinks. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE'S BIG SATAN (Wednesday) Mr. Berne, a vigorous and exploratory alto saxophonist, makes interplay the driving force in his band with the guitarist Marc Ducret and the drummer Tom Rainey. This one-night stand kicks off a month of touring. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON CARTER/KARRIN ALLYSON (Tuesday through April 23) Mr. Carter, an august and influential bassist, has had mixed success as a bandleader; his best efforts usually involve the articulate pianist Stephen Scott, who joins him in this quartet. Ms. Allyson comes bearing a new album, ''Footprints'' (Concord), which delves into Jon Hendricks-style vocalese; as on the album, she digs in here with a strong ensemble spearheaded by the pianist Bruce Barth. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LARRY CORYELL, VICTOR BAILEY AND LENNY WHITE (Through Sunday) Their recent album, ''Electric'' (Chesky), works hard to deserve the moniker; it relies equally on Mr. Coryell's searing guitar, Mr. Bailey's electric bass and Mr. White's earthy drumming. 8 and 10 p.m., with 11:30 sets tonight and tomorrow night. Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE DAVIS QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A trombonist steeped in precise and pugnacious hard bop, with a group consisting of Steve Nelson on vibraphone, Larry Willis on piano, Nat Reeves on bass and Joe Farnsworth on drums. 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, Manhattan, (212) 885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE FRANK AND JOE SHOW (Wednesday) Exuberance is the currency of this four-piece band, which finds equal inspiration in swing (both the American and Gypsy varieties) and Latin music (or some approximation thereof). Frank is Frank Vignola, a guitarist; the Joe in the equation is Joe Ascione, a drummer. 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BILL FRISELL QUINTET (Tuesday through April 23; April 25 through 30) On his latest Nonesuch releases -- ''East/West'' and ''Further East/Further West,'' both partly recorded at the Village Vanguard -- the guitarist Bill Frisell conjures a compelling hallucination of the American popular songbook, with Tony Scherr and Kenny Wollesen on bass and drums. The addition of the saxophonist Greg Tardy and the trumpeter Ron Miles should alter the ensemble's chemistry as well as its size. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Fridays and Saturdays, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EDDIE GALE'S NOW BAND (Tomorrow through Monday) Mr. Gale is a trumpeter with serious avant-garde credentials, having worked closely with the trailblazers Cecil Taylor and Sun Ra, among others. Visiting from the West Coast, he makes three stops in as many days, with a group of estimable players including the trombonist Dick Griffin and the bassist Todd Nicholson. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Sistas' Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766. Sunday at 3 p.m., Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681; cover, $10 per set; $7 for students; free for ages 14 and under. Monday at 9 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near North Third Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARY HALVORSON AND JESSICA PAVONE (Thursday) Ms. Halvorson plays guitar in this duo, and Ms. Pavone plays viola. Their experimental instincts, sharpened by an affiliation with Anthony Braxton, commingle with a folksy lyricism; sometimes they even sing, without a trace of protective irony. 8 p.m., The Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village; cover, $10. www.thestonenyc.com. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY HART QUARTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Hart, a loose but focused drummer with a sterling résumé, fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HEBERT'S BYZANTINE MONKEY QUARTET (Wednesday) A progressive ensemble featuring the original music and bass playing of Mr. Hebert, along with the typically thoughtful contributions of Ralph Alessi, trumpeter; Mat Maneri, violist; and Nasheet Waits, drummer. 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HOLLENBECK'S CLAUDIA QUINTET (Tomorrow) This improvising chamber ensemble pursues texturally oriented and often contrapuntal exploration; Mr. Hollenbeck's drumming is one color on a palette that also includes Chris Speed's clarinet and tenor saxophone, Ted Reichman's accordion, John Hebert's bass and Matt Moran's vibraphone. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, Mr. Liebman plays here with a group featuring a frequent foil, the guitarist Vic Juris. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LIONEL LOUEKE TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Loueke, a distinctive guitarist and vocalist, favors a form of global jazz deeply informed by his West African homeland, Benin; his bandmates are the bassist Massimo Biolcati and the drummer Ferenc Nemeth. 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RUDRESH MAHANTHAPPA QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Mahanthappa uses both his razor-sharp alto saxophone tone and his compositional acumen in this group, with the pianist Vijay Iyer, the bassist François Moutin and the drummer Dan Weiss. The group is introducing ''Code Book,'' a work created with support from Chamber Music America, that will be the substance of Mr. Mahanthappa's next release. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>REBECCA MARTIN (Thursday) A singer-songwriter with no small affinity for jazz harmony, Ms. Martin gets more than the usual support from her ensemble, which includes the tenor saxophonist Bill McHenry and the bassist Larry Grenadier, her husband. She shares a bill with Trevor Exter, a cellist and vocalist riding the contemporary current of acoustic pop. 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO QUINTET (Thursday through April 23) The guitarist Pat Martino's new Blue Note album, ''Remember: A Tribute to Wes Montgomery,'' does exactly what it purports to do. And it works, because of the untroubled self-assurance of the emulation and the simple satisfaction of a hard-swinging band. 8 and 10 p.m., with 11:30 sets on Friday and Saturday, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MULGREW MILLER QUARTET (Through Saturday) Mr. Miller is a smart pianist with roots firmly planted in jazz tradition, especially the blues. Here he corrals some strong younger players: Myron Walden, alto saxophonist; Ivan Taylor, bassist; and Rodney Green, drummer. 9 p.m., 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARC MOMMAAS AND GLOBAL MOTION (Thursday) Mr. Mommaas, a Dutch tenor saxophonist, employs a fluid post-bop language in this band, with the Danish pianist Nikolaj Hess and the American rhythm team of John Hebert on bass and Tony Moreno on drums. Here the group workshops new pieces by Mr. Hess that draw inspiration from African music. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, 212 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK MORGAN QUARTET (Tuesday through April 23) Now in his 70's, the alto saxophonist Frank Morgan is one of the last survivors of the bebop era (and in his case, ''survivor'' is truly the appropriate term). He leads a sympathetic group consisting of John Hicks on piano, Curtis Lundy on bass and Victor Lewis on drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN TRIO (Tuesday) As a violist and violinist, Ms. Scheinman often goes for rustic charm, but she never ceases to be an exploratory improviser. Her more experimental side is purposefully exposed in this setting, featuring the darkly consonant bass playing of Todd Sickafoose and the explosively elastic drumming of Jim Black. 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JANIS SIEGEL (Wednesday through April 21) With her new album, ''A Thousand Beautiful Things'' (Telarc), Ms. Siegel applies her self-assured alto to songs by Raul Midón, Suzanne Vega and Nellie McKay. It's the same sort of popular eclecticism she enjoys in Manhattan Transfer, but a few degrees less cloying. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30; $40 on April 21; with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN TCHICAI TRIO (Sunday) The Danish saxophonist and clarinetist John Tchicai developed a reputation for fiery exertions during the first wave of free jazz, but ''Good Night Songs'' (Boxholder), his new double CD with the saxophonist Charlie Kohlhase and the guitarist Garrison Fewell, conveys an often tenderhearted intimacy. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ACIS AND GALATEA'  (Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) Mark Lamos's enchanting production of Handel's opera, introduced in 2001, returns to the New York City Opera with two artists making their company debuts in the leading roles. The soprano Sarah Jane McMahon is Galatea, the sea nymph hopelessly in love with a young sailor, Acis, sung by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Ransom Wilson conducts. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $110. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHèME' (Tonight) James Robinson's production punts the Puccini favorite forward by some 80 years, placing the action in the opening months of World War I and lending an extra tug of pathos. A mostly new cast at the City Opera has taken over, with Yunah Lee as Mimi, Gerard Powers as Rodolfo, Jennifer Black as Musetta and Philip Torre as Marcello. David Wroe conducts. 8, New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $110. (Jeremy Eichler)</p>
        <p>'CARMEN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Devilish is what you want in a Carmen, and on opening night at the New York City Opera, Kate Aldrich came through in that role, capturing not only Carmen's seductiveness but also her radical proto-feminist pride in her own independence. Unfortunately, there was scant chemistry between her and Robert Breault as Don José. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; sold out tomorrow; $25 to $120 on Wednesday. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI' (Tomorrow) A new cast takes over for the end of the spring run of Mozart's nearly perfect opera at the New York City Opera. Timothy Kuhn will make his company debut in the title role; Claudia Waite will make hers as Donna Anna; and Caroline Worra should be a credible Donna Elvira. Steven Mosteller conducts, adequately. 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $45 to $79. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Amato's venerable recipe -- no rehearsals, changing casts at every performance -- should make for an unusual version of Mozart's classic dish, but at least the theater's small scale represents a kind of period fidelity. 7:30, Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200; $30; $25 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'DON PASQUALE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The veteran Austrian director Otto Schenk understands that the way to make a rich, comic opera like Donizetti's ''Don Pasquale'' work is to treat it seriously. In his wonderful new production for the Met he taps into the emotions -- jealousy, yearning, fear of death -- that swirl below the surface of this farcical tale about a miserly bachelor who foolishly decides to take a young wife and disinherit his shiftless nephew. The cast is splendid, especially the charismatic soprano Anna Netrebko, the dynamic young baritone Mariusz Kwiecien and, in the title role, the stylish Italian bass Simone Alaimo. (On Tuesday, Lyubov Petrova sings Norina in place of Ms. Netrebko, and John Del Carlo replaces Mr. Alaimo.) Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out tomorrow; $26 to $175 on Tuesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LOHENGRIN' (Monday and Thursday) Robert Wilson's luminous production of this luminous opera is not to every taste, but many find that it shines, and Karita Mattila should shine in it as Elsa. The title role should also fit Ben Heppner well. Luana DeVol, an American soprano who has been active mainly in Germany, is Ortrud. Replacing James Levine in the pit is the promising conductor Philippe Auguin, who made his Met debut replacing Mr. Levine in Busoni's ''Doktor Faustus.'' 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to $175. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Tonight) The Met's long-running and highly successful production finally comes to a close, here with Hei-Kyung Hong, Frank Lopardo and Dwayne Croft. 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight, tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) A weekly presenter of chamber music, this floating concert hall also offers great views of Lower Manhattan. Tonight at 7:30, Dmitri Alexeev performs piano works by Shostakovich, Tchaikovsky, Scriabin and Rachmaninoff. Concerts tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 4 p.m. feature rarely heard music by the 18th-century Russian violinist Ivan Khandoshkin, along with Haydn, Shostakovich and Schubert. Sunday evening at 7:30 is a rescheduled performance of music by Messiaen, Beethoven and others. Thursday evening at 7:30, Carlos Prieto (cello) and Doris Stevenson (piano) survey more Shostakovich, as well as Piazzolla's ''Grand Tango.'' Fulton Ferry Landing, next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35, tomorrow and Sunday afternoon, $40. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Wednesday) There will be Beethoven and Janacek quartets, and then the Pacifica and Miro Quartets will merge in the Mendelssohn Octet. 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788; $30 to $52. (Holland)</p>
        <p>IL DOLCIMELO (Sunday) This German period-instrument ensemble makes its New York debut with works by Vivaldi, Scarlatti, Corelli and Telemann. 5 p.m., Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700; $20. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>JUILLIARD STRING QUARTET (Tuesday) The venerable Juilliard offers Mozart, Shostakovich and Brahms. 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406; free, but tickets are required. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) Mstislav Rostropovich approaches the music of Shostakovich with more authority and close personal knowledge than just about anyone. He returns to the Philharmonic to lead the composer's 10th Symphony and his gripping First Violin Concerto, with Maxim Vengerov as soloist. 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $33 to $104. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>ORCHESTRA OF THE AGE OF ENLIGHTENMENT (Sunday) The key names here are less the orchestra's than that of René Jacobs, a conductor (and singer) who has reawakened many corners of period performance, and of Solomon, the title character in Handel's oratorio. Handel switched largely from opera to oratorio in the 1740's and wrote new oratorios for each Lenten season, so this offering is seasonal as well as inherently appealing. 3 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $56 (Midgette)</p>
        <p>POMERIUM (Tomorrow) Alexander Blachly's superb early-music choir offers an Easter program with motets composed for Holy Week by Renaissance and early-Baroque composers, including Dufay, Senfl, Lassus, Gesualdo, Monteverdi and Byrd. 1 and 3 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'ST. MATTHEW PASSION' (Tonight and tomorrow) After acclaimed presentations in 1997 and 2001, Jonathan Miller's revelatory staging of Bach's astounding sacred work has returned to the Harvey Theater at the Brooklyn Academy of Music. The chorus members and orchestra musicians wear everyday clothing and sit facing one another in a circle so that they can enact the scenes from the story of Jesus' Crucifixion. Instrumentalists and singers interact with and even comfort one another during the sublime arias. Rufus Müller is a charismatic Evangelist; Curtis Streetman makes an affectingly husky and noble Jesus. Paul Goodwin, who conceived the production with Mr. Miller, conducts. 7:30 p.m., 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $30 to $90. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* SAN FRANCISCO SYMPHONY (Wednesday and Thursday) Michael Tilson Thomas has made this orchestra into one of the country's best, and its visits to Carnegie Hall are invariably illuminating. His programs include a range of composers from the late-19th and early-20th centuries, among them, Debussy, Ravel, Wagner and Mahler on Wednesday, and Webern, Stravinsky and Ives on Thursday. Jean-Yves Thibaudet is the soloist in the Ravel Piano Concerto in G. 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800; $28 to $97. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>FAZIL SAY (Tonight) This young Turkish pianist plays with energy and, when he is at his best, the improvisatory sensibilities of a jazz performer. His program includes the Brahms Intermezzi (Op. 117) and plenty of Bach, both straight (the Italian Concerto and the French Suite No. 6) or hyphenated (Busoni's transcription of the Chaconne, along with arrangements by Liszt and Mr. Say himself). 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949; $40. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ALLEN BODY GROUP AND JENNIE MARYTAI LiU (Tonight and tomorrow) Science is the inspiration for Malinda Allen's ''Einstein's Dreams'' and Ms. Liu's ''Learning in Lower Animals.'' 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org. Tickets: $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>'A BENEFIT OF THE DOUBT' (Tomorrow) This benefit for Jonah Bokaer's new Chez Bushwick Studios is a tribute to Charles Atlas, a filmmaker who has worked with Merce Cunningham. The evening includes a screening of a film and video work by Mr. Atlas (5 p.m.), a performance by artists who have collaborated with Mr. Atlas (7:30 p.m.) and a ''Shtudio Show'' (at 9 p.m. ) Chez Bushwick Studios, 304 Boerum Street, Apt. 11, Bushwick, Brooklyn, (917) 459-1072. Tickets: $50 and $150; $250 includes cocktails and dinner. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BALLET FIESTA MEXICANA (Tonight through Sunday) Yloy Ybarra's company returns in a program of music and dance from Mexico, with live music performed by the group Semilla. Through April 30. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 4 p.m. Thalia Spanish Theater, 41-17 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens, (718) 729-3880. Tickets: $25 to $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHILDREN OF UGANDA (Tonight through Sunday) Twenty children, ages 8 to 18, will celebrate the culture of their country and of East Africa in song and dance to raise money for Uganda's 1.7 million AIDS and war orphans. Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 2 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $25; $15 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SELMA JEANNE COHEN: A TRIBUTE TO HER LIFE AND WORK (Tomorrow) The last event in this free series is ''Next Week, Swan Lake: Approaches to Dance History and Criticism,'' a panel discussion including Mindy Aloff, Jack Anderson, Marcia Siegel and George Dorris. 3 p.m., Bruno Walter Auditorium, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, 111 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 642-0142. Free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCE PLUS SPRING' (Thursday through April 23) The program includes dances by David Dorfman, Julia Ritter, John Evans, Randy James and Paulette Sears, all dance teachers, and Megan Hebert, a student choreographer. Thursday, next Friday and April 22 at 8 p.m.; April 23 at 2 p.m., Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, 85 George Street, between Route 18 and Ryders Lane, Douglass College campus, New Brunswick, N.J., (732) 932-7511 or masongross.rutgers.edu. Tickets: $20 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARTHA GRAHAM DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) The company seems to be in transition, to put it mildly, but it is still the primary keeper of some of the great modern-dance repertory of the last century, and of some wonderful dancers. The major event is a gala on Tuesday that includes Richard Move, the Graham impersonator, performing a duet with Desmond Richardson, and a solo by Fang-Yi Sheu. 7:30 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South. For $45 performance tickets, (212) 992-8484; for $150 and $500 gala tickets, (212) 521-3667, or marthagraham.org. Also on Tuesday, five generations of Graham performers will give a master class in the studio where Graham taught in the 1930's. 11:30 a.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5553. Audience: $15. Participants: $12 for professionals, $15 for others. Ancillary events continue on April 21 and 25. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>MARIA HASSABI (Tonight and tomorrow) Hip, rawly emotional and mysterious, Ms. Hassabi will present her new program, ''Still Smoking,'' which investigates the frenetic experience of city life. Tonight at 7 and 9:30; tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, ext. 11, thekitchen.org. Tickets: $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LEADING LADIES: ALETHEA ADSITT &amp; COMPANY  (Tonight and tomorrow) This festival of dances by women continues with ''the new jalopy,'' a new multimedia, site-specific piece presented by Alethea Adsitt &amp; Company. 8 and 10 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, SoHo, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com or dnadance.org. Tickets: $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEWSTEPS (Thursday through April 22) Miriam Hess, Jessica Ray and Adrienne F. Westwood are among those featured, as the Mulberry Street Theater's semiannual choreographers' showcase explores themes of power, relationship and memory. 8 p.m., 70 Mulberry Street, second floor (corner of Mulberry and Bayard Streets), Chinatown, (212) 349-0126. Tickets: $12. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DAVID PARKER AND THE BANG GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow) The irrepressible Mr. Parker will present dances that include his new ''Backward and in Heels,'' a piece for six dancers that is set to music. That music incorporates excerpts from the score from ''The Sound of Music''; ''Hava Nagila,'' played by a hand-bell choir; and Schubert's ''Ave Maria.'' 8:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org. Tickets: $21. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARISSA PEREL (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Perel, who has worked with Miguel Gutierrez, will present her new ''Burden,'' a dance performance and installation that also features the dancer Kayvon Pourazar and the musician Jon Moniaci. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8. The Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com. Tickets: $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* STEPHEN PETRONIO COMPANY (Tuesday through Sunday) What do you get when you mix the singer-songwriter Rufus Wainwright, the Young People's Chorus of New York City and Stephen Petronio's extravagant movement language? A concert not to be missed. Tuesday through April 22 at 8 p.m., April 23 at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800. Tickets: $40. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA (Tonight through Sunday) It almost doesn't matter what this New York favorite performs, but for the record, the program will include some of Ms. Rioja's favorite flamenco dances. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday at 3 p.m.; Monday at 11 a.m. Repertorio Español, 138 East 27th Street, between Lexington and Third Avenues, (212) 225-9920. Tickets: $25 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RUSSIAN NATIONAL BALLET (Tomorrow) An indefatigable touring company based in Moscow, with guest stars from elsewhere in Russia, in ''Swan Lake,'' of all things. 8 p.m., Queensborough Performing Arts Center, Queensborough Community College, 222-05 56th Avenue, Bayside, Queens, (718) 631-6311. Tickets: $39 and $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* SOURCING STRAVINSKY (Wednesday through April 22) Six choreographers take on Stravinsky, with Yvonne Rainer (in a rare new dance work) using both Stravinsky and Balanchine's ''Agon.'' The other choreographers are Cynthia Hopkins, Dayna Hanson and Linas Phillips, David Neumann and Rennie Harris. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org. Tickets: $15 and $25. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'TRAS LADOS' (Thursday through April 23) Artists from Mexico to Japan come together for the latest installment of Danspace Project's Global Exchange series. Choreographed by Eun Jung Gonzalez, in collaboration with Pulso Compañía de Danza. 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org. Tickets: $15. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>TRINAYAN COLLECTIVE (Tonight through Sunday) This New York-based company of Indian classical dancers will explore the notion of the witness in ''Sakshi/Witness,'' a dance in the Odissi style. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, SoHo, (212) 334-7479. Tickets: $25; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 14. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to, and settlement in, the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Brooklyn Museum: WILLIAM WEGMAN: 'FUNNEY/STRANGE,' through May 28. Descended from Marcel Duchamp and Buster Keaton, Mr. Wegman has straddled high and low for more than three decades, using his signature Weimaraners to make the art world's funniest videos, as well as television commercials, calendars and children's books. His popular success has tended to obscure his originality and influence, along with a multifarious production that includes wittily captioned drawings, wonderfully irreverent paintings and a host of nondog photographic work. This thorough and thoroughly entertaining retrospective highlights not only the accessibility of his richly human art, but also its dedication to the 1970's notion that art should not look like art. (See above.) (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'GOYA's LAST WORKS,' through May 14. This compact show is sublime. The most humane portraits are mixed with sketches, like diary entries, in which society is an irredeemable mob of lunatics and murderers. In exile in Bordeaux, Goya spent his last days in physical misery, lamenting man's essential evil while experimenting with the new medium of lithography and inventing the most exquisite, luminous paintings on tiny chips of ivory. Like the late works of Titian or Rembrandt, Goya's late works achieve a whole new level of freedom and depth, haunted by death but exalted. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum: 'David Smith: A Centennial,' through May 14. David Smith is best known for his worst work, bulky sculptures of the ''important'' kind that museums and banks like to buy. Much (though not all) of that material has been excised from this survey in favor of smaller, earlier, nonmonumental pieces that the curator, Carmen Gimenez, presents with plenty of air and light. The result is exemplary as a David Smith experience, an American Modernism experience and a Guggenheim Museum experience. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'Snap Judgments: New Positions in Contemporary African Photography,' through May 28. If Martians tuned into our television news broadcasts, they'd have a miserable impression of life on Earth. War, disease, poverty, heartbreak and nothing else. That's exactly how most of the world sees Africa: filtered through images of calamity. The Nigerian-born curator Okwui Enwezor offers a bracing alternative view in this show of recent photography from Africa. He isn't interested in simply exchanging an upbeat Africa for a downbeat one, smiles for frowns, but in engineering a slow, complex, panoptical turn in perspective, one that takes in many moods and directions. The results are stimulating, astringent, brimming with life. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'HATSHEPSUT,' through July 9. Can a queen be a king, too? Consider the case of Hatshepsut, an Egyptian ruler of the 15th century B.C. She assumed the supreme title of pharaoh and ruled Egypt in that powerfully masculine role until her death. Hatshepsut is the subject of a celebratory show at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, one that commemorates the 100th anniversary of the Met's department of Egyptian art. Organized by the Met and the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, it includes many objects from the Met's own extensive holdings, excavated at its digs in the 1920's and 30's. But it isn't so easy to follow Hatshepsut's trail in this ambitious show, what with the number of relatives, subordinates, minor officials and such who also have a place in it, along with scarabs, jewelry, pottery, furniture and other artifacts. (212) 535-7710. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Met: KARA WALKER AT THE MET: 'AFTER THE DELUGE,' through July 30. The Metropolitan Museum of Art's first foray into artist-organized shows is a small tour de force of curatorial creativity. Inspired partly by Hurricane Katrina, Ms. Walker has combined works from the Met with examples of her own art, connecting shared themes of race, poverty and water to illuminate contemporary art's inevitable dialogue with past art. The show has as many crosscurrents and undertows as a river. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'EDVARD MUNCH: THE MODERN LIFE OF THE SOUL,' through May 8. This affecting, full-scale retrospective is the first survey of this Norwegian painter in an American museum in almost 30 years. Its more than 130 oils and works on paper cover Munch's entire career, from 1880 to 1944. (212) 708-9400. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'ON SITE: NEW ARCHITECTURE IN SPAIN,' through May 1. Since the early 1970's, when Spain began to awaken from the isolation of a four-decade dictatorship, Spanish architects have produced designs of unusual depth, often with a firm connection to the land, a sense of humility and a way of conveying continuity with the past while embracing the present. Packed with pretty images and elegant models, this exhibition lacks the scholarly depth you might have hoped for on such a mesmerizing subject. (See above.) (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* The Museum of Modern Art: 'Without Boundary: Seventeen Ways of Looking,' through May 22. This excellent group show considers what ''Islamic'' means in the work of several contemporary artists, and it means many things, none simple. Just to see the uses made of calligraphy by Shirazeh Houshiary, Rachid Koraichi and Shirin Neshat is to understand the lesson in variety put forward here. At the same time, the show is far from didactic. It's beautiful, sexy and, in the case of Raqib Shaw's painting and Kutlug Ataman's video of Sufi meditation, ecstatic. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>National Academy Museum: 'Treasures from Olana: Landscapes by Frederic Edwin Church,' through April 30. Exquisite small landscape studies by the best of the Hudson River School painters. They are from the collection at Olana, the Persian-style Victorian mansion -- now a museum -- that Church built on an upstate hill overlooking the Hudson River. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE GALERIE: 'KLEE AND AMERICA,' through May 22. For a long time, the Swiss-born artist Paul Klee (1879-1940), regarded as a leading Modernist figure in Europe, didn't believe his delicate, chimerical work had much of a future in the United States. Yet, thanks to artists, collectors and dealers with close contacts in Germany who had begun to discover his work, by the early 1920's, Klee's impact began to be felt here. This show of more than 60 paintings and drawings assembled exclusively from American holdings covers the wide spectrum of Klee's work. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'The Thirteen: Chinese Video Now,' through April 24. A snappy roundup of recent video, a favored medium among young artists in a digitally savvy 21st-century China, this show has two fine pieces by Cao Fei, who has garnered much attention recently. It is also the occasion for several worthy New York debuts. Some of the art is light, slight, and MTV-ish, but artists like Cui Xiuwen, Xu Zhen, Li Songhua, Xu Tan, Meng Jin and Dong Wensheng give us a lot. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Studio Museum In harlem: 'Energy/Experimentation: Black Artists and Abstraction, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art, abstraction. This show is stylishly installed (one gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer); the 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. One, the sculptor Tom Lloyd (1921-96), opened the Studio Museum with a solo show in 1968. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'WHITNEY BIENNIAL 2006: DAY FOR NIGHT,' through May 28. This biennial will provoke much head-scratching by uninitiated visitors. A hermetic take on what has been making waves, it's packaged -- branded might be the better word -- as a show long on collaboration and open-endedness: several shows under one roof, including a revival of the 1960's ''Peace Tower,'' which rises like a Tinker Toy construction from the Whitney courtyard, with contributions by dozens of artists. As a counter to the image of the art world as rich, youth-besotted and obsessed with crafty little nothings, the ethos here is provisional, messy, half-baked, cantankerous, insular -- radical qualities art used to have when it could still call itself radical and wasn't like a barnacle clinging to the cruise ship of pop culture. That was back in the 1970's. And much of what's here (including works by bohemians and other senior eccentrics around then) harks back to that moment. (800) 944-8639 or www.whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>PETER BEGLEY Parisian esprit enlivens Peter Begley's latest multipanel paintings. Their motif is the cornice: a ubiquitous emblem of Baron Haussmann's grand boulevards, which, abstracted and made delicately ornate, permits Mr. Begley to add illusory depth to his usual richly worked, waxy fields of warm color. Partly the filigree, partly the gentle rapture with his recently adopted city give to these new works a bit of the élan of old Raoul Dufy. Salander-OReilly, 20 East 79th Street, (212) 879-6606, through April 22. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Tony Cragg: 'Five Bottles' In the early 1980's, this eminent English sculptor made flat, mosaiclike works out of found colored plastic objects and fragments. This show presents a set of five wall-works, each representing a different giant colored bottle composed of toys, combs, cigarette lighters and other pieces of ordinary commercial detritus. Vivian Horan, 35 East 67th Street, (212) 517-9410, through April 21. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'1968: All in a Dream' In 1968 the photographer Lenny Gottlieb saved 30,000 snapshots that were supposed to have been thrown out at the photographic processing lab where he was working. Approximately 500 of them are on view here; collectively, they offer an enthralling cross-section of American life during a year of tremendous change. Andrew Roth, 160A East 70th Street, (212) 717-9067, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NAGASAWA ROSETSU This rare survey of this eccentric painter of 18th-century Kyoto consists of 14 works that reveal a breathtaking command of different skills and styles in portraiture, landscape, nature painting and calligraphic minimalism, and an almost chameleonlike instinct for using them. Koichi Yanagi Oriental Fine Arts, 58A East 66th Street, (212) 744-5577, through Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>Darren Almond /Janice Kerbel: 'The Impossible Landscape' Nothing is obvious in this handsome show of works by two London-based Conceptualists. The connection is that both make visible things that are in different ways impossible. Ms. Kerbel's elegantly abstracted designs for gardens in an office, a Laundromat and other unlikely places are meant to be imagined but never actually built. Mr. Almond's sumptuous, subtly eerie landscape photographs were shot at night using long exposures, making visible what would be invisible to the naked eye. The Horticultural Society of New York, 128 West 58th Street, (212) 757-0915, through May 5. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>Rico Gatson: 'African Fractals' Mr. Gatson's suave geometric paintings and sculptures of symbolically charged vernacular objects -- a whipping post in the form of a Christian cross with wrist-holes, for example -- feature African-style stripe patterns, creating a dialogue between utopian modernism and tragic social history. A video installation produces hypnotic patterns out of films of the pageantry surrounding the great boxing match between Muhammed Ali and George Foreman that took place in Zaire in 1974. Ronald Feldman, 31 Mercer Street, (212) 226-3232, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Joëlle Tuerlinckx: 'Drawing Inventory' A prominent Belgian Conceptualist presents a dry and oblique installation consisting of a large quantity of ordinary materials more or less related to the art of drawing. The Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, (212) 219-2166, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'When Artists Say We' This timely sociological experiment of a show features 17 artists or artist groups who were invited to create wall-diagrams or mini-exhibitions reflecting on the social networks out of which contemporary art emerges. Artists Space, 38 Green Street, (212) 226-3970, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>Tara Donovan Known for creating improbable accumulations of ordinary things, Ms. Donovan here has arranged three million plastic cups in stacks from ankle-high to five feet. They make a 50-by-60-foot rectangle on the floor, resembling a lumpy field of snow. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 929-7000, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NAN GOLDIN: 'CHASING A GHOST' A riveting if flawed three-screen video projection titled ''Sisters, Saints &amp; Sibyls'' hauntingly details the trauma that drives Ms. Goldin's invasive, yet oddly solitary photographs, as well as her lifelong battle with addiction: the suicide of her troubled older sister in 1965 at the age of 18. The piece mixes video, family snapshots and the artist's photographs, and is heightened by a sensitive selection of music that may almost do too much of the work. But its unalloyed honesty offers extreme evidence that most art begins in an attempt to heal a deep psychic wound. Matthew Marks Gallery, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200, through April 22. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Markus Hansen: 'Other People's Feelings Are Also My Own' In high-definition video projections of pairs of photographs, Mr. Hansen, a Paris-based German artist, dresses like and adopts the facial expression of the man, woman or child in the picture next to his. Whatever his project means to say about modern identity, it is absorbing to study how closely he is able to match other people's feelings, which range from carefree happiness to doleful anxiety. Virgil de Voldere, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 343-9694, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MARK LECKeY: 'DRUNKEN BAKERS' This cinematically gifted British artist raises his game with a stop-action animation made by simply shooting a raunchy, well-drawn comic strip for adults in close-up, turning its speech balloons into spoken dialogue and adding realistic sound effects. Shown in an increasingly grubby white-on-white cube, the work is elegantly efficient, funny and dark, and adds another twist to the convoluted history of appropriation art. GBE @ Passerby, 436 West 15th Street, (212) 627-5258, through April 22. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Eve K. Tremblay: 'Tales Without Grounds' A rising young Canadian photographer presents glossy staged photographs of people doing enigmatic things in and around a large facility for hydroponic lettuce cultivation. With their cinematically intense colors, Ms. Tremblay's pictures are like stills from a Tarkovskian science fiction movie. Buia, 541 West 23rd Street, (212) 366-9915, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'B-Side' This engaging group show includes Tim Spelios's beautifully made Surrealistic drum set in which the components are square rather than round; Matt Freedman's life-size sculpture of a boy with a lion's teeth and elephant eyes; Mary Carlson's crocheted works resembling splats of blood on the wall; Joyce Pensato's expressionistically painted clown face; Judith Page's ghoulish and viscous small portraits; Meredith Allen's funny and scary photographs of dogs; and a painting by Jim Torok that declares: ''You have no worries. Things are going well. Don't wake up.'' Sarah Bowen, 210 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 302-4517, through April 30. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Zoo Story' A clay gorilla by Daisy Youngblood, a bronze she-wolf by Kiki Smith, a flock of concrete sheep by Françoise-Xavier Lalanne and works about animals by more than 20 other artists, including John Baldessari, Katharina Fritsch, Ross Bleckner and Rebecca Horn, turn the first floor of this sleek, three-story private museum into a diverting menagerie. Fisher Landau Center for Art, 38-27 30th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-0727, through June 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>TIM BARBER A fresh, even touching reprise of the overused convention of walls papered with unframed photographs and small, cartoonish drawings, this show has been culled from Mr. Barber's Web site, tinyvices.com. With 250 people represented, it blurs the line between professional and amateur and introduces a savvy curatorial eye. Spencer Brownstone Gallery, 39 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 334-3455; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* BLUE GLAZE OF THE TANG This exceptional exhibition of Tang horses, court ladies, equestrian figures and grooms brings together rare examples of the unusually painterly sancai ware in which the traditional three-color glaze includes cobalt blue. Berwald Oriental Art, 5 East 57th Street, (212) 319-1519; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Marcel Broodthaers This reverential exhibition of just three works by a Belgian Conceptualist regarded as a Duchampian saint in some sectors of the art world includes a hat painted white and attached to a canvas painted black and white; a work called ''L'Erreur,'' consisting of 45 eggshells attached to a canvas labeled ''moules,'' the French word for mussels; and a set of canvases neatly inscribed with words relating to the composition and sale of paintings. Peter Freeman, 560 Broadway, near Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 966-5154; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>PHIL COLLINS In his third New York solo show, this British artist presents two video pieces in which interviews with Turkish reality show participants and a series of karaoke performances create a kind of ambient documentary about life, television and the pursuit of celebrity. While the show is a bit short on artistic nutrients, the cumulative effect says almost more than is bearable about the combination of delusion and oppression that fuels everyday life. Tanya Bonakdar Gallery, 521 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-4144; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Dan Fischer Velvety graphite drawings copied from Xerox copies of book and magazine images of well-known artists like Robert Smithson and Sol LeWitt and artworks like Jeff Koons's iconic ''Rabbit'' evoke and possibly satirize the reverence that some people feel for modern and contemporary art. Derek Eller, 615 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-6411; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Daniel Johnston: 'The Story of an Artist' The nearly 70 ballpoint and felt-tip drawings by this semi-outsider artist, rock musician and 2006 Whitney Biennial pick don't live up to the hype, but they are fun to look at. In a distracted but versatile faux-adolescent style, the Texas-based Mr. Johnston creates sweet and sometimes hair-raising cartoon improvisations on themes of love, sex, hope, despair and death. Clementine, 632 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 243-5937; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRANCIS PICABIA: 'WORKS ON PAPER, 1901-1951' Consistent with the predominantly linear, sometimes kitschy imagery of the artist's proto-postmodern transparency paintings, the 100 works on paper here reveal a lifelong involvement with drawing, marked by an indifference to notions of style, taste, consistency, skill or progress. It is both a challenge and a treat. Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Selective listings by critics of The New York Times of new and noteworthy cultural events in the New York metropolitan region this week. * denotes a highly recommended film, concert, show or exhibition.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Approximate running times are in parentheses. Theaters are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of current shows, additional listings, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/theater.</p>
        <p>Previews and Openings</p>
        <p>'LANDSCAPE OF THE BODY' Opens Sunday. John Guare, never satisfied with an overly tidy play, throws comedy, tragedy, satire and mystery into this cult drama, which first opened almost three decades ago. Lili Taylor and Sherie Rene Scott star (2:15). Signature Theater's Peter Norton Space, 555 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 244-7529.</p>
        <p>'SCREWMACHINE/EYECANDY OR: HOW I LEARNED TO STOP WORRYING AND LOVE BIG BOB' Opens Sunday. C. J. Hopkins's dark drama, a hit at the 2005 Edinburgh Festival, is about a game show host even more bizarre than Bob Barker (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200.</p>
        <p>'AWAKE AND SING!' Opens Monday. Lincoln Center Theater revives Clifford Odets's classic fist-shaking drama about a Jewish family struggling to survive during the Depression. The impressive cast includes Mark Ruffalo, Ben Gazzara and Zoë Wanamaker (2:30). Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE IMPORTANCE OF BEING EARNEST' Opens Tuesday. Closes May 14. Sir Peter Hall stages Oscar Wilde's indestructible comedy. Lynn Redgrave stars as Lady Bracknell (2:25). Brooklyn Academy of Music, Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, (718) 636-4100.</p>
        <p>'THREE DAYS OF RAIN' Opens Wednesday. Julia Roberts stars in this year's most closely watched star vehicle, a revival of the Richard Greenberg time-traveling drama about how we divide the legacy of our parents. Paul Rudd also stars (2:30). Bernard B. Jacobs Theater, 242 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE THREEPENNY OPERA' Opens Thursday. If any Broadway theater was made for a revival of Brecht's classic, it's the cabaret-style Studio 54, which is host to an intriguing cast that includes Alan Cumming and Cyndi Lauper (2:40). Studio 54, 254 West 54th Street, (212) 719-1300.</p>
        <p>'THE CAINE MUTINY COURT-MARTIAL' Previews start today. Opens May 7. Try not to think of Ross from ''Friends'' when you see David Schwimmer in this revival of Herman Wouk's adaptation of his Pulitzer Prizewinning novel about a lawyer who defends a Navy lieutenant accused of mutiny. Jerry Zaks directs (2:15). The Gerald Schoenfeld Theater, 236 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'THE DROWSY CHAPERONE' Opens May 1. This little-musical-that-could about an unscrupulous Broadway producer in the 1920's (some things never change) began at the Toronto Fringe Festival and now makes its unlikely premiere on the Great White Way (1:40). Marquis Theater, 1535 Broadway, at 45th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'FAITH HEALER' Previews start Tuesday. Opens May 4. Ralph Fiennes, Cherry Jones and Ian McDiarmid make up the dream cast of this revival of Brian Friel's classic collection of ''Rashomon''-like monologues about a man peddling salvation, his long-suffering wife and his manager (2:35). Booth Theater, 222 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'A FINE AND PRIVATE PLACE' Opens April 27. Redemption is a major theme of this musical fantasy adapted from a Peter S. Beagle novel about a recluse who lives in a Bronx cemetery (2:00). York Theater, St. Peter's Lutheran Church, Lexington Avenue at 54th Street, (212) 868-4444.</p>
        <p>'THE HISTORY BOYS' Previews start today. Opens April 23. Alan Bennett's acutely observed hit drama about English schoolboys arrives stateside with the best buzz of any new play this year. The National Theater's artistic director Nicholas Hytner directs (2:45). Broadhurst Theater, 235 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'HOT FEET' Previews start Thursday. Opens April 30. Earth, Wind and Fire get in on the jukebox musical trend with this new show about a woman who dreams of dancing on Broadway. Maurice Hines directs and choreographs (2:30). Hilton Theater, 213 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'LESTAT' Opens April 25. Elton John and Bernie Taupin have a good track record for making pop hits, but can they find success in the cursed genre of the vampire musical? Hugh Panaro stars (2:30). Palace Theater, 1564 Broadway, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE LIEUTENANT OF INISHMORE' Previews start Wednesday. Opens May 3. The Atlantic Theater Company's acclaimed production of Martin McDonagh's very bloody, exceptionally black comedy about Irish terrorism moves to Broadway (1:45). Lyceum Theater, 149 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'SHINING CITY' Previews start Thursday. Opens May 9. A guilt-ridden man tells his therapist that he has seen the ghost of his wife in Conor McPherson's new play, which received good reviews at the Royal Court in London. Brian F. O'Byrne, Martha Plimpton and Oliver Platt star (1:45). Biltmore Theater, 261 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>'TARZAN' Opens May 10. Phil Collins lends his invisible touch to the score of the latest Disney musical. David Henry Hwang wrote the book (2:30). Richard Rodgers Theater, 226 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>'THE WEDDING SINGER' Opens April 27. Stephen Lynch plays the goofy title character in this musical adaptation of the Adam Sandler film about leg warmers, Billy Idol and other artifacts from the 1980's. John Rando (''Urinetown'') directs (2:20). Al Hirschfeld Theater, 302 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>Broadway</p>
        <p>'BAREFOOT IN THE PARK' For a work that celebrates the liberating force of spontaneity, this revival of Neil Simon's 1963 comedy doesn't have one scene that feels organic, let alone impromptu. Directed by Scott Elliott, and starring Patrick Wilson and a miscast Amanda Peet as newlyweds in Greenwich Village, this ''Barefoot'' has the robotic gait of Frankenstein's monster (2:20). Cort Theater, 138 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Ben Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'BRIDGE &amp; TUNNEL' This delightful solo show, written and performed by Sarah Jones, is a sweet-spirited valentine to New York City, its polyglot citizens and the larger notion of an all-inclusive America. In 90 minutes of acutely observed portraiture gently tinted with humor, Ms. Jones plays more than a dozen men and women participating in an open-mike evening of poetry for immigrants (1:30). Helen Hayes Theater, 240 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Charles Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'THE COLOR PURPLE' So much plot, so many years, so many characters to cram into less than three hours. This beat-the-clock musical adaptation of Alice Walker's Pulitzer Prize-winning novel about Southern black women finding their inner warriors never slows down long enough for you to embrace it. LaChanze leads the vibrant, hard-working cast (2:40). Broadway Theater, 1681 Broadway, at 53rd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DIRTY ROTTEN SCOUNDRELS' The arrival of Jonathan Pryce and his eloquent eyebrows automatically makes this the season's most improved musical. With Mr. Pryce (who replaces the admirable but uneasy John Lithgow) playing the silken swindler to Norbert Leo Butz's vulgar grifter, it's as if a mismatched entry in a three-legged race had become an Olympic figure-skating pair (2:35). Imperial Theater, 249 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'FESTEN' An intensely staged, indifferently acted production of David Eldridge's adaptation of a 1998 Danish film about a grim family reunion, which was a big hit in London under the same director, Rufus Norris. While the mise en scène remains unsettlingly stark, the Broadway cast (which includes Michael Hayden, Julianna Margulies, Jeremy Sisto and Ali MacGraw) registers the tension and testiness of people suffering from a collective bad hair day. Music Box Theater, 239 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JERSEY BOYS' From grit to glamour with the Four Seasons, directed by the pop repackager Des McAnuff (''The Who's Tommy''). The real thrill of this shrink-wrapped bio-musical, for those who want something more than recycled chart toppers and a story line poured from a can, is watching the wonderful John Lloyd Young (as Frankie Valli) cross the line from exact impersonation into something far more compelling (2:30). August Wilson Theater, 245 West 52nd Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LIGHT IN THE PIAZZA' Love is a many-flavored thing, from sugary to sour, in Adam Guettel and Craig Lucas's encouragingly ambitious and discouragingly unfulfilled new musical. The show soars only in the sweetly bitter songs performed by the wonderful Victoria Clark, as an American abroad (2:15). Beaumont Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE ODD COUPLE' Odd is not the word for this couple. How could an adjective suggesting strangeness or surprise apply to a production so calculatedly devoted to the known, the cozy, the conventional? As the title characters in Neil Simon's 1965 comedy, directed as if to a metronome by Joe Mantello, Nathan Lane and Matthew Broderick reprise their star performances from ''The Producers,'' and it's not a natural fit. Don't even consider killing yourself because the show is already sold out (2:10). Brooks Atkinson Theater, 256 West 47th Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE PAJAMA GAME'  Sexual chemistry in a Broadway musical? Isn't that illegal now? If it were, then Harry Connick Jr. and Kelli O'Hara -- the white-hot stars of Kathleen Marshall's delicious revival of this 1954 musical -- would be looking at long jail terms. This intoxicating production, which features a charming supporting cast led by Michael McKean, allows grown-up audiences the rare chance to witness a bona fide adult love affair translated into hummable songs and sprightly dance (2:30). American Airlines Theater, 227 West 42nd Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RING OF FIRE'  The man in black turns sunshine yellow in a show that strings songs associated with Johnny Cash into a big, bright candy necklace of a musical revue, created and directed by Richard Maltby Jr. In the current bio-flick ''Walk the Line,'' Cash wrestles demons; ''Ring of Fire'' wrestles with a really bad case of the cutes (2:00). Ethel Barrymore Theater, 243 West 47th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'SWEENEY TODD' Sweet dreams, New York. This thrilling new revival of Stephen Sondheim and Hugh Wheeler's musical, with Michael Cerveris and Patti LuPone leading a cast of 10 who double as their own musicians, burrows into your thoughts like a campfire storyteller who knows what really scares you. The inventive director John Doyle aims his pared-down interpretation at the squirming child in everyone who wants to have his worst fears both confirmed and dispelled (2:30). Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>* 'THE 25TH ANNUAL PUTNAM COUNTY SPELLING BEE' The happy news for this happy-making little musical is that the move to larger quarters has dissipated none of its quirky charm. William Finn's score sounds plumper and more rewarding than it did on Off Broadway, providing a sprinkling of sugar to complement the sass in Rachel Sheinkin's zinger-filled book. The performances are flawless. Gold stars all around (1:45). Circle in the Square, 1633 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* 'WELL' Lisa Kron's sparkling autobiographical play about illness, integration and her mother (portrayed with majestic warmth and weariness by Jayne Houdyshell) helps restore the honor of that tarnished literary form, the memoir. Though it shows the strain of scaling up for Broadway, this singular work, which stars Ms. Kron as herself, opens windows of insight and emotion found in no other show (1:40). Longacre Theater, 220 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'BASED ON A TOTALLY TRUE STORY' A chatty, autobiographical comedy by Roberto Aguirre-Sacasa about a writer for comic books who moonlights as a screenwriter and playwright. Juggling his two jobs, the busy writer begins backsliding in his unofficial third, ''being a loving, giving, emotionally available boyfriend.'' Minor-key angst ensues in this perky two hours of comic navel-gazing (2:00). Manhattan Theater Club at City Center Stage II, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'DEFIANCE' The second in John Patrick Shanley's cycle of morality plays that began with ''Doubt,'' this ambitious tale of racial relations and the military mindset on a North Carolina marine base feels both overcrowded and oddly diffuse. If ''Doubt'' has an elegant and energy-efficient sprinter's gait, ''Defiance'' progresses with a flustered air of distraction. The excellent Margaret Colin, as an officer's wife, provides a welcome shot of credibility (1:30). Manhattan Theater Club, Theater 1, 131 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1212. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'ENTERTAINING MR. SLOANE' Miscasting is the mother of invention. Or so it proves to be for Jan Maxwell, who re-tailors an ill-fitting part and makes it as snug as a glove in this underpowered revival of Joe Orton's scandalous 1964 comedy. Scott Ellis's production of Orton's great farce of sexual hypocrisy, which also stars Alec Baldwin, is breezy, often funny and rarely convincing. (2:00). Laura Pels Theater at the Harold and Miriam Steinberg Center for Theater, 111 West 46th Street, (212) 719-1300. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'GEORGE M. COHAN TONIGHT!'  The all-singing, all-dancing Jon Peterson summons the spirit of this legendary Broadway entertainer in this engaging one-man musical, devised and directed by Chip Deffaa (1:30). Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. (George Hunka)</p>
        <p>'GREY GARDENS'  As the socialite in limbo called ''Little'' Edie Beale, Christine Ebersole gives one of the most gorgeous performances ever to grace a musical. Unfortunately, she's a pearl of incalculable price in a show that is mostly costume jewelry. Adapted from the Maysles brothers' 1975 cult documentary movie, a camp favorite, and directed by Michael Greif, with the excellent Mary Louise Wilson as Edie's bedridden mother (2:40). Playwrights Horizons, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'JACQUES BREL IS ALIVE AND WELL AND LIVING IN PARIS' A powerfully sung revival of the 1968 revue, presented with affectionate nostalgia by the director Gordon Greenberg. As in the original, two men (Robert Cuccioli and Rodney Hicks) and two women (Natascia Diaz and Gay Marshall) perform a wide selection of Brel's plaintive ballads and stirring anthems. Ms. Marshall's captivating performance of ''Ne Me Quitte Pas,'' sung in the original French and with heart-stirring transparency, represents Brel at his best. (2:00). Zipper Theater, 336 West 37th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'LOS BIG NAMES'  In the lesbian comic Marga Gomez's friendly new solo show, she measures out affection and mockery in equal doses as she recalls her parents, Willy and Margarita, a comic and a dancer who lived a splashy life on a small scale in the circumscribed world of New York Latino culture in the 1960's. Ms. Gomez pairs stories of their performing careers with comic tales of her own struggles to pursue success in the entertainment industry. A sendup of the movie ''Sphere'' is particularly delicious (1:30). 47th Street Theater, 304 West 47th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'MACRUNE'S GUEVARA' The Young Mirror arm of Mirror Repertory revives John Spurling's odd 1969 play about an artist who left behind a wall full of drawings of Che Guevara and the man who saw something profound in them. Parts of the play read today like a funny sendup of art critics who see too much brilliance in outsider-art gibberish; other parts seem a bit like gibberish of their own (2:15). St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 868-4444. (Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'RED LIGHT WINTER'  A frank, occasionally graphic story of erotic fixation and the havoc it can wreak on sensitive types. Written and directed by Adam Rapp, this play is both a doomy romantic drama and a morbid comedy about the anxieties of male friendship. Although somewhat contrived, it features a lovely performance by Christopher Denham as a lonely soul starved for intimacy (2:25). Barrow Street Theater, 27 Barrow Street, West Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'A SAFE HARBOR FOR ELIZABETH BISHOP' The life of a great poet becomes the stuff of stale prose in this one-woman bio-play by Marta Goes, starring Amy Irving (1:30). 59E59 Theaters, 59 East 59th Street, (212) 279-4200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SANDRA BERNHARD: EVERYTHING BAD AND BEAUTIFUL' Sandra Bernhard was a proverbial rock star long before headline-making folks in even the most prosaic walks of life were being referred to as such. Her new show, a collection of songs interspersed with musings on her life and on public figures ranging from Britney Spears to Condoleezza Rice, is casual to the point of being offhand. That said, it's invigorating to be in the presence of a true original (2:00). Daryl Roth Theater, 101 East 15th Street, at Union Square, East Village, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'SHOW PEOPLE'  Paul Weitz's eyebrow-pencil-thin comedy about a man who hires actors to impersonate his family feels like one long, occasionally amusing party game whose players don't know when to call it a night. The excellent four-member cast, led by Debra Monk and directed by Peter Askin, finds charm and energy amid the vaporous bait-and-switch plot reversals (2:00). Second Stage Theater, 307 West 43rd Street, Clinton, (212) 246-4422. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>* '[TITLE OF SHOW]' Jeff Bowen and Hunter Bell are the authors, stars and subject matter of this delectable new musical about its own making. The self-consciousness is tempered by a wonderful cast performing with the innocence of kids cavorting in a sandbox. It's a worthy postmodern homage to classic backstage musicals, and an absolute must for show queens (1:30). Vineyard Theater, 108 East 15th Street, Flatiron district, (212) 353-0303. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'TRYST' A suspense drama of a distinctly old-fashioned stamp about the romance between a handsome cad (Maxwell Caulfield) and a lonely spinster (Amelia Campbell). Will the wily predator seduce and abandon the mousy milliner? Karoline Leach's play springs a few twists that lack psychological credibility but keep the plot on the boil (2:00). Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Isherwood)</p>
        <p>Off Off Broadway</p>
        <p>'THE PRIVATE LIFE OF THE MASTER RACE' Bertolt Brecht's middle-period classic in a robust new translation by Binyamin Shalom and a spare and powerful production by the Roust Theater Company, directed by James Phillip Gates (2:45). Walkerspace, 46 Walker Street, SoHo, (212) 868-4444. (Hunka)</p>
        <p>Long-Running Shows</p>
        <p>* 'ALTAR BOYZ' This sweetly satirical show about a Christian pop group made up of five potential Teen People cover boys is an enjoyable, silly diversion (1:30). New World Stages, 340 West 50th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200.(Isherwood)</p>
        <p>'AVENUE Q' R-rated puppets give lively life lessons (2:10). Golden, 252 West 45th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'BEAUTY AND THE BEAST' Cartoon made flesh, sort of (2:30). Lunt-Fontanne Theater, 205 West 46th Street, (212) 307-4747. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'CHICAGO' Irrefutable proof that crime pays (2:25). Ambassador Theater, 219 West 49th Street, (212) 239-6200.(Brantley)</p>
        <p>'DOUBT, A PARABLE' (Pulitzer Prize, Best Play 2005, and Tony Award, Best Play 2005) John Patrick Shanley makes subversive use of musty conventions in the clash between the head of a parochial school and the young priest who may or may not be too fond of the boys in his charge (1:30). Walter Kerr Theater, 219 West 48th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'HAIRSPRAY' Fizzy pop, cute kids, large man in a housedress (2:30). Neil Simon Theater, 250 West 52nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE LION KING' Disney on safari, where the big bucks roam (2:45). New Amsterdam Theater, 214 West 42nd Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'MAMMA MIA!' The jukebox that devoured Broadway (2:20). Cadillac Winter Garden Theater, 1634 Broadway, at 50th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PHANTOM OF THE OPERA' Who was that masked man, anyway? (2:30). Majestic Theater, 247 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'THE PRODUCERS' The ne plus ultra of showbiz scams (2:45). St. James Theater, 246 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'RENT' East Village angst and love songs to die for (2:45). Nederlander Theater, 208 West 41st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'SPAMALOT' (Tony Award, Best Musical 2005) This staged re-creation of the mock-medieval movie ''Monty Python and the Holy Grail'' is basically a singing scrapbook for Python fans. Such a good time is being had by so many people that this fitful, eager celebration of inanity and irreverence has found a large and lucrative audience (2:20). Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, (212) 239-6200. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>'WICKED' Oz revisited, with political corrections (2:45). Gershwin Theater, 222 West 51st Street, (212) 307-4100. (Brantley)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>'THE CATARACT' Though it begins promisingly -- a funny Midwestern noir in the style of the Coen brothers -- Lisa D'Amour's play about Southern drifters unsettling upright Minnesotans soon loses its balance, swamped by a torrent of magical realism and psychobabble (2:15). Women's Project/Julia Miles Theater, 424 West 55th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200; closing tomorrow. (Miriam Horn)</p>
        <p>'CONFESSIONS OF A MORMON BOY' Steven Fales, a sixth-generation Mormon, describes leaving his family and becoming a gay escort in this fairly conventional, although admittedly compelling, piece of confessional theater (1:30). SoHo Playhouse, 15 Vandam Street, between Avenue of the Americas and Varick Street, (212) 691-1555; closing Sunday. (Zinoman)</p>
        <p>'PEN'  David Marshall Grant's sometimes preachy new three-character play is about an unhappy Long Island family in 1969. J. Smith-Cameron is fascinating to watch as she exposes the anguish behind the tough, angry exterior of the wheelchair-bound mother; Dan McCabe is uneven but believable as the troubled teenage son who wants to get away from her; and Reed Birney is less persuasive as the ex-husband who has already left. The title object is a gift from the author to himself: it allows something impossible to happen (2:15). Playwrights Horizons, Peter Jay Sharp Theater, 416 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing Sunday. (Andrea Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'TRANSATLANTIC LIAISON'  A play fashioned from Simone de Beauvoir's love letters to the American novelist Nelson Algren and scenes from her novel ''The Mandarins'' (which tells the story of their affair). Wonderful performances by Elizabeth Rothan as de Beauvoir in love, and Matthew S. Tompkins as the emotional Algren (1:30). Harold Clurman Theater on Theater Row, 412 West 42nd Street, Clinton, (212) 279-4200; closing tomorrow. (Moore)</p>
        <p>Movies</p>
        <p>Ratings and running times are in parentheses; foreign films have English subtitles. Full reviews of all current releases, movie trailers, show times and tickets: nytimes.com/movies.</p>
        <p>'AQUAMARINE' (PG, 109 minutes) In this sweet comedy for the crowd that has outgrown ''The Little Mermaid,'' two likable pals (Emma Roberts and Joanna Levesque, a k a the singer JoJo) try to help a mermaid (Sara Paxton) find love and learn how to use her feet properly.(Neil Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'ATL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) A couple of rap stars make respectable starts on acting careers in this tale of black teenagers in Atlanta, despite a script marred by clichés and predictability. Tip Harris -- the rapper T. I. -- is intriguing as a young man who takes on the responsibility of raising his younger brother when their parents are killed, and Antwan Andre Patton -- Big Boi from OutKast -- makes a terrific drug lord. ( Genzlinger)</p>
        <p>'BASIC INSTINCT 2' (R, 120 minutes) A joyless calculation, starring Sharon Stone and directed by Michael Caton-Jones, that is also a prime object lesson in the degradation that can face Hollywood actresses, especially those over 40. (Manohla Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'THE BEAUTY ACADEMY OF KABUL' (No rating, 74 minutes, in English and Dari) In the summer of 2004, a group of volunteer American hairstylists arrived in Kabul to open a school. In ''The Beauty Academy of Kabul,'' the director Liz Mermin documents the hilarious, moving and sometimes fractious meeting of diametrically different cultures, one having suffered unimaginable horrors and the other believing a good perm is the answer to everything. (Jeannette Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'CAPOTE' (R, 114 minutes) Philip Seymour Hoffman's portrayal of Truman Capote is a tour de force of psychological insight. (Mr. Hoffman won the Academy Award for best actor.) Following the novelist as he works on the magazine assignment that will become ''In Cold Blood,'' the film raises intriguing questions about the ethics of writing. (A. O. Scott)</p>
        <p>'CRASH' (Academy Award, Best Picture) (R, 107 minutes) A gaggle of Los Angeles residents from various economic and ethnic backgrounds collide, sometimes literally, within an extremely hectic 36 hours. Well intentioned, impressively acted but ultimately a speechy, ponderous melodrama of liberal superstition masquerading as realism. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'DAVE CHAPPELLE'S BLOCK PARTY' (R, 103 minutes) The setup is blissfully simple: a free block party on a dead-end street in Bed-Stuy, with a lineup of musicians, some of whom, like Kanye West and Mos Def, have put in appearances on ''Chappelle's Show.'' The nominal idea, Mr. Chappelle explains on camera, was ''the concert I've always wanted to see.'' The result, which ping-pongs between Brooklyn and Mr. Chappelle's hometown in Ohio, is a tantalizing sketch-portrait of the artist amid an outpouring of hard beats and soul. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'DEVIL AND DANIEL JOHNSTON' (PG-13, 110 minutes) The romantic cliché that all artists are a little bit mad is put through its paces (if never seriously questioned) in this documentary about Daniel Johnston, a mentally ill songwriter whom Kurt Cobain, the lead singer for Nirvana, once called the greatest living. Jeff Feuerzeig, who won the best director award at the 2005 Sundance Festival, cobbles together a moving portrait of the artist as his own ghost, using a wealth of material provided by Mr. Johnston, from home movies to audiocassette diaries to dozens of original, and often heartbreakingly beautiful, songs. (Dana Stevens)</p>
        <p>* 'DON'T COME KNOCKING' (R, 122 minutes) The visually majestic but dramatically inert reunion of Sam Shepard (who stars) and the director Wim Wenders, 22 years after their auspicious collaboration on ''Paris, Texas,'' might be described as a magnificent ruin. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>* 'DRAWING RESTRAINT 9' (No rating, 135 minutes) Most of this stately film of few words, conceived and directed by the artist Matthew Barney, who co-stars with his wife, Bjork, takes place on a Japanese whaling ship afloat in Nagasaki Bay. Steeped not only in Japanese seafaring lore but also in centuries-old traditions of Japanese ritual, the film could be described as Mr. Barney's ''Moby-Dick.'' (Holden)</p>
        <p>'ICE AGE: THE MELTDOWN' (PG, 93 minutes) Creative exhaustion haunts ''Ice Age: The Meltdown,'' as the characters from 2002's ''Ice Age'' face global warming and the submersion of their valley. While the animals head for safety in a giant, arklike boat, the director, Carlos Saldanha, indulges in biblical imagery and bad science. Over all, a flat and uninspired follow-up to a vastly superior movie. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>* 'INSIDE MAN' (R, 128 minutes) The latest from Spike Lee takes a familiar setup -- in this case, a Wall Street bank heist that mutates into a hostage crisis -- and twists it ever so slightly and nicely. Among the film's most sustained pleasures are its holy trinity -- Denzel Washington, Clive Owen and Jodie Foster -- and the best lineup of pusses and mugs outside ''The Sopranos.'' (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'LA MUJER DE MI HERMANO' (R, 93 minutes, in Spanish) Zoë (Bárbara Mori) is a gorgeous, vapid wife who longs for children, but her distant spouse (Christian Meier) makes love only on Saturdays. Enter the rebellious brother-in-law (Manolo Cardona), a smoldering artist whose schedule is less regimented. Bubbling with incest, adultery, religion and homosexuality, ''La Mujer de Mi Hermano'' is an overheated telenovela that considers procreation more important than honesty, and what we want more important than who we are. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LOOK BOTH WAYS' (PG-13, 100 minutes) Written and directed by the Australian animator Sarah Watt, ''Look Both Ways'' follows a group of disparate and desperate characters over the course of one of the most depressing weekends in movie history. The principal sufferers are Meryl (Justine Clarke), a morbid illustrator, and Nick (William McInnes), a terminally ill photographer, who discover that a mutual fixation on catastrophe can be quite the aphrodisiac. Bogged down by stylistic gimmickry, ''Look Both Ways'' aims for existential drama but succeeds only in reminding us that misery loves company. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'LUCKY NUMBER SLEVIN' (R, 110 minutes) This star-studded jigsaw puzzle of revenge and mistaken identity thinks that it's terribly smart, although it amounts to an empty, self-satisfied imitation of ''Pulp Fiction'' that reputable actors like Morgan Freeman and Ben Kingsley can't salvage. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'MARILYN HOTCHKISS BALLROOM DANCING AND CHARM SCHOOL' (PG-13, 103 minutes) John Goodman plays a dying crash victim on his way to a 40-year-old appointment, and Robert Carlyle is the widowed baker entrusted with keeping it. Instead, he meets Marisa Tomei, who teaches him to dance and, more important, throw away his wife's ashes. Toggling back and forth between past and present, ''Marilyn Hotchkiss Ballroom Dancing and Charm School'' is a soggy, endless wallow in nostalgia and the healing power of very bad dancing. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'ON A CLEAR DAY' (PG-13, 99 minutes) Set in and around the dockyards of Glasgow, ''On a Clear Day'' follows Frank (the great Peter Mullan), a laid-off shipbuilder who decides to fix his life by swimming the English Channel. Despite a familiar crop of lovable eccentrics and predictably inspirational thrust, the movie balances the sentimentality with excellent performances and a healthy dose of working-class vulnerability. (Catsoulis)</p>
        <p>'SHE'S THE MAN' (PG-13, 105 minutes) ''Twelfth Night'' is recast as a hysterically peppy romantic comedy about a she-jock penetrating the boys' soccer team. Because girls can do anything boys can do, although their ultimate ambition is to put on a nice dress and go steady with a stupid jock. (Nathan Lee)</p>
        <p>'16 BLOCKS' (PG-13, 105 minutes) If Richard Donner's presence suggests that his new action flick, ''16 Blocks,'' is a throwback to the 1980's, so does one of the names holding pride of place above the title, Bruce Willis. Mr. Willis has always been an acquired taste, but for those who did acquire that taste, it's a pleasure to see him doing what comes naturally. Which means holding a gun and fending off bad guys with as few words as possible. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'SISTERS IN LAW' (No rating, 108 minutes, in English and pidgin) Grass-roots feminism thrives in a Cameroon village, thanks to the pair of warm-hearted, tough-minded women of law profiled in this excellent verité documentary. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'SLITHER' (R, 96 minutes) A horror film about an extraterrestrial monster with a hunger for flesh that slaloms from yucks to yuks, slip-sliding from horror to comedy and back again on its gore-slicked foundation. The writer and director James Gunn knows his icky, scary stuff. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TAKE THE LEAD' (PG-13, 108 minutes) Hip-hop and ballroom dancing styles fuse in a South Bronx high school at which a dance teacher, Antonio Banderas, turns gawky ducklings into gliding swans. It's sloppy but mildly endearing. (Holden)</p>
        <p>'Thank You for Smoking' (R, 92 minutes) The director Jason Reitman has made a glib and funny movie from Christopher Buckley's glib and funny novel about a Big Tobacco lobbyist, but the real attraction here is the hard-working star, Aaron Eckhart. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'TORO NEGRO' (No rating, 87 minutes, in Spanish) A disturbed young matador stabs animals, beats his wife and drinks himself to the edge of oblivion in this harrowing, deeply suspect documentary set in rural Mexico. (Lee)</p>
        <p>* 'TRISTRAM SHANDY: A COCK AND BULL STORY' (R, 91 minutes) Michael Winterbottom both confirms and refutes the assumption that Laurence Sterne's 18th-century masterpiece of digression could never be made into a movie by making a movie about the making of such a movie. Steve Coogan is wonderful as Tristram, Tristram's father and himself, though Rob Brydon steals more than a few of Mr. Coogan's scenes. (Scott)</p>
        <p>'Tsotsi' (R, 94 minutes) (Academy Award winner for best foreign film.) Written and directed by Gavin Hood, from a novel by Athol Fugard, this South African film centers on a 19-year-old thug who steals a baby and finds redemption. You don't have to read crystal balls to see into Tsotsi's future; you just need to have watched a couple of Hollywood chestnuts. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>'V for Vendetta' (R, 131 minutes) James McTeigue directs this D-for-dumb future-shock story about a masked avenger (Hugo Weaving) and his pipsqueak sidekick (Natalie Portman) at war against a totalitarian British regime. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>* 'NEIL YOUNG: HEART OF GOLD' (PG, 103 minutes) Filled with country memories, bluesy regret and familiar and piercing sentiment, Jonathan Demme's concert film sounds like quintessential Neil Young, which, depending on your home catalog, will be either an enormous turn-on or a turnoff. (Dargis)</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>AGAINST THE TIDE (Through Sunday) The Japan Society's spring film series concludes this weekend. 333 East 47th Street, Manhattan, (212) 715-1258; $10. (Anita Gates)</p>
        <p>PRIX JEAN VIGO (Through Dec. 30) The Museum of Modern Art is honoring Vigo (1905-34), the French filmmaker, with a series of 41 films from directors who have won the prize that bears his name. ''Black Girl'' (1965), Ousmane Sembène's cultural-identity drama about a young African woman living with a French family, will be shown on Thursday. 11 West 53rd Street, (212) 708-9400; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>RECENT FILMS FROM DENMARK (Through April 22) Scandinavia House continues its overall Scandinavian film series tomorrow. 58 Park Avenue, between 37th and 38th Streets, (212) 879-9779; $8. (Gates)</p>
        <p>THE COMPLETE KIESLOWSKI : A ROAD MAP OF THE SOUL (Through April 23) To commemorate the 10th anniversary of Krzysztof Kieslowski's death, the Film Society of Lincoln Center, the Polish National Film Archive and the Polish Cultural Institute in New York are presenting a retrospective of his work. This weekend's films include ''The Double Life of Veronique'' (1991), and all 10 parts of Kieslowski's 1989 Decalogue, inspired by the Ten Commandments. Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5600; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>SHELLEY WINTERS VS. THE WATER (Through April 25) BAMcinématek is honoring Winters, who died in January at 83, with screenings of four of her best-known films. BAM Rose Cinemas, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>ANNA MAY WONG (Through Sunday) Wong, the first Chinese-American movie star, would have turned 100 last year. (She died in 1961.) The Museum of the Moving Image's seven-week retrospective of her work concludes this weekend. 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens, (718) 784-0077; $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>village voice best of 2005 (Through April 26) This annual series, which opened yesterday, continues this weekend. BAM Rose Cinemas (see above); $10. (Gates)</p>
        <p>Pop</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>ACID MOTHERS TEMPLE (Wednesday) The manic Japanese guitarist Kawabata Makoto leads his long-running band in hard-rocking psychedelic explorations rooted in riffy dirt-rock. 8 p.m., Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006; $15. (Laura Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ALKALINE TRIO, AGAINST ME (Monday) The drummer and bandleader Mike Skiba continues to add 80's brood-pop wrinkles to the straightforward pop punk that made his band's reputation when it began almost a decade ago. 7:30 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>B. B. KING (Monday through Wednesday) The great bluesman B. B. King and his latest guitar called Lucille can, on a good night, summon all the tribulation and joy and resilience of the blues. This show was moved from May 31, and those tickets will be honored. 8 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; (sold out). (Jon Pareles)</p>
        <p>BRAIN SURGEONS NYC (Monday) With Blue Oyster Cult, Albert Bouchard inspired a generation of metal and punk bands. His current band also features the former Dictator Ross the Boss and the veteran rock critic Deborah Frost. 8 p.m., Northsix, 66 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 599-5103; $12. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>CHAMILLIONAIRE, LIL' FLIP (Sunday) The Houston rapper Chamillionaire had been lending rhymes to regional records for years. His turns of phrase establish him as an MC, but by singing his own hooks in a deep authoritative voice, he stands out among his peers. Lil' Flip is another Houston luminary with a sing-song flow and class-clown snaps. 9 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, (212) 997-4144; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ABDULLAH CHHADEH (Wednesday) Abdullah Chhadeh plays the qanun (an 81-string zitherlike instrument) with his ensemble Nara. The group uses jazz double bass and Western percussion, as well as the nay (reed flute), darbuka (hand drum) and Arabic accordion. 7:30 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 239-6200; $20. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>CLAP YOUR HANDS SAY YEAH (Tonight and tomorrow) The Brooklyn quintet Clap Your Hands Say Yeah recalls the shamanic whine and thrum of the mid-1990's lo-fi rockers Neutral Milk Hotel, and sometimes the slippery paranoid quirk of the Talking Heads. 8:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE COUP (Tomorrow) The funky, political Coup took flak in 2001 for a pre-9/11 album cover featuring exploding twin towers. But the group's main man, Boots Riley, has lost none of the oppositional fervor. 10 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South, Greenwich Village, (212) 992-8484; $25 general admission; $15 for New York University faculty and staff; $7 for N.Y.U. students. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LILY CUSHMAN CULHANE, THE REPUTATION (Monday) Lily Cushman Culhane sings dry, breathy torch songs over rattletrap grooves that recall Tom Waits's early-90's albums. Elizabeth Elmore of the Reputation writes punchy melodic rock anthems about tricky romance. 8 p.m., Mercury Lounge, 217 East Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700; $8. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ELBOW, THE CLOUD ROOM (Thursday) Elbow is one of many British bands that have emerged in the wake of Radiohead and Spiritualized, mixing cinematic sonic drift with pointillist emotional disclosure. The new-wave-influenced naïf rockers the Cloud Room garnered wild, though deeply underground, buzz for their best song, ''Hey Hey Now,'' which never broke into the larger indie-pop consciousness. 7 p.m., Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 353-1600; $2o in advance, $23 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THE FIERY FURNACES (Wednesday) This brother-and-sister art-rock duo's music cuts melodies with carnivalesque keyboard vamps and digressive skronk. 7:30 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; $20. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FIGURINES (Wednesday) The Danish rock band Figurines distinguishes itself from the current glut of post-punk formalists by aping instead the frustrated eeriness of Northwestern indie-rock bands like Modest Mouse. The vocalist Christian Hjelm balances art-song archness and lonely busker frailty. 9 p.m., Rothko, 116 Suffolk Street, Lower East Side, (212) 475-7088; $10. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>FRANZ FERDINAND, DEATH CAB FOR CUTIE (Tonight) At the vanguard of the post-post-punk trend, the poker-faced Franz Ferdinand plays herky-jerky party music. Death Cab is a decorous diarist-rock band whose sound gets added alternative-rock heft on the recent ''Plans'' (Atlantic). 6, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, (212) 564-4882; $40. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JAMMY AWARDS (Thursday) This is the night when the jam band world proves that its vision extends beyond Grateful Dead approximations. This year's performers include a grab bag of classic rock vets (Little Feat, Peter Frampton); legends of quick-fingered instrumentalism (Bela Fleck, Joe Satriani); and beat scientists (Mad Professor, DJ Logic), as well as the Senegalese great Baaba Maal, the august folkie Richie Havens and the road-tested heroes of the jam scene, Blues Traveler. 8 p.m., Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741; $39.50 to $54.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>SHOOTER JENNINGS, DIAMOND NIGHTS (Tuesday) Mr. Jennings follows the outlaw tradition of his legendary father, Waylon, and shares his rough-hewn singing style. But while the younger Mr. Jennings's music is decidedly country, he adds his own classic-rock-informed sensibility. The Diamond Nights of New York play 70's hard-rock with a dollop of new wave. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $17.50 in advance, $18 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ROBERT EARL KEEN (Tomorrow) This gravel-voiced Texas songwriter, a contemporary of Lyle Lovett and Nanci Griffith, is a storyteller who can unfurl a sad-luck tale with genuine heart and a sardonic twinge. Webster Hall, 125 East 11th Street, East Village, (212) 353-1600; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>R. KELLY (Tuesday) Few artists have turned their personal travails into unique pop music like R. Kelly, whose multi-part R&amp;B saga ''Trapped in the Closet'' is a singularly strange psychosexual ramble. He is billing himself as Mr. Showbiz for this ''Light It Up'' tour, presenting a parade of hits that downplays any voyeuristic weirdness without skimping on the up-front sexuality that has made him famous and dangerous. 8 p.m., Radio City Music Hall, (212) 247-4777; $39.50 to $89.50. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TALIB KWELI (Tomorrow) The brainy rapper Talib Kweli's agile attack still lacks Jay-Z's precision, 50 Cent's swagger and Nas's anguish. But his thrust can be raw and his struggle beautiful when he laments things like Lauryn Hill's absence from the music scene. 11 p.m., B. B. King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144; $25 in advance, $30 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>LADYTRON (Tomorrow) Influenced by 1980's synth-pop's great songwriting as well as its style, Ladytron arrived before New York's fleeting electroclash moment, and it has survived it, playing dark, droning dance-pop cut with a romantic sense of alienation. 9 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; (sold out). (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ALAN LICHT AND THE PRIX (Monday) For this get-together of indie-rock vets, the experimental guitarist Alan Licht will be backed by the guitarist Chris Brokaw (formerly of Come and Codeine), the bassist Doug McCombs (of Tortoise), and the drummer Elliott Dicks. 8 p.m., Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503; $8. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>THOMAS MAPFUMO AND THE BLACKS UNLIMITED (Tuesday) A musical pioneer with a rebel's courage, Thomas Mapfumo made music for the revolutionaries who unseated the white-ruled government from what was Rhodesia and is now Zimbabwe. The music transferred the brisk patterns of traditional thumb-piano music to guitar; the words sometimes sent coded messages. 9 and 11:30 p.m., S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940; $20 in advance, $22 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>JOAN OSBORNE (Tuesday) Best known for her hit song musing on the Almighty, ''One of Us,'' Joan Osborne has since focused on the blues and R&amp;B tradition in which she got her start. Expect lots of classic covers and possibly a display of the Qawwali singing she learned from Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan. 8 p.m., Coda, 34 East 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 685-3434; $25. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>ROBERT POLLARD, RICHARD DAVIES (Thursday) The prolific recording maven Robert Pollard may have disbanded his much beloved band, Guided by Voices, but he continues to record and perform with undeterred gusto. The Australian singer-songwriter Richard Davies has pursued a solo career after playing in the baroque-pop outfit the Cardinal. 8 p.m., Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800; $20 in advance, $25 at the door. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Sufi music with AHMET OZHAN AND THE WHIRLING DERVISHES (Tomorrow) Accompanied by the ritual Sufi dancers of the Istanbul Mevlevi Order, the singer Ahmet Ozhan will perform songs in the classical mystic tradition. 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $20 to $100. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>TV ON THE RADIO (Tuesday) TV on the Radio tops its jittery rhythms and paranoid guitars with the haunting vocal yelps of Tunde Adebimpe and Kyp Malone. They are soon to release a major-label debut, reportedly even more out-there than their indie releases. 8 p.m., Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111; (sold out) . (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>DAR WILLIAMS (Tuesday) This adorable coffeehouse singer-songwriter augments her sweet voice with that rare quality of seeming like a real person. 7 p.m., Avalon, 662 Avenue of the Americas, at 20th Street, Chelsea, (212) 807-7780 or Ticketmaster.com or (212) 307-7171; $30. (Sinagra)</p>
        <p>Cabaret</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent cabaret shows: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>* KAREN AKERS (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) The regal cabaret singer and the brassy songs of Kander and Ebb that she is offering in her new show may not be an obvious fit. But Ms. Akers locates the heart inside the brass and sass. 9 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 11:30, Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $60 cover, with a $20 minimum; $60 prix fixe dinner required on Thursdays and at the early shows tonight and tomorrow. (Stephen Holden)</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL (Sunday) Even when swinging out, this Lady of a Thousand Songs remains an impressionist with special affinities for Thelonious Monk and bossa nova. 2 p.m., Algonquin Hotel, Oak Room, 59 West 44th Street, Manhattan, (212) 419-9331; $75, including brunch at noon. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BLOSSOM DEARIE (Tomorrow and Sunday) To watch this singer and pianist is to appreciate the power of a carefully deployed pop-jazz minimalism combined with a highly discriminating taste in songs. The songs date from all periods of a career remarkable for its longevity and for Ms. Dearie's stubborn independence and sly wit. Tomorrow at 7 p.m., Sunday at 6:15 p.m., Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133; $25, with a $15 minimum, or $54.50 for a dinner-and-show package. (Holden)</p>
        <p>BABY JANE DEXTER (Tomorrow) This booming pop-blues contralto may not be demure, but she is tasteful in a smart, regal, big-mama way, and she is astute in her choices of often obscure soul, blues and jazz songs that play to her contradictory mixture of the lusty and the philosophical. 7 p.m., Helen's, 169 Eighth Avenue, near 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-0609; $20, with a $15 minimum. (Holden)</p>
        <p>* MARY CLEERE HARAN  (Tonight and tomorrow, and Tuesday through Thursday) A wonderful no-frills singer with a sophisticated wit, Ms. Haran has a remarkable talent for simultaneously interpreting standards in the spirit in which they were written and looking at them through 21st-century eyes. 8:45 p.m., with additional shows tonight and tomorrow night at 10:45, Café Carlyle, at the Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, Manhattan, (212) 744-1600; $60 tonight and tomorrow; $50 Tuesday through Thursday. (Holden)</p>
        <p>Jazz</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent jazz concerts: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>DARCY JAMES ARGUE'S SECRET SOCIETY (Tuesday) As the name implies, this 18-piece big band is calibrated for maximum intrigue, with a sound that suggests Steve Reich minimalism as well as orchestral jazz in the lineage of Bob Brookmeyer (one of Mr. Argue's mentors). The ranks of the band include such hale improvisers as the trumpeter Ingrid Jensen, the tenor saxophonist Donny McCaslin and the trombonist Alan Ferber. 10 p.m., Bowery Poetry Club, 308 Bowery, between Houston and Bleecker Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 614-0505; cover, $12. (Nate Chinen)</p>
        <p>OMER AVITAL GROUP (Thursday) The bassist Omer Avital, a staple of the West Village club Smalls during its premillennial first run, is back after a spell in his native Israel, with new music and a new stable of bands. This one consists of Joel Frahm on tenor saxophone, Avishai Cohen on trumpet, Omer Klein on piano and Greg Hutchinson on drums. 10 p.m. and midnight, Smalls, 183 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 675-7369; cover, $20; includes two drinks. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>TIM BERNE'S BIG SATAN (Wednesday) Mr. Berne, a vigorous and exploratory alto saxophonist, makes interplay the driving force in his band with the guitarist Marc Ducret and the drummer Tom Rainey. This one-night stand kicks off a month of touring. 10 p.m., 55 Bar, 55 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 929-9883; cover, $10. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RON CARTER/KARRIN ALLYSON (Tuesday through April 23) Mr. Carter, an august and influential bassist, has had mixed success as a bandleader; his best efforts usually involve the articulate pianist Stephen Scott, who joins him in this quartet. Ms. Allyson comes bearing a new album, ''Footprints'' (Concord), which delves into Jon Hendricks-style vocalese; as on the album, she digs in here with a strong ensemble spearheaded by the pianist Bruce Barth. 8 and 10:30 p.m., Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, West Village, (212) 475-8592; cover, $35 at tables, $20 at the bar, with a $5 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LARRY CORYELL, VICTOR BAILEY AND LENNY WHITE (Through Sunday) Their recent album, ''Electric'' (Chesky), works hard to deserve the moniker; it relies equally on Mr. Coryell's searing guitar, Mr. Bailey's electric bass and Mr. White's earthy drumming. 8 and 10 p.m., with 11:30 sets tonight and tomorrow night. Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>STEVE DAVIS QUINTET (Tonight and tomorrow night) A trombonist steeped in precise and pugnacious hard bop, with a group consisting of Steve Nelson on vibraphone, Larry Willis on piano, Nat Reeves on bass and Joe Farnsworth on drums. 8 and 9:45, Kitano Hotel, 66 Park Avenue, at 38th Street, Manhattan, (212) 885-7119; cover, $20, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>THE FRANK AND JOE SHOW (Wednesday) Exuberance is the currency of this four-piece band, which finds equal inspiration in swing (both the American and Gypsy varieties) and Latin music (or some approximation thereof). Frank is Frank Vignola, a guitarist; the Joe in the equation is Joe Ascione, a drummer. 8 and 10 p.m., Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>* BILL FRISELL QUINTET (Tuesday through April 23; April 25 through 30) On his latest Nonesuch releases -- ''East/West'' and ''Further East/Further West,'' both partly recorded at the Village Vanguard -- the guitarist Bill Frisell conjures a compelling hallucination of the American popular songbook, with Tony Scherr and Kenny Wollesen on bass and drums. The addition of the saxophonist Greg Tardy and the trumpeter Ron Miles should alter the ensemble's chemistry as well as its size. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20; $25 on Fridays and Saturdays, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>EDDIE GALE'S NOW BAND (Tomorrow through Monday) Mr. Gale is a trumpeter with serious avant-garde credentials, having worked closely with the trailblazers Cecil Taylor and Sun Ra, among others. Visiting from the West Coast, he makes three stops in as many days, with a group of estimable players including the trombonist Dick Griffin and the bassist Todd Nicholson. Tomorrow at 9 p.m., Sistas' Place, 456 Nostrand Avenue, at Jefferson Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 398-1766. Sunday at 3 p.m., Clemente Soto Vélez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, at Rivington Street, Lower East Side, (212) 696-6681; cover, $10 per set; $7 for students; free for ages 14 and under. Monday at 9 p.m., Zebulon, 258 Wythe Avenue, near North Third Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 218-6934; no cover. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARY HALVORSON AND JESSICA PAVONE (Thursday) Ms. Halvorson plays guitar in this duo, and Ms. Pavone plays viola. Their experimental instincts, sharpened by an affiliation with Anthony Braxton, commingle with a folksy lyricism; sometimes they even sing, without a trace of protective irony. 8 p.m., The Stone, Avenue C and Second Street, East Village; cover, $10. www.thestonenyc.com. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>BILLY HART QUARTET (Through Sunday) Mr. Hart, a loose but focused drummer with a sterling résumé, fronts a dream team of younger players: the tenor saxophonist Mark Turner, the pianist Ethan Iverson and the bassist Ben Street. 9 and 11 p.m., Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037; cover, $20 to $25, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HEBERT'S BYZANTINE MONKEY QUARTET (Wednesday) A progressive ensemble featuring the original music and bass playing of Mr. Hebert, along with the typically thoughtful contributions of Ralph Alessi, trumpeter; Mat Maneri, violist; and Nasheet Waits, drummer. 10 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN HOLLENBECK'S CLAUDIA QUINTET (Tomorrow) This improvising chamber ensemble pursues texturally oriented and often contrapuntal exploration; Mr. Hollenbeck's drumming is one color on a palette that also includes Chris Speed's clarinet and tenor saxophone, Ted Reichman's accordion, John Hebert's bass and Matt Moran's vibraphone. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>DAVID LIEBMAN QUARTET (Tuesday through Thursday) An incantatory saxophonist working in the post-Coltrane idiom, Mr. Liebman plays here with a group featuring a frequent foil, the guitarist Vic Juris. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232; cover, $20. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>LIONEL LOUEKE TRIO (Tonight and tomorrow night) Mr. Loueke, a distinctive guitarist and vocalist, favors a form of global jazz deeply informed by his West African homeland, Benin; his bandmates are the bassist Massimo Biolcati and the drummer Ferenc Nemeth. 9 and 10:30, Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>RUDRESH MAHANTHAPPA QUARTET (Wednesday and Thursday) Mr. Mahanthappa uses both his razor-sharp alto saxophone tone and his compositional acumen in this group, with the pianist Vijay Iyer, the bassist François Moutin and the drummer Dan Weiss. The group is introducing ''Code Book,'' a work created with support from Chamber Music America, that will be the substance of Mr. Mahanthappa's next release. 9 and 10:30 p.m., Jazz Gallery, 290 Hudson Street, at Spring Street, South Village, (212) 242-1063; cover, $15. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>REBECCA MARTIN (Thursday) A singer-songwriter with no small affinity for jazz harmony, Ms. Martin gets more than the usual support from her ensemble, which includes the tenor saxophonist Bill McHenry and the bassist Larry Grenadier, her husband. She shares a bill with Trevor Exter, a cellist and vocalist riding the contemporary current of acoustic pop. 7 p.m., Joe's Pub, at the Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778; cover, $15, with a two-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>PAT MARTINO QUINTET (Thursday through April 23) The guitarist Pat Martino's new Blue Note album, ''Remember: A Tribute to Wes Montgomery,'' does exactly what it purports to do. And it works, because of the untroubled self-assurance of the emulation and the simple satisfaction of a hard-swinging band. 8 and 10 p.m., with 11:30 sets on Friday and Saturday, Iridium, 1650 Broadway, at 51st Street, (212) 582-2121; cover, $30, with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MULGREW MILLER QUARTET (Through Saturday) Mr. Miller is a smart pianist with roots firmly planted in jazz tradition, especially the blues. Here he corrals some strong younger players: Myron Walden, alto saxophonist; Ivan Taylor, bassist; and Rodney Green, drummer. 9 p.m., 11 p.m. and 12:30 a.m., Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662; cover, $25. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>MARC MOMMAAS AND GLOBAL MOTION (Thursday) Mr. Mommaas, a Dutch tenor saxophonist, employs a fluid post-bop language in this band, with the Danish pianist Nikolaj Hess and the American rhythm team of John Hebert on bass and Tony Moreno on drums. Here the group workshops new pieces by Mr. Hess that draw inspiration from African music. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, 212 989-9319; cover, $10, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>FRANK MORGAN QUARTET (Tuesday through April 23) Now in his 70's, the alto saxophonist Frank Morgan is one of the last survivors of the bebop era (and in his case, ''survivor'' is truly the appropriate term). He leads a sympathetic group consisting of John Hicks on piano, Curtis Lundy on bass and Victor Lewis on drums. 7:30 and 9:30 p.m., with an 11:30 set Fridays and Saturdays, Dizzy's Club Coca-Cola, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Jazz at Lincoln Center, 60th Street and Broadway, (212) 258-9595; cover, $30, with a minimum of $10 at tables, $5 at the bar. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JENNY SCHEINMAN TRIO (Tuesday) As a violist and violinist, Ms. Scheinman often goes for rustic charm, but she never ceases to be an exploratory improviser. Her more experimental side is purposefully exposed in this setting, featuring the darkly consonant bass playing of Todd Sickafoose and the explosively elastic drumming of Jim Black. 7 p.m., Barbès, 376 Ninth Street, at Sixth Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 965-9177; cover, $8. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JANIS SIEGEL (Wednesday through April 21) With her new album, ''A Thousand Beautiful Things'' (Telarc), Ms. Siegel applies her self-assured alto to songs by Raul Midón, Suzanne Vega and Nellie McKay. It's the same sort of popular eclecticism she enjoys in Manhattan Transfer, but a few degrees less cloying. 9 and 11 p.m., Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080; cover, $30; $40 on April 21; with a $10 minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>JOHN TCHICAI TRIO (Sunday) The Danish saxophonist and clarinetist John Tchicai developed a reputation for fiery exertions during the first wave of free jazz, but ''Good Night Songs'' (Boxholder), his new double CD with the saxophonist Charlie Kohlhase and the guitarist Garrison Fewell, conveys an often tenderhearted intimacy. 8:30 p.m., Cornelia Street Cafe, 29 Cornelia Street, West Village, (212) 989-9319; cover, $12, with a one-drink minimum. (Chinen)</p>
        <p>Classical</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent music performances: nytimes.com/music.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>'ACIS AND GALATEA'  (Sunday, Tuesday and Thursday) Mark Lamos's enchanting production of Handel's opera, introduced in 2001, returns to the New York City Opera with two artists making their company debuts in the leading roles. The soprano Sarah Jane McMahon is Galatea, the sea nymph hopelessly in love with a young sailor, Acis, sung by the tenor Philippe Castagner. Ransom Wilson conducts. Sunday at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday and Thursday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $110. (Anthony Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LA BOHèME' (Tonight) James Robinson's production punts the Puccini favorite forward by some 80 years, placing the action in the opening months of World War I and lending an extra tug of pathos. A mostly new cast at the City Opera has taken over, with Yunah Lee as Mimi, Gerard Powers as Rodolfo, Jennifer Black as Musetta and Philip Torre as Marcello. David Wroe conducts. 8, New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $25 to $110. (Jeremy Eichler)</p>
        <p>'CARMEN' (Tomorrow and Wednesday) Devilish is what you want in a Carmen, and on opening night at the New York City Opera, Kate Aldrich came through in that role, capturing not only Carmen's seductiveness but also her radical proto-feminist pride in her own independence. Unfortunately, there was scant chemistry between her and Robert Breault as Don José. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Wednesday at 7:30 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; sold out tomorrow; $25 to $120 on Wednesday. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI' (Tomorrow) A new cast takes over for the end of the spring run of Mozart's nearly perfect opera at the New York City Opera. Timothy Kuhn will make his company debut in the title role; Claudia Waite will make hers as Donna Anna; and Caroline Worra should be a credible Donna Elvira. Steven Mosteller conducts, adequately. 8 p.m., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $45 to $79. (Anne Midgette)</p>
        <p>'DON GIOVANNI' (Tonight and tomorrow night) Amato's venerable recipe -- no rehearsals, changing casts at every performance -- should make for an unusual version of Mozart's classic dish, but at least the theater's small scale represents a kind of period fidelity. 7:30, Amato Opera, 319 Bowery, at Second Street, East Village, (212) 228-8200; $30; $25 for students and 65+. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>* 'DON PASQUALE' (Tomorrow and Tuesday) The veteran Austrian director Otto Schenk understands that the way to make a rich, comic opera like Donizetti's ''Don Pasquale'' work is to treat it seriously. In his wonderful new production for the Met he taps into the emotions -- jealousy, yearning, fear of death -- that swirl below the surface of this farcical tale about a miserly bachelor who foolishly decides to take a young wife and disinherit his shiftless nephew. The cast is splendid, especially the charismatic soprano Anna Netrebko, the dynamic young baritone Mariusz Kwiecien and, in the title role, the stylish Italian bass Simone Alaimo. (On Tuesday, Lyubov Petrova sings Norina in place of Ms. Netrebko, and John Del Carlo replaces Mr. Alaimo.) Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., Tuesday at 8 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out tomorrow; $26 to $175 on Tuesday. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>'LOHENGRIN' (Monday and Thursday) Robert Wilson's luminous production of this luminous opera is not to every taste, but many find that it shines, and Karita Mattila should shine in it as Elsa. The title role should also fit Ben Heppner well. Luana DeVol, an American soprano who has been active mainly in Germany, is Ortrud. Replacing James Levine in the pit is the promising conductor Philippe Auguin, who made his Met debut replacing Mr. Levine in Busoni's ''Doktor Faustus.'' 7 p.m., Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; $26 to $175. (Midgette)</p>
        <p>'LA TRAVIATA' (Tonight) The Met's long-running and highly successful production finally comes to a close, here with Hei-Kyung Hong, Frank Lopardo and Dwayne Croft. 8, Metropolitan Opera House, Lincoln Center, (212) 362-6000; sold out. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC (Tonight, tomorrow, Sunday and Thursday) A weekly presenter of chamber music, this floating concert hall also offers great views of Lower Manhattan. Tonight at 7:30, Dmitri Alexeev performs piano works by Shostakovich, Tchaikovsky, Scriabin and Rachmaninoff. Concerts tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 4 p.m. feature rarely heard music by the 18th-century Russian violinist Ivan Khandoshkin, along with Haydn, Shostakovich and Schubert. Sunday evening at 7:30 is a rescheduled performance of music by Messiaen, Beethoven and others. Thursday evening at 7:30, Carlos Prieto (cello) and Doris Stevenson (piano) survey more Shostakovich, as well as Piazzolla's ''Grand Tango.'' Fulton Ferry Landing, next to the Brooklyn Bridge, Brooklyn, (718) 624-2083; $35, tomorrow and Sunday afternoon, $40. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER (Wednesday) There will be Beethoven and Janacek quartets, and then the Pacifica and Miro Quartets will merge in the Mendelssohn Octet. 7:30 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5788; $30 to $52. (Holland)</p>
        <p>IL DOLCIMELO (Sunday) This German period-instrument ensemble makes its New York debut with works by Vivaldi, Scarlatti, Corelli and Telemann. 5 p.m., Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700; $20. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>JUILLIARD STRING QUARTET (Tuesday) The venerable Juilliard offers Mozart, Shostakovich and Brahms. 8 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 769-7406; free, but tickets are required. (Holland)</p>
        <p>* NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC (Wednesday and Thursday) Mstislav Rostropovich approaches the music of Shostakovich with more authority and close personal knowledge than just about anyone. He returns to the Philharmonic to lead the composer's 10th Symphony and his gripping First Violin Concerto, with Maxim Vengerov as soloist. 7:30 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $33 to $104. (Eichler)</p>
        <p>ORCHESTRA OF THE AGE OF ENLIGHTENMENT (Sunday) The key names here are less the orchestra's than that of René Jacobs, a conductor (and singer) who has reawakened many corners of period performance, and of Solomon, the title character in Handel's oratorio. Handel switched largely from opera to oratorio in the 1740's and wrote new oratorios for each Lenten season, so this offering is seasonal as well as inherently appealing. 3 p.m., Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500; $56 (Midgette)</p>
        <p>POMERIUM (Tomorrow) Alexander Blachly's superb early-music choir offers an Easter program with motets composed for Holy Week by Renaissance and early-Baroque composers, including Dufay, Senfl, Lassus, Gesualdo, Monteverdi and Byrd. 1 and 3 p.m., the Cloisters, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, (212) 650-2290; $35. (Allan Kozinn)</p>
        <p>* 'ST. MATTHEW PASSION' (Tonight and tomorrow) After acclaimed presentations in 1997 and 2001, Jonathan Miller's revelatory staging of Bach's astounding sacred work has returned to the Harvey Theater at the Brooklyn Academy of Music. The chorus members and orchestra musicians wear everyday clothing and sit facing one another in a circle so that they can enact the scenes from the story of Jesus' Crucifixion. Instrumentalists and singers interact with and even comfort one another during the sublime arias. Rufus Müller is a charismatic Evangelist; Curtis Streetman makes an affectingly husky and noble Jesus. Paul Goodwin, who conceived the production with Mr. Miller, conducts. 7:30 p.m., 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 636-4100; $30 to $90. (Tommasini)</p>
        <p>* SAN FRANCISCO SYMPHONY (Wednesday and Thursday) Michael Tilson Thomas has made this orchestra into one of the country's best, and its visits to Carnegie Hall are invariably illuminating. His programs include a range of composers from the late-19th and early-20th centuries, among them, Debussy, Ravel, Wagner and Mahler on Wednesday, and Webern, Stravinsky and Ives on Thursday. Jean-Yves Thibaudet is the soloist in the Ravel Piano Concerto in G. 8 p.m., (212) 247-7800; $28 to $97. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>FAZIL SAY (Tonight) This young Turkish pianist plays with energy and, when he is at his best, the improvisatory sensibilities of a jazz performer. His program includes the Brahms Intermezzi (Op. 117) and plenty of Bach, both straight (the Italian Concerto and the French Suite No. 6) or hyphenated (Busoni's transcription of the Chaconne, along with arrangements by Liszt and Mr. Say himself). 8, Metropolitan Museum of Art, (212) 570-3949; $40. (Kozinn)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Full reviews of recent performances: nytimes.com/dance.</p>
        <p>ALLEN BODY GROUP AND JENNIE MARYTAI LiU (Tonight and tomorrow) Science is the inspiration for Malinda Allen's ''Einstein's Dreams'' and Ms. Liu's ''Learning in Lower Animals.'' 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077, dtw.org. Tickets: $20. (Jennifer Dunning)</p>
        <p>'A BENEFIT OF THE DOUBT' (Tomorrow) This benefit for Jonah Bokaer's new Chez Bushwick Studios is a tribute to Charles Atlas, a filmmaker who has worked with Merce Cunningham. The evening includes a screening of a film and video work by Mr. Atlas (5 p.m.), a performance by artists who have collaborated with Mr. Atlas (7:30 p.m.) and a ''Shtudio Show'' (at 9 p.m. ) Chez Bushwick Studios, 304 Boerum Street, Apt. 11, Bushwick, Brooklyn, (917) 459-1072. Tickets: $50 and $150; $250 includes cocktails and dinner. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>BALLET FIESTA MEXICANA (Tonight through Sunday) Yloy Ybarra's company returns in a program of music and dance from Mexico, with live music performed by the group Semilla. Through April 30. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 4 p.m. Thalia Spanish Theater, 41-17 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens, (718) 729-3880. Tickets: $25 to $30. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>CHILDREN OF UGANDA (Tonight through Sunday) Twenty children, ages 8 to 18, will celebrate the culture of their country and of East Africa in song and dance to raise money for Uganda's 1.7 million AIDS and war orphans. Tonight at 7, tomorrow at 2 and 7 p.m., Sunday at 2 p.m. Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800, joyce.org; $25; $15 for children. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>SELMA JEANNE COHEN: A TRIBUTE TO HER LIFE AND WORK (Tomorrow) The last event in this free series is ''Next Week, Swan Lake: Approaches to Dance History and Criticism,'' a panel discussion including Mindy Aloff, Jack Anderson, Marcia Siegel and George Dorris. 3 p.m., Bruno Walter Auditorium, New York Public Library for the Performing Arts, 111 Amsterdam Avenue, at 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 642-0142. Free. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>'DANCE PLUS SPRING' (Thursday through April 23) The program includes dances by David Dorfman, Julia Ritter, John Evans, Randy James and Paulette Sears, all dance teachers, and Megan Hebert, a student choreographer. Thursday, next Friday and April 22 at 8 p.m.; April 23 at 2 p.m., Mason Gross Performing Arts Center, 85 George Street, between Route 18 and Ryders Lane, Douglass College campus, New Brunswick, N.J., (732) 932-7511 or masongross.rutgers.edu. Tickets: $20 (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* MARTHA GRAHAM DANCE COMPANY (Tuesday) The company seems to be in transition, to put it mildly, but it is still the primary keeper of some of the great modern-dance repertory of the last century, and of some wonderful dancers. The major event is a gala on Tuesday that includes Richard Move, the Graham impersonator, performing a duet with Desmond Richardson, and a solo by Fang-Yi Sheu. 7:30 p.m., Skirball Center for the Performing Arts, 566 LaGuardia Place, at Washington Square South. For $45 performance tickets, (212) 992-8484; for $150 and $500 gala tickets, (212) 521-3667, or marthagraham.org. Also on Tuesday, five generations of Graham performers will give a master class in the studio where Graham taught in the 1930's. 11:30 a.m., 92nd Street Y, 1395 Lexington Avenue, (212) 415-5553. Audience: $15. Participants: $12 for professionals, $15 for others. Ancillary events continue on April 21 and 25. (John Rockwell)</p>
        <p>MARIA HASSABI (Tonight and tomorrow) Hip, rawly emotional and mysterious, Ms. Hassabi will present her new program, ''Still Smoking,'' which investigates the frenetic experience of city life. Tonight at 7 and 9:30; tomorrow at 8 p.m., the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793, ext. 11, thekitchen.org. Tickets: $12. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>LEADING LADIES: ALETHEA ADSITT &amp; COMPANY  (Tonight and tomorrow) This festival of dances by women continues with ''the new jalopy,'' a new multimedia, site-specific piece presented by Alethea Adsitt &amp; Company. 8 and 10 p.m., Dance New Amsterdam, 280 Broadway, at Chambers Street, SoHo, (212) 279-4200, ticketcentral.com or dnadance.org. Tickets: $17. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>NEWSTEPS (Thursday through April 22) Miriam Hess, Jessica Ray and Adrienne F. Westwood are among those featured, as the Mulberry Street Theater's semiannual choreographers' showcase explores themes of power, relationship and memory. 8 p.m., 70 Mulberry Street, second floor (corner of Mulberry and Bayard Streets), Chinatown, (212) 349-0126. Tickets: $12. (Claudia La Rocco)</p>
        <p>DAVID PARKER AND THE BANG GROUP (Tonight and tomorrow) The irrepressible Mr. Parker will present dances that include his new ''Backward and in Heels,'' a piece for six dancers that is set to music. That music incorporates excerpts from the score from ''The Sound of Music''; ''Hava Nagila,'' played by a hand-bell choir; and Schubert's ''Ave Maria.'' 8:30 p.m., Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400, symphonyspace.org. Tickets: $21. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>MARISSA PEREL (Tonight and tomorrow) Ms. Perel, who has worked with Miguel Gutierrez, will present her new ''Burden,'' a dance performance and installation that also features the dancer Kayvon Pourazar and the musician Jon Moniaci. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8. The Chocolate Factory, 5-49 49th Avenue, Long Island City, Queens, (212) 352-3101 or theatermania.com. Tickets: $15. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>* STEPHEN PETRONIO COMPANY (Tuesday through Sunday) What do you get when you mix the singer-songwriter Rufus Wainwright, the Young People's Chorus of New York City and Stephen Petronio's extravagant movement language? A concert not to be missed. Tuesday through April 22 at 8 p.m., April 23 at 2 and 7:30 p.m., Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800. Tickets: $40. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>PILAR RIOJA (Tonight through Sunday) It almost doesn't matter what this New York favorite performs, but for the record, the program will include some of Ms. Rioja's favorite flamenco dances. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; Sunday at 3 p.m.; Monday at 11 a.m. Repertorio Español, 138 East 27th Street, between Lexington and Third Avenues, (212) 225-9920. Tickets: $25 to $50. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>RUSSIAN NATIONAL BALLET (Tomorrow) An indefatigable touring company based in Moscow, with guest stars from elsewhere in Russia, in ''Swan Lake,'' of all things. 8 p.m., Queensborough Performing Arts Center, Queensborough Community College, 222-05 56th Avenue, Bayside, Queens, (718) 631-6311. Tickets: $39 and $42. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>* SOURCING STRAVINSKY (Wednesday through April 22) Six choreographers take on Stravinsky, with Yvonne Rainer (in a rare new dance work) using both Stravinsky and Balanchine's ''Agon.'' The other choreographers are Cynthia Hopkins, Dayna Hanson and Linas Phillips, David Neumann and Rennie Harris. 7:30 p.m., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077 or dtw.org. Tickets: $15 and $25. (Rockwell)</p>
        <p>'TRAS LADOS' (Thursday through April 23) Artists from Mexico to Japan come together for the latest installment of Danspace Project's Global Exchange series. Choreographed by Eun Jung Gonzalez, in collaboration with Pulso Compañía de Danza. 8:30 p.m., Danspace Project, St. Mark's Church, 131 East 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194 or danspaceproject.org. Tickets: $15. (La Rocco)</p>
        <p>TRINAYAN COLLECTIVE (Tonight through Sunday) This New York-based company of Indian classical dancers will explore the notion of the witness in ''Sakshi/Witness,'' a dance in the Odissi style. 8 p.m., Joyce SoHo, 155 Mercer Street, between Houston and Prince Streets, SoHo, (212) 334-7479. Tickets: $25; $20 for students and 65+. (Dunning)</p>
        <p>Art</p>
        <p>Museums and galleries are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted. Full reviews of recent art shows: nytimes.com/art.</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>* BROOKLYN MUSEUM: 'SYMPHONIC POEM: THE ART OF AMINAH BRENDA LYNN ROBINSON,' through Aug. 14. This prodigious show, by an artist born and still living in Columbus, Ohio, celebrates her heritage in paintings, drawings, sculpture, stitchery, leather work and less classifiable forms of expression. Besides its sheer visual wizardry, using materials like leaves, twigs, bark, buttons and cast-off clothes, her art is compelling in that it ruminates on the history of black migration to, and settlement in, the United States, from early times to the present, in a garrulous, very personal way. 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, Brooklyn, (718) 638-5000. (Grace Glueck)</p>
        <p>* Brooklyn Museum: WILLIAM WEGMAN: 'FUNNEY/STRANGE,' through May 28. Descended from Marcel Duchamp and Buster Keaton, Mr. Wegman has straddled high and low for more than three decades, using his signature Weimaraners to make the art world's funniest videos, as well as television commercials, calendars and children's books. His popular success has tended to obscure his originality and influence, along with a multifarious production that includes wittily captioned drawings, wonderfully irreverent paintings and a host of nondog photographic work. This thorough and thoroughly entertaining retrospective highlights not only the accessibility of his richly human art, but also its dedication to the 1970's notion that art should not look like art. (See above.) (Roberta Smith)</p>
        <p>* FRICK COLLECTION: 'GOYA's LAST WORKS,' through May 14. This compact show is sublime. The most humane portraits are mixed with sketches, like diary entries, in which society is an irredeemable mob of lunatics and murderers. In exile in Bordeaux, Goya spent his last days in physical misery, lamenting man's essential evil while experimenting with the new medium of lithography and inventing the most exquisite, luminous paintings on tiny chips of ivory. Like the late works of Titian or Rembrandt, Goya's late works achieve a whole new level of freedom and depth, haunted by death but exalted. 1 East 70th Street, (212) 288-0700. (Michael Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>* Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum: 'David Smith: A Centennial,' through May 14. David Smith is best known for his worst work, bulky sculptures of the ''important'' kind that museums and banks like to buy. Much (though not all) of that material has been excised from this survey in favor of smaller, earlier, nonmonumental pieces that the curator, Carmen Gimenez, presents with plenty of air and light. The result is exemplary as a David Smith experience, an American Modernism experience and a Guggenheim Museum experience. 1071 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 423-3500. (Holland Cotter)</p>
        <p>* International Center of Photography: 'Snap Judgments: New Positions in Contemporary African Photography,' through May 28. If Martians tuned into our television news broadcasts, they'd have a miserable impression of life on Earth. War, disease, poverty, heartbreak and nothing else. That's exactly how most of the world sees Africa: filtered through images of calamity. The Nigerian-born curator Okwui Enwezor offers a bracing alternative view in this show of recent photography from Africa. He isn't interested in simply exchanging an upbeat Africa for a downbeat one, smiles for frowns, but in engineering a slow, complex, panoptical turn in perspective, one that takes in many moods and directions. The results are stimulating, astringent, brimming with life. 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at 43rd Street, (212) 857-0000. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART: 'HATSHEPSUT,' through July 9. Can a queen be a king, too? Consider the case of Hatshepsut, an Egyptian ruler of the 15th century B.C. She assumed the supreme title of pharaoh and ruled Egypt in that powerfully masculine role until her death. Hatshepsut is the subject of a celebratory show at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, one that commemorates the 100th anniversary of the Met's department of Egyptian art. Organized by the Met and the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, it includes many objects from the Met's own extensive holdings, excavated at its digs in the 1920's and 30's. But it isn't so easy to follow Hatshepsut's trail in this ambitious show, what with the number of relatives, subordinates, minor officials and such who also have a place in it, along with scarabs, jewelry, pottery, furniture and other artifacts. (212) 535-7710. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>Met: KARA WALKER AT THE MET: 'AFTER THE DELUGE,' through July 30. The Metropolitan Museum of Art's first foray into artist-organized shows is a small tour de force of curatorial creativity. Inspired partly by Hurricane Katrina, Ms. Walker has combined works from the Met with examples of her own art, connecting shared themes of race, poverty and water to illuminate contemporary art's inevitable dialogue with past art. The show has as many crosscurrents and undertows as a river. (See above.) (Smith)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'EDVARD MUNCH: THE MODERN LIFE OF THE SOUL,' through May 8. This affecting, full-scale retrospective is the first survey of this Norwegian painter in an American museum in almost 30 years. Its more than 130 oils and works on paper cover Munch's entire career, from 1880 to 1944. (212) 708-9400. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>THE MUSEUM OF MODERN ART: 'ON SITE: NEW ARCHITECTURE IN SPAIN,' through May 1. Since the early 1970's, when Spain began to awaken from the isolation of a four-decade dictatorship, Spanish architects have produced designs of unusual depth, often with a firm connection to the land, a sense of humility and a way of conveying continuity with the past while embracing the present. Packed with pretty images and elegant models, this exhibition lacks the scholarly depth you might have hoped for on such a mesmerizing subject. (See above.) (Nicolai Ouroussoff)</p>
        <p>* The Museum of Modern Art: 'Without Boundary: Seventeen Ways of Looking,' through May 22. This excellent group show considers what ''Islamic'' means in the work of several contemporary artists, and it means many things, none simple. Just to see the uses made of calligraphy by Shirazeh Houshiary, Rachid Koraichi and Shirin Neshat is to understand the lesson in variety put forward here. At the same time, the show is far from didactic. It's beautiful, sexy and, in the case of Raqib Shaw's painting and Kutlug Ataman's video of Sufi meditation, ecstatic. (See above.) (Cotter)</p>
        <p>National Academy Museum: 'Treasures from Olana: Landscapes by Frederic Edwin Church,' through April 30. Exquisite small landscape studies by the best of the Hudson River School painters. They are from the collection at Olana, the Persian-style Victorian mansion -- now a museum -- that Church built on an upstate hill overlooking the Hudson River. 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, (212) 369-4880. (Ken Johnson)</p>
        <p>NEUE GALERIE: 'KLEE AND AMERICA,' through May 22. For a long time, the Swiss-born artist Paul Klee (1879-1940), regarded as a leading Modernist figure in Europe, didn't believe his delicate, chimerical work had much of a future in the United States. Yet, thanks to artists, collectors and dealers with close contacts in Germany who had begun to discover his work, by the early 1920's, Klee's impact began to be felt here. This show of more than 60 paintings and drawings assembled exclusively from American holdings covers the wide spectrum of Klee's work. 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street, (212) 628-6200. (Glueck)</p>
        <p>P.S. 1 Contemporary Art Center: 'The Thirteen: Chinese Video Now,' through April 24. A snappy roundup of recent video, a favored medium among young artists in a digitally savvy 21st-century China, this show has two fine pieces by Cao Fei, who has garnered much attention recently. It is also the occasion for several worthy New York debuts. Some of the art is light, slight, and MTV-ish, but artists like Cui Xiuwen, Xu Zhen, Li Songhua, Xu Tan, Meng Jin and Dong Wensheng give us a lot. 22-25 Jackson Avenue, at 46th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 784-2084. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>* The Studio Museum In harlem: 'Energy/Experimentation: Black Artists and Abstraction, 1964-1980,' through July 2. During one of the most radical periods in 20th-century American politics, the Black Power era, a group of African-American artists was working in one of the most radical forms of 20th-century art, abstraction. This show is stylishly installed (one gallery bursts with color, another has a cool platinum shimmer); the 15 artists are intensely individualistic and part of an important history. One, the sculptor Tom Lloyd (1921-96), opened the Studio Museum with a solo show in 1968. 144 West 125th Street, (212) 864-4500. (Cotter)</p>
        <p>Whitney Museum of American Art: 'WHITNEY BIENNIAL 2006: DAY FOR NIGHT,' through May 28. This biennial will provoke much head-scratching by uninitiated visitors. A hermetic take on what has been making waves, it's packaged -- branded might be the better word -- as a show long on collaboration and open-endedness: several shows under one roof, including a revival of the 1960's ''Peace Tower,'' which rises like a Tinker Toy construction from the Whitney courtyard, with contributions by dozens of artists. As a counter to the image of the art world as rich, youth-besotted and obsessed with crafty little nothings, the ethos here is provisional, messy, half-baked, cantankerous, insular -- radical qualities art used to have when it could still call itself radical and wasn't like a barnacle clinging to the cruise ship of pop culture. That was back in the 1970's. And much of what's here (including works by bohemians and other senior eccentrics around then) harks back to that moment. (800) 944-8639 or www.whitney.org. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Uptown</p>
        <p>PETER BEGLEY Parisian esprit enlivens Peter Begley's latest multipanel paintings. Their motif is the cornice: a ubiquitous emblem of Baron Haussmann's grand boulevards, which, abstracted and made delicately ornate, permits Mr. Begley to add illusory depth to his usual richly worked, waxy fields of warm color. Partly the filigree, partly the gentle rapture with his recently adopted city give to these new works a bit of the élan of old Raoul Dufy. Salander-OReilly, 20 East 79th Street, (212) 879-6606, through April 22. (Kimmelman)</p>
        <p>Tony Cragg: 'Five Bottles' In the early 1980's, this eminent English sculptor made flat, mosaiclike works out of found colored plastic objects and fragments. This show presents a set of five wall-works, each representing a different giant colored bottle composed of toys, combs, cigarette lighters and other pieces of ordinary commercial detritus. Vivian Horan, 35 East 67th Street, (212) 517-9410, through April 21. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'1968: All in a Dream' In 1968 the photographer Lenny Gottlieb saved 30,000 snapshots that were supposed to have been thrown out at the photographic processing lab where he was working. Approximately 500 of them are on view here; collectively, they offer an enthralling cross-section of American life during a year of tremendous change. Andrew Roth, 160A East 70th Street, (212) 717-9067, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* NAGASAWA ROSETSU This rare survey of this eccentric painter of 18th-century Kyoto consists of 14 works that reveal a breathtaking command of different skills and styles in portraiture, landscape, nature painting and calligraphic minimalism, and an almost chameleonlike instinct for using them. Koichi Yanagi Oriental Fine Arts, 58A East 66th Street, (212) 744-5577, through Thursday. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Galleries: 57th Street</p>
        <p>Darren Almond /Janice Kerbel: 'The Impossible Landscape' Nothing is obvious in this handsome show of works by two London-based Conceptualists. The connection is that both make visible things that are in different ways impossible. Ms. Kerbel's elegantly abstracted designs for gardens in an office, a Laundromat and other unlikely places are meant to be imagined but never actually built. Mr. Almond's sumptuous, subtly eerie landscape photographs were shot at night using long exposures, making visible what would be invisible to the naked eye. The Horticultural Society of New York, 128 West 58th Street, (212) 757-0915, through May 5. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: SoHo</p>
        <p>Rico Gatson: 'African Fractals' Mr. Gatson's suave geometric paintings and sculptures of symbolically charged vernacular objects -- a whipping post in the form of a Christian cross with wrist-holes, for example -- feature African-style stripe patterns, creating a dialogue between utopian modernism and tragic social history. A video installation produces hypnotic patterns out of films of the pageantry surrounding the great boxing match between Muhammed Ali and George Foreman that took place in Zaire in 1974. Ronald Feldman, 31 Mercer Street, (212) 226-3232, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Joëlle Tuerlinckx: 'Drawing Inventory' A prominent Belgian Conceptualist presents a dry and oblique installation consisting of a large quantity of ordinary materials more or less related to the art of drawing. The Drawing Center, 35 Wooster Street, (212) 219-2166, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'When Artists Say We' This timely sociological experiment of a show features 17 artists or artist groups who were invited to create wall-diagrams or mini-exhibitions reflecting on the social networks out of which contemporary art emerges. Artists Space, 38 Green Street, (212) 226-3970, through April 29. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Galleries: Chelsea</p>
        <p>Tara Donovan Known for creating improbable accumulations of ordinary things, Ms. Donovan here has arranged three million plastic cups in stacks from ankle-high to five feet. They make a 50-by-60-foot rectangle on the floor, resembling a lumpy field of snow. PaceWildenstein, 545 West 22nd Street, (212) 929-7000, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>NAN GOLDIN: 'CHASING A GHOST' A riveting if flawed three-screen video projection titled ''Sisters, Saints &amp; Sibyls'' hauntingly details the trauma that drives Ms. Goldin's invasive, yet oddly solitary photographs, as well as her lifelong battle with addiction: the suicide of her troubled older sister in 1965 at the age of 18. The piece mixes video, family snapshots and the artist's photographs, and is heightened by a sensitive selection of music that may almost do too much of the work. But its unalloyed honesty offers extreme evidence that most art begins in an attempt to heal a deep psychic wound. Matthew Marks Gallery, 522 West 22nd Street, (212) 243-0200, through April 22. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Markus Hansen: 'Other People's Feelings Are Also My Own' In high-definition video projections of pairs of photographs, Mr. Hansen, a Paris-based German artist, dresses like and adopts the facial expression of the man, woman or child in the picture next to his. Whatever his project means to say about modern identity, it is absorbing to study how closely he is able to match other people's feelings, which range from carefree happiness to doleful anxiety. Virgil de Voldere, 526 West 26th Street, (212) 343-9694, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* MARK LECKeY: 'DRUNKEN BAKERS' This cinematically gifted British artist raises his game with a stop-action animation made by simply shooting a raunchy, well-drawn comic strip for adults in close-up, turning its speech balloons into spoken dialogue and adding realistic sound effects. Shown in an increasingly grubby white-on-white cube, the work is elegantly efficient, funny and dark, and adds another twist to the convoluted history of appropriation art. GBE @ Passerby, 436 West 15th Street, (212) 627-5258, through April 22. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Eve K. Tremblay: 'Tales Without Grounds' A rising young Canadian photographer presents glossy staged photographs of people doing enigmatic things in and around a large facility for hydroponic lettuce cultivation. With their cinematically intense colors, Ms. Tremblay's pictures are like stills from a Tarkovskian science fiction movie. Buia, 541 West 23rd Street, (212) 366-9915, through April 22. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Other Galleries</p>
        <p>'B-Side' This engaging group show includes Tim Spelios's beautifully made Surrealistic drum set in which the components are square rather than round; Matt Freedman's life-size sculpture of a boy with a lion's teeth and elephant eyes; Mary Carlson's crocheted works resembling splats of blood on the wall; Joyce Pensato's expressionistically painted clown face; Judith Page's ghoulish and viscous small portraits; Meredith Allen's funny and scary photographs of dogs; and a painting by Jim Torok that declares: ''You have no worries. Things are going well. Don't wake up.'' Sarah Bowen, 210 North Sixth Street, Williamsburg, Brooklyn, (718) 302-4517, through April 30. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>'Zoo Story' A clay gorilla by Daisy Youngblood, a bronze she-wolf by Kiki Smith, a flock of concrete sheep by Françoise-Xavier Lalanne and works about animals by more than 20 other artists, including John Baldessari, Katharina Fritsch, Ross Bleckner and Rebecca Horn, turn the first floor of this sleek, three-story private museum into a diverting menagerie. Fisher Landau Center for Art, 38-27 30th Street, Long Island City, Queens, (718) 937-0727, through June 12. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Last Chance</p>
        <p>TIM BARBER A fresh, even touching reprise of the overused convention of walls papered with unframed photographs and small, cartoonish drawings, this show has been culled from Mr. Barber's Web site, tinyvices.com. With 250 people represented, it blurs the line between professional and amateur and introduces a savvy curatorial eye. Spencer Brownstone Gallery, 39 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 334-3455; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* BLUE GLAZE OF THE TANG This exceptional exhibition of Tang horses, court ladies, equestrian figures and grooms brings together rare examples of the unusually painterly sancai ware in which the traditional three-color glaze includes cobalt blue. Berwald Oriental Art, 5 East 57th Street, (212) 319-1519; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>Marcel Broodthaers This reverential exhibition of just three works by a Belgian Conceptualist regarded as a Duchampian saint in some sectors of the art world includes a hat painted white and attached to a canvas painted black and white; a work called ''L'Erreur,'' consisting of 45 eggshells attached to a canvas labeled ''moules,'' the French word for mussels; and a set of canvases neatly inscribed with words relating to the composition and sale of paintings. Peter Freeman, 560 Broadway, near Prince Street, SoHo, (212) 966-5154; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>PHIL COLLINS In his third New York solo show, this British artist presents two video pieces in which interviews with Turkish reality show participants and a series of karaoke performances create a kind of ambient documentary about life, television and the pursuit of celebrity. While the show is a bit short on artistic nutrients, the cumulative effect says almost more than is bearable about the combination of delusion and oppression that fuels everyday life. Tanya Bonakdar Gallery, 521 West 21st Street, Chelsea, (212) 414-4144; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
        <p>* Dan Fischer Velvety graphite drawings copied from Xerox copies of book and magazine images of well-known artists like Robert Smithson and Sol LeWitt and artworks like Jeff Koons's iconic ''Rabbit'' evoke and possibly satirize the reverence that some people feel for modern and contemporary art. Derek Eller, 615 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 206-6411; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>Daniel Johnston: 'The Story of an Artist' The nearly 70 ballpoint and felt-tip drawings by this semi-outsider artist, rock musician and 2006 Whitney Biennial pick don't live up to the hype, but they are fun to look at. In a distracted but versatile faux-adolescent style, the Texas-based Mr. Johnston creates sweet and sometimes hair-raising cartoon improvisations on themes of love, sex, hope, despair and death. Clementine, 632 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 243-5937; closes tomorrow. (Johnson)</p>
        <p>* FRANCIS PICABIA: 'WORKS ON PAPER, 1901-1951' Consistent with the predominantly linear, sometimes kitschy imagery of the artist's proto-postmodern transparency paintings, the 100 works on paper here reveal a lifelong involvement with drawing, marked by an indifference to notions of style, taste, consistency, skill or progress. It is both a challenge and a treat. Michael Werner, 4 East 77th Street, (212) 988-1623; closes tomorrow. (Smith)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
