<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Annan Faults 'Frightening Lack of Leadership' for Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="16climate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/16/world/16climate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kyoto Protocol</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettleman, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">United Nations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Annan, Kofi</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2D7173EF935A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Annan Faults 'Frightening Lack of Leadership' for Global Warming</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Annan Faults ‘Frightening Lack of Leadership’ for Global Warming</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN; Andrew C. Revkin contributed reporting from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gettleman, Jeffrey</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, Nov. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan puts blame for global warming on 'frightening lack of leadership'; says poorest people in world, who do not even create much pollution, bear brunt of rising temperatures; denies singling out United States, world's biggst source of smokestack and tailpipe gases, and also one of few countries that has not ratified Kyoto Protocol; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan on Wednesday put the blame for global warming on ''a frightening lack of leadership,'' saying the poorest people in the world, who do not even create much pollution, bear the brunt of rising temperatures.</p>
        <p>''The impact of climate change will fall disproportionately on the world's poorest countries, many of them here in Africa,'' Mr. Annan said in a speech to a major climate conference here. ''Poor people already live on the front lines of pollution, disaster and the degradation of resources and land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>U.N. Secretary General Kofi Annan also said the poorest people in the world bear the brunt of rising temperatures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary General Kofi Annan on Wednesday put the blame for global warming on ''a frightening lack of leadership,'' saying the poorest people in the world, who do not even create much pollution, bear the brunt of rising temperatures.</p>
        <p>''The impact of climate change will fall disproportionately on the world's poorest countries, many of them here in Africa,'' Mr. Annan said in a speech to a major climate conference here. ''Poor people already live on the front lines of pollution, disaster and the degradation of resources and land.</p>
        <p>''For them,'' the United Nations leader said, ''adaptation is a matter of sheer survival.''</p>
        <p>When pressed at a news conference afterward about his comments on poor leadership, Mr. Annan denied that he was singling out the United States, the world's biggest source of the smokestack and tailpipe gases that are linked by most scientists to rising temperatures. The United States is also one of the few countries that has not ratified the Kyoto Protocol, the first treaty setting limits on the heat-trapping pollutants.</p>
        <p>''My speech was not directed at a particular individual or leader,'' Mr. Annan said. ''I just want leaders around the world to show courage, because this is one of the greatest challenges of our time.''</p>
        <p>Among other issues, negotiators at the climate conference are exploring how to set new emissions limits for the period after 2012, when Kyoto's terms expire. Bush administration officials have said the United States has no plans to accept any binding limits.</p>
        <p>The delegation from the United States, meanwhile, denied that it was part of the leadership failure that Mr. Annan spoke about.</p>
        <p>Paula J. Dobriansky, the under secretary of state for democracy and global affairs, said Wednesday that ''we think the United States has been leading in its groundbreaking initiatives.'' She listed several measures, including financial incentives for businesses to reduce pollution and strict domestic rules that she said had helped in the fight against global warming.</p>
        <p>Each year thousands of environmental experts, government officials and activist groups gather for a nearly two-week-long conference on how to battle global warming.</p>
        <p>This year's conference in Nairobi, partly because it has drawn so many Africans, has focused on the possibility that those least responsible for pollution-induced climate change may suffer the most from it. Africa, one of the least industrialized areas in the world, is a case in point.</p>
        <p>The herders of Kenya's grassy plains, for example, whose total pollution basically boils down to their cooking fires and the few cigarettes they smoke, are being displaced by increasingly frequent droughts, which many scientists blame at least partly on global warming.</p>
        <p>Malaria, one of Africa's leading killers, is spreading to higher altitudes because of rising temperatures. The Sahara is expanding, turning farmland into desert and contributing to conflicts like the one in the Darfur region of Sudan. And the list goes on.</p>
        <p>''Africa faces some of the fiercest effects of climate change,'' Kenya's president, Mwai Kibaki, said in a speech on Wednesday at the climate conference. He said warmer temperatures could destroy agriculture and tourism, two of Kenya's brightest hopes for a way out of poverty.</p>
        <p>The emphasis on poor countries has led to another running theme at this year's climate caucus: adaptation. Experts and politicians concede that so much carbon dioxide, one of the dominant heat-trapping gases, has already accumulated in the atmosphere that the world must accept global warming and figure out how to adapt to it.</p>
        <p>''For too long the international community focused almost exclusively on mitigation,'' said Kivutha Kibwana, Kenya's environmental minister, who is president of the conference. ''Let Nairobi be the starting point whereby adaptation and mitigation efforts go hand in hand.''</p>
        <p>The conference has succeeded in establishing the broad outlines of an adaptation fund that calls for industrialized countries to help poor countries deal with the adverse effects of climate change through measures like relocating coastal people displaced by floods.</p>
        <p>Though the fund is still tiny, around $3 million, United Nations officials say that it will grow rapidly and that there is now a plan for how to manage it. Each country will get one vote, which will give the developing world a larger voice than that of industrialized nations.</p>
        <p>Still, much work remains, and the conference ends Friday. One bogged-down proposal is the effort to limit the average global temperature increase to 3.5 degrees Fahrenheit or so, which may not sound like much but would significantly change the environment. In the past century, average global temperatures have risen about 1 degree.</p>
        <p>Even moderate projections of warming under current emissions trends foresee four or five times that temperature increase by 2100, accompanied by a substantial rise in sea levels and disruption of climate patterns and water supplies.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, a group of island nations objected to the 3.5-degree ceiling, saying that even that would be too high for them to bear, because of all the flooding.</p>
        <p>Participants were also divided over the idea of a carbon dioxide tax. On Wednesday the president of Switzerland, Moritz Leuenberger, proposed using such a tax to finance adaptation programs. The tax would serve the dual purpose of discouraging rich countries from polluting and helping poor countries deal with the consequences of pollution.</p>
        <p>''This is not a fight against nature,'' Mr. Leuenberger said. ''It is a battle against shortsighted egoism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
