<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gas Giant Gets Offer For Buyout</title>
    <meta content="30deal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/30/business/30deal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Kinder Morgan Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDC1F3EF933A05756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gas Giant Gets Offer For Buyout</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gas Giant Gets Offer for Buyout</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN and JAD MOUAWAD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group led by Richard D. Kinder announced a buyout offer yesterday valued at $22 billion for Kinder Morgan Inc., the parent of the pipeline giant he founded in 1997.</p>
        <p>The deal, which includes the assumption of about $8 billion in debt, would be the largest leveraged buyout since Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company bought RJR Nabisco in 1989 for $25 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group led by Richard D. Kinder announced a buyout offer Monday valued at $22 billion for Kinder Morgan Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group led by Richard D. Kinder announced a buyout offer yesterday valued at $22 billion for Kinder Morgan Inc., the parent of the pipeline giant he founded in 1997.</p>
        <p>The deal, which includes the assumption of about $8 billion in debt, would be the largest leveraged buyout since Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company bought RJR Nabisco in 1989 for $25 billion.</p>
        <p>The offer by Mr. Kinder, a former president of Enron who was ousted after a dispute with Enron's founder, Kenneth L. Lay, is backed by a group of investors that includes Goldman Sachs, American International Group, the Carlyle Group and Riverstone Holdings. Mr. Kinder owns about 20 percent of Kinder Morgan.</p>
        <p>Under the buyout's proposal, shareholders of Kinder Morgan would receive $100 a share in cash, an 18.5 percent premium over the $84.41 closing price of Kinder Morgan's shares on Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinder; William Morgan, the company's co-founder; and two current directors, Fayez S. Sarofim, the billionaire financier, and Mike Morgan, William's Morgan son, will invest $2.8 billion in the transaction. The other investors will put in $4.5 billion. The group will also raise $14.5 billion to finance the rest of the deal.</p>
        <p>After leaving Enron at the end of 1996, Richard Kinder started a pipeline business by buying some of Enron's assets and quickly expanding through a series of mergers and acquisitions.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Kinder said he wanted to take the company private, in part because he thought that investors had ''discounted'' Kinder Morgan's shares, which have traded as high as $103.75 in the last year.</p>
        <p>He blamed the share slump on plans to build a $4 billion natural gas pipeline to link the Rocky Mountain region to the Eastern markets. While calling the offer fair, he said, ''Clearly I and the rest of the management team think this has very good value or we wouldn't be doing this.''</p>
        <p>But the offer is not without risk. Mr. Kinder's bid could put Kinder Morgan in play, opening it to rival offers. Late yesterday, energy investment bankers who were not involved in the deal had started calling clients to evaluate their interest in a competing bid.</p>
        <p>A special committee of Kinder Morgan's board has been formed to evaluate the offer. Typically in management buyouts, the buyers are eventually forced to increase their offer from their original bid to fend off counteroffers.</p>
        <p>''If someone wants to present themselves, so be it,'' he said. ''As someone once said, 'You're for sale every day on the New York Stock Exchange.' ''</p>
        <p>After leaving Enron, Mr. Kinder became known for his use of limited partnerships -- contractual arrangements giving investors a direct ownership interest in assets and redistributing most of their income each quarter to their shareholders. These partnerships bought stable assets like pipelines that generated steady cash flows and then grew through acquisitions -- increasing their payout.</p>
        <p>In 1997, when the limited partnership Kinder Morgan Energy Partners was created from the Enron assets, the general partnership had an enterprise value of $325 million, reflecting equity minus debt, and only a handful of assets. The company is now one of the largest publicly traded limited partnerships operating pipelines. According to its Web site, it now has an enterprise value of more than $13 billion.</p>
        <p>In 1999, Mr. Kinder engineered a merger between Kinder Morgan Energy Partners and KN Energy, a gas utility in the Midwest, which ultimately created Kinder Morgan Inc. That deal was followed by a number of smaller acquisitions that expanded its holdings in storage terminals, distribution networks and other so-called midstream assets.</p>
        <p>Kinder Morgan now operates about 43,000 miles of pipelines of natural gas, oil, petroleum products and carbon dioxide. It also runs more than 150 terminals for gasoline and other petroleum products and provides natural gas distribution service to over 1.1 million customers. Mr. Kinder receives an annual salary of one dollar and receives no bonus, options or restricted stock.</p>
        <p>Among its larger assets, Kinder Morgan owns Plantation Pipelines, one of the nation's main transportation networks for petroleum products, carrying gasoline from refineries on the Gulf Coast to markets on the Atlantic Coast.</p>
        <p>Bolstered by high energy prices, Kinder Morgan's latest project is to build a $4 billion, 1,300-mile natural gas pipeline linking the Rocky Mountains to markets in the East. Nicknamed the Rockies Express, the project would be one of the biggest new pipelines constructed in the United States in more than two decades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
