<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Momentary Pause</title>
    <meta content="26sun3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/26/opinion/26sun3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1749840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="The Rural Life"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1D61730F935A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Momentary Pause</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Momentary Pause</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERLYN KLINKENBORG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg, in Rural Life column, notes that it is only late March, but it feels as though time has almost stopped because he has been waiting eagerly for spring (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I have to keep reminding myself that it is only late March. I have been so eager for spring that it feels as though time has almost stopped. One reason may be that it was warm a few weeks ago and then the cold returned, putting the season on ice. But there is something else going on as well. Scientists say that spring comes earlier than it used to. The snow cover dwindles sooner and bud break comes earlier. And yet our awareness of that makes it feel as though spring comes even earlier than it is already coming. Global warming accelerates faster in our heads than it does in fact. March is not quite the new April yet.</p>
        <p>The other day I passed at least a hundred wild turkeys in separate flocks among the cornfields that line the highway. They were stooped over the stubble, somber backs perfectly rounded, except for a few that kept watch. Above them, the woods were every bit as bare as they were in mid-December. Every day I look for that first reddish flush along the tree line, or perhaps the eruption of a willow down in the valley. I passed a flock of Canada geese in the fields and had to remind myself that it was not quite time to be seeing their young. When I return home from the city, I find myself testing the ground underfoot as I walk to the mud room door in the dark. How much give is there? How long before it is time to start spading the garden? When will I start tracking mud into the house?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the country it's easy to find yourself leaning forward all through the year, always waiting on the next season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I have to keep reminding myself that it is only late March. I have been so eager for spring that it feels as though time has almost stopped. One reason may be that it was warm a few weeks ago and then the cold returned, putting the season on ice. But there is something else going on as well. Scientists say that spring comes earlier than it used to. The snow cover dwindles sooner and bud break comes earlier. And yet our awareness of that makes it feel as though spring comes even earlier than it is already coming. Global warming accelerates faster in our heads than it does in fact. March is not quite the new April yet.</p>
        <p>The other day I passed at least a hundred wild turkeys in separate flocks among the cornfields that line the highway. They were stooped over the stubble, somber backs perfectly rounded, except for a few that kept watch. Above them, the woods were every bit as bare as they were in mid-December. Every day I look for that first reddish flush along the tree line, or perhaps the eruption of a willow down in the valley. I passed a flock of Canada geese in the fields and had to remind myself that it was not quite time to be seeing their young. When I return home from the city, I find myself testing the ground underfoot as I walk to the mud room door in the dark. How much give is there? How long before it is time to start spading the garden? When will I start tracking mud into the house?</p>
        <p>For all this anticipation, a part of me wants to hold on to the old schedule. I remember a piece I wrote for this page five years ago noting that the garden was buried under 20 inches of snow. The date was April 2. It seemed like a betrayal at the time. But the wind has been blowing steadily for a month now. There has been little rain. The earth is chapped. Twenty inches of snow right now would bring out the curmudgeon in all of us who live here. There would be grousing and grumbling everywhere. But I have learned that all that grousing and grumbling usually conceals a satisfaction with the way things are. It is the wry, ironic language of the hardware store. The fact is, we need the moisture.</p>
        <p>In the country it's easy to find yourself leaning forward all through the year, always waiting on the next season, getting through your life as though you were walking into a stiff wind. This is one of those days when I catch myself in that posture -- pitched forward into the gale of time. So I'll try to slow down and straighten up. I'll walk down to the barnyard later this morning and fix the gate on the horse corral, which has sagged since the warm weather last month. It should be good for another year once I am done.</p>
        <p>VERLYN KLINKENBORG</p>
        <p>The Rural Life</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
