<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at the Pump, Circumspection by the Barrel</title>
    <meta content="07landler" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/07/weekinreview/07landler.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1759997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDA1F3FF934A35756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at the Pump, Circumspection by the Barrel</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Abroad at the Pump, Circumspection by the Barrel</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>MUNICH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Soaring of gasoline prices prompts howls of anguish in US, but only mild discomfort in Europe, Japan and other countries that pay far more at pump; steep gasoline taxes make Europeans less sensitive to surges in wholesale price of crude oil than Americans are; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE German mass-market newspaper Bild carried a banner headline last week complaining about all the new taxes being proposed by the government: a higher sales tax, a health care tax and a surtax on rich people.</p>
        <p>Nowhere did it mention fuel taxes, which account for more than half of every euro spent at the gas pump. On that very day, gasoline had hit the equivalent of $6.40 a gallon. But even at today's prices, few people here are calling for gasoline taxes to be cut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lack of debate about gasoline prices in Europe is instructive at a time when American politicians are scrambling to soothe angry constituents with ill-fated proposals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE German mass-market newspaper Bild carried a banner headline last week complaining about all the new taxes being proposed by the government: a higher sales tax, a health care tax and a surtax on rich people.</p>
        <p>Nowhere did it mention fuel taxes, which account for more than half of every euro spent at the gas pump. On that very day, gasoline had hit the equivalent of $6.40 a gallon. But even at today's prices, few people here are calling for gasoline taxes to be cut.</p>
        <p>The lack of debate about gasoline prices in Europe is instructive at a time when American politicians are scrambling to soothe their angry constituents with ill-fated proposals like a $100 rebate for motorists.</p>
        <p>It's not that Europeans like paying $6 a gallon to fill up their Fiats. Nor do they relish paying taxes; Bild warns that the new taxes being proposed could strangle Germany's economic rebound. But for now, people here seem to agree that taxing gasoline is both necessary -- as a way to raise money to pay down their huge public debts -- and beneficial for the environment.</p>
        <p>So while the latest spike in fuel prices has provoked howls of anguish from many Americans, Europeans have reacted like, well, Europeans -- with a mixture of weary resignation, halfhearted anger toward ''price-gouging'' oil companies and bemusement at the furor across the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>''We've been debating these issues intensely for the last few decades, while the Americans were paying no attention to them,'' said Hans-Werner Sinn, the president of the Ifo Institute for Economic Research here. ''People have gotten tired of talking about it, quite frankly.''</p>
        <p>Other countries with high gas prices are coping quietly as well. In Japan, people are turning to self-service gas stations, which are a few pennies a gallon cheaper. Truckmakers are giving drivers lessons on how to avoid wasting fuel (do not put the pedal to the metal when accelerating).</p>
        <p>Gasoline in Japan costs nearly twice what it does in the United States because of the taxes. The other high-tax countries include Europe's two big oil producers, Norway and Britain, as well as Turkey, South Korea and Poland.</p>
        <p>Perhaps surprising, the steep taxes make Europeans less sensitive to surges in the wholesale price of crude oil than Americans, for whom the producer's price represents far more of the total. In addition, many of the taxes here are fixed, allowing only the underlying oil price to fluctuate.</p>
        <p>In the United States, some of the taxes, though lower over all, are levied as a percentage of the oil price, which means a jump in the price of a barrel has an even more pronounced effect at the pump.</p>
        <p>Europe, in addition, is reaping the benefits of trying to cut its dependence on fossil fuels: it has smaller cars and better public transportation. Not least, these days, it has the help of a strong currency, the euro, which acts as a hedge against changes in the dollar-denominated oil market.</p>
        <p>Despite this, a few Europeans are starting to point fingers. Last week, Luxembourg's prime minister, Jean-Claude Juncker, called on the European Union to impose a windfall profit tax on oil companies, which he said were ''starting to irritate parts of our public opinion.''</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether his proposal will get any farther than a similar one in the Congress, which President Bush has threatened to veto. Some of Europe's equanimity may have to do with a simple change in the public mood: the economy, after three years of sputtering, has begun to rev up.</p>
        <p>''When gas prices went up two years ago, we were able to live off it for days,'' said Klaus-Peter Siegloch, the head of news for the German television network ZDF. ''Now we barely put it on TV.''</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
