<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wary of Bureaucrats, Beachfront Property Owners Oppose Effort to Stop Erosion</title>
    <meta content="15dunes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/15/nyregion/15dunes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coastal Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dunes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFD9163FF936A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wary of Bureaucrats, Beachfront Property Owners Oppose Effort to Stop Erosion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wary of Bureaucrats, Beachfront Property Owners Oppose Effort to Stop Erosion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS; Bruce Lambert contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald; Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Beachfront property owners in New Jersey and Long Island oppose United States Army Corps of Engineers 50-year plan of beach replenishment and dune construction; say plan requires broad property easements in perpetuity, giving corps carte blanche, and does not require corps to maintain dunes, repair damage to views or remove any danger created for swimmers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, residents of barrier islands such as Long Beach Island in New Jersey have lived precariously on the front lines of an ever-shifting battle between people and the forces of nature: enjoying the seasonal profit and glamour of oceanfront property while knowing that in the long run, the sands will succumb to the forces of waves and wind.</p>
        <p>Enter the United States Army Corps of Engineers and the state Department of Environmental Protection with a long-studied, 50-year beach replenishment and dune construction program that they say is necessary to stave off nature's onslaught, at least temporarily, in some 20 communities along the island, an 18-mile-long sliver of land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oceanfront property owners in New Jersey and Long Island don't want to grant large easements to lawmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, residents of barrier islands such as Long Beach Island in New Jersey have lived precariously on the front lines of an ever-shifting battle between people and the forces of nature: enjoying the seasonal profit and glamour of oceanfront property while knowing that in the long run, the sands will succumb to the forces of waves and wind.</p>
        <p>Enter the United States Army Corps of Engineers and the state Department of Environmental Protection with a long-studied, 50-year beach replenishment and dune construction program that they say is necessary to stave off nature's onslaught, at least temporarily, in some 20 communities along the island, an 18-mile-long sliver of land.</p>
        <p>The $71 million plan -- 65 percent of it financed by federal funds and 35 percent paid for by the state -- calls for dune construction that would put 11 million cubic yards of new sand on the shore. Earth movers would cast it all to create and firm up 125-foot-deep beaches, as well as dunes that are at least 22 feet above the mean high tide point and 30 feet wide. Every five years, engineers would add more sand, if necessary, to maintain the new shoreline.</p>
        <p>By cost, volume of sand and distance covered, it is the largest single beach replenishment and dune construction program ever in New Jersey, according to Army Corps officials.</p>
        <p>But hundreds of shorefront property owners and surfing groups are wary of the plan and are balking at some parts of it, much to the chagrin of lawmakers and the Army Corps, who have fought for nearly a decade to get Congressional approval of the appropriation.</p>
        <p>At the core of the concerns are the broad easements that homeowners must grant to allow the bulking up of the existing dunes that are technically on their property and in front of their homes. The easements are in perpetuity, they say, and specify no limitations on dune size. Some homeowners also argue that the easements do not include any requirement that the Army Corps maintain the dunes, repair any damage to the views or remove any danger created for swimmers.</p>
        <p>''They want to do things on a massive scale and want us to give bureaucrats carte blanche in perpetuity,'' said Eugene Schulz, a Brant Beach resident, whose home sits relatively well protected behind and atop a massive dune. ''Nobody is opposed to a moderate program and to easements with some parameters. But I just think this is just a big thing to justify the Corps and the D.E.P.'s existence.''</p>
        <p>For surfers like John Weber, executive director of the New Jersey Surfrider Foundation, there is a fear that the Army Corps's engineering will remake the underlying sea bottom, scouring out deep and dangerous pools for swimmers and eliminating the close-in wave action favored by surfers.</p>
        <p>Such sentiments are not universal on the island. Residents whose homes are not bordering the beach and those whose homes face Manahawkin Bay, are all for the program, which the Army Corps said would not only stem beach erosion but also protect the island and its brisk summer commerce from storms. But to go through with it, the engineers must get agreement on the easements from about 900 owners whose homes butt up against the sandy shore.</p>
        <p>Work was scheduled to start this month but without all the easement agreements signed, that is unlikely. The delay places the federal money in peril; it will be taken back if none is spent by the end of the federal fiscal year on Sept. 30. The state allocation, which is a matching percentage of the federal money, would disappear as well.</p>
        <p>''The key here is for at least one town to get their easements from residents and get started,'' said Jonathan Oldham, the mayor of Harvey Cedars, a tiny community near the northern tip of the island. ''If we miss this opportunity it won't come again for a long, long time.''</p>
        <p>State Senator Leonard T. Connors Jr., who is also the mayor of Surf City, was more blunt about the impact of inaction. ''This is like throwing federal money into the sea,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The dispute is not restricted to New Jersey. On Long Beach in New York, whose 50,000 residents make it the most densely populated waterfront in Nassau and Suffolk Counties, debates are raging over a similar plan to build high dunes to preserve the beach and shoreline. Among the issues are that dunes would block the views from some apartments in the buildings lining the boardwalk, and that they would enable people to hop over the railing to the beach without paying at the entrance booths. Residents also complain that the dredged sand would be coarser and darker than the light ''sugar'' sand there now.</p>
        <p>The disputes come as coastal geologists are reaching the conclusion that the sea will eventually have its way with barrier islands. Norbert P. Psuty, a professor at Rutgers University's Marine and Coastal Sciences Center, said that the barrier islands emerged about 3,000 years ago, when sea levels around the globe stabilized, allowing a relative surplus of sand and sediment in shoreline systems to accrete and grow vertically.</p>
        <p>But stabilization, he pointed out, is a relative term. Storms, winds and waves shape and reshape the islands, causing them to move and migrate closer to the coast, and wax and wane in width, all in a stubborn attempt to maintain themselves.</p>
        <p>Systems of dunes have emerged in recent years as one of the major tools, followed by beach replenishment, employed by the Army Corps of Engineers and state coastal management agencies to withstand or at least blunt the ocean forces, Dr. Psuty said. The method became an article of faith for those seeking to stave off erosion and the ravages of storms.</p>
        <p>''But it was more subjective than scientific,'' said Dr. Psuty of the man-made efforts.</p>
        <p>Keith Watson, the Army Corps' project director for the Long Beach Island program, said though, that after years of study, the agency had determined that ''adding sand to the systems'' affecting the shore was the best solution to storms and erosion. How to get people to accept it is another matter.</p>
        <p>''The dynamics of barrier islands are determined by nature, and we will eventually figure that out,'' he said. ''But people and human behavior, that, we may never understand.'' Mayors of towns on the island have reacted differently to the impasse. Mr. Connors of Surf City is losing patience. Fourteen of the 25 shorefront property owners in his town have signed the easements, and he has proposed an ordinance that would require those who do not participate in the program to repair their own dunes at a cost that could run into the tens of thousands of dollars per homeowner.</p>
        <p>In Harvey Cedars, where half of the 82 residents who need to sign the easements have done so, Mr. Oldham is a bit more optimistic. He thinks that between now and Sept. 30, the rest of the residents will agree to the easements.</p>
        <p>But Dianne C. Gove, the mayor of Long Beach Township, the island's largest municipality, said that it might not be so easy. In her town, only 40 property owners of the 600 who need to grant easements have signed on to the program, she said.</p>
        <p>Residents of some of the wealthier areas such as Loveladies and North Beach, where $4 million homes are not uncommon, have also criticized an additional state requirement that there be access to the beach every quarter mile along the main road down the spine of the island, rather than every half mile as recommended by the Army Corps. The rationale for this requirement is that lawmakers do not want tax money to be spent solely for the benefit of owners of private property. In the wealthier areas, many people seeking beach access are greeted with no trespassing signs at driveway entrances.</p>
        <p>But even in the less wealthy areas of the town, where there is beach access at every block, some homeowners are resisting giving the Army Corps the right to place restrooms at some of these access roads and against their small lots, also a requirement for spending tax dollars.</p>
        <p>Kenneth A. Porro, a lawyer who has been hired by more than 100 of the residents, said that the major concern of most is the breadth of the easements themselves, and he is pressing state and federal officials to negotiate some limitations with his clients or face a court challenge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
