<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passage of Energy Measure Appears Assured as Senate Begins Debate</title>
    <meta content="27energy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/27/washington/27energy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1778781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royalties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gulf of Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Gulf of Mexico</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D7153FF934A15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passage of Energy Measure Appears Assured as Senate Begins Debate</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Senate Passage of Energy Bill Appears Assured</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate shows bipartisan support for bill that would expand energy production in Gulf of Mexico; consensus may be fragile, and bill, if approved in final vote, would have to be reconciled with different drilling bill approved by House; bill identifies 8.3 million acres for new energy development in gulf; it would create protections for Florida's western coastline and give other gulf states percentage of royalties that now accrue to government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate moved closer on Wednesday to passing a bill that would expand energy production in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>A procedural vote of 86 to 12 allowing the debate to begin signaled wide support for opening up large new tracts for drilling. Thirty-one Democrats and one independent joined all but one Republican, Olympia J. Snowe of Maine, in the early test vote, usually a strong indicator of a bill's potential to pass with bipartisan support.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A procedural vote signaled wide support for opening up large new tracts for drilling in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate moved closer on Wednesday to passing a bill that would expand energy production in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>A procedural vote of 86 to 12 allowing the debate to begin signaled wide support for opening up large new tracts for drilling. Thirty-one Democrats and one independent joined all but one Republican, Olympia J. Snowe of Maine, in the early test vote, usually a strong indicator of a bill's potential to pass with bipartisan support.</p>
        <p>But the consensus may be fragile, and the bill, if approved in a final vote that is expected next week, would still have to be reconciled with a very different drilling bill approved by the House.</p>
        <p>The bill identifies 8.3 million acres for new energy development in the gulf, four times the area sought by the Bush administration through its lease program for 2007-12. It would also create protections for Florida's western coastline and establish a program that gives other gulf states -- Texas, Louisiana, Mississippi and Alabama -- 37.5 percent of royalties from energy production that now accrue to the federal government, potentially a shift of billions of dollars in revenues.</p>
        <p>Republicans as well as some Democrats from energy-rich states have long sought efforts to increase domestic supplies of oil and natural gas as a way to reduce the high costs of gasoline and home heating fuel and to reducing the nation's dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Democrats generally favor conservation and the development of alternative fuels as part of any major energy legislation. But many of them followed Senator Harry Reid of Nevada, the minority leader, in voting for the bill as a way to support Senator Mary L. Landrieu of Louisiana, one of just a few Democratic senators from the South, whose re-election prospects in 2008 would be enhanced by the revenue-sharing provisions for a state still recovering from last year's hurricanes.</p>
        <p>''I think the vote reflects the Senate's recognition that this focused, bipartisan energy bill is the most important thing we can do in the near term to ease our energy supplies and stabilize energy prices,'' said Senator Pete V. Domenici, Republican of New Mexico, who is chairman of the energy committee and chief sponsor of the bill.</p>
        <p>In remarks on the Senate floor before the vote, Ms. Landrieu called the bill ''balanced, smart, necessary and needed.''</p>
        <p>Pointing to a photograph taken after Hurricane Katrina that showed a submerged federal highway leading to Louisiana's main oil and gas port, she said the percentage that states would receive was fair. ''We're not trying to be hogs, but we're drowning down here,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Despite the one-sided nature of the vote, the measure still faces uncertainties. Senate support, especially among Democrats, is likely to erode after an expected decision by Senator Bill Frist of Tennessee, the majority leader, not to accept major amendments.</p>
        <p>''The goal is to keep the bill clean,'' said Carolyn Weyforth, a spokeswoman for Mr. Frist.</p>
        <p>That prospect angered several Democrats, including Senator Jeff Bingaman of New Mexico, the ranking member of the energy committee, who voted for the motion to proceed but said he would vote against final passage. Mr. Bingaman called the bill ''seriously flawed'' for including coastal protections limited to Florida and for its revenue-sharing arrangement.</p>
        <p>''We need good, long-term energy and fiscal policy for the country,'' Mr. Bingaman said. ''Our energy problems cry out for thoughtful solutions.''</p>
        <p>Senator Ron Wyden of Oregon, a Democrat who voted against the motion to proceed, said Republicans were carrying out ''business as usual'' in keeping the Senate's only major energy bill this year narrow in scope.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wyden called on Mr. Frist to consider amendments that would address fuel efficiency standards for cars, price-gouging measures directed toward oil companies, development of renewable energy sources and elimination of tax credits for oil companies that are reporting record profits.</p>
        <p>''This subject is too important to ban the Senate from offering meaningful amendments,'' Mr. Wyden said.</p>
        <p>Other problems loom in negotiations with the House, which last month passed a much broader measure for drilling in coastal waters. The House bill would end 25-year-old federal bans on drilling off the Atlantic and Pacific coasts and give all coastal states new controls over drilling.</p>
        <p>Senate leaders say they doubt that any drilling legislation beyond the narrow scope of the gulf measure could pass in the time remaining for legislation this year while House leaders say they are eager to negotiate a final bill that looks more like their approach.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard W. Pombo, the California Republican who heads the Resources Committee, said in an interview that he would be open to changes, including the kind the Senate leadership is resisting, like new fuel efficiency standards for cars, if they would help achieve compromise legislation that could pass both houses.</p>
        <p>''At this point, just about everything is on the table to consider,'' Mr. Pombo said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Landrieu said in an interview that she recognized that the Senate bill was only ''half the solution.''</p>
        <p>''But it's an important half,'' she added, describing herself as cautiously optimistic that enough Senate Democrats would sustain their support to get the bill passed.</p>
        <p>''Normally, I don't support limiting amendments,'' Ms. Landrieu said, ''but we're very limited on time in the session and in this Congress. I support Frist's decision. Debating the pros and cons of additional elements only get us off track.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
