<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calendar: New York by Foot and Boat</title>
    <meta content="03cal" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/03/garden/03cal.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1780471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D6103FF930A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calendar: New York by Foot and Boat</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Calendar: New York by Foot and Boat</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment; (718) 788-8500, extension 208.</p>
        <p>Sharon Seitz and Stuart Miller, the authors of The Other Islands of New York City: A History and Guide (Countryman Press, 2001), will lead a tour by water taxi to Roosevelt Island, and Randalls, Wards and the Brother islands, on Sunday from 9 a.m. to noon. Advance payment, $50 (members, students and those 63 and older, $40), is required for this tour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York by Foot and Boat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment; (718) 788-8500, extension 208.</p>
        <p>Sharon Seitz and Stuart Miller, the authors of The Other Islands of New York City: A History and Guide (Countryman Press, 2001), will lead a tour by water taxi to Roosevelt Island, and Randalls, Wards and the Brother islands, on Sunday from 9 a.m. to noon. Advance payment, $50 (members, students and those 63 and older, $40), is required for this tour.</p>
        <p>Other tours include a walk following the path of the High Line, the abandoned elevated railway slated to become a park, on Aug. 12 at 11 a.m.; the Boerum Hill neighborhood in Brooklyn on Aug. 19 at 10:30 a.m.; and a walk in Green-Wood Cemetery to the graves of influential women, on Aug. 20 at 1 p.m. The fee for each tour is $11; members, $9; students and those 63 and older, $8. Meeting places are available by phone or at www.bcue.org.</p>
        <p>International Flavors</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden, 200th Street and Southern Boulevard, the Bronx; (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>There will be a series of demonstrations and events for children during August in the plots known as the global gardens in the Ruth Rea Howell Family Garden. These plots, growing produce from other countries, have been cared for by volunteers, who will be on hand each day from 1 to 5:30 p.m. to talk about the plants. On Saturdays and Sundays, visitors can sample dishes made from the garden harvest.</p>
        <p>The global gardens will be featured as follows: the China Garden, through Aug. 6; the Korea Garden, from Aug. 8 to 13; the Italy and Ireland Gardens, from Aug. 15 to 20; and the Caribbean Garden, from Aug. 22 to 27.</p>
        <p>The botanical garden is open Tuesday through Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission, Friday through Sunday and Monday holidays, $18; students and those 65 and older, $16; Tuesday through Thursday, $15; students and those 65 and older, $13, children, 2 to 12, all times, $5.</p>
        <p>Designs Intricate and Fantastic</p>
        <p>Bard Graduate Center for Studies in the Decorative Arts, Design and Culture, 18 West 86th Street; (212) 501-3000.</p>
        <p>Two exhibitions will be at Bard through Oct. 15. The first, Sheila Hicks: Weaving as Metaphor, features 150 small woven textiles created by the artist over the last 50 years. The detailed works, made of such materials as cotton, wool, linen, silk, goat hair, alpaca, paper, leather and metal, provided Ms. Hicks with a form for creative expression and a manageable way to master techniques and styles used for large-scale textiles and site installations.</p>
        <p>Lions, Dragons and Other Beasts: Aquamanilia of the Middle Ages, Vessels for Church and Table is an exhibition of aquamanilia, the medieval vessels used for washing before mass and serving water in wealthier households. The hollow-cast vessels, which had an opening for filling the container and a spout for pouring, were shaped like fantastic animals and figures. Most of the works are from the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art.</p>
        <p>Open Tuesday through Sunday, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. (Thursday evenings until 8). Admission is $3; those 65 and older, $2; children under 12, no charge.</p>
        <p>Kites at Rest</p>
        <p>World Financial Center Winter Garden, 220 Vesey Street; (212) 945-0505.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of 258 kites made by Buteo Huang, a kite master from Taiwan, will be on display through Aug. 19. The kites are shaped like animals, seashells, boats, dragons and abstract designs. Open daily 9 a.m. to 11 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>Alfresco Artworks</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway at Washington Avenue; (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>Graffiti, an exhibition of large-scale paintings by graffiti artists known for painting artworks and signatures on walls, subway cars and other surfaces, will be at the museum through Sept. 3. The artists in the exhibition include Michael Tracy, who had the tag, or signature, Tracy 168; Melvin Samuels Jr. (NOC 167); Sandra Fabara (Lady Pink); and Chris Ellis (Daze).</p>
        <p>Open Wednesday through Friday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturday and Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. (open on the first Saturday of every month until 11 p.m.). Admission is $8; students and those 62 and older, $4; children under 12, no charge.</p>
        <p>Ellsworth Kelly: Botanical Prints</p>
        <p>AXA Gallery, 787 Seventh Avenue (51st Street); (212) 554-1704.</p>
        <p>Drawn From Nature: The Plant Lithographs of Ellsworth Kelly, an exhibition of all of the artists plant lithographs, will be at the gallery through Aug. 14. Mr. Kelly, whose work is known for its simplicity of line and shape, has made several series of prints inspired by nature, including Twelve Leaves (1978); Series of Plant and Flower Lithographs (1983 to 1985) and Oak Leaves (1992). Open Monday through Friday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturday, noon to 5 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>Art and Nature</p>
        <p>Wave Hill, Independence Avenue and West 249th Street, Riverdale, the Bronx; (718) 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Two exhibitions are taking place at Wave Hill. Garden Improvement, in the Glyndor Gallery on the grounds through Aug. 27, examines how people remake nature so it is more personal and domesticated. The projects include a bird observation area with chairs made of tractor parts and ornate birdhouses mounted on ornamented poles, and picnic tables made of wood from trees that are endangered due to deforestation or damaged by acid rain. There is also a solar-powered, portable fountain, and a video of its journey from Brooklyn to the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The second exhibition, which will run through Oct. 31, is Please, Please, Pleased to Meetcha, an outdoor audio installation by Nina Katchadourian. The work consists of a series of bird songs, which have been transliterated by several translators from the United Nations from the natural bird sounds to the songs as they are pronounced by the human voice. Recordings of birds and human interpretations have been placed in the branches of various trees on the grounds. The title of the exhibition is similar to the song of the chestnut-sided warbler, a bird common to Wave Hill.</p>
        <p>The grounds at Wave Hill are open Tuesday through Sunday, from 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. (until 9 p.m. on Wednesdays in June and July). The galleries are open Tuesday through Sunday, from 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. (until 8 p.m. on Wednesdays in June and July). Admission is $4; students and those 65 and older, $2; free all day on Tuesdays and Saturday, from 9 a.m. to noon.</p>
        <p>Design From Finland</p>
        <p>Scandinavia House, 58 Park Avenue (38th Street); (212) 847-9717.</p>
        <p>From Wood to Architecture, an exhibition of photographs, drawings and models featuring recent projects in Finland, including houses, cultural centers and churches, will continue through Aug. 25. Open Tuesday-Saturday, noon to 6 p.m. Admission is $3.</p>
        <p>Garden Glasswares</p>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden, 200th Street and Southern Boulevard, the Bronx; (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of glass sculpture by Dale Chihuly will be at the garden through Oct. 29. The installation will feature thousands of blown-glass works in the Haupt Conservatory and in the pools surrounding the glass house.</p>
        <p>The garden and the conservatory are open Tuesday through Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Advance purchase of timed-admission tickets is required for the Chihuly show. Tickets, $20; students and those 65 and older, $18; children, 2 to 12, $5.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
