<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Stresses Tax Cuts in Address Reprising Early Themes</title>
    <meta content="05pataki" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/05/nyregion/metrocampaigns/05pataki.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1729725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Speeches and Statements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speeches and Statements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DF1E30F936A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Stresses Tax Cuts in Address Reprising Early Themes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pataki Stresses Tax Cuts in Address Reprising Early Themes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM; Michael Cooper contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Jan. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his final State of the State address, Gov. George E. Pataki tried Wednesday to recapture part of the formula that got him elected nearly a dozen years ago, offering a wide array of tax cuts, crime-fighting strategies and environmental measures.</p>
        <p>Specifically, the governor called for eliminating the so-called marriage penalty in the tax code, cutting state income tax rates, ending the state's estate tax and providing property tax rebates. The proposals come a day after the governor said the state was projected to have a $2 billion surplus in a total budget of $106.7 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his final State of the State speech, Gov. George E. Pataki tried to recapture some of what got him elected nearly 12 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his final State of the State address, Gov. George E. Pataki tried Wednesday to recapture part of the formula that got him elected nearly a dozen years ago, offering a wide array of tax cuts, crime-fighting strategies and environmental measures.</p>
        <p>Specifically, the governor called for eliminating the so-called marriage penalty in the tax code, cutting state income tax rates, ending the state's estate tax and providing property tax rebates. The proposals come a day after the governor said the state was projected to have a $2 billion surplus in a total budget of $106.7 billion.</p>
        <p>''We've proven time and again how tax cuts create the financial freedom that yields even greater opportunities for New York citizens,'' Mr. Pataki said, in an address that lasted just shy of an hour and ran for about 6,600 words.</p>
        <p>But if his 12th address to open the legislative season appeared intended for a broad audience as he ponders a run for the presidency, it lacked the teeth of the speeches of his early years, and their more conservative appeals to fiscal austerity. Even the reform-minded message of his speech a year ago was largely absent, even though many of his previous proposals remain undone, including campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Instead of spending cuts, there were more potentially costly undertakings, focused largely on the environment and education. His proposals to reduce dependence on foreign oil included putting alternative fuels at service stations along the New York State Thruway and providing incentives to bring ethanol refineries to the state. He said he would seek free tuition for public university students who pursue math and science degrees and also agree to teach in the state.</p>
        <p>But his failure to address a legal battle over school financing in the speech drew criticism, even within his own party.</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, a Republican, standing with his schools chancellor, Joel I. Klein, said after the speech that he would rather see the state's budget surplus used to begin complying with a court order requiring the state to spend billions of dollars more on the city's public schools. The Pataki administration is appealing that order.</p>
        <p>''I think lower taxes would stimulate the economy, but first and foremost for New York City, we need monies that the state, the courts say, owe us,'' the mayor said.</p>
        <p>Details of what the governor's proposals would cost the state will have to wait until Mr. Pataki proposes his budget later this month. While a surplus is expected for this year, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, also a Republican, said on Wednesday that he expected a $1.5 billion deficit in the coming fiscal year, ending in March 2007.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who has been accused of becoming part of the dysfunctional Albany political system he once promised to reshape, spent the day trying to be conciliatory; he even appeared at a brunch held by his top Democratic antagonist, Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, and invoked President Kennedy in his speech to the Legislature.</p>
        <p>''I was 15 years old when I heard President John F. Kennedy's inaugural address, and like so many Americans of my generation, I was inspired by the energy, optimism and patriotism of his message,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silver did not appear ready for an olive branch. ''In college, I remember a president named John F. Kennedy who was quite inspiring,'' he said, in opening a press conference to respond to the governor's speech. ''He's no John Kennedy. The governor has the opportunity to establish the legacy for the benefit of New Yorkers, not for the benefit of Republican primary voters in Iowa and New Hampshire or elsewhere in the country.''</p>
        <p>Alan G. Hevesi, the Democratic state comptroller, faulted the governor's focus on cutting taxes, saying, ''Tax cuts, with no spending cuts, means more deficits, means more debt.'' That debt, he added, ''means our children will be paying for these tax cuts, so let's see if he fills that gap in the budget.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi added that he had heard ''nothing about public authorities reform, procurement reform, about debt reform, about fiscal reform.''</p>
        <p>Republicans had kinder words, with Mr. Bruno calling the speech ''a great overview.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''we never met a tax cut that we don't embrace.''</p>
        <p>John Faso, a former assemblyman and a candidate to succeed Mr. Pataki, said, ''I thought he focused on the transcendent issue that faces America, which is how do we compete in the global economy.''</p>
        <p>The speech comes as Mr. Pataki courts a much different audience these days: the bedrock Republicans to whom he must appeal should he pursue a presidential run in 2008. He has been spending time in New Hampshire and Iowa in recent months trying to build support, and by returning to the early themes he used to build a reputation as tax-cutting Northeastern governor, he could be re-establishing his credentials on the right.</p>
        <p>Many of his crime measures were familiar. He proposed once again to offer legislation this year for creating a civil confinement system to prevent the release of sexual predators who have finished their prison terms. He also proposed to end the statute of limitations on rape and other sexual assaults, and to require criminals to submit DNA samples to be compiled in a database. He did not bring up the state's death penalty, which he pushed through after becoming governor, but which was recently struck down by the courts.</p>
        <p>His tax cuts were the most sweeping proposals. In addition to calling for the elimination of the tax disadvantage for married couples, and proposing unspecified income tax cuts, Mr. Pataki proposed providing a $500 ''heating fuel tax credit'' to the elderly, eliminating the state's portion of the estate tax, cutting business taxes and providing partial rebates of school property taxes.</p>
        <p>While state officials provided few details, eliminating the marriage penalty could save families several hundred dollars, or even thousands, depending on income and situation. In one hypothetical case provided by the State Division of Budget, a married couple with two children, using the standard deduction and with a combined income of $150,000, would save $821 under the plan to eliminate the penalty. And perhaps trying to couch it in a manner to appeal to more conservative voters, Mr. Pataki portrayed the plan as a ''pro-family tax cut.''</p>
        <p>But he also portrayed himself as a centrist brand of Republican governor, citing among his achievements a seven-state pact to reduce global warming emissions from power plants, a topic largely rejected by Republicans in Washington.</p>
        <p>''For him, I think the goal of the speech was to write the first draft of his legacy,'' said Blair Horner, the legislative director with the New York Public Interest Research Group. ''He's clearly presenting himself as kind of an innovative, progressive Republican. I could make arguments for why all of those things aren't true, but that's what he stands for.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
