<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Real Estate When It Fizzles</title>
    <meta content="l29housing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1786229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC113EF93AA1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Real Estate When It Fizzles</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Read Between All Those For-Sale Signs'' (Week in Review, Aug. 27) speculated that a real estate crash is unlikely. One of the pivotal reasons used to illustrate this unlikelihood is that ''homes seem to be much less vulnerable to crashes than other assets, because people rarely sell them in a panic.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Read Between All Those For-Sale Signs'' (Week in Review, Aug. 27) speculated that a real estate crash is unlikely. One of the pivotal reasons used to illustrate this unlikelihood is that ''homes seem to be much less vulnerable to crashes than other assets, because people rarely sell them in a panic.''</p>
        <p>That is exactly why I feel a real estate crash is inevitable.</p>
        <p>The rapid rise of prices has changed the primary function of houses and apartments from homes to investments in many people's eyes. The more this shift takes hold, the more likely a crash.</p>
        <p>People may tend to hold on to their homes in a panic, but if history has taught us anything, it is that people all too often do sell off investments in such a way.</p>
        <p>Noel Dinneen  New York, Aug. 27, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Living on wishful thinking can have disastrous consequences, yet borrowing against an uncertain future did not bother scores of multiple bidders and self-styled real estate speculators.</p>
        <p>Incomprehensibly, in the last three years, the more prices leaped, the greater the interest in dubious properties by average-salary earners. Homeowners and brokers were not to blame for the escalation, but a delusional feeding frenzy that seemed to infect otherwise sane people everywhere.</p>
        <p>Now we face an overdue and welcome reality check, not a bursting bubble or a crash.</p>
        <p>Laura Lombardo Zirulnik  Scotch Plains, N.J., Aug. 28, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Housing Gets Ugly,'' by Paul Krugman (column, Aug. 25):</p>
        <p>While a downturn in the economy is not a good thing -- even for environmentalists like myself -- there is a lesson in all this for the building industry. It needs to learn from its counterparts in other major industries who are beginning to see ''greener.''</p>
        <p>We have a limited amount of land and clearly cannot continue building larger and larger houses on more and more green spaces. Also, we cannot continue to erect buildings that will produce more and more carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Our ancestors knew how to build on an island. Our cities need to become more ''Manhattans,'' yet with green spaces as well.</p>
        <p>Tearing up the countryside, using virgin materials and making inefficient structures is not the way to go for the housing industry, if it is to make a contribution to sustainability.</p>
        <p>Dorothee E. Krahn  Silver Spring, Md., Aug. 25, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
