<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Happened to Those Frozen Ponds and Warm Fires?</title>
    <meta content="22njCOLUMN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1733833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DF123FF931A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Happened to Those Frozen Ponds and Warm Fires?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terry Golway</byline>
      <dateline>MAPLEWOOD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEAR a pond across from the sturdy municipal building here, there's a big sign posted on a tree that reads, NO SKATING. To which the only reply can be, NO KIDDING. If there's any ice to be found in the vicinity, it was dumped there by late-night revelers with to-go cups.</p>
        <p>They just don't make winter like they used to. And for those of us who get through summer's heat and humidity with dreams of ice-covered ponds, pickup hockey games and skating hand in hand, this is all bad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEAR a pond across from the sturdy municipal building here, there's a big sign posted on a tree that reads, NO SKATING. To which the only reply can be, NO KIDDING. If there's any ice to be found in the vicinity, it was dumped there by late-night revelers with to-go cups.</p>
        <p>They just don't make winter like they used to. And for those of us who get through summer's heat and humidity with dreams of ice-covered ponds, pickup hockey games and skating hand in hand, this is all bad.</p>
        <p>Never mind the brief cold snap last weekend that turned the state's roads into luge runs. What was remarkable about that frigid blast was the reaction that greeted it. A friend of mind, Les Hollander of Madison, noted that he went for a run on Saturday afternoon in short sleeves. Six hours later, his dinner guests were scraping ice off their windshields.</p>
        <p>That's what winter has become -- an annoying dinner guest who shows up unannounced, causes momentary chaos, and departs without leaving an impression.</p>
        <p>Some winterists (those with a bias against a perfectly good time of the year) may well regard the season's disappearance as the positive side of global warming. Oh, sure, it's a shame about those polar ice caps, and we all feel bad about the reindeer in the Circle formerly known as ''Arctic,'' but isn't it great to be wearing short-sleeved golf shirts in January? Being in New Jersey in January almost as good as being in Florida, and there's no wait for the early bird special.</p>
        <p>Personally, I don't see the point in living in a congested, densely populated, highly taxed blue state if we don't get the benefits of being, well, blue -- as in cold, not depressed. And one of those benefits ought to be a nice smooth-as-glass glaze over that pond by Maplewood Town Hall.</p>
        <p>Actually, it's not a pond, but rather a little perk Maplewoodians get in return for high property taxes. The township's fathers and mothers, in their wisdom, annually create an outdoor skating rink by flooding a low-lying section of Memorial Park.</p>
        <p>They've been doing this for decades. Longtime residents of a certain age speak of another time and another climate, when children gathered on winter days after school and skated until dark, and sometimes longer. A nearby hut -- still called the skatehouse though more recent arrivals can't figure out why -- served up hot beverages. Occasionally someone would start a bonfire, and everybody would sigh contentedly and remember why life was better in places where you can't golf 12 months a year.</p>
        <p>Today, the old skatehouse is a repository for softball equipment. There's no need for hot beverages because, well, there's no need for hot beverages. The pond is regarded as an attraction only by Canada geese, who flock to it and leave behind their predictable calling cards.</p>
        <p>I wish I were among the many who have spent the last few weeks thanking the weather forecasters for arranging a mild winter. Perhaps if I spent more time in the car or worked outdoors I would. But I can't help but get depressed every time I pass that unfrozen pond. It reminds me that my children are not having and may never have the winter memories I have. And that is their loss.</p>
        <p>Oh, they know how to skate, but only in circles -- they way they do on the indoor rinks. If they were put on a pond one fine cold day and told to just play, that would actually be cruel, like abandoning a dog in the wilderness.</p>
        <p>Back in the day, in the woods of southern Staten Island, a bunch of adolescent boys and girls spent long, happy days on places like Long Pond and its younger sibling, Short Pond, as well as the curiously named Discontinued Pond (christened, perhaps, in honor of somebody's favorite old sitcom). That stuff just doesn't happen in two-hour sessions at your local arena.</p>
        <p>If this sounds like the lament of somebody in the thrall of midlife crisis, perhaps it is. But I'm not asking for much in the way of recaptured youth. I'm not looking to buy a sports car.</p>
        <p>All I want is a week of bitter cold weather, a hockey stick and two of my favorite pre-teenagers asking me how to skate backward. That's not too much to ask.</p>
        <p>The other day I passed that unfrozen pond in Maplewood, and I could swear those geese were making noises that sounded like laughter.</p>
        <p>JERSEY TerryGolway@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">TerryGolway@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
