<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ocean Rescue</title>
    <meta content="25sun2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/24/opinion/25sun2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1814195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Research Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Inslee, Jay</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kolbert, Elizabeth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0D91131F937A15751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ocean Rescue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ocean Rescue</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because it was approved at about 3 o'clock in the morning in the frantic final hours of the 109th Congress, one important and positive piece of legislation has gone largely unnoticed. This was the reauthorization of the 30-year-old Magnuson-Stevens Act, the basic law regulating fishing practices in American waters from 3 to 200 miles offshore.</p>
        <p>Despite a few unfortunate last-minute compromises, the revised law is an improvement on the old, and is long overdue. One report after another over the last few years -- including two major studies by Congress and by the Pew Oceans Commission -- has documented the degradation of the world's oceans and predicted a catastrophic decline in important fish species if nothing is done to regulate fish harvests and control pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reauthorization of a basic law regulating fishing practices in American waters may prove to be of great importance to future ocean health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because it was approved at about 3 o'clock in the morning in the frantic final hours of the 109th Congress, one important and positive piece of legislation has gone largely unnoticed. This was the reauthorization of the 30-year-old Magnuson-Stevens Act, the basic law regulating fishing practices in American waters from 3 to 200 miles offshore.</p>
        <p>Despite a few unfortunate last-minute compromises, the revised law is an improvement on the old, and is long overdue. One report after another over the last few years -- including two major studies by Congress and by the Pew Oceans Commission -- has documented the degradation of the world's oceans and predicted a catastrophic decline in important fish species if nothing is done to regulate fish harvests and control pollution.</p>
        <p>Just last month, a paper published in the journal Science warned that the progressive unraveling of marine ecosystems up and down the food chain could lead to the ''collapse'' of all commercial species, possibly by the middle of this century.</p>
        <p>The revised law establishes timetables for the rebuilding of depleted species and, perhaps most important, gives impartial scientists a much greater say in setting catch limits and charting recovery programs. Current law allows the nation's regional fishery management councils -- mostly dominated by fishermen with a direct financial interest in exploiting the fish stocks they are supposed to protect -- to set harvest limits, which are usually much too generous and in any case are often ignored.</p>
        <p>For the first time, too, the bill attempts to do something to moderate the fishing practices of heavily subsidized foreign fleets whose huge bottom trawlers have cause widespread environmental damage to coral and other ocean formations. It would authorize the secretary of commerce to deny access to American ports to countries that are found to engage in such practices in unregulated waters on the high seas.</p>
        <p>As useful as these changes are, however, the bill contains one obscure provision (Section 701 of Title VII) that may prove to be of even greater importance to ocean health. The handiwork of Representative Jay Inslee, a Washington State Democrat, it is a one-sentence directive to the secretary of commerce to ask the National Research Council, part of the National Academy of Sciences, ''to conduct a study of the acidification of the oceans and how this process affects the United States.''</p>
        <p>Scientists are increasingly coming to believe that the carbon dioxide that humans are pumping into the air -- the same carbon dioxide that is responsible for global warming -- is also changing the chemistry of the oceans. Oceans act as a sink for carbon dioxide, absorbing it and then releasing it back into the atmosphere in roughly equal quantities. But as humanity has produced more and more carbon dioxide, the balance has been upset -- the oceans, in effect, have had to absorb more carbon dioxide than they can handle. The result is acidification, a process that is already damaging tiny corals and that many scientists believe could ultimately wreak havoc on the delicate oceanic food chain.</p>
        <p>This disheartening prospect has been discussed in peer-reviewed articles in Nature and, more recently, in an extensive and alarming article by Elizabeth Kolbert in The New Yorker. Much remains to be learned about the process and how to deal with it, although cutting carbon dioxide emissions would obviously be a good place to start. Mr. Inslee wants to know more, and so should we all. The fish limits imposed by the Magnuson-Stevens law would become irrelevant if there were in fact no more fish to limit.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
