<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Panel Prods NASA for Improvement on Openness</title>
    <meta content="17nasa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/17/politics/17nasa.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1740364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffin, Michael D (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dale, Shana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3DD103EF934A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Panel Prods NASA for Improvement on Openness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">House Panel Prods NASA for Improvement on Openness</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY and ANDREW C. REVKIN; Warren E. Leary reported from Washington for this article, and Andrew C. Revkin from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C; Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawmakers of both parties urge NASA's leaders to improve ways agency conveys scientific information to public; are responding to cascade of reports about efforts by political appointees in space agency's press office to restrict interviews or alter news releases that might conflict with Bush administration policies on pollution, global warming and other issues; photo of Michael D Griffin, NASA administrator, and Shana Dale, deputy administrator (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers of both parties urged NASA's leaders on Thursday to improve the ways the agency conveys scientific information to the public.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers were responding to a cascade of reports about efforts by political appointees in the space agency's press office to restrict interviews or alter news releases that might conflict with Bush administration policies on pollution, global warming and other issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The panel was responding to reports about efforts in the space agency to restrict information that might conflict with Bush administration policies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers of both parties urged NASA's leaders on Thursday to improve the ways the agency conveys scientific information to the public.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers were responding to a cascade of reports about efforts by political appointees in the space agency's press office to restrict interviews or alter news releases that might conflict with Bush administration policies on pollution, global warming and other issues.</p>
        <p>At a House Science Committee hearing on the agency's $16.8 billion budget request for the next fiscal year, the chairman, Representative Sherwood Boehlert, Republican of New York, said that while NASA had responded well so far, it ''still has a lot of work to do to ensure openness.''</p>
        <p>The committee's ranking Democrat, Representative Bart Gordon of Tennessee, said he was eager to see Michael D. Griffin, the NASA administrator, follow through on a pledge he made to the agency's 19,000 employees on Feb. 3 to review its communications policies.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid that scientific censorship permeates this administration, and NASA is no exception,'' Mr. Gordon said. ''But the administrator is taking a forthright role.''</p>
        <p>After the hearing, Dr. Griffin told reporters that ''certain individuals have done things they shouldn't have'' but that he doubted there was a widespread practice of muzzling NASA scientists or misrepresenting science.</p>
        <p>He added that agency employees needed to feel free to speak out and that NASA was particularly concerned about openness because in the wake of the space shuttle disasters of 1986 and 2003, ''people said certain views'' had not been listened to beforehand.</p>
        <p>Dr. Griffin said his review should be completed, and a new policy put in place, ''in the next few weeks.''</p>
        <p>Two efforts aimed at change are under way. Shana Dale, the deputy administrator, established a group of 12 NASA scientists, administrators and public affairs employees on Wednesday to recommend provisions of a policy to replace the existing one, which dates from 1987 and is largely unknown within the agency. And other senior administrators, several officials said, are reviewing reports of communications trouble that are flowing from NASA's research centers around the nation.</p>
        <p>Franco Einaudi, director of the Earth-Sun Exploration Division at the agency's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., said some of the problems reported by scientists or staff members were simply cases of public affairs officers' getting the science wrong.</p>
        <p>''Communication needs a lot of cooperation,'' Dr. Einaudi said. ''Generally scientists don't know how to write and public affairs people don't know the science.''</p>
        <p>But in some cases, he said, changes have been made in which ''it is clear that the motivation is not just to make the English better.'' He declined to discuss those incidents because the review had just begun.</p>
        <p>In an interview, David R. Mould, the assistant administrator for public affairs, defended the agency's handling of news releases and the media, saying his goal was to keep it free of spin of any sort.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't want anyone's political agenda to be associated with NASA publications,'' Mr. Mould said.</p>
        <p>But many NASA scientists and public affairs workers have said they have felt far more influence on the flow of information than their predecessors did during the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>Paul C. Light, a professor at the Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service at New York University, who is an expert on political appointees, said the issues surfacing at NASA were a result of a general ballooning of political influence in government public affairs offices over the last decade, ''with a particular acceleration under Bush.''</p>
        <p>''The units are focusing heavily on editing, spinning, doctoring just about anything that leaves their agencies via reports, interviews, Congressional testimony,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Robert E. Moffitt of the Heritage Foundation, co-author of a 2001 paper that called on the Bush administration to increase political appointments in influential offices within government agencies, said public affairs offices were ideal places for people hired to promote an administration's worldview.</p>
        <p>''Better to have them in a public affairs office, where they can speak for the president, than, for example, servicing the space shuttle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>James E. Hansen, the NASA climate scientist who was the first to complain of restrictions on his speaking and news media contacts, said that Dr. Griffin's recent statements were encouraging but that the political appointees at headquarters might not yet have gotten the message.</p>
        <p>''The administrator has it exactly right,'' Dr. Hansen said. ''We live in a free country and work for the taxpayer. We should provide useful information, not propaganda. But based on their recent remarks, public affairs still doesn't get it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
