<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Much Talk of a Nuclear Renaissance, but So Far Little Action</title>
    <meta content="03power" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/03/politics/03power.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1743808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toshiba Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westinghouse Power Generation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Standard &amp; Poor's Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timmons, Heather</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Toshiba Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D61731F930A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Much Talk of a Nuclear Renaissance, but So Far Little Action</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Much Talk of a Nuclear Renaissance, but So Far Little Action</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD and HEATHER TIMMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Timmons, Heather; Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toshiba's recent acquisition of Westinghouse's former nuclear division adds to talk of rebirth of nuclear construction; no action has been taken to begin building more than dozen planned new reactors; nuclear power plants are more expensive than gas or coal plants but generate steady, cheap energy once they are built; China announces intention to quadruple nuclear output in next twenty years; Standard &amp; Poor's report concludes that it is too early to talk of nuclear renaissance (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With industry hopes rising for a revival in orders for nuclear power reactors, the sale last month of Westinghouse's former nuclear division to Toshiba might stand out as a landmark. But not necessarily because the industry seems ready to take off.</p>
        <p>Toshiba surprised many in the industry by agreeing to pay a lofty $5.4 billion for a collection of nuclear power manufacturing facilities, with Westinghouse's being the centerpiece, assembled by British Nuclear Fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite industry hopes for a revival in orders for nuclear power reactors, analysts say that the talk of a rebirth of nuclear construction is still just that  talk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With industry hopes rising for a revival in orders for nuclear power reactors, the sale last month of Westinghouse's former nuclear division to Toshiba might stand out as a landmark. But not necessarily because the industry seems ready to take off.</p>
        <p>Toshiba surprised many in the industry by agreeing to pay a lofty $5.4 billion for a collection of nuclear power manufacturing facilities, with Westinghouse's being the centerpiece, assembled by British Nuclear Fuels.</p>
        <p>That move has only added to the talk of a rebirth of nuclear construction, but analysts say that most of it is still just that -- talk. In the United States, Energy Secretary Samuel W. Bodman recently referred to more than a dozen new reactors on the drawing boards, but not one has yet been ordered, and industry analysts do not expect to see any orders until late 2007, at the earliest. ''I think we all were surprised by the price,'' said Michael G. Morris, the president and chief executive of American Electric Power, the largest power generator in the United States. Mr. Morris, whose company serves five million customers in 11 states, favors more nuclear power.</p>
        <p>China has announced its intention to quadruple its nuclear output in the next 20 years, but at the same time the country has also stated that it wants to develop its own reactor.</p>
        <p>Politicians in Italy, Britain and Poland have been examining the merits of new nuclear plants. But to date, the only nuclear plant being built in Europe is a Finnish reactor that was the focus of 12 years of debate before construction began last year.</p>
        <p>Much of the optimism on nuclear construction is based on the idea that two recent trends will continue: the cost of competing fuels will rise, as will government controls on carbon emissions. And it assumes that methods of lowering carbon emissions from other energy sources, like coal, will not become widespread.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power plants are more expensive to build than gas or coal plants, and take several years longer to construct. But once built, they generate energy steadily and cheaply, and emit negligible amounts of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>In European countries where rules about carbon emissions are already firmly established -- in contrast to the United States, where limits are more lenient -- some critics of nuclear power have started to question whether building new reactors is a cost-effective way to lower these emissions.</p>
        <p>More nuclear power generation ''doesn't make sense economically and environmentally,'' said Norman Baker, a specialist on environmental issues for the Liberal Democrat Party in Britain. Spending £1, or about $1.70, on improving energy efficiency yields seven times the reduction in carbon emissions as spending the same amount on new nuclear construction, he said. ''If you're interested in climate change, you should demand clean coal and renewable resources'' instead, Mr. Baker said.</p>
        <p>Energy markets have changed significantly across Europe since the 1970's, the last time a significant number of nuclear plants were built. Many European power companies have been privatized, and the energy market opened up to competition in many countries.</p>
        <p>Any new construction would need to be financed by a private company, which would have to guarantee its investors that the reactor would earn profits in the future. It is not a sure bet, energy analysts say.</p>
        <p>It is ''too early to speak about a nuclear renaissance,'' a recent report on Europe by the rating agency Standard &amp; Poor's concluded.</p>
        <p>''The market environment is now significantly riskier than it was when the original nuclear plants were built,'' said Peter Kernan, an analyst at S.&amp; P. who was a co-author of the report. ''Operators would need to be convinced there is a sound and robust business case'' for building a plant before they start devoting capital to it, Mr. Kernan said. He said there was no evidence yet to suggest that.</p>
        <p>Mark Herlach, a lawyer at Sutherland, Asbill &amp; Brennan who represented British Nuclear Fuels in the deal and who specializes in energy asset sales, defended the price of the transaction, saying it made sense because of the rising costs of other fuels and concerns over greenhouse gases. ''This is a different environment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission recently approved the design of a new Westinghouse model, the AP-1000, an ''advanced passive'' reactor that would have fewer moving parts in its safety systems. No one has bought it yet.</p>
        <p>''What Toshiba has done by this acquisition is acquired a leading technology in the AP-1000, '' Mr. Herlach said. And China, the largest emerging market in the world, has expressed a preference for that type of reactor, called a pressurized water reactor.</p>
        <p>With the Westinghouse deal, Toshiba has acquired more than a new reactor design. The bundle of assets being sold to Toshiba is the distilled result of years of scrambling and reassembling the companies that built reactors in the 1970's and 80's and still service them.</p>
        <p>The core asset in the sale is the former nuclear division of Westinghouse Electric, which had already absorbed Combustion Engineering. So, with Westinghouse, Toshiba gains two of the four companies that built the existing complex of American reactors. A third company, the commercial nuclear division of Babcock &amp; Wilcox, is now in the hands of Areva, a French-German consortium. The fourth company is General Electric, which is trying to sell a newly designed reactor.</p>
        <p>With the sale, Toshiba becomes the only vendor to sell updated versions of both types of reactors now in use. But in the short term, the least glamorous parts of Westinghouse's business may prove the most valuable for Toshiba: the company's extensive repair and maintenance services.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
