<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Save the Planet! Own Just One Home!</title>
    <meta content="l14tierney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1782902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foote, Lisa L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goetsch, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Orman, Jeanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vaughan, William Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DD173EF937A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Save the Planet! Own Just One Home!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four letters respond to Aug 8 John Tierney Op-Ed column noting that many fervent environmentalists own second homes, which use resources; Lisa L Foote agrees and says second-home ownership is irresponsible; Douglas Goetsch expresses disappointment in celebrities who choose life of luxury instead of setting powerful example; Jeanne Van Orman argues that not all second homes are sinful; William Vaughan Jr suggests other tips for saving environment that might not be welcome; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Sinful Second Homes'' (column, Aug. 8):</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Sinful Second Homes'' (column, Aug. 8):</p>
        <p>Bravo to John Tierney for pointing out the outrageous eco-sin of second-home ownership.</p>
        <p>There's an aspect of the energy consumption involved in second-home ownership that has always bothered me far more than the cost of traveling to the home: even when empty week after week in the off season, second homes still have to be minimally heated in the winter (and sometimes even cooled in the summer, depending on the location).</p>
        <p>Add in the additional cost of keeping your primary home minimally heated or cooled while you're away, and it's always been enough to deter any thought of second-home ownership for me -- it's just irresponsibly expensive.</p>
        <p>Lisa L. Foote  Minneapolis, Aug. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>John Tierney does well to examine the carbon footprints of celebrity environmentalists, though it's hard to tell if he's really concerned about reducing global warming or just debunking the cause -- I hope it's the former.</p>
        <p>But I, too, am disappointed by ''do-gooders,'' from Oprah Winfrey to Bono, who choose lives of luxury when they could be setting real examples, more powerful than anything they preach, for millions of admirers.</p>
        <p>Much of that Gandhi quote -- ''You must be the change you wish to see in the world'' -- comes down to living simply.</p>
        <p>Douglas Goetsch  New York, Aug. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I'm inviting John Tierney to my seaside cottage so he can see that not all second homes are sinful.</p>
        <p>This little cottage withstood the 1938 hurricane and has barely been modernized since. My friends and family (particularly the Russian ones -- used to dachas, not McMansions) regard it as a small bit of heaven.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tierney can take public transportation from Times Square to within two miles of the cottage.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Tierney surely knows, one measures environmental impact in part by weighing costs and benefits of a proposed action.</p>
        <p>Using that method, I save energy when I'm at the cottage. The wind off Buzzards Bay cools the air; the water (only feet away) cools me.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Tierney revisits in five years, he may have the pleasure of looking out on the 400-foot-tall propellers from the Buzzards Bay wind farm.</p>
        <p>Jeanne Van Orman  Arlington, Mass., Aug. 8, 2006</p>
        <p>The writer serves on the Fairhaven, Mass., Conservation Commission.</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>John Tierney takes those who own second homes to task because of the increase in carbon dioxide associated with such possessions. He says that ''in all the years I've been reading lists of energy-saving tips, I've never noticed, 'Sell second home.' ''</p>
        <p>My own favorite never-noticed energy-saving tip: ''Have fewer children.''</p>
        <p>Or is this tip a little too inconvenient?</p>
        <p>William Vaughan Jr.  Chebeague Island, Me., Aug. 8, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
