<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Nominates Wall Street Chief for Treasury Job</title>
    <meta content="31treasury" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/31/business/31treasury.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="A CHANGE AT TREASURY: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DF1631F932A05756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Nominates Wall Street Chief for Treasury Job</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Nominates Wall Street Chief for Treasury Job</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS and JIM RUTENBERG; Sheryl Gay Stolberg, Elisabeth Bumiller and Felicity Barringer in Washington and David Barboza in Shanghai contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said Tuesday that he had chosen Henry M. Paulson Jr. of Goldman Sachs as his next Treasury secretary, a move intended to add economic star power to his administration as it tries to fight its way through a thicket of political difficulties.</p>
        <p>If confirmed by the Senate, Mr. Paulson would succeed John W. Snow at a time when the economy, while strong, is facing fresh challenges from high energy prices, a falling dollar and shakiness in the stock market, where the Dow Jones industrial average fell 184 points, or 1.6 percent, Tuesday. [Page C1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henry M. Paulson Jr. is expected to face immediate international challenges, which include increased uncertainty in global financial markets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush said Tuesday that he had chosen Henry M. Paulson Jr. of Goldman Sachs as his next Treasury secretary, a move intended to add economic star power to his administration as it tries to fight its way through a thicket of political difficulties.</p>
        <p>If confirmed by the Senate, Mr. Paulson would succeed John W. Snow at a time when the economy, while strong, is facing fresh challenges from high energy prices, a falling dollar and shakiness in the stock market, where the Dow Jones industrial average fell 184 points, or 1.6 percent, Tuesday. [Page C1.]</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson, 60, is chairman and chief executive of the Goldman Sachs Group and one of Wall Street's most highly compensated executives, with a net worth estimated at more than $700 million. He had initially rebuffed overtures about the Treasury job, which is widely viewed as having declined in influence and prestige during Mr. Bush's presidency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush and other officials -- eager to bring aboard someone who could potentially do for this administration what another former Goldman chief, Robert E. Rubin, did for President Bill Clinton as a senior economic adviser and as Treasury chief -- persisted. They enlisted mutual friends to persuade Mr. Paulson to accept, and had an advantage in Mr. Bush's new chief of staff, Joshua B. Bolten, a former Goldman executive.</p>
        <p>The courtship included an invitation to Mr. Paulson and his wife, Wendy, to lunch at the White House last month with President Hu Jintao of China, and culminated in a weekend meeting with Mr. Bush at the White House residence two Saturdays ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson formally accepted the job the next day, May 21, a fact Mr. Bush hid when asked at a news conference four days later whether he had any indication that Mr. Snow intended to leave soon.</p>
        <p>''No, he has not talked to me about resignation,'' Mr. Bush replied then, resorting to what the White House acknowledged Tuesday was an artful attempt to keep the move secret.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson, whose confirmation seems assured, would bring some different views to the administration, including support for more aggressive efforts to deal with global warming than Mr. Bush has supported.</p>
        <p>He would also bring credibility in the financial markets at a time of huge budget and trade deficits. And he offers expertise in dealing with the rise of China, one of the biggest economic and foreign policy challenges facing the United States.</p>
        <p>In announcing his decision in the Rose Garden on Tuesday morning, with Mr. Snow and Mr. Paulson at his side, Mr. Bush said Mr. Paulson would serve as his ''principal adviser on the broad range of domestic and international economic issues that affect the well-being of all Americans.''</p>
        <p>The phrasing seemed to signal that Mr. Paulson would have top billing on an economic team that has often been overshadowed in policy making by Mr. Bush's inner circle, including Vice President Dick Cheney and Karl Rove, the president's political strategist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson, who has supported Mr. Bush's economic policies in the past, including his tax cuts, said he had a ''keen appreciation for the role that capital markets play in driving economic growth'' and added, without being specific, that the United States had to ''take steps to maintain our competitive edge in the world.''</p>
        <p>Initial reaction from Capitol Hill was positive, with some Democrats joining Republicans in praising the choice of Mr. Paulson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's announcement brought to a close a long period in which Mr. Snow had been reported to be on his way out at the Treasury. Mr. Snow, 66, a Ph.D. economist and former chairman of the CSX Corporation, was a loyal and persistent promoter of Mr. Bush's economic policy and record.</p>
        <p>But many administration allies, including some Republicans in Congress, had pressed the White House to bring in someone more prominent who could do a better job of communicating the economy's strength and could reassure voters of the administration's economic competence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson is expected to face immediate international challenges. Those include increased uncertainty in global financial markets, resulting in part from the United States' huge trade imbalance and rapidly growing foreign indebtedness.</p>
        <p>Lately, the value of the dollar has slumped sharply against the euro and other major currencies. That trend provides a lift to American exports by making them cheaper abroad, but can also feed inflation and slow consumer spending by making imports more expensive in this country.</p>
        <p>The administration has also been struggling to develop a policy for dealing with China, which is seen by many American specialists as keeping its currency undervalued to give it an advantage in global markets for its manufactured goods.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no Treasury secretary would bring closer ties to China than Mr. Paulson. In more than 70 trips, he has repeatedly met with top Chinese officials, including Mr. Hu. Indeed, when Mr. Hu visited the United States in 2002, Mr. Paulson joined Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg of New York in giving him a tour of ground zero.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson's nomination drew praise from business groups, and also from at least a few prominent Democrats who have fiercely criticized Mr. Bush's tax cuts and budget deficits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin said Mr. Bush's choice was ''well done'' and praised Mr. Paulson as ''very well respected'' and ''thoughtful.''</p>
        <p>Representative John M. Spratt Jr., a South Carolina Democrat, was more enthusiastic. "President Bush could not have made a stronger choice,'' Mr. Spratt declared.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York, who has close ties to Wall Street, said Mr. Paulson was ''the best pick that America could have hoped for.''</p>
        <p>But some analysts on Wall Street were cooler. Paul Ashworth, a senior economist at Capital Economics, predicted that Mr. Paulson would not bring major policy changes and would have to grapple with underlying economic forces that include a steady decline in the value of the dollar.</p>
        <p>"The best he can do is try to ensure that decline continues in an orderly fashion and does not turn into a collapse,'' Mr. Ashworth wrote in a note to clients on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>As recounted by administration officials and other Republicans in Washington, the interest in Mr. Paulson intensified in February, after Secretary Snow alerted officials that he intended to leave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson's appointment is the latest in a series of White House personnel changes managed by Mr. Bolten, who took over as chief of staff in April.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolten has said he wants to bring the administration's ''mojo back'' after seeing major initiatives like the overhauls of Social Security and income taxes grind to a halt.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Paulson was not an automatic choice. Mr. Bush, a former oil executive, has often viewed Wall Street with thinly veiled suspicion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson is also an environmentalist who has taken positions at odds with those of the administration. He is chairman of the board of the Nature Conservancy, which strongly supported the Kyoto Protocol to reduce the production of greenhouse gases considered responsible for contributing to global warming.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Paulson, Goldman Sachs released an ''environmental framework'' in which the firm acknowledged a ''scientific consensus'' that ''climate change is a reality, and that human activities are largely responsible'' for increases in greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Still, Rob Portman, a former Republican member of Congress who is now White House budget director, subtly distinguished Mr. Paulson's passion for protecting parks and wilderness areas from a broader urge to restrict economic activity for the sake of the environment or to protect endangered species.</p>
        <p>''I would call him more of a conservationist,'' Mr. Portman said. ''The distinction might be that he focuses on preserving and protecting sensitive environments, sensitive land, and some of that land has endangered species in it.''</p>
        <p>Either way, Mr. Paulson has no shortage of Republican credentials.</p>
        <p>Though his firm's political giving has tended to lean slightly more to Democrats than Republicans, Mr. Paulson is himself a major Republican donor, according to an analysis by the Center for Responsive Politics, a nonpartisan group that tracks campaign spending.</p>
        <p>Of the more than $426,000 Mr. Paulson and his wife have contributed to federal candidates and political organizations since 1989, $370,000 went to Republicans. Nearly all of that was from Mr. Paulson himself (three-quarters of his wife's share went to Democrats, among them Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton of New York.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson, though, appears to be a relative latecomer to raising money for Mr. Bush; he apparently did not contribute at all in 2000. But the center reported that he raised more than $100,000 for the president's re-election from other donors, making him what the campaign called a Pioneer.</p>
        <p>He also worked in the administration of President Richard M. Nixon in the early 1970's, including as an aide on the White House Domestic Council, which reported to John D. Ehrlichman. A Republican with ties to the administration said Mr. Paulson got to know Dick Cheney then, though administration officials said Mr. Cheney did not play a leading role in recruiting him.</p>
        <p>A senior White House official who was granted anonymity to discuss internal personnel deliberations said Mr. Paulson was on the ''short list'' as soon as the White House began seriously searching for Mr. Snow's successor -- someone with credentials that suited the times domestically and internationally.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson, if confirmed, would immediately take the lead in negotiations with China over the valuation of its currency.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Beijing's top officials, Mr. Paulson told an audience at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania last year: ''The leaders are very bright, pragmatic and aware of their problems. They have done a great job at economic reform. In my opinion, that's a better first step because, until you have economic stability, political freedom isn't going to make any difference. But I think the Chinese will loosen up on human rights and allow more political freedom.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson's frequent trips to China have paid big dividends for Goldman Sachs, helping the firm snare some of the biggest investment banking deals of the last decade there and giving it the first direct access to Chinese investors of any Western financial institution.</p>
        <p>The White House official said that even as Mr. Paulson balked at overtures to come aboard, the search kept coming back to him, and Mr. Bush instructed Mr. Bolten to keep pressing him.</p>
        <p>The official said that Mr. Paulson's concerns also included his family life and succession issues at Goldman. But ultimately it was the meeting with the president at the White House residence where the Bush team was able to hammer home its argument that reports of the Treasury Department's diminution were exaggerated.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes it's more myth and perception than reality,'' the official said, ''and when you get briefed on the reality, it becomes reassuring.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paulson accepted the job the next day.</p>
        <p>A CHANGE AT TREASURY: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
