<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor Says No National Bid, But Actions Keep Question Alive</title>
    <meta content="29bloomberg" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/29/nyregion/29bloomberg.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1765277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Political Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cardwell, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloomberg, Michael R (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stem Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6DD1F3EF93AA15756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor Says No National Bid, But Actions Keep Question Alive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mayor Says No National Bid, but Actions Keep Question Alive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE CARDWELL; Winnie Hu contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cardwell, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Michael R Bloomberg continues to say that he will not run for president in 2008 but there is sense in some political circles that he could be persuaded to run as independent candidate; Bloomberg himself has changed flavor of his public statements, casting himself as non-ideological problem-solver, trait pollsters say Americans are calling for at national level (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a man who says he is not running for president, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has been sounding a lot like a candidate for the White House lately.</p>
        <p>He spent last week thrusting himself into national politics, making pointed comments on issues like illegal immigration, stem-cell research and global warming. But then on Friday, he denied any interest in higher office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a man who says he is not running for president, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has been sounding a lot like a candidate for the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a man who says he is not running for president, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg has been sounding a lot like a candidate for the White House lately.</p>
        <p>He spent last week thrusting himself into national politics, making pointed comments on issues like illegal immigration, stem-cell research and global warming. But then on Friday, he denied any interest in higher office.</p>
        <p>''I'm not running for president,'' he said while discussing immigration that day on his weekly call-in radio show. ''I've got a city with 500,000 undocumented, and I want to leave a better world for my kids, and your kids.''</p>
        <p>Still, there is substance fueling the sense in some political circles that the mayor, nominally a Republican, could be persuaded to run. Kevin Sheekey, the deputy mayor for government affairs and Mr. Bloomberg's lead political architect, continues to work behind the scenes, chatting up lobbyists and other operatives to promote the idea of Mr. Bloomberg running as an independent.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Bloomberg has been auditioning a new political persona in his public statements, casting himself as the kind of pragmatic, results-oriented problem-solver that Americans tell pollsters they are looking for.</p>
        <p>As Democrats and Republicans argue over the future of their parties and the national debate remains polarized, there are signs that voters are becoming increasingly dissatisfied with President Bush and the Republican leaders of Congress, and that they aren't necessarily energized by the Democrats, either.</p>
        <p>''Most people are not satisfied with their politics and would very much like to see more politicians who just got things done,'' said Al From, founder and chief executive officer of the Democratic Leadership Council, a centrist policy group. ''Most people really aren't about ideology. Most people really are about, 'Let's get something done that's going to make my life better.' ''</p>
        <p>Of late, Mr. Bloomberg's remarks have been almost pitch-perfect renditions of those sentiments. In his speech at Johns Hopkins University on Thursday, he railed against allowing ideology to get in the way of progress on global warming or stem-cell research. He then detailed a list of ''common sense'' solutions that his administration has devised for public-health issues facing New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''I work at the city level, dealing with real world problems and delivering actual services,'' Mr. Bloomberg said.</p>
        <p>''We have to put the care and treatment of our neighbors front and center. We can't let ideology get in the way of truth,'' he continued, adding that the city's approach to smoking, AIDS, diabetes and unintended pregnancy was ''a patient-driven program that cares about outcomes, not incomes.''</p>
        <p>Marshall Wittmann, a senior fellow at the Progressive Policy Institute, which is affiliated with the Democratic Leadership Council, said that in many ways Mr. Bloomberg had been building on the political legacy of moderate New York Republicans like Nelson A. Rockefeller and Jacob K. Javits. ''It's hard-headed, but liberal on social issues and fiscally responsible,'' said Mr. Wittmann, who has worked for Senator John McCain. ''He very much fits that mold that's been dormant, even in the Democratic Party.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bloomberg has continually shot down the notion that he might seek the presidency, in some ways his persistence in trying to shape a national agenda sends a different message. In continuing to reach across state lines in his fight against illegal gun trafficking, for example, he is building not only a national platform but also national alliances that could prove useful should he mount a presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>All along, Mr. Bloomberg has said he is simply trying to accomplish his policy goals, and indeed many of the issues he is championing -- like stemming gun trafficking and the flow of illegal immigrants, with an eye toward legalizing some of those already here -- are of particular importance to New Yorkers. Still, it is difficult to imagine the champions of intelligent design, a subject Mr. Bloomberg took on last week, suddenly taking over city evolution curriculums.</p>
        <p>At the same time, there are concrete benefits simply to promoting the idea of a Bloomberg presidential run, even if the mayor has no intention of mounting one. The hovering image of a man who became mayor against all expectations throwing hundreds of millions of his own dollars toward becoming president gives Mr. Bloomberg more leverage to get his way than does the image of a lame-duck mayor being forced from office by term limits.</p>
        <p>And, political analysts say, although some of Mr. Bloomberg's words may signal national political ambitions, his key actions do not. Mr. Bloomberg has not been making the kinds of preliminary rounds that Rudolph W. Giuliani, Gov. George E. Pataki and Senator McCain are making, and members of his inner circle say Mr. Bloomberg is not yet mulling a run. Few political consultants or analysts see a possibility for Mr. Bloomberg to win a Democratic or Republican primary, and even with nearly unlimited financing, a successful third-party candidacy has thus far proved elusive.</p>
        <p>''I just don't think that a New York liberal can run as an independent nationally, and he would already have to be speaking out against the national party,'' Mr. Wittmann said.</p>
        <p>And besides, as the Republican mayor of a liberal city, Mr. Bloomberg now has a special place in American politics, free to toggle between the right and the left as it suits him.</p>
        <p>''He's a contrarian,'' Mr. Wittmann said. ''It gives him a unique role to play nationally.''</p>
        <p>Political Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
