<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Pataki, New York Republican</title>
    <meta content="05thu3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/05/opinion/05thu3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1729668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EED71130F936A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Pataki, New York Republican</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mr. Pataki, New York Republican</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Normally a governor's State of the State address is a chance to plant legislative seeds. The idea is to be a little upbeat. Thank the troops. Brag about success. Share some glory. But for Gov. George Pataki of New York, and perhaps for several other governors, this year's opening homilies are rehearsals of sorts for the presidential primary campaign that officially begins in 2008.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki presented himself in a surprisingly straightforward way as a moderate Republican. There was no pandering to the capital punishment crowd. No mention of abortion or gun control. Instead, he refined his place as the Republican green candidate. It's a lonely position, but Mr. Pataki might have considered that to have any chance in the big leagues, he will have to wave his strong record on the environment like a regimental flag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Gov. George Pataki's State of the State address was one of his first speeches as a presidential contender, he made it clear that he would play to the middle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Normally a governor's State of the State address is a chance to plant legislative seeds. The idea is to be a little upbeat. Thank the troops. Brag about success. Share some glory. But for Gov. George Pataki of New York, and perhaps for several other governors, this year's opening homilies are rehearsals of sorts for the presidential primary campaign that officially begins in 2008.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki presented himself in a surprisingly straightforward way as a moderate Republican. There was no pandering to the capital punishment crowd. No mention of abortion or gun control. Instead, he refined his place as the Republican green candidate. It's a lonely position, but Mr. Pataki might have considered that to have any chance in the big leagues, he will have to wave his strong record on the environment like a regimental flag.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's speech featured proposals on developing cleaner, renewable energy sources to help decrease dependency on foreign oil. His plan to provide refineries to make ethanol won't hurt him with Midwestern farmers. But there was also a promise of more clean-coal power plants and development of hybrid vehicles, including ones that would run on biofuels. Mr. Pataki even promised to make renewable fuels available, tax-free, across the state. And the governor reaffirmed his support for the Northeast regional greenhouse gas emissions pact, which has already drawn fire from people in his own party.</p>
        <p>His 12th, and presumably last, State of the State address made it clear, once again, that Mr. Pataki is no orator. With a kind of breathless urgency that makes even his most passionate ideas sound a little forced, he laid out his philosophy for an ''active but limited government.'' He promised to propose tougher anticrime legislation, more tax cuts and more high-tech jobs -- all standard Republican fare. But he also said that to compete globally, the state would have to reform its education system, partly by giving more money to high-needs schools in New York City and statewide. It was a nod to one of the largest problems facing the Legislature, how to satisfy a court ruling to add billions of state dollars to New York City's school system.</p>
        <p>If this was indeed one of Mr. Pataki's first speeches as a presidential contender, he made it clear that he would play to the middle. In New York, at least, that's a good place for a Republican to be.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
