<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming Is in Our Hands</title>
    <meta content="l07herbert" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1781382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kenosian, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtzman, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cavallo, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Primack, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Inconvenient Truth, an (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EEDC1E3FF934A3575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming Is in Our Hands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four letters comment on Aug 3 Bob Herbert Op-Ed column linking heat wave to global warming; David Kenosian says Americans should not expect action from Bush administration and calls for individual action; Jack Holtzman urges people to see Al Gore movie An Inconvenient Truth; Alfred Cavallo suggests measures homeowners can take to limit greenhouse emissions; Robert B Primack agrees with assessment of Pres Bush's leadership</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Hot Enough Yet?,'' by Bob Herbert (column, Aug. 3):</p>
        <p>If we continue to consume energy at the present rate, the resulting heating of our climate will cause serious economic problems and the death of more people who are too weak to survive record heat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re ''Hot Enough Yet?,'' by Bob Herbert (column, Aug. 3):</p>
        <p>If we continue to consume energy at the present rate, the resulting heating of our climate will cause serious economic problems and the death of more people who are too weak to survive record heat.</p>
        <p>Politicians should be carrying out solutions like cleaner energy sources, higher fuel standards for cars, and ethanol fuels for cars, but sadly, there is no reason to expect leadership from the Bush administration and its allies in Congress.</p>
        <p>But each of us can do more to reduce energy consumption: walking or biking for errands, using public transportation to go to work instead of the car, turning the thermostat up in the summer and down in the winter, buying more efficient appliances and replacing gas guzzlers with hybrid cars are just a few of the things that we can do.</p>
        <p>But we also have to vote out the politicians who act like employees of the coal and oil companies.</p>
        <p>David Kenosian  Berwyn, Pa., Aug. 3, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Bob Herbert says the best way to learn about global warming is to see Al Gore's documentary, ''An Inconvenient Truth.'' Unfortunately, many Republicans are not seeing it because of Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>I urge all to see it. The science should not be a partisan issue. The scientific evidence is very clearly explained for those with and without a scientific background.</p>
        <p>Those who see the movie will be in a much better position to understand the arguments pro and con.</p>
        <p>The movie is in accord with the views of the vast majority of credible scientists. To listen only to the few dissenters could result in dire consequences for our families and the earth.</p>
        <p>Jack Holtzman  San Diego, Aug. 3, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Five years ago, we replaced our oil burner with a ground source (geothermal) heat pump, which heats and cools our house and provides some hot water.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, one can buy renewable energy from the local utility for a small premium, which for us amounts to an extra $5.50 per month on an average $85 per month utility bill.</p>
        <p>Thanks to these measures (which every homeowner can take), our house emits virtually no carbon dioxide. We also bought a hybrid car.</p>
        <p>My main motivation at the time was my understanding that oil and natural gas were soon going to become much more expensive because of OPEC price increases for oil and a shortage of supply in North America for natural gas. The cost of these fossil fuels has and will continue to rise substantially.</p>
        <p>Homeowners now have two compelling reasons to stop burning fossil fuels: climate change and much higher and increasing prices.</p>
        <p>Alfred Cavallo  Princeton, N.J., Aug. 3, 2006</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Bob Herbert makes a point that is dangerously disheartening. He suggests that we have been so deprived of good leadership from President Bush for so long that we may fail to recognize it when it is actually offered to us in the future.</p>
        <p>Robert B. Primack  Gainesville, Fla., Aug. 3, 2006</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
