<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TODAY IN BUSINESS</title>
    <meta content="16biztoday" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1D6173EF935A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TODAY IN BUSINESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AIRLINE TAKEOVER BID -- US Airways made an $8 billion offer for Delta Air Lines in an effort to become the nation's largest carrier. The surprise offer may presage a wave of mergers in the struggling airline industry, but must first overcome several large hurdles, including antitrust scrutiny and the apparent lack of support of Delta's management. US Airway's chief executive, Doug Parker, above, is a longtime proponent of airline consolidation. [Page A1]</p>
        <p>STUBBORN COMPETITOR -- Don't write off US Airways. In the last four years, it has filed for bankruptcy twice, faced extinction from discount airlines, been bled nearly dry by soaring fuel prices and entered a merger that critics said would not work. It emerged from these trials scarred but with a re-energized business strategy that emboldened it to make an offer for Delta. [C1]</p>
        <p>TOYOTA'S BIG TRUCK -- Toyota's cautious approach to the pickup market is coming to an end. Toyota officially opens its $1.2 billion assembly plant in San Antonio tomorrow. The plant will make the biggest version yet of Toyota's Tundra pickup, which goes on sale Feb. 12. [C1]</p>
        <p>A BIGGER CASINO -- Mohegan Sun, already one of the largest casino resorts in the country, will unveil plans to spend $740 million on a major expansion that will include a 1,000-room hotel, a new casino and more stores and restaurants. The resort's goal is to remain competitive with the neighboring Foxwood's Resort Casino as well as casinos in Atlantic City and Las Vegas. [B8]</p>
        <p>NEW HEART RISK -- A medical study to be released today suggests that high doses of a best-selling drug used to treat anemia in dialysis and cancer patients may increase the risk of heart problems and deaths. Almost a million Americans are annually prescribed the drug, known as epoetin, or a closely related drug, darbepoetin, for anemia. [C1]</p>
        <p>EXCHANGE BID DROPPED -- Deutsche Börse, parent company of the Frankfurt Stock Exchange, abandoned its goal of buying Euronext, the pan-European stock and derivatives exchange. The move increases the chances of the New York Stock Exchange's planned acquisition of Euronext will be completed. [C14]</p>
        <p>IMMIGRATION MEASURES -- In a sign of rising passions over immigration issues, Texas lawmakers prepared for the 2007 session this week by filing a flurry of bills that would deny public assistance and other benefits to the children of illegal immigrants, tax money transfers to Mexico and Latin America and sue the federal government for the costs of state border control. [A22]</p>
        <p>TRADE BILLS IN TROUBLE -- The failure by the House this week to approve a bill to extend normal trade relations to Vietnam showed the likely difficulty of winning approval of such bills. Lobbyists said that the administration is going to have to make concessions in order to get such bills through a Democratic-controlled Congress. News Analysis. [C1]</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING -- The United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, put the blame for global warming on ''a frightening lack of leadership,'' saying the world's poorest people, who do not even create much pollution, bear the brunt of rising temperatures. Mr. Annan said he was not singling out the United States. [A18]</p>
        <p>LESS FARMS, MORE FARMERS -- The number of family farms is dwindling but the National FFA Organization, once known as the Future Farmers of America, is growing. The group, which has almost half a million members, says more members now come from towns, suburbs and city neighborhoods, including Queens and the South Side of Chicago, than from rural farm regions. [A30]</p>
        <p>NEW AOL CHIEF -- Time Warner switched chiefs at its AOL unit, naming Randy Falco, the No. 2 executive at the NBC Universal Television, chairman and chief executive. He replaces Jonathan F. Miller, who held the position since 2002. Mr. Falco, 52, made the move after it became clear that he was not in the running to succeed Bob Wright, who is 63, as NBC Universal's chairman and chief executive. [C3]</p>
        <p>MERCK WINS AGAIN -- Merck won a sixth verdict in a case over its Vioxx painkiller when a federal jury ruled against a Utah man who claimed the drug caused his heart attack. Jurors in New Orleans rejected claims by Charles Mason, 64, who blamed Vioxx for his 2003 heart attack. Merck, which withdrew Vioxx in 2004, has won six cases over the drug and lost four. [C4]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing</p>
        <p>Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>THE CAREER EDUCATION Corporation said it would sell 13 schools, including its nine-campus Gibbs division, to shed unprofitable operations and focus more on its culinary, medical, computer-training and fashion schools. McIntosh College, two campuses belonging to Brooks College, and Lehigh Valley College also will be sold, the company, based in Hoffman Estates, Ill., said. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>VOLKSWAGEN's former personnel director, Peter Hartz, was charged by prosecutors with 44 counts of breach of trust in connection with a corruption scandal involving the company's labor council. Mr. Hartz, 65, who was also responsible for helping overhaul Germany's labor market when Gerhard Schröder was chancellor, has largely confessed to the crime, said Joachim Geyer, a spokesman for prosecutors in Braunschweig. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AIRLINE TAKEOVER BID -- US Airways made an $8 billion offer for Delta Air Lines in an effort to become the nation's largest carrier. The surprise offer may presage a wave of mergers in the struggling airline industry, but must first overcome several large hurdles, including antitrust scrutiny and the apparent lack of support of Delta's management. US Airway's chief executive, Doug Parker, above, is a longtime proponent of airline consolidation. [Page A1]</p>
        <p>STUBBORN COMPETITOR -- Don't write off US Airways. In the last four years, it has filed for bankruptcy twice, faced extinction from discount airlines, been bled nearly dry by soaring fuel prices and entered a merger that critics said would not work. It emerged from these trials scarred but with a re-energized business strategy that emboldened it to make an offer for Delta. [C1]</p>
        <p>TOYOTA'S BIG TRUCK -- Toyota's cautious approach to the pickup market is coming to an end. Toyota officially opens its $1.2 billion assembly plant in San Antonio tomorrow. The plant will make the biggest version yet of Toyota's Tundra pickup, which goes on sale Feb. 12. [C1]</p>
        <p>A BIGGER CASINO -- Mohegan Sun, already one of the largest casino resorts in the country, will unveil plans to spend $740 million on a major expansion that will include a 1,000-room hotel, a new casino and more stores and restaurants. The resort's goal is to remain competitive with the neighboring Foxwood's Resort Casino as well as casinos in Atlantic City and Las Vegas. [B8]</p>
        <p>NEW HEART RISK -- A medical study to be released today suggests that high doses of a best-selling drug used to treat anemia in dialysis and cancer patients may increase the risk of heart problems and deaths. Almost a million Americans are annually prescribed the drug, known as epoetin, or a closely related drug, darbepoetin, for anemia. [C1]</p>
        <p>EXCHANGE BID DROPPED -- Deutsche Börse, parent company of the Frankfurt Stock Exchange, abandoned its goal of buying Euronext, the pan-European stock and derivatives exchange. The move increases the chances of the New York Stock Exchange's planned acquisition of Euronext will be completed. [C14]</p>
        <p>IMMIGRATION MEASURES -- In a sign of rising passions over immigration issues, Texas lawmakers prepared for the 2007 session this week by filing a flurry of bills that would deny public assistance and other benefits to the children of illegal immigrants, tax money transfers to Mexico and Latin America and sue the federal government for the costs of state border control. [A22]</p>
        <p>TRADE BILLS IN TROUBLE -- The failure by the House this week to approve a bill to extend normal trade relations to Vietnam showed the likely difficulty of winning approval of such bills. Lobbyists said that the administration is going to have to make concessions in order to get such bills through a Democratic-controlled Congress. News Analysis. [C1]</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING -- The United Nations secretary general, Kofi Annan, put the blame for global warming on ''a frightening lack of leadership,'' saying the world's poorest people, who do not even create much pollution, bear the brunt of rising temperatures. Mr. Annan said he was not singling out the United States. [A18]</p>
        <p>LESS FARMS, MORE FARMERS -- The number of family farms is dwindling but the National FFA Organization, once known as the Future Farmers of America, is growing. The group, which has almost half a million members, says more members now come from towns, suburbs and city neighborhoods, including Queens and the South Side of Chicago, than from rural farm regions. [A30]</p>
        <p>NEW AOL CHIEF -- Time Warner switched chiefs at its AOL unit, naming Randy Falco, the No. 2 executive at the NBC Universal Television, chairman and chief executive. He replaces Jonathan F. Miller, who held the position since 2002. Mr. Falco, 52, made the move after it became clear that he was not in the running to succeed Bob Wright, who is 63, as NBC Universal's chairman and chief executive. [C3]</p>
        <p>MERCK WINS AGAIN -- Merck won a sixth verdict in a case over its Vioxx painkiller when a federal jury ruled against a Utah man who claimed the drug caused his heart attack. Jurors in New Orleans rejected claims by Charles Mason, 64, who blamed Vioxx for his 2003 heart attack. Merck, which withdrew Vioxx in 2004, has won six cases over the drug and lost four. [C4]</p>
        <p>ONLINE</p>
        <p>Business Briefing</p>
        <p>Articles on these developments are at nytimes.com/business.</p>
        <p>THE CAREER EDUCATION Corporation said it would sell 13 schools, including its nine-campus Gibbs division, to shed unprofitable operations and focus more on its culinary, medical, computer-training and fashion schools. McIntosh College, two campuses belonging to Brooks College, and Lehigh Valley College also will be sold, the company, based in Hoffman Estates, Ill., said. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>VOLKSWAGEN's former personnel director, Peter Hartz, was charged by prosecutors with 44 counts of breach of trust in connection with a corruption scandal involving the company's labor council. Mr. Hartz, 65, who was also responsible for helping overhaul Germany's labor market when Gerhard Schröder was chancellor, has largely confessed to the crime, said Joachim Geyer, a spokesman for prosecutors in Braunschweig. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
