<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Dilemma of the Levees</title>
    <meta content="01levees" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/01/us/nationalspecial/01levees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1751181"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Katrina (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Army Corps of Engineers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Donald E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D61230F932A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Dilemma of the Levees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Dilemma of the Levees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SCHWARTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Schwartz analysis notes that Donald E Powell, federal coordinator for Gulf Coast rebuilding, has announced that levees in New Orleans region that were being rebuilt would not meet insurance standard of protecting against 100-year flood, category that has 1 percent chance of occurring in any given year; holds that Powell's announcement was admission that old ways of building flood protection no longer applied; contends that before Hurricane Katrina and global warming, experts assumed that New Orleans was protected by levees that Army Corps of Engineers had built; says since then, emerging science of weather and climate change has led to understanding that world is entering cycle of stronger and more frequent storms, with higher surges and waves (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sense of just how much the world had changed for the Army Corps of Engineers struck Daniel Hitchings in a tense conference call last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hitchings, director of the hurricane response task force for the Corps of Engineers, was on a call with representatives of the Federal Emergency Management Agency and the National Flood Insurance Program. He explained that the levees and floodwalls around New Orleans, both existing and new, had been designed to be tall enough to hold back storm surges, but would allow about two feet of a six-foot wave to splash over the top.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent tense conference call gave a sense of just how much the world had changed for the Army Corps of Engineers in the wake of Gulf Coast flooding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sense of just how much the world had changed for the Army Corps of Engineers struck Daniel Hitchings in a tense conference call last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hitchings, director of the hurricane response task force for the Corps of Engineers, was on a call with representatives of the Federal Emergency Management Agency and the National Flood Insurance Program. He explained that the levees and floodwalls around New Orleans, both existing and new, had been designed to be tall enough to hold back storm surges, but would allow about two feet of a six-foot wave to splash over the top.</p>
        <p>The representatives from the insurance program were stunned. Water splashing over the top would violate the requirements of the federal flood insurance program, they said, though the corps has been designing levees that way for decades.</p>
        <p>It was an impasse. One federal agency's rules had come face to face with those of another, and the emergency officials were not pleased.</p>
        <p>''We were frustrated, angry and disappointed with the news we got from the corps,'' said a senior administration official who was granted anonymity to avoid straining relations between the agencies.</p>
        <p>Those differing perceptions of flood control help explain why Donald E. Powell, federal coordinator for Gulf Coast rebuilding, announced on Thursday that the levees in the New Orleans region that were being rebuilt would not meet the insurance standard of protecting against a 100-year flood, the category that has a 1 percent chance of occurring in any given year.</p>
        <p>The announcement was in many ways a candid admission that the old ways of building flood protection no longer applied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell insisted that the $3.4 billion in work currently under way would make the levee system stronger than ever and prevent catastrophic failure in another storm of Hurricane Katrina's strength.</p>
        <p>But he said work to bring the levees up to the standard required by the insurance agency would require as much as $6 billion in additional spending to raise levee heights, replace suspect floodwalls and take other corrective action.</p>
        <p>If FEMA cannot certify the flood-stopping power of the levees, the agency's maps will have to treat them as if they are not there. In other words, as if the land behind them is unprotected.</p>
        <p>That will have a significant effect on how neighborhoods will be rebuilt, how high off the ground homes will have to be constructed and the cost of insurance.</p>
        <p>In the old days, before Hurricane Katrina and before global warming, experts assumed that New Orleans was protected by the levees that the corps had built. Since then, however, the emerging science of weather and climate change has led to an understanding that the world is entering a cycle of stronger and more frequent storms, with higher surges and waves.</p>
        <p>Scientists have also discovered that the land under the New Orleans metropolitan area has subsided and that the levees are now lower than their original design height. Problems with the original design have also been found.</p>
        <p>Fundamentally, the notion of what constitutes a powerful storm has been altered.</p>
        <p>''We now have a new storm of record,'' Mr. Hitchings said. ''Katrina.''</p>
        <p>The data drawn from the experience of last August changes the equation of risk, he said.</p>
        <p>For all the new data, however, the levee system that the corps has been building is largely based on a model of a hurricane derived from data first collected in 1959. By the 70's, the National Weather Service had conducted new research that suggested that definition was too weak, but the corps did not alter its plans to accommodate the new data.</p>
        <p>''The corps, once it's locked on a track, will not take input from outside groups,'' said Ivor van Heerden, a leader of the task force investigating the levee breaches for Louisiana and a professor with the hurricane center at Louisiana State University.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Col. Lewis F. Setliff, the head of the team rebuilding levees, said the corps was not like the man on the street who is free to do what he pleases and change his mind at will. ''We have to have a law in Congress that tells us to do something,'' Colonel Setliff said.</p>
        <p>Robert G. Bea, a professor of engineering at the University of California, Berkeley, said the problem with that lack of flexibility was that ''the data is not stable.'' Even the repairs, Professor Bea said, are problematic.</p>
        <p>''They're building new walls, but they're building them to the old standard,'' he said. ''But we already know the old standard is inadequate.''</p>
        <p>The corps has undertaken a two-year project at the request of Congress to propose substantial upgrades for hurricane protection in southern Louisiana. A preliminary report from that project is due in June, with a final report in December 2007.</p>
        <p>If the study comes up with proposals for what the people of Louisiana say they truly want, protection against the strongest Category 5 storms, the cost would make the additional $6 billion look like a bargain. But it would more than exceed the insurance needs, Mr. Hitchings said, adding, ''Obviously, if it was Category 5, it would be much bigger than 100-year protection.''</p>
        <p>D. J. Nordquist, a spokeswoman for Mr. Powell, said that ''there's obviously a bigger question'' facing New Orleans, which will always have the threat of storms.</p>
        <p>''What level of protection are people comfortable with, and what are they willing to spend?'' Ms. Nordquist asked. ''What's even feasible?''</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
