<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Endless Bummer</title>
    <meta content="03LI-drumm" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/03/opinion/nyregionopinions/03LI-drumm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1809048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Drumm, Russell</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D9113EF930A35751C1A9609C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Endless Bummer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Endless Bummer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Russell Drumm</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drumm, Russell</byline>
      <dateline>Montauk</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ECOLOGICALLY speaking, the days of the Montauk Point Lighthouse are numbered. To forestall its inevitable collapse into the sea, the Army Corps of Engineers has designed a massive stone revetment to fortify the bluff upon which the historic lighthouse sits. Members of the eastern Long Island chapter of the Surfrider Foundation originally objected to the proposed strategy last year by saying it would destroy one of the premier surf spots on the East Coast. These days, they're saying the revetment would set a dangerous environmental precedent. The foundation's official solution is to forgo the revetment in favor of moving the 110-foot, 210-year-old structure back from the brink.</p>
        <p>Like salmon, surfers become imprinted with particular stretches of water. My fellow surfers and I (I've surfed in Montauk for 30 years) will go through hell and (preferably) high water in order to return again and again to a favorite spot -- if not to spawn, then to experience something pretty close to it on an emotional level. We are attached to, and protective of, waves. Kind of weird, when you consider that waves are not things, like the Montauk Point Lighthouse, but bundles of energy generated by distant storms. As the energy approaches land a number of variables -- reefs, swell direction, wind -- sculpt the sea into the moving shapes that give a surf spot its singular identity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Save the Montauk Lighthouse — or the perfect wave?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ECOLOGICALLY speaking, the days of the Montauk Point Lighthouse are numbered. To forestall its inevitable collapse into the sea, the Army Corps of Engineers has designed a massive stone revetment to fortify the bluff upon which the historic lighthouse sits. Members of the eastern Long Island chapter of the Surfrider Foundation originally objected to the proposed strategy last year by saying it would destroy one of the premier surf spots on the East Coast. These days, they're saying the revetment would set a dangerous environmental precedent. The foundation's official solution is to forgo the revetment in favor of moving the 110-foot, 210-year-old structure back from the brink.</p>
        <p>Like salmon, surfers become imprinted with particular stretches of water. My fellow surfers and I (I've surfed in Montauk for 30 years) will go through hell and (preferably) high water in order to return again and again to a favorite spot -- if not to spawn, then to experience something pretty close to it on an emotional level. We are attached to, and protective of, waves. Kind of weird, when you consider that waves are not things, like the Montauk Point Lighthouse, but bundles of energy generated by distant storms. As the energy approaches land a number of variables -- reefs, swell direction, wind -- sculpt the sea into the moving shapes that give a surf spot its singular identity.</p>
        <p>On the south side of the lighthouse, a beloved surf spot known as Alamo breaks when conditions are right. It is home, in surfer's parlance, to an awesome left-hander, a hollow wave that breaks top-to-bottom with world-class perfection given a strong southeast swell and northerly winds. The spot is named for the huge, concrete structure that rests on the shore at the foot of Turtle Hill, the sand and clay prominence the lighthouse sits on. Alamo, the wave, breaks about 70 yards directly offshore of its namesake because of a reef, a pile of stones the last glacier dumped there. The proposed revetment won't ruin the hallowed wave.</p>
        <p>Long before it fell from Turtle Hill's eroded south face, the Alamo was a fire-control bunker where observers were stationed to help Montauk's 16-inch guns zero in on German U-boats should they be foolish enough to surface during the day.</p>
        <p>Long before that, President George Washington authorized the construction of the lighthouse. In 1792, he reasoned that while navigational confusion served a purpose in dealing with the British blockade, it was a serious impediment to trade after the Revolution. At the time of its completion, the lighthouse stood 300 feet from the bluff edge. Only about 50 of those feet remain.</p>
        <p>Waves are loved on a deep, almost mystical level because, while they are transitory, the many conditions that cause them to wondrously appear are fundamental. Although the time scale is far different, lighthouses are loved for the same reason.</p>
        <p>Montauk has great waves, and great history. Members of the historical society, supported by the Army Corps of Engineers, believe the way to prevent the lighthouse from sharing the Alamo bunker's fate is to expand the stone revetment that now rings the base of Turtle Hill like a protective necklace. According to a design already approved by the Army Corps and historical society consultants, the revetment would extend farther north and west, and move the bluff's buttress farther offshore by about 20 feet.</p>
        <p>Surfrider's official position is that, in the face of global warming and an inexorable rise in the sea level, retreat is the answer. Other lighthouses have been moved, most notably Block Island's Southeast Light. The organization has embraced the orthodox view that hard structures like the revetment cause downdrift scouring, and warns that such scouring could one day make an island of Turtle Hill. Furthermore, if built, the lighthouse's new revetment would also become a precedent, opening the way for a plague of similar structures.</p>
        <p>Many foundation members are my surf buddies, but I have to take issue with their position. Experts say that moving the lighthouse would be near impossible. The topography landward of its historic location is downhill and steep. And the mortar holding the bricks of the old tower together is soft.</p>
        <p>Besides, if the foundation's goal is to protect a surf spot, it should say so instead of claiming to be concerned about erosion. Saving a wave is a worthy cause. Cape St. Francis, the South African ''perfect wave'' made famous in Bruce Brown's ''Endless Summer,'' disappeared after a housing development blocked the wind that carried the sand that coated the bottom and made the wave break with perfection. Sewage and industrial pollution have poisoned surf spots along the California, Oregon and Washington coasts.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, Threes, a perfect right-hander that used to break inside the Shinnecock Inlet, was killed by a dredging project. Parks department regulations keep surfers from some of Montauk's best waves on the north side of the lighthouse.</p>
        <p>Surfrider, a respected national organization, works hard to protect surf spots, beaches, water quality and access. Credibility is lost, however, when such a useful group argues beyond its expertise or dresses protection of a surf spot in politically correct clothing. It should be noted that Surfrider has not backed efforts to remove stone jetties in East Hampton, although they are blamed for serious erosion in Bridgehampton and Sagaponack. The jetties also happen to be responsible for a terrific right-hand barrel, a popular wave.</p>
        <p>Alamo is easy and legal to get to. The water is clean. Only the crowds are a drag. Surfrider should pick its fights more carefully. An improved revetment is the way to go. The worst that could happen is a backwash, and some of the best waves in the world have a backwash. Adds to the stoke.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Russell Drumm, a writer at The East Hampton Star, is the author of "In the Slick of the Cricket.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Russell Drumm, a writer at The East Hampton Star, is the author of "In the Slick of the Cricket.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
