<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="27forsum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1807752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DA103EF934A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Draft Report on Iraq Urges Talks With Iran and Syria  A draft report on strategies for Iraq that will be debated by a bipartisan commission urges an aggressive regional diplomatic initiative that includes direct talks with Iran and Syria, but sets no timetables for a military withdrawal, according to officials who have seen all or parts of the document.  A1</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki said Iraq's politicians were largely responsible for the surge in violence that engulfed the country over the past week, a departure from his previous assertions blaming militants for inciting the mayhem. A10</p>
        <p>Afghan Mission Tests NATO  NATO is bigger than ever, and is reaching further than ever before, by taking the lead in the war in Afghanistan. But the Afghan mission threatens a rift within the Atlantic alliance between those nations able and willing to participate fully in combat operations in Afghanistan -- and those nations that are not. A11</p>
        <p>A suicide bomber walked into a packed restaurant in southeastern Afghanistan and set off his explosives, killing 15 other people and wounding 25, Afghan officials said. The attack came after weeks of relative quiet and raised fears that insurgents were resuming their campaign of suicide bombings. A11</p>
        <p>Gaza Cease-Fire Seems to Hold  A cease-fire in Gaza appeared to be holding after Palestinian factions stopped firing rockets at Israel in exchange for an Israeli troop withdrawal from the territory.  A3</p>
        <p>Shiites Dominate Bahrain Vote  Shiite opposition candidates won 16 of the 17 seats they contested in elections for the lower house of Parliament in Bahrain, the election commission said. The 17th contested seat is set to be decided in a runoff on Dec. 2.  A3</p>
        <p>Korean Leader Sinks in Polls  Bruised by South Korea's no-holds-barred politics, bewildered by voters' rapidly changing concerns and battered mercilessly in the polls, President Roh Moo-hyun is limping toward the last year of his term. But it is not Mr. Roh's engagement of North Korea, or even its recent nuclear test, that has saddled him with a current approval rating of 11 percent. It is the economy. A6</p>
        <p>Correa Likely Victor in Ecuador  Rafael Correa, an urbane economist who has rattled nerves in Washington with plans to limit American military activities in Ecuador and renegotiate its foreign debt, seemed headed to an easy victory on Sunday in the presidential election, according to several exit polls.  A8</p>
        <p>British Retrace Steps of Spy  The British police sought to retrace the movements of Alexander V. Litvinenko, a former Russian secret agent, before he fell ill from the radiation poisoning that killed him. But the police insisted that Mr. Litvinenko's macabre death remained in the ''suspicious'' category and that they were not treating the case as a murder inquiry.  A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-19</p>
        <p>The Very Rich Are Leaving the Merely Rich Behind  Three decades ago, compensation among occupations differed far less than it does today. That growing difference is diverting people from some critical fields, experts say. The American Bar Foundation has found that fewer law school graduates are going into public-interest law or government jobs and filling all the openings is becoming harder.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New England G.O.P. Thins  The recent midterm elections dealt the already-fading New England Republican an especially strong blow, one that some fear will increase the divide between the two parties nationally by removing a longstanding bridge between them. Now, of 22 members of the House of Representatives from New England, only one is a Republican.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Seattle Nears Rain Record  Seattle's official rain gauge at Seattle-Tacoma International Airport has passed 14 inches and is rising. Now some wonder whether this month will break the single-month record for rainfall, 15.33 inches, which was set in December 1933.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Copper Price, and Theft, Rise  In the last year, a worldwide surge in demand for copper, largely because of construction booms in China and India, has pushed up its value, making the theft of copper more profitable and more popular.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-8</p>
        <p>Rejoining of German Museums  With the reopening of the Bode Museum, the Museum Island cultural park in the former East Berlin has taken another step toward recovering its place as one of the world's great centers of art. E1</p>
        <p>Important Greek Find  An international project to decipher 1,000-year-old, moldy pages is yielding new clues about ancient Greece as seen through the eyes of Hyperides, a fourth-century B.C. Athenian orator and politician.  E1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-8</p>
        <p>Officer Accounts Surface In Fatal Queens Shooting  The undercover police officer who fired the first shots at a carload of men in Queens, triggering a storm of police bullets that killed a man on the eve of his wedding and injured two of his friends, suspected at least one of the men had a gun and was intent on returning with it to a nearby strip club, according to a person briefed on the accounts of officers involved in the shootings. B1</p>
        <p>Police experts suggested that ''contagious shooting,'' police parlance for gunfire that spreads among officers who believe that they, or their colleagues, are facing a threat, may have played a role in the fatal police shooting. A1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A21</p>
        <p>Phyllis Cerf Wagner  The socially dynamic wife of two of New York's most prominent men who was always proudest of her collaboration with a former advertising colleague, Dr. Seuss, on a series of landmark children's books, she was 90. A21</p>
        <p>Rhodes W. Fairbridge  An early expert of climate change who edited an influential series of encyclopedias covering the earth sciences, he was 92.  A21</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>New Path in Heart Research  Recognizing that surgical interventions and drugs have not been enough to prevent tens of thousands of deaths from coronary artery disease, researchers will undertake a program to study fatty deposits called plaque in the hope of devising new treatments.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Still Backing a Game Maker  In what should be a golden time for video game makers, the stock of Midway Games has continued to plummet. But Sumner M. Redstone, the 83-year-old media mogul and main shareholder of the video game maker, seems committed to it.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Holiday Profits at the Mall  Midnight openings and deep discounts appeared to give merchants at the mall an edge over discount retailers, as a study showed that mall sales for the day after Thanksgiving rose 6 percent this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Question of Wi-Fi Ethics  Several new mobile phone devices allow users to make calls over wireless access points in cafes, parks and even homes, raising ethical and legal questions about piggybacking on unsecured private networks.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: When don't smoke means do; a poisoned spy; the test of time; Dorothy Samuels on payoffs to public officials.</p>
        <p>Column: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E6  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E7  Weather A20</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>Draft Report on Iraq Urges Talks With Iran and Syria  A draft report on strategies for Iraq that will be debated by a bipartisan commission urges an aggressive regional diplomatic initiative that includes direct talks with Iran and Syria, but sets no timetables for a military withdrawal, according to officials who have seen all or parts of the document.  A1</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki said Iraq's politicians were largely responsible for the surge in violence that engulfed the country over the past week, a departure from his previous assertions blaming militants for inciting the mayhem. A10</p>
        <p>Afghan Mission Tests NATO  NATO is bigger than ever, and is reaching further than ever before, by taking the lead in the war in Afghanistan. But the Afghan mission threatens a rift within the Atlantic alliance between those nations able and willing to participate fully in combat operations in Afghanistan -- and those nations that are not. A11</p>
        <p>A suicide bomber walked into a packed restaurant in southeastern Afghanistan and set off his explosives, killing 15 other people and wounding 25, Afghan officials said. The attack came after weeks of relative quiet and raised fears that insurgents were resuming their campaign of suicide bombings. A11</p>
        <p>Gaza Cease-Fire Seems to Hold  A cease-fire in Gaza appeared to be holding after Palestinian factions stopped firing rockets at Israel in exchange for an Israeli troop withdrawal from the territory.  A3</p>
        <p>Shiites Dominate Bahrain Vote  Shiite opposition candidates won 16 of the 17 seats they contested in elections for the lower house of Parliament in Bahrain, the election commission said. The 17th contested seat is set to be decided in a runoff on Dec. 2.  A3</p>
        <p>Korean Leader Sinks in Polls  Bruised by South Korea's no-holds-barred politics, bewildered by voters' rapidly changing concerns and battered mercilessly in the polls, President Roh Moo-hyun is limping toward the last year of his term. But it is not Mr. Roh's engagement of North Korea, or even its recent nuclear test, that has saddled him with a current approval rating of 11 percent. It is the economy. A6</p>
        <p>Correa Likely Victor in Ecuador  Rafael Correa, an urbane economist who has rattled nerves in Washington with plans to limit American military activities in Ecuador and renegotiate its foreign debt, seemed headed to an easy victory on Sunday in the presidential election, according to several exit polls.  A8</p>
        <p>British Retrace Steps of Spy  The British police sought to retrace the movements of Alexander V. Litvinenko, a former Russian secret agent, before he fell ill from the radiation poisoning that killed him. But the police insisted that Mr. Litvinenko's macabre death remained in the ''suspicious'' category and that they were not treating the case as a murder inquiry.  A7</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-19</p>
        <p>The Very Rich Are Leaving the Merely Rich Behind  Three decades ago, compensation among occupations differed far less than it does today. That growing difference is diverting people from some critical fields, experts say. The American Bar Foundation has found that fewer law school graduates are going into public-interest law or government jobs and filling all the openings is becoming harder.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New England G.O.P. Thins  The recent midterm elections dealt the already-fading New England Republican an especially strong blow, one that some fear will increase the divide between the two parties nationally by removing a longstanding bridge between them. Now, of 22 members of the House of Representatives from New England, only one is a Republican.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Seattle Nears Rain Record  Seattle's official rain gauge at Seattle-Tacoma International Airport has passed 14 inches and is rising. Now some wonder whether this month will break the single-month record for rainfall, 15.33 inches, which was set in December 1933.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Copper Price, and Theft, Rise  In the last year, a worldwide surge in demand for copper, largely because of construction booms in China and India, has pushed up its value, making the theft of copper more profitable and more popular.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-8</p>
        <p>Rejoining of German Museums  With the reopening of the Bode Museum, the Museum Island cultural park in the former East Berlin has taken another step toward recovering its place as one of the world's great centers of art. E1</p>
        <p>Important Greek Find  An international project to decipher 1,000-year-old, moldy pages is yielding new clues about ancient Greece as seen through the eyes of Hyperides, a fourth-century B.C. Athenian orator and politician.  E1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-8</p>
        <p>Officer Accounts Surface In Fatal Queens Shooting  The undercover police officer who fired the first shots at a carload of men in Queens, triggering a storm of police bullets that killed a man on the eve of his wedding and injured two of his friends, suspected at least one of the men had a gun and was intent on returning with it to a nearby strip club, according to a person briefed on the accounts of officers involved in the shootings. B1</p>
        <p>Police experts suggested that ''contagious shooting,'' police parlance for gunfire that spreads among officers who believe that they, or their colleagues, are facing a threat, may have played a role in the fatal police shooting. A1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES A21</p>
        <p>Phyllis Cerf Wagner  The socially dynamic wife of two of New York's most prominent men who was always proudest of her collaboration with a former advertising colleague, Dr. Seuss, on a series of landmark children's books, she was 90. A21</p>
        <p>Rhodes W. Fairbridge  An early expert of climate change who edited an influential series of encyclopedias covering the earth sciences, he was 92.  A21</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>New Path in Heart Research  Recognizing that surgical interventions and drugs have not been enough to prevent tens of thousands of deaths from coronary artery disease, researchers will undertake a program to study fatty deposits called plaque in the hope of devising new treatments.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Still Backing a Game Maker  In what should be a golden time for video game makers, the stock of Midway Games has continued to plummet. But Sumner M. Redstone, the 83-year-old media mogul and main shareholder of the video game maker, seems committed to it.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Holiday Profits at the Mall  Midnight openings and deep discounts appeared to give merchants at the mall an edge over discount retailers, as a study showed that mall sales for the day after Thanksgiving rose 6 percent this year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Question of Wi-Fi Ethics  Several new mobile phone devices allow users to make calls over wireless access points in cafes, parks and even homes, raising ethical and legal questions about piggybacking on unsecured private networks.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest C2</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: When don't smoke means do; a poisoned spy; the test of time; Dorothy Samuels on payoffs to public officials.</p>
        <p>Column: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6  Crossword E6  Metro Diary B2  TV Listings E7  Weather A20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
