<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Commend NASA's Progress on Communications</title>
    <meta content="14nasa" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDA1330F937A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Commend NASA's Progress on Communications</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A review of communications policies at NASA, set off by reports that political appointees had tried to muzzle some agency scientists, received a public vote of support yesterday from dozens of scientists and other staff members at the space agency.</p>
        <p>More than 140 NASA scientists, engineers and other civil servants from research centers across the country put their names on a statement, distributed in an e-mail message last night, that applauded the agency's administrator, Michael D. Griffin, for following up on his Feb. 4 pledge of "scientific openness."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A review of communications policies at NASA, set off by reports that political appointees had tried to muzzle some agency scientists, received a public vote of support yesterday from dozens of scientists and other staff members at the space agency.</p>
        <p>More than 140 NASA scientists, engineers and other civil servants from research centers across the country put their names on a statement, distributed in an e-mail message last night, that applauded the agency's administrator, Michael D. Griffin, for following up on his Feb. 4 pledge of "scientific openness."</p>
        <p>"His subsequent actions have reinforced his words," the statement said.</p>
        <p>A dozen senior NASA scientists and public affairs officials are drafting the agency's first new policy on public communications since 1987.</p>
        <p>The review began after political appointees altered news releases and Web presentations against the wishes of some NASA scientists and tried to restrict public comments by James E. Hansen, a top NASA climate scientist. Dr. Hansen has repeatedly said that global warming caused by humans poses an urgent threat, a position at odds with that of the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Several civil servants involved in the review said in recent interviews that they were confident that the changes being considered would, if they gained final approval, limit the potential for political interference.</p>
        <p>A NASA official working on the draft policy, which is about five pages long, said it would probably be ready for review by Dr. Griffin and other senior officials by midweek.</p>
        <p>The official, who was granted anonymity because he was not authorized to discuss the review, said that for the moment, the policy met Dr. Griffin's stated goal of allowing NASA employees to discuss the implications of their work and not just the scientific facts, as long as they emphasized that they were speaking as individuals and not for the agency.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, political appointees in the NASA press office repeatedly said that agency scientists could not discuss the broader implications of their work.</p>
        <p>The official involved in the review also said the new draft policy would ensure that if a reporter sought to speak with a specific NASA scientist, that could take place if the scientist was amenable.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen had been told earlier this year that his supervisors had the right to pre-empt him and do interviews in his place.</p>
        <p>"The goal is that the people directly responsible for a particular thing, a particular piece of research, should be the ones who speak," said the official.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Dr. Hansen distributed an e-mail message to dozens of colleagues and other contacts saying that he, too, was satisfied that the review was substantive and that it was time for him to return to his climate research.</p>
        <p>Citing reports of efforts to filter scientific information and limit news media access to reporters at other scientific agencies, Dr. Hansen wrote: "The battle to achieve open communication between government scientists and their employer, the public, is far from won. Nevertheless, I agree with the opinion of colleagues that the focus should be on discussing solutions to global warming."</p>
        <p>"My personal aim is to get back to science research full time," he said, "especially on quantifying options for dealing with global warming."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
