<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What, Get My Precious Towel Wet?</title>
    <meta content="06TOWELS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Thursday Styles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/06/fashion/06TOWELS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1773991"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Towels</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Thursday Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3DE1330F935A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What, Get My Precious Towel Wet?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What, Get My Precious Towel Wet?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC WILSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Famous designers are offering luxury beach towels that owners use more for decor than for functionality; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POOLSIDE on Fire Island or at the beaches of East Hampton, there is only one shame greater than seeing a better-looking body in the same designer bikini you are wearing. That is seeing that body and bikini on a better-looking beach towel.</p>
        <p>Yet it is a common error made by people who spend hundreds of dollars for the latest Prada sunglasses and Teflon-coated swim trunks, coordinated to match their Coach canvas totes and Gucci sandals, to overlook the Tao of towels. The towel, for seriously label-oriented beachgoers, is the source of being. It holds one's place in the sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is only one shame greater than seeing a better-looking body in the same designer bikini you are wearing. That is seeing that body and bikini on a better-looking beach towel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POOLSIDE on Fire Island or at the beaches of East Hampton, there is only one shame greater than seeing a better-looking body in the same designer bikini you are wearing. That is seeing that body and bikini on a better-looking beach towel.</p>
        <p>Yet it is a common error made by people who spend hundreds of dollars for the latest Prada sunglasses and Teflon-coated swim trunks, coordinated to match their Coach canvas totes and Gucci sandals, to overlook the Tao of towels. The towel, for seriously label-oriented beachgoers, is the source of being. It holds one's place in the sun.</p>
        <p>''I love towels the way I love sheets,'' said the retailer Jeffrey Kalinsky, whose summer house in Fire Island Pines is stocked with a couple of Hermès beach blankets and two brand-new oversize Louis Vuitton nautical checkerboard styles, which he is currently favoring. His home in Atlanta is outfitted with a veritable retrospective of Emilio Pucci, as told through beach towels.</p>
        <p>For guests, Mr. Kalinsky offers something more distinguished: eight cheerfully fluffy beach towels from the Beverly Hills Hotel gift shop ($75 apiece at www.thebeverlyhillshotel.com). Mr. Kalinsky was introduced to those towels by DD Allen, a partner in the architecture and interior-design firm Pierce Allen. Ms. Allen uses them as bath towels.</p>
        <p>''They make me really happy,'' Mr. Kalinsky said. ''They're pink and white, a little kitschy and very serviceable. They do the job.'' Many people would consider luxury beach towels to be impractical things, but others would attest to their potential worth as investment pieces, regardless of global warming trends. Hermès towels are the classic examples. Their heft and mosaic patterns are like that of Berber carpeting, dense and hypnotic. The price is $450 for a 36-by-60-inch towel: at $30 a square foot, that is a bargain compared with Manhattan real estate.</p>
        <p>Jane DeFlorio, an investment banker, bought two Hermès towels on eBay, one for $75 and another for $225, indicating a fairly impressive resistance to depreciation. Ms. DeFlorio plans to keep them in mint condition at her summer house in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>''They are purely meant as an interior design element,'' she said. ''I have to tell my guests to please not take them to the beach.'' For functionality, she swears by the oversize white bath sheets from WestPoint Stevens, buying the $19.95 irregulars by the cartload at Bed Bath &amp; Beyond.</p>
        <p>Many luxury towel owners are reluctant to actually use them because they are so expensive. And the towels also encourage irresponsibly addictive behavior, as one Southampton homeowner suggested after realizing he had to buy more Hermès towels to fill out a complete set for his deck chairs.</p>
        <p>An experienced eye can spot an Hermès towel from the parking lot of Egypt Beach, deserving of a nod for taste, but no points for originality. As July unfolds, there are more daring choices, including Chanel's $395 charm motif cruising towel, the $285 sea-blue paisleys of Etro and, at $195, Tory Burch's wonderfully jarring prints, which resemble terry renditions of Moroccan tilework. They may clash with your bathing suit, but people will notice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
