<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Gas Prices Go Up, Impact Trickles Down; New Hope for Ethanol</title>
    <meta content="30gas-4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1758416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crop Controls and Subsidies</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crop Controls and Subsidies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DF113FF933A05757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Gas Prices Go Up, Impact Trickles Down; New Hope for Ethanol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Price of grain-alcohol fuel is up sharply as demand has surged and more and more vehicles are able to burn commercially available ethanol fuels, like E85, which sells for 30 to 60 cents a gallon less than unleaded gasoline; some economists warn that farm subsidies blur fuel's real cost; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are happy days for an ethanol man.</p>
        <p>The price of grain-alcohol fuel is up sharply as demand has surged, and Colorado's newest ethanol plant is almost ready to open after four years of preparation and sweat by Dan R. Sanders and his family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These are happy days for an ethanol man.</p>
        <p>The price of grain-alcohol fuel is up sharply as demand has surged, and Colorado's newest ethanol plant is almost ready to open after four years of preparation and sweat by Dan R. Sanders and his family.</p>
        <p>''It's great for us,'' said Mr. Sanders, 28, as he watched one of the first loads of corn -- ethanol's main ingredient -- arrive on Friday morning from a farm in northeastern Colorado.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Sanders's company, Front Range Energy, begins shipping next month from this $60 million factory in Windsor, Colo., an hour north of Denver, it will just about double Colorado's ethanol production, adding 40 million gallons a year to the pipeline. And at least two other plants around the state are in planning.</p>
        <p>Ethanol, which is essentially identical to the old corn liquor of moonshine fame, is increasingly blended with gas to reduce emissions and replace other additives like MTBE, or methyl tertiary butyl ether, which is a suspected carcinogen.</p>
        <p>But more and more vehicles are also able to burn commercially available ethanol fuels like E85 -- 85 percent grain alcohol -- and kits can also be bought that allow cars to burn an even higher percentage of ethanol. All this has further increased the demand, and the price. In most parts of the country, E85 sells for 30 cents to 60 cents a gallon less than regular unleaded gasoline, but most cars get fewer miles to the gallon burning ethanol.</p>
        <p>Ethanol has its critics. Some economists say that farm subsidies blur the fuel's real cost, making it a less than perfect long-term alternative in thinking about the world after oil.</p>
        <p>But here in Colorado, people like Mr. Sanders say the economics make more sense than ever. Until recently, ethanol could only make money if distilled close to its fuel source, he said. That is why corn-country Iowa dominates the nation's production.</p>
        <p>Increasing demand is shattering that boundary, making factories feasible closer to where the product gets sold. About half of Front Range's output, Mr. Sanders said, will go no further than Denver.</p>
        <p>The Sanderses have also lined up local buyers for the waste. The left-over corn mash will be sold as cattle feed, while the carbon dioxide produced by fermentation will be made into dry ice and sold in the Denver market.</p>
        <p>But operations like this are still small potatoes by the scale of big oil. On a day when the Chevron Corporation was announcing $4 billion in profits, Mr. Sanders and his wife, Jana, and their 2-year-old daughter, Ellie, were watching the corn arrive. And Ellie was not even very interested.</p>
        <p>KIRK JOHNSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
